<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Chirurgicall Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">R221201_Bo1_29_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A66951</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7487</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">R221201</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Chirurgicall Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nostōdia : In serenissimi, potentissimi, et inuictissimi monarchae, Iacobi Magnæ Britanniæ, Franciæ &amp; Hiberniæ Regis, fidei defensoris, &amp;c. felicem in Scotiam reditum, Academiæ Edinburgensis congratulatio</title>
                 <author>University of Edinburgh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hart, Andro</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>50, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>To the Chirurgicall Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oving Reader, I held it not altogether imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to acquaint thee as by the way with some customes which I have observed concerning Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions in forraign parts in my younger dayes travels, and chiefly in the Germane Empire, as touching their manner of allowing or approving of Chirurgions in those parts, if by accident any young Artist should affect to make trial by travel thither for his better experience, as I my self have done, he may take notice hereby for his instruction.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Imprimis,</hi> their orders there generally are, that every City, Town Corporte, or place priviledged, hath a constant rule, as by ancient tradition of the allowing of onely an usuall accustomed number of Chirurgions thereunto appertaining, so that for one instance if the Citie of Hamburge hath twelve Chirurgions belonging thereto, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a thousand pound should be tendered in any way to produce a freedome for a thirteenth Chirurgion, it could not prevail, nor would be taken there; as likewise generally it is so all over Germany, and each Chirurgion is bred and must be a Barber, and so are all Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Chirurgions; and if any one die, his Office, Art, and place rests in the power or disposing of his wife, to the use of her and hers, so that who so marrieth her, or compoundeth with her, of what Nation or Countrey soever he be that shall exercise the place, it is alike provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he be brought in by the widdow, as her husband or agent for her, he is capable of a place void, having first made his master-piece, and performed some Manuall exercises usuall with them in his art of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie, thereby to give a sufficient testimony to the world of his answerable skill in his Art or Science, as namely, either by grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and setting a delicate lancet, and therewith opening severall veins smoothly, for the more manifest effecting whereof to the brethren of his calling, one will lend him his vein, namely, one on the thumb, one on the foot, and one on the arme, one other on the forehead, as also by the neat and exact making an artificial Emplaster, Vnguent, or the like: which done, being by rest of the Masters of the Citie approved of, and some other rites and ceremonies an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering to his calling by him performed, according to the custome of the place that he intendeth to reside in, he is then being
<pb n="234" facs="127"/>
esteemed a Regular person, and also having made the Brotherhood of the place and himself well drunk once, twice, or thrice, he is, I say, <hi>(ipso s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cto)</hi> admitted to be a brother, and freely to use his Function, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> styled by the name and honour of a Master of his profession. Thus much of their custome. But our customes are different from theirs, and are far better, namely, our Company of Chirurgions of the Citie of London, in the Hall of the Society, have a more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable custome, for we not onely examine Chirurgions, and try their skils in that way, as being of ancient time used and practised a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us, but also we have profitable, learned and experienced Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures read amongst us, having two laudable ends and effects in them, the one in testifying their own, I mean the Readers sufficiencies; the other in seasoning and instructing of their auditours, namely, the younger sort of practitioners in the Art they professe: and yet they have a third good end, namely, they serve for the publick good of the whole Common-wealth, by training up, and breeding of able Chirurgions upon all occasions.
<q>
         <l>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> Medicos tantum facit experientia doctos:</l>
         <l>Qui facit artifices, usus ab arte venit.</l>
      </q>
And of these our laudable customes and exercises in our Hall, my self have been both an eye and eare witnesse to divers worthy Artists at their Lectures there, that have shewed themselves Masters indeed in their Arts to their due commendations <hi>(Virtus landatur ab illis)</hi> as also at the Lectures of divers learned Doctors in that place: but as for my self, although I have there as I may not deny exercises by publick reading of Lectures in my turn and place, yet my ambition at the highest hath been openly to deliver my self to the world to the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions Mate, as aspiring to soar no higher, <hi>(Ne sutor ultra crepidam.)</hi> In which being, first I have explained to the world a Modell of the Military Chirurgions chest, with the instruments and medicines fitting thereunto, as elsewhere is recited, thereby to intimate to the younger Chirurgions in some sort how they may make use of them in all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick services for the better performance of their duties in their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, upon all military occasions, for the more speedy curing of such infirmities as Sea-men and Souldiers are most incident unto, and having finished my intent therein, at the intreaty of some of my good friends, I thought it fit, though in brief, to write somewhat by way of addition to my former edition of <hi>Sal, Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> and, namely, how they are made the more known and useful unto us by the Chymick art, or the art of Alchymie which the Chirurgions ought to be versed in, and which in brief is thus defined.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>