<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE TOUCHING The definition of Gangrena.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">R221201_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A66951</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7487</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">R221201</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE TOUCHING The definition of Gangrena.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nostōdia : In serenissimi, potentissimi, et inuictissimi monarchae, Iacobi Magnæ Britanniæ, Franciæ &amp; Hiberniæ Regis, fidei defensoris, &amp;c. felicem in Scotiam reditum, Academiæ Edinburgensis congratulatio</title>
                 <author>University of Edinburgh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hart, Andro</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>50, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="193"/>
   <pb n="379" facs="193"/>
   <head>A PREFACE TOUCHING The definition of <hi>Gangrena.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving in part ingaged my self by promise to my good Friends, before the Edition of this my work, to explain to the World, amongst other parts of Surgery, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Amputating or cutting off, of putrid members, in the mortified part: I after considered with my self, that I could not properly proceed therein, except by the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a <hi>Gangrene,</hi> in the first place, because a <hi>Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene</hi> is ever the fore runner of a <hi>Sphacelus,</hi> and the material cause of Amputation, either in the general body of Man, or in any the particular parts thereof, and from the which, no Animal creature, no not Man himself can decline from.</p>
   <q>Ab initio statutum est omnibus semel mori.</q>
   <p>For from the beginning, all men are constituted once to dye, and yet there is an interim for each man, of not being in health, neither really dead, but <hi>quafi moriens, vel semi mortuus,</hi> dying, or half dying. In the which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>terim, or intermission of time, a man may by an accident be said to be in such a distemper, as he may be gangrenated, or in a <hi>Gangrena,</hi> as the Artist tearms it, either in part, or in all; and yet by the permission of God, and by the help of Art, that supposed dying man, or member of man, may receive cure, and be hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d again, although in mans judgment, not well versed in the mystery of healing, he be supposed to be at the gates of death: Even so a <hi>Gangrene,</hi> presaging a <hi>Spha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celus,</hi> may in some cases be cured, as daily experience sheweth, that divers <hi>Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grenes</hi> receive cure; so that to conclude, a man that hath a <hi>Gangrene,</hi> in one or more parts of his body, untill it be taken away, that man is ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r as it were, under the Shadow of Death.</p>
   <q>Nam Mors sequitur ut umbra,</q>
   <q>Death attendeth us as our shadow.</q>
   <p>Thus much briefly, by way of Preface, touching the <hi>Gangrene.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>