<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Letter]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">R2909_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07649</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17642</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">R2909</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Letter]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Roman actor : A tragædie. As it hath diuers times beene, with good allowance acted, at the private play-house in the Black-Friers, by the Kings Majesties Servants. Written by Philip Massinger</title>
                 <author>Massinger, Philip</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Crooke, Andrew 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had seriously considered how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Reader to receive this piece, with apprehensions becomming It's merit; I discern'd my selfe uncapable to contrive an Ornament beyond the noble name of the admir'd Author: When I have once intituled it to <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Walter Mountague,</hi> &amp; assur'd it genuine, I conceive the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression imports an Elogie, above the designe and reach of the most alluring Commendation. 'Tis known, these Papers have long slept, and are now rais'd to put on that immortality, which nothing has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itherto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>'d them of, but their concealement. They addresse themselves to the inspir'd and more refin'd part of men! Such as are capable to be ravish'd when they find a fancy bright and high, as the <hi>Phoebus</hi> that gave it: Such as have experienced those extasies and Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which are the very Genius of Poetry; P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>etry its selfe being nothing else but a brave and measur'd En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thusiasm: Such as know, what it is to have the Soul up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wing (suspending its commerce with clay) reaching a room almost as losty as the proper Scene of Spirits, till warm'd with divine flames, it melts it selfe into numbers as charming as the Harmony of those Spheres it left beneath it: Such as are thus qualified,
<pb facs="3"/>
may here read upon the square; Others will finde themselves unconcern'd.</p>
   <p>Happy Pen! that hast blest us with such conceptions as render it equally impossible to celebrate, and to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate: Happy Pen! that hast given the little-God a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as soft as the down of his Mothers doves.</p>
   <p>This is all, my thoughts commission'd me to say; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be, that I am</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your humble Servant, <hi>T.D.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>