<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE REVEREND AND LEARNED EXAMINERS and Readers, humble and heartie saluta∣tion in Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100095_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16752</idno>
           <idno type="STC">366</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100095</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE REVEREND AND LEARNED EXAMINERS and Readers, humble and heartie saluta∣tion in Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treasurie of catechisme, or Christian instruction. The first part, which is concerning the morall law or ten Commandements of Almightie God: with certaine questions and aunswers preparatory to the same</title>
                 <author>Allen, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 308, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE REVEREND AND LEARNED EXAMINERS and Readers, humble and heartie saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may well be (Reuerend fathers and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing brethrē in the Lord) that your graue and godly mindes being iustly setteled in preiudice against all vainglorious or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduised &amp; needlesse attēpts to write and publish bookes (as against that wherein the vaine and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious minde of man will alwayes be restlesse, and so with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out restraint would put the Reader to much causlesse and frutelesse wearinesse) ye will at the first viewe require a reason, both of this booke, and also of the title of it. Of the booke, why it should be published after so many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent books alreadie set forth of the same argument, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may seeme to be a superfluous attempt. Of the title, how it may beseeme the modesty of him who offereth it to examination, seeing albeit he cannot but confesse of him selfe, that he is in truth a verie poore man, yet may be su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected to make boast of great wealth, and thereby to fall vnder the rebuke of that holy Prouerbe which saith: <hi>There is that maketh himselfe rich, and hath nothing.</hi> VVhich surely were a foule fault, specially in the Church of Christ, and concerning the holy matters of God; and the same also in a time of great learning, &amp; in the cleare light of the Gospell, wherein vaine boasting and beggery cannot possibly be concealed and hid.</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>To either of these demaunds, or secret and sudden con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts of the mind (seeing by the Law of God concerning the ordinarie gift of prophesie and interpretation of the Scriptures, <hi>The spirites of the Prophets are subiect to the Prophets</hi>) I thinke it my dutie to bewray and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto you the secrets of my thoughts, so farre as your wisedomes, and the cause it selfe may seeme to require at my hands; that so the honour of the iudgement, may in a lawfull course of proceeding, be committed vnto you.</p>
   <p>Touching the first therefore, what may better beseeme me for answere, then (that being my selfe intreated, first by some such, whose request could not but thus farre pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with me) that I should humbly referre the present booke to the examination of you, who beside the gift of spirituall discerning, haue a speciall power and authority, to determine whether it befit that it should be published or no. To you therefore I referre it, not desiring the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing of it, vnlesse it may be found meete to haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment and allowance among the bookes of the same argument: as that, which hauing receiued great helpe from the former, may yeeld at the least some litle helpe, to such as (answerable to the greater measure of their gifts) shall write yet more exactly of the same most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent points at any time hereafter. As touching my selfe it shall suffice me, that I haue offered it to your godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations, tendring herein the best dutie I could both to you and those that so desired and incouraged me, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of Gods glory, and the benefite of his Church, as they were in their owne heartes perswaded.</p>
   <p>And now cōcerning the title, although peraduenture it may seem to be prefixed with a mind, to make some vaine boast of an imagined excellency to be in this booke aboue others: I do likewise humbly desire that it may not so be
<pb facs="6"/> misconstrued; but first according to that common vse of titles, whereby each booke is distinguished from others, and specially from those of the same argument; and then in respect of the doctrine it selfe, rather then of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and forme of the deliuerie, and contriuing or dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting of it; according to that which the Spirit of God saith of the most excellent Law of God, and doctrine thereof, that it is more to be desired <hi>then gold: yea, then much fine gold,</hi> and more earnestly to be sought and searched after, then any other iewell or treasure whatsoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side.</p>
   <p>In hope therefore that it shall be so interpreted of you, and nothing doubting of your ingenuous and incorrupt iudgement of the whole booke, I do willingly offer it to be read, tried, and examined of you: heartily praying God by you, to giue that iudgement and successe, which he himselfe in his most excellent wisedome shall best ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue of. To whose most gracious direction and blessing in all things, I do both hartily and dutifully commend you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord vnfeinedly desirous to learne of all, that so happily he might be fit to teach some: <hi>ROBERT ALLEN a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of the word of God.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>