<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100459_Fr1_14</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11035</idno>
           <idno type="STC">164</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100459</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A registre of hystories : conteining martiall exploites of worthy warriours, politique practises of ciuil magistrates, wise sentences of famous philosophers, and other matters manifolde and memorable. Written in Greeke, by Ælianus a Romane: and deliuered in Englishe (as well, according to the truth of the Greeke text, as of the Latine) by Abraham Fleming. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Aelian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 178 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div xml:lang="eng" type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>To the Courteous <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>This booke replenished with varietie &amp; chaunge, (Courteous Reader) may be compared to a greate &amp; stately building, which is not altogether outwardly voide of beuty, but inwardly also, gaily decked &amp; finely furnished With all sightly and sumptuous implemēts. yt is lyke vnto an inestimable Iuell, or precious pearle, which although yt be inclosed in a homly woddē box, and shut vp in a simple casket, litle or nothing worthe in comparison, yet is it neuer a whit the lesse in vallue notwithstanding, but reserueth his price vndimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed. Wherfore (Courteous Reader) in consideration of thine owne profit, and vauntage, pleasure, and harts ease, enter into this princely pallace, view euery roome circumspectly, behold eache seuerall chamber and lodging aduisedly, and vse the benefite of euery thing liberally, to thine owne contentation. Open this base boxe, and lifte vp the lydd of this course casket, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in so riche and costly a Iuell is inclosed, wey yt, and weare it, the commodity issuing from the same is sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, so is the delight redundant and plentifull. Take all, and possesse all, thy title is substantiall, and thine interest sufficient.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell. </salute>
      <signed>Abraham Fleming.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>