<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohan Bale to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100594_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02599</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1273.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100594</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohan Bale to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first two parts of the Actes, or vnchast examples of the Englysh votaryes : gathered out of their owne legenades and chronycles by Iohan Bale, and dedycated to our most redoubted soueraigne kynge Edward the syxte</title>
                 <author>Bale, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 <publisher>Bale, John, Bishop.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, cxx, 4 leaves, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="vij" facs="96"/>
   <head>Iohan Bale to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T wyll be thought of many (most gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll reader) that I haue not herin done wele, in bryngynge so many fylthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes vnchast masmō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to lyght,<note place="margin">Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</note> whych ought rather to haue bene buryed in oblyuyon. I wyshe these to consydre whose vyces the scripture hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and whose it detecteth to rebuke and shame. The same God whych couered the nakednesse of Adam and Eue with skyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes after their fall,<note place="margin">Adam.</note> Gene. iij. The same God hath dyscouered the shame of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon (whych now is the Romysh churche) and shewed fourth her vncomely preuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, accordynge to promyse, Esay. xlvij. Beholde (sayth the lorde of hostes) I wyll brynge thyne owne wayes vpon thyne heade, Ezech. xvi. I wyll vpon the,<note place="margin">Holy churche.</note> thou bewtyfull harlot and maistres of witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft (sayth God) and wyll pull thy clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes ouer thy heade, that I maye shewe thy nakednesse amon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e the Heythen, and thy shame amonge the kyngedomes. I wyll caste durte vpon the, to make the be
<pb facs="97"/>
abhorred and a gasynge stocke, Nahum iij for he that commytteth aduoutry, getteth hym selfe shame and dyshonour, such as neuer shall be put out of memory. Prouer. vi.<note place="margin">The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</note> Partly haue these with a great sort more of the scriptures, prouoked me to fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysh thys worke, partly the incessaunt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge on of a great nombre of men both worshypfull, godly, and learned, whych with Dauid, Psal. Cxxxviij. do perfyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and throughly hate these bandy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thels, contempners of marriage, and vtter enemyes of God. I haue oft tolde them (I hope, in the zele of God) that I wolde as lyttle abashe to shewe their fylthy actes, by the wytnesse of their owne legendes &amp; Chronycles, as they haue abashed to do them. I haue tarryed these foure yeares,<note place="margin">tarryed.</note> sens I wrote the fyrst part of thys worke, to beholde their repentaunce for this kynd of wyckednesse, and I fynde them now more wyllfull and peruersed in their deuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lysh opynyon than afore. Therfore wyll I now ernestly detect the Sodometrouse ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of their holy Romysh chastyte. The admonyshementes of S. Paule, to their forefathers the Romanes, of their hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cresy,<note place="margin">Ghostly fruytes.</note> ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, falsehede, vnclennesse, ydola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, prodygyouse lustes, defylynges of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, chaungynge of the naturall vse into an vse agaynst nature, and other vnspea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable beastlynesse, Roma, i. haue they not
<pb n="viij" facs="97"/>
regarded, but haue wrought those most execrable myscheues, and worke them styl in effect without repentaunce. Therfore wyll I declare them in effect to cause gods people (as necessary it is) effectually to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre them. Iudge me not herein to gyue a doctryne of vyce,<note place="margin">Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne.</note> but rather an earnest doctryne to the contrarye, in contēpt of such abhomynacyons as that college of the deuyll hath offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the worlde for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyouse fruttes of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall holynesse. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
   <q>
      <p>¶ The shame of Aegipt shall be dyscouered. They that dwell in the yles, shall se euen the same daye.</p>
      <bibl>Esay. xx.</bibl>
   </q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>