<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentle Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100122_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19032</idno>
           <idno type="STC">545</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100122</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentle Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The moste excellent and pleasaunt booke, entituled: The treasurie of Amadis of Fraunce : conteyning eloquente orations, pythie epistles, learned letters, and feruent complayntes, seruing for sundrie purposes. ... Translated out of Frenche into English</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hacket, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 307, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>A VERY</hi> frend of myne (most gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) instantly desired me, to english him this french booke, intituled the <hi>Treasurie of Amadis,</hi> the whiche when I had well perused it, pleased me not a little, as wel for the elegant phrase thereof, as for the diuersities and arguments therin wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and inclosed. For truly it aboundeth with such eloquent orations and wyse counsels: with such swéete and delicate Epistles and letters especially of loue, so curteously and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nnably handled: with suche exhortations and admonitions so prudently penned: with suche lamentations &amp; complaints so sorowfully and mournfully expressed: with suche consola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and comforts in aduersitie, so frendly and louingly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced: with such answers and replications so ingeniously inuented: with reproches and tauntes so bitingly and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spoken: with requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sts so humainly and ciuilly demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: with excuses so craftily and subtilly painted and colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: with defyances so stoutly and courageously sente to the aduersarie and receiued, that if a man were astonied &amp; much amazed, it woulde quicken him, and sodeynly reuiue his spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites againe. For what a dullarde is he, that wise counsell. vertuous exhortations, friendly admonitions, wittie and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till persuasions shall not quicken and reuiue? and how farre without sense is he, whom amiable, fine, and beautifull la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies with their ticklyng and flatteryng wordes shall not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, stirre vp, and call to their lure, wanton fansie, &amp; fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>? What stonie and harde hearte hath he, that with the glittering and twinkeling of the eye, the abundant tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, the dulcet and swéete parolls of his paramour (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with this fine flattering booke is infarced) will not be molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed and melted? And how depely are they drowned in sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, that with godly and vertuous consolation will not be comforted? What weake and cowardly heartes and sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes
<pb facs="4"/>
haue they that will not be stirred or moued with the rhetorical &amp; eloquent orations, the vehement persuasiōs, and liberall promises and rewards of wise, noble &amp; worthie capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, pluck vp their harts, inuade their enimies, &amp; (for wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie renoume sake, &amp; immortall glorie) fight stoutly and cora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geously, as <hi>Amadis,</hi> the king of England &amp; France, &amp; <hi>Flor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>an</hi> with other did (as this proper booke in diuers places reciteth) most cordially? Wherout men may learne to be noble ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, wise and prudent counsellours, excellent Rhethorici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, expert captains, amorous companions, feruent &amp; honest louers, secrete messengers, obedient seruāts, elegant enditers of louely Epistles, swéete pronouncers &amp; true ortographers, of the french tong so pleasant, so highly cōmended, and so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced of all men. Wherfore (gentle Reader) let it not lothe thée (I pray thée) to reade this fine and fruitfull booke, nor to ensue the honest and vertuous lessons, the prudent admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and good counsels of the same: for thou shalt not at any tyme (as I thinke) repent thée more for the reading of it, than I for the translating therof, the which although it be but rude and vnpleasant, yet my mynde and hand were neyther ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent nor slacke to profite thée, and to english it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation and comfort. Therfore receyue it, I pray thée, as it is, in good part and with thanksgiuing for my good will and paines taking, if thou estéeme it thankes wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rthie, if not, amende it I beséeche thée, and I with all my heart shal thanke thée nowe and euer.</p>
   <closer>Farewel.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>