<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>2. Tim. 3. 4. To the Christian Reader being none of those men▪ who, (accor∣ding to S. Paul's prophecy,) love pleasures more than God.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100662_Bo1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03243</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1336</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100662</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>2. Tim. 3. 4. To the Christian Reader being none of those men▪ who, (accor∣ding to S. Paul's prophecy,) love pleasures more than God.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A modest reply to certaine answeres, which Mr. Gataker B.D. in his treatise of the nature, &amp; vse of lotts, giveth to arguments in a dialogue concerning the vnlawfulnes of games consisting in chance : And aunsweres to his reasons allowing lusorious lotts, as not evill in themselves. By Iames Balmford, minister of Iesus Christ</title>
                 <author>Balmford, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Boyle, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                            <distributor>Boyle, Richard</distributor>
                            <distributor>Boyle, Richard</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>143, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="26" facs="14"/>
   <head>
      <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 4.</note> To the Christian Reader being none of those men▪ who, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>S. Paul's</hi> prophecy,) love pleasures more than God.</head>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Ionah. 1. 7.</note>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome yeares are past since <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> tooke occasion, from casting of Lotts to finde out for whose sake a daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous storme was, to justisie play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Dice, Cards, &amp;c. and to confute me <hi>by name</hi> in open pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. I hearing thereof by many, sent him this message. If it would please him to send the substance of the Confutation (for I dare not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon report) I would either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, or chaunge mine opinion
<pb n="27" facs="14"/>
with thankes to God for him; though for the present, I thought he failed in Indgment, Discretion, and Charity. In <hi>Iudgment.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that Doctrine was not draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne from his Text; Except this be a judicious deduction. Gentiles cast Lotts in a most serious matter, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore Christians may vse Lottery in dicing, carding, &amp;c. In <hi>Discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Because that Doctrine (though occasioned by his text, yet) so insisted vpon, incourageth gamesters in their sinfull course and buildeth vp those abuses, which the Lawes of our Land, would pull downe. In <hi>Charity;</hi> Because he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futeth me <hi>by name,</hi> (as I was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified) not having had any confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with me either by speech, or by writing, though I be his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Minister. Well; <hi>Mr. Gataker,</hi> sent me his answere to my dialogue. I acknowledge it with hearty than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.
<pb n="28" facs="15"/>
But why have I not replyed in so many yeares? I answere, <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>itò, si sat benè.</hi> To speake freely I thinke, I should never have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, in hope that the question would have died, had not <hi>Mr. Gata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> confuted my Dialogue in print▪ But now, the rather, being provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked▪ by many learned Ministers &amp; other, who tell me, that, seeing of all those whom <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, viz: <hi>Peter Martyr, Zuinglius, Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi>
      <note place="margin">10 1.</note>
      <hi>Danoeus, Perkins, Fenner,</hi> &amp;c. I onely live, I ought to reply, least my silence should give way to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piousiniquity, I am ready to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme my promise in replying. Which (indeed) I could not have done so conveniently before, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the answer, which <hi>Mr. Gata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> sent me, had not the positiue groundes of his opinion, which the printed booke hath.</p>
   <p>Before I proceed▪ I protest be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="26" facs="15"/>
God, that I esteeme <hi>Mr. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aker</hi> as a learned, painfull, and faithfull Minister, and a right honest man, and therefore pray thee <hi>(Christian Reader)</hi> that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever I write may be conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as concerning the question betweene vs, and not in any wise applied to the least praejudice of so reverend a brother, or to any of his excellent parts; So excellent, that I wonder what mooved him to publish his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in print, and the more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of many passages in his booke. <hi>First,</hi> He taketh know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge<note place="margin">1▪</note> of many enormous crimes, which accompany Dice, Cardes, &amp;c. <hi>pa. 193.</hi> &amp; in the quotations. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly;</hi>
      <note place="margin">2.</note> He giveth this rule, That, that, which is no necessary duety, but a thing indifferēt onely, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, may not be done, where is strōg presumptiō vpō good ground
<pb n="30" facs="16"/>
yet it shall spiritually endanger a mans selfe, or others, by giving oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of sinne vnto the one, or the other. <hi>pag. 107. 108. 109.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If many and greivous sinnes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend dice, cardes, &amp;c. If those ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes be too too commonly abused, as he confesseth. <hi>pa: 194.</hi> and if an indifferent thing may not be done which giveth occasion of sinne, I wonder why <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> writeth in defence of dice, &amp;c. and the more, because he graunteth, that, where the vse, and abuse of a thing are so inwrapped, and intangled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, that they cannot easily be severed the one from the other, then the vse of the thing it selfe, (if it be vnnecessary otherwise) would be wholely abandoned, <hi>pag. 262. 263. Thirdly;</hi> He sheweth in many pages▪ how <hi>severely</hi> tables, but es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially dice, be condemned by Lawes, <hi>Civill, Canonicall,</hi> and <hi>Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall,</hi>
      <pb n="31" facs="16"/>
that is, our <hi>English</hi> statutes, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e sheweth at large, <hi>Lib. 8. § 5. 8.</hi> He wisheth the Lawes were yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore severe, &amp; putt in better exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ution, <hi>pà. 206.</hi> He saith, yet our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ommon dicers may be marshalled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mong ye flock, of ye Devill's fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>owers, <hi>pa. 217.</hi> He affirmeth most <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ifelings, and Lotteries to be little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>etter than vnlawfull games, <hi>pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 20.</hi> And he teacheth, that, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>heis games, we must not give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ence to the Lawes vnder which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ee live, <hi>pa. 251.</hi> Now I wonder, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat so good a man is not affraid to offend our Law by allowing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>idden games, even Dice, as well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s Cardes, &amp;c. which consist not onely of Lottery. Here I have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to thinke, that I may have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ome more comfort in mine opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, than <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> can have in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>is; For he nameth famous, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and godly men concurring
<pb n="32" facs="17"/>
with me in opinion: But in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> multitude o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> his quotations, I find none approoving Dice in play, an whereas some learned Divines, i some sort, allow games consistin of Lott, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itt, but altogethe condemne D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e, <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> defe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth mine opinion, disapproovin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> a <hi>mixt▪</hi> as well as a <hi>mere</hi> Lott, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause (as he saith) a true Lott is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> either, <hi>pa. 126.</hi> and, He deemet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> them to be amisse, who allow Lott in game, and yet adde for a cautio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that Religionsnesse be vsed in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> action, in regard that Holy thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> must be done in an holy manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">4.</note>
      <hi>pa. 133. Fourthly,</hi> He graunteth tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Prayer specially applied to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Lott may be conceived, where th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> matter is more weighty, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> event of some consequence, <hi>pa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> And yet he holdeth, that the less<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> weighty the matter is, wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Lott is vsed, the lawfuller the Lott
<pb n="33" facs="17"/>
      <hi>is, pag. 111.</hi> The reason, why I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at this passage, shall be given in my Reply. The last passage now to be observed as matter of my wondering, is this; Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, he confidently affirmeth that we may not doe ought without warrant, <hi>pag. 301.</hi> Sufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth the same, because such an Act is not done of Faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not free from sinne, <hi>Rom. 14. 23.</hi> but is a mere presumption, and tempting of God, <hi>pag. 313.</hi> and <hi>quot. A▪</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> and Earnestly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooveth one kinde of Lottery (why not all, against which the same reason is of like validity?) because not found revealed in any word of God, but brought in either by Sathan, or by some of his instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments who are addicted to Vanity, <hi>pag. 315.</hi> and <hi>316.</hi> and, yet he avoucheth, That it is a sufficient warrant for the vse of Lottes,
<pb n="34" facs="18"/>
In that the oppugners, being lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, can say nothing against them▪ but what hath beene, or may be sufficiently answered, <hi>pag. 235.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>May I not wonder that so judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a scholler doth not observe this discrepance? Lottery is vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if not warranted by the word which positiō supposeth the Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to be perfect, as is the Authou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thereof, and 2. Lottery is lawful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> if Learned men can say nothing ou of the Word against it. Which po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition supposeth <hi>two things,</hi> viz That the Word is like the Lawes o men, that is, Imperfect, as be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours therof; and, That Learne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> men cannot so faile in Diligence o reading, Clearenesse of vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and Firmenesse of Memory but that▪ if there were in the Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> anything against Lottery, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> could nor but see it. Well; It ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> be seene shortly, how <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,
<pb n="35" facs="18"/>
Vnderstanding, and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry have served him in defenoing Lusorious Lotts. In the meane while, <hi>Sufficiency</hi> of his answering is but vpon the Triall, and not yet adjudged.</p>
   <p>All theis passages well reveiwed by <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> I should thinke he cannot wonder that a man of 64. <hi>yeares compleate,</hi> (and therefore his wittes may faile) doth wonder that so godly, wise, and learned a man, the faculties of whose minde are at the best, did not say to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, before he preached, much more before he penned this luso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious doctrine, Let Baal plead for<note place="margin">Iudg. 6▪ 31. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>2. Esa. 5. 18</note> himselfe; and, Theis gamesters shall, without any encouragment from me, draw on their iniquity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ith theis cordes of vanity; and the rather, because he acknowledgeth that accoumpt is to be given vnto God of gaming <hi>pa. 261.</hi> If of the act
<pb n="36" facs="19"/>
much more of justifying it. Fro m which account good Lord deliver me. For I feare, that in iustifying lusorious Lottes, I should put false spectacles on a gamester's nose, whereby the bridge seemeth broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, than it is, and so he falleth in without feare, to vse <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, <hi>pag. 264.</hi> But <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> beleveth, that he hath written the truth, (Preface to the Reader) and is confident that truth is to be knowne, especially concerning matters of common practise, <hi>pag. 263.</hi> and giveth <hi>foure</hi> reasons, by which he was mooved to defend<note place="margin">1.</note> lusorious Lottes, <hi>pag. 264.</hi> The <hi>first</hi> is, To draw men from Superstition in restraining themselves, when God doth not restraine them. This beggeth the question, (as I hope) will appeare in the Reply.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> A 2. motive is, Because arguments against lusorious Lottes have made
<pb n="37" facs="19"/>
many stagger in the necessary vse of serious civill Lottes. It may be so some failing in their judgment: But it may be also, that many moe will be made to stagger by reading <hi>Mr. Gatakers</hi> exceptions against ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments for, and cautions, in those serious Civill Lottes, <hi>Cap. 5.</hi> and by his <hi>Maxime,</hi> [The lesse weighty the matter is, wherein a Lott is vsed, the lawfuller the Lott is, <hi>pag. 111.]</hi> A 3. motive is, To take away<note place="margin">3▪</note> much heart-burning; Nay, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this justifying Lusorious Lottes will not onely cause more heart-burning; but incourage also gamesters to overcrow such, as are scrupulous. For, if many well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected have beene constrained, in regard of scruple, in this kinde, to straine themselves to some inconveniences by refusall of those games, when by those, whom they had dependance vpon,
<pb n="38" facs="20"/>
vpon or familiarity withall, they have beene vrged occasionally therevnto (which to prevent here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, is a 4. cause of his writing) How will those supporters, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliars insult vpon the scrupulous▪ now they have so learned a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone</hi> of their gaming? Some have strained themselves, to some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences for not pledging drunken <hi>Healths,</hi> being drinke offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings to <hi>Bacchus.</hi> To prevent which hereafter, should <hi>Mr. Gata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> doe well, vnto aedification, to preach, and write in Iustification of these <hi>Healths?</hi> The summe of his causes (as he expresseth himselfe in his preface to the Reader) is, To sett at Liberty the intangled consciences of Godly disposed persons. Indeed; If any conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, simply for playing with Lottes, should seeke his his satisfaction in private, then if <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="39" facs="20"/>
him by his grounds (supposed true) it were not amisse. But is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doctrine, though true, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted vpon both by preaching, and printing, and that affirming matter in question, and of no necessary vse? I say, <hi>Affirming,</hi> remembring the holy wisedome of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> who decreed touching offensive things (yet some of them lawfull, if conveniently vsed) onely <hi>negatively,</hi> and deemeth it not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary<note place="margin">Act. 15. 28. 29.</note> to decree affirmatively things that were then, and might be in vse for a time. Many (I feare too many) learned Divines approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve Vsury in their Iudgment, thouh condemned by Law. Yet none, that I know, ever insisted vpon the Iustification thereof by preaching and printing. Againe; Was there ever any so troubled with playing with Lotts? I doubt it; But without doubt thousandes will now more
<pb n="40" facs="21"/>
boldly vse lusorious Lotts without regard of the cautions, in theis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious times. As Vsurers regard not the cautions which Divines sett downe. For it is enough to them, that some godly Divines affirme Vsury to be lawfull. O that <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> had considered what he writeth, <hi>pag. 107.</hi> before cited, and what he writeth, <hi>pag. 103.</hi> and <hi>104.</hi> viz: Where inconveniences, that shall necessarily, or in good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, appeare to accompany the thing questioned, or ensu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vpon the doing thereof, shall be such, and so great as the Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, which stand on the other side, shall not be able to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, there that action is worthily disallowed as Inconvenient, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Lott consequently vnlawfull, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> he writeth in his spirituall Watch <hi>pag. 27.</hi> viz: The rifer any evill i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in those places, or ages we live i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="41" facs="21"/>
the more carefull should we be to shunne, and avoide such a sinne. No doubt he would have taken heede how by writing he make way to the sinne of, or by, Lusorious Lotts. Many Divines and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent men, though of opinion that Lusorious mixed Lotts may be vsed lawfully, yet wish that <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> had never published his booke. For a running horse (say they) needeth no spurring. For my part I wish, that <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi> had beene affected in writing, as he professeth himselfe to be in the vse of luso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Lottes, <hi>pag. 266.</hi> Wel; What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever he writeth <hi>dogmatically,</hi> he wisheth thee (good Reader) to imitate him in▪ his practise, to witt, That, albeit in judgment thou art rightly informed of the truth concerning the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of theis games in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; yet in godly discretion,
<pb n="42" facs="22"/>
thou wouldst rather abandō them, considering the too too common, and ordinary abuse of them, and that many (it may be) among whom thou livest may remaine vnresol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and vnsatisfied, touching the lawfulnes of them, <hi>pag. 267.</hi> I desire the same, and therewith a suspen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thy judgment vntill thou hast well considered my <hi>Dialogue, Mr. Gatakers</hi> answeres, and my <hi>Reply,</hi> together with mine answere to his positive groundes. Here I promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se (with <hi>Mr. Gataker, pag. 128.)</hi> to raze what I have reared, if my <hi>Reply</hi> and aunsweres be prooved insuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, and so commend thee to God, and to the Word of his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, which is able to build further. Onely, consider what I say, and the Lord give thee vnderstanding in<note place="margin">Act. 20. 32. 2. Tim▪ 2. 7.</note> all things.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>
            <hi>14.</hi> Septemb. 1620.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>