<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HO∣NOVRABLE, IV∣DITIOVS, AND GE∣NEROVS; Sr. EDVVARD SACKVILE, Knight of the Bath; My Honourable, and singular good MASTER.</title>
           <author>Reynolds, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100002_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20993</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7367</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100002</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HO∣NOVRABLE, IV∣DITIOVS, AND GE∣NEROVS; Sr. EDVVARD SACKVILE, Knight of the Bath; My Honourable, and singular good MASTER.</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the court or Instructions for courtiers : Digested into two books. Written in French by the noble, and learned iuris-consull Monsr Denys de Refuges, Councellor of Estate, and many tymes ambassador (in foraigne parts) for ye two last French kings his masters* Done into English by Iohn Reynolds</title>
                 <author>Refuge, Monsieur de (Eustache)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lee, William 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 189, 21, 189, 63 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>TO THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, IV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DITIOVS, AND GE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEROVS; S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. EDVVARD SACKVILE, Knight of the <hi>Bath;</hi> My Honourable, and singular good MASTER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F your curious Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had not sought this excellent Treatise of the Court, my Ignorance had not
<pb facs="8"/>
found him; for I ingeniously con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, that before you first wrate me for him to <hi>Paris,</hi> I neuer heard of him, when led by the excellency of your choyce, and the soliditie of your approbation, vpon the peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall thereof, I was soone induced, both to affect him for his Fidelitie, and to admire him for his Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; when considering (because knowing) that you (resembling your selfe) not onely cherish Wit, Courtship, Iudgement and Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in your selfe, but also honour it generally in all men, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in the Noble and Learned Author hereof, <hi>Monsieur de Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> (so famous to France for his wholesome councell at home, and happy Lega ions abroad), I vpon these foundations eraised the struc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="8"/>
of this resolution to deuest this his Worke out of his French habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liments, and to sure him in our in English atire, that England aswell as France might participate in the acquaintance, and enioy the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of this his accomplished Courtier, which hauing done, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in a phrase and stile, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnworthy the lustre and sublimaty of his Originall (which is still subiect to lose a part of her prestine Grace and Beauty in her Metamorphosis) albeit your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Trauels haue showne you so great variety of Courts, that you are farre more capable to teach, then be taught in matters of this nature; yet I had all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of the World (as well of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie as Merit) to proffer vp the
<pb facs="9"/>
first Booke hereof, to the Honour of your Patronage, and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of your Honour, sith it is not a Donation, but a Retribution in lastly restoring you backe that in English, which (as before) you formerly gaue me in French, in the perfection of which exquisite Tongue (without either flattering you, or infringing the truth) I may boldly affirme, few English can paralell, none excell you. Againe, I did it in your seruice, it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yours by propriety, I did it out of mine owne priuate obligation to your immerited fauours, it is therefore yours in the right of debt and requitall: which considered, before I shall bee so happy to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face my arreareges in some more reall and serious manner, I hope
<pb facs="9"/>
you will pardon my Zeale, though condemne my Ambition herein, especially sith it is addressed and deuoted you by him, who will eternally remaine both zealous and Ambitious, as well to enioy the honour to liue, as the felicitie to dye</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest Seruant, IOHN REYNOLDS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>