<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian
Reader. S.</title>
           <author>Rogers, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100329_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23061</idno>
           <idno type="STC">950</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100329</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian
Reader. S.</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A right Christian treatise, entituled S. Augustines praiers: published in more ample sort than yet it hath bin in the English tong; purged from diuers superstitious points; and adorned with manifold places of the S. Scripture, by Thomas Rogers. Wherevnto is annexed Saint Augustines psalter: translated and quoted by the same T.R</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 218, 24 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian
Reader. S.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this place both to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
thee, beloued, and that
thou also the better maist,
if it please thee, answere
mine aduersaries, I thinke
it my part to show the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
of my translating, correcting, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning
this booke. For some perhaps, to
translate that which is once done alreadie,
wil thinke it vanitie; to amend that which
no godlie man would euer enterprise to
correct, wil iudge it presumption; and to
adorne that which was, though often im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed,
yet neuer so put-forth, wil deeme
it curiositie. And so I shal be counted vane
for my translating; ouer-bold for my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting;
and verie curious for my quoting
this booke. It stands me therefore vpon to
show the causes of dooing what I haue
done; wherein I wil be the more briefe,
because else-where<note n="a" place="margin">In the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle dedicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie before S. Augustines Priuate talke with God: and also in the second Epistle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of Christ.</note> I haue somwhat tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
these general points, and what there
I haue spoken hath apt relation vnto this
place.</p>
   <p>And first for my translating (to ouer-passe
in silence the wel acceptation of S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines
<hi>Priuate talke with God,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Causes why this booke was transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, being in English be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> by the godlie
zelous, for whose sake I did bestowe my
paines; and the approbation of the same
by the Honorable of famous memorie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster
Secretarie Wilson, for whose iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
sake chieflie, which I knew was verie
learned and sound, I choase him to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone
thereof: sufficient causes both to
encourage me to go forward, and to cleere
<pb facs="3"/>
me from al suspition either of vanitie, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption,
or curiositie for doing as I haue
done) I saie, the rather I put this booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
English, for that I saw the other, before
in our vulgar tongue (whosoeuer was the
translator of the same, or what copie soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
the Printer folowed) was verie vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect;
as by comparing this my translation
with the other in English, and both with
the Latine copie, may easilie appeere. And
therfore that neither the aduersarie might
haue iust occasion to carpe; nor the godlie
to complaine hence-foorth that it is not
perfected, I thought good faithfulie to
translate the same. Furthermore were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
at al, as more than halfe was left-out,
yet good cause I had to translate it, both
because of the errors therein contained,
which were necessarilie to be corrected;
and of the manifold sentences of holie
scripture comprehended therein, which
were needful to be quoted. So that, both
that the godlie might not be either infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
or offended by the one; and that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
might be allured to reade, and in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
confirmed by the other, I tooke the
translation thereof vpon me, for otherwise
neither could the faults be rightlie amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
nor the places dulie applied.</p>
   <p>Secundarilie,<note place="margin">Causes of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting this booke.</note> my correcting of this
booke, I haue hope no good man wil mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.
For I did it not rashlie of presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
but with the testimonie of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science;
with the warrant of God his word;
and after the example too of such, who for
doing the like are not dispraised. For if the
Spirit of God command vs, <hi>To trie euerie
<pb facs="3"/>
Spirit</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">1. Iohn. 4, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>; <hi>to trie al things, and to keepe that
which is good</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">1. Thes. 5. verse. 21.</note>; <hi>to doe al things vnto edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 14. verse. 26.</note>, not vnto the destruction of soules;
&amp;, if both those noble &amp; good men of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea
did examine the doctrine euen of the
Apostles themselues<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 17, 10. 11.</note>; and diuers godlie
men in our age haue tried, and purged the
writings of other men, &amp; that to the great
benefit of the Church, and their owne
commendation: I trust I am not blame
worthie for trieng, and for chusing that
which good is, and refusing that which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
might infect, or be offensiue to the
godlie, but should do verie il, both against
God, against man, and against my consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
too, if I did not so, hauing both so ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
a commander to obeie, and so worthie
examples to imitate. Againe, by the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
euen of anie indifferent iudge, I may
with as good, and better auctoritie either
quite-omit, or Christianlie conuert that
which il is vnto good purpose, than some
euil disposed persons either altogether
leaue-out, or wickedlie change that which
good is to the ingraffing of il opinions; as
did both <hi>Io. Baptist a Ficklerus</hi> a Papist in his
handeling that booke entituled, <hi>De iure
Magistratus in Subditos;</hi> and also <hi>Iohan. de
Ales</hi> another Papist in corrupting the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
Psalmes of Dauid, and applieng them
most sacrilegiouslie vnto the virgine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.
And thus brieflie for my correction in
general.</p>
   <p>Now furthermore would be showed par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularlie
what I haue corrected;<note place="margin">What things corrected.</note> how I
haue corrected the same; and why. The
places which I haue corrected, be either
<pb facs="4"/>
manifestlie erroneous; or scapes vnwit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinglie,
for so charitie and circumstances
wil me to iudge, committed.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Of the former sort be praiers which tend
either to make works meritorious,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Faults mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festlie erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous.</note>
      <hi>as
where among other things petition is
made by the Auctor, that he may</hi> Amando
mala sua red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nere<note n="f" place="margin">Med. cap. 1</note>; <hi>and haue teares gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi>
Quae peccatorum possint dissoluere vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la
<note n="g" place="margin">Medit. cap. 40.</note>: <hi>or to make Saints intercessors for vs,
as doth this praier vnto the House of God,</hi>
Tu d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>c, tu roga Deum, vt dignum me faciat par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipatione
gloriae tuae<note n="h" place="margin">Medit. cap. 20.</note>; <hi>againe vnto the same
House of God,</hi> Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ent me merita tua, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniant
prauitati meae sanctae &amp; purissimae
orationes tuae, quae inefficaces apud Deum nulla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus
esse possint<note n="i" place="margin">Medit. cap. 20.</note>; <hi>so doth this,</hi> Da mihi effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum
petitionis, &amp; desiderij mei intercedente, &amp;
orante, &amp; impetrante gloriosa virgine, genetrice
tua Maria, Domina mea, cum omnibus sanctis<note n="k" place="margin">Med. cap. 35. &amp; ca. 36.</note>;
<hi>and this,</hi> Da mihi gratiam lachrimarum, &amp;c.
propter merita, &amp; orationes corum, qui tibi pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerunt,
&amp; deuotissimè s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ruierunt<note n="l" place="margin">Medit. cap. 36.</note>; <hi>and this
especialie,</hi> Exa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>di nos Trinitas sancta, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serua
ab omni malo, &amp;c. per orationes Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charum,
per merita Prophetarum, per suffragia
Apostolorum, per constantiam Martyrum, per
fidem Consessorum, per cast<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tatem Virginum, &amp;
per intercessionem omnium Sanctorum, qui tibi
placuerunt ab mitio mundi<note n="m" place="margin">Medit. cap. 40.</note>: <hi>or praiers fina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
either vnto the dead, as is both the
whole</hi> 24. <hi>Chapter after the Latine copie;
and these also in another place</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">Medit. cap. 40.</note>, Sancta,
&amp; immaculata virgo, Dei genetrix, Maria, &amp;
Mater Domini nostri Iesu Christi, interuenire
pro me digneris apud illum cuius meruisti effici
templum. S. Michaël, S. Gabriel, S. Raphaël,
<pb facs="4"/>
S. chori Angelorum, Archangelorum, Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charum,
at{que} Prophetarum, &amp;c. vos rogare praesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,
vt pro me culpabili ipsi Deo supplicare dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemini,
quatenus de faucibus Diaboli, &amp; de mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
perpetua merear liberari: <hi>or praiers for the
dead, as this is,</hi> Praesta Domine, &amp;c. defunctis
fidelibus requiem sempiternam<note n="o" place="margin">Medit. cap. 40.</note>, <hi>Againe</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">Medit. cap. 40.</note>,
Omnibus etiam Christianis defunctis adiutorium
praestare digneris, &amp; defunctis fidelibus absoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem,
&amp; requiem sempiternam per aeterna saecula.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Of the later sort be these especialie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Seapes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wittinglie committed.</note>
      <hi>and
such like words in one chapter</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">Medit. cap. 6.</note>, Respice
clementissime Rex, qui patitur, &amp; reminiscere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignus
pro quo patitur, &amp;c. Candet nudum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,
rubet cruentum latus, tensa arent vescera
&amp;c. <hi>and these, and such like in another</hi>
      <note n="r" place="margin">Medit. cap. 7.</note>,
Ego iniquè egi, tu poena mulctaris, ego crimen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didi,
tu torturae subijceris; ego superb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ui, tu humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaris;
ego tumui, tu attenu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ris, &amp;c. <hi>Such is the
whole</hi> 19. <hi>Chap. in a maner after the Latine
copie, and finalie, so be these, and such like,
(for to recite al the words, I thinke it not
conuenient) in another</hi>
      <note n="s" place="margin">Medit. cap. 41.</note>, Hei mihi, quia vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere
non potui Dominum angelorum, humiliatum
ad cōuersationem hominū, &amp;c. Vtinam cum feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce
Ioseph Dominū meū de cruce deposuissem, aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matibus
condijssem, in sepulchro collocassem, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>In which my correction, I haue had spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial
care to leaue as little out as might be,<note place="margin">Maner of correcting this Booke.</note>
and therefore did I thinke it better to
change vnto good purpose that which is
contrarie vnto the Christian faith, where
aptlie I could so do, than quite to omit
whatsoeuer was amisse. In which respect I
haue changed the 24. Chapter after the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine
copie in my traslation, the 23. which is
a praier vnto Saincts, as also these words,
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>Propter merita, &amp; orationes, &amp;c.</hi>
      <note n="t" place="margin">Medit. cap. 36.</note>, and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
them vnto Christ. The other errors I
haue quite left out. Likewise among the
scapes, some things I haue omitted, and
some things I haue changed. I haue omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
the whole 19. Chap. in the Latine co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie,
which is the cause I haue one Chapter
lesse in my translation, than is in the Latine:
and also these words, and the rest tending
to the like effect<note n="u" place="margin">Medit. cap. 41.</note>, <hi>Hei mihi quia videre non
potui Dominum angelorum, humiliatum ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersationem
hominum, &amp;c. vtinam cum felice Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph
Dominum meū de cruce deposuissem, aroma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus
codijssem, in sepulchro collocassem, &amp;c.</hi> That
which I haue altered, are y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rest specified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:
the onlie difference betwene the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine
copie and mine in those places is, for
that I turne the present tence into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terperfect
tence, which agreeth to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> truth.</p>
   <p>It remaineth now that I do yeeld the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
why I haue corrected these faults.<note place="margin">Special rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting the errors and scapes in this booke.</note> And
first for the errors: the chiefest causes of
my correcting them was, for that they be
contrarie to Scripture, and might both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
the simple, and coole the zeale euen of
the strong; but another was, because I saw
manie places in this booke did ouerthrow
them quite. As first the places for merits
are ouerthrowne, as by other, so especialie
by these, <hi>I acknowledge that no penance can
satisfie for my sinnes</hi>
      <note n="x" place="margin">August. praiers. ch. 38. pa. 198.</note>, and againe, <hi>If thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminest
my righteousnes, lo, I stinke like dead ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion</hi>
      <note n="y" place="margin">August. praiers. ch. 39. pa. 206.</note>. Secondlie, intercession vnto Saints,
with praieng vnto the dead, is ouerthrowne
by these and such like places, <hi>What other
intercessor should I direct vnto thee, but euen him</hi>
      <note n="z" place="margin">August. praiers. ch. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. pag. 23.</note>, <hi>who is the reconciliation for our sinnes, and sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="5"/>
at thy right hand, making request for vs.</hi> For,
<hi>what is it to cal vnto the truth in truth</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">August. in the same cha. pa. 21.</note>, <hi>but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
to cal vnto the Father in the name of the
Sonne</hi> (not of Saincts {reversed ?}) <hi>There is nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde
to adde, for I haue sent mine whole hope
vnto thee</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">August. praiers. ch. 8. pag. 35.</note>. <hi>I haue directed thy beloued Sonne
mine aduocate, vnto thee, and haue sent thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
child to be a mediator betweene me and
thee: I haue sent I saie an intercessor, through
whome</hi> (not through Marie, or anie other
Sainct) <hi>I hope to get pardon. For what is more
acceptable</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">August. praiers. ch. 5. pag. 21.</note>, <hi>than to cal vpon the begetter in the
name of his onlie begotten? to moue the Father vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
mercie, in the recordation of his Sonne? to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate
the wrath of the King, through naming of
his deere child? &amp;c.</hi> Thirdlie, praieng that the
faithful departed out of this life, may
haue rest, is also in diuers places ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne,
as where it is said<note n="d" place="margin">August. praiers. ch. 22. pag. 90.</note>, <hi>Happie is the
soule; which departing from the earthlie bodie, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
directlie into heauen, secure it is, and quiet,
&amp;c! Oh happie are al thy Saincts, o Christ, which
haue passed ouer the sea of this mortalitie</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">August. praiers. ch. 23. pag. 93.</note>, <hi>&amp; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
vnto the hauen of perpetual quietnes, secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
and peace, where they are at rest, and alwaie
ioiful, &amp; merie!</hi> And therfore considering this
contrarietie in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Auctor, I thought it best
to publish those things which were conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> true faith, and to omit whatsoeuer
sauored either of heresie, or superstition.</p>
   <p>And for the scapes, I am to yeeld the
same reason, which I haue giuen for my
correcting the errors. For as they, for the
most part, be contrarie vnto the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:
so be diuers places in this booke, as
easelie I could showe, against them. I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
onlie the scapes contained in the 41.
<pb facs="6"/>
Chapter after the Latine copie: the which,
as also the other scapes and errors, I am
persuaded, were the Auctor liuiug, hee
would gladlie either amend himselfe, or
suffer them to be reformed. I often make
mention of the Latine copie, because that
hath one Chapter more than this hath,
which commeth to passe by leauing out
the 19. Chapter.</p>
   <p>Thirdlie,<note place="margin">Causes of quoting this booke with places of Scripture.</note> and last of al, I haue adorned
this booke with places of Scripture, both
to show from whence that which good is
both is, and ought to be taken: and also to
moue the zealous Christian the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestlie
to reade this booke. For when it is
apparent, that praiers, and meditations be
deriued out of the pure fountane of Gods
holie word, manie are not a little not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
pricked forward vnto the reading, but
also strengthened and comforted much in
mind, when they doe reade them.</p>
   <p>Which being so, I trust thou wilt accept
my trauel in good part, and at the leastwise
reade this booke as diligentlie now, being
both made perfect, corrected, and adorned,
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> earst thou hast done when it neither had
so manie praiers in it by halfe as now it
hath; nor was so pure fró error<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; nor so au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorized
with the warrant of Gods word
for the comfort of thy soule, as now it is.</p>
   <p>And thus I commend both thee and my
selfe into his hands who hath not onelie
made, but also redeemed vs for his owne
glorie, and praise.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>The tenth of Iune. An. 1581.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord, THO. ROGERS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>