<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Faults escaped in the Printing.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100526_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01943</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1209</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100526</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Faults escaped in the Printing.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The composition or Making of the moste excellent and pretious oil called oleum magistrale : First published by the commaundement of the King of Spain, vvith the maner hovv to apply it particulerly. The which oyl cureth these diseases folowi [n] g ... Also the third book of Galen of curing of pricks and wounds of sinowes. A method for curing of vvounds in the ioynts, and the maner how to place them. Abreef [sic] gathering togither of certain errours which the common chirurgians dayly vse ... Faithfully gathered and translated into English by George Baker chirurgian. 1574</title>
                 <author>Baker, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 51, 3 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="69"/>
   <head>¶ Faults escaped in the Printing.</head>
   <p>¶ Note wheras you finde this letter (a) that dooth signifie the first side of the leaf, and this letter (b) the second side.</p>
   <p>In the first page, read (the third Book of <hi>Galen</hi> of the composition of medicines in general). Then in the first page of the Epistle to the Reader the xij. &amp; xvi. lines, for iudications read (indications).</p>
   <p>In the 11. leaf a. the xiij. and xiiij, lines read <hi>(drachmas)</hi> for <hi>drachmas,</hi> &amp; <hi>(Opo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponacis)</hi> for <hi>Apoponax.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the 14. leaf a. and the xix, line read (the sixth he dooth) for he dooth vi. loose.</p>
   <p>In the 26. leaf a. and the vi. line read, <hi>(Maron)</hi> for <hi>Maron.</hi> And in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> xij. line of the same read <hi>(phou idest)</hi> for <hi>phoud est</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the 27. leaf a. the xviij. line. red (the childes parēts did send for <hi>Galen</hi>) for, did send him to <hi>Galen.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the 30. leaf a the first line read (Paps or Brests) for, Dugs.</p>
   <p>In the 31. leaf a. the iiij. and v. line leue out, the whole and sound partes.</p>
   <p>In the 33. leaf b. the xv. line read <hi>(Olei mirtiles)</hi> for, <hi>Olei mirh.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the 36 leaf a. the iij. line read (bowing for, lowing.</p>
   <pb facs="70"/>
   <p>In the 38. leaf a. the xvi. line read (no apostume in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> groin: then acording) for Apostume: according.</p>
   <p>In the 41. leaf a the iiij. line read (qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie) for, qualtitie. And in b. the xxiij. line (read woūd potions) for, wunted potions Fo. 47. line .6. read, is none other thing,</p>
   <p>Gentle Reader I shall most hartely desire thee that if in the reading this work other faults you finde then heer is noted not rashly to cōdemne the Author for assure your self that by his wil none should haue escaped, and though the Printer be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so careful, yet in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting some wil escape.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Vale</salute>
   </closer>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>