<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the GRAVE and GODLIE VVISE, in Highest Authoritie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100765_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07549</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17928</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100765</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the GRAVE and GODLIE VVISE, in Highest Authoritie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The custumers apology : That is to say, a generall answere to informers of all sortes, and their iniurious complaints, against the honest reputation of the collectors of her Maiesties custumes, specially in the out-portes of this realme. Written onely for vnderstanding readers and wise in highest authoritie, to reade and discerne by. Alwaies prouided, in reading reade all, or nothing at all</title>
                 <author>Milles, Tho (Thomas)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the GRAVE and GODLIE VVISE, <hi>in Highest Authoritie.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> GENTLEMAN a friend and louer of learning,</hi> comming into a free Schoole, wher diuers yong Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers were learning their Grammer, desirous to feele how they thryud at their Bookes by some familiar question; demaunded, (their Huishers standing by) <hi>When an English is giuen to be made into Latine, whats first to be done?</hi> The answere is easie, namely, <hi>To seeke out the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Verbe:</hi> yet all stoode silent, and halfe amazed, till <hi>ONE</hi> at the last (the Question est-soones repeated, and hee vrged to say,<note place="margin">Men affecting to doe the Prince and Common-wealth seruice, in some honest calling, enter the charge of Custumes simply, &amp; doubting no harme.</note>
      <hi>What was to bee done</hi>) replied; <hi>NO HARME SIR I HOPE, at least THAT I VVOT OF.</hi> Which the Gentleman taking in very good part, as suspecting rather ignorance in the Huishers, then want of wit in the Schollers, departed, smyling.</p>
   <p>Most <hi>REVEREND</hi> and <hi>RIGHT HONORABLE.</hi> This Question &amp; Answere includeth the present estate of al the students in the Schoole of her <hi>Maiesties Custumes,</hi> where such as the Teachers be, such are the Schollers. There is a reason for al things. And the reason hereof is not so much, for want of wit or will in the Learners, <hi>To deale iustly betweene the Prince and her People</hi> (which in this kind of doctrine is supposed to be the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal verbe</hi>) as in the ignorant &amp; indiscrete Husshers, who whilst the graue <hi>Masters</hi> and <hi>Moderators</hi> of the Schoole, were distrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and busied in the studie &amp; practise of higher points of learning; haue vsed no method, but bearing the Schollers.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>"Qui paria esse volunt peccata, Ipsique laborant</l>
      <l>"Cum ventum ad verum est: Sensus moresque repugnant,</l>
      <l>"Atque <hi>ipsa vtilitas, Iusti</hi> prope mater &amp; <hi>Aequi.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <p>Which kind of discipline, discouraging al men &amp; driuing many good wits from the Schoole, to the secrete iniury of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; forcde me to my Booke, and as well as I could, to <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lise</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>my lesson, meaning thereby with the foresaid plaine Scholler <hi>(NO HARME AT ALL)</hi> such therefore as it is, I haue briefely set downe in the <hi>Discours</hi> following. The Matter whereof being partly drawne from mine owne Patience and experience, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obserued and learned from others: The Forme is meerely mine owne, and hath for my warrant the Rules of my Grammer.</p>
   <p>But since <hi>Things are then wel done, when things are wel taken;</hi> to cleare and acquite me from partiall clamor, or the sinne of presumption, The Will appliant to Reason, is guiltlesse of passion, and Nature ouerborne appeales to Necessitie. <hi>Quae quod cogit, ipsa, solet vti{que} defendere.</hi> Hard therefore and aboue measure extreame should their cases appeare, that still subiect to beating, might neither bemoane themselues, nor be suffred to crie. And so much the rather, when as <hi>(SO FAR AS I VVOT OF)</hi> in all their Complaints,<note place="margin">The Lawe of Nature and Nations both, allow all men, to stand in defence of their Callings and honest Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> there is nothing concluded nor included, at least intended therby, but a natural defence of their honest reputation in that kind of Calling, which the Law it selfe by great wisdome hath laid out, and reserued <hi>For men of the best sorte onely,</hi> and a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Zeale to find out thereby <hi>The principall Verbe.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>