<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Loue and Liue.
TO ALL THE NOBI∣litie,
and all other in office, God
graunte wisedome and all thinges nede∣full
for the preseruation of their
Estates. Amen.</title>
           <author>B., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100555_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02389</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1252</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100555</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Loue and Liue.
TO ALL THE NOBI∣litie,
and all other in office, God
graunte wisedome and all thinges nede∣full
for the preseruation of their
Estates. Amen.</title>
                 <author>B., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The last part of the Mirour for magistrates : wherein may be seene by examples passed in this realme, vvith howe greenous [sic] plagues, vyces are punished in great princes &amp; magistrats, and hovv frayle and vnstable vvorldly prosperity is founde, where fortune seemeth mos highly to fauour</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 183, that is 171, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Loue and Liue.
TO ALL THE NOBI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,
and all other in office, God
graunte wisedome and all thinges nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
for the preseruation of their
Estates. Amen.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lato among many of his</hi>
notable sentences concernyng the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of a common weale hath this: well is
that Realme gouerned, in which the ambici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
desire not to beare office. Whereby you
may perceiue (right honourable) what of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices
are, where they be duely executed: not gainfull spoyles
for the gredy to hunt for, but painefull toyles for the heady to
bee charged with. You may perceiue also by this sentence,
there is nothing more necessary in a common weale, then that
Magistrates be diligent and trusty in their charges.</p>
   <p>¶And sure in whatsoeuer Realme such prouision is made, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
officers be forced to do their duties: there is it as hard a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
to get an officer, as it is in other places to repulse &amp; shift of
those that with flattery, brybes, and other shiftes, sue &amp; preace
for offices. For the ambitious (that is to saye prollers for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
or gayne) seeke not for offices to helpe other, for whych
cause officers are ordained: but with the vndoing of other, to
enrich themselues. And therfore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ar them once of this bayt, &amp;
force them to do their dueties, then will they geue more to be
rid from their charges, than they did at y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> first to come by e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ē:
For they seeke onely their priuate profite. And therfore, where
<pb facs="3"/>
the ambitious seeke no office: there no doubt, offices are duely
ministred. And whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e offices are duely ministred, it cannot be
chosen, but the people are good, whereof must nedes follow a
good common weale. For if the magistrates be good, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
cannot be ill. Thus the goodnes or badnes of any Realme
lieth in the goodnes or badnes of the Rulers. And therfore not
without great cause do the holy Appostles so earnestly charg
vs to pray for the magistra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es: For in dede the wealth &amp; quiet
of euery common weale, the disorder also and miseries of the
same, come specially thorough them. I neede not go eyther to
the <hi>Romaines</hi> or <hi>Greekes</hi> for the profe hereof, neither yet to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
Iewes, or other nations: whose common weales haue alway
florished whyle their magistrates were good, and decayed and
ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to ruyne, when vici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>us men had the gouernement.</p>
   <p>Out countrey stories (if we reade and marke them) wil show
vs examples enow, would God we had not sene mo thā enow.
I purpose not to stand herevpon the particulars, because they
be in parte setforth in the tragedies folowing. Yet by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> waye
this I note (wishing all other to doe the like) namely, that as
good gouernours haue neuer lacked their deserued praises: so
haue not the bad escaped infamy, besides such plagues as are
horrible to heare of. For God (y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ordeiner of offices) although
he suffer them for punishment of the people to be often occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied
of such, as are rather spoilers and Iudasses, than toilers
or Iustices (whom the scriptures cal Hypocrits) yet suffereth
he them not to scape vnpunished, because they dishonour him.
For it is Gods own office, yea his chief office which they beare
and abuse. For as Iustice is the chief vertue, so is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ministra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
thereof, the chiefest office: and therfore hath God establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
it with the chiefest name, honouring and calling Kinges
and all officers vnder them by his owne name: Gods. Ye be al
Gods, as many as haue in your charge any ministration of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice.
What a foule shame were it for any nowe to take vpon
them the name and office of God, and in their doings to shew
<pb facs="3"/>
themselues deuils? God cannot of Iustice, but plague suche
shamelesse presumption and hipocrisie, and that with shamful
death, diseases, or infamye. Howe he hath plagued euil rulers
from time to time, in other nations, you may see gathred in
<hi>Bochas</hi> boke intituled <hi>The fall of Princes,</hi> trāslated into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish
by <hi>Lydgate</hi> a Monke of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Abbey of Bury in Suff. How
he hath delt with some of our countrymen your auncestours,
for sundry vices not yet left, this boke named, <hi>A Mirrour for
Magistrates,</hi> shall in parte pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>inye set forth before your eyes
which boke I humbly offer vnto your honours, beseching you
to accept it fauorably. For here, as in a mirror or lokīg glasse
you shal se if any vice be foūd, how the like hath ben punished
in other heretofore, wherby admonished, I trust it will bee a
good occasiō to moue mē to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> soner amēdmēt. This is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chief
end why this booke is setforth, which God graūt it may talke
according to the maner of the makers. The worke was beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>̄
&amp; part of it printed in quene Maries time, but staid by such as
thē were chief in office, neuertheles, through y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meanes of the
right honorable <hi>Hēry Lord Stafford,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first part was licēced,
&amp; imprinted y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first yeare of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> raign of this our most noble and
vertuous Quene, &amp; dedicated to your honours with this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face,
Since w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> time, although I wāted such help as before, yet
the said good Lord <hi>Stafford</hi> hath not ceased to cal vpō me, to
publish so much therof as I had gottē at other mēs hands, so
y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> through his Lordships earnest meanes, I haue now also set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth
another part, conteining as much as I could obtaine at
y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hands of my frends: Which in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> name of al the authours, I
hūbly dedicate vnto your honours, instātly wishing, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it may
so like &amp; de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>te your minds, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> your chereful receiuīg thereof▪
may encourage worthy wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s to enterprise &amp; performe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> test.
Which assone as I may procure. I entēd through Gods leaue
&amp; your fauorable allowance, to publish with all expedicion.</p>
   <p>In the meane whyle my Lordes and Gods, (for so It may cal
you) I moste humbly besech your honours fauorably to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb facs="4"/>
this rude worke, and diligentlye to reade and consider it.
And although you shal find in it, that some haue for their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
bin enuied and brought vnto misery: yet cease not you to
be vertuous, but do your office to the vttermost. Embrace
vertue and suppresse the contrary, both in your selues
and other, so shall God whose officers you are, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
so maintaine you that no malice shall
preuaile, or if it do, it shall be for your
good, &amp; to your eternall glory both
here and in heauen which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech
God you may both
seeke and attaine,
Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours most humble
VV. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>