<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his Friend.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100406_Fr1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22622</idno>
           <idno type="STC">91</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100406</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his Friend.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The loves of Clitophon and Leucippe : A most elegant history, written in Greeke by Achilles Tatius: and now Englished</title>
                 <author>Achilles Tatius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Allam, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 255, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>To his Friend.</head>
   <l>DEare Friend, I will not say what's due to thee</l>
   <l>Either from Court or Vniversitie;</l>
   <l>Both are upon thy score; For some there be.</l>
   <l>In each place, that may tender thee a fee</l>
   <l>For what they learne by thy Translation,</l>
   <l>We are not all borne <hi>Greekes</hi>; nor is't a fashion</l>
   <l>To speake all Tongues: many there be 'mongst All</l>
   <l>Who might have read the first Originall,</l>
   <l>But in the end, profess'd, we cannot tell</l>
   <l>What the man meanes, but yet the <hi>Greeke</hi> sounds well.</l>
   <l>But here the Criticke spatters like a Cat,</l>
   <l>And with a Pish damnes all, and cries 'tis flat</l>
   <l>And dull what thou hast done. But we say no;</l>
   <l>Till he shall better it, or equall show.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Tatius</hi> hath had no wrong, if through thy pen</l>
   <l>He seemes to be one of our Countrimen:</l>
   <l>Or if thou, Words and Sense, dost by thy light</l>
   <l>Make that, which seem'd to <hi>some</hi> meere <hi>black</hi> &amp; <hi>white.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Doe we take from an Author, if we looke</l>
   <l>With Spectacles on a small-printed booke?</l>
   <l>Or is't a wrong, if, to set off a bright</l>
   <l>Taper, we put a Christall 'fore the light?</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="9"/>A Pearle's a Pearle, though in the shell 'tis coucht;</l>
   <l>Yet 'tis more glorious, when ta'ne forth and oucht</l>
   <l>In glittering gold. Then gemmes more briskly shine,</l>
   <l>Not when they're in the Sea, but when they're mine.</l>
   <l>Thy Lovers had without thy second Forme</l>
   <l>Beene more obscur'd i'th Greeke, than in the storme.</l>
   <l>And though they scap't by Sea, yet had we found</l>
   <l>Thy Amorous Paire still in the Language drown'd.</l>
   <l>Well (Friend) thou dost excell thy Authors fate;</l>
   <l>He made the Sound, thou dost Articulate.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>W: Wallwyn</hi>: S: Io: Bap: Col:</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>