<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A briefe SUMMARIE OF THE CHIEFEST things contained in this ADIOYNDER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100127_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03944</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14050</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100127</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A briefe SUMMARIE OF THE CHIEFEST things contained in this ADIOYNDER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An adioynder to the late Catholike new yeares gift, or explication of the oath of allegeance : Wherein certaine principall difficulties, obiected by a very learned Roman-Catholike, against the sayd New-yeares gift, and explication of the oath, are very clearely explained. Published by E.I. the author of the New-yeares gift</title>
                 <author>Preston, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 118 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>A briefe SUMMARIE OF THE CHIEFEST things contained in this ADIOYNDER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the <hi>first Section</hi> is shewed, that to proue the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> to bee vnlawfull, eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent demonstrations are required, but to proue it to be lawfull, only probable arguments, and answers are sufficient.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>second Section</hi> is shewed; <hi>First,</hi> that the immediate obiect of an <hi>Oath</hi> must bee morally certaine to the iudgement of the Swearer, and that it neede not to be moral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly certaine to all others. <hi>Secondly,</hi>
      <pb facs="13"/>that in the <hi>second Branch</hi> of the Oath is denyed, both the <hi>Popes power</hi> to practise the deposition of <hi>Princes,</hi> and also the <hi>practice</hi> it selfe in all cases whatsoeuer: and that albeit the deniall of some particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar practice doth not imply a deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of the power it selfe to practise, yet a deniall of all practices and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, is a vertuall deniall of the power it selfe to practise. And <hi>thirdly</hi> it is shewed, that a meere probable power to depose, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish is no true, reall, lawfull, and sufficient power, and for practise, as good as no power at all, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, or punish.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>third Section</hi> is shewed, that euery doctrine which contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a falshood against the holy Scriptures, is truely and properly hereticall, both according to the doctrine of <hi>Protestants,</hi> who hold the holy Scriptures to be the only
<pb facs="13"/>rule of faith, and also of most Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Diuines, who hold that the Church doth not make any Catholike veritie, or heresie; but doth onely declare it, and make it knowne to all, which before her declaration was not known to all. Neither is it required in the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Protestants,</hi> to make any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine hereticall, that it subuert the foundation of faith, <hi>ex parte obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti materialis,</hi> or of the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall things, which are to bee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, which are the generall articles of our Creede, or Christian Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, but that it contain a falshood (although it be in poynts of a lesse matter, then are the <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Creed</hi>) repugnant to the Word of God, which is the rule of faith: and consequently, subuerteth the foundation of faith, <hi>ex parte obiecti formalis,</hi> or the formall cause of our beleefe, which is the infallible
<pb facs="14"/>truth of God, reuealed to vs in the holy Scriptures.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>fourth Section</hi> is shewed <hi>First,</hi> both by manifest reason, and also by the testimony of many learned <hi>Catholike Diuines,</hi> that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>Theologicall Conclusion,</hi> which is euidently deduced from <hi>two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses,</hi> whereof <hi>the one</hi> is expressely contained in the Word of God, and <hi>the other</hi> manifest by the light of Nature, is <hi>of faith,</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie <hi>hereticall,</hi> and against faith, and that therefore although it bee not cleare in Scriptures, <hi>expressely</hi> and <hi>directly,</hi> that it is manifest wrong to depose a <hi>Prince,</hi> excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated and depriued by the <hi>Pope,</hi> yet it is cleere in Scriptures <hi>indirectly, vertually,</hi> and by a <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary consequence,</hi> that it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest wrong to depose such a <hi>Prince,</hi> and consequently to deny the same is properly <hi>hereticall:</hi> and <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi>
      <pb facs="14"/>that <hi>maxime</hi> of the Logici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>The conclusion followeth the weaker part,</hi> is clearely explained.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>fifth Section</hi> is shewed; <hi>First,</hi> that it is against the holy Scriptures <hi>indirectly, vertually,</hi> and by a <hi>necessarie consequence,</hi> and therefore <hi>against faith,</hi> and properly <hi>hereticall,</hi> that it is lawfull to <hi>murther Princes excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, or depriued by the Pope. Secondly,</hi> that it is very false and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, to apply the doctrine of killing <hi>manifest Vsurpers,</hi> to the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Princes excommunicated, or depriued by the Pope;</hi> for that <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest Vsurpers</hi> haue no probable title to the Crowne, but <hi>Princes,</hi> after the <hi>Popes</hi> sentence of <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> and also <hi>depriuation,</hi> haue besides reall possession, a true probable title, and right to the Kingdomes, which they possesse. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that albeit a <hi>Prince</hi> should
<pb facs="15"/>yeeld vp his <hi>Crowne</hi> after depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet it were not <hi>hereticall,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my <hi>Aduersary</hi> his grounds, to kill such a Prince, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though my <hi>Aduersary</hi> doth grant it to be euident murther, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>vertually</hi> repugnant to the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the <hi>sixth Section</hi> is shewed <hi>First,</hi> that the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>New-yeeres Gift</hi> did not bring those <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,</hi> of taking a purse from one, who leadeth a wicked life, or kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him with a pistoll, to compare them to the deposing, or murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Princes excommunicated, or depriued by the Pope; but hee brought them onely to proue, that to make a particular proposition to be hereticall, it sufficeth, that it be contained in the generall proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is expressed in the <hi>holy Scriptures,</hi> so that it be sufficiently proued, to bee contained therein.
<pb facs="15"/>
      <hi>Secondly,</hi> that the comparison ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelesse had beene apt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to proue, that to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doctrine hereticall it sufficeth, that it bee indirectly, vertually, or by a necessarie consequence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the holy Scriptures. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that no Catholike Writer, except onely <hi>Suarez,</hi> durst euer aduenture to teach expressely, that a Prince after depriuation, may by the Popes commission be killed by any priuate man; but because this pernicious doctrine of <hi>Suarez</hi> is grounded vpon a most false and absurd supposition, and which all the world seeth to bee false and absurd, to wit, that the doctrine for the Popes power to depose and murther wicked Princes, is most certaine and of faith, and out of all controuersie among learned Catholikes, his doctrine being grounded vpon a supposition so
<pb facs="16"/>manifestly false &amp; absurd, cannot by any Catholike bee accounted probable.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>seuenth Section</hi> is shewed, that M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> explication of those words <hi>[depose, or murther]</hi> being grounded vpon the nature of a conditionall disiunctiue, is true, proper, and agreeable to the common sense and vnderstanding of the words, nor repugnant to <hi>His Maiesties</hi> intention, albeit M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Widdrington</hi> doth not rely onely vpon that explication.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>eighth Section</hi> is shewed, that according to the doctrine of many learned Catholike Diuines, and manifest reason, that rule of the Law, <hi>In the like case the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the possessour is the better,</hi> ought to be vnderstood, not onely of a true doubt, and when the minde doth fluctuate, and giueth no assent to either part, but also of
<pb facs="16"/>a probable doubt; neither can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man with reason imagine, that when both parts haue probability, the case is not therein alike.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>ninth Section</hi> is shewed, that a <hi>Prince</hi> in keeping his posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, to which he hath a probable title or right, doth neither wrong the <hi>Pope, Church,</hi> or any other, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that vulgar maxime, <hi>He that vseth his own right, doth no man wrong,</hi> nor hindereth vniustly any greater good, and the same is in the beginning of the next <hi>Section</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by a most manifest argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>ad hominem.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the <hi>Tenth Section</hi> is shewed, that according to <hi>Vasques</hi> doctrin, which he thinketh to be certaine, and the contrarie false, <hi>improbable, absurd,</hi> and <hi>pernicious,</hi> it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any Prince onely vpon a probable title to make war against an other Prince, who hath not only
<pb facs="17"/>a probable title, but also possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But this question is imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to the matter of this present Oath, and to the right, which Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may pretend to make warre vpon probable titles, which are grounded vpon the Popes power to depose Princes, as it is more at large declared in the thirteenth <hi>Section.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the <hi>eleuenth</hi> and <hi>twelfth Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> is shewed, that a <hi>Prince,</hi> in keeping his possession, to which he hath a probable right or title, doth no man wrong, nor hindreth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iustly any greater good, and that although a probable title be good for something, and in some cases better then no title at all, yet foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as concerneth the making of warre against him who hath both a probable title, and also possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is in <hi>Vasques</hi> doctrine, which he thinketh to be certaine, as good
<pb facs="17"/>as no title, although we suppose the title to be meerely temporall, but if the title be grounded vpon a probable spirituall authoritie, in all learned mens iudgement, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the approued grounds of Diuinitie, it is as good, as no title at all, which is at large confirmed in the <hi>thirteenth Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the <hi>thirteenth Section</hi> is shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a manifest disparitie betwixt the lawfulnesse of making warre vpon probable titles, which are meerely temporall, and which are grounded vpon a probable spirituall authoritie, for that there is no assured and infallible way on earth to decide, or know vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, by way of sentence and iudgement, the truth of meere temporall titles, which are in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie betwixt two absolute Princes, who in meere temporall
<pb facs="18"/>affaires are subiect to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and sentence of none but God alone, but <hi>Christ</hi> hath left in his Church an infallible way to decide, and know vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly the truth of all titles, which are grounded vpon whatsoeuer pretended spirituall authoritie, to wit, the determination and decision of a lawfull and vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted generall Councell: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it is cleerely inferred, that albeit Princes might lawfully make warre vpon probable titles which bee meerely temporall, because there is no way to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide the controuersie but by war, yet they can not lawfully make warre vpon probable titles, which are grounded vpon a probable spirituall authoritie, because Christ hath left in his Church an infallible and peaceable way to decide certainely by way of
<pb facs="18"/>sentence and iudgement, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making of warre, the truth of all such doubtfull and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersed titles, which infallible and peaceable way he hath now left to decide by way of sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and iudgement, the truth and certainety of probable ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, which are meerely tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>fourteenth Section</hi> is shewed, that M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> last Explication of those words <hi>[as hereticall]</hi> is true and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and agreeable to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sence and vnderstanding of the words, nor repugnant to <hi>His Maiesties</hi> intention, although he doe not rely onely vpon that Explication.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>fifteenth Section</hi> is shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the obligation of all <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratiue Breues,</hi> as well belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to faith, as manners, depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="19"/>vpon the fundamentall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, &amp; former precept, which they suppose and declare, and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Popes Breues</hi> forbidding the Oath, for that it <hi>containeth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things flat contrarie to faith and saluation,</hi> which is the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall reason of his declaratiue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, haue not force to bind, because this fundamentall reason is grounded vpon two suppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are manifestly false, to wit, that the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate</hi> is denied in the Oath, and that his authoritie to <hi>depose Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> is an vndoubted point of faith, nor in controuersie among lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Catholikes.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>sixteenth Section</hi> is shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the <hi>sixt Branch</hi> of the Oath is lawfull, to wit, that <hi>the Oath is ministred by good and full authoritie,</hi> euen to those Catholikes, who are perswaded the Oath to be vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
   <pb facs="19"/>
   <p>In the <hi>Last Section</hi> is shewed, that the <hi>last Branch</hi> of the Oath is lawful, for that euerie good &amp; loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all subiect may and ought to take it very <hi>willingly,</hi> although great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties be imposed against those, who refuse to take the same: And lastly the <hi>Author,</hi> who hath brought these exceptions against the Oath, is friendly admonished not to make any Schisme or Disunion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong English Catholikes, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending that doctrine, <hi>which the Pope himselfe tolerateth in France,</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>So satth</hi> Card. Peron <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n Harangue austiers estat. pag. <hi>94.</hi> Card. Peron <hi>in his last great</hi> Reply cap. <hi>91.</hi> pag. <hi>633.</hi>
      </note> and <hi>which</hi> (as <hi>Card. Peron</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth) <hi>ought not hinder the reunion of those, who should desire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Church,</hi> especially seeing that it hath been by many publike <hi>Decrees</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>France</hi> approued, &amp; the contrary doctrine vnder <hi>paine</hi> of <hi>Treason</hi> condemned, for <hi>false, perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, scandalous,</hi> and <hi>sedicious.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>