<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100662_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03243</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1336</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100662</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A modest reply to certaine answeres, which Mr. Gataker B.D. in his treatise of the nature, &amp; vse of lotts, giveth to arguments in a dialogue concerning the vnlawfulnes of games consisting in chance : And aunsweres to his reasons allowing lusorious lotts, as not evill in themselves. By Iames Balmford, minister of Iesus Christ</title>
                 <author>Balmford, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Boyle, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                            <distributor>Boyle, Richard</distributor>
                            <distributor>Boyle, Richard</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>143, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <p>
      <pb n="21" facs="11"/>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader;</hi> it is no new thing that men▪ learned, wise, and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, holding the same orthodox, and sound truth of God, in respect of maine, and fundamentall points of <hi>Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Religion,</hi> doe sometimes differ in their opinions, and be of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent judgments touching some things of lesse importance▪ It plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth God (who ordereth all things most wisely for the spirituall good of his owne) by his wise disposing hand to order differences in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and judgment in the <hi>smallest</hi> matters for the further good of his <hi>Church.</hi> Though the iarring of <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas (Act. 15. 37.)</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed a separation of the one from the other, yet (God so disposing)
<pb n="22" facs="12"/>
the Church gott much good by it and things questioned, and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted (though of lesser weight are commonly more narrowly se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arched into, and vpon diligen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> search into them, they come to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> better cleared, and the gifts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> worthy men to be better knowne It were no hard matter to instanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in many particulars clearing thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> from many ages fore-going; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> list not to enter into that large field. The ensuing Reply conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the occasion of it, may, in part, evidence, the truth herein▪ Some yeares since, the <hi>Authour</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> this Reply, published a <hi>Dialogu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> touching Lottery, and Lotts, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooving, (by diverse arguments,) the vsing of Lotts in sport, and in play; and now some few yeares past finding his arguments oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and helde as weake, and insuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, by a worthy, reverend, and
<pb n="23" facs="12"/>
judicious <hi>Divine,</hi> in a treatise of his printed touching the Nature, and vse of Lotts, he held himselfe bound, vpon further, and more se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious consideration of the point called into question, either to alter his judgment, or to endeavour, to strengthen his former arguments: He hath sett vpon the buisinesse, and now offered to thy view <hi>(Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Reader)</hi> his Reply tending to the further strengthning▪ and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of those arguments. My poore judgment touching this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply being desired by the <hi>Authour,</hi> I could not but yeeld it vnto him, he being my reverend, and loving freind, to whom I am obliged by many bondes of love. I have pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rused it, &amp; so farre as I, (in my wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knesse) can judge, the <hi>Authour</hi> hath herein carried himselfe wisely, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>udiciously, and so as, I thinke, may satisfie any indifferent reader, and
<pb n="24" facs="13"/>
with all (as I take it) modestly, and temperately, and without the least breach of charity towards the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Opponent.</hi> Happily I may be thought vnfitt thus to giue mine opinion, because (as I freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, &amp; have openly made know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne) I iumpe with this <hi>Authour</hi> in iudgment in the point controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but I professe before him, who knowes the hearts of all men, that, which here I putt downe, is (as I conceive) according to the truth, without any inclining, or partiall affection to the one one side, or to the other, and I desire not to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the least thought, that may praeiudice the worth of the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, learned, and godly <hi>Opponent,</hi> being alsoo my deare, and loving freind, and one whom I am bound, in many respects, both to love, and reverence. Looke vpon this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply (whosoever thou art) with an
<pb n="25" facs="13"/>
vnpartialleye, and consider it se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously, and fin ding that good by it, which is intended, blesse God for it, who guideth, and blesseth all things to his owne glory, and to the good of his owne.</p>
   <p>Thine in the Lord Iesu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Edw: Elton.</hi> B. in D. and Pastor of S. Mary Magda len's Bermond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey neare London.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>