<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>I., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100127_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03944</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14050</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100127</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>I., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An adioynder to the late Catholike new yeares gift, or explication of the oath of allegeance : Wherein certaine principall difficulties, obiected by a very learned Roman-Catholike, against the sayd New-yeares gift, and explication of the oath, are very clearely explained. Published by E.I. the author of the New-yeares gift</title>
                 <author>Preston, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 118 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the New of this yeere, I presented to your chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>(Deare Country-men) A Catholike New-yeeres gift,</hi> or <hi>A brief, &amp; clear Explication of the Oath of Allegiance,</hi> partly vpon occasion of the <hi>publike acknowledgment,</hi> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Thomas Greene,</hi> a very learned Diuine, and <hi>Religious Priest</hi> of the Order of S. <hi>Benedict,</hi> made of his opinion concerning the said Oath, to wit, <hi>that in his owne priuate iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he thought, that there is nothing in the Oath, which may not, according
<pb facs="3"/>to</hi> Roger Widdringtons <hi>Glosse, and Explication, bee lawfully taken by English Catholikes;</hi> and partly to instruct and appease more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the consciences of you, <hi>my Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Brethren,</hi> concerning the said Oath, then you were instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by that false, and pestiferous Explication, compiled by <hi>I. E.</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Treatise</hi> commonly called, <hi>The Prelate and the Prince.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2. Now in the last end thereof, I am bold to annex, for your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter instruction, a little <hi>Addition,</hi> or <hi>Adioynder</hi> to the aforesayd <hi>New-yeeres gift,</hi> vpon occasion of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> which a <hi>Religious Priest</hi> hath made to a very learned <hi>Roman-Catholike,</hi> in answer to diuers diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, doubts and scruples, which he obiected against the sayd <hi>New-yeeres gift,</hi> or <hi>Explication</hi> of the <hi>Oath.</hi> By which <hi>Reply</hi> you may clearely see, that this difficult, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous,
<pb facs="3"/>and scandalous contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie, concerning the <hi>Popes</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to <hi>depose Princes,</hi> and the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegeance,</hi> is now in some sort brought to a finall issue, for that all the exceptions, which hitherto haue beene vrged, or with any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of reason may bee alledged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the aforesayd <hi>Oath,</hi> are fully satisfied by these <hi>foure</hi> generall as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertions, which partly in the <hi>New-yeeres gift,</hi> and partly in this <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynder</hi> are made so plaine and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest, that no man of learning and conscience can contradict the same.</p>
   <p n="3">3. The <hi>first assertion</hi> is, that it is a doctrine <hi>truely probable</hi> (it being approued by <hi>so many</hi> learned Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Diuines, and Lawyers, both ancient and moderne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by <hi>so many</hi> publike <hi>Decrees</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon <hi>so many</hi> pregnant
<pb facs="4"/>proofes, which are taken from the authority of the <hi>holy Scriptures,</hi> the doctrine of the <hi>ancient Fathers,</hi> the practice of the <hi>Primitiue Church,</hi> and diuers other <hi>Theologicall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi>) that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not any power, or authority, to <hi>depose ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Princes,</hi> or to <hi>dispose</hi> of their <hi>Crownes and liues,</hi> for any cause, crime, end, or good whatsoeuer. And this <hi>assertion</hi> is so manifest, that the most learned and <hi>Illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cardinall Peron</hi> not onely affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, <hi>That the Pope doth tolerate in France, those Catholikes, who hold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him in this point</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">En Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tier Estat. pag. <hi>98.</hi>
      </note>, and, <hi>That this controuersie ought not to hinder the re-vnion of those, who should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to be reconciled to the Church</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">In his Reply. ca. 91. p. 633.</note>, but also (which is more to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired) he seeketh to excuse <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> himselfe<note n="c" place="margin">See be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath Sect. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. num. 9.</note>, as though he thought it absurd for any man to conceiue, that so learned a man, as
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> is, should pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely teach, that the doctrine for the <hi>Popes power</hi> to dispose of all temporalls, is an vndoubted point of faith, and to which all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes are bound, to adhere vnder paine of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathema.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="4">4. The <hi>second assertion</hi> consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth of these <hi>three</hi> points. 1. That a meere probable, and imaginary power, to wit, which is onely in the imagination, conceipt, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of learned Catholikes, and is contradicted by others, is no true, reall, lawfull and sufficient power, or ground, to punish, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, or depriue any man of that; which he actually possesseth, and to which also hee hath a probable title. 2. That it is not lawfull for the <hi>Pope,</hi> or other <hi>Christian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> to dispossesse by violence, or force of Armes, any lawfull <hi>Prince</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>of his Dominions, vnder pretence of any probable title, which is grounded vpon an vncertaine spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall authoritie, especially suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing (which is most certaine) that <hi>Christ</hi> hath left in his Church a peaceable way to finde out, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide infallibly the truth and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of all such controuersed and doubtfull titles. 3. That it is most certaine, and out of all controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, that a lawfull <hi>Prince,</hi> who is in peaceable possessiō of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, may lawfully defend himself, &amp; his Dominions, against all such, that shall inuade him &amp; his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, vnder pretence of any such probable title, which is grounded vpon spirituall authority, and that hee may lawfully put them to death, as Traytours, or enemies to his Crowne and State, that shall in hostile manner assault him and his Dominions, vnder pretence of
<pb facs="5"/>any such vncertaine, and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersed right and authority. And these <hi>two assertions</hi> do make cleare the <hi>Second Branch</hi> of the <hi>Oath,</hi> wherein is acknowledged, <hi>That the Pope hath not any power, or authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to depose the King, to absolue his Subiects from their allegeance, or to authorize any forraine Prince to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade, or annoy him, or his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
   <p n="5">5. The <hi>third assertion</hi> is, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery false doctrine, which is either directly and expressely repugnant to the Word of God, or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vertually, and by a necessarie consequence deduced from <hi>two premises,</hi> whereof the <hi>one</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressely contained in the <hi>holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> euidently knowne by the light of nature, is, both in the opinion of <hi>Protestants,</hi> and also of most <hi>Catholike Diuines,</hi> truely and properly <hi>hereticall,</hi> and
<pb facs="6"/>that the <hi>Church</hi> hath not any au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to make any Catholike ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or heresie, but onely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, when there is made any doubt thereof, and to make it knowne to all Catholikes, which before her declaration was not knowne to all, but onely to some, more or lesse, who saw the necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the consequence deduced from both the premises. And by this <hi>assertion</hi> the veritie of the <hi>Fourth Branch</hi> is made plaine and manifest, for that all the stiffe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugners of the Oath, doe ground all their exceptions against that <hi>Branch,</hi> vpon the word <hi>[hereticall.]</hi> So that by the aforesaid <hi>three asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> are cleared all the particular <hi>Branches</hi> of the Oath, for that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the verity of the <hi>Second,</hi> and <hi>Fourth Branch,</hi> is wholly groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the verity and Iustice of euery particular clause, except onely of
<pb facs="6"/>the <hi>First Branch,</hi> wherein <hi>our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord King Iames is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be the lawfull and rightfull King of this Realme &amp;c.</hi> which <hi>Branch</hi> is so cleere and manifest, that no English Catholike euer durst be so impious and presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, as to take the least excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on against the same.</p>
   <p n="6">6 The <hi>Fourth assertion</hi> is, that it is no disobedience, or irreuerence against the <hi>See Apostelike</hi> for Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes not to obey the <hi>Popes</hi> commandement, whensoeuer they haue doubt, that it is vniust,<note place="margin">Sotus de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegendo se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creto memb. <hi>3.</hi>q; <hi>2.</hi> Vasques <hi>and others cited by</hi> Wrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dringt. <hi>in the discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of</hi> Schul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cken. <hi>his slanders, §. 15.</hi>
      </note> and in preiudice of a third person, who is in possession of his goods, &amp; good name, so that they doe most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly propound to his <hi>Holinesse</hi> the reasons of their doubt. This <hi>asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is in plaine &amp; expresse tearmes set downe by that most learned and religious <hi>Dominicus Soto,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by <hi>Vasques</hi> and many other
<pb facs="7"/>Diuines, grounded vpon manifest reason, and sufficiently confirmed by the Canon Law it selfe, in <hi>Cap. si quando, extra, de Rescriptis,</hi> where <hi>Pope Alexander</hi> the <hi>third</hi> giueth this aduertisement to the <hi>Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop</hi> of <hi>Rauenna,</hi> that <hi>he ought either to obey</hi> the said <hi>Popes commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which he enioyned him by his <hi>Breues, or else by his letters to yeeld a reasonable cause, why he ought not to obey it.</hi> Whereupon <hi>obserue,</hi> saith the <hi>Glosse,</hi> expounding that <hi>Canon, that the Superiours comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement ought either to be obeyed, or a cause to be yeelded, why it is not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Seeing therefore, that M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> hath by diuerse publike and printed letters signified to his <hi>Holinesse</hi> in most humble manner the reasons, why English Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes thinke themselues bound not to obey his <hi>Breues</hi> forbidding the Oath, as <hi>conteyning in it many things
<pb facs="7"/>flat contrarie to faith and saluation,</hi> because they are grounded, by the bad information of <hi>Card. Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and his adherents, vpon <hi>two</hi> very false suppositions, <hi>The one,</hi> that the <hi>Popes power</hi> to <hi>excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> is denyed in the Oath, which is manifestly false, <hi>The other,</hi> that his power to <hi>depose Princes</hi> is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted point of faith, which is no lesse vntrue; neither as yet hath he, or other Catholikes receiued from his <hi>Holinesse,</hi> or any other, any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere or satisfaction of these their doubts, truely they cannot be iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taxed of any disobedience, or irreuerence against his <hi>Holinesse,</hi> for not obeying his <hi>Breues</hi> in the aforesaid case, but contrariwise (as in a case not much vnlike very well obserueth and proueth, that holy and learned <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> S. <hi>Robert,</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Apud Matth. Paris pag. <hi>843.</hi> in vita Henrici tertij.</note> in answere to certain <hi>Breues</hi> of <hi>Pope Innocentius</hi> the
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>fourth,</hi> which he thought vniust) it were disobedience, irreuerence, and rebellion against <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>See Apostolike</hi> to obey any such <hi>Breues,</hi> which are grounded vpon false informations, and suppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and tend to so great dishonor, and iniurie of <hi>his Maiesty,</hi> and the whole kingdome.</p>
   <p n="7">7 So that with farre greater reason might be taxed with diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and irreuerence against the <hi>See Apostolike,</hi> not only the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid holy <hi>Bishop S. Robert,</hi> for the cause alleaged, but also that most learned and religious <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus Soto,</hi> and other famous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uins, for contradicting the <hi>Popes Breues</hi> concerning their dispensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in actuall, but not consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate marriage, and for saying, <hi>that the Popes erred therein following the doctrine and opinion of the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists,</hi> as <hi>hauing in it no shew or sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<pb facs="8"/>at all of probabilitie,</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Sotus in <hi>4.</hi> Dist. <hi>27.</hi> q <hi>31.</hi> ar. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note> then <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Widdrington,</hi> and other English Catholikes, may be iustly taxed of any disobedience, or irreuerence against the <hi>See Apostolike</hi> for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting the <hi>Popes Breues,</hi> which forbid the Oath, as <hi>conteyning in it many things flat contrarie to faith and saluation,</hi> and for saying, that he erred therein, following the bad information and opinion of <hi>Card. Bellarmine,</hi> &amp; other Iesuites, which hath in it a farre lesse shew and shadow of probabilitie, then hath the doctrine of the <hi>Canonists</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Popes power to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in actuall, but not consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Marriage: for that all the world now seeth plainly, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Popes power</hi> to <hi>excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate</hi> is denied in the Oath, nor the doctrine for his <hi>power to depose</hi> is an vndoubted point of faith, but a great controuersie among lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="9"/>Catholikes, and which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ought not to hinder the reunion of those, who should desire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Church</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">See <hi>Card. Peron</hi> aboue <hi>num.</hi> 3.</note>
   </p>
   <p n="8">Considering therefore, that the aforesaid <hi>foure</hi> generall positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are now made so plaine and manifest, that no man of learning and conscience can with any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of reason contradict them, and that by them all the chiefe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, which can be obiected either against any particular clause of the Oath, or against the Oath in generall in regard of the Popes <hi>Breues</hi> forbidding the same only in generall tearmes, are most clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly answered, I beseech and adiure you (my deare <hi>Catholike brethren</hi>) by the loue you beare to <hi>God,</hi> by the dutie you owe to your <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and by the care you ought to haue of your eternall sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, that you will not any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb facs="9"/>for feare or flatterie, seeke to impugne, especially by indirect, sinister, and vncharitable courses, so manifest a truth, to the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie and dishonour of your <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,</hi> to the great scandall of your <hi>Religion,</hi> and to the great danger of your temporal and spirituall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw. For assure your selues, that <hi>Truth is great, and will</hi> in the end <hi>preuaile,</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">3. <hi>Esdr.</hi> 4</note> and rather then it shall be ouercome, <hi>God</hi> almightie, the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> of all <hi>Truth,</hi> yea and <hi>Truth</hi> it selfe, will raise vp <hi>Babes</hi> &amp; <hi>Infants</hi> to defend it, to the confusion of the greatest <hi>Rabbins,</hi> that shall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the same: and into what danger you cast your soules either by coyning new articles of faith, or concurring and consenting to the coyners thereof, and by seeking in that respect to make a <hi>Schisme</hi> and <hi>Disunion</hi> among your Catholike brethren, you may with feare and
<pb facs="10"/>trembling perceiue by this, which the beloued Disciple of Christ S. <hi>Iohn</hi> threatneth in the end of his <hi>Apocalyps, If any man shall add to these things, God shall add vpon him the plagues written in this booke.</hi> For vndoubtedly whosoeuer shall add to the holy Scripture that which is not Scripture, or to Catholike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe that which is not Catholike, or shall belieue with Catholike faith that which is not Catholike, or shall forge new articles of faith, or consent to the forgers thereof, especially in things belonging to temporall allegiance, and shall se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate himselfe in Ecclesiasticall communion from those, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict such forgeries, and cause a <hi>Schisme</hi> or <hi>Disunion</hi> in regard of opinions <hi>which ought not to hinder the reunion of those, who should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to be reconciled to the Church,</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">For so <hi>Card. Peron</hi> expresly saith about <hi>num.</hi> 3</note> can not in that respect be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="10"/>a <hi>loyall subiect,</hi> a <hi>true Catholike,</hi> or <hi>right beleeuer;</hi> but endangereth himselfe to be blotted out of the booke of life, and to be punished in the next world with <hi>Traytors, Schismatikes,</hi> and <hi>Misbeleeuers,</hi> and in the meane time he will haue much adoe to cleere himselfe in this world from the guilt, penaltie, and imputation of manifest <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, Schisme,</hi> and <hi>Misbeliefe:</hi> of all which crimes (besides most mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest forgerie, detraction, and slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering) those violent hot spurres, that exclaim so bitterly against the Oath, and their Catholike brethren who fauour the same, will to their great shame and confusion, ere it belong, be publikly accused, and in my iudgement most cleerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted, vnless they speedely change their vncharitable courses, &amp; cease to make a <hi>Schisme</hi> and disunion among Catholikes in regard onely
<pb facs="11"/>of opinions, which as witnesseth <hi>Cardinall Peron, ought not to hinder the reunion</hi> of those who are not <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and <hi>should desire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Catholike Church.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="9">9 And <hi>lastly,</hi> for my owne part I protest vnfaignedly, that as I haue not beene affraid, in regard of the dutie &amp; obligation, wherein I stand bound to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Caesar,</hi> to my <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and to the <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> which I professe, to defend with my pen this mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest truth, concerning the <hi>indissolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bond</hi> g of temporall <hi>Allegiance,</hi>
      <note place="margin">See the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie</hi> for the <hi>Roman Church tract'</hi> 3. <hi>sect.</hi> 5.</note> due to our <hi>Soueraign Prince</hi> by the law of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> although I foresaw the great disgraces, which both in the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and also here in <hi>England</hi> among our <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like brethren,</hi> would come to me thereby, so I will (God willing) be euer readie to confirme and seale the same truth, if need shal require,
<pb facs="11"/>with my blood, vntill the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> which <hi>is the pillar &amp; ground of truth,</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> (to whose censure I most humbly submit my self, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer hath, or shall be written by me) shall infallibly define the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, which as I am fully perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, she neuer will (not to say can not)<note n="i" place="margin">See <hi>Card. Caiet. in opasc. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. B. virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis cap.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; Canus lib.</hi> 7. <hi>de locis cap.</hi> 3 who vpon the like grounds thinke as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suredly, that the Church neuer will (though <hi>Canus</hi> saith expresly she can not) define, that the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued from original sin.</note> define, for that in my priuate iudgement, speaking with all sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, she hath no sufficient grounds, either from the holy Scriptures as they are expounded by the <hi>ancient Fathers,</hi> or from any other vndoubted rule of faith, so to define; but that, if she will deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine either part, she will declare and define according to the true and vniuersall doctrine of the <hi>anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers,</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">See the <hi>ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> in M. <hi>Widdringt.</hi> discouerie of <hi>Schulke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders § 17</note> that <hi>absolute Princes</hi> are <hi>supreme</hi> in temporals, &amp; therein subiect to none, but <hi>God</hi> alone, and also that the <hi>Ecclesiasticall power,</hi> by the institution of <hi>Christ,</hi> doth
<pb facs="12"/>extend to the <hi>giuing</hi> of spirituall graces, not earthly kingdomes, to the <hi>remitting</hi> of sinnes, not of debts, to the <hi>loosing</hi> of spirituall, not corporall bonds, to the <hi>infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting</hi> of spirituall, not temporall punishments, and to the <hi>disposing</hi> of spirituall, not temporall goods.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>
            <hi>This</hi> 27 <hi>of</hi> December 1620.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours in all loue, and dutie,</hi> E. I. <hi>The</hi> Author <hi>of the</hi> New-yeeres <hi>gift.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>