<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE concerning the PSALMES.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100465_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08800</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19085</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100465</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE concerning the PSALMES.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true Catholike : Collected out of the oracles, and psalteries of the Holy Ghost. for instruction, and deuotion</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blackmore (Blackamore), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 256, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="111"/>
   <pb facs="111"/>
   <head>A PREFACE concerning the PSALMES.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>DAVID</hi> is said to be the instrumentall cause of the Psalmes, to whom all things were reuealed, and by him set downe Hee is also esteemed the greater,<note place="margin">2. Samuel 23.2.</note> and more excellent Prophet, in that hee did not Prophesie by certaine visions of things, or darke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerings of words, but by the inward motion onely of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost: which is most eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, because the manifold and most beautifull riches in that <pb facs="112"/> tresurie conteined, are impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be matched by any other. Among which the inuocation of Almightie God (being the greatest defence for our salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, against the continuall as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saults of Satan) is most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently composed for a presedent, and direction vnto vs vpon all occasions.<note place="margin">Eph.
6.18</note> We are commanded to pray alwayes, with all prayer and supplication in the spirit, which is impossible for vs to do, vnlesse we be learned in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of Pietie, and guided therein by the holy Spirit of God. The true rule whereof is to be taken out of the Booke of the Psalmes. For by reading them we are as well stirred vp to the vnderstanding of our infirmities, as admonished and taught how to seeke a sure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie <pb facs="112"/> for them. They are doubtlesse the Anatomie of all the parts of the soule: for wee cannot finde any disposition or affection of the minde in our selues, the forme and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, is not in this glasse represented. When in this language we prepare our selues to speake vnto God, we are drawne to so strict an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of our transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions that all our secret offences being disclosed, and our hearts cleansed from hypocrisie, wee cannot but deliuer a reall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and full confession of them. By this language (which is <hi>Verba spiritus sancti,</hi> The words of the holy Ghost) wee haue not onely a familiar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse vnto God, but do also find it more safe and auaileable for <pb facs="113"/> vs to acknowledge and confesse our sinnes before him, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 1.9.</note> for he is faithfull and iust to forgiue vs our sinnes, and to cleanse vs from all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteousnesse.<note place="margin">Psal. 118.8.</note> And it is better to trust in him then to put confidence in man. In them wee haue examples and directions of thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing for blessings recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and dangers escaped. They are most comfortable in all times of temptation, trouble and affliction.</p>
   <p>The Psalmes therefore ought to be our meditations in all holy exercises, both pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and publike; they are the key of knowledge. Almost all holy write and misteries are briefely contained in them. Their scope is the right way <pb facs="113"/> to eternall felicitie.</p>
   <p>Some of the Fathers do coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saile the young souldiers of Christ Iesus,<note place="margin">Cassidor</note> first to learne them, before they learne the other holy Scriptures.</p>
   <p>Others affirme that they are <hi>Arma Iuuenum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Climac. ex sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia Patrum.</note> The armour and weapons of young men; And I doubt not but they may also truely be accounted,
<hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaria senum;</hi> The armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and storehouses of old men. Another saith,<note place="margin">Basil.</note>
      <hi>Liber Psalmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ū quidvi, in se complectitur quod vsui sit, &amp; omni. bonae doctrinae promptua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ium est;</hi> The booke of the Psalmes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in it whatsoeuer is vse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and is the storehouse of all good doctrine. In them cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely is expressed as in a liuely resemblance, the true
<pb facs="114"/> rule of religious seruice, and worship; for the example of a godly man assaulted by all manner of temptations, is of more power to moue, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs to flie vnto God, in time of necessitie, then a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement alone.<note place="margin">In proem. in 7. Psal. poenitent.</note>
      <hi>INNOCENT</hi> the third saith; <hi>Inter omnes orationis species, post oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem dominicam, perfecta in Psalmis forma orandi reperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Among all kinds of prayer, next vnto the Lords prayer, the absolute forme of praying is sound in the Psalmes, yet not onely the words are to bee read, and rehearsed in our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, but our hearts also must be attendant, and eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto heauen; for wee are taught to lift vp our hands with our hearts vnto God in <pb facs="114"/> the heauens.</p>
   <p>The holy Ghost being the dictator and guide of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids penne,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.41.</note> and tongue when they were by him registred, It is most meete and requisite, that in all times of our deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they bee recited with the assistance of the same blessed Spirit, which wee must before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand inuocate, lifting vp holy hands,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2 8.</note> without wrath or doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
   <p>S. <hi>AVGVSTINE</hi> in his last sicknesse appointed
<hi>DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIDS</hi> Penitentiall Psalmes to be written,<note place="margin">Possidius in vita August.</note> and set vpon the foure sides of the wall, which on his sicke daies lying on his bed, he did behold and reade; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies shedding forth teares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly. S. <hi>BASIL</hi> also be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his death bed, desired <pb facs="115"/> that the Psalmes might bee read vnto him by <hi>GREGO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE NAZIANZEN.</hi> A man certainely in his greatest sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and anguish of conscience occasioned by Gods wrath, and iudgement, may by them learn to raise vp, and comfort him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self. Come then, let vs bring our offering of the finest gold to lay vpon Gods Altar, the least graine whereof is more precious in his sight, then all the Alcumie of the world. Let vs drinke of the purest foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and forsake the troubled and muddie riuers.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Isa. 55.1.</note>Euery one that thirsteth, come ye to these waters, and he that hath no money, yea, come buy wine, and milke without money, and without price. Wherefore doe ye spend monie
<pb facs="115"/> for that which is not bread? and your labour for that which satisfieth not? Hearken dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently vnto the vndoubted te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies of our God, and eate ye that which is good, and let your soule delight it selfe in fatnesse. Incline your eare, and come vnto him, heare, and your soule shall liue; and he will make an euerlasting couenant with you, euen the sure mercies of <hi>DAVID.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>