<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH, AND ILLVS∣TRIOVS PRINCE, CHARLES PRINCE OF WALES, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Baret, Michael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100900_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04062</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1412</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100900</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH, AND ILLVS∣TRIOVS PRINCE, CHARLES PRINCE OF WALES, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Baret, Michael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An hipponomie or the vineyard of horsemanship : deuided into three bookes. 1. The theorick part, intreating of the inward knowledge of the man.2. The first practicke part, shewing how to worke according to that knowledge. 3. The second practicke part, declaring how to apply both hunting and running horses to the true grounds of this art. In which is plainly laid open the art of breeding, riding, training and dieting of the said horses. Wherein also many errors in this art, heretofore published, are manifestly detected. By Michaell Baret</title>
                 <author>Baret, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 48, 51-122, 20, 139, 13, 101, 1, 23, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH, AND ILLVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRIOVS PRINCE, <hi>CHARLES</hi> PRINCE OF WALES, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost Excellent Prince: as it is a true saying, that the tree is knowne by the fruit: so in like manner the fruit is hoped by the tree; wherefore you being of such Royall descent, in which are inherent such fulnesse of Morall and Deuine vertues, there can bee no doubt, but this peaceable happinesse shall futurely continue: For as the Earth (which is said to be a Magneticall body) doth not onely hold it selfe, in one certaine, and vniforme Scituation, Eleuation, and Place, by the disponent faculty, and Magneticall vigour of the two Poles, and by vertue of the grauity vnto the Center; but also doth attract, and conforme all other substances (of the like quality, (as directory Needles, inclinatory Needles, Sea Compasses, and such
<pb facs="6"/> like,) to aspect the Poles, and so vnite themselues in all corespondency, at conuenient angles and positions, by a constant and certaine apprehension of the same, and so become as guides to direct men in doubtfull and vncertaine passages; Euen so, your Grace, being so truely and firmely touched with the Vertue, Power, and Potency, of so High and Precious a Magneticall Body, will site your selfe Parallel to his Axis, and when you shall approach neare his Articke Pole, you will ioyne and make a straight line with the same: (to whose Poles, all mens indeauours doe attract and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themselues in all doubtfull causes:) because that if a Magnet be taken from the whole rocke, (whence it was vnited, and did grow in the bowels of the Earth) although before he was taken away he was but a part of the whole body, yet after it is seperated, will then become a perfect, complete, and sole Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall body, retayning all the proprieties and vertues of the whole nature.</p>
   <p>But I insist too much to proue that which no man can or once dare to deny; wherefore (assuredly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Highnesse is so richly endowed with all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall Vertues,) I am also imboldned to Dedicate these my rude and vndigested Labours, vnto your most Excellent Fauour, being (as yet) of such tender yeares, as your prosperous time may quicken and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue
<pb facs="6"/> this low and debased Art of Horsemanship, and by whom these low shrubbs may spread and grow vp like Oliue plants, so as this Realme shall not neede to dull the eares of any other strange countries, (by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for assistance,) if you will but vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to countenance the Fauorits thereof with your Smyling Grace. For I haue planted this <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi> vpon a firme and true ground, and haue fenced it about in such sort by Reason, and weeded and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it by Practise, that there is no Impe, (if conceipt hinder not,) but may keepe it from such weeds, and rauenous beasts as would deuour or choke him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by these excellent and so necessary Creatures, may be brought to such obedience and subjection, as shall be needfull for the vse and seruice of Man; (for whom they were created, as his hereditary possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:) Although my Artlesse pen hath not made it so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull as to reuiue the dead senses of all scrutenous braines, which no <hi>Tullies</hi> Eloquence as yet could euer perswade. And therefore I most sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missiuely intreate that it would please you to accept of this my first and new born Infant, (being but as yet in the swadling Clothes, which desireth to be Fostred vnder your wings, and to be protected vnder your Fethers: and I hope it will proue such a thankefull Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan as it will also nourish many Impes, and
<pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="8"/> cause them to flourish, so, in this plantation, as they shall bring forth such pleasant grapes, as will relish the Pallat, and delight the eye. And so with my vnfeigned prayers to Almighty God, for your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies most prosperous successe and endlesse happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, I rest deuoted as vnworthy of your least Fauours.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Excellencies most lowly, and poore Seruant. MICHAELL BARET.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>