<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE NO∣ble and Religious Lady, the Lady Eliza∣beth Hare, Wife to the Honourable Sir Iohn Hare of Srow in Norff. and daughter to the Right Honourable Tho∣mas Lord Couentry, Lord Keeper of the great Seale, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Watts, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100303_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22627</idno>
           <idno type="STC">912</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100303</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE NO∣ble and Religious Lady, the Lady Eliza∣beth Hare, Wife to the Honourable Sir Iohn Hare of Srow in Norff. and daughter to the Right Honourable Tho∣mas Lord Couentry, Lord Keeper of the great Seale, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Watts, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Saint Augustines confessions translated: and with some marginall notes illustrated. Wherein, diuers antiquities are explayned; and the marginall notes of a former Popish translation, answered. By William Watts, rector of St. Albanes, Woodstreete</title>
                 <author>Augustine, of Hippo, Saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Norton, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Partridge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 1012, 8 pages, 1 leave of plates, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Religious Lady, the Lady</hi> Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Hare, <hi>Wife to the Honourable</hi> Sir Iohn Hare <hi>of</hi> Srow <hi>in</hi> Norff. <hi>and daughter to the Right Honourable</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas <hi>Lord</hi> Couentry, <hi>Lord</hi> Keeper <hi>of the great Seale, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Madam,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW great aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage a natiue disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to goodnesse is, we confesse all; all know how much the goodnesse of the <hi>Stock,</hi> conferres towards the sweetnesse of the <hi>Fruite.</hi> And yet haue our Gardeners
<pb facs="4"/>
obserued another aduancement of Nature: namely, how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully the goodnesse of the Stock, is improued by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the <hi>Cyon:</hi> and that tis the Graft, and not the Plant alone, which renders the fruit more pleasant. Besides that naturall preeminence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which your <hi>Ladyship</hi> hath, to be <hi>honorably</hi> descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; you are (as the world acknowledges) <hi>vertuously</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended also (your <hi>Stock</hi> is good) and you are (which the world knowes not) <hi>high borne</hi> too (your <hi>Cyon</hi> is better) <hi>borne from aboue;</hi> not onely <hi>once,</hi> but <hi>againe;</hi> and I fully perswade my selfe, that I haue long since seene many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayned assurances of it. <hi>I</hi> must not tempt your <hi>Ladyship</hi> with your own prayses (your neighbours can speake foorth them) and did <hi>I</hi> not know you to be most discreetly humble,
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>I</hi> might not haue sayd so much. Let me now be bold (good <hi>Madame)</hi> to adde one <hi>Counsell</hi> after many <hi>Commendations,</hi> (it shall be but such a one as <hi>I</hi> know you most apt to take) giue mee leaue to put you in mind, that al this, though the <hi>chiefe,</hi> yet is it not the <hi>onely</hi> Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment your <hi>Ladyship</hi> stands ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to <hi>Almighty God</hi> in; but that <hi>you</hi> owe <hi>him,</hi> aboue most women, a daily thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse both for his domesticke and worldly blessings. <hi>God</hi> hath endowed your <hi>Ladyship</hi> with a most plentifull <hi>fortune:</hi> And aboue that, with a <hi>well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chosen</hi> and a <hi>towardly Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,</hi> one of the early hopes and prayses of his Country; a <hi>yoake-fellow</hi> equall to your Selfe in blood, in youth, <hi>in personage:</hi> And to increase all these blessings, hath <hi>God</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creast <hi>you both,</hi> with a sweete &amp; numerous <hi>Issue,</hi> euen so nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous,
<pb facs="5"/>
that your <hi>Oliue bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are already round about your table:</hi> So that (blessed be <hi>God)</hi> neyther of <hi>you both</hi> are likely to want <hi>Heyres,</hi> nor they, <hi>Inheritances.</hi> Thus hath <hi>God</hi> blest you, as he did <hi>Ioseph,</hi> with <hi>blessings of the Heauen</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 25</note>
      <hi>aboue, and blessings of the Deepe beneath, blessings of the brests and of the womb. And what could God haue done more to his Vine?</hi> And what remaines for your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to doe, but to <hi>cultiuate,</hi> to <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>une,</hi> and to <hi>water</hi> both <hi>Stock and Cyon,</hi> with a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious industry? I know your <hi>Ladyship</hi> to be addicted as well to the <hi>Closet,</hi> as to the <hi>Church;</hi> to priuate <hi>Reading,</hi> as to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Hearing:</hi> and I haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofare serued your <hi>Ladyship</hi> in both. In thankfulnesse therfore for your salt which I haue ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tē, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>here make present of a most fit instrument for your Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb facs="5"/>
culture, <hi>St. Austens own Pruning knife,</hi> by which <hi>Hee cut off his sinnes by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance:</hi> an exercise for your <hi>Closet</hi> deuotion; the deuout st piece of all St. <hi>Austen,</hi> and the vsefullest: by which, <hi>Confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made vnto Saluation.</hi> I <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 10</note> direct not this <hi>to your Name</hi> by any <hi>chance,</hi> but vpon deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate <hi>choyce:</hi> for <hi>I</hi> presume to be so priuy to the way of your Religion, as to know that euen this Subiect of <hi>Priuate Confessions</hi> will much please you. It will, <hi>I</hi> hope, do your soule good; Let it therefore, <hi>I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you <hi>Madam,</hi> partake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of your <hi>Goodnesse:</hi> Countenance it, <hi>I</hi> intreate your <hi>Ladyship,</hi> with your <hi>Nime,</hi> and defend it with the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a <hi>Ladies Honour,</hi> which no man (I hope) will be so vnmannerly as to viv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. <hi>God</hi> blesse your Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Husband, and Selfe,</hi> and
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>Children,</hi> and <hi>Kinred,</hi> and Family, with <hi>Grace</hi> in this Life, and with <hi>Glory</hi> in the next. Thus prayes he affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately, who still remaines,</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Madame,</salute>
      <signed>Your good Ladyships obliged to honour and serue you, VVilliam VVatts.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>