<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translator to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100406_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22622</idno>
           <idno type="STC">91</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100406</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translator to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The loves of Clitophon and Leucippe : A most elegant history, written in Greeke by Achilles Tatius: and now Englished</title>
                 <author>Achilles Tatius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Allam, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 255, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Translator to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, how this recreation of my idle houres (whose hard for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune it is now to come under thy cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure) shall please thee, it matters not much; since I begge not thy approbation, or feare thy dislike; either because thy phancy may be mother to the one, thy prejudice to the other; or because I my selfe cannot
<q>—digito monstrari &amp; dicier hic est:</q>
wherefore thou maist condemn the Translator, not me. If thou cry me downe for a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>inquent, I may perhaps be sory for taking so much pains to offend, yet never feare comming to executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But lest I should so farre betray my owne cause, anticipate thee in thy censure, or passe too hard a censure upon so petty a crime (as abusing a Readers patience is now adaies accounted) heare what I can say in my owne defence. First, how difficult a thing it is to maintaine the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy of a Greeke author in our language, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to thee, if thou hast read either <hi>Aristaene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Eustathius, Longus</hi> the Sophist, or <hi>Parthenius</hi>; from whose pens, as sometime from the tongue of <hi>Vlysses,</hi>
      <q>
         <l>—<gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>:</l>
         <l>A voice more sweet than hony did distill;</l>
      </q>
      <pb facs="4"/>
yet were they Englisht, they would bee as little esteemed of, as the Latine translation of <hi>Plato,</hi> or that of my Author done by <hi>Hanniball Crucei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>; which I may in <hi>Photius</hi> language truly call <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: The second thing which may excuse me, is, that by the exection of the two testicles of an unchaste dispute, and one immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest expression, I have so refined the author, that the modestest matron may looke in his face and not blush. Besides, I present him not here clad in the ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>es of mine owne phancie, nor yet in language rackt and disjoynted out of its proper idiom; but I have observed a medium betwixt both: I could with some unnecessary paines have given it a flourish, but I preferred the fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Translation before the Ornament. That little which I have spared to English, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted my author not onely to the censure of the Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> but also of some of these times, and would have appeared as a mole in his face; whose worth, were it not so great, I might have good colour to piece out my unseasonable advertisements with; but sparing thee, and not willing to injure him, I bid thee farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>