<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my Reader.</title>
           <author>Reynolds, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100002_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20993</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7367</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100002</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my Reader.</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the court or Instructions for courtiers : Digested into two books. Written in French by the noble, and learned iuris-consull Monsr Denys de Refuges, Councellor of Estate, and many tymes ambassador (in foraigne parts) for ye two last French kings his masters* Done into English by Iohn Reynolds</title>
                 <author>Refuge, Monsieur de (Eustache)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lee, William 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 189, 21, 189, 63 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>To my Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was my desire, and withall my resolution not to haue affoorded thee the bare <hi>Complement</hi> of an <hi>Epistle,</hi> although the affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; iniquity of our times (in this <hi>Wane</hi> and <hi>Crisis</hi> of the world) rather make it Customarie, then Commendable, if thou wilt know the reason why my thoughts were thus wedded to my will. I answere: because I as much disdaine to insinuate for the Sugar of thy applause, as to feare the Gall of thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction: for how well or ill thy curious <hi>English</hi> Pallat relish this my <hi>French</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation, I neither passe to know, nor care to vnderstand. That I haue done it well, I am not so vaine to conceiue, much lesse to arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate. That I have done it ill, my Ignorance retaines this hope, that albeit I am condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by my petty censuring <hi>Iurors,</hi> yet I shall be at least reprieued by my vnderstanding and competent <hi>Iudges,</hi> to whom, and to no
<pb facs="11"/>
others I appeale; those for their smattering in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue, hauing onely their eyes in their heads to see and censure; these for their perfection thereof, their heads in their eyes to obserue and distinguish, so, though those report, that I leuell not at the letter, but at the sense; yet these will truly find out, that I haue chiefly aimde to strike the sence, without extrauagantly straying or impertinently roauing from the letter. Neither had I either Defended or Apologisd this my Translation, if the Presse (which runnes swifter then our thoughts) had not made me guilty of many faults, whereof my Pen was innocent, which I hope the <hi>Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>Iuditious</hi> will winck at, though the <hi>Captious</hi> and <hi>Ignorant</hi> carpe at, and those passe it ouer with a iuditious modesty, though these perchance) stumble at it with a mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious dep<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>auation.</p>
   <p>Howsoeuer, my comfort is, that if I haue not righted myselfe, yet that I haue no way wronged mine <hi>Author,</hi> the preseruation of whose intent, candeur, and integritie, hath been my greatest▪ Ambition, and not my least care; not that I delight either to prayse him in his <hi>Booke,</hi> or his <hi>Booke</hi> in him, sith that
<pb facs="11"/>
were a take as needles to attempt, as vaine to performe, especially sith the greatest <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers</hi> aswell of <hi>England</hi> as <hi>France,</hi> know, that as he gaue life to this his <hi>Treatise</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> so it is so farre from <hi>Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> as with a happy exchange and interest it hath returnd him Immortalitie; for such a weauing and contexture of matter, so great variety of Heads so curiously anotomisd and so concisely and accutely both commented and cymented, few <hi>Treatises</hi> haue (and I assure my self) none of this nature can iustly <hi>Vaunt</hi> of. The Inke wherewith he wrate it, was rather <hi>Milke</hi> then <hi>Vinegar,</hi> as teaching <hi>Courtiers</hi> how to preuent their fall, in forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying their subsistance, seeming equally bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced, as well in commiserating the deaths of misfortunate <hi>Courtiers,</hi> as prouiding for the prosperitie of the liuing.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Grace, Wit,</hi> and <hi>Fidelitie,</hi> are the <hi>Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> wherewith hee striues to adorne his <hi>Courtier,</hi> reputing nothing so inciuil in him as <hi>Ignorance,</hi> nor so execrable as <hi>Treason;</hi> and then (resembling himselfe) hee with a prayse-worthy <hi>Deuotion &amp; Zeale</hi> (though not in expresse tearmes, yet in a dependant and necessary consequence) wisheth that the
<pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>Court</hi> were (by <hi>Antithesis)</hi> opposite to the <hi>Athenian Ostracisme,</hi> that <hi>Vertue</hi> might not be robbed of her <hi>Deserts</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> by <hi>Vice,</hi> but that <hi>Merit &amp; Reward</hi> might still march hand in hand as <hi>Iumeals,</hi> or else as two destinct Sisters, whereof that the <hi>Aisne,</hi> and this the <hi>Puisnè,</hi> which propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates not onely the ioy, but the glorie of a <hi>Kingdome.</hi> In a word, he hath delineated him in so liuely a shape, and depainted him in such rich Colours, that when wee find a Common-wealth so gouernd and reformd, as that of <hi>Plato</hi> an <hi>Orator;</hi> so fluent and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as that of <hi>Cicero;</hi> or a Captaine so Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and Ingenious as that of <hi>Zenephon;</hi> then it is possible for vs to meete with the <hi>Courtier</hi> of <hi>Monsieur de Refuges,</hi> diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultly before.</p>
   <p>And now (for mine owne discharge) I am to aduertise thee that in the first Book, &amp; 31. Chapter, I found the fifth <hi>Section</hi> wholly left out of the Originall: but whether mine <hi>Author</hi> did it vnwittingly, or the <hi>French Printer</hi> ignorantly, sith I know not, I will not define; and therefore I haue purposely left a blanke for it, as holding it very vnfit for mee to fill it vp with any thing of mine
<pb facs="12"/>
owne. And here to shake hands at parting, and to part as friendly Enemies, if not as lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng Friends: if thou wilt not consider this my ensuing conclusion for my sake, yet (at least) remember it for thine owne. Some Readers are curteous, some ingratefull, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers iniurious; and as it is in thy choyce to be either, so it is, and shall bee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in mine either to care, or not to care which thou be.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Iohn Reynolds.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>