<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORABLE
SIR WILLIAM GOSTWICKE
Baronet, and his worthy Lady, the
Lady IANE GOSTWICKE.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100383_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01573</idno>
           <idno type="STC">117</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100383</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORABLE
SIR WILLIAM GOSTWICKE
Baronet, and his worthy Lady, the
Lady IANE GOSTWICKE.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gallants burden : A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the twentie nine of March, being the fift Sunday in Lent. 1612. By Tho. Adams</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Knight, Clement</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 34 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORABLE
SIR WILLIAM GOSTWICKE
Baronet, and his worthy Lady, the
Lady IANE GOSTWICKE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onorable Sir, I acknowledge freely that
the World is oppressed with the Presse, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d
the confluence of Bookes hath bred a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
of errours, of Vices; so hard is it to
distinguish betwixt profitable and vaine
Writinges; and hauing culled out the best, so easie is it
with much good Meate to surfet; yet is not therefore Meate
vnnecessarie: It is no sober inference, because both Text
and readers haue been corrupted with false Glosses, to reiect
all Expositions, all Applications: both are fitte, this latter
most necessary; for our Vnderstanding is better then our
Conscience: there is some light in our Minds, litle warmth
in our Affections: So against Nature is it true in this, that
the essentiall qualities of Fire, Light, and Heat, are deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;
and to say, whether our light of Knowledge be more,
or our heate of Deuotion lesse, is beyond me: Let this (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered)
plead for me, that I (doe but) rubbe this sowning
Knowledge in vs, to bring it backe to some life of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:
If any feele their thicke eyes hence to receiue any
clearenesse, or their nummed Affections to gather (the
least) Spirit, let th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m at once, giue God the glory, and take
to themselues the comfort. Sinne hath got strength with
age, and against all naturall order, is more powerfull, sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tile,
<pb facs="3"/>
and fuller of actiue dexteritie now in the dotage of it,
then it was in the nonage: Both Pulpit &amp; Presse are weake
enough to resist it. It therfore this small Arrow of Reproofe
can wound (but euen) one of his Limbes, it shall a litle ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
his tyranny. Whatsoeuer this Sermon is, it is wholly
yours, and he that made it: whose Patronage, I could not be
ambitious of, if I should onely fixe my eyes on my owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruinges:
but in the affiance of your good natures, mature
iudgementes, and kind constructions of my weake endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours,
I haue presumed to make you the Patron of my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
who was freely the Patron of my selfe. I know, that
Gods word can countenaunce it selfe, and needes not the
shelter of an humaine arme, not, though it had as many
<hi>Edomites</hi> to deride it, as it hath <hi>Patrons</hi> to defende it:
But I find not onely the best Writinges of the best Men, but
euen some of those Holy Bookes, inspired from Heauen, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
in their foreheads (as from the pen-men) a dedication.
I confesse, it is not all for your Protection, somewhat for
your vse; and you are blessed in fauouring that, which shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be
best able to fauour you: May I therefore intreate your
Honors, to giue it happy entertainement to your owne
heartes, fauourable protection to the worldes eyes; so shall
that, and my selfe be (yet more) yours. The God of all power
and mercie, be as f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ythfull a shadow of refreshing to your
soules, as your kindnesse hath been free to my wantes, who
must euer remaine.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors in all
faythfull obseruance,
<hi>Tho. Adams.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>