<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable EDVVARD Viscount CONVVAY, Lord President of his Majesties Hono∣rable privie Counsell: My most honored Lord.</title>
           <author>Squire, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100545_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12807</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23114</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100545</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable EDVVARD Viscount CONVVAY, Lord President of his Majesties Hono∣rable privie Counsell: My most honored Lord.</title>
                 <author>Squire, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine exposition vpon the first part of the second chapter of Saint Paul his second epistle to the Thessalonians : Wherein it is plainly proved, that the Pope is the Antichrist. Being lectures, in Saint Pauls, by Iohn Squire priest, and vicar of Saint Leonards Shordich sometime fellow of Iesus Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Squire, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterhouse, Philip</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 383, 390-768, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable EDVVARD Viscount CONVVAY, Lord President of his Majesties Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable privie Counsell: My most honored Lord.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese Lectures I laboured prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to satisfie mine own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, in this great point. But understanding, that some consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable persons, have received some small satisfaction, by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them: I print them. And
<pb facs="3"/> presume to present thē to your Honor to read them, or some of them, at your Lordships leasure. That I may publish to the world how I am assured of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors sincere affection to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth now in opposition to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> VVhich that it may be daily confirmed, and increased in your Honour, and in the rest of our Honorable English Nobilitie, shall be the daily and sincere prayer of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most unworthy, yet most humble Chaplaine IOHN SQVIRE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>