<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100171_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19065</idno>
           <idno type="STC">548</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100171</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christian offices crystall glasse : In three bookes. First written in Latine, by that famous and renowned Father, Saint Ambrose Bishop of Millane. Whereunto is added his conuiction of Symmachus the Gentile. A worke tending to the advancement of vertue, and of holinesse: and to shew how much the morality of the Gentiles, is exceeded by the doctrine of Christianity. Translated into English by Richard Humfrey</title>
                 <author>Ambrose, Saint, Bishop of Milan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Greene, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dawson, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>66, 126, 2, 127-142, 10, 75, 9, 64, 38, 20, 41, 1 page, folded table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="108"/>
   <pb facs="108"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O remove away scandall from the mind of some, whom the very name of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophie doth offend, because of the cautell of the<note n="a" place="margin">Coloss. 2.8.</note> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, it shall bee necessarie to cleare his doctrine from such sinister suspiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Wee are to understand therefore, that there bee certaine naturall notions, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> termes <hi>the truth of God, and the law written in the heart,</hi> ingrafted still, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the fall, in the mindes of men: as of numeration, writing, reading,<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 31.3.</note> architecture,<note n="c" place="margin">Syrac. 38.1.</note> Physicke, gift of tongues, all which with the like are good things, and the gifts of God, and doe testifie his wisdome. Hence <hi>Salomon,</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Prov. 20.12.</note> That the eye doth see, and eare doth heare, God is the author of them both: and another saith well, the renowne, that is spread abroad of God in the<note n="e" place="margin">Grata de Deo fama in artibus sparsa est. Plato.</note> sciences, is acceptable. Nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther doe the arts, among which is Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, draw us to acknowledge God to be the fountaine of wisdome only, but the guider of our whole bodily life, namely in their principles, and demonstrations: insomuch,
<pb facs="109"/> that such as cast the least aspersion upon them, are abrept with fury to the hurt of mankind, and contumelie of the Almighty. Wee must know this beside, that Sciences fetched from the light of nature have their limitations, and extend no further then to what is within humane capacity, not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to what in the Gospell is given by spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall revelation, as to that, which is therein manifested of Gods owne essence, will, and promise of grace, transforming of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell into philosophie, as the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> and Monkes of old have grossely done, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressing the due bounds thereof, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding them together without discretion, is that which the Apostle would have Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians to beware of. It is to bee observed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, that he wills not to take heed of Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie only, but of many other kindes of wiles no lesse perilous to pull away from the truth, and sinceritie of the Gospell, adding withall vaine deceipt through the<note n="f" place="margin">Worshipping of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and other beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly worldly ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, <hi>v.</hi> 18. &amp; 20.</note> traditions of men, according to the rudiments of the world, and not according to Christ. A third sort likewise there was, when the <hi>Colossians</hi> made a commixture of<note n="g" place="margin">Verse 11.16.</note> Christianisme, and <hi>Iudaisme:</hi> of baptisme, and circumcision: of the law, and the Gospell, which was the common error together with this Church, of that of<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 2.27.10.5.</note>
      <hi>Rome,</hi> and<note n="i" place="margin">Gal. 4.10.</note>
      <hi>Galatia.</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">The name of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophie is here used not properly, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, for ostentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of wit vented in painted speech, with a purpose to beguile the simple.</note> And from this ground did <hi>Pelagius</hi> himselfe, the <hi>Semi-pelagians,</hi> and some of the Schoolemen build
<pb facs="109"/> up their doctrine of humane merits.<note n="*" place="margin">Another exposition.</note> All these impostures are signified by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, which is to carry away the mindes of the world as a prey: and to captivate them under Sathan. It followes not therefore from hence the study of Philosophie in the schoole of Christ to be forborne. Yea rather, if we truly weigh the matter, there be among sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry other, three singular commodities, why it ought to bee specially fostered in the Church. First it is an ample witnesse of God, and his attributes. Next, when it, and the Gospell bee compared together, it brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in much light to the comprehending of the severall doctrines contained in them both. Lastly, the sundry parts thereof throughly learned, yeeld no small advantage above such as want them, no lesse for more facilitie in opening, then for solidity in defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the divine tenets. Notwithstanding we confesse, that not <hi>the wisdome of the</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 8.6. Pbilosophie to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>flesh, but that of the spirit is it alone, which is life, and peace.</hi> For might that bee admitted for a good kind of arguing, Philosophie, because it is the wisdome of the flesh, is death, and therefore utterly to bee rejected: With the like reason might wee conclude against the sacred bookes, for that without faith, and the holy Spirit they bring not life, and peace. Wherefore this taketh not away the good that may bee reaped by the use of Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, though in an infinite inferiour degree to
<pb facs="110"/> that received from the divine Oracles. The very name of Vertue likewise, how glorious soever, seemes to some not to sort with Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and the appellation of good Workes to bee much more proper to it, and therefore frequently used, and that of vertue rarely, and not above once<note n="m" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.5. Phil. 4.8.</note> or twice in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The rarity of it is partly, because the Scriptures, especially of the new Testament have little to doe with warres, from which it<note n="n" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Mars.</hi>
      </note> is derived, and those of the old Testament are styled the<note n="o" place="margin">1 Sam. 25.18.</note>
      <hi>warres of God,</hi> as his worke: and partly because it imports an heroicall spirit extraordinarily inflamed to the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing great adventures, and that with a forcible,<note n="p" place="margin">And therefore ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers habites <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> and constant inclination which is seldome found. S. <hi>Peter</hi> putting it downe doth evidence the same, noting thereby in generall the efficacie of the doctrine of the Gospell, and that it passes not away without fruit, but stirreth up a fiery affection, and firme purpose of performance in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. I cannot say that those speciall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the <hi>Ethnicks, Alexander, Scipio, Augustus,</hi> and the rest were meerely naturall: but rather the worke<note n="q" place="margin">Nemo sibi quicquam sumere potest, nisi fit datum ei desuper. Nullus fuit vir magnus fine afflaru divino, Cic.</note> of God to manifest his powerfull presence in ordering of the state Politicall. Hence were those noble spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits called the children of the Gods, and in that any excelled in goodnesse, hee did seeme to bee not of mortall, but of<note n="r" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, &amp;c. Homer. &amp; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, &amp;c. Plato.</note> immortall, generation, and where God hath not the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion
<pb facs="110"/> there to be no<note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Genes.</hi> 10.9. We must discerne betweene the thing, that is, politicall order, which is of God, <hi>&amp; vitia rei,</hi> the vices incident there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, which are from the divell. <hi>Deus trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert. &amp; stabilit regna.</hi> Dan. 4.22. Psal. 18.32. Psal. 144.1.2. St. <hi>Augustine</hi> striving that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> in the Septuagints signifies as well <hi>contra,</hi> as <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> and thereby col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects that <hi>Nimrod</hi> was an oppressor, makes nothing against this, that the hand of God set him up to rule: yea, himselfe confesses the same, <hi>credibilius est quòd seorsum de illo Scriptura propter ejus emenantiam locuta sit, de Civit. Dei. Lib.</hi> 19. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> evasion of evill, and calamitie. The sacred Scripture confirmes this giving to<note n="t" place="margin">That they be volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, &amp; of right judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
      <hi>Nimroth,</hi> not only the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a strong hunter, but adding withall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, that is, the bestowing upon him strength, victory, and happy successe for the erecting of an Empire to proceed from divine ordinance. In these regards therefore the word of God hath good workes, and not ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in common use being much more perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous, and expressing better the<note n="u" place="margin">Psalmista heroicos vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros comparat sagittis Validâ manu contortis, quae omnia prosiernunt, <hi>Psal. 18.32.</hi>
      </note> properties of humane actions well managed. Some workes are of externall discipline, and not raised from <seg rend="sup">x</seg> magnanimitie, and from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine instinct, as the efficient: these latter are as gemmes, and pearles of highest price; those common to many, as their subject; in the one doth appeare nothing, but what is of ordinarie forme; in the other, sundry parts of admiration; here no undertaking, but what is triviall; there such effects, and happy suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, as is beyond all expectation. Howbeit what is heroicall, is not in like manner in <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph,</hi> and <hi>Alexander; David</hi> and <hi>Scipio.</hi> For the one sort were moved by the Spirit of san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification; the other not so: the one sought the honour of God, as the finall cause; the other shot at pompe, and policie, greatnesse of government together with their owne praise, as the upshot of all their hopes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>