<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE FORME OF THE OATH DIVIDED INTO EIGHT branches in that manner as it is treated of in this Disputation.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100389_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15315</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25603</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100389</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE FORME OF THE OATH DIVIDED INTO EIGHT branches in that manner as it is treated of in this Disputation.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A theologicall disputation concerning the oath of allegiance : dedicated to the most holy father Pope Paul the fifth. Wherein all the principall arguments which haue hitherto beene brought by Cardinall Bellarmine, Iacobus Gretzer, Leonard Lessius, Martin Becanus, and diuers others, against the new oath of allegiance, lately established in England by act of Parliament, are sincerely, perspicuously, and exactly examined. By Roger Widdrington, an English Catholike. Translated out of Latin into English by the author himselfe,whereunto hee hath also added an appendix, wherein all the arguments, whach that most learned diuine Franciscus Suarez, hath lately brought for the Popes power to depose princes, and against the aforesaid oath of allegiance, are sincerely rehearsed, and answered</title>
                 <author>Preston, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60, 421, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="30"/>
   <head>THE FORME OF THE OATH DIVIDED INTO EIGHT branches in that manner as it is treated <hi>of in this Disputation.</hi>
   </head>
   <p n="1">1. I <hi>A. B.</hi> do truly and sincerely acknowledge, professe, testifie and declare in my conscience before God and the world, that our Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Iames</hi> is lawfull and rightfull King of this Realme, and of all other his Maiesties Dominions and Countries <hi>pag.</hi> 13.</p>
   <p n="2">2. And that the <hi>Pope</hi> neither of himselfe, nor by any authority of the Church or Sea of Rome, or by any other meanes with any other, hath any power or authoritie to depose the King, or to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose any of his Maiesties Kingdomes or Dominions, or to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize any forraigne Prince to inuade or annoy him, or his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, or to discharge any of his Subiects of their Allegiance and obedience to his Maiestie, or to giue license or leaue to any of them to beare Armes, raise tumult, or to offer any violence, or hurt to his Maiesties Royall person, State, or gouernment, or to any of his Maiesties Subiects within his Maiesties Dominions. <hi>pag.</hi> 19.</p>
   <p n="3">3. Also I doe sweare from my heart, that notwithstanding any declaration or sentence of Excommunication or depriuation made or granted, or to be made or granted by the Pope or his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, or by any Authoritie deriued or pretended to be deriued from him or his Sea against the said King, his Heires or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, or any absolution of the said Subiects from their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: I will beare faith and true allegiance to his Maiestie, his Heires and Successors, and him and them will defend to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of my power against all Conspiracies and attempts whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, which shall bee made against his or their Persons, their Crowne and dignitie, by reason or colour of any such sentence or declaration or otherwise, and will doe my best endeauour to disclose and make knowne vnto his Maiestie, his Heires and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, all Treasons and Traiterous Conspiracies, which I shall
<pb facs="31"/>
know or heare of to be against him or any of them. <hi>pag.</hi> 52.</p>
   <p n="4">4. And I do further sweare, That I do frō my heart abhorre, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, and abiure, as impious and hereticall, this damnable doctrine and position, That Princes which be excommunicated or depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the Pope, may be deposed or murthered by their Subiects, or any other whatsoeuer. <hi>pag.</hi> 68.</p>
   <p n="5">5. And I doe beleeue and in conscience am resolued, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope nor any person whatsoeuer, hath power to absolue me of this Oath, or any part thereof. <hi>pag.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>8.</p>
   <p n="6">6. Which I acknowledge by good and full authoritie to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ministred vnto me, and do renounce all pardons and dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations to the contrary, <hi>pag.</hi> 128.</p>
   <p n="7">7. And all these things I do plainly and sincerely acknowledge and sweare, according to these expresse words by me spoken, and according to the plaine and common sense and vnderstanding of the same words, without any Equiuocation, or mentall euasion, or secret reseruation whatsoeuer. <hi>pag.</hi> 154.</p>
   <p n="8">8. And I doe make this recognition and acknowledgement heartily, willingly, and truly, vpon the true faith of a Christian. So helpe me God. <hi>pag.</hi> 160.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>