<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honourable Sir Iohn
Puckering, Knight Lorde Keeper of the great
Seale of England, Thomas Tymme, wisheth
increase of honour here, to Gods glo∣rie;
and perpetuall felicitie in the
worlde to come.</title>
           <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100442_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05059</idno>
           <idno type="STC">152</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100442</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honourable Sir Iohn
Puckering, Knight Lorde Keeper of the great
Seale of England, Thomas Tymme, wisheth
increase of honour here, to Gods glo∣rie;
and perpetuall felicitie in the
worlde to come.</title>
                 <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe description of Hierusalem and of the suburbs therof, as it florished in the time of Christ : Wherto is annexed a short commentarie concerning those places which were made famous by the Passion of Christ, and by the actes of holye men, confirmed by certeine principall histories of antiquity. Verie profitable for all Christians to read, for the understanding of the Sacred Scriptures and Iosephus his Historie. Hereunto also is appertaining a liuely and beawtifull mappe of Hierusalem, with arithmeticall directions, correspondent to the numbers of this booke. Translated out of Latin into English by Thomas Tymme minister</title>
                 <author>Adrichem, Christiaan van</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Wight, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 <publisher>Bing, Isaac.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cawood, Gabriel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 112, 4 pages, map, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right honourable Sir <hi>Iohn
Puckering,</hi> Knight Lorde Keeper of the great
Seale of England, Thomas Tymme, wisheth
increase of honour here, to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie;
and perpetuall felicitie in the
worlde to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orsomuch as (right
honorable) <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>
the citty of our
God, euen vppon
his holy mountaine
the ioy of the whole
earth, and the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of the greate
King, that faire and
most auncient Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
by a speciall prerogatiue is by God him
selfe bewtified aboue all other Citties: and
was therefore the cheefe, most noble and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Cittie of the worlde: Many trauellers
and Pilgrimes, haue at sundry times both in
Mappes and histories, described the same.
By the aduantage of whose laboures therein,
now of late one <hi>Christien Adrichom,</hi> hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb facs="3"/>
a most liuely description, and in the
Latine tongue enriched with diuers antiquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.
The profit that might come hereby to
my countrimen of the vulgar sorte, both for
the better vnderstanding of the story of the
Bible, where <hi>Jerusalem</hi> and the partes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
are often times mentioned, and also for the
ready conceauing of <hi>Josephus his history,</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
me to translate it into the english tongue:
And the book thus translated, with the charts
expressed in naturall coloures, I haue presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
to dedicate vnto your honour. And bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
the maister workeman in this new plat
of ould decayed <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> hath left behind
him sum rubbish and reliques of the Romish
superstition, I haue in some measure purged
and swept the stretes and corners of the same,
with the broome of truth, and carying them
out by the Scouregate haue layed them on
the Leystall of obliuion. My paines herein ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
though not so great, as the laying of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>salems</hi>
foūdation, or the raising of a chief cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
stone or the squaring &amp; finishing any part
of this exquisite plat: yet such it is, as euen in
the meanest degree of a poore labourer, that
doth but sweepe the streetes, I most humbly
beseech your honor to accept as a small mite
<pb facs="3"/>
of my good will: The which I gladly offer, to
the ende, that amidst the greate burdens of
your most weighty affaires, your honour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlding
this most braue cittie, adorned with
so glorious a temple, and contemplating the
passion of our sauiour Christ therein, may be
delighted and recreated: And further, that
viewing this terrestriall cittie, whose glory is
now vanished, may thinke still as the Apostle
did say, <hi>Non habemus hîc manentem ciuitatem,</hi>
and so aspire to that heauenly <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished
and full stored with all manner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights
which abideth for euer: wherein <hi>I</hi> doo
moste humbly and hartely wish your good
Lordship a most happie residence, after you
haue performed your most honorable course
in this life, in the seruice of your
country, the pleasure of your
prince, the generall benefit
and comfort of your
own soule.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors most dutifull
to command,
Tho: Tymme.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>