<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER in God, George, L. Archbishop of Canterbury his Grace Primate of all England and Metropolitane, And one of his Maiesties most hono∣rable priuie Councell.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100494_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14185</idno>
           <idno type="STC">245</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100494</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER in God, George, L. Archbishop of Canterbury his Grace Primate of all England and Metropolitane, And one of his Maiesties most hono∣rable priuie Councell.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lectures upon the vvhole Epistle of St. Paul to the Philippians, deliuered in St. Peters Church in Oxford: by the reuerend and faithfull seruant of Christ Henry Airay ... and now published for the vse of Gods Church by C.P</title>
                 <author>Airay, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bladen, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 376, 376-598, 592-864, 711-950 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER in God, <hi>George,</hi> L. Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury his Grace Primate of all England</hi> and Metropolitane, <hi>And one of his Maiesties most</hi> hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable priuie Councell.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most reuerend father,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Could not presume to shroud this vnpolished worke vnder so high a Patronage, if J did not hope, that (as <hi>Dauid</hi> loued lame <hi>Mephibosheth</hi> for his good father <hi>Ionothan,</hi> so) your gracious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to this <hi>Author</hi> (now with God) would excuse and pardon, yea accept this
<pb facs="3"/> vnperfited issue of his paines. These pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers were neuer entended for the common view, being fitted in a plaine and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar stile to a popular assembly; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (J confesse) not worthy of your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation: Yet I thought it iniustice ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to depriue the Church of God of the benefit of his labours, or not to consecrate them to your <hi>Graces</hi> hands, to whom the Author was so much obliged. Your graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous countenance and loue vnto him (vpon experience of his integritie whereof you were long a witnes and sometime a iudge) did much comfort him amidst other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of griefe and deiection: His onely requitall were holy praiers for your hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse, which he forgat not in the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of his last sicknes, euen then deuout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entreating the Lord for his blessing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your person, and gouernment. Besides your <hi>Grace</hi> is pleased to make your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours
<pb facs="3"/> (as it were) hereditary, extending them in great measure to his <hi>Successor</hi> our present Gouernour and to our <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> Jn which respect, the best of all our labours are iustly deuoted to your <hi>Grace,</hi> as a small discharge of our duty, if not rather as an acknowledgement of our obligation. These <hi>Lectures</hi> which now I present, are an Exposition of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> diuine letter to the <hi>Philippians:</hi> An Exposition, indeed not sutable to the nicenesse and curiositie of our times, not elegant in words, and without all affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (vnlesse of plainesse:) But yet (lest I too much disparage the Author and his Worke) if I be not mistaken, the naked and naturall sense of this holy Text is here so faithfully opened, and withall so powerfully and thoroughly applied, that (J doubt not) Gods Church and people may hence reape much benefit, which was
<pb facs="4"/> the Authors only aime in the exercise of his ministerie, and shall be my chiefe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Whatsoeuer it is, I humbly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to the blessing of God and to the vse of his Church, desiring to honour it with your <hi>Graces</hi> name, whose Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage shall procure it respect from others. The Lord <hi>Iesus</hi> long preserue your <hi>Grace</hi> (after the ioy of our hearts and the breath of our nostrills his most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maiestie) a great and sure friend of religion, and a worthy instrument of the welfare and peace of this holy and happy Church of <hi>England.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Graces humble Orator</hi> Christopher Potter.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>