<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Post-script for the personate Iesuite Lysimachus Nicanor.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100522_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68103</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1206</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100522</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Post-script for the personate Iesuite Lysimachus Nicanor.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ladensium autokatakrisis, the Canterburians self-conviction : Or an evident demonstration of the avowed Arminianisme, poperie, and tyrannie of that faction, by their owne confessions. With a post-script to the personate Iesuite Lysimachus Nicanor, a prime Canterburian</title>
                 <author>Baillie, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>‘Richt Right’ Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 128, 2, 28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb facs="77"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="77"/>
   <head>A Post-script for the personate Iesuite Lysimachus Nicanor.</head>
   <p>GOod Father <hi>Lies-maker,</hi>
      <note place="margin">It is the common strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme of the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburiās to slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posites with Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suitisme.</note> you doe no new thing to paralell the <hi>Scotish</hi> Covenanters with Jesuites, it is the old and oft rechanted song of your fellows, to put Jesuites and Puritanes (which name all must be content to beare, who will not under your conduct be led back to <hi>Rome</hi>) in one categorie, to make them but two singulars under one spece, both most furious rebels, and by open prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssion most seditious traitours, yet with this difference; that the one, because more opposite to you, must partake more of the nature of the spece; The Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane (as ye must have leave in this season of your Kingdome to play the nomenclat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rs) is growne so big a traitour, that scarce any roome is left for the Iesuite to stand beside him: Not long agoe it was the equitie of your brother <hi>Montagu,</hi> to grant the Iesuite the favour to march with the Puritane under the same colours, in the same ranke, as devils equally furious unhappily borne and fostered to keepe <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> asunder.</p>
   <p>
      <note n="(a)" place="margin">Supra chap 7. A. A.</note>But now it is the wisedome of your grand-father <hi>Laud</hi> to marshall them much better, the Puritane must be farre ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, the <hi>Iesuite</hi> must stand at his back, that so all stroakes, all darts, may light in the bodie of the one, while the other escap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth without any wound, so much as of a word.</p>
   <p>In the very face of that honourable court of the <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> his Grace dare be bold to avow his advice to the King to goe with the Puritanes beyond nose-slitting, cheek-burning, fining above their worth, perpetuall prisoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g; But for the Iesuites, his moderation, his Christian patience must be proclaimed to the world, hee must glorie before the King, that hee counts it unbeseeming his Grace, to serve them with so much as course <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>guage, let be to intēd their persecutiō in the least measure.</p>
   <pb n="2" facs="78"/>
   <p>
      <note n="(b)" place="margin">
         <p>Chap. L.M. N.</p>
         <p>For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes, the Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burians are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to turne Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites.</p>
      </note> Yee must therefore Master <hi>Lies maker</hi> bee content to want the honour of the invention, of this parallell, for the strategeme is old, and now become triviall, onely in this, the rare quicknesse of your wit is to be applauded, and the glory of some new invention here, is not to be denyed to the singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar dexteritie of your engine; Yee are the first of the <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buriane</hi> I know, who for the hatred of their party was content avowedly to enter the <hi>Iesuites</hi> order, and put on their habite, that from under the maske of their broad hatt, might bee spewed out on the face of the Covenanters, such a spet of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiferous venome, as none would suspect could flow from any other fountaine, then the heart of a very <hi>Iesuite:</hi> Surely ye act the <hi>Iesuites</hi> part so well, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> it seemeth ye have much more of him then his hatt and habit: By too curio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s imitation of his behaviour, ye are so habituate in his nature, that ye are not like in haste, though ye would, to lay it aside.</p>
   <p>In this your pamphlet yee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ent so much impudencie, so many lies and slanders, so much spight &amp; crueltie, so high and disdainefull pride, so salt and bitter scoffings, mockings, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, and which is worst of all, so profane and blasphemous abuse of holy Scripture, for yee make it alway the channell where through your wicked humours must runne, for the overwhelming of your enemies; In these <hi>Iesuiticke</hi> arts yee prove so excelent, that in the very first ye are of your noviciat, yee may put in for promotions <hi>per saltum:</hi> Sundrie Provincials have not all their dayes shewed such cunning as you already, if yee make a proportionall progresse, a few yeares may make you generall of the order, if so be your minde can serve you to change your nation the third time; And as ye have turned from Scottish to English, from English to Irish, yee can be content to sweare your selfe full <hi>Spaniard,</hi> at least a devoute Servant to <hi>Philip</hi> the fourth,<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciphering of the name Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simachus Nicanor.</note> for advancement of his Catholick Monarchie, though never so much to the prejudice of your old. Master K. <hi>Charles,</hi> and all Christendome beside.</p>
   <p>Your name demonstrates your vanitie and pride, qualities familiar to your order: Yee must be no lesse then the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>der of
<pb n="3" facs="78"/> the plea, and that by a victorie; Truely ye come in good time to the <hi>Canterburian</hi> troupes, no Christian can be so welcome to them as you, if a <hi>Lysimachus</hi> will convoy them, &amp; break the battell of the poore Covenanters without stroake; or if some stroakes must be distribute, yet it <hi>Nicanor</hi> be on their side, it is the top of their desires. But things are not alwayes correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to their names; Etymologies are sometimes antiphrastick: who before the fight, must needs stamp their ensignes with stiles of victorie and triumph, are compelled sometimes to see their too precipitat joy and gloriation end in disgracefull dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure.</p>
   <p>Or is this onely your vanitie in hiding of your name to proclaime it, in <hi>Lysimachus</hi> to tell us you are D. <hi>Leslie,</hi> in <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canor,</hi> that yee are B. of <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nn</hi> and <hi>Conor,</hi> though this had not beene put in the Frontispiece of your booke, yet any who had perused your former schenick writs, that comedie of your se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Sages, that tragick harrang to your sillie priests, which for the glorie of your name behoved to walk over-sea in a Latine gown, might easily have guessed at your stile and humour in this your last writ: Your professed abode over Sea, your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencie even without all occasion to keepe your selfe off the Irish oath, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ff these Scottish Ministers whom yee did banish from <hi>Ireland,</hi> off the excessive praises of your patron the Deputie.</p>
   <p>These and such other passages of your booke, lift up your maske, and lead any who will, under the shaddow of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites hart, to behold D. <hi>Leslies</hi> head, that upon it, without mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, may be cast all the garlants of honour, which the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of so brave a piece in so necessary a time doth deserve.</p>
   <p>But whoever you bee, whether <hi>Leslie,</hi> or <hi>Maxwell,</hi> or <hi>Michell,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The lāds griefe is the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburiās joy.</note> or who else of the faction, certainly yee are a mirrie man in a very unseasonable time; When the whole Yle is in sadnesse and dule, in feare and trembling, ye are upon your congratularie Epistles; And why not? These are the dayes yee have pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted long for, fire and Sword is your Element, rather then Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall honour should lye in the dust; fire &amp; water, heavē &amp; hel
<pb n="4" facs="79"/> must all goe thorow other: yet who knoweth but your singing in so foule weather may end in mourning to you, and jot to all those who now are weeping for that black storme which ye &amp; his Grace your Prince, have raised in our clemat.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">If wee in one point our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries in an hundreth are Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suited.</note>The onely point wherein yee make Covenanters, draw neare to <hi>Iesuitisme</hi> is in their doctrine of the civill Magistrate, which ye branch out in 16 particulars; Is it not then your mind that whoever leaveth the Protestants in one head of doctrine, doth give to the <hi>Iesuites</hi> matter of congratulation, and a good ground to expect their totall apostasie to the popish religion; This is the onely scope of your whole booke: What then doe you thinke of your fellowes, whom I have assayed to convince by their owne testimonies of a defection from the Protestant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to the worst of the <hi>Iesuites,</hi> not in one head, but so exceeding many, that very few contraverted heads doe remaine, wherein they are not joyned long agoe with the <hi>Jesuites:</hi> Shall partialitie so farre predomine with you, that we Covenanters for confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie with <hi>Jesuites</hi> in one point alone, must be reputed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states from the reformed church of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet ye <hi>Canterburians</hi> though ye declare your conformitie with <hi>Rome</hi> in twentie, in an hundreth, yea, well neare in all the contraverted heads of Doctrine, yet no man without a great dash to a charitie, may begin so much as to doubt of your full Protestanisme.</p>
   <p>That one point wherein ye make us Iesuited, <hi>is the doctrine of the Magistrate:</hi> This to you is the head of the Protestant Faith, and all their other teners but members following that head, your practice is very consonant to this your profession; for your new doctrine of the Magistrate is the first and most be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved article of your Creed, which above all other ye preach and presse with extreame violence: Your new stamped oath of alleadgeance and Supremacie whereby yee would set up the King in a place so farre above the ty of all Lawes, divine and humane, as his royall heart hath ever abhorred to be ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e such an idol. Good Princes in this are like the Saints in glory, all which giveth to them a degree of honour, exceeding the Sphere of man, and entrenshing upon Gods proper glorie,
<pb n="5" facs="79"/> they esteeme them as they are indeed, nothing but flattering effronters of their sacred persons.</p>
   <p>That which ye call the head of all Protestant Religion,<note place="margin">The bounds of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and peoples subiectiō are points of state, not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily doth not concerne Religion at all: Religion indeed doth oblige the conscience to give unto all Magistrates their due honour and obedience, but the bounds and limits of that obedience, which is the onely point ye speake off, Religion meddleth not with them till the civill Lawes of States &amp; Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires have clearly defined them.</p>
   <p>No Religion will oblige a <hi>Spaniard</hi> to be so farre subject to King <hi>Philip,</hi> as a <hi>Grecian</hi> slave must be to the Great <hi>Turke,</hi> neither doth any Religion equall the <hi>Polonish</hi> Subjection to their King, with the Spanish to theirs.</p>
   <p>Doth any Religion oblige the Electours of <hi>Germanie</hi> to be so much subiect to their Emperour, as the Nobles in <hi>Pole</hi> are to their King, or so little subject as the <hi>Venetian</hi> Senate is to their Duke, or the States of <hi>Holland</hi> is to the Prince of <hi>Orange?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The civill Lawes and Customes, set downe the limites both of the Soveraignes commanding, and the subjects obedience: Religion causeth these march-stones conscienciously to bee kept when once Policie hath fixed them.</p>
   <p>It seemeth ye intend to make <hi>England</hi> quit their <hi>Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> and burn their <hi>magna charta;</hi> to make <hi>Scotland</hi> bury their <hi>Assemblies</hi> &amp; <hi>Parliaments,</hi> that a blank may be put in <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buries</hi> hand to write down what Lawes he will for the Church and State of both the Nations: But thankes be to God that King <hi>Charles</hi> doth live, to be judge betwixt you and us in so materiall a question.</p>
   <p>Yee tell us further in your preambles,<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of this Yle to fall in hands of the Pope &amp; Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard.</note> before ye come to your first paralell of <hi>Pope Ʋrbans</hi> hope, to make <hi>Scotland</hi> return to <hi>Rome,</hi> yee might have told us further from your companion <hi>Con,</hi> who is more acquainted with <hi>Ʋrbans</hi> secrets then other men, that the Pope hath a pretty confidence to joyne <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Scotland,</hi> that so the reduction of the whole Yle, &amp; your <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with it, to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> may be set up as an eternall
<pb n="6" facs="80"/> trophee to the honour of this p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pes family; Surely the ground-stones of this hope are laid on so deepe plots, that except the hand of God and the king in this present Parliament pull them up, Pope <hi>Ʋrban</hi> for all his age, may yet live to putt the triumphall cope stone upon that building.</p>
   <p>We grant you also, that the Pope and Jesuites, as yee say, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re hovering above the head of us all, to fall upon the prey of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll Britaine, when both parties, which your mallice will compell to fight, are wearied with mutuall wounds; in this prophecie we thinke you but too true divines, specially if ye will adde, which all without the gift of prophecie may see to be conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that when the Pope hath gotten the soules of those who out-live this warre for his part, his Sons the <hi>French</hi> or Catholik King, will not be quiet, except for their share they gett the bodies,<note place="margin">The most hated of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, their covenant it self, is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the king.</note> the goods, and liberties of all this poore Yle.</p>
   <p>Your other gybes at the Covenanters proceedings yee might have holden in, if the honour of the King had any wayes been deare unto you; the worst of all our actions, even that which ye were wont to proclaime our most vile, and hellish rebellion, Sedition, Treason, and what else ye could devise, is now by our gracious Prince after a full search of it to the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, not onely absolved of all crime, but so farre approved, that by act of Assembly, Counsell, articles of Parliament, it is commanded to be subscribed by the hearts and hands of all in this Kingdome without exception; So that new there stands at the back of that long blasphemed Covenant among the first and most conspicuous hands, not onely <hi>Roxburgh, Lawder-dale, South<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ke,</hi> and others of the prime Counsellours, but also <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quair</hi> the Kings great Commissioner for that effect; We hope then that you and your like, if there remaine any sparke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence in your breast towards that authoritie, which oft yee pretend to adore, will not onely for ever hereafter bridle your very loose tongues, but also eate in againe, or at last cover so farre as ye can, for hidding of your shame, these most false lies, and unchristian railings, which these two yeares by-gone in word, writ, Print, ye have vomitted out against our proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="7" facs="80"/> especially that most hatred &amp; slandered passage of them, the renewing of our Covenant.</p>
   <p>The fi st point wherein ye parallell us with <hi>Jesuites,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. paralel Wee are for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, but aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inst Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical tyranny.</note> is in our opposition to Monarchicall government. By Monarchicall government yee expresl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> enough declare that ye understand such an absolute and illimitate power, as exeemeth the Prince from the tye of all Law▪ and puts in his hand the full libertie to make what Lawes he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll, with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut the advice, let bee consent of Parliament, of Counsell, or of any others, and taketh abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely all Liberty from his Subjects, though met together in Parliament to defend them elves by Armes in any imaginable oppression, even such a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>narchie as the great Turke, or the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>gor of I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dia,</hi> or the <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m of Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tarie,</hi> this day doth enjoy over their slaves even that strange kinde of government, which in my last Chapter I descrived in the words of your brethren. We confesse freely; that our heart is much opposite to such a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>narchie; yet no more then our gracious Prince king <hi>Charles</hi> &amp; his glorious Father king <hi>Iames</hi> give us expresse warrant: The one in his fore-cited writ of his Atturney<note n="(c)" place="margin">Supr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> chap 8. Q.R.</note> abhorring these injurious flatterers, who would impute unto him the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Lawes without his Parliament; the other in his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Speach<note n="(d)" place="margin">Page 531. A king go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning in a set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, leaveth to bee a King, &amp; degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth in to a tirāt as soone as hee leaveth off to rule ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Lawes. Therefore all Kings that are no tyrants, or perjured, will be glad to bound themselves within the limits of their Lawes: They that perswade them the contrarie, are vipers, and posts▪ both against them and the Common-wealth.</note> making that Prince a perjured tyrant, who would not gladly bound himself within the limits of his laws, and these men to be taken for vipers, pests, and common enemies to Princes and people, who would assay by their flatteries to loose Princes from their pactions made with their people at their Coronation, and the setled lawes of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, yea, we show that your own great Bishop <hi>Laud</hi> (possibly as great a Royalist as is needfull) goeth before us with his own mouth, what ever he directeth you and many other of his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers to the contrary, to teach that no statute<note n="(e)" place="margin">Supra. Cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Q</note> Law can bee made any where but in Parliament, even in England, let bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cotland, where to this day never any conquerour did dwell.</p>
   <pb n="8" facs="81"/>
   <p>But as for true Monarchie so high as the lowable lawes any where do make it, we are in nothing opposite thereto, for what have we to doe to condemne the setled state &amp; Lawes of any other Nation? Certainly the royall authority of our owne gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Soveraigne, so far as the lowable lawes of our Kingdome doe extend it, we are sworne in our Covenant heartily to the uttermost of our power to maintaine.</p>
   <p>As for the lawfulnesse<note place="margin">The law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulnesse of defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Arms</note> of resistance in the present case of our invasion, I may not enter in this short postscript in any such question; onely ye may, if ye please understand, that it hath been the tenet of our Church since the reformation, it hath been the right and practice of our Kingdome since the first foundation, a number of instances thereof are approved in our standing acts of Parliament unrepealed to this day, it hath been the practice of all the reformed Churches abroad, wherein, by Queen <hi>Elizabeth, King Iames,</hi> &amp; <hi>King Charles</hi> they have been all allowed, and the most of them countenanced with power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full assistance of men and money. Your self cannot deny, but in the judgement of reformed Divines, resistance in many cases is lawfull, even in Kingdomes where the Prince is tyed in the fundamentall lawes by paction to his people: That this is the State of the kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> though ye may deny it, yet King <hi>James,</hi> who is like to have as great understanding in the rights of the Crowne and Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> as you, or your like, gives us assurance that by a fundamentall law the King of Scotland is obliged at his coronation to paction under his great oath the preservation of the established Religion, of the Lawes of the Kingdome, of the Liberties, and priviledges of the Subjects.<note n="(f)" place="margin">P. 105 In the Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, our Kings give their oath, first to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Religion present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed, &amp; punish al those that should alter or disturbe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession thereof: and next to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the lowable &amp; good lawes made by their predecessours; &amp; lastly, to maintain the whole Countrie and every state therein. And this oath in the Coronation is the clearest, civill &amp; fundamentall Law, whereby the Kings office is properly defined.</note> However we love your ingenuity, who doe not dissemble but professe openly your minde, that when a faction about a Prince by divine providence is permitted to take courses for the evident overthrow both of the Religion, of the Lawes, of the Liberties, of the goods, of the lives, and all that is deare to an whole kingdome; that in those or any other
<pb n="9" facs="81"/> imaginable cases of tyrannie, whole Parliaments may not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed for their defence one step beyond teares, prayers, and flight: That what ever is done more by whole and consentient nations against a faction of Court misleading the Prince, is simplie unlawfull.</p>
   <p>Your scoffes about the questions of Bishops and Elders de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve no answer;<note place="margin">Our Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout bish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops and ruling El<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders, the king hath appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> nothing doe we maintaine in them but what the assemblies of our church at our first reformation ordained, and was in peaceable practice among us ever, till men of your coat by fraudulent and violent wayes for their owne ambition and avarice, set up their novations: We have no other minde in those questions then the Church of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>France:</hi> All our tenets are so well cleared by that Learned <hi>Hollander, Gersome Bucerus,</hi> as none of your partie, hath yet beene bold, after 22. yeares advisement, to make any reply; yea, we main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine no more in these questions then that wherewith our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Prince by his Commissioner and act of Counsell in our last generall assemblie hath declared himselfe to be well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; but ye are a notable deceaver, while ye would make the world beleeve that the great questions betwixt you and us are alone about Bishops and Elders, while as ye are very like (if ye be not marred) by the hands of Bishops to bring in upon us the whole bodie of Poperie, and to overthrow the whole civill Priviledges of both the Nations without any possible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie as your selfe in this same place doeth too evidently declare.</p>
   <p>Upon your first parallell we make but one other remarke:<note place="margin">The <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburiās</hi> in all their le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of tyrannie, have the Jesuites for their Masters.</note> Yee wrong much the <hi>Iesuites</hi> in denying them the honour to be your adiuncts in the re-erection of a tyrannick and turkish Monarchie in Christendome: Your ambition herein is too great, it were better to admitt these pregnant wits to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partners in your glorie, then to venture you alone upon so high a designe.</p>
   <p>The opposition, which that worke can not but suffer, may make it breake in your hands, if ye be not supported with their effectuall assistance, in this art they are your Masters,
<pb n="10" facs="82"/> yee are but meere novices; it is unjustice to dissemble from whom ye have learned, if ye deny your theifts from them, the world about you is not blinde, they see &amp; laugh at your poore and ill contrived cunning, for who now is ignorant, that the Jesuites above all men living, have obtained long agoe the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to sit in <hi>Machiavels</hi> chaire, that from thence they may teach every where their lectures of tyrannie, for the re-erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a spirituall Monarchie in the whole Church for the pope, in their owne societie for the generall, in the whole universe, in things temporall, a Catholick Monarchie for the <hi>Spaniard;</hi> And while these furthest ends may bee gotten and compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, an absolute Monarchie for the Prince in every countrie where they can gett footing. What ever paines of old the Pope did take to weaken Emperours and Kings, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of his owne greatnesse, yet now, being fully assured of their constant affection to beare his Yoake, he hath this last age beene as busie as lay in his power, in lifting up of their head by the hands, chiefly of the Jesuites, to the toppe of all Tyrannie, with the extreame prejudice of their Subiects, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Lawes.</p>
   <p>Who else were the prime Counsellours of <hi>Philip</hi> the second, for to spoile his ancient Kingdome of <hi>Arragon</hi> of their great priviledges, and to bring them downe to the same basenesse of Subiection, wherein his great grand father <hi>Ferdinand</hi> had putt the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ores of Granada?</hi> Who else did stirre him up to begin that course of tirannie with <hi>Flanders,</hi> which hath cost him more money alreadie, then this day all <hi>Europe</hi> can command, and more men then are living <hi>Spaniards?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Who else were the advisers of King <hi>Lues</hi> the 13. to spoile his ancient Kingdome of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and his Fathers best friends the Protestants, of these priviledges which they had long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed peaceably under former Kings?</p>
   <p>Who wakened the late King of <hi>Pole,</hi> to present the Yoake of tirannie to the necke of his ancient Subiects in <hi>Swaine?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Had the late Emperour any other movers to these cruell op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions, which first in his own hereditarie Estates, then in the
<pb n="11" facs="82"/> Kingdome of <hi>Boheme,</hi> and last in the whole Empire, hee did practise to the very evident hazard of his Crowne, to the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite &amp; unspeakable afflictions of <hi>Germanie,</hi> through the mids and all the foure corners thereof; was not the maine and graund quarrell of all these Troubles, the too great affection of a Monarchick tyrannie, of an absolute domination without tye of Lawes, Oaths, Covenants, wherewith the Jesuites in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired the heart of that man, otherwise not the worst of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Though therefore it be your craft for your better lurking to professe your Separation from the Jesuits in this your great enterprise of erecting in <hi>Britaine</hi> a new Monarchicke tirannie; Yet the world is not so blinde as you suppose, but seeth you clearly linked hand in hand, the Jesuites leading the ring, and you but following and dancing to their measures.</p>
   <p>Your second paralell is wholie <hi>Jesuitick,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell. We are farr from subiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Crowne of our King, to will of his people.</note> the throwing of holie Scriptures unto your wicked Scoffes at the gracious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, the laying to our charge imputations, which never entred in our thoughts; Did anie of us ever teach that royall authoritie did depend upon the multitude, and that it was in their power to give Crownes to whom they would? When these men are bold to put in print before the Eyes of the world such slanders of us, what doe they instill in the eares of our King and his Servants in their privie Conferences? Shall anie wonder that so long as such men get leave to spread, without a reply, such horrible calumnies of us, that the heart of our gracious Prince, and manie about him should be much inflammed to our hatred?</p>
   <p>What he speaketh of divine institution of Kings, wee doe believe it, that by God Kings doe reigne, it is plaine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; as also that all advancement is neither from the East, nor the West, but from the hand of the most High: So that all who denie to any Superiour the obedience which is due to their Lawfull commands, must sinne against God: We grant that some of our Opposites have here a conceit which we doe not well understand, they seeme to teach that royaltie alone, and that most absolute, without any limitation, is of divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution,
<pb n="12" facs="83"/> that all other governments whether of republick or aristocracies are but humane inventions, opposite to the Law of nature and the first institution of God; This state-speculia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion seemeth to us a curiositie, wherewith we have nothing to doe; it is enough for us to beleeve that our King is set over us by God as his Deputy; that since the time our old ancestours did choose <hi>Fergus</hi> for their King, oblidging themselves by their oath to be ruled by his race alone, according to the laws made, and to be made with publick consent, yea, since the days of King <hi>Kenneth</hi> the third, to be governed by his nearest heire: Our subiection to the nearest heire of that race is now simplie unchangeable:</p>
   <p>The least motion of any such change hath as little come in the minde of our Nation in these dayes of King <hi>Charles,</hi> as in any age of the last two thousand Yeares, wherein our Fathers have shewed more constant affection to the service of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecessours, then any other Nation under the Heaven this day to their royall families. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>at here ye rechant of our minde to a resistance and defensive warre in some cases, is nothing contrarie to this our profession; Many bickerings have our predecessours had with misleading factions, to which the Prince for a time hath given his countenance, but they were ever willing to distinguish betwixt the Prince and his mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informers,<note place="margin">3. Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell, The Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburiās give to the Prince much more power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Church, then the Iesuites give to the Pope.</note> to see them punished when their insolent tyrannie become intolerable; but the Prince setled in the full strength of his authoritie, which for a time the cloud of these grasse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers did eclipse in the hearts of his people.</p>
   <p>The third point wherein ye joyne us with the <hi>Iesuites</hi> is our denying to the King the government of the Church: In this ye doe us wrong, as in all the rest, for we reiect the Popish doctrine here; They make Princes meer sheep, they command them to follow the Pope their pastor, where ever he leads, were it to the bottome of Hell, without asking so much as <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine quid facis,</hi> but we esteeme it to be a chiefe part of the Magistrates office to command all Church-men to doe their dutie, and when they will not be perswaded with cleare rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
<pb n="13" facs="83"/> to compell them by force to reforms the corruptions in the worship of God; But ye skift out here much further to an extravagance, wherein ye have no approved divine to be your patron.</p>
   <p>Yee teach, that all Soveraignes are the true heads of the Churches in their Dominions; Such styles the Bishops of England since the beginning of Queene <hi>EliZabeths</hi> reigne, have ever denyed to their Princes, with their owne content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Ye will have not only the Magistrate to command that which is right in the service of God, as <hi>Austine</hi> and wee doe gladly grant, but also ye make it his right, were he a professed heretick, or Pagan, to give what lawes he will to the Church, without her consent, or so much as advice: Ye give to the Prince much more, then the <hi>Iesuites</hi> will grant to the Pope, to doe in the Church even without a Counsell, what he thinkes meetest, and if it be his pleasure to call a Counsell, ye make it his only right to call either of the laitie or the Cleargie, whom he will, to be members thereof, and when these members are conveened, ye give to the Prince alone the power of judging and deciding, and to all others but of meere advice; Except so farre as the Prince is pleased to communicate to so many of them as he thinkes meete his owne decisive voice. In such a Counsell, or without it, ye make it the Princes right, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy at his pleasure all Church-Canons, Church-judicatories, and formes of divine worship, which by Lawes and long customes have been established, and to impose new Confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Faith, new Ecclesiasticke judicatories, new Bookes of Canons, Leiturgie, Ordination, Homilies, Psalmes, by meere authoritie.</p>
   <p>All this by your perswasion yee moved our Prince to assay, but upon better information his royall justice is now pleased to reiect all such your designes, for his Majestie hath given to us assurance, not only at his Campe, but by his Commissioner in our last Assemblie; and we hope also that at once this assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance shall be confirmed in Parliament, that no ecclesiastick no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation shal over be required by his Maj: but that wherto a free
<pb n="14" facs="84"/> generall Assemblie shall give their full assent. In this point therefore betwixt us and our Prince there is no discrepance, neither here had wee ever any difference with any reformed Divine:</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">4. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell. About convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Synods we have no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiō with the king.</note>Your fourth challenge, that we deny to the King power to convocate Assemblies, yet know the contrarie, that we give to all Christian Soveraignes so much interesse in the affaires of the Church as to convocate Assemblies where and whensoever they please: But we grant that we are no wayes of your minde in this point, that the Church may never lawfully meere in any case, though Heresie and Schisme were eating up her life, and drinking her heart bloud, without the call of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate, that no Church meeting at all is lawfull, no, not for prayer or Sacraments without the Magistrates permission: That all Churches must lye under an interdict and no publick meeting in them must bee, till the Magistrates, licence bee first obtained.</p>
   <p>Is all opposition to you in these things <hi>Iesuitisme?</hi> what ever difference we have here with you, yet with our Prince in this point we are fully agreed.</p>
   <p>Your gratious Brethren and Fathers when we had beene in possession continually after the reformation, for common, of two generall Assemblies yearlie, by their wicked dealing spoiled us of all that Libertie, so that for 38 Yeares space wee had no generall Assemblie to count of but two, both which were thrust upon us against our heart for the advancement alone of their evill purposes: Yet now, thankes be to God, our Prince being wel informed of the mischivous wrong your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie did to us in this matter, hath granted our reasonable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, if so be the like of you, make not this grant fruitlesse unto us, as ye truely intend; The old act of Parliament for yearlie generall Assemblies, and ofter <hi>pro re nata,</hi> is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the Kings Commissioner to be very reasonable, and with his consent hath past the articles of our late Parliament, so that our Prince now is very well content that from the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Assemblie the highest Ecclesiastick Court, being so fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="15" facs="84"/> to bee keept, should come no appeale at all to him.</p>
   <p>Your fift and sixt parallell are cast together,<note place="margin">The 5. &amp; 6. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell. We have no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion with our Prince, about his presiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in counsels.</note> the Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidencie in generall Assemblies, &amp; Supremacie in Ecclesiastick affaires yee handle these so confusedlie with so many wicked scoffings and scurrilous abusing of scripture, that your meaning can scarce be understood.</p>
   <p>Wee are so fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re from denying to the Prince the place of royall presidencie and moderation in our Assemblies, as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> used it at <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> and King <hi>Iames</hi> oft in Scotland, that it is one of the things our hearts m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st desire to see King <hi>Charles</hi> possessing in his owne person that priviledge. His royall S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>premacie we willingly yeel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, so farre as the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Lawes of our C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>urch and Kingdome extend it, yea we make no question that in that sense <hi>Bilson,</hi> and the old Bishops of England understood it. But your late Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie of the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ngs Supremacie, whereby ye ascrive to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Soveraigne much more then any <hi>Iesuite</hi> ever gave to the Pope, wee doe reject it with the Kings good leave, as before was said,</p>
   <p>Your repeated cavills at our Elders, Sessions, Presbyteries, and Assemblies is not worth the answering: The frame of our Discipline established by the Lawes of our Church and State, in <hi>Holland</hi> &amp; <hi>France,</hi> practized peaceably in the happiest times of our Church, and in daily use since the first reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without any quarrell is now ratified by our Prince:<note place="margin">7. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel. We are much for ther then our op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posites from the doctrine of the churches infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</note> So your mouth should bee stopped and your tongue silent what ever boyling be in your breast.</p>
   <p>In your seventh parallell, ye lay upon the <hi>Iesuites</hi> and our back, that which is your owne burden, ye might have knowne that the <hi>Iesuites</hi> ascrive to no Counsell any infallibilitie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out many distinctions: And as for us, none is ignorant that we beleeve all meetings of men since the Apostles dayes to be fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible and subject to errour. Wee did indeed in our Covenant promise to abstaine from the practise of these novations, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by yee had long keept our poore Church in a flaming fire,
<pb n="16" facs="85"/> till a generall Assemblie hath brought them to the touch stone of a new triall: When the Assemblie of <hi>Glasgow</hi> had passed this tryall upon them according to our desire, we embraced the Synodick Sentence, and resolve to adhere thereto, because we finde it agreeable to cleare reason, else be sure, that all the Assemblies of the world should never have obliged our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences to have beleeved any thing which to us did appeare erroneous.</p>
   <p>Such an inslaving of mens consciences was a part of your tyrannie among us: No orders from your hands could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted, till a man had sworne and subscribed simple obedience to all your decrees, not only past, but to come: An expression of any condition of consonancie to the word of God, or any other such limitation, was a certaine note of Puritanisme and disaffection to the present government. Yea such an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie ye wont to ascribe to a few of your Bishops, let be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Assemblies, that ye made a Canon for the excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of all, who should be bold to affirme the least errour in any of their workes, whether of Canons, Leiturgie, Homilies<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> or any thing else,<note place="margin">The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-booke, Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, &amp; other corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which the King hath cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure, are still de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by our opposits.</note> that came through their holy hands.</p>
   <p>What here ye cavill at our reiection of your manifold cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the doctrine and discipline of our Church, as if we did set up so many new articles of Faith, as ye did lately, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours which now we doe reiect, is not worth a reply: But that open declaration which here ye make of your great affection towards the articles of <hi>Perth,</hi> Episcopacie, bookes of Service, and Canons, and great disaffection to the very confession of Faith, made by <hi>King Iames,</hi> we cannot passe without observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The inclination of your mind to these articles, we did truely suspect by many probable signes; But that with your patron, <hi>Canterburies</hi> permission, ye should so soone have beene licenced to put these, your thoughts in print wee did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect: Yee will we hope hereafter esteeme it no calumnie nor want of charitie in us, to avow, that notwithstanding our Assemblies ordinance, and the Kings Majesties command with the consent of his Counsell, to all this Nation, to subscribe
<pb n="17" facs="85"/> the abjuration of these novelties, yet that our poore Church is in great danger to be pestered againe with them all, since the like of you are countenanced to print, even to this day, such ample defences of all these corruptions, and to give to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-booke so high a commendation, that if it be true, our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing of it cannot be but a high sinne against God, and as you told us before, an intollerable insolence before the King, whom ye teach, to discipline us for that fault with a strange punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Ye will have that rejected Booke resumed and stuffed with a new supplement of more Romish stuffe, and then quickly thrust upon us with this peremptour alternative, either quietly to beare that Yoake, or presently to be banished the Land.</p>
   <p>As for Episcopacie, ye will have us embrace it with as great faith as we doe the Bookes of Canonicall Scripture. Yee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, that Scripture is for neither of the two, that Tradition is for both; and that Tradition is to be received with no smaller assent then a divine and undoubted faith, albeit <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie</hi> your patron permitt you to print all these things, yet upon your word in this place, we must take him for an arch-enemie to all poperie.</p>
   <p>In your eight paralell,<note place="margin">8. Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell. The Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburiās offer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more disgraces to Kings, thē their opposits.</note> ye object to us the excommunication of Kings; This is but your slander; We goe not so farre in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of <hi>Ambrose</hi> course with the Emperour <hi>Theodosus,</hi> as <hi>Bilson</hi> alloweth. Of our moderation in this point we have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven good proofe; For in all the troubles which your faction first and last hath moved our Princes to bring upon us, ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not say without a manifest lie, that ever any of us had the least thought of putting upon them any Church censure: What ye might doe, if Kings were turned your enemies, we know not, only now when they are your benefactours, farre above your deserving, we see how coursly ye serve them; they must as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faine laicks be kept far aback with railes from that holy place, where ye, the Lords priests with your consecrate and anointed bodies doe stand at the Altar: Emperours must light downe from their horse and adore you, they must acknowledge their
<pb n="18" facs="86"/> Crownes to be so farre subiect to your Miters as a bodie is to the Soule, or a man to God.</p>
   <p>
      <note n="(g)" place="margin">Supra cap. 3. M. N.</note> Readily so base persons might get a whip of your Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall rod, if once ye were firmly established in your Episcopall Thrones, as long agoe ye would have beene, if these turbulent Puritanes, who still have beene rocking and keeping your Chaires in motion, had beene put out of the world.</p>
   <p>What thornes Bishops have beene in the sides of Kings, especially in England, the Chronicles of that Nation doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and above all other Bishops, these of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> the mischivous conspiracie of one of them with <hi>Henrie of Darbie</hi> against his great Benefactour <hi>Richard</hi> the second, ought never to be out of <hi>King Charles</hi> eye: No passage of the English storie is more worthie of his meditation.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">9. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel. We are nothing opposite to the power of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but wee make Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be meere cyphers.</note>In the ninth Paralell, your scoffing and railing veine flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after the old manner; ye obiect our annulling of the acts of Parliament by the decrees of our Assemblie, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending of the power of our Synods to many secular affaires: Doubtlesse ye are the men, who by your shoulders most care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully will under-prop the decaying power of Parliaments: It grieveth much your Soules to see Parliaments slighted in any of their due rights; Alwayes remember your owne, and your brethrens Tenets, whereby ye make all Parliaments but meere ciphers the arbitrarie Counsels of the Prince, to which by his Letters he hath right to call what Commissioners he will, and hold back whom he pleaseth; with whom or without whom as he thinketh meet, it is his owne only right to make, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret, to abolish Lawes, to publish them by himselfe alone, and command them by a meere Proclamation to be received by all the Subiects, without the consent or advice of any man, further then is his pleasure to crave:</p>
   <p>This your brethren oft in formall tearmes,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Supra cap. 8. E. E. F. F. G. G, &amp;c.</note> and your selfe in the same page sets downe in effect. What ye speak of our encroaching upon Parliaments, is no wayes true, only some evill acts of your evidently corrupted Assemblies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ye had obtained by your familiar arts of fraud and force:
<pb n="19" facs="86"/> the ratification of some Parliaments, we did recognosce, and that alone in their Ecclesiastick part, with the good leave of the Kings Commissioner: As for the civill sanction of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to the ordinary Ecclesiastick proceeding of our Church in all by gone times, wee did appoint Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners from our Assembly, to supplicate the Parliament for the abolition thereof. Neither doe we meddle at all in our Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods with secular affaires, remember what your selfe in your Canons doe pronounce, to be the due and lawfull Subject of Ecclesiastick jurisdiction, ye will finde that our generall Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies did never take in so much matter as ye appropriate to any of your officiall Courts.</p>
   <p>Our act anent the going of Mills and Salt-pans upon the Sabbath-day, was but a renovation, and that with the Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners consent, of an old act in a former Assemblie, whereat <hi>King Iames</hi> was present; It seemeth it grieveth you to see the Sabbath sanctified among us, that yee are but like your brother, to whom Sunday is no Sabbath, but a day wherein games of all kinde, also diverse kindes of Husband labour should publickly be allowed, for the crossing of that Jewish Superstition, whereby Puritanes abuse that Festivall. What further here ye obiect of our unwillingnesse to subscribe at the Counsels direction the Covenant, at it was dated in the yeare 1581. without the application of it to your later corruptions, which addition we had sworne before, yee will finde that we had good reason so to doe, your selfe being judge; for ye tell us that all these your corruptions, even the Service-Booke it selfe, are very consonant with that Covenant, and that the main end why the Subscription thereof was urged, was the cleane quiting of these additions formerly sworne, and now by the mercy of God fully approved by the King, by his Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by his Counsell, by the Assemblie, by the articles of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all, but men of your stuffe, who resolve to die, let all the world about you be never so fickle, with the untainted glorie of constant obstinacie.</p>
   <p>In your tenth Paralell, Yee act the <hi>Iesuite</hi> so perfectly,<note place="margin">10. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell. Both out Covenāt and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steriour proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings shew us no wayes to be oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site to the oath of allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</note>
      <pb n="20" facs="87"/> that few hereafter will hope for the praise of going beyond you in their arts: your pen drops so many Sentences, so many cursed lyes, so many blasphemous wrestings of mens words and writs. Deny we the Oath of alleadgeance, the words of our Covenant and mutuall defence, whereupon yee would build that denyall, let be that they are approved by our King as said is, doe not they stand expresly in <hi>King James</hi> Covenant, yea in the vesy first Confession of our Fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>?</p>
   <p>Is not our late Covenant an expresse renewing of our oath of alleadgeance in so strict tearmes as is possible?</p>
   <p>Did our armed defence, in that desperate extremitie which your faction put us unto, import any danger to the Kings person or Crowne? Did we not then before all the world give a sufficient proofe of our humble loyaltie and practice of our Covenant?</p>
   <p>At the very hight of all our advantages and your too well knowne unreadinesse at that time for fighting, at the least ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of his Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sties minde, to lay by armes, to leave the prosecution of your bloudy desires, were we not content to cast our selves at his feete, to put our Munition in his hand, and all our Castles in his power, to be stockes to our feet, and roaps to our neckes; had our hearts been in the least measure so trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable as you slander, would these have been our actions?</p>
   <p>What ye speake of our Forfathers actions in Queen <hi>Regent</hi> and Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, ye are into it, but answerable to your name a true Jesuite. The defence of the Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Kingdome against the Guisian usurpations in the minoritie of our Queen, and our Queens voluntary dimission of the government to her Sonne <hi>King James,</hi> after many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable misaccidents: These and such like proceedings of our Forfathers, confirmed by our standing acts of Parliament, <hi>Iesuites</hi> of old wont to blaspheme, but all the reformed, and none more then the Bishops of England, especially Doctor <hi>Bilson,</hi> doe vindicate from their wicked aspersions, which yet ye have a stomach to resorbe; to spew them out once againe upon our face: But ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> are priviledged to speake all your
<pb n="21" facs="87"/> pleasure, for yee are here on a Stage under the maske of a furious phrentick <hi>Iesuite,</hi> at the back of this curtaine, yee may belch out what yee will, all is conforme to the person yee sustaine.</p>
   <p>In your eleventh, twelve, and thirteenth parellel,<note place="margin">11. 12, 13. Para. Blinde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to mens Lawes, binding of the consciē<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e by them, works of Supere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation are not ours, but your te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets.</note> ye doe but toy; the three faults ye object to us of blinde obedience, of binding the conscience, workes of Supererogation, we are free of them all: But see if ye can free your owne faction of any one thereof, for your brethren teach, that all men must give quicke obedience unto all their injunctions, not only in the midst of their deepest ignorance of any reason for these in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions, but also in the midst of never so many doubts and perplexities and strong inclinations to thinke your acts most unlawfull. Ye will admitt neither ignorance nor the greatest doubtings to bee any impediment to the present obedience of your Episcopall injunctions, how farre is this from that yee pronounce in us, blinde obedience.</p>
   <p>Againe, yee make all the commandements of the Church to be branches of the fift command, and to be obeyed as the precepts of God, which we suppose doe binde the conscience.</p>
   <p>For the third, yee teach more merite of workes then <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> yea, yee proclaime that the following of the counsels of perfection, that the keeping of the three Monastick vowes doth deserve an augmentation, as ye call it, an <hi>Aureola</hi> above common happinesse.</p>
   <p>In your fourteenth also yee cast upon us your owne dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick fault of Equivocation:<note place="margin">14. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell. No equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation used by us in any of our proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</note> Are you ignorant how your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Bishops of Scotland did swear their famous caveats: In the very time while they were dressing for our Church, their Canons and Leiturgie, which the large declaration tells us, were alwayes in hand from the 16 yeare to the 38, how oft did they swear to many who proponed to them their feares of their underminding practices, that they were utterly ignorant of all further novations to bee brought into our Church: As for these matters, wherein yee make us equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators, we were farre in any of them from that Crime.</p>
   <pb n="22" facs="88"/>
   <p>We truely without any equivocation doe thinke our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to be for the King, and no wayes against either his perso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> or authoritie, we thinke in our minde, that in some cases resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance to Princes is much better service, and one day will be so acknowledged, then present obedience: How oft have Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces professed at last themselves much more beholden to those who with displayed banners hath come against their Campe, then to others, who by their flattering service and wicked perswasions, moved them to take up their unjust armes.</p>
   <p>Ye doe well by the passages of <hi>King James</hi> writs which hee let fall in passion against some few persons as himselfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth to incite <hi>King Charles</hi> to destroy the whole generation of your opposits.</p>
   <p>For that equivocation which ye obiect to some in their sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing of the Covenant at the Commissioners and Counsels direction; sufficient satisfaction is given long agoe to all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable men by published writs: The matter shortly was this, one of your factious ingines, to draw us subtilie from that Covenant, wherein we did abiure Bishops, Bookes, and the rest of your novations, which were contrarie to the doctrine and discipline of our Church, was, a new subscription to the first part of this Covenant, as it was first set downe in the yeare 1580, without our late addition, wherein it was applyed to your newly obtruded novations: Upon hope by this new subscription, that not only, the formerly subscribed addition and abjuration of these novelties expressed in that addition, should be forgotten; but also that meanes should be gotten to perswade that these once abiured novations were in nothing contrary to the Kings Covenant, yea that all of them were so much conforme to it, and virtually contained therein, that all the subscrivers should finde themselves oblidged by that oath and subscription, to embrace the articles of <hi>Perth,</hi> the Canons, the Leiturgie, and all the intended novations, at least, without all doubt Episcopacie, the Fountaine whence the rest had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded; and from which they knew they would flow againe in due time, if it alone could be gotten preserved.</p>
   <pb n="23" facs="88"/>
   <p>This was the true intention of the Commissioner in pressing that new subscription, as his Grace did publish thereafter in print, but in the first proposition of that new oath, all such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe was carefully concealed, yet wise men among us, fearing and foreseing the plot, did carefully diswade that new sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription, as a dangerous master piece, invented for the utter destruction of the true sense of our first subscribed Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
   <p>Their advice was heard by the most part, who thereupon refused that new subscription, yet some knowing perfectly well, that the Covenant in the 1581, did not include Episcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, or any of the late novations, but clearely enough excluded them; Since the Commissioner his Grace in the proponing that subscription, did make no declaration at all, neither of his owne, nor of his Master the Kings minde, to have Episcopacie, or any of these novations included in that Covenant, they were content at his desire to subscribe it, but with this expresse de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, which they required and obtained to be acted in the Counsell Bookes (so farre were they from any Equivocation) that they did subscribe that Covenant in that same sense and no other, wherein it was understood at the first framing in the 1580.</p>
   <p>What that sense was, we had for a time too much dispute, but at last the Registers of our Church in the generall Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, being carefully cast over, it was found that the doctrine and discipline of our Church in that 80. yeare, did runne so crosse to Episcopacie, to <hi>Perth</hi> articles, to the Leiturgie, and all the rest of our troublesome novelties, that whosoever did heartily subscribe the Covenant of our Church in that sense, it behoved to have in the yeare of his first framing, did stand no lesse oblidged thereby to renounce the posteriour novati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then those who had subscribed the other Covenant with the addition, wherein all these novations were expressely named: It was found even in our last Assembly, whereto <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaire</hi> according to his commission from the King did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, that both these Covenants, that with the application, and
<pb n="24" facs="89"/> that without the application were but both one. So that your equivocation, whereupon your brethren also have too much tinkled, is cleared without the disgrace of any, but the like of you, who were the authours of all the mistake that for a time was in this matter.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">15. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell.</note>The fifteenth paralell of your <hi>piae fraudes</hi> is but like the rest, the ground of this great commotion could not be the malcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of any man, for losse of what they possessed in the tyths, or any thing else of the Church patrimonie, or for want of such favour they desired to have with their Prince: All these are but sillie fables: These whose hand hath beene prime in this high affaire from the beginning, hath had very little, or no entresse at all in any part of the Church patrimonie, ye may know that the most of the tithes were in the hands of the not covenanting Lords, and that the small portion which remained with Covenanters, was made so sure to them as the King and his Lawes were able to make it.</p>
   <p>Also it is very well knowne that the chiefe in the Covenant had so much favour of their Prince, as their heart could wish, which they constantly did brook, till their zeale unto this cause did crack their credit: Yee are exceedingly injurious to say, that we did ever slander our King with any idolatrie, with any poperie; Our thoughts of that gracious Prince<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> are farre more considerate, and our words of so sacred person more full of due regard: But indeed though we both say, preach, and print that so long as the like of you gett leave to possesse his eare, we can have little hope that any true Protestant, so farre as ye are able, shall ever gett living in quiet in this Ile, and though we avow that by the Service-booke and other novati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons yee intended, to make us all trot backe againe unto <hi>Rome,</hi> believe us, that in those Speeches we wrong not our minde, that we speake no other then we thinke, and we hope now have given tolerable evidence for these our thoughts and Speeches, though ye and the Pope both should laugh in the <hi>Sardonian</hi> fashion, when ye are like to lose your game.</p>
   <pb n="25" facs="89"/>
   <p>In your last paralell<note place="margin">The last paralell. The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of a perfect Iesuite.</note> your motion that it may appeare to be naturall, is swifter then at the beginning, ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ere overcome your very selfe, &amp; any <hi>Iesuite</hi> J have ever read in vilenesse of lies, slanders, filthie Speeches, railings, sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ffings, and blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous abuse of the holy Scripture to all this stuffe.</p>
   <p>Ye prove a good Scholler to your Masters <hi>Petroneus Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Lucian, Rabelais,</hi> none that come in your way whether men or w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>men, whether living or dead, Nobles, Pastors, Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, People may escape the fire and filth of your envenomed tongue: All your opposites, if the King can be perswaded to follow your advice, must quickly be packing out of these do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, as the vilest straitours, but to our nobles and leaders ye will not shew such favour; they, as ye, tel us, with <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>villiack</hi> &amp; <hi>Coppinger</hi> must be hanged, drawen, quartered, and buried with the buriall of an asse. That Jesuite <hi>Abernethy</hi> should have become Protestant, ye can not abide with patience, for so is the doctrine of your Society, that separation from <hi>Rome</hi> is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse.</p>
   <p>That noble gentle-man <hi>Generall Leslie</hi>
      <note place="margin">Generall Leslies vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> cannot escape the scrapes of your empoysoned pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; Ye are on a stage playing the part of a <hi>Fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ioso,</hi> who ever commeth in your way, the first dirt and stones ye can grip must flie at their faces. When ye have searched that great personage from his birth, to his old age, nothing can yee espy in all his life whereupon to fasten your tuske, but that which among all Nations, as well barbarous as civill, hath ever beene reputed a marke of honour and matter of gloriation: When ye have curiously eyed that excellent piece, from top to toe, your malice can espy no blemish, but a skar of an old most honourable wound, which maketh him the more glorious, with all who understand the tearmes of true honour, and the dearer to every one who hath any spark of affection toward that service wherin that wound among many more was received by him: But ye &amp; your like cannot hold in the passion of your soule, but must vent your hatred &amp; malice, your disdainfull indignation against all the valarous acts of any in the reformed religion, against the popish partie, whether in these dayes, or the dayes of our forfathers. Ye cannot dissemble
<pb n="26" facs="90"/> your passionate affection to the side of <hi>Q. Marie</hi> at our first reformation; rather ere your loyal heart had played the pranks of the rebellion, the treason, and what not of our ancestours, ye would have joyned with the enemies of our Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> &amp; State, for the cutting off of the blessed root of <hi>King Charles</hi> race, for the setling upon the throne of <hi>Britaine</hi> after the dispatch of <hi>Q. Elizabeth</hi> &amp; <hi>K. Iames,</hi> these hereticall Schismaticks, the poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of <hi>Iohn of Austria,</hi> of the Duke of <hi>Northfolke,</hi> or of any whom it should have pleased the Pope, the Catholick King, &amp; the Duke of <hi>Guise</hi> to have matched with <hi>Q Marie:</hi> Thus d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e ye and your faction stand affected toward the former age, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is your minde any better toward this present: The D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tch Princes &amp; the head of their league that true <hi>Hero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat wonder of the world, the <hi>K. of Swaine,</hi> must all be to you but villanes &amp; traitours, who for their zeale to the reformed Religion &amp; Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of <hi>Germanie,</hi> durst be so peart as to lift up armes to stop that very far advanced reformation of <hi>Ferdinand:</hi> The wounds that famous <hi>Lesl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e</hi> did get in this cause, must be slandered and made a matter of reproach to you &amp; your like; but it is good that men of honour doe think of you &amp; your language as it is. Who is acquainted with the world abroad, they know full well that <hi>Leslies</hi> most valarous, very wise, &amp; happie deportments in the wars over Sea, have brought more true glorie to our Natiō then the cariage of any man, who went out of our Land these manie ages; Certainly, this brave Souldiers late conduct of our Nation in the time of the greatest danger that our land did see this hundreth yeares, was so full of wisedome, stoutnesse, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, successe, that his memory will be fragrant &amp; blessed in all generations to our posteritie. This sight of that mans ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, did draw to him so much love from all that followed his Campe, &amp; so much honour from all the English Nobilitie, that served in the opposite armie, that we may say truely, There li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not in this Yle a gentle-man of comparable reputation with all sorts of men, except alone of you in the faction, by whose hearts to be hated, by whose pens to be defamed, it is an increase of contentment &amp; praile of all honest men.</p>
   <p>But being unable to stand any longer upon your dung hill,
<pb n="27" facs="90"/> least I be suffocat with the stink therof, I must turn my back, &amp; flie, leaving you to dwell upon these your excrements; &amp; if so be ye cannot be drawn from them, to die &amp; be buried; therin only my parting a little of one purpose which so oft in your whole writ ye inculcate.</p>
   <p>Ye will have us in the doctrine of Episcopacie<note place="margin">we agree in our Tenets of Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacie with all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed abroad.</note> to differ from all other reformed Churches, yet it will appeare to those who goe not beyond the very passages, your selfe doth bring in this matter, that betwixt us &amp; any reformed Church there is no discrepance at all. For that Episcopacie which ye maintaine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side the manifold unhappy accidents that use to hang both upō the persons and office which your selfe will scarce defend, hath into it essentially, the power of ordination &amp; all Ecclesiastick j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>risdiction annexed, &amp; that by a divine right to the person of one man in a whole diocesse: that ever any reformed divine, except some few, &amp; that but lately in England, did approve let be commend such an office, it is so false as any thing can be: That kind of episcopacie, wherof the divines ye alleadge speak off, is so farre from the present English and late Scotish one, as light is from darknesse, as reformed doctrine from grosse Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, contrarie both to the word of God, &amp; all sound antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Beside, even that kinde of Episcopacie which they seem not much to oppose, is such an office as they make to be no way ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary in any Church but removeable out of all, to which they thought never meet to give any footing in their own churches, but at the beginning did cast it out, and to this day have care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie holden it at the doore; This, ye cannot be ignorant, is the known practice let be the doctrin of al the reformed churches over Sea, &amp; of all their divines without the exception of one man. Doe ye think that any of them will be offended with us for following their owne example for casting out that which they have rej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cted before us upon lesse occasions; For it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that Episcopacie is no way so opposite to the discipline of any reformed church, as to that discipline which many Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies &amp; Parliaments have setled in our land; it is certain that no church over Sea, hath ever been halfe so much grieved with that unhappie office, as ours oft times hath beene; we all know
<pb n="28" facs="91"/> that from it alone hath flowed all the miseries schisms dangers wherwith our church since the reformation hath been vexed, none of us is ignorant that this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ffice was the only horse wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon our later novations of <hi>Perth</hi> articles, high Cōmission, Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, Canons came riding unto us; And now the world may see that it is only Bishops that threaten this whole Yle with the danger of the most cruell warre it saw these 500 yeares. That any reasonable man will blame us for our firm resolution to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose their re-entrie among us for ever, we doe not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ear, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side that our whole land is al utterly impatient of their but thē, our last two generall Assemblies, &amp; articles of our late P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with our Princes approbatiō, have ordained their office to be abjured by our whole nation with solemne oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h &amp; subscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō. As for our neighbour churches in <hi>Eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ād</hi> &amp; <hi>Ire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ād,</hi> though hitherto we have been m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st sparing to meddle with any thing which concerneth them, yet now since ye put us so hardly to it we can̄ot dissemble any lōger our hearty wishes, that since the <hi>bishops</hi> there, beside the manifold evils, that is in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ffice, which they doe use &amp; defend, &amp; the needlesnes of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; since I say, their bishops have been the first fountain of all our churches trouble, since they are the prime instrumēts, which now infect this Yle with <hi>Arminianisme</hi> &amp; <hi>popery;</hi> since they have raised, &amp; yet doe further, so hot a persecutiō against our whole nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ō in <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>land,</hi> as no reformed church to this day hath ever beē acquainted with; since after our full agreemēt with our gratious king, &amp; neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>natiō of Eng ād</hi> they without any cause, that yet we know or can hear tel of, have been the bellows to kindle the wrath of our king against us, to stir up a most blodie war for the undoing (if God prevent it not) first of the most flourishing churches in these dominiōs, &amp; thē of the whole reformed el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>where; we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse it our wish to God, that the king &amp; his present parliamēt might seriously cōsider, if it were not for the good of the <hi>crown</hi> for the welfare of their natiō, for the peace of their church, that <hi>Englād</hi> after the exāple of all the reformed should rid thēselvs at least of their bishops trouble, as they did of old, without any repentance to this day, of their Abbots &amp; Monks: This we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive would much increase the joy and prosperitie of all the three Dominions.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="91"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>