<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100391_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00564</idno>
           <idno type="STC">107</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100391</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blacke devill or the apostate : Together with the wolfe worrying the lambes. And the spirituall navigator, bound for the Holy Land. In three sermons. By Thomas Adams</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 78, 2, 4, 34, 2, 4, 58, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader,</hi> this Booke stands at the mercy of thy capacity for thy censure. Perhaps thou wilt iudge it done for oppositions sake; the <hi>Blacke Deuill</hi> to the <hi>White:</hi> perhaps for imitation; perhaps for affectation. Thou mayst for me causes enough in thy imagination to produce it, yet misse the right. It was to shew thy selfe, and all other perusers, the <hi>blacknesse</hi> of Sinne; and among the rest, of <hi>Apostacie.</hi> Would you not behold Impiety in the true colours: you may for beare. If you would, look here, and detest it. If you will take out a good lesson, and hate to doe it; neither you nor I shall haue cause to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent our labours. Once we must giue account, what we haue heard, and seene, and done; when the pleasures of Sinne, like old surfets, shall giue a bitter reluctancie in the stomacke of the conscience; and wee are going to Gods colde earth. Learne wee now to preuent the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that, which we shall one day be sorry to haue done.
<pb facs="4"/>
There is no man liuing, but shall repent of his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, either on earth, or in hell. Reade and be instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. If you finde iust fau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ts heere, I submit my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to your censure. <hi>In omnibus meis scriptis, non modo pium Lectorem, sed liberum correctorem</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug in Prooem. Lib. 3. de Trin.</note>
      <hi>desidero.</hi> But to those Censurers, <hi>Qui vel non intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendo reprehendunt, vel reprehendendo non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligunt,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Idem co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>tra Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>stum, Lib. 22. Cap. 34.</note> I wish either a more sound vnderstanding, or more sober affection.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Criminor, amplector; tibi sunt communia, lector.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But as he <hi>that commendeth himselfe, is not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, but whom the Lord commendeth.</hi> So if <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10, 18</note> the Lord approue, <hi>I passe not for mans iudgement.</hi> If you snib me for writing so frequently, and not confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my selfe to the Pulpit; I answere, (besides that I will not neglect this to do that)
<q>
         <l>Quo liceat libris, non licet ire mihi.</l>
      </q>
My Bookes may be admitted, where I cannot come. If you say, there are bookes too many: I answere; restrain them to this quality, and <hi>Abundans cautela non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet.</hi> Farewell, be satisfied, be blessed.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Wingraue, <date>Iuly 7.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>THO. ADAMS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>