<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>B., M.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100900_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04062</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1412</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100900</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>B., M.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An hipponomie or the vineyard of horsemanship : deuided into three bookes. 1. The theorick part, intreating of the inward knowledge of the man.2. The first practicke part, shewing how to worke according to that knowledge. 3. The second practicke part, declaring how to apply both hunting and running horses to the true grounds of this art. In which is plainly laid open the art of breeding, riding, training and dieting of the said horses. Wherein also many errors in this art, heretofore published, are manifestly detected. By Michaell Baret</title>
                 <author>Baret, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 48, 51-122, 20, 139, 13, 101, 1, 23, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere it not (most courteous Reader) that the great desire I haue to doe somthing, that might either profit my Countrey or the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale; did vrge mee forward to the publishing and setting forth this Treatise (intituled the <hi>Vineyard of Horsemanship)</hi> both the insuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of my selfe through the imbecillity of knowledge and also the intricacie &amp; obsourenesse of the Art, (being so much darkened through the abuse thereof) might haue disswaded me from so bold an enterprise, but more especially knowing that it cannot bee without scandalous taunts: For so much as it shall come to a publike view of <hi>Momus</hi> and his Associates.</p>
   <p>For neither is my wit so finely filed, as to proue my assertions by strong reasons and inuincible Arguments; nor yet my learning so largely lettered, as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ecke and garnish it with Rhethoricall am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifications and flowing speeches; But onely to set it forth in such plaine and simple manner a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> shall be fit for the instruction of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, hoping that the meekest will take it in the best sence, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my goodwill; for it (being wrought <hi>in plano)</hi> hath no curiosity to delight the eares of the curious; but yet it is supported with a strong Piller which is the truth: Trusting you wil not esteeme it to be any deale defaced in being set forth without any painted at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and by one of so weake performance; for gold is nothing the
<pb facs="9"/> worse if it be found on the dunghill, nor poyson any deale the better being drunke forth of a guilded cup. But rather as <hi>Seneca</hi> saith,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note>
      <hi>Non quis sed quid dicit attendite,</hi> rather respect what is deliuered then who or in what manner it is deliuered: For in regard that I haue neither the Art of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lighting, nor perswading; yet if I haue any part of teaching, it shall not grieue me to bestow my small talent into the Treasury of the World, hauing proued it onely by practise to be perfect; Knowing, that a little water, being cast into the Sea is preserued, but being kept by it selfe is soone dryed vp. Euen so, this little Treatise being committed to the World, will bee preserued (by some) but being kept close, it will soone d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cay. But it is<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection.</note> obiected by some, that this part of Horsemanship is so easie that there need little instruction for the teaching thereof, and also it is holden by other some, (and some of them reputed good Horsemen)<note place="margin">Theo. 3. <seg rend="sup">d</seg>.</note> that to bring a Horse to his pace is not onely idle, but also to spoyle his<note place="margin" type="runSum">Answer.</note> other pace. To whom I answer, for the first, if they rightly consider the stayd seating of the Horses body, and also the true placing of his<note place="margin">Idem. 1.</note> head, with the easie cariage of his reine, and the proper motion of his going forward, with the easinesse of his going; and moreouer, the iust and true handling of his legges: they shall finde that the Art hath such obscurity and intricatenesse, that it would require a whole Ʋo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, for the explayning thereof, rather then a small Treatise.</p>
   <p>And as for the second, which hold it to be idle. Is that an idle thing that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s necessary for all sorts of people? for if a man haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to trauaile but two or three miles from the towne, will not hee be desirous to be carted both freely, easily and safely, which cannot be so truely done by any Horse, as vpon a pacer: much more then (ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f hee be to trauaile two hundred or three hundred miles. Therefore I could wish, that they should ride vpon Trotting Asses all their liues (for penance,) to kee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>em from idlenesse, till they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r themselues to search mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e diligent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y into the trueth of this Art: to teach them to giue sentence in that thing they haue such small ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in. But it is the nature of a great number, to enuy that in others, which they cannot attaine vnto themselues. Thinking that to be idle, which their idle braines cannot comprehend: and so iudge them to be phantasticall (as is the manner of ignorant men) which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing beyond their reach and the compasse of their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: thinking the world to be no greater then the Cages of their
<pb facs="9"/> braines can comprehend. Therefore although they be reputed for good Horsemen, yet to them I answere, with the <hi>Ciuillian, Fama per</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ciuillian.</note>
      <hi>se, paruura momenti habet ad probandum,</hi> onely fame is a very small moment of proofe. And whereas they say there are many Horses spo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>led by this Art, I grant it to be true. But it is not the Art that doth spoyle them, but the abuse thereof. For though meat<note place="margin">Theo. 3. <seg rend="sup">d</seg>.</note> and drinke, be both necessary and good, yet they may say (by the same conclusion) because they haue seene many surfet by it, that (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) it is nought: whereas (indeed) it is not the vse of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures but the abuse, for as it is the nature of most men to thinke that which they most affect to be the best; so many men in their particular knowledge, thinke themselues the wisest, in that they doe best conceipt. And so if at any time, they (by chance) haue made two or three Horses to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ace, (though neuer so vnseemely) then straight they hold themselues as excellent as the best, thinking there is no more to be knowne. Whereas to make a Horse pace onely, without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther respect, it is the least part of the Art; for it is not the pace onely that is to be respected, but also his comely cariage (in euery parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular) to be regarded. And therefore no maruaile, though there be so many Horses spoyled, being taught vpon vntrue ground.</p>
   <p>For (as the learned saith) <hi>Quod nemo didicit, nemo docere potest,</hi> it is hard for a man to teach that to another, which he neuer learned himselfe.</p>
   <p>Now seeing the truth of this Art is so darkened with ignorance, and drowned in the whirle-poole of conceipt; I haue thought it my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as much as in me lyeth, to illustrate some darke corners thereof: for (as <hi>Cicero</hi> saith) <hi>Non nobis solum nati sumus, sed partim patriae,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cicero.</note>
      <hi>partim parentibus, partim amicis, debemus,</hi> that we are not borne, onely for our selues, but partly for our country, partly for parents, and partly for our friends, but the least part to our selues.</p>
   <p>But me thinkes I heare some Zoylists obiect and condemne me of<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection.</note> arrogancy, for attempting to set forth this Booke to the eyes of the world, my selfe being of no greater credit, for the authority thereof: and also for my education, neuer to haue beene brought vp amongst Horse-men: and further, my country wherein I haue liued the most part of my life (which is <hi>Holland</hi> in <hi>Lincolneshire</hi>) to be of no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeme for Horsemanship: Moreouer, that I iustifie my worke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> too much for truth, whereas others (of better iudgement then my selfe)
<pb facs="10"/> haue left their workes, to be examined at the discretion of others, all which I will answere as well and as briefely as I can.</p>
   <p>And for the first, I grant my selfe to be very meane of credit, to giue authority to my workes, but is it not meere vanity, to giue grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter respect to a man or to his place, then to his knowledge? For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> a man get a place of credit, either by following some Noble Man, or else by some other meanes, then are both his words and workes holden most Authenticall, although he (for the true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of himselfe) doth deserue, neither the one nor the other. And therefore <hi>Socrates</hi> being asked whether <hi>Archclaus,</hi> (who was estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a very hardy and valiant man) by his iudgement, were to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted happy or no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l cannot tell (quoth he) I neuer had any confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with him: Inferring, that happinesse doth not consist in the esteeme of the worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, but in knowledge.</p>
   <p>And herein doth man greatly erre: For there is not any thing<note place="margin">Act 10. 34.</note> which regardeth greatnesse but man onely. Not GOD: for he is no accepter of persons; and he maketh the simple things of the world<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. 21.</note> to confou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d the wise: And also the wisdome of the world, is meere Foolishnesse with GOD. Not nature: for we see the poore mans<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 19,</note> child to be borne, as fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d well fauoured, as wise, and as rich (in respect of it selfe) as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eire of the Noble. And likewise, hath not Nature giuen to the Ant, such prouidence, that Man is wished to<note place="margin">Pro. 6. 6.</note> learne at her; and to the Bee, Art to gather (as <hi>Galen</hi> saith) from some flowers M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ate, from others Waxe, and from other some Honey: and likewise, to make her Nest (in her Combe) so Artificially, that the cunning<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st work-man cannot performe the like. And further, to the Spider, to spinne her thred so s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>all, (through the quicknesse of her touch) and make her webbe so proportionable, that it would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the beholders, if custome did not make it more frequent. All which are sim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le creatures to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>udgement of Man, and yet they haue their gifts aboue Man: then why may not both GOD, and Nature, giue knowledge to some Man (though held simple) in one Art, (if he endeuour himselfe thereto) as well as vnto others that are of greater authority?</p>
   <p>For (as the wiseman saith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>) <hi>qui addit scientiam, addit et laborem,</hi> he which will be cunning be must be painful. Wherfore (as M. Doctor <hi>Hall</hi> saith) I had rather applaud my selfe for hauing much that I<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> his Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> show not, then others shoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> appla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d me for showing more then I haue.</p>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <p>And for the second, true it is I was neuer trained vp vnder any <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> particular Horseman: but yet my desire was continually, to conuerse with the best and yet I could neuer reape such content as I did desire. Wherefore, I louing Horsemanship from my infancy, was desirous to ioyne delight with my loue, and also knowledge with my delight, I wholy gaue my selfe to heare the opinion, of any that were reputed Horsemen: and so practised vpon their opinions; but yet I could not finde such reliefe in my greatest necessity, as I did desire, which made me relye vpon experience, the mother of knowledge (though some terme it the mother of fooles) and so I did o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>serue, that what things proued hurtfull by succession, I recalled, although they seemed profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table at the beginning. By the which I found the word of <hi>Cicero</hi> true: who saith, that he found more by experience then by reading. But if I had yeelded my selfe to a teacher, no doubt, I should haue trodden, the steppes of my maister, howsoeuer: for there is nothing more consonant to the nature of man then Imitation.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, for my Country, I see no reason why it should be so stained <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> with ignorance: in regard truth is not tyed to any particular place, or any place exempted from the truth. Indeed I must confesse, that, that place (onely) is not of any great note; but yet in other parts of that country there are as good Horsemen as in most places else wheresoeuer. Therefore of particular instances, there can be no good conclusions.</p>
   <p>But yet, if this worke had proceeded forth of Yorkeshire, or any other place of fame, then it should haue beene held very probable, although the worke were frought with many errors. And what can argue greater ignorance, then for one to giue greater credit to the authority of the place, then to the trueth: except it were onely nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se places, and others branded with vtter ignorance, or else they thinke that men are confined within the limits of their owne Country: and banished from all the rest; and yet if they should tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile they (being more wedded to affection, then reason) will alledge the old saying; <hi>Coelum, non animum mutat, qui trans mare cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> he may change the Horison but not his minde, which p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sseth the seas. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> true, there are many might come vnto knowledge, if they thought they had it not before. For if a man tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>atle neuer so farre if he be wed to his owne conceipt, he shall not make any profit (for all his trauaile) to helpe his knowledge, for (as the wise-man sayth)
<pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>Consuetudinem vincere, dura pugna est:</hi> It is a great Conquest to ouercome a mans will. And yet if he will not bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yed to his owne Conceit but to Reason, he shall not onely change the Clime, but also his mind.</p>
   <p>And for the last, I hold Mr. <hi>Morgans</hi> opinion. Let no man thinke he hath certaine and vndoubted knowledge, which thinketh a th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng to be otherwise then he knoweth it to be, which when he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the report of the Ancients and Elders, is then presently danted, thinking it not possible to know more then they know, or for them not to erre. And so suffer themselues like sheepe to be led to the slaughter of ignorance without searching the truth. Wherefore seeing truth comprehendeth nothing but sure and perfect knowledge, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tten by experience, and experience by practise, and practise by time; and also I find by practise in time, that this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod will bring any horse (of what age soeuer) to true and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable pace: I see no reason wherefore I may not defend this as truth, although other Horsemen, of farre better esteeme then my selfe, haue set downe their opinions to be left or taken, at the wils and opinions of others.</p>
   <p>Wherefore if I shall any way distast the iudiciall and willing Practitioners in this Art; I humbly craue their fauourable cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures for my conceipted assert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>on, (as they may terme it) Hoping that when they haue rightly considered the grosse abuse of this Art, and the seuerall conceipts and opinions of euery man, for <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ot homines, tot sensus,</hi> so many men so many mindes: I trust they will in some sort excuse me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or standing vnto my owne, hauing truely proued it; for as <hi>Varro</hi> saith, <hi>Nusquam deueniet, qui quot videret calles sequitur:</hi> Hee shall neuer come to his iourne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es end, which followeth euery by-path: So hee shall neuer ariue at the Hauen of Knowledge, that is tossed with the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestuous waues of euery mans braine.</p>
   <p>Now because this is such an excellent Art, in regard it is vsed about so famous a Subiect (for <hi>Ea scientia nobilior est, quae circa nobilius subiectum versatur:)</hi> I being sory to see it in such ruine, through the abuse of many (who are rather destroyers then buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) haue thought good to repaire one decayed place, not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to build all for want of ability, (not of good will.) I haue wrought one sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> by the line of leuel, and squared it, <hi>per normam
<pb facs="11"/> rationis,</hi> and although it be not curiously carued, yet being wrought in perpendicular w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se, it will agree with the next parallel, and so make a firme foundation: desiring the ingenious, to allow it a place in the building. And also, seeing the streame is so shallow through the drinesse of the Spring from whence it doth flow, that the Swanne cannot swim, yet the little Tittemouse may wash her selfe therein: Trusting that where the water shal chance to stop its current through the shallownesse of the riuer, some painfull labourer will concaue the superficies, and so make it r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ceptable for the greater sort of birds.</p>
   <p>Now therefore in regard I haue done the best that I can, in dinul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging this Treatise to the world, diuiding it into three Bookes, the first treating onely of the <hi>Theoricke</hi> knowledge of the man, how to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his will to reason, and the other two shewing how to bring a Horse to the obedience of his will by breeding and riding both of the Trotter and Pacer, and also to traine hunting and runing Horses to their best perfection, though it be not so well as I would, yet it is as well as I could: (For euery man cannot bring gold to the temple.) And though it be not so excellent, as the curious doe desire, nor as the Art doth deserue: Yet I hope the milder will take it in good part, and censure it according to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> goodwill. But as for those, who carry such Tyrannicall minds, that will neither doe well themselues, nor admit a tolleration for them that doe their best: I leaue one of them in the Lake o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Enuy, which doth ouerflow them, like an Aegip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Nyle: and the other to labour with <hi>Sisiphus,</hi> and to feed with the <hi>Camelian,</hi> on the substance of their owne desire: and onely take my leaue of the true louers, and painefull practitioners in this Art. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>M. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>