<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100900_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04062</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1412</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100900</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An hipponomie or the vineyard of horsemanship : deuided into three bookes. 1. The theorick part, intreating of the inward knowledge of the man.2. The first practicke part, shewing how to worke according to that knowledge. 3. The second practicke part, declaring how to apply both hunting and running horses to the true grounds of this art. In which is plainly laid open the art of breeding, riding, training and dieting of the said horses. Wherein also many errors in this art, heretofore published, are manifestly detected. By Michaell Baret</title>
                 <author>Baret, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 48, 51-122, 20, 139, 13, 101, 1, 23, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="159"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus, (gentle Reader) I haue aduentured through the hard and craggy Rockes of ineuitable ignorance, to make the path more spacious and so more passable, for those which are desirous to trauell in that tract which leadeth to the chiefest place of this Plantation. In which peregrination, because there hath so many wandred out of the way, through the num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber<note place="margin">Imitation as a mist darkeneth our vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> of so many crosse by-wayes that are trodden by the steps of those which haue trauayled in the thick mists and desert places of the ancients; I haue taken paines to set downe notes in the margeant (at euery doubtfull turne) which will serue as guides to direct them when they are in distresse, and obliuion should obscure this path. The which trauaile, being (now) finished, I had thought to haue commanded my pen to a full period.</p>
   <p>But being further incited by some gentlemen, my very good friends, to persist further in this so famous Art, to set forth my opinion and experience of the other excellent part<note place="margin">The cause of this last booke.</note> thereof, to wit, the training vp of hunting, and running horses, perswading mee what light and benefit would come thereby (to the good of my Country and Nation) in in showing how these Impes also might flourish in this <hi>Vineyard,</hi> and how they might suppresse and keepe downe
<pb facs="159"/> those weeds which may gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w therein, whereby they might bring forth fruit also most pleasant and profitable.</p>
   <p>I haue (for their sakes) aduentured the Pike of my Pen to<note place="margin">Old hard forn▪</note> march among the boysterous and roaring Cannons, of emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue and slanderous tongues, to satisfie their desire, and to shew by Application, how and what Appendix these haue to the former Principles, and wherein likewise they who haue spent their whole time in this part (and are esteemed<note place="margin">The Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> of many as a <hi>Phoenix)</hi> haue slided out of the way, and yet not perceiued, because they haue (likewise) had the nature of the horse to vaile their crooked paths: But because my<note place="margin">Strar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> altho</note> assertions are (many of them) opposite to the practise of this our time, I looke that there will be <hi>Iudasses</hi> to betray them, (by detraction) hauing a Pharisaicall conceipt of their owne traditions, and so cannot indure any counterbuffe.</p>
   <p>And therefore I am nothing danted to prostitute the truth, for any <hi>Zoylist,</hi> because my intention is not (in the publishing of this) to reuiue and quicken the numnesse of their preiudicated conceipt, but onely to plant such Impes as whose rootes are not eaten with the canker of obstina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, whereby they shall not be maimed, but complete; for no man can bee approued a perfect Horse-man, who hath not knowledge in euery part thereof</p>
   <p>And therefore, gentle Reader, if this my great paines taken, and the whole course of my time spent, in an honest care for erecting the truth, shall be but thankfully receiued: it will encourage mee to prune and dresse the whole Vine, from the highest to the lowest part thereof: For although I haue set forth the platforme and grownd of this whole plantation, yet I haue left the chiefe Stemme thereof vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pruned,<note place="margin">That is how to ride horses for seruice to their perfection.</note> (although it be planted) for diuers causes (to my selfe best knowne;) which heereafter (if God permit) I meane
<pb facs="160"/> also to graft in my second addition, as this shall be accepted, and as time and leysure will consent, besides the prouiding for my necessary affaires: And so farewell. But as for the other whose ambitious conceipt hath carried them so high, that they seeke to beat downe other mens honest and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full indeauours, I leaue them onely with these Verses of <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. BASSE.</hi>
   </p>
   <lg>
      <l>REade Sir, if you will, but if you will not, chuse,</l>
      <l>This Booke (Sir) will be read if you refuse,</l>
      <l>But if you read I pray commend my wit,</l>
      <l>It is (in truth) the first that e're I writ:</l>
      <l>Who reades and not commends, it is a rule,</l>
      <l>Hee's either very wise or very foole:</l>
      <l>But whosoere commends and doth not read,</l>
      <l>What ere the other is, hee's foole indeed.</l>
      <l>And who doth neither read nor yet commend,</l>
      <l>God speed him well, his labour's at an end:</l>
      <l>But reade, or not, or how, I passe not for it,</l>
      <l>I rest your honest carelesse friend M. <hi>Baret.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>