<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100171_Fr4_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19065</idno>
           <idno type="STC">548</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100171</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christian offices crystall glasse : In three bookes. First written in Latine, by that famous and renowned Father, Saint Ambrose Bishop of Millane. Whereunto is added his conuiction of Symmachus the Gentile. A worke tending to the advancement of vertue, and of holinesse: and to shew how much the morality of the Gentiles, is exceeded by the doctrine of Christianity. Translated into English by Richard Humfrey</title>
                 <author>Ambrose, Saint, Bishop of Milan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Greene, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dawson, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>66, 126, 2, 127-142, 10, 75, 9, 64, 38, 20, 41, 1 page, folded table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="210"/>
   <head>The Argument.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here were three Emperours called by the name of <hi>Valentinian,</hi> the first was styled the elder succeeded in the Empire, <hi>Iovian</hi> who succeeded <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apostate, an<note n="a" place="margin">He was staine toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Heraclius</hi> by certaine souldiers of <hi>Aetius</hi> through the treason of <hi>Maximus, Evagr. l.</hi> 2. <hi>C.</hi> 7.</note> other was created by <hi>Theod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius junior,</hi> who was son to <hi>Placidia</hi> his Aunt, daughter to <hi>Theodosius Magnus;</hi> another sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the younger was sonne to the elder, raigning<note n="b" place="margin">Hee was stifled to death by the conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of <hi>Eugenius</hi> and <hi>Arbogastus Socra. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 25. which plainly evidenceth that they were divers one from the other, were there none other proofes.</note> immediatly after him, and comming up to the Empire in the middle, as it were, betweene them both. Hee was the sonne of <hi>Iustina</hi> a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond wife, whom hee married, <hi>Severa</hi> his first wife being living: This was shee, that being an <hi>Arian</hi> wrought the exilement of St. <hi>Ambrose,</hi> but was withstood, and intercepted in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, through the singular affection of the people toward him. This <hi>Valentinian</hi> her sonne, chosen by the souldiers, after the death of his father it is, to whom St. <hi>Ambrose</hi> here wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, being young in yeares: yet now, as it should seeme, out of his minority, during which time, the prudent Governour <hi>Probus</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sull ruled <hi>Italie.</hi> Here was the Empire first di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, after the time of the three sonnes of <hi>Constantine</hi> the great, into three severall Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; <hi>Gratian</hi> his elder brother had the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion
<pb facs="211"/> over the East, he over the West, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dosius</hi> over <hi>Egypt,</hi> with the other parts of the South. To him therefore <hi>Symmachus</hi> being Consul and head Senator of the city of <hi>Rome</hi> sent this Epistle, labouring vehemently therein, (and he being of small iudgement might easily be seduced,) to obtaine his grant, to receive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againe into <hi>Rome</hi> the old Ceremonies, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations of the Gentiles: which from the time of <hi>Constantine</hi> the great, save only in the dayes of <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apostate, who raigned not three yeares, they had forsaken, and embraced the Christian religion. Our renowned author Bishop of <hi>Millan</hi> the chiefe City of <hi>Insubria</hi> now Lumbardie, lying in that part of <hi>Italy</hi> called <hi>Gallia Cisalpina;</hi> a man of great fame in those dayes in the Church of God for his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, learning, wisdome, and courage: no sooner heard of this seditious Epistle, but straight way being moved in zeale for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian cause wrought the former of these two Epistles to the young Emperour, desiring him to send him the relation of <hi>Symmachus,</hi> wherein in the meane time hee meeteth stoutly, and sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the subject, and when it was sent him fully and effectually replieth to it, worthily convinceth it in the second Epistle. Which also tooke so good effect, that the relator prevailed not, though a man of rarest eloquence, and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est estimation. Notwithstanding, such confidence had hee in his oratorie joyned with his reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (so presumptuous spirits, and hot-spurres
<pb facs="211"/> are Sathans proctors) that to bring his precious enterprise to passe, hoping <hi>Maximus</hi> the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine should have obtained the Empire, hee gave another attempt. For compiling a booke in his praise, and pronouncing it before him with his best elocution, hee sought to draw him strongly to him, which was easily done, hee being a barbarous tyrant: specially when he saw this to serve as a baite to bring <hi>Rome</hi> to him. But herein againe he was deceived, and had not something happened better then he deserved, hee had beene catched, and strangled in his owne snare. For <hi>Theodosius</hi> shortly after slew <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> and then was he charged with treason for that libell of his, and had sufferd death, as his due guerdon, had not <hi>Leontius</hi> the B. of the <hi>Novatian</hi> Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> hee flying thither for sanctuarie, intreated <hi>Theodosius</hi> for him: who because he bare love to the priesthood, and was a Prince full of clemency easily pardoned him. And whether afterward he became a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian convert the story shewes not, but<note n="c" place="margin">Socrat. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
      </note> there it appeareth that hee wrote an Apologie to <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dosius.</hi>
   </p>
   <q>
      <lg>
         <l>
            <note n="d" place="margin">Plutarch de garruli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note>
            <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>The<note n="e" place="margin">Prov. 16.9.</note> heart of man purposeth his way, but the Lord doth direct his steps.</l>
         <l>Many<note n="f" place="margin">Prov. 19.11.</note> devises are in a mans heart, but the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of the Lord shall stand.</l>
      </lg>
   </q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>