<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE History of Life and Death. The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100506_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01454</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1158</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100506</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE History of Life and Death. The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>History naturall and experimentall, of life and death. Or of the prolongation of life : Written in Latine by the Right Honorable Francis Lo. Verulam, Vis-count St. Alban</title>
                 <author>Bacon, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <distributor>Lee, William 2</distributor>
                            <distributor>Moseley, Humphrey</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 395, that is 435, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>THE History of Life and Death. <hi>The Preface.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>IT</hi> is an ancient Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Complaint; That <hi>Life</hi> is <hi>Short,</hi> and <hi>Art Long.</hi> Wherefore, it behoveth us, who make it our chiefest Aime, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Arts;</hi> to take upon us, the Consideration, of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing Mans Life; God</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
the Author, of all <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> prospering our Endevours. For though the <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, but a Masse, and Accumulation, of Sins, and Sorrowes; And they that looke for an Eternall Life, set but light by a Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; Yet the Continuation of workes of Charity, ought not to be contemned, even by us <hi>Christians.</hi> Besides, the <hi>Beloved Disciple</hi> of our <hi>Lord,</hi> survived the other Disciples; And many of the Fathers of the Church, especially of the Holy Monkes, and Hermits, were
<pb facs="10"/>
long liv'd; which shewes, that this Blessing of <hi>Long life,</hi> so often promised in the old Law, had lesse A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement after our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours</hi> Dayes, than other Earthly Blessings had. But to esteeme of this, as the chiefest Good, we are but too prone. Onely the Inquirie is difficult, how to attaine the same; And so much the rather, because it is corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with false opinions, and vaine Reports. For both, those Things, which the <hi>Vulgar Physitians</hi> talke, of <hi>Radic all Moisture,</hi> and <hi>Naturall Heat,</hi> are but
<pb facs="11"/>
meere Fictions; And the Immoderate praises <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Chymicall Medicines,</hi> first puffe up with vain hopes, and then faile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Admirers.</p>
   <p>And as for that <hi>Death,</hi> which is caused by Suffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Putrefaction, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Diseases, wee speake not now; For that pertains to an <hi>History</hi> of <hi>Physick;</hi> But onely of that <hi>Death</hi> which comes by a totall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of the Body, and the Inconcoction of old Age. Neverthelesse, the last Act of <hi>Death,</hi> and the very Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguishing of <hi>Life</hi> it selfe;
<pb facs="11"/>
which may so many wayes bee wrought, outwardly, and inwardly; (which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding have, as it were, one common Porch, before it comes to the point of Death;) will bee perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, to be inquired of in this Treatise; But wee reserve that for the last place.</p>
   <p>That which may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired by Degrees, without a Totall waste of the first Stocke, is potentially eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; As the <hi>Vestall Fire.</hi> Therefore, when <hi>Physici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Philosophers</hi> saw, that Living Creatures were nourished, and their
<pb facs="12"/>
Bodies repaired; But that this did last only for a time; And afterward came old Age, and, in the end, Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution; they sought <hi>Death</hi> in somewhat, which could not properly bee repaired; Supposing a <hi>Radical Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture</hi> incapable of solid Reparation; And which, from the first infancie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Spurious Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but no true Reparation; wherby it grew daily worse and worse; And, in the end, brought the Bad, to None at all. This conceit of theirs, was both ignorant and vain. For all Things, in Living
<pb facs="12"/>
Creatures, are, in their youth, repaired entirely; Nay, they are, for a time, increased in Quantitie, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in Qualitie; so as the Matter of Reparation might be Eternall, if the Manner of Reparation did not faile. But this is the Truth of it: There is, in the Declining of Age, an unequall Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; Some Parts are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired easily, others with Difficultie, and to their losse; So as, from that time, the Bodies of Men begin to endure the Torment of <hi>Mezentius; That the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving die in the Embraces</hi>
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <hi>of the Dead;</hi> And the Parts easily reparable, through their Conjunction with the Parts hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable, doe decay. For the <hi>Spirits, Bloud, Flesh,</hi> and <hi>Fat,</hi> are, even after the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline of yeares, easily repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; But the Drier, and more Porous parts, (As the <hi>Membranes;</hi> All the <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles;</hi> The <hi>Sinewes, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, Veines, Bones, Cartilages;</hi> Most of the <hi>Bowels;</hi> In a word, almost all the <hi>Organicall parts;</hi>) are hardly Reparable, and to their losse. Now these hardly Reparable Parts,
<pb facs="13"/>
when they come to doe their office, of Repairing the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which are easily repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, finding themselves deprived of their wonted Abilitie, and strength, cease to performe any longer, their proper Functions. By which meanes, it comes to passe, that in processe of time, the whole tends to Dissolution; And even those very Parts, which in their owne nature, are, with much case, Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; Yet through the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of the Organs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, can no more receive Reparation; But decline and, in the end, utterly fail.
<pb facs="14"/>
And the cause of the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Life, is this For that the <hi>Spirits,</hi> like a gentle Flame, continually preying upon Bodies; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiring with the outward <hi>Aire,</hi> which is ever Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and Drying of them; Doe, in time, destroy the whole Fabricke of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die; As also the particular Engines, and Organs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; And make them unable, for the worke, of Repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. These are the true wayes, of <hi>Naturall Death,</hi> well, and faithfully, to bee revolved in our Mindes. For He that knowes not the
<pb facs="14"/>
wayes of <hi>Nature,</hi> how can he succour her, or turne her about?</p>
   <p>Therefore, the <hi>Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ought to bee two-fold: The one touching the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption,</hi> or <hi>Depredati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> of the Body of Man; The other, touching the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration,</hi> and <hi>Renovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the same: To the end, that the Former may, as much as is possible, be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden and restrained; And the Latter, comforted. The Former of these, pertaines especially, to the <hi>Spirits,</hi> and Outward <hi>Aire;</hi> By which the <hi>Depredation,</hi>
      <pb facs="15"/>
and Waste, is committed; The Latter, to the whole Race of <hi>Alimentation,</hi> or Nourishment; whereby, the Renovation, or Restitution, is made. And as for the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part, touching <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption;</hi> This hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Things common, with <hi>Bodies Inanimate,</hi> or without Life. For such Things, as the <hi>Native Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> (which is in all Tangi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bodies, whether Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, or without Life;) And the Ambient, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, <hi>Aire,</hi> worketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Bodies Inanimate;</hi> The same it attempteth, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="15"/>
      <hi>Animate,</hi> or <hi>Living Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;</hi> Although the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Spirit</hi> super added, doth partly breake, and bridle, those Operations; Partly exalt, and advance them wonderfully. For it is most manifest, that <hi>Inanimate Bodies,</hi> (most of them,) will endure a long time, without any Reparation; But <hi>Bodies Animate,</hi> without Food, and Repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, suddenly fall, and are extinguished; As the <hi>Fire</hi> is. So then, our <hi>Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> shall be double; First we will consider the <hi>Bodie</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> as <hi>Inanimate,</hi>
      <pb facs="16"/>
and not <hi>Repaired</hi> by <hi>Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishment;</hi> Secondly, as <hi>Animate,</hi> and <hi>Repaired</hi> by <hi>Nourishment.</hi> Thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving prefaced these Things, we come now to the <hi>Topick</hi> Places of <hi>Inquisition.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>