<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>GOOD READER BEARE with these small faultes, or other, which in this difficulty of prin∣ting, there where oure ton∣ge is not vnderstāded, must needes be committed.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100096_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16809</idno>
           <idno type="STC">371</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100096</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>GOOD READER BEARE with these small faultes, or other, which in this difficulty of prin∣ting, there where oure ton∣ge is not vnderstāded, must needes be committed.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defense and declaration of the Catholike Churchies [sic] doctrine, touching purgatory, and prayers for the soules departed. by William Allen Master of Arte and student in diuinitye</title>
                 <author>Allen, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Laet (Latius), Hans (Jan) de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>289, 6 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>GOOD READER BEARE with these small faultes, or other, which in this difficulty of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, there where oure ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge is not vnderstāded, must needes be committed.</head>
   <list>
      <item>Fo. 12. Pag. 2. Li. 14. <hi>Reade for sacraledge sacriledge</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 16. Pag. 1. Li. 7. <hi>Reade for iokyng yokyng.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 29. Pag. 2. Li. 17. <hi>Reade for mamed named.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 37. Pag. 2. Li. 11. <hi>Reade for hauno haue no.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 45. Pag. 2. Li. 21. <hi>Reade for non sum non sim.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 110. Pag. 2. Li. 13. <hi>Reade for appirition apparition.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 120. Pag. 2. Li. 13 <hi>Reade for vnfayded vnfayned.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 152. Pag. 1. Li. 6. <hi>Reade for maked naked.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 152. Pag. 2. Li. 1. <hi>Reade for so set to set.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 157. Pag. 1. Li. 10. <hi>Reade for so say to say.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 186. Pag. 2. Li. 17. <hi>Reade for author altare.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 196. Pag. 1. Li. 12. <hi>Reade for playnes plaine.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 224. Pag. 1. Li. 19. <hi>Reade for langnange language.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 231. Pag. 1. Li. 3. <hi>Reade for Carthagiēsi cruditius, Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginensi eruditus.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 234. Pag. 2. Li. 8. <hi>Reade for ys his.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 241. Pag. 1. Li. 2. <hi>Reade for it is</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 243. Pag. 1. Li. 6. <hi>Reade for is it say is to say.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Fo. 270. Pag. 1. Li. 1. <hi>Reade for Nire Nice.</hi>
      </item>
   </list>
   <pb facs="8"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>