<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL, Sir RICHARD YOUNG, Knight Barone the Worshipfull, Mr. GILBERT HAR∣RISON, Alderman; M•. ROBERT ED∣WARDS, Deputy of the R Worshipfull Company of Merchant Adventurers▪ M•. HH WINDHAM, M•. EDWARD FOORD, Mr. HUMPHR: BERINOTON; MERCHANTS: And the rest of the worthy Inhabitants of the Parish of Aldermanbury, LONDON: Saving Health, true Riches, and eternall Happinsse.</title>
           <author>B., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100140_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13014</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23307.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100140</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL, Sir RICHARD YOUNG, Knight Barone the Worshipfull, Mr. GILBERT HAR∣RISON, Alderman; M•. ROBERT ED∣WARDS, Deputy of the R Worshipfull Company of Merchant Adventurers▪ M•. HH WINDHAM, M•. EDWARD FOORD, Mr. HUMPHR: BERINOTON; MERCHANTS: And the rest of the worthy Inhabitants of the Parish of Aldermanbury, LONDON: Saving Health, true Riches, and eternall Happinsse.</title>
                 <author>B., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A forme of wholsome words; or, an introduction to the body of divinity : in three sermons on 2 Timothy, 1. 13. Preached by John Stoughton, Doctor in Divinity, sometimes fellow of Immanuel College in Cambridge, late preacher of Aldermanbury, London</title>
                 <author>Stoughton, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raworth, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Crooke, Andrew 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Crooke, John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Frere (Fryer), Daniel</distributor>
                            <distributor>Overton, Henry</distributor>
                            <distributor>Rothwell, John 2</distributor>
                            <distributor>Sergier, Richard 2</distributor>
                            <distributor>Smith, Ralph</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 95, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E pleased to take notice, that here is
presented to publike view, the true
legitimate birth of the Authour,
whose name it beares. He left se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
Sermons under his owne
hand, preached at speciall times,
and in Auditories of greatest worth and estimation,
the chiefe of which are now made publike, in these
ensuing Sermons: other of his Sermons were onely
taken from his mouth, in the publishing of which,
the best care is and shall be taken, to publish them by,
and compare them with the exactest copies that can
be gotten. In both you have the Authours mind,
as neare as can be, expressed, in his own words, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
adding or detracting. In the latter, you shall
finde the heads of the Sermons (which were all that
were last perfected by the Authour) in a methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
Analysis prefixed before them: they were his
owne, both for forme and words; onely what he
wrote in Latine, is translated into English, for the
benefit of all, and the Latine you shall have inserted
in the margin, in his own words, answerable to the
severall particulars treated on in the Sermons: you
may see a proofe of it in the Sermon upon 1 <hi>Sam.</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
2. 30. if it had been sooner thought on, you should
have found the like in all, you may expect it in the
rest, except in some few, which are already in the
Presse, or prepared for it. This shall be the token in
every Sermon, by which the true birth shall be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguished
from such counterfeits, as might other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
be fathered upon him. Be intreated to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
the slips of the pen in writing, and of the Presse
in printing, and then I hope you shall not finde any
materiall imperfections: so I commend these la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
together with thy selfe, to the blessing of
God.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>