<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100428_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02959</idno>
           <idno type="STC">131</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100428</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhite deuil, or The hypocrite vncased : in a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, March 7. 1612. By Thomas Adams minister of the gespell at Willington, in Bedford-shire</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradwood, Melchisidec</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 61, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onest</hi> and <hi>vnderstanding</hi> Reader; (if neither, hands off) I neuer saluted thy <hi>Generall</hi> name by a <hi>speciall</hi> Epistle, till now: and now, perhaps, soone enough: but if <hi>Honesty</hi> be <hi>Vsher</hi> to thy <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,</hi> and <hi>vnderstanding Tutour</hi> to thy <hi>Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie;</hi> as I cannot feare, so I need not doubt, or treat with thee for Truce: Truce, of what? of <hi>Suspense,</hi> not of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spension;</hi> it belongs to our Betters: <hi>Suspend</hi> thy cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, doe not <hi>suspend</hi> me by thy censure. I doe not call thee aside, to aske, with what applause this <hi>Sermon</hi> pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, but (it is all, I would haue and heare) with what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite. I had rather conuert one soule, then haue an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth praise me. Whereof, if I were (so besotted to bee) ambitious, by this I could not hope it: for it puls many tender and tendred sins out of their downy neasts; and who strikes <hi>vice,</hi> and is not stricken with <hi>calumnies?</hi> I must rather thinke, it hath passed from one presse to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, to a worse, hazarding it selfe to be pressed to death with censures: which yet (though I lowly hope better) I cannot feare; since it speakes no more, nor other, then iustifiable truth. What hath beene obiected already, I must breefly answer. It is excepted, that I am too mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb facs="4"/>
in describing some vices. Indeed, such is their ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous nature, that their best <hi>conuiction</hi> is <hi>derision;</hi> yet I abominate any pleasantnesse heere, but <hi>Christian;</hi> and would prouoke no smile but of <hi>Disdaine:</hi> wherein the <hi>grauitie</hi> of matter, shall free my forme of words from <hi>lightnesse.</hi> Others say, I am other-where too <hi>Satyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally-bitter.</hi> It is partly confest: I am bitter enough to the <hi>sins,</hi> and therein (I thinke) <hi>better</hi> to the <hi>sinners,</hi> more charitable to the persons. Some wish I would haue spared the <hi>Church-theeues,</hi> because it is not yet gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally granted, that <hi>Impropriations</hi> of Tythes, are <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations</hi> of wrongs; but if there bee a competent maintenance to the <hi>Minister,</hi> and not to him neither, except of worthy gifts, (prouided, that they iudge of his <hi>gifts</hi> and <hi>competencie)</hi> it is enough: well, if any such be greeued, let him allow his <hi>Minister</hi> a <hi>Sufficiency,</hi> vnder which he cannot liue, without want to his family, or disgrace to his profession (at least, so taken.) and heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of certified, I will take counsell to draw the bookes, and put his name out of the <hi>Catalogue</hi> of <hi>Theeues:</hi> But it would be strange if any of these <hi>Ziba's</hi> should yeeld to <hi>Mephibosheth</hi> a diuision of his owne <hi>lands</hi> or goods; when they doe, I will say, <hi>Dauid</hi> is come againe to his <hi>Kingdome,</hi> or rather, the <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>Dauid</hi> is come to <hi>Iudgement.</hi> Others would haue <hi>Inclosers</hi> put out, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause (commonly) great men, but therefore the greater their finnes, and deseruing the greater taxation. Nay some would perswade <hi>Vsury</hi> to steppe in, to trauerse his <hi>Inditement,</hi> and prooue himselfe no <hi>Theefe,</hi> by the verdict of the Countrie; because <hi>Sub Iudice lis est,</hi> it is not yet decided, that <hi>Vsury</hi> is a Sinne. It is <hi>Sub Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice</hi> indeed, but the Iudge hath already interposed his
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Interlocutory,</hi> and will one day giue his <hi>Definitiue Sentence,</hi> that <hi>Vsurie</hi> shall neuer dwell in his <hi>holy Mountaine.</hi> Others blunder in their verdict, that I haue too violently baited the <hi>Bagge</hi> at the stake of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch,</hi> and all because I want it: I will not returne their censure, that they are hence knowen to haue it, that speake against me, for speaking against it: who yet, if they would light the candle of their <hi>Speech,</hi> at the fire of their <hi>Vnderstandings,</hi> would easily see and say, that it is not the <hi>fulnesse</hi> of the <hi>Bagge,</hi> but the <hi>fowlenesse</hi> of the <hi>Bagge-bearer,</hi> that I reprooue: I could allow your purses fuller of <hi>wealthinesse,</hi> so your mindes were emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier of <hi>wickednesse:</hi> but the <hi>Bagges</hi> effects, in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, vsually load vs, either with <hi>parcimony</hi> or <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digallity;</hi> the lightest of which burdens, saith <hi>Saint Bernard,</hi> is able to sincke a <hi>Shippe.</hi> Others affirme, that I haue made the Gate of <hi>Heauen</hi> too narrow, and they hope to finde it wider; <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are more mercifull. True it is, that Heauen-Gate is in it selfe wide enough; and the narrownesse is in respect of the <hi>Enterer:</hi> and though thy sins cannot make that too little to receiue thee, yet they make thee to grosse and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, to get into that: thus the <hi>Straitenesse</hi> ariseth from the deficiency, (not of their <hi>Glory,</hi> but) of our <hi>Grace.</hi> Lastly, some haue the <hi>Title</hi> sticking in their stomacks; as if <hi>Christ</hi> him selfe had not called <hi>Iudas</hi> a <hi>Deuill;</hi> and likened an <hi>Hypocrite</hi> to a <hi>Whited Sepulcher:</hi> as if <hi>Luther</hi> did not giue <hi>Iudas</hi> this very <hi>Attribute;</hi> and other <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> from whom <hi>Luther</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riues it. Good <hi>Christian</hi> Reader, leaue <hi>cauils</hi> against it, and fall to <hi>caueats</hi> in it: read it through: if there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it to better thee, either the fault is in my hand, or
<pb facs="5"/>
in thy hart. Howsoeuer, giue <hi>God</hi> the <hi>praise;</hi> let none of his. <hi>Glory</hi> cleaue to vs <hi>earthen Instruments.</hi> If thou likest it, then <hi>(quo animo legis, obserua, quo obseruas, serua)</hi> with the same affection thou readest it, remember it, and with the same thou remembrest, practise it. In hope of this, and prayer for this, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this Booke to thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, and thy conscience to God. Willington, March. 27. 1613.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine if thou be Christs
T. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>