<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Book.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100526_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01943</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1209</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100526</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Book.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The composition or Making of the moste excellent and pretious oil called oleum magistrale : First published by the commaundement of the King of Spain, vvith the maner hovv to apply it particulerly. The which oyl cureth these diseases folowi [n] g ... Also the third book of Galen of curing of pricks and wounds of sinowes. A method for curing of vvounds in the ioynts, and the maner how to place them. Abreef [sic] gathering togither of certain errours which the common chirurgians dayly vse ... Faithfully gathered and translated into English by George Baker chirurgian. 1574</title>
                 <author>Baker, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 51, 3 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>The Preface to the <hi>Book.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Realme</hi> of Spain there inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a people called in the Spanish tung <hi>Moris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> of the which nation this Oyl was first pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised, vnknowen to the Spaniards: which afterwards came to their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderstāding by the baptised <hi>Affricans,</hi> of the which nation there are a great number in <hi>Granado</hi> and <hi>Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> and as yet they folow the orders of the Turks, bothe in their meats, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel and language, and haue no affinitie with the Spaniards, but only that they be baptized and become Christiās. And although they be not as yet growen so suttle &amp; crafty as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said Spaniards: yet neuerthelesse it hath béene wel prooued and séen by experience that they haue had more knowledge then the said Spa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niards, both in the secrets of nature, and also in the properties of herbs and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in the art of curing.</p>
   <p>In this said nation, there was one na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Aparice,</hi> the which about the yéere
<pb facs="13"/> of our Lord, 1566. did take his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place at <hi>Madrid</hi> a town situated in <hi>Castille la neufeue,</hi> 12 legues from <hi>Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leta,</hi> at the which place the court is most commonly kept: where he did think best to be for his profit, and there did begin to practise the art of Chirurgery and to cure Wounds, Contusions, Hargubush shot, Canckers, pain of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Rains, Apostumes, Hemorhoids, olde Vlcers, pain of the gout, and indifferently all maner of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seases, so that within short time he did such cures worthy of praise that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (hauing intelligence of his merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous experience) resorted vnto him thrée score miles about, to the end that by his help they might receiue their helth. And after that he had healed them: he delt so fauourably with them, that moste com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly he took lesse then they did offer vnto him, and healed them in viij. dayes which the Chirurgians of the Towne could not doo in iij. wéeks.</p>
   <p>In so much that he was estéemed of all men, aswel for the excellency of his art: as also for his great curtesy whiche he shewed vnto them.</p>
   <p>Yet neuertheles as we sée that science and vertue is neuer peaceable (although
<pb facs="13"/> that the common people were wel certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of his labour and seruice) yet the M. Chirurgians of the town (féeling their perticuler profit and authoritie to decay by this aforsaid <hi>Aparice</hi>) began to be at great strife with him, and sūmoned him to appéer before the <hi>Alcaldes,</hi> which are the Iudges of the aforesaid town, saying that he did them great iniury &amp; wrong in medling with the art of the which he had no knowledge, which art did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain onely to them béeing sworn to that facultie, and that they would bring in good proof in the common welth, that hée did more harme then good. So that their desire was to haue him imprisoned, to the intēt that if he should fear any thing in the meane time, to absent him self, and also laying many haynous crymes against him. The Iudges could doo no lesse then commit him to prison.</p>
   <p>Vpon whose imprisonment: certain gentlemē and others (which hauing by his meanes receiued their helth of great hurts and diseases, and regarding the profit of the common welth, and also see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great wrong which the said Chi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rurgians vsed against the said <hi>Aparice,</hi> béeing so honest and vpright in his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb facs="14"/> concerning his art, &amp; that nothing which was laid against him could be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued: thought among them selues that he deserued a better rewarde then he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued at their hands.</p>
   <p>Whervpon they made with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent a Supplication in his behalf for the bayling of him out of prison, the whiche (by reason of his long béeing sick in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son) they obtained vpon that condition that hee should medle no more with any cures, vntil suche time as he were authorised.</p>
   <p>Yet neuerthelesse many diseased per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons béeing afflicted with diuers greefs, would not abstain from him, but resor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him dayly, the which he would not by any meanes medle with for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of his great charge that he had to the contrary, yet not withstanding the importaunce of the people was so great: that he was constrayned secretly to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister vnto them.</p>
   <p>The which at length was disclosed vnto the Chirurgians of the town, and immediatly after they made their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to the aforesaid Iudges and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto them that the said <hi>Aparice</hi> had doon contrary to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> order y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was made
<pb facs="14"/> wherupon he was committed to prison again, which caused that the whole as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of the town bothe Gentlemen, Burgesses &amp; merchants (in his behalf) complained to the Iudges, in so muche that in th' end it came to the kings eare, which beeing a wise prince and desiring the profit of his common welth: was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to knowe the aforesaid Prisoner, and the true &amp; right cause in all things.</p>
   <p>And when he vnderstood the iust cause and that whiche the said <hi>Aparice</hi> did, was by the vertue of a simple Oyl: he was desirous to knowe the composition of it. The which the said <hi>Aparice</hi> (what for the gréef of his wrongful imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the vncurteous dealing of the Chirurgians) refused to declare, saying that it was the meanes wherby he did get his liuing, so that if it were common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly knowen: it would be an occasion that he should be no more sought vnto.</p>
   <p>When the King perceiued that hee could not obtain it: he offred vnto him (in consideratiō that he should shew the receipt) a thousand Duckets, which the said <hi>Aparice</hi> refused, saying that he did holde him self better contēt with his sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then he could with golde &amp; Siluer.</p>
   <pb facs="15"/>
   <p>So that immediatly folowing the said <hi>Aparice</hi> (béeing very sore hādled w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his foresaid sicknes, and partly for the gréef that he took of his wrongfull imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ended his life, for the which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny noble personages did much lament, thinking that with his dead carkas: this noble treasure should haue béen buryed, and also the king him self was very sore greeued for the losse of suche a rare and precious science.</p>
   <p>Neuerthelesse the said <hi>Aparice</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing maried a Spanish woman (by the which he had certain children) declared the secret of this pretious Oyl vnto her as shalbe shewed héer after.</p>
   <p>Immediatly after the death of the said <hi>Aparice,</hi> the king beeing very sory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he could not get the knowledge of such a science: made a diligent serch to knowe if their were any of his fréends which had this secret medicine, and also to knowe whether his wife had it, to the which they all answered that there was none other that euer had the knowledge therof but onely he him self, and that he kept it from his owne wife, for fear lest she should (béeing a woman) disclose it and make it common although she dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssed
<pb facs="15"/> patients in her husbands absence, and also whilest he was prisoner.</p>
   <p>At his last imprisonment, he féeling him self not like to liue because of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sease, and cōsidering that he should leue his wife and Children but in a wofull state: discouered this secret vnto her, and did leaue it vnto her for a pretious trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure and there withall gaue her a great charge that she should not disclose it to any man, what soeuer shuld be offred vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to her for it.</p>
   <p>But as in the end all things come to light, she (for to get her owne lyuing and her poor Childrens) began to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medle for to cure secretly with the said Oyl and solde it vnto them whiche stood in néed of it, saying that it was of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same Oyl that her husband had made.</p>
   <p>Not w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>standing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people (perceiued that it lasted very long &amp; that it could not be chosen but that she must haue the receit) offred vnto her for the composition ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, fiue hundred duckets, but she answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that she had it not, and said if she had it: she would rather dye then declare it.</p>
   <p>For the cause of the which sharp an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere: she was expresly inhibited from curing with the said Oil, neither to sel it
<pb facs="16"/> for any maner price. By y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which menes (what with the councell of her freends and necessitie constrayning her) she of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to declare the the secret, in conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that she might haue the thousād Duckets, but in th'end she was constrai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to take fiue hundred Duckes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the King graunted in the presence of certain Phisitions and Chirurgians which were appointed, vnto whome she declared the secret and shewed by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience the composition and the manner how to make it.</p>
   <p>And they to prooue whether it were the same or no: applyed it to many disea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed persons, and it was found of the same vertue and effect of that that her husbād had made. And then was named by the Phisitions and Chirurgians the Oyl <hi>Magistrale,</hi> estéeming it to be the best and moste pretious among all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
   <p>So that when they had iustly approoued that it was the very same secret that her husband left vnto her: they deliuered vnto her the fiue hundred Duckets whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che the King promised vnto her.</p>
   <p>Then by the commandement of the King: the Phisitions and Chirurgians
<pb facs="16"/> of the Town had the perfit knoweledge of it, in such sort, that at this present day almoste all the whole Realme of Spain vseth none other medicines, what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of hurt or wound so euer it bee, whiche is a moste excellent and approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Mitigatiue</hi> or appeaser of pain, and is a very good secret necessary tobe kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen in a common welth.</p>
   <p>And as for my parte: I would it were aswell knowen and experimented in this Realme as it is there. Therfore for the good wil and affection the whiche I bere towardes my countrey (to the which I am bound to serue to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moste of my power) I thought good to write this secret and to bring it to light, although I knowe that there be some which wil not be wel pleased heerwith, and paraduenture wil demaund of me the experience of it, for the whiche I doo not force séeing that I haue the trueth on my side, and that it is not vnknowen to a great number (which haue traue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Realme of Spain) the nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and singuler vertues of this Oyle, the which they doo dayly sel to all other Nations, and I my self hauing séene the notable vertues therof approoued vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="17"/> diuers of our owne nation, at the hands bothe of Merchants and Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which brought the said Oyle from thence.</p>
   <p>And now chauncing with the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of the making of the said Oyle, and béeing so wel assured, that it is the right and perfet order, and for the which I wil answere: I thought it my dutie to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>close such a noble secret, for the profit of so many as I knowe shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ayd therby, rather then to please some perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler persons.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>