<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Worshipfull and his very loving Si∣sters, Mris Dorothie Ger∣rard, Mris Elizabeth Har∣vie, &amp; Mris Anne Moul∣son; All increase of true happinesse.</title>
           <author>R., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100071_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07776</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18156</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100071</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Worshipfull and his very loving Si∣sters, Mris Dorothie Ger∣rard, Mris Elizabeth Har∣vie, &amp; Mris Anne Moul∣son; All increase of true happinesse.</title>
                 <author>R., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three homilies upon these three sentences folowing : Psal. 55.22. Cast thy burthen vpon the Lord. Iohn 14.27. My peace I giue vnto you. Luk.10.42. One thing is necessarie. Composed by Philip Mornay, lord of Plessis-Marly</title>
                 <author>Mornay, Philippe de, seigneur du Plessis-Marly</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 177, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Worshipfull and his very loving Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
      <hi>Dorothie Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
      <hi>Elizabeth Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie,</hi> &amp; M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>
      <hi>Anne Moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son;</hi> All increase of true happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eare and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Sisters, seing it hath pleased God to vnite vs together by most neere and strict bands of amity, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, those of nature and grace, I haue often beene
<pb facs="3"/>proiecting with my selfe which way I might (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my departure out of this world) leaue with each of you some expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of that loue, which in regard of both these bands, I finde my selfe obliged vnto you in. Wherevpon it being my hap during this late and great Visitation (never to be forgotten) to light vpon a subiect, well sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to these troublous times, <hi>viz.</hi> these 3. Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises ensuing, written by a Noble and Iudicious personage, in his owne natiue Language: I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved
<pb facs="3"/>out of that little insight I had thereinto; by reason of my trauels in my yonger yeares, to set vpon the translation thereof; time and leisure serving me so fitly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. And the rather, least with the vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble servant, I might iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be taxed in mine own conscience, either of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp in a Napkin,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.20 Mat. 25.25.</note> or burying in the earth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this one talent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto my trust. Now howsoever some may here not vntruely obiect, that moe Tracts in this kinde haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="4"/>bin brought to light, then are either carefully read, or of the Readers kindly respected, yet wel weighing the worth of the points herein cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, it seemed to mee, that I could not without some wrong done to my selfe &amp; others, withhold them any longer from the publicke view. For what burdened soule, would not gladly accept of case? What trembling heart would not reioyce to find peace? And who is he or shee, whose heart &amp; head being distracted &amp; cumbred about many
<pb facs="4"/>carking cares, would not willingly light vpō that one thing, which being obtained, would breed in them a world of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment? So that vpon the point, these 3. Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises carefully read, dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, and well practised, may in some cases proue more beneficiall; then to be left by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gift of friēds, thousands of gold &amp; sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Now as I am bold to publish them (my good sisters) to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world, vnder each of your names &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tronage, so is it my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning also to bequeath y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same vnto you, not as a
<pb facs="5"/>worldly, but as a spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al legacy, the fruit wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of my hope is shall abide with you forever. Let me intreate you all then, my deare sisters, with good <hi>Mary</hi> to chuse the better part, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> as Christ sayth, <hi>shall never be taken from you,</hi> lest being overmuch busied about the things of this life, you should seeme to come short of the heavenly: as it is to be feared too many haue already done, doe, &amp; will doe, till they repent the same at leisure. <hi>For what will it profit vs, to gain the whole world, and to lose
<pb facs="5"/>our owne soules; or what can wee giue in exchange for our soules?</hi> Mat. 16.26. But beloved Sisters, I am perswaded better things of you, &amp; such as accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany salvation, though I thus speake. Wherefore accept in loue, what is here presented vnto you, from a loving heart: and cease not I pray you, to pray for him, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires from the heart, ever to rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your very lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Brother, <hi>A. R.</hi>
      </signed>
      <date>Ianuary 5. 1625.</date>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>