<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the memorie of the Author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100435_Fr1_13</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03379</idno>
           <idno type="STC">135</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100435</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the memorie of the Author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The muses threnodie, or, mirthfull mournings, on the death of Master Gall : Containing varietie of pleasant poëticall descriptions, morall instructions, historicall narrations, and divine observations, with the most remarkable antiquities of Scotland, especially at Perth By Mr. H. Adamson</title>
                 <author>Adamson, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Anderson, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 87, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>To the memorie of the Author.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>Dear Soul, thou hast obtain'd more lasting Fame,</l>
      <l>In follies collours wisedome setting forth,</l>
      <l>Than if ten fabriks like <hi>Mausolios</hi> frame</l>
      <l>Were for thee rear'd in witnesse of thy worth.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thy <hi>Perth</hi> may boast of such a gratefull son,</l>
      <l>Who thus hath honoured his deare aged another,</l>
      <l>Thy Muse such glorie and such fame hath won</l>
      <l>To her, as no oblivioun can it smother.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <pb facs="11"/>
Art, wit, and learning; learning, wit, and art</l>
      <l>Do joyntlie justle here, each of them striving</l>
      <l>Which carrie shall the prise, and beare chiefe part</l>
      <l>In these thy layes, thy native Town describing.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thy <hi>Georges gabions</hi> shew to underlings</l>
      <l>That all things trifles be, that heaven not reaches,</l>
      <l>By what thy <hi>Gall</hi> and he, in rapture, sings,</l>
      <l>Much wisedome divine and humane thou teaches.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thy death the Muses darlings all shall mourne,</l>
      <l>And shall a tombe erect unto thy name</l>
      <l>Of teares turn'd cristall; and upon thine urne</l>
      <l>These words shall write, as blazon of thy fame:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Heere lyes his dust, by whose most learned quill</l>
      <l>He and his Perth doe live, and shall live still.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>IO. MOORE.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>