<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS ADMONITION TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100389_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15315</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25603</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100389</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS ADMONITION TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A theologicall disputation concerning the oath of allegiance : dedicated to the most holy father Pope Paul the fifth. Wherein all the principall arguments which haue hitherto beene brought by Cardinall Bellarmine, Iacobus Gretzer, Leonard Lessius, Martin Becanus, and diuers others, against the new oath of allegiance, lately established in England by act of Parliament, are sincerely, perspicuously, and exactly examined. By Roger Widdrington, an English Catholike. Translated out of Latin into English by the author himselfe,whereunto hee hath also added an appendix, wherein all the arguments, whach that most learned diuine Franciscus Suarez, hath lately brought for the Popes power to depose princes, and against the aforesaid oath of allegiance, are sincerely rehearsed, and answered</title>
                 <author>Preston, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60, 421, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS ADMONITION TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be foure things, <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader,</hi> which I thought good to admonish thee of. <hi>The first</hi> is, that if perchance thou art resolued to make an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere to this Disputation, which I haue composed, thou must call to thy remembrance what is the true state of this present controuersie. For it is not sufficient for thee, as I haue before declared, to produce only <hi>probable</hi> arguments either against the whole <hi>oath,</hi> or any part thereof, or else against the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweres,</hi> which I, in the name of them who defend the <hi>oath,</hi> haue alleadged, but thou must bring arguments, which are plainely <hi>demonstratiue,</hi> and to which no <hi>probable answere</hi> can be made; otherwise thou wilt neuer sufficiently <hi>demonstrate,</hi> that this <hi>oath</hi> cannot be taken by any man with a <hi>probable,</hi> and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a <hi>safe conscience.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2 The second,</hi> is; that whereas not long since two <hi>Doctors</hi> of Diuinitie, <hi>Adolphus Schulcke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> (if he be the only Author of that booke which is published in his name) and <hi>Edward Weston</hi> haue
<pb facs="13"/>
seemed in some sort to answere my <hi>Apologie for the Soueraignety of Princes,</hi> to whom at this time I being detained with other occasions, cannot commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously returne a full answere, which neuerthelesse thou shalt, God willing, ere it be long receiue, I thought it conuenient to propound vnto thee at this present some things, which thou maist obserue in them. And first of all both of them haue so guilefully dissembled the true state of the controuersie, as though they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade the Reader, that I intended to bring <hi>euident,</hi> &amp; <hi>demonstratiue</hi> reasons against that doctrine, which defendeth the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to depose Princes, and to dispose of their temporalls, and to proue <hi>inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciblie,</hi> that the reasons, and authorities, which Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> bringeth to confirme the said autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, to be <hi>altogether improbable;</hi> whereas contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwise Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> pretendeth to <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate,</hi> and therefore is not afraid to charge those Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes with <hi>heresie,</hi> who denie the aforesaid autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and I, as both in my Apologie,<note n="a" place="margin">Nu. 3. &amp; nu. 463.</note> and in my Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geticall Answere<note n="b" place="margin">In the places aboue cited in the epistle to his <hi>Holinesse</hi> nu. 2.</note>, I did purposely obserue, intended onely <hi>probably</hi> to shew, that Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine hath not hitherto sufficiently demonstrated, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the testimonie of holy Scriptures, or tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Apostles, or any definition of the Church, or by any Theologicall arguments, that the Pope hath by Christ his institution any au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie at all, either directly, or indirectly, either absolutely, or respectiuely to the spirituall good to depriue Soueraigne Princes of their temporal Dominions</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">By which it is manifest that I haue not any way altered the state of the question from that I propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in <hi>my Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> as some do apprehend, but that they did not dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obserue the words, which both in the beginning of my Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, <hi>nu.</hi> 3. and in the end, <hi>nu.</hi> 463 I did pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely and in expresse words set downe.</note>: and consequently, that those Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, who denie that authoritie, are not to bee branded
<pb facs="13"/>
with any marke of <hi>heresie,</hi> or <hi>error,</hi> as Cardinall <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> ouer rashly affirmeth, or also to bee charged with any crime of <hi>temeritie.</hi> Which obseruation if thou carefully wilt consider, thou shalt very easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that neither Doctor <hi>Schulckenius,</hi> nor Doctor <hi>Weston</hi> doe in there <hi>Apologies</hi> set forth in defence of Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> impugne that doctrine which I haue taught, but which they themselues haue inuented. For neither doe they <hi>demonstrate,</hi> that the reasons, or authorities, which Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath brought, are such, that no <hi>probable answere</hi> can be made vnto them, neither that the <hi>Solutions</hi> which I haue made vnto them are void of <hi>all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie.</hi> For if this doctrine concerning the <hi>Popes</hi> power to depose <hi>Princes</hi> be necessarily to bee held as a point of <hi>faith,</hi> as these <hi>Doctors</hi> following Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will needes haue it to be, it must of neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie follow, that either <hi>Christ,</hi> or the <hi>Apostles</hi> haue deliuered it to the <hi>Church</hi> by word, or writing, or else it must be gathered, I do not say, only by <hi>probable,</hi> but by <hi>euident, and necessary consequence</hi> from those things, which we haue receiued from <hi>Christ,</hi> or the Apostles. But let them produce but one only <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> out of holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> but one only <hi>Apostolicall tradition,</hi> but one only <hi>definition,</hi> but one only <hi>Theologicall demonstration,</hi> let them insist there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let them vrge it as much as they are able, if I doe not giue thereunto a <hi>probable answere,</hi> I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly acknowledge my selfe to be vanquished: if they refuse to doe this, it is manifest, that they seeke euasions, and that they not for desire to find out the truth, but least they should seeme to be ouercome, will rather with
<pb facs="14"/>
clamours, then with reasons yet contend: and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer that they doe great iniurie both to the faith of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the faithfull, whiles they doe not desist to thrust vpon the faithfull people, to their notable tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall preiudice, their owne vncertaine opinions for <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible</hi> assertions of the Catholike faith.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> And verily if for desire to find out, and teach the truth, Doctor <hi>Schulckenius</hi> had bin sincerely mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to write, he would doubtlesse haue bin greatly asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med both to delude his Reader so grossely, and also to charge me falsely with such manifest vntruths. And first of all to make me odious to <hi>Secular Princes</hi> thus he writeth in his Dedicatorie Epistle:<note n="c" place="margin">Not farre from the end.</note>
      <hi>An other thing there is that the same my Aduersarie</hi> (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Widdrington) who for his owne aduantage crieth out with open mouth,</hi> that the power of Princes is diuine, that it is most holily ordained by God through the law of Nature, that Subiects by the law of God owe obedience to Princes; <hi>the same my Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie, I say, when so it fitteth his purpose, cryeth out,</hi> that Subiects haue power inherent in themselues, and due vnto them by the law of God and nature, which they can neuer loose or transferre from them selues, ouer Kings, to iudge them, to depose them, to choose others, to transferre Kingdomes, to change the manner of gouernment: <hi>Thus writeth my Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie. num. 439. and 460.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> But truly I cannot but wonder that Doctor <hi>Schulckenius</hi> is not abashed to impose vpon me so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest an vntruth. For I neuer affirmed, <hi>that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects haue power ouer Kings, to iudge them, to depose thē, to choose others, &amp;c.</hi> But this only I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb facs="14"/>
in that place,<note n="d" place="margin">Nu. 438. &amp; seq.</note> that whensoeuer Emperours do vtterly forsake the Empyre, neither will protect it any longer, but do leaue the Kingdome to be spoyled by the enemies, and consequently wil no longer reigne ouer the people, nor be their <hi>Emperours,</hi> or <hi>Protectors</hi> (as, according to the opinion of <hi>Lupoldus Babenbergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> &amp; <hi>Michael Coccinius,</hi> it happened when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Rome transferred the Empire to the Germans) <hi>in that case the Pope, Senate, and people of Rome</hi> by the vertuall, <hi>at leastwise consent of all the other people of the West-parts, who were subiect to the Empire, had full right, and authority (which by no custome, or translation of the Imperiall Seate they could loose, it being connaturall and due vnto them by the law of nature</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">To wit, in that case when they had no Emperour, for then they were absolute of themselues, and subiect to none.</note>) <hi>euen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the doctrine of Cardinall</hi> Bellarmine <hi>but now related, to appoint ouer themselues a new Emperour, and consequently to transferre the Empire, which the</hi> Grecians <hi>did</hi> only in name <hi>hould in the Westerne parts to</hi> Charles <hi>the great, and his Successours, or to any other, the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all See being in those parts at that time as it were vacant,</hi> or without any <hi>Emperour.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5. Secondly,</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Pag. 561. ad nu. 567.</note> the same <hi>Schulckenius</hi> towards the end of his booke doth foully belie me as affirming an other thing, which is farre more dangerous, and doth with more spitefull words aggrauate the same. For, whereas I answering to the authoritie, which Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> had brought from the example of <hi>Queene Athalia,</hi> who by the commandement of <hi>Ioiada</hi> the high Priest was slaine, did write, <hi>that</hi> Ioiada <hi>the high Priest in killing</hi> Athalia <hi>did no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="15"/>
thing, then which euery faithfull Subiect</hi> in the like case <hi>ought to haue done;</hi> which for that cause I did affirme, as in the same place I did declare, for that <hi>Ioiada</hi> not of his owne authority, but in the name of the <hi>King,</hi> and of the <hi>Common wealth</hi> did command that <hi>Athalia</hi> being an Vsurper, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to raise a Conspiracie against the true and lawfull <hi>King,</hi> and who by the Common wealth was acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and receiued for such a one, crying out, in the temple to the people as the Scripture relateth<note n="g" place="margin">The fourth of the <hi>Kings chap.</hi> 11. and 2. Paralip. <hi>chap.</hi> 23.</note>, <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, Treacherie, Conspiracie, Conspiracie;</hi> Doctor <hi>Schulckenius</hi> doth so misconstrue my words, as though I should auerre, <hi>that euery faithfull Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, if he</hi> only thinke, <hi>that one hath by a bad title vsurped the Kingdome, may, and not only may, but also ought to kill such a Prince.</hi> And at last he exclaimeth in this manner: <hi>Behold O Kings, and Princes, you haue one who is carefull of your se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie; So obseruant are they of your Princely Maiestie, who doe violate and calumniate the Pontificiall authoritie. Euery Subiect,</hi> saith <hi>Widdrington, not only may, but also ought in such a case to do that, which</hi> Ioiada <hi>did. O mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable state of Princes, whose Kingdome, and life is subiect to the iudgement of euery pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man? If Cardinall</hi> Bellarmine <hi>had written such a thing, what tumults would not</hi> Widdring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>make! what clamours would he not raise?</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6.</hi> But where is your conscience O <hi>Schulckenius?</hi> where is your sincere and vpright dealing? what hath so greatly blinded your mind, that you should not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed to impose vpon me so manifest a slander? Did
<pb facs="15"/>
      <hi>Ioiada</hi> only thinke, and not also certainely know, that <hi>Athalia</hi> had by an vniust title vsurped the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? Did he not also certainly know that <hi>King Ioas</hi> a child of seauen yeares age, the true Heire to the King. dome, whom he himselfe had deliuered from being murthered, was with him aliue and safe in the howse of God? Did not he, before he put <hi>Ioas</hi> in possession of his Kingdome, and caused <hi>Athalia</hi> to be slaine, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into league with the <hi>Centurions, who</hi> as the <hi>Scripture</hi> saith, <hi>went round about</hi> Iuda, <hi>and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together the</hi> Leuites <hi>of all the cities of</hi> Iuda, <hi>and the chiefe men of the families of</hi> Israell, <hi>and they came into</hi> Ierusalem: <hi>and all the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude made a couenant in the howse of God with the</hi> King: to wit, to put <hi>Ioas</hi> their lawfull <hi>King,</hi> who was wrongfully detained from his Kingdome in possession thereof: <hi>and in the Kings name, and by his authoritie</hi> to cause <hi>Athalia</hi> the vsurper to bee slaine, especially if he should raise any conspiracie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>King:</hi> For <hi>Ioiada</hi> did not by his owne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but in the Kings name, and by the <hi>Kings</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thority command <hi>Athalia</hi> to be slaine. <hi>Ioiada,</hi> saith <hi>Abulensis,</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">4. Reg. q. 20. nu. cap. 11.</note>
      <hi>represented the Kings person, it was lawfull for the</hi> King <hi>to command</hi> Athalia <hi>to be slaine; Therefore also it was lawfull for</hi> Ioiada, <hi>who represented the</hi> Kings <hi>person in all things.</hi> Tell me now, I beseech you, O <hi>Schulckenius,</hi> may not euery faithfull Subiect lawfully, and ought not he also <hi>in the</hi> like case, that is, not by his owne priuate authority, as you faigne, but by the publike authority of the true <hi>King,</hi> and who is certainely knowen to bee true <hi>King,</hi> the Common wealth also consenting there
<pb facs="16"/>
unto, kill an vsurper, not who is only reputed, but also certainely knowen to be such a one, and who plotteth treason against the true King? Neither doth this doctrine open the way to rebellions, and conspiracies, or expose the liues of Princes to the iudgement of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men. But you in this very place doe lay open a wide gapp to rebellions, and reuoltings, whiles too too vnaduisedly you do affirme, that <hi>the consent of the people is sufficient to giue away to an other, the rightfull title to a kingdome from the lawfull Heire,</hi> and who also hath no way offended. <hi>Athalia,</hi> say you,<note n="i" place="margin">Pag. 558.</note>
      <hi>without doubt did tyrannically vsurpe the Kingdome, but hauing reigned peaceably six yeares, it is credible, that, the people by little and little giuing their consent, she obtained a lawfull right to the Kingdome.</hi> And neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse you knew right well, O <hi>Schulckenius,</hi> that <hi>Ioas,</hi> who by inheritance was the true and rightfull <hi>King,</hi> was at that time safe and aliue in the house of God. And this your seditious doctrine was perchance one cause among others, wherefore your booke was publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly burnt in <hi>Paris.</hi> And therefore prudently <hi>Becanus,</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">Pag. 120.</note> who in the first edition of his <hi>Controuersia Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana</hi> did teach this very same doctrine, perceiuing his errour, did in his later corrected <hi>Edition</hi> cause that very same sentence to be cleane blotted out.</p>
   <p n="7">
      <hi>7. Thirdly,</hi> the same Doctor <hi>Schulckenius,</hi> to disgrace me also with the <hi>See Apostolike,</hi> as though I taught flat <hi>hereticall doctrine,</hi> thus hee writeth in the sixt Chapter of his Apologie. <hi>The second Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">Pag. 256.</note>: <hi>It is hereticall to affirme, that the Pope as Pope, and by the law of God hath not any
<pb facs="16"/>
power in temporals. This is against</hi> Widdrington, <hi>the Lutherans, and the Caluinists. The third Conclusion</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">Pag. 258.</note>. <hi>It is hereticall, that the Pope as Pope, and by the law of God hath not any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to command Secular Princes in temporall matters, at leastwise in order to spirituals. This is against</hi> Widdrington, <hi>the Lutherans, Caluinists, &amp;c.</hi> And neuerthelesse all my writings do most mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly teach the flat contrary. For I do not only by the way, but of set purpose, neither once or twice, but very oftentimes in expresse words teach, repeate, and incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, <hi>that the Pope hath power in temporals not indeed to dispose of them, but to command Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Princes in temporals in order to spirituall good.</hi> With what face therefore dare <hi>Schulckenius</hi> auouch, that I deny that very thing, which in the very same expresse words not once or twice, but most fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently I doe affirme? I omit now diuers other slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which this Doctor doth very falsly lay to my charge, of which I will ere it be long, if God permit, most cleerely purge my selfe. In the meane time let the prudent Reader iudge, how little credit is to be giuen to these kind of men, and whether our English Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes may safely repose their faith, there consciences, and all the temporall estate of themselues, and of their whole posteritie, vpon the writings of such men, who, to disgrace their Aduersarie, doe of set purpose corrupt his sayings and sentences, in such an important matter as is the teaching of <hi>heresie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="8">
      <hi>8.</hi> Concerning Doctor <hi>Weston</hi> I will say little at this present, being also hereafter, God willing, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postulate with him more at large (but modestly) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="17"/>
his dangerous doctrine, the bitternes of his stile and diuers slanders wherewith hee falsly doth charge me. He saith,<note n="n" place="margin">Pag. 463.</note>
      <hi>that his months worke Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation is not a reuengement of an angry mind against me, (and of that hee calleth God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) but a courteous admonition rather of a friend, and brother; and that patience,<note n="o" place="margin">Pag. 156.</note> and contempt of wrong doth moderate the sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his stile; and that he is not willing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke me to anger, and to requite me with railing speeches.</hi> And neuerthelesse his booke, or rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous libell is so stuft with railing speeches, that his very friends are ashamed of the spitefull bitternes of this man. For behold the admirable patience of this writer, behold the courteous admonition of a friend, and brother. <hi>Impietie, pride, flatterie,</hi> and also <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie</hi> almost in euery other page he layeth to my charge. <hi>Thou lyest</hi> O Widdrington, <hi>thy lyes</hi> O Widdring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton are familiar to him, he often calleth me <hi>enemie of mankind, a wicked man, a blasphemer, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Idolater of the Ciuill state, impious Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logist, impious flatterer, full of Caluin, and Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the vicar of Hell, and impious heretike</hi> is frequent in his mouth, and diuers other reprochfull speeches hee is often times pleased to bestow vpon me. But if this Doctor, when he is <hi>patient, not angry, a contemner of iniurie, my friend</hi> and also <hi>louing brother</hi> could belch vp such soule, and spitefull nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names, what bitter, and venemous speeches, I pray you, if he had bin angrie, would he haue cast out against me from his raging stomach? But I pittie the weake iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this man, of what a weake iudgement hee is
<pb facs="17"/>
this his booke doth plainly shew, whereof also certaine Doctors of <hi>Doway</hi> haue giuen sufficient testimonie, who for that cause would not permit, that his booke should be printed at <hi>Doway</hi> with publike approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. His spitefull speeches do nothing hurt me, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit his cause; doubtlesse they doe great harme to his owne conscience. But in this hee doth me exceeding great wrong, (and thereof I call God to bee a witnes, and reuenger against him) in shamefull affirming, that I conspired to take away his life. <hi>First of all,</hi> saith hee, <hi>thou beginnest a tragedie against me which should haue gloriously ended with my blood, if it had succeeded according to thy desire.</hi> God is my witnes, that this is most false, which he chargeth me withall. For I neuer, I call the same God to witnes, did euen in thought plot any thing against the person of this man, neither did I euer wish to him any thing worse then to my selfe. That also which he saith, <hi>that I vpon spleene against the Iesuites, wrote my Apologie for the rightfull power of Princes, and that hee by priuate letters did admonish me of my impietie, and heresie,</hi> is most vntrue; For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon any spleen against the <hi>Iesuites,</hi> whose Order I doe reuerence with all dutifull respect, whom this <hi>Doctor</hi> hauing now with the aire changed also his mind, doth in his book egregiously flatter, I was moued to write my <hi>apology;</hi> This only did very much dislike me, and which at the first caused me to write, that some of these Religious men did so stifly cleaue to their owne opinions, that they would needs haue them to be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all Catholickes to the exceeding scandall of the Church, and to the great temporall preiudice of our
<pb facs="18"/>
English Catholickes. Neither did this <hi>Doctor</hi> send his letters to me, or imagined that they should come to my hands, but by chance by meanes of a friend of mine I came to a sight of them. And verily, if both in the Westerne, and Northerne parts of this Land it had not been reported by many, that a <hi>Doctor</hi> of Diuinitie had excellently confuted my <hi>Apologie,</hi> and shewed most cleerely, that many hereticall propositions were, forsooth, therein contained, I would neuer haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered such an idle Pamphlet. But seeing that hee se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, and treacherously accusing me of <hi>heresie,</hi> and <hi>Paganisme</hi> did first assault me, the most iust law of nature giueth me leaue to haue care of my credit and good name, in a matter of such moment as is the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into heresie, and to free my selfe by lawfull meanes from such a foule imputation. And if he in assaulting me hath by the blamelesse defending of my innocencie receiued any scarre, let him not attribute the same to my iust defence, but to his wrongfull setting vpon me, who hath prepared for himselfe a pitfall, wherein bee might be caught. I am a <hi>Catholicke,</hi> and a child of the <hi>Catholicke Romane Church;</hi> and if any man of what degree soeuer he be, shall wrongfully accuse me of heresie, let him know assuredly, that by the assistance of almightie God, I will by all those meanes, which <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>nature</hi> hath granted to innocent men to defend themselues, to the vttermost of my power cleere my selfe of those slanders, vntill the <hi>Church</hi> being perfectly informed of my opinion, shall in plaine, and particular words, (for no man can recall errours, vnlesse he know particularly what they be) condemne the same.</p>
   <p n="9">
      <pb facs="18"/>9. <hi>The third</hi> thing, which I would admonish thee of <hi>(courteous Reader)</hi> is, that when this present <hi>Disputation</hi> was in the Presse, I had a sight of the <hi>Apologeticall Disputation</hi> of <hi>Leonard Lessius,</hi> wherein I found an obiection alleaged by him to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the <hi>Oath,</hi> which his <hi>English Recapitulator</hi> (fearing perchance that it would not be pleasing to our English Catholickes) did make no mention thereof, whereas of the rest of <hi>Lessius</hi> his arguments against the said <hi>Oath,</hi> he doth not so much make an <hi>Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or <hi>Recapitulation,</hi> but rather relate them word by word. This <hi>Lessius</hi> therefore affirmeth, that the Kings of England are <hi>Feudaries</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and hould their <hi>Kingdome</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi> as it were in free-farme, and consequently that no man can lawfully sweare, that the <hi>Pope</hi> in no case whatsoeuer hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to depose the <hi>King.</hi> And this obiection, saith <hi>Lessius,</hi> he neuer saw well answered. The same excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion also, although not in expresse words, yet in very deede is taken by <hi>Martin Becanus,</hi> who although in his <hi>English Controuersie</hi> set forth by him this last yeere, he doth expresly affirme,<note n="p" place="margin">Pag. 102.</note>
      <hi>that it is certaine to him, that all the parts of the Oath are not false, if they be well declared: For these be true, 1. That King</hi> Iames <hi>is lawfull King of England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Ireland. 2. That in the same Kingdomes he is Soueraigne, or supreme Lord in temporals;</hi> yet in the same his <hi>English Controuersie</hi> corrected, and set forth by him againe this present yeere,<note n="q" place="margin">For his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Edition was censured at Rome by a speciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his <hi>Holines,</hi> as in the Censure it is expressed.</note> he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth with Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> that the <hi>Kings</hi> of England are <hi>Feudaries</hi> to the <hi>Pope.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whereas before he did write, <hi>that it is certaine to
<pb facs="19"/>
him, that King</hi> Iames <hi>is Soueraigne Lord in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals,</hi> now in his corrected <hi>Edition</hi> hee leaueth out this word <hi>(Soueraigne)</hi> or <hi>supreme,</hi> and only saith, <hi>that King</hi> Iames <hi>is Lord in temporals.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="10">
      <hi>10.</hi> But to this obiection Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> once <hi>Lord Chancelour</hi> of England, whose authoritie both for his singular learning, and particular deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the <hi>See Apostolicke</hi> is greatly to be regarded, doth very well answere<note n="r" place="margin">In the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of soules, pag, 296</note> in these words. <hi>If he</hi> (the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Beggers Supplication) <hi>say, as indeede some writers say, that King</hi> Iohn <hi>made</hi> England, and Ireland <hi>tributarie to the</hi> Pope, <hi>and the</hi> See Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicke <hi>by the grant of a thousand markes: wee dare surely say againe, that it is vntrue; and that all</hi> Rome <hi>neither can shew such a grant, nor neuer could, and if they could, it were nothing worth: For neuer could any</hi> King of England <hi>giue away the</hi> Realme <hi>to the</hi> Pope, <hi>or make the land tributa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, though he would.</hi> Seeing therefore that no <hi>King</hi> hath power to giue his Kingdome to an other man without the consent of the Kingdome, which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth not only the <hi>Barons,</hi> but also the <hi>communal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> neither doth Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> or <hi>Becanus</hi> alleage any one writer, who affirmeth that the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munaltie</hi> consented to this gift, or donation of <hi>King Iohn,</hi> or of any other <hi>King</hi> whatsoeuer, if that may be called a gift, which was not freely giuen, but rather extorted through feare (for <hi>Pope Innocent,</hi> as <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Paris</hi>
      <note n="s" place="margin">In the life of King <hi>Iohn:</hi> the yeare of our Lord, 1212. and 1213.</note> relateth, would not absolue, or make peace with <hi>King Iohn,</hi> who was excommunicated, and forsaken almost by the whole Kingdome, and was by the King of France brought into great distresse, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse
<pb facs="19"/>
he would resigne his Kingdome into the <hi>Popes</hi> hands: wherefore King <hi>Iohn</hi> (as <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> saith<note n="t" place="margin">The yeere 1213.</note>) <hi>being brought into despaire, did conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend to the perswasions of</hi> Pandulfus <hi>the Popes Legate, and did grant not without griefe the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwritten forme of peace)</hi> I do not perceiue, how the aforesaid obiection doth sufficiently proue, either the kingdome of England to be tributarie to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> to be his <hi>Feudarie,</hi> although we should also admit, that the <hi>King</hi> did giue the Kingdome to the <hi>Pope</hi> by the consent of his <hi>Barons,</hi> or that the English Catholickes may not probably perswade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and this their perswasion confirme by <hi>Oath,</hi> that <hi>King Iames,</hi> and not the <hi>Pope</hi> is their <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord</hi> in temporals, and that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not by reason of this <hi>Soueraigntie</hi> or supreme domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in temporals any power to depose the <hi>King.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="11">
      <hi>11.</hi> To conclude, I would gladly, that <hi>Becanus</hi> would sincerely declare vnto vs, for what cause hee in his new corrected English Controuersie, was moued to put out that word <hi>(lawfull King)</hi> whereof in his former <hi>Edition</hi> he made no scruple, but was certaine thereof. This very last yeere <hi>Becanus was certaine, that King</hi> Iames <hi>is lawfull King of England, and that hee is</hi> Soueraigne <hi>or supreme</hi> Lord <hi>of this Kingdome in temporals.</hi> This yeare it is lawfull for vs English men, according to <hi>Becanus</hi> opinion, to acknowledge <hi>King Iames</hi> to bee <hi>King of England,</hi> but not <hi>lawfull King,</hi> to be our <hi>Lord in temporals,</hi> but now <hi>our Soueraigne Lord.</hi> What manner of <hi>Allegiance</hi> we may according to his opinion make the next yeare, seeing that <hi>certainties</hi> doe so easily become
<pb facs="20"/>
to him <hi>vncertainties,</hi> we cannot know as yet. In very truth I am sorrie, that such and so learned men doe in a matter of so great importance vpon slight reasons so easily change their opinions, and doe by their incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie, and mutabilitie seeke to bring vs English Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes into so great calamities. And whether ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie compelleth vs to oppose our selues with all our might against this kind of doctrine, which especially here in England is both very scandalous to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion, and greatly preiudiciall to the temporall estate of vs English Catholickes, I remit to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any indifferent man, who is both well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the <hi>See Apostolike,</hi> and also to the <hi>Kings Maiestie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="12">
      <hi>12. The fourth</hi> and last thing, whereof I would admonish thee, is, that when the printing of this Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation was almost fully finished, there was sent vnto me an English booke printed but lately, and entituled, <hi>A Supplement to the discourse of</hi> Master Doctor Barlowes <hi>Answere, &amp;c. composed by F. T.</hi> Wherein this Author in the two first chapters ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a long discourse to proue, that this <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance</hi> is altogether vnlawfull, and cannot with a safe conscience be taken by any Catholicke. And this is the summe and substance of his whole Discourse. First of all he supposeth that in this <hi>Oath</hi> is denyed the Popes power not only to depose, but also to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate Princes, if they shall deserue it, and the safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of soules shall necessarily require it. From whence he afterwards<note n="u" place="margin">Pag. 66. nu. 117.</note> concludeth, <hi>that although the Oath doth not expresly affirme, the</hi> Kings Maiestie <hi>to bee the supreme head of the English Church,
<pb facs="20"/>
nor in plaine words denie the</hi> Pope <hi>so to be; yet it supposeth, and implyeth both the one, and the other; and thereupon denyeth the Popes autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to excommunicate, and depose a temporall Prince. And howsoeuer the matter bee other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise coloured, it is euident enough, that the true reason, for which the said authoritie of the</hi> Pope <hi>is impugned in the Oath, is no other, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the</hi> Kings Maiestie <hi>is held to be no way subiect to the</hi> Pope, <hi>yea and to bee himselfe su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme head of the Church of God in England.</hi> This being supposed, this Author endeuoureth to proue the <hi>Oath</hi> to bee repugnant to the law of God, of nature, of Nations, to the Ciuill, and Canonicall law.</p>
   <p n="13">
      <hi>13.</hi> Out of the old Testament hee produceth that saying of Deuteron. <hi>17. Si difficile &amp; ambiguum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If thou forsee the iudgement to be hard and ambiguous</hi> &amp;c. <hi>rise and goe vp to the place which the Lord thy God shall choose, and thou shalt come to the Priests of the Leuites stocke, and to the Iudge that shall bee for the time,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And if any shall be so proud as not to obey the commandement of the Priest, that shall for that time minister vnto the Lord thy God, by the sentence of the Iudge let that man die,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>So that it belonged to the High Priest absolutely, to command the Iudge to giue sentence of death against the transgressions of his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therefore the same authority haue also the High Priests in the new Testament.</hi> He bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth also out of the old Testament, certaine other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb facs="21"/>
facts of <hi>Priests,</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> to proue the same. Out of the new Testament he alleageth that saying of our Sauiour to Saint <hi>Peter, whatsoeuer thou shalt loose,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Feede my sheepe,</hi> the killing of <hi>Anani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> and some other such like examples. Out of the law of nature he sheweth,<note n="x" place="margin">Nu. 69.</note> that in all Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties an inferiour is subiect to the Superiour, the lesse perfect to the more perfect, as the wife to the husband, the seruant to his Lord, the scholler to his Master, the subiect to his Prince, policie to Religion, temporals to spirituals, and he that hath care of temporals to him who is Superiour in spirituals, and so the Common wealth must be subiect to the Church. Out of the law of Nations he sheweth,<note n="y" place="margin">Nu. 77.</note> that in all Common wealths, euen among the Panyms, the Religious Societie had the preheminence aboue the Common wealtb in all things that any way appertained to Religion. Out of the ciuill law he bringeth many Constitutions of <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,</hi> and the Statute lawes also of this Kingdome to proue the Popes Primacie in spirituals. And finally in the second chapter hee only alleageth that decree of the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Lateran,</hi> which hath bin so often vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and answered. This is the substance and summa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his discourse.</p>
   <p n="14">
      <hi>14.</hi> But first of all, who knoweth not, but that one inconuenience being granted, many absurdities do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently follow, The <hi>Supposition</hi> of this <hi>Author</hi> for so much as concerneth the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate</hi> Princes and his <hi>Primacie</hi> in spirituals, to wit, that they are denyed in this <hi>Oath,</hi> as this <hi>Author</hi> supposeth as manifest, but proueth it with no reason at all, is very vntrue, as in this <hi>Disputation</hi> we haue
<pb facs="21"/>
abundantly shewed. And verily it is exceeding strange, that learned men should not blush to affirme, with such confidence, that to be his <hi>Maiesties</hi> intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and meaning which hee himselfe in publicke wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings doth expresly professe not to be his meaning, and so often to inculcate without any solide proofe that very argument, which both his <hi>Maiestie</hi> himselfe, and many others haue oftentimes very sufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.</p>
   <p n="15">
      <hi>15. Secondly,</hi> how vaine that consequence is, which this <hi>Author</hi> doth inferre<note n="z" place="margin">Pag. 67.</note> from that maxime of the Lawyers, <hi>Accessorium sequitur principale, The accessorie followeth the principall, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church hauing power ouer the soule, hath consequently power ouer our bodies, and goods,</hi> vnlesse it be vnderstood of power to command corporall things, as they are referred to spirituals, euery man of learning may easily perceiue. For out of this principle we might also argue in this manner: <hi>The accessorie followeth the principall, therefore he that is Lord of all horses, must bee Lord of all bridles: The Pope hath power ouer the soules of Kings, therefore also ouer their liues.</hi> Let this <hi>Author</hi> explaine vnto vs, what the Lawyers do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand by this word <hi>(accessorie,)</hi> and what by this word <hi>(principall)</hi> in this their vulgar <hi>maxime,</hi> which hath many limitations, and by diuers learned men, is diuersly vnderstood; in the meane time we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny his consequence. The like argument <hi>Lessius</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">In his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logeticall Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation pag. 201.</note> doth make: <hi>The Pope,</hi> saith he, <hi>hath power to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate Kings, therefore he hath power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose them; because hee that can punish with a
<pb facs="22"/>
greater punishment, can also punish with a lesse.</hi> But if we may rightly argue from one thing to another which is of a diuers nature, condition, and degree, wee may also conclude thus: <hi>The Pope hath power to excommunicate Kings, therefore hee hath also power to kill them; because he that hath power to do the greater, hath power to doe the lesse</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">And that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a greater punishment, then corporall death, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> expresly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth lib. 3. de <hi>Ecclesia.</hi> cap. 6. &amp; lib. 3. de <hi>Laicis</hi> cap. 21. and citeth for it Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> lib. 1. <hi>contra Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarium legis, &amp; prophet</hi> cap. 17. as I obserued in my <hi>Apologie</hi> nu. 183.</note>. <hi>A man hath power to vnderstand, therefore also to flie. A Priest, who is no Bishop, hath power to absolute from sins, therefore also from debts. The same Priest hath by the meanes of the Sacraments power, to giue the Kingdome of heauen, therefore also earthly Kingdomes.</hi> Be not these I beseech you, very faire arguments to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade English Catholikes to cast away all their goods, and to deny their dutifull allegiance to their Prince?</p>
   <p n="16">
      <hi>16. Thirdly,</hi> it is vntrue which this <hi>Author</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that the doctrine concerning the Popes power to depose Princes is in this <hi>Oath</hi> plainly abiured as <hi>impious and hereticall:</hi> For only this doctrine is in this <hi>Oath</hi> abiured as impious, and hereticall, <hi>that Princes which be excommunicated, or depriued by the Pope may be deposed, or murthered by their Subiects or any other whatsoeuer.</hi> Which position, as we will declare beneath, is according to the common sense of the words so to be vnderstood, that it is in the free power of the Subiects, or any other what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>soeuer to depose, or if they will, to murther Princes, which he excommunicated, or depriued by the Pope, and therefore it may worthily bee abiured as <hi>hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="17">
      <pb facs="22"/>
      <hi>17. Fourthly,</hi> whosoeuer will attentiuely read the discourse of this Author, will most cleerely perceiue, that hee doth not forcibly proue any other thing from the law of God, or nature, then that the temporall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is in spirituals, and in temporals, as they become spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals subiect to the spirituall power of the Church to command, but not to punish <hi>by way of coercion</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">I said <hi>by way of coercion</hi> for the Church as I haue often repeated in my <hi>Apologie,</hi> and <hi>Apologeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Answere</hi> hath power to impose a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>by way of command</hi> if it be necessary for our soules health, but not <hi>by way of coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.</hi> So that if we will not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Church impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing such a temporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, she can only for our disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence punish vs finally with spirituall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments, as by inflicting spirituall Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, but not by depriuing vs of our lands, or liues.</note> with temporall punishments, but only with spirituall. And so the light of reason doth teach vs, that euery Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour may chastise him who in subiection is his infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour with some punishments, to wit, which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to his Superioritie,<note n="d" place="margin">As a Master may punish his scholler with whipping him, or expelling him his schoole, a father the sonne in like manner and by disheriting him, and thrusting him out of his familie, a husband his wife almost in like manner, and so the spirituall Common wealth with spirituall, and the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall with temporall punishments.</note> that is, by depriuing him of those goods, and priuiledges, which are proper to that communitie, whereof he is Superiour; But that any Superiour besides the supreme Gouernour of the Ciuill Common-wealth hath power to punish his infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, with punishment of death, depriuing of any corporall member or of all temporall goods, cannot ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily be deduced from the light of naturall reason.</p>
   <p n="18">
      <hi>18. Fifthly,</hi> hee that will diligently consider the vnder written sentences of Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> and Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will presently comprehend of what force is that text of Deuteronomie <hi>17.</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">If this text had bin a forcible argument to proue the Popes power to dispose of temporals, doubtlesse it would not haue bin omitted by Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his Controuersies, where hee bringeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places of the ould Testament to the same purpose, which I haue in my <hi>Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> answered.</note> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther such like places of the old Testament, which is a
<pb facs="23"/>
figure of the new, <hi>to proue that the Pope hath power to depose, or kill Princes, because the High Priest of the old law had that power, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we should admit, which cannot be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently proued, (as hereafter,</hi> God willing, we will shew more at large) that the <hi>High Priest had that authoritie. Excommunication,</hi> saith Cardinall Bellarmine,<note n="f" place="margin">Lib. 2. de Ecclesia. cap 6.</note> is now in the Church in steed of corporal death, which was in the old Testament, and which a common wealth hath in temporals. And Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">q. 39. in Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teron.</note> Excommunication doth now this in the Church, which killing did in the old Testament. <hi>In which place hee compareth that saying of</hi> Deuteronomie cap. 24. Hee shall bee slaine, <hi>and thou shalt take away euill from among you,</hi> with that saying of the Apostle, <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>5. Take away euill from among your selues.</hi> And in his booke <hi>de fide &amp; operibus</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> hee saith, <hi>that the materiall sword, which</hi> Moyses, <hi>and</hi> Phinees <hi>did vse, was a figure of the degradations, and excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, which are to bee vsed in the new law, seeing that in the Church discipline,</hi> saith Saint <hi>Augustine, the visible sword was to cease.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="19">
      <hi>19. Sixthly,</hi> those places of the new Testament, <hi>Whatsoeuer thou shalt loose, &amp;c. Feede my sheepe,</hi> also the reason which this <hi>Author</hi> alleageth out of Father <hi>Parsons,</hi> to wit, that otherwise the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall Common-wealth should bee imperfect, and not sufficiently prouided for, I haue heretofore in my Apologie<note n="h" place="margin">Nu. 35. &amp; seq. &amp; nu. 203. &amp; seq.</note> satisfied. That corporall killing of <hi>Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> and the visible deliuering of the forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catour into the hands of Satan, are to be referred to the
<pb facs="23"/>
grace of miracles. Neither doe I thinke this <hi>Author</hi> will affirme to bee in the Popes power to kill wicked men with his only word.</p>
   <p n="20">
      <hi>20. Seuenthly,</hi> from the law of Nations this <hi>Author</hi> proueth no other thing, then that all Nations had euer Religion in most great estimation, and that they preferred Religion before policie, but that the <hi>Priests</hi> of the Gentiles, <hi>as Priests,</hi> had power to punish any man with paine of death, or losse of all goods, this did not proceede from the law of nature granting to Priests such an authoritie, but from the priuate, and peculiar positiue lawes of euery Nation. Which <hi>Cicero</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">Pro domo sua.</note> cited by this Author doth most cleerely confirme, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>that it was most notably, and diuinely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the ancient Romanes, that the Bishops should haue the chiefe command in matters that appertained as well to the Common-wealth, as to the Religion of the Gods.</hi> Out of the Ciuill law, this <hi>Author</hi> doth only proue that the <hi>Pope</hi> is supreme head of the Church in spirituals.</p>
   <p n="21">
      <hi>21. Lastly,</hi> to that decree of the <hi>Councell of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran,</hi> which is by our Aduersaries so often inculcated, I haue giuen diuers Answeres in the <hi>Preface</hi> of my <hi>Apologeticall Answere,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Nu. 43.</note> which this <hi>Author</hi> doth dissemble. One only of them he doth briefly insinuate, and most slenderly confute, to wit, <hi>that by those men, who there are said, not to haue principall Lords ouer them, are not vnderstood Emperors, Kings, and absolute Princes, but other pettie Lords, who are subiect to Kings, and absolute Princes: for that</hi> Fridericke <hi>the Emperor in the fifth yeere after this Councell of Laterane, did make the
<pb facs="24"/>
same law in the selfe same words, changing only spiritual punishments into temporall, who could not by the name of them, who haue not princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Lords ouer them, vnderstand himselfe, and other absolute Princes.</hi> From whence I probably collected, that those words <hi>(who hath not a principall Lord)</hi> could not of themselues comprehend <hi>Kings,</hi> and absolute <hi>Princes,</hi> who vnlesse they are expresly named, are not to be vnderstood in penall lawes. And to say, as this <hi>Author</hi> barely, and without proofe affirmeth, that the <hi>Emperour</hi> did not indeede by those words comprehend Kings, but the Pope did comprehend them, is to say, not to demonstrate: considering that if that Councell would in that decree haue comprehended <hi>absolute Princes,</hi> it might as easily haue specified them by the proper and peculiar names of <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>absolute Princes,</hi> as by those generall words of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Lords,</hi> or who haue not <hi>principall Lords</hi> ouer them, especially seeing that the same <hi>Councell</hi> in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Decrees did expresly vse the peculiar names of <hi>Princes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="22">
      <hi>22.</hi> Therefore vntill any one shall <hi>cleerely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate,</hi> I do not say <hi>probably</hi> only <hi>shew,</hi> that the <hi>Answeres,</hi> which I haue giuen to that <hi>Lateran Councell,</hi> are <hi>altogether improbable,</hi> there can no forcible argument be drawne from that <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> to proue <hi>euidently and inuincibly,</hi> that the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which holdeth the <hi>Pope</hi> to haue power to depose <hi>Princes,</hi> is so certaine that the contrary cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by Catholickes without note of <hi>heresie, errour, or temeritie.</hi> And let this suffice for this present to shew the weaknes of this Authors more long then solide
<pb facs="24"/>
discourse, for that it may bee, that we will hereafter more exactly examine all his arguments in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and shew the weakenes of euery one of them.</p>
   <p n="23">
      <hi>23. Lastly,</hi> this <hi>Author</hi> vrgeth greatly certaine words of Saint <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> which I thought expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in this English Edition to examine, for that I vnderstand some of our Countrimen haue of late made great reckoning of those words, as though they were cleere for the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to depose Princes. This <hi>Author</hi> therefore endeuouring to proue out of the law of <hi>Moyses, that the spirituall power was then the supreme power on earth and commanded all temporall authoritie, and consequently might chastise temporall Princes,</hi> (he meaneth with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall punishments) <hi>when it was necessarie for the glorie of God, and the good of the Church,</hi> hee bringeth<note n="k" place="margin">Cap. 1. nu. 31.34.</note> the example of King <hi>Ozias,</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">2. Paralip 26.</note> (to which neuerthelesse I haue fully answered in my Apologie<note n="l" place="margin">Nu. 354. &amp; seq.</note>) <hi>whom</hi> AZarias <hi>the high Priest</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Azarias</hi> was not the high Priest as this <hi>Author</hi> imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but only a weekely Priest with 80. others. <hi>Genebrard in his Chronologie the yeere of the world</hi> 3408.</note>
      <hi>with the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of 80. Priests, most valiant men (saith the Scripture) because he presumed to offer incense, and would not obey his admonition but threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him and the Priests, and was therefore stric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by almightie God with leprosie, did not only command him to depart out of the temple, saying Egredere de Sanctuario,</hi> &amp;c. Go out of the Sanctuary, &amp;c. <hi>but also thrust him out of the same, festinatò expulerunt eum,</hi> they thrust him out in haste, <hi>and was forced by the sentence of the Priests (according to the prescript of the law,</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">Leuit. 13.</note>) <hi>to liue in a house a part so long as he liued. And I cannot omit,</hi> saith this Author,<note n="o" place="margin">Nu. 34. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>to touch here
<pb facs="25"/>
by the way, what Saint</hi> Chrysostome<note n="p" place="margin">Hom. 4 de verbis. Isaiae <hi>Vidi dominum.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>obserueth further in this example, to wit, that whereas</hi> OZias <hi>being leprous did not only dwell in the City (though in a house a part) but also reigne still for some yeares euen vntill he died, he ought to haue beene cast both out of the City, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so out of his Kingdome, and that Almighty God was so highly offended, because the same was not performed, that he withdrew the spirit of prophecie from</hi> Esay, <hi>and other Prophets du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the life and reigne of</hi> OZias.</p>
   <p n="24">
      <hi>24.</hi> Exiuit, <hi>saith</hi> Saint Chrysostome, cum lepra, &amp;c. <hi>The King went out of the temple with a leprosie, and yet they did not cast him out of the City, for the respect they bare to the Kingly diademe, but he still sate in his throne breaking againe the law of God: what then? God being angry with the Iewes interrupted the prophecie. So Saint</hi> Chrysostome: <hi>And againe a little after, speaking in the person of God.</hi> Ego, <hi>(saith hee)</hi> quod mei numeris feci, &amp;c. <hi>I haue done my part</hi> (that is to say, I haue strucken <hi>Ozias</hi> with a leprosie) <hi>and you are afraid to cast him being vncleane out of the City: you beare reuerence to his Kingly dignity violating the law of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I do therefore speake no longer to the Prophets, neither do I any more giue the grace of spirit,</hi> &amp;c. Silet spiritus, &amp;c. <hi>The grace of propheticall spirit was silent or ceased, and God did not shew himselfe, because vnder that vncleane man there was no grace. Thus saith Saint</hi> Chrysostome <hi>vpon occasion of these words of the Prophet</hi> Esay,
<pb facs="25"/>
      <note n="q" place="margin">Isai. 6.</note> Et factum est anno quo mortuus est <hi>Ozias</hi> Rex, vidi Dominum, &amp;c. <hi>For where as all the Prophets vsed to declare the time and yeere of the Kings reigne when they prophecied, Saint</hi> Chrysostome <hi>noteth, that</hi> Esay <hi>here omitted that custome, and did not speake of the life and reigne of</hi> Ioathan, <hi>in whose time he had his vision, but of the death of</hi> King OZias, <hi>during whose reigne the spirit of prophecie had ceased for the causes before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="25">
      <hi>25. Well then hereby it appeareth that God was offended, not only because</hi> Ozias <hi>was not cast out of the Citty, but also because hee was suffered still to reigne.</hi> Consedit in solio, <hi>saith the holy Father,</hi> legem Dei rursum transgrediens, <hi>hee sate still in his throne transgressing againe the law of God, that is to say,</hi>
      <note n="r" place="margin">This <hi>(that is to say)</hi> of this Author as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst that which Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> saith in this place.</note>
      <hi>as he had broken the law of God before, in presuming to sacrifice, and threatning the Priests; so also did he againe trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse, and violate the same in retaining his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome being Leprous: and because the same was permitted, and more respect borne to his Kingly dignitie, then to the execution of Gods law, therefore saith Saint</hi> Chrysostome, <hi>God punished the whole state not permitting his Prophets to prophecie, as they were wont.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="26">
      <hi>26. Whereupon I infer, that seeing the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse law of God ordained, that the cause of Leprosie should bee iudged and determined wholy by the Priests, and that</hi> Ozias <hi>was subiect to this law, it followeth that as he was expelled out of the temple by the Priests and forced by
<pb facs="26"/>
their sentence to liue in a house apart, (though within the Citty) so ought hee also to haue bin by their sentence cast out both of the Citie, and of his Kingdome. And if we consider but only that which was done by the Priests in this case of</hi> OZias, <hi>it cannot be denied but that they had a iudiciall power ouer his person, seeing that they both commanded him to go out of the temple before he was leprous, and afterwards thrust him out, yea &amp; confinde him to liue in a house apart. For though the Scripture doth not expresse, that his confining and separation was ordained by them, yet it could not bee otherwise: seeing that the law ordained</hi>
      <note n="s" place="margin">Leuit. 13.</note>
      <hi>expresly, that euery leprous man should be brought vnto the Priest, and that</hi> ad arbitrium eius separabitur, hee should be separated at his iudgement, or arbitrement, <hi>which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himselfe</hi>
      <note n="t" place="margin">Matth. 8. Marc. 1. Luc. 17.</note>
      <hi>acknowledged, when he remitted the leprous (whom hee cured) to the Priests.</hi> Thus writeth the Author of this Supplement.</p>
   <p n="27">
      <hi>27.</hi> But I wonder that this <hi>Author</hi> would vrge so vehemently for him selfe the authoritie of S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome,</hi> who in this very place is so plaine against his doctrine. <hi>First</hi> therefore this <hi>Author</hi> affirmeth, that <hi>Azarias</hi> and the other Priests did not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand King <hi>Ozias</hi> to depart out of the temple, but they did also thrust him out of the same, meaning as it seemeth, as we say, <hi>by head and shoulders,</hi> and by laying violent hands vpon him, whereas Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome</hi> in that very place seemeth to affirme, that they did not thrust him out by violēce, but only by their words, and commandement, and crying out against
<pb facs="26"/>
him as an vncleane person, <hi>Et egressus est Rex,</hi> saith Saint <hi>Chrysostome, omnibus exemplum factus, purgatumque est templum &amp; erectus est nemine propellente, qui{que} sacerdotium sibi vellet sumere, &amp; hoc quod habebat perdidit: Et exiuit è templo. And the King went forth being made an example to all, and the temple was purged, and he was cast forth no man driuing him forth, and whereas he would arrogate to himselfe the Priesthood, he lost that which he had: And hee departed out of the temple.</hi> And the reason why the Priests ought not to lay violent hands on the Kings person, Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> did a little before giue in these words. <hi>But the King did not abide the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the Priest, but being puffed vp with arrogancy opened the Temple, and entred into the Sanctuarie to offer incense. But what did God? After the Priest was contemned, and the Priestly dignity troden vnder foote,</hi> nec quicquam praeterea potuit Sacerdos (Nam sacerdotis tantum est arguere, &amp;c. <hi>Neither could the Priest doe any thing more (For it is the office of a Priest only to reproue, and to giue a free admonition, not to raise armes, not to vse targetts, not to shake a lance, nor to shoote arrowes, nor to cast darts, but only to reproue and to giue a free admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.) After therefore the Priest had reproued, and yet the King did not yeeld, but tooke wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, sheilds, and speares, and vsed his power, then the Priest said to God, I haue done that which belonged to my office, I can do no more, helpe thou the Priesthood, which is troden vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="27"/>
foote,</hi> &amp;c. Thus Saint <hi>Chrysostome.</hi> By which you may perceiue, how farre was the apprehension of Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> from those violent and bloody courses, which some vehement defenders of the Popes power to depose and kill Princes<note n="u" place="margin">
         <hi>Suarez</hi> es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, as shall appears beneath in my <hi>Appendix</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him in the last Sec. of the first part. See also be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath cap. 5. sec. 3. nu 4. &amp;c.</note> doe affirme, may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by the law of God to Priestly function.</p>
   <p n="28">
      <hi>28.</hi> Neither can this <hi>Author</hi> sufficiently proue, that it belonged to the Priests of the old law to thrust out by violence a leper out of the City, but only by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and by declaring that hee was a leper, which declaration did appertaine only to the Priests by the expresse appointment of almightie God, but that the Priests, after they had declared one to be infected with leprosie, and had charged him to depart, and the people to put their command in execution according as the law did prescribe, had any further authoritie <hi>(as they were Priests)</hi> to cast him out by violence, cannot bee conuinced out of the old law. Euen as in the new law it belongeth only to the Clergie to declare whether one be infected with heresie, which was figured in the old law by leprosie, but after they haue declared one to bee infected with heresie, and haue vsed against him Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall Censures, and haue deliuered him to the Secular Magistrate, commanding or requesting him to proceede according to the equity of the law, they haue no further power, <hi>(as they are Cleargie men)</hi> to vse any corporall violence against him, and if it shall please the temporall Prince to pardon his life, the Clergy cannot take it away, as out of <hi>Dominicus Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi>
      <note n="x" place="margin">Cap 7. sec. 2. nu. 17. in the end.</note> I will shew beneath.</p>
   <p n="29">
      <hi>29. Secondly,</hi> that other saying of this <hi>Author,</hi> to wit, that according to Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> God
<pb facs="27"/>
was offended not only because <hi>Ozias</hi> was not cast out of the City, but also because he was suffered still to reigne, is also contrary to Saint <hi>Chrysostomes</hi> words, which haue bin related by this Author. And in the very next homile Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> declareth the whole matter more particularly in these words: <hi>I will one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adde one thing,</hi> saith he,<note n="y" place="margin">Hom. 5. de verbis Isaiae.</note>
      <hi>which we demanded in the beginning, what is the cause, that seeing in prophecies all are wont to set downe the time, wherein the Kings did reigne, this</hi> Prophet Esay <hi>omitting that nameth the time, wherein</hi> OZias <hi>died, speaking in this manner,</hi> And it came to passe in the yeare wherein King <hi>Ozias</hi> dyed. <hi>And yet hee might haue expressed the time of the King, as all prophets vsually did. But he did not so: For what cause did he not so? It was an ancient custome to cast a leprous out of the City, to the end that those who liued in the City might be the better, and that the leprous himselfe should not present to men, prone to giue reprochfull speeches an occasion of scoffing and derision: but that he abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of the city might haue solitarines to be in steed of a vaile, or couer, against the reproch of calamitie. And this ought this King to haue suffered after his leprosie, but he did not suffer it, those that were in the City reuerencing him for his Soueraigntie: but hee remained at his house priuately. This prouoked God to wrath, this hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the prophecie, and which came to passe in the time of</hi> Hely <hi>the word of God was precious, neither was there any commanding vision.</hi> Thus Saint <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> whereby it is manifest, that Saint
<pb facs="28"/>
      <hi>Chrysostome</hi> doth not affirme, that God was offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that <hi>Ozias</hi> was thrust out of his Kingdome, but only that he was not thrust out of the City, according as the law in <hi>Leuiticus</hi> did ordaine.</p>
   <p n="30">
      <hi>30.</hi> Wherefore the meaning of those former words of Saint <hi>Chrysostome, he sate in his throne brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againe the law of God,</hi> is cleere by these later which I did now relate. For as before he being no Priest transgressed by presuming to offer incense, so now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he being leprous transgresseth by presuming to remaine in the City, which the law did forbid. Also this Author may perchance vse some cunning in trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating those words of Saint <hi>Chrysostome, Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in solio legem Dei rursum transgrediens, He sate still in this throne breaking againe the law of God,</hi> as though <hi>Ozias</hi> had offended againe by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining still in his throne, or continuing to be King; wherefore this word <hi>still</hi> may be equiuocall, and of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose put by this <hi>Author</hi> to signifie the sense aforesaid, whereas the words of Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> are only, <hi>He sate in this throne breaking againe the law of God;</hi> not for that he sate in his throne, or which is all one, kept still his Royall dignitie, although his sonne <hi>Ioa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>han</hi> did administer it in his name, but for that he departed not out of the City, as Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> expresly declareth.</p>
   <p n="31">
      <hi>31.</hi> Now concerning the example it selfe of King <hi>Ozias,</hi> who for his leprosie was cast out of the temple, and perchance also out of the City, which Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> brought to proue that the Pope hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to depose Princes, I haue in my <hi>Apologie</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered at large, neither hath Doctor <hi>Schulckenius,</hi>
      <pb facs="28"/>
as hereafter, God willing, I will plainely shew, conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced those answeres to bee improbable. The argument which <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine</hi> brought was in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance this: <hi>The Priests of the old law had autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to thrust a leper, who doth in the new law signifie an heretike, out of the temple and out of the City, yea and if he were a King to depriue him of his Kingdome, or at leastwise of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration thereof, as appeareth by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of King</hi> Ozias, <hi>therefore the Priests of the new Testament haue authoritie to depriue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Kings of their Kingdomes, or at least wise to suspend them from the administration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="32">
      <hi>32.</hi> Among other sufficient answeres, which I gaue to this argument, I denyed the consequence; to wit, that although the Priests of the old Testament had autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to depriue a King, being infected with leprosie, of the administration of his Kingdome, so long as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained a leper, (for that I doe not thinke it to be scarce probable that they had authoritie to depriue him who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his Regall authority,) neuerthelesse it doth not therefore follow, that the Priests of the new law haue the like authority. My reason was, for that the Priests of the old Testament had by the speciall law of God au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority granted to iudge and determine when any man was infected with leprosie, and withall there was a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar punishment appointed by the law against those who were infected with leprosie, to wit, that they should liue <hi>extra castra out of the campe,</hi> that is, a part from the rest, (for then the Isralites were as an armie of men marching forwards day by day, in the desert
<pb facs="29"/>
For if it should be so, that a King liuing out of the City, could not possibly gouerne his Kingdome, and in the old Testament Kings being infected with leprosie were by the law of God compelled to liue out of the City, it followeth necessarily, that God gaue leaue to the Priests or to the people to depriue a leprous King, or to declare him depriued of the gouernment of his Kingdome, so long as he remained a leper: But the Priests in the new Testament haue doubtlesse authority giuen them by Christ to iudge, determine and decide, what is heresie, and who is infected therewith, and also to punish with Excommunication and other Ecclesiasticall punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments any one who is infected with heresie, which pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment of Excommunication (which as <hi>Suarez</hi>
      <note n="z" place="margin">Tom. 5. disp. 1. sec. 4.</note> defineth it, <hi>is an Ecclesiasticall Censure, whereby one is depriued of the Ecclesiastical communion of the faithfull)</hi> was figured by that separation of the leper from the company of those who were in the campe: yet because the depriuing a King of the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration of his Kingdome doth not by the law of God follow the sentence of Excommunication, which by the law of God only depriueth of Ecclesiasticall communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as in the old Testament it did follow the liuing of a King out of the City, and a part from the rest of the people, as our Aduersaries doe suppose, this example of King <hi>Ozias</hi> is of little worth to proue the <hi>Popes</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to depose hereticall Princes.</p>
   <p n="33">
      <hi>33.</hi> Finally I cannot but obserue, how well forsooth this <hi>Author,</hi> who is so vehement against the <hi>Oath,</hi> and for the Popes power to depose Princes, doth agree with Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in vrging this argument, which is taken from the example of King <hi>Ozias;</hi> For
<pb facs="29"/>
Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> affirmeth, that King <hi>Ozias</hi> was thrust out both of the City, and also depriued of his Kingdome, this Author auerreth, that he was neither thrust out of the City nor out of his Kingdome: Others, as <hi>Abulensis,</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Nu 4. Reg. cap. 15. q. 4.</note> do affirme that he liued indeed out of the City, wherein <hi>Iosephus</hi> also doth agree,<note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Lib. 9. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitat. cap. 11.</hi> A great Historio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher of the Iewes, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing before Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed by the Romanes, and therefore it is likely that hee know all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular facts of those Kings. <hi>So writeth</hi> Abulens. <hi>q. 9. in 15. cap. lib. 10. Regum.</hi>
      </note> but not depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of his Kingdome, but that hee remained still true King not only in name but also by right, although by reason of his infirmitie his sonne <hi>Ioathan</hi> did in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers name and by his authoritie gouerne it: and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son doth confirme the same, for <hi>the depriuing of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion,</hi> as well obserueth <hi>Suarez, when it is done, doth alwaies continue,</hi> but King <hi>Ozias</hi> was only to liue out of the City for the time of his leprosie, so that if he had bin cured, he might haue returned againe to his palace within the City, and consequently to the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Kingdome, and therefore he could not bee depriued of his Regall authoritie, but at the most as it were suspended, for the time of his leprosie,<note n="c" place="margin">Disp. 15. de Excommun. sec. 6. nu. 3.</note> from exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting thereof, neither is it strange, that a man may haue right or dominion of a Kingdome, which hee cannot gouerne as appeareth in chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who may be true Kings, although they cannot gouerne it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>