<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Kinges most Sa∣cred MAIESTIE.</title>
           <author>Roffens, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100897_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04357</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1447</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100897</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Kinges most Sa∣cred MAIESTIE.</title>
                 <author>Roffens, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A brand, Titio erepta : On the fift day of Nouember last, before the Honourable Lordes of his Maiesties Priuie Councell, and the graue iudges of the law, &amp;c. this sermon preached by the Reuerend Father in Christ, William, Lord Bishoppe of Rochester</title>
                 <author>Barlow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Law (Lawe), Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Kinges most <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred</hi> MAIESTIE.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat Kings</hi> haue vouchsafed poore presentsfrom mean persons: a poorer or more base then <hi>TITIO,</hi> a <hi>Brand,</hi> a <hi>Cole-Brand,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>King</hi> accepted, because no <hi>stayed Subiect</hi> durst euer offer it; and yet I must. Not for that I dare doe it, yea, I dare not but doe it. For what am I, that I should either gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say, or delay to execute the commaunde of so great a <hi>Monarch,</hi> and <hi>my most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Maister?</hi> Perhappes my <hi>obedience</hi> in performing your pleasure, will not counter-ballance this <hi>presumption,</hi> in fronting it with your <hi>Highnes Name;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause, published it might haue beene, and yet not aspired to so <hi>glorious a PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRONAGE.</hi> If that bee the offence, I humbly craue pardon, (onely of your <hi>Maiestie).</hi> For this being a <hi>BRAND,</hi> fitte matter for <hi>fire</hi> to worke vppon, and my case as the <hi>Prophetts, Iaceo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wentes, I liue among men, that are</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psa. 37.</note>
      <hi>set on fire, whose teeth are dartes,</hi> euen those <hi>Ignea tela,</hi> Ephe. 6: for the <hi>tongue</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eph. 6</note>
      <hi>is inflamed by Hell,</hi> saieth Saint Iames): to whose protection, should I rather submit it, then to HIS, whose graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous countenance, like vnto thar <hi>Angels roscidus flatus,</hi> in the middest of the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, shall so keepe it, that the most <note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note>
      <hi>fiery</hi> spirit shall not touch it to <hi>scorch</hi> it: Since therefore it pleased your <hi>Maiestie, (most dreade Soueraigne)</hi> to commaund the diuulging thereof, I here in the
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>duety</hi> of a <hi>Subiect,</hi> and in all <hi>humilitie,</hi> as becommeth a <hi>Christian,</hi> offer it to your <hi>Highnes,</hi> wishing that it may aunswere the report, which those worthy <hi>Perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages</hi> of great <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Wisedome,</hi> who were present and heard it, <hi>vouchsafed</hi> to afforde it. If your <hi>Maiestie</hi> in the depth of your iudgement approue it, it neede not feare the censure of any. For why? I neuer yet heard▪ But I must stay my selfe, least that your Maiesties <hi>due prasyes</hi> (such is some mans hap) be as they are, by many, accounted for <hi>vndue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flatteries.</hi> My <hi>prayers</hi> I trust shall not so bee; namely, that seeing the <hi>Highest King</hi> hath grauntēd vnto your <hi>Maiestie,</hi> as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Salomon,</hi> a <hi>LARGE HEART,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenished with all, capable of more then <hi>Royall Endowmentes,</hi> it woulde please him to increase his <hi>Graces</hi> in you, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long your daies among vs, and to giue vs thankfull heartes for the fruition and affections loyally seruiceable to the
<pb facs="4"/>
pleasure of so <hi>Wise,</hi> so <hi>Learned,</hi> so <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,</hi> so <hi>Religious</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> whose <hi>vnworthy seruant</hi> I am, euen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your MAIESTIES poore <hi>Chaplein,</hi> VV. ROFFENS.</signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <hi>Non omne quod nigrum est, continuô deforme est.</hi>
      </q>
      <bibl>Bern. in Cant.</bibl>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>