<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>On Clitophon and Leucippes Loves translated.</title>
           <author>Allen, H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100406_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22622</idno>
           <idno type="STC">91</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100406</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>On Clitophon and Leucippes Loves translated.</title>
                 <author>Allen, H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The loves of Clitophon and Leucippe : A most elegant history, written in Greeke by Achilles Tatius: and now Englished</title>
                 <author>Achilles Tatius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Allam, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 255, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>On <hi>Clitophon</hi> and <hi>Leucippes</hi> Loves translated.</head>
   <l>THus thrive the Printers: the wise Gnomists paine</l>
   <l>Might well be spared now; each humerous braine</l>
   <l>Knowes, that <hi>his knowing profits not, unlesse</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Others know't too:</hi> this agitates the Presse:</l>
   <l>This stops the Passenger, when he shall spy</l>
   <l>Some pamphlets glorious front courting his eye.</l>
   <l>Some love-toy, such as this, whose furious zeale</l>
   <l>Will not permit Antiquitie conceale</l>
   <l>Her follies past: as if our age could throw</l>
   <l>Them in her teeth without a blushing brow.</l>
   <l>Are <hi>Clitophons</hi> so scarce? doth not each street</l>
   <l>Afford us <hi>Melites?</hi> every cloake you meet</l>
   <l>May wrap <hi>Thersanders</hi> rising forehead: though</l>
   <l>Exc'lent <hi>Leucippes</hi> peere we scarce can show.</l>
   <l>Thus may some sager Criticke, who would have</l>
   <l>Vs straight from Cradle thinke upon the Grave,</l>
   <l>Condemne our youths delight: we must expect</l>
   <l>The worst of censures for the least defect.</l>
   <l>Love is a Passion, and who e're will touch</l>
   <l>Ought that is his, must looke to finde him such.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="8"/>Nor shall the wounded onely bleed, but <hi>Hee</hi>
   </l>
   <l>That dares describe <hi>Cupids</hi> Artillerie.</l>
   <l>And yet he shall not suffer, let me call</l>
   <l>Lovers, the better part o'th' world, who all</l>
   <l>Will vindicate our Author. Here may youth</l>
   <l>Loves Copie draw, to act their owne in truth:</l>
   <l>Here may the Non-plust wooer fetch a wile</l>
   <l>To breake all <hi>Remora's,</hi> plots to beguile</l>
   <l>All Fortune's crosses: and if language faile,</l>
   <l>Here may he learne to court, triumph, bewaile▪</l>
   <l>I'th eloquentest straines. Nay here the man</l>
   <l>Of a severer brow may deigne to scan</l>
   <l>Maximes of morall goodnesse: tis the End</l>
   <l>Of both our Authors, by delight to bend</l>
   <l>Our Soules to Good, which in its owne course dresse</l>
   <l>Would move her faculties, would please them lesse.</l>
   <l>This thanke Wee'le owe their labours, and let them</l>
   <l>Commend their owne, that others paines condemne.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>H. Allen</hi> è C.C.C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>