<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all wearied sinners, all happinesse here and hereafter bee granted, and this following Treatise be dedicated.</title>
           <author>Whately, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100737_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15010</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25314</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100737</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all wearied sinners, all happinesse here and hereafter bee granted, and this following Treatise be dedicated.</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The oyle of gladnesse. Or, Comfort for dejected sinners : First preached in the parish church of Banbury in certaine sermons, and now published in this present treatise. By William Whately minister there</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Edwards, George 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 199, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all wearied sinners, all happinesse here and hereafter bee granted, and this following Treatise be dedicated.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved in our LORD. You know it was one part of <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptists office,<note place="margin">Isa. 40.4 &amp; Luk. 3.5.</note> to fill valleys, as was foretold of him. Valleys are dejected sinners, filling the valleys, is, comforting of such sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. This Worke is both
<pb facs="3"/>necessary and difficult. For to what purpose is it to beate downe a sinner, if he be not raised up againe? The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molishing of an old house doth not affoord habitation, if a new building be not set up in its roome: so neither doth the casting downe of mens high thoughts, make them a fit dwelling for God; if the faire pallace of spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comfort be not also erected in them. Our soules are not united to God in hearty love, nor subjected to him in sincere obedience, by bare terrors: (nay, that bitter anguish, which flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from the sight of sinne,
<pb facs="3"/>and death deserved by sin, will rather increase our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity against God, and irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate our rebellious nature, if it be not somewhat ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by hope.) It is the sweetnesse of God (the taste whereof affordeth more content in him, then any thing could give, which would allure us from him) that makes the heart to cleave to him, and to his waies. Worldly businesses, are better dispatched, after Sunne-rising, then at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night; so men doe make best speede in a journey, by day-light: so doth the journey of a godly conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation,
<pb facs="4"/>and the whole work of righteousnesse, goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward most prosperously, when the shining beames of spirituall gladnesse, have inlightened the soule, as it were a quiet and light morning after a darke and tempestuous night. How hard a thing it is to quiet the troubled soule, they can best tell, that have beene most imployed in it. The divell opposeth the successe of that labour with all his might, and craft; for hee findeth inexperience, that the Lord hath none so faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and valiant souldiers, in all his army as those
<pb facs="4"/>whom he hath first deepely wounded and after soundly healed. Terrors are the sores of the very consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the tenderest part of the whole soule, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are not easily cured. Carnall reason, the false guide of man-kinde, doth alwaies follow sence, which in this case, doth minister nothing but appearing ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, of never bing comforted, and a world of labour it will prove to withdrawe a man from following this guide. The truth is, none can rebuke these waves and stormes, (saying to them peace and
<pb facs="5"/>be still, that a great calme may follow) but alone our Lord Iesus Christ whom even the windes and the seas do obey. Yet the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Isaias</hi> telleth us,<note place="margin">Isa. 57.19</note> that God createth the fruit of the lips to be peace peace. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions, exhortations, directions, comfortable spee-&amp; perswasions of the godly, cheefely the Ministers of the Gospell, that stand in Christs stead, these be the fruit of the lips, these are the meanes by which the Lord doth stablish the soules of his servants in assured quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse at last. I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to contribute
<pb facs="5"/>something, to the cheering up of spirituall weepers, in this Treatise. This I offer to you burdened soules; as for others, I know how little agreement such foode hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with their pallates. But before you reade, what I have here written and published, take with you an advertisement or two. The principall hinderances of comfort, are unfitnesse for it, and aversenesse from it. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitnesse springs either from want of sincerity, in ones not being ready to see and acknowledge some sinne or sinnes, which God would have him see, but he hangs
<pb facs="6"/>backe: or else from want of humility in that a man doth not bring his heart, to stoope so low to Gods justice, as to yeeld himselfe into his hand without murmuring or quarreling. Till God have wrought us to his own bent (as it were) in these two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects, there is no hope of cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; Make haste therfore to let the Lord have his will in these two points. Now aversenesse from comfort, is a kinde of spirituall pettish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, or peevishnesse (which was sometimes in the Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist,<note place="margin">Psal. 77.2.</note> who saith, <hi>My soule refused comfort</hi>) which makes men love to strive
<pb facs="6"/>against their owne peace, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king great paines to thrust comfort away from them, &amp; giving over themselves, either still to renew the old or multiply new objections against themselves, to study to have something to say against all that may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for them, never considering, nor observing how true and reasonable the things are, which be spoken on their owne behalfe. The divell, (a great wranglex, that labours still to darken truths of this kinde and not to cleere them) suggesteth these cavils to the minde and the dazelling eye, is
<pb facs="7"/>ready to fixe it selfe upon them, as if they were mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of some weight and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments or answers of good force. Be warned to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare thus to abuse your wits to your owne hurt. Study to be able to defend your selves, and to learne how to doe it. What mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is it, to lay ones naked brest open to his enemies weapon? Reject not the consolations of God, neither let them seeme small unto you. Know your selves tyed in conscience, as to humble, and to purge, so likewise to comfort your selves, without which the former is done in
<pb facs="7"/>vaine, and the latter cannot be done at all. Be willing therefore to receive Gods goodnesse, when it is made evident that you have inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest thereunto. This is all I have to say in this Epistle. Now I leave you to the booke it selfe, beseeching God to make you reade joy and gladnesse, that your broken bones may rejoyce,<note place="margin">
         <hi>April</hi> 20. 1637.</note> and so wilrest a well-wisher to you all</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>WILLIAM WHATELY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>