<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>E., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100246_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21107</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7470</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100246</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>E., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The maintenance of the ministery : VVherein is plainely declared how the ministers of the Gospell ought to be maintayned: and the true and ancient practise of our Church in this case, shewed to be agreeable to the word of God, and all antiquity. Necessary in these times t be read and considered of all sorts of Christians, but specially of such as liue in townes and citties. By Richard Eburne, minister of the word</title>
                 <author>Eburne, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Edgar, Eleazar</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 176 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccept I pray thee (Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)
in good parte, what I present
vnto thee, to good purpose. Let
not my plainenesse displease thee;
which for to profit thee, as the fittest
phrase for an argument of this forme, I haue more
then ordinarily affected. In other stile I might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely
more better haue pleased a few, but am assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
should lesse haue satisfied all. It is the hearers
dutie that I principally teach: necessarie therfore I
should so expresse it, that they, euen they of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest
reach, and slowest capacitie, husbandmen,
trades-men, artificers, and whosoeuer else, might
fully conceiue me. As heere is whereby to direct
the vnlearned, so there wanteth not wherewith
to exercise the learned, whether teacher or hearer.
Th' one shall find his due, th' other his dutie, more
plainlie taught then hitherto by any. To whom
this seemeth not enough, occasion at least is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
the way thus opened, to performe more.
Mine attempt is no restraint of other mens liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
For the matter, I nothing doubt of thine as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb facs="6"/>
in most points. If in some we dissent, so it be
not in the chiefest, the matter is not great. Yeelde
mee these, That the Minister ought to haue <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
sufficient,</hi> and <hi>liberal</hi> maintenance: that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
euery one of anie abilitie, ought (according to
his abilitie, and of such goods as hee hath) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute:
That the best meanes to raise it, must
needes be that, which God, Gods church, and all
Antiquitie haue, by practise, approoued: and for
the rest I will not contende, nor when these are
duely practised (for of that, questionles we come
yet farre too short) any more complaine.</p>
   <p>Thus hoping, if my labours like thee, thou wilt
wishe to them such successe as thou perceiuest I
desire: if not, yet thou wilt affoord me that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie
fauor, which other men in works of lesse
moment, &amp; worse argument, doe often obtaine,
I wish to thee as much good as thine own heart,
christianly affected, can desire.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, and for the
seruice of the Churche,
R. E.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>