<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
TO THE RIGHT WORTHY, AND MY Truely honoured Favourer, Sir PETER TEMPLE, Knight and Baronet.</title>
           <author>B., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100297_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22598</idno>
           <idno type="STC">905</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100297</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
TO THE RIGHT WORTHY, AND MY Truely honoured Favourer, Sir PETER TEMPLE, Knight and Baronet.</title>
                 <author>B., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Love and valour: celebrated in the person of the author, by the name of Adraste. Or, the divers affections of Minerva. One part of the unfained story of the true Lisander and Caliste. Translated out of the French by W.B</title>
                 <author>Audiguier, Vital d'</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Slater (Slaughter), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 226, that is 224 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <pb facs="3"/>
TO THE RIGHT WORTHY, AND MY Truely honoured Favourer, Sir PETER TEMPLE, Knight and Baronet.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owsoever I have received more encouragement from your selfe alone, then all men living besides, had not my Author deemed his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour worthy the survey of so great a Prince, I should not have entitled you to my worthlesse labours in the conversion; since the difference between his originall, drawn by a free and art commanding hand, and my rough Copy being the first essay of my abilities
<pb facs="4"/>
in this nature, may be more then the distance between your condition and a Princes. In supplyance of which defect, being unable to adde any thing but the bare figure of my devotion to serve you, it were but ill rhetoricke, and worse arithmeticke in me through many words multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying ciphers, by ciphers to blot my paper with infinite nothings. Yet gracious Sir, I perswade me that I see, though I have not delivered in the booke, many lines and draughts resembling the patheticke facility and gentlenesse of our best writers: which draughts being but bare disse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and curious anatomies of humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is impossible to be over-tedious, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent therein. But I flourish as if I would say something, where I am in truth a sceptique igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and doubting all things, but my own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and the strength of those affections borne your service,</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
      <signed>by your vertues honourer,
W. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>