<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100521_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16485</idno>
           <idno type="STC">34</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100521</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition vpon the prophet Ionah : Contained in certaine sermons, preached in S. Maries church in Oxford. By George Abbot professor of diuinitie, and maister of Vniuersitie Colledge</title>
                 <author>Abbot, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Garbrand (Harkes), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 638, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="636" facs="324"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN Reader, hauing learned this lesson, that a Minister of the Gospell is to do good, in and to the Church of Christ, so farre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth as possibly he may while he liueth in this world; I do not refuse to publish to the view of many men these small labours of mine, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learned or vnlearned may reape some profite from them. And if in the perusing of them, thou do find either directly or by cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance, that mention is made of some things, which were done or suffered now some yeares past; vnderstand it for a truth, that I first aduentured on the handling of this Prophecie in the yeare <hi>1594,</hi> and brought it to an end in <hi>99.</hi> For it is the manner of our Vniuersitie, that no one man doth continually keepe and reade our English Lectures or Sermons, as it is in diuerse other charges in this Realme; but in as much as there be among vs many, who are furnished with great gifts and graces from aboue, our exercises here are supplied by sundry persons; who when they haue perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med any of these solemne ones, are not immediatly called againe, but haue a conuenient space left to employ their talent, in other Churches of the citie, or countrie adioyning, or in their priuate Colledges, or where else it pleaseth God to offer them oportunitie. But among other the most holy, religious, and fruitfull exercises in our assembly, there is none in my opinion more honorable to the Almightie, nor more profitable to our brethren among vs, then those Lectures, which with solemnitie are kept both winter and sommer on the thursday mornings early; where sometimes before day-light, the praises of God are by preaching sounded out in the great congregation. For there euen on the working dayes, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our youth which are sent hither for good education from most places of this land, are trained vp in the knowledge of godlinesse, which maketh them afterward the more deuoutly able, to do ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and performe a dutie in Church and common-wealth: but
<pb n="637" facs="324"/>
the elder and strongest sort, by fresh and various remembrances are quickened to go forward in the way of righteousnesse, the weak are comforted, the straying are recalled, the obstinate are conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and all kinds of men which will repaire thither are duly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed. It were great pittie therefore, but that the reuerend &amp; godly Vice-chauncellers, and chiefe gouernours of this body, shold from time to time take faithfull care, to perpetuate this holy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and businesse, by stirring vp the spirits of many of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren with alacritie and chearefulnesse to continue this free-will offering to the Lord, which he himselfe certainly will requite, and alreadie in his mercie hath not left vnrewarded in many of them who haue taken paines this way. There is no man that in the end loseth, but gaineth by the true seruice of our Almightie maker. In the turnes of this voluntarie Lecture, haue the most part of these Sermons vpon Ionas bene preached: which hath bene the cause that I haue bene forced to be so long, in perfecting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>summating this worke. But yet, now that I am resolued to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it farther, I thinke it not vnfit therein to recount those things, which vpon speciall occasions of the times, had their first and most direct vse before; in as much as I haue warrant thereof by examples of holy Scripture, where there be plentifully recorded to vs matters past: and in the Sermons and Homilies of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers of the Primitiue Church, we at this day reade mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of famines, or pestilences, or warres, or vnseasonable weather, or such other like occurrents, from which great vtilitie may now be reaped; as to teach the people (for their comfort in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie, or warning in prosperitie) that God dealeth by men in this age as in former times; and the Minister, that he shold not be blind but quick-sighted, to make application to his auditorie, of such be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites or punishments, as are sensibly represented to his congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The same or the like vse we may make of hearing that good or euill, which lately before befell our selues or our brethren, that so by things which are past, as well as by the present, Gods name may be glorified, and our consciences religiously edified. As for the most part of matters handled here, be they either exhortations, or applications, or doctrines, or refutations of any opinions, Popish, or otherwise erronious, they haue their perpetuall commoditie, and
<pb n="636" facs="325"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="637" facs="325"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="638" facs="326"/>
somewhat may euermore be sucked out of them. In the reuoluing whereof if any man shall take profite, I shall be right glad, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it a blessing of God on me, that he maketh my weaknesse the meanes and instrument to build any thing, be it but little in his spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall house. The Lord direct vs aright in our knowledge and vnderstanding: the Lord guide our waies, that we may euermore walke in his feare, that passing ouer the dayes of this pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage with comfort, we may in the end dwell in ioyfull and euerlasting habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="326"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>