<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE Protestant Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100159_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19373</idno>
           <idno type="STC">580</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100159</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE Protestant Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triple cord or a treatise proving the truth of the Roman religion, by sacred scriptures taken in the literall sense : expounded by ancient fathers. interpreted by Protestant writers. With a discouery of sundry subtile sleights vsed by Protestants, for euading the forc of strongest arguments, taken from cleerest texts of the foresaid scriptures</title>
                 <author>Anderton, Lawrence</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72, 24, 33-801, 11 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div n="Protestant" type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="18"/>
   <pb facs="18"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE <hi>Protestant Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>EEING it was euer houlden as a thing most worthy of greatest prayse, for a man to excell in all, or any of the liberal Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the knowledge therof being not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to himselfe, but also to others most vsefull and commodious; much more then is he to be honoured, who shall wholly, or chiefly imploy his paines and studies in the attaining of the Science of Sciences, sacred Diuinity, true Wisdome, whose Obiect is God, and whose supreme end is the Omnipotent glory, and mans Beatitude. This Science it is, for the teaching wherof the best Maister, Christ our Lord, came into this world, according to those his blessed wordes,<note n="(1)" place="margin">
         <hi>Io.</hi> 18.37.</note>
      <hi>For this was I borne, and for this I came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, that I should giue testimony to the truth:</hi> Which truth he<note n="(2)" place="margin">
         <hi>Io.</hi> 18.20.</note>
      <hi>taught in the Synagogue, and the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mple:</hi> And<note n="(3)" place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.35.</note>
      <hi>went about all the Cityes and Townes teaching in their Synagogues, and preaching the Ghospell of the kingdome &amp;c.</hi> And not content that this prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="19"/> of the Ghospell should only be vsed by his owne person, and for his owne time, he gaue also in chiefest charge to his Apostles, and their Successors, that they should<note n="(4)" place="margin">
         <hi>Mat. 28.</hi>19.20.</note>
      <hi>Teach all Nations &amp;c. Teaching them to obserue all thinges, whatsoeuer he had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them.</hi> Now, for their encouragement, the better to performe this Charge imposed, he assureth them by his Apostle, that<note n="(5)" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.</note>
      <hi>Thus doing, they shall saue both themselues, and them that heare them.</hi> By which last words it also appeareth, that the knowledge of this Truth, this Ghospell, this Diuinity is requisite and necessary for mans Saluation.</p>
   <p>This truth and Ghospell we only learne aright by the vertue of Faith, through which we firmly as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to all such Doctrines as the prime Verity, God himselfe, doth reueale, and his holy Church doth propose vnto vs. A blessing so great, as that without it,<note n="(6)" place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.1.</note>
      <hi>It is impossible to please God,</hi> and attayne Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in being <hi>the foundation of all such thinges, as are to be hoped, or expected.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This faith as it is only gained by the free Guift of God, so is it only loste by Infidelity and Heresy, these being the opposites which destroy faith, and with which possibly she cannot subsist. And if it be most true that euery Heresy is a certaine Infidelity, and a true deniall of all faith; what shall we thinke of the Heresy of this vnfortunate Age, by which the integrity of faith is not only violated in one or other Article, or those of lesse moment and necessity (which yet by no meanes were to be tolerated, but by all Christian hartes to be detested and accursed) but generally in all as it were by an vniuersall deluge of Apostacy, euen in the pointes of greatest waight
<pb facs="19"/> concerning God, Christ, the Church, her Sacrifice and Sacramentes, Mans Iustification, Grace, Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, the Commandments, &amp; many other such lyke; All which with singular impiety are so depraued and impugned by the Sectaries of these dayes, as that their Endeauours may seeme to ayme, and to be wholly imployed, insteed of an Heresy, to introduce with g eatest boldnes, Madnes, and Malice, a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Apostacy or Atheisme from the faith of Christ.</p>
   <p>The serious Consideration, and feeling Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seration of this so great a mischiefe, I must confesse (worthy Reader) was the mayne Motiue for my vndertaking and compyling this Treatise following: for whilest I remembred, that without entyre diuine Faith, and true worship and Religion towards God, no Saluation was to be expected: and withall saw such innumerable Soules (so dearly bought by the precious Bloud and death of Christ our Lord, Soules also most deare to me in sundry other most iust res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectes) so continually to perish through the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Heresy; I could not forbeare, but after my humble Prayers, adde also my poore and vnworthy labours, which if through Gods blessing, they may proue so effectuall, as to reduce any seduced Soule to the state of Saluation, I shall thinke them all most happily vndertaken, and ioyfully sustayned, and my selfe plentifully rewarded at the holy Hand of God.</p>
   <p>Now, that my writings might proue more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, and powerfull with the Prot. Reader, whose Saluation I thirst▪ I haue purposely restrayned my selfe to that sole kind of Argument, which himselfe doth affect, and euer vrge, which is the sacred Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, or Written Word of God, to which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth
<pb facs="20"/> in all Disputes to appeale, and in all Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines to subscribe; esteeming, and making it his sole Rule, and Square, wherby to be directed in all points of faith and Religion necessary to Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uation. To this also for the present I likewise appeale, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this the subiect of my whole Discourse no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubting, but to make it appeare, and that most cleerly, that the Written Word, is our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Word, speaking and teaching our<note n="(7)" place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8.</note> Roman faith, so anciently renowmed in the whole world.</p>
   <p>And that it may be rightly obserued how diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent are the proceedings of Catholickes and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes, in the religious and sincere handling and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of this sacred Word, I desire briefly to giue a iust account, of the Method, and order which I haue prescribed to my selfe, and is generally obserued, throughout this whole Treatise.</p>
   <p>First then, seeing the true staring of the Matter in dispute, doth of it selfe often discouer the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and falshood of a bad Cause, and therfore all Heretickes do fraudulently set downe the state of the Question, changing and peruerting the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning therof, therby the better to hyde their owne Errors, &amp; to traduce their Aduersaries; I haue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in preuention herof, in the first place euer sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Controuersy aright, shewing what the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church doth teach and belieue as matter of faith, and this from her sacred Councels &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued Doctors: and what she permitteth her Schoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemen to dispute as pointes indifferent, not defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by her Decrees: for with these I fynd our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Sectaries<note n="(8)" place="margin">D. Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, White, Featley.</note> greatly to delude their Vulgar Readers, vrging these Schoole differences, as though
<pb facs="20"/> they were Differences in Articles, and Conclusions of faith, which to affirme, is a <hi>Grand Imposture,</hi> much frequented by D. Morton, who for want of better matter, storeth and stuffeth his writinges with toyes in this kind</p>
   <p>But not content with this, it is ordinary with Protestantes in their Sermons and Writings, most fowly to bely our Catholicke Cause, ascribing vnto vs infinite grosse, and most absurd opinions, which we vtterly detest and deryde: they intending by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious vntruthes to disgrace that, which with sound Argumentes they are not able to confute. I giue plentifull Examples of this bad dealing throughout this whole Booke.</p>
   <p>Hauing thus cleered our Catholicke Doctrine, I next set downe what Prot. teach concerning the point in Controuersy. In which I fynd them often at deadly wars amongst themselues, and that not for Points disputable and indifferent, but for the Chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest Articles, and Conclusions of Faith, the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe wherof is necessary to Saluation. In these their differences, I ordinarily set downe for Prot. Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, that which is most commonly taught by the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Prot. Church; or by such others, as are most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned amongst their Brethren, for their supposed Wisdome, and Learning.</p>
   <p>But in thus searching what their opinions are, I still obserue, and accordingly proue, that wherin they disagree from the Catholicke faith, therin they do agree with some Ancient Hereticke, formerly confuted, and condemned by Councels and Fathers.</p>
   <p>And not only this, but I fynd further, that they runne themselues vpon fundry grosse Errors, which
<pb facs="21"/> were not euen dreamed on by any former Heretikes, and which once admitted, would ineuitably inferre a generall Apostacy from the Christian faith. This is the Course which I generally vse for the true expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the point in Controuersy; which point thus cleered, I addresse my selfe in the nexte place to such proofes for the Catholicke cause, as the sacred Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures do plentifully affoard: from whence yet I on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly produce such textes, as being taken in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, simple, and literall signification, do speake most plainly for the Catholicke Truth. But because no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be spoken in termes so playne, but what the wit and malice of the Deuill and his Ministers will in some sorte depraue, inuenting for that end some Euasion or other, therby to weaken the force of the wordes being taken in their proper significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I do therfore also take notice of these poore shiftes, and do further shew, that they are mere fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes, faigned and taught without all ground or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of truth, wholly impertinent, often ridiculous, and euer such, as with the like liberty, any Heresy though neuer so forlorne may easily be defended, &amp; any Article of our Christian faith, though neuer so necessary, be dangerously impugned.</p>
   <p>But neither is this detorting of the wordes of Scripture from their proper meaning, the greatest iniury now adayes offered to the word of God: For Sectaries further proceed, when all other meanes faile them, most accursedly to corrupt the sacred wordes and sentences of Gods diuine word, adding wordes of their owne stamping to the holy textes, omitting, or taking away some of the sacred-words themselues, mistranslating wordes, making them to
<pb facs="21"/> speake thinges most different, and repugnant from their owne proper signification. And if all this will not serue their turne, through the euidence &amp; fulnes of Scripture condemning their Errors, then they betake themselues to that last most desperate &amp; dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Refuge, of that Atheisticall denying, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Apocryphall whole entyre Bookes of holy Writ: which impious freedome, if it might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, would shortly discharge the whole Canon of Scripture from any Scripture at all.</p>
   <p>But because it is another vsuall shifte vsed by Protestantes, to fly from the wordes to the sense, that neither they, nor we, as partiall Iudges, should giue sentence therof; I do therfore appeale for the fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of the true sense of the Scriptures to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations, and Expositions made by the Ancient Fathers, who liuing in the purest tymes of the Church, neighbouring vpon the Apostles, flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing in learning, shining in sanctity, and ignorant of our present Contentions, may in all reason be thought, &amp; accepted for Iudges most competent, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt, and impartiall. Neither do I produce these as barely affirming what themselues thought or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised, or spake in heat of disputation against their Aduersaries, but what they dogmatically taught in their Commentaries, Expositions, and Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the sacred Scriptures: or what is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, confessed, and disliked in them by Prot. as making vnanswerably for our Catholicke faith, and strongly confuting, and condemning the Prot. Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
   <p>Neither do I wholly rest in this manner of proofe, though superabundant for my Cause: But
<pb facs="22"/> I likewise in greatest surplussage adioyne herunto, the aboundant Interpretations of Scriptures made by Prot. writers, most agreable to the former made by Fathers, and wholly confirming our Catholicke faith, and therin impugning their other Brethren who oppose against it. Now, if the Textes of sacred Scriptures, taken in their proper and literall sense, and the answerable Expositions made by the holy Fathers, and sundry of the learnedst Prot. writers, do all of them conspire in making that sense of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which wholly agreeth with the doctrine and practise of the Catholicke Roman Church; I do not see what more can be required by any indifferent, &amp; vnderstanding man, for the making it to appeare cleere, as the sunne at Noone day, that the Written Word of God is that which teacheth vs our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke faith, and confuteth and condemneth such Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and heresyes as aryse against it.</p>
   <p>Lastly seeing, all this notwithstanding, Prot. do not desiste to obiect some darker passages of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture against others most plaine, and for such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed by Fathers &amp; Prot; I do therfore not forbeare to take notice of them, but withall do plainly shew, that the said textes taken in their literall sense, do nothing make against vs, and so most impertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vrged; and being explayned by other plainer pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, do strongly make against themselues who vrge them. And if not the wordes but the sense, must be regarded, then I frequently alleadge both Fathers and Prot. so expounding the same, as that their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions are full answers to what is obiected by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prot. So weakely, and not at all, is Heresy truly grounded vpon the word of God.</p>
   <pb facs="22"/>
   <p>This, Christian Reader, is the course obserued by me through this whole worke, which whether I be iudged duly to performe or no, I most willingly leaue to the dispassionate Censure of the Iudicious: who will easily herby perceiue, that Prot. pretending to fly to the Scriptures, as their only refuge, do ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in make flight to their mortall Enemy, who cutteth their throates. That which for my poore paynes at the handes of the good Reader I shall only request, is, that all former preiudicate opinion against Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Religion set apart, and all base and vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy feare of temporall losses in Honours, Estates, or Liberties couragiously shaken off, that he firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, and constantly professe that only Faith, and Religion which Gods diuine Word doth teach, the holy Fathers do confirme, and sundry of the learnedst Prot do acknowledge for true: which doing, he shall gayne that faith, without which, according to the Apostle,<note n="(9)" place="margin">
         <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6.</note>
      <hi>It is impossible to please God.</hi> Which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to S. Ambrose,<note n="(10)" place="margin">In Ps. <hi>40.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Is the firme foundation of all vertues.</hi> According to S. Chrysostome,<note n="(11)" place="margin">Ser. de fide, spe, &amp; charit.</note>
      <hi>The ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of Iustice, the head of Sanctity, the beginning of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, the ground-worke of Religion.</hi> And according to S. Austine,<note n="(12)" place="margin">Ser. de Temp. <hi>38.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>The beginning of mans saluation, without which no man can come to the fellowship of the Sonnes of God: because without it, neither in this world can any man obtayne the Grace of Iustification, nor in the world to come shall possesse lyfe Eternall</hi> A fearefull Sentence, &amp; much to be pondered by Infidels, and Heretickes, who are certainly deuoyd of this diuine Faith.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>