<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL SIR
IOHN LEVENTHORPE
Knight, and to the right-vertuous
Ladie, the Ladie IOANE
LEVENTHORPE,
his louing Wife.
(∵)</title>
           <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100586_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13996</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24307</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100586</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL SIR
IOHN LEVENTHORPE
Knight, and to the right-vertuous
Ladie, the Ladie IOANE
LEVENTHORPE,
his louing Wife.
(∵)</title>
                 <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse of death, bodily, ghostly, and eternall : nor vnfit for souldiers warring, seamen sayling, strangers trauelling, women bearing, nor any other liuing that thinkes of dying. By Thomas Tuke</title>
                 <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Norton, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 113, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL SIR
IOHN LEVENTHORPE
Knight, and to the right-vertuous
Ladie, the Ladie IOANE
LEVENTHORPE,
his louing Wife.
(∵)</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT WORSHIPFVLL, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
write, and many more doe
speake of <hi>Death:</hi> and it were
not much, if as many wrote
thereof, as could write at all.
For it is the <hi>Way,</hi> that <hi>all</hi> must walke in: and
although to all it be either very <hi>fortunate,</hi> or
very <hi>fatall,</hi> yet of the most it is forgotten, till
it seeme to seize vpon them: yea, euen we,
that speake and write about it, are sometimes
too vnmindful of it; perhaps then also, when
we speake and write vpon it. But howsoeuer
<pb facs="3"/>
wee doe forget it, it will bee sure to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
vs. It hath been wisely said, that <hi>to speake
and thinke often and seriously of hell, is a good
meane to saue the soule from hell:</hi> so I suppose
that a sad and sober thinking, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring
of <hi>bodily</hi> death, will bee a blessed helpe
to keepe the soule and bodie from <hi>eternall</hi>
death. It is strange to see the feares of many:
yet euen the fearefull sometimes shew small
feare of death, except then, when it is to bee
embraced. Others well neare with the feare
of death are brought to death. Some will not
beginne to liue, till they feele themselues
beginne to die. And how many are there,
that are a-fraid of death, and yet dare play
with the <hi>sting</hi> of death? It were no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
to handle a <hi>Snake,</hi> when her <hi>poysoning
tooth</hi> is pulled out: but to flie a <hi>Snake,</hi> and in
the meane time not to feare that, which
makes her venome, were (I wot not well)
whether more <hi>base,</hi> or <hi>foolish.</hi> I know not why
death should not be counted terrible, whiles
her venomous and <hi>killing</hi> tooth is in her head;
but that being once pulled out, why shee
should affright a man, I see no reason. For
why should he feare death, whom death
doth <hi>helpe,</hi> not hurt, and <hi>ease</hi> rather then end?
<pb facs="3"/>
Hee that dies, whiles he liues, liues whiles he
is dead: yea, and that death at last shall meet
with death it selfe. Certainly death cannot
be ill to him, that liues well: neither is that
worthie the name of death, which is made
the doore of life. Yet I finde the vertuous
sometimes appalled with her grisly lookes.
They are loth to part, that haue liued long
together: and a man can scarce without some
reluctation forsake the house, wherein he was
bred, and hath euer liued, since he liued, to
dwell in another, though a better, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.
But (me thinks) the delicacie of the place,
the affluence of all good things there, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
these the fellowship of the <hi>Saints,</hi> the
presence of that louing and beloued <hi>Sauiour,</hi>
the fruition of the <hi>All-sufficient</hi> God, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with a certaine expectation of a ioyfull
<hi>returne</hi> at last, should satisfie the <hi>departing</hi>
Soule, and settle her <hi>vnruly</hi> passions.</p>
   <p>As for you <hi>(Right Worshipfull)</hi> I doubt not
but that God, to whom you striue to liue,
hath taught you both ere now to die. I write
not these things therefore, as intending to
instruct you, but rather to shew that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie
of your loue doth liue within me, and
as one desirous by putting you in minde of
<pb facs="4"/>
those things, which ye know alreadie, that,
whiles you liue, the remembrance of them
might not die. Read them at your leysure,
and enioy them. And that God, vnder whom
they were begunne and ended, giue a blessing
to them: vnto whose sauing grace I do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
you both, beseeching him in Christ
<hi>Iesus</hi> to vouchsafe you his loue while ye liue
on earth, and to crowne you after death with
eternall life in heauen. London S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Clem.
Ann.</hi> 1612. Nouember 5. <hi>A day neuer to bee
forgotten of true English hearts.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
in the Lord,
Thomas Tuke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>