<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100410_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10309</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20594</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100410</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the sacrament of confirmation : wherein is shewed the necessitie, spirituall profit, and excellencie of this sacrament. Composed by W.R</title>
                 <author>Smith, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Pinchon (Pinson), Gerard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 134, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE READER</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I was induced to compose this short treatise of the Sacrament of Confirmatiō for two Causes: The one was to supplie the Bishop of Chalcedon his want of opportunitie suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb facs="3"/> to instruct those to whome hee ministreth this Sacrament; For the holy Councell of Trent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding Bishops, that at what times they administer this Sacrament, they should declare to the people the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and profits thereof, that thereby they may come more worthely to receiue it, and that hee hath seldome opportunitie to make any such sufficient declaration: I thought it fit to supplie the want of his Speech, by this my writing. The other was to instruct both those who had receiued this Sacrament
<pb facs="3"/> how greate a benefite they had receiued; that thereby they may bee the more grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto Almighty God, and more carefull not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the grace of God in vaine, but to make vse there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to theire greater glorie and happines; and also to let those who haue not yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, knowe, what obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they haue to receiue it, and what a greate good they want, that thereby they may doe theire best to procure it. And because I write onely to Catholicks, I proue not that either it is a Sacrament, or that it giueth grace, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printeth
<pb facs="4"/> a spirituall Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in our Soules; but suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing all these points (which the Catholicke faith teacheth vs) I onely attend to shewe the necessitie, spirituall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and excellencie of this Sacrament: and this I doe not so fully as perhaps the learned would expect, and the matter requireth, nor as perchance I could, If I had more leasure or more store of bookes, but so farre as may giue the learned occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to thinke of more, and so to profect this treatise, and as may suffice to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned to knowe theire du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="4"/> towards this Sacrament, as by diuers good treatises in our English tounge, they learne theire dutie concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Sacraments of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession and of the holy Altar: And I wish they had the like Treatises of all the other Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, that thereby they might better knowe the boū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Allmightie God, the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall riches and treasure of the Catholicke Church, and theire owne happines and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie in beeing Catholicks; Farewell the 24. of Iune 1629.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>