<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader.</title>
           <author>Stoughton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100120_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13024</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23314</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100120</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader.</title>
                 <author>Stoughton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christians sacrifice : much better then all the legall sacrifices of the Iewes; and without the which, all the said legall sacrifices of the Iewes, euen when they were in force, were not acceptable to God. Or, a logicall and theologicall exposition of the two first verses of the twelfth to the Romanes, with all the doctrine in the said two verses, plainly laid forth, and fitly applied according as these times do require the same. Wherein also besides the orthodoxall exposition of the said words, diuers other places of Scripture by the way occurring, before somewhat obscure, are so naturally interpreted, as that the iudicious reader shall thinke his paines well bestowed in vouchsafing to reade this treatise following. With the authors postscript to his children, as it were his last will and testament vnto them</title>
                 <author>Stoughton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 258 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued,</hi> I am not ignorant of two other treatises al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready published, in Title somewhat like to this of mine following: the one only translated into English, and compiled by another, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a name expressed. The other being the worke of a godly brother amongst vs, Master <hi>Thomas Cooper.</hi> Notwithstanding▪ because neither the one nor the other, either in matter or in forme doe agree with this of mine, therefore as I feare no disgrace to mine by theirs, so I wish no preiudice to theirs by mine. The godly minded reader may well make vse both of theirs and of mine. Yet this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any disgrace to either of theirs I may safely say, that hereinmine differeth from theirs, both in handling a speciall place of Scripture, and also that in the interpretation of the said Scripture, I discusse diuers points of doctrine, making such particular application of them, as the times require. Now whereas in this treatise vpon the second verse, I write some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what largely, and it may be in some mens conceite, somewhat sharpely against conformitie to this worlde I desire such as shall so thinke to consider that the more generall the fault is, as well of them that would be accounted louers of the Gospell, as of them that are open contemners and scorners thereof, therefore also it is the more dangerous, and for curing thereof requireth the more sharpe reprehensions. The bitterer any potion is, the
<pb facs="12"/> more any ointment or plaister smarteth, the more effectually for the most part such portions and ointments and plaisters doe worke in or vpon them to whom they are administred. Such also as shall so iudge of my writing I entreate further to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how sharpely the Prophets haue enveyed, and how fearefull iudgements of the Lord they haue thundred out against offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders<note place="margin">Isay. 3 13. Zeph. 1. 8.</note> in this kind. The Prophets indeed were imediatly sent and commanded of God to speake that which they spake. But why? Because the ordinarie Priests and Levites, either did not that which they should haue done, or were not regarded in doing thereof. This therefore is no iust exception against the Ministers declaming and exclaming against this sin in these dayes: neither is it any excuse at all for any so sinning. The grace of God in the Gospell doth not tolerate but agrauate such things. Notwithstanding I doe not alike condemne all persons in like sort offending: but the sin it selfe I condemne alike in all. Some infected with this disease of the fashions I grant do diligently heare the word: yea rise earely (though of great place and state) to go some miles to heare the word; and do often heare it against such fashions, and yet reforme not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues therein, what then? Shall I iudge them so to come ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to shew themselues, then for loue of the word? I dare not be so vncharitable. I know better things by some of them, and such as accompanie saluation. God openeth not the eyes of all<note place="margin">Heb. 6. 9. Mark. 8. 24.</note> to see all at once. I do not therefore so much wonder thereat, as hope and pray they may still come, that so at the last they may heare that, whereby they may be conuerted and reformed. <hi>The wordes of the wise are as goades and nailes &amp;c.</hi> The<note place="margin">Eccles. 12. 11.</note> The more therefore any are pricked with such goades, the more they will be quickened: the oftener such nailes are smitten, the deeper they will peirce. A little <hi>coale from Gods altar</hi> may<note place="margin">Isay. 6. 6.</note> grow, yea will grow to a great fire.</p>
   <p>The women indeed that in these daies are so shameles as to poule their heads, (so likewise changing their sex; and opposing themselues to the expresse word of God, are also most hopelesse. Yet if any of them shall come to the word, though nothing lesse minded then to profit by the word, they may for all that be
<pb facs="12"/> either caught by the net of the word, and conuerted; or else be so peirced with the nailes of the word, as that the same may enter as deepely into their heartes for their confusion, as the naile of <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ael the wife of Heber peirced and was stricken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iud. 4. 21. &amp;. 5. 26.</note>
      <hi>the temples of Sisera his head to his destruction.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That which afterward I haue written for the reuerence and maintainance of the Ministers of the Gospell, I haue not without griefe written, to see the great contempt and strange neglect of such Ministers, as are both in their ministrie most faithfull and laborious, and for their life and conuersation most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable. For doth not many a man of any great abilitie, and kind disposition, better respect a seruant that hath beene with him some yeeres, and faithfully also serued him during the said time, then many that would be taken great professors, doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect their Ministers, though neuer so long and painefully preaching vnto them? Do not also such persons by some pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment more bountifully reward such seruants at their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from them, then such people do reward such Ministers, euen whilst they are with them? And may not such iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God be feared against the whole land for this sinne as heeretofore haue bin executed vpon other people for the like? The same I say for that which I haue written of the itching eares of some to heare other preachers farther off dwelling, with neglect of their owne, and neerer dwellers, though they cannot iustly except any thing against them: yea I haue written the more in this behalfe, not onely because of the great discourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of such their owne and other neere dwelling Ministers, but also because somtime such itching ears vpon a light report of some stranger preaching 3 or 4 miles off on the Lordes day going to heare him, &amp; haue lost their labour, heard no Sermon at all.</p>
   <p>That notwithstanding which I haue written of hearing the next dwelling Preachers after their owne, rather then further dwellers, I doe not meane of Preachers in the same Cittie or Towne that hath diuers Churches, because in such places far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dwellers may be heard after their owne Preachers without any great labour of the hearer, and without any preiudice to
<pb facs="13"/> neerer dwellers. In such places more libertie may be vsed, then where further dwellers cannot be heard without more labour, then is fit to be taken on the Lords day.</p>
   <p>Neither also do I so condemne all hearing of further dwellers (mens owne or neere dwelling Preachers not being neglected) but that in some extraordinarie causes, and at sometimes, for comfort of afflicted consciences, or for resolution of some doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mindes in some things, men may heare some furthers dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, whom they shall vnderstand either to preach of such a text as may minister most comfort to such troubles of conscience, or to handle such points as are especially doubted of: Prouided not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding that it be no ordinarie matter, neither often but seldome.</p>
   <p>These things I haue heere promised to preuent all miscon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of any thing in this treatise by me written: and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to auoid all offence by such misconstruction. If any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing shall seeme strange, I hope that loue and iudgement shall qualifie the strangnesse thereof.</p>
   <p>Loth I am, and very loath to offend any of Gods children. But touching such as are so curious that nothing will please them: and that rather read mens workes to carpe at them then to profit by them: seeming alwaies <hi>to learne and yet</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 7.</note>
      <hi>neuer attaining sound knowledge,</hi> I care not to please their humors.</p>
   <p>Thus crauing thy praiers for my owne comfort in my old &amp; weake age, and for the blessing of God vpon this my Treatise, that many may present themselues such sacrifices to God as in this Scripture he requireth, and may also according there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto take the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re heed of all conformitie to this world, and be the more carefull to be reformed in their minds &amp;c, <hi>I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 20. 32.</note>
      <hi>thee to God, and to the word of his grace, whereby we may all be built vp,</hi> and at the last haue that inheritance <hi>which he will giue to all them which are sanctified.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine vnfaignedly in the Lord Iesus. THOMAS STOVGHTON.</signed>
      <dateline>From my poore lodging, in the poore Hospitall called S. <hi>Bartholomewes</hi> by <hi>Sandwich</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>August</hi> 21. 1622.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>