<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Ayscu, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100373_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00142</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1014</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100373</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Ayscu, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A historie contayning the vvarres, treaties, marriages, and other occurrents betweene England and Scotland : from King William the Conqueror, vntill the happy vnion of them both in our gratious King Iames. With a briefe declaration of the first inhabitants of this island: and what seuerall nations haue sithence setled them-selues therein one after an other</title>
                 <author>Ayscu, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 108, 113-396 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue here (curteous reader) vndertaken to set downe in a continued discourse, whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hath passed betweene <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland</hi> from the last Conquest, vntill the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cease of our late Soueraigne (neuer to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) the renowned <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> My trauel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth wholy in this, that I haue reduced into an entire History, a true report of things passed which al other writers before me (as farre as I know) haue deliuered onely by partes and peece-meales: whereby you may with more delight and facility conceiue and digest the coherence of the whole, and withall carrie the matter the better in memory. The chiefe &amp; principal rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son which mooued mee to take this taske vpon me, I shall not neede to speake of in this place,
<pb facs="5"/> hauing touched it before in my Epistle to the Prince, and made it so apparent throughout my whole Booke, as that the reader may decerne it running. For though the right and title of King <hi>Iames</hi> was pregnant enough, and euen palpable to euery valgar capacitie: Neuerthelesse what reason the best affected to the same had, to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cast some perill in his Maiesties accesse and pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage vnto it, the sequell hath declared. But it pleased the Lord our good God (the disposer of mens wills and affections so to worke in the heartes of our graue and most prudent <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> as by them he brought that to passe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the tearme of very few howers, which (if the aduersaries vnto our happinesse had had their wils) would not in so many monthes, nay happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yeares haue bin attained vnto. For, did they not by proclaiming his Maiesty <hi>in tempore oportuno,</hi> without delay preuent the malice of those two raging Buls (not of <hi>Bashan,</hi> but of <hi>Typical Babilō,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Reuel.</hi> 18.</note> that is to say <hi>Rome</hi>) whose pestiferous breath might otherwise haue poiso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and infected we know not how many male-contents and seditious <hi>Romanistes.</hi> Against
<pb facs="5"/> the former King <hi>Dauid</hi> alone complained,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 22.</note> but of the latter how many Kings &amp; Emperors shal we read of, that haue bin fronted and foyled, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny brought downe to their knees, others laid groueling on their faces, some thrust out of their Kingdōes, &amp; some gored euen vnto death.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 28.</note>
      <hi>But (O Lord) saue thy people &amp; giue thy bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing vnto thine inheritance. &amp;c.</hi> An other reason ayming at the same end was this. That wheras the Chronicles of both Nations containe matter of reproach and disgrace one against the other: I haue had an especiall care to carry my selfe so indifferently betweene them as I hope neither of both shall haue iust cause to take of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence therat. So as in that respect if any at all may be admitted (which none J thinke will op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne) then shall this of mine haue priueledge before all other that J know. Since wee al now: happily become Subiects vnto one most gratious Soueraigne, let vs value one the others vertues at one and the same price, and setting apart all partialitie, detraction, and vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, let vs deuide the true honour and glorie attayned on both sides indifferētly betweene vs.
<pb facs="6"/> Are we not all (for the most part) the broode and off-spring of the same parents, the auntient <hi>English Saxons?</hi> what preheminence then shall wee giue to the one Nation aboue the other? Admit the <hi>Englishmen</hi> haue beene victorious in more battailes, haue entred more often and passed further in Hostile manner into the others Countries and dominions, and haue gotten grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter booties both by Land and Sea: what then? is not this our Nation farre more populous and plentifull of all store of prouision and comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments pertayning to warre? Whereof then shall wee boast? These vauntes are therefore full of vanitie: Let vs now contende who shall giue more sincere and acceptable praise and thankes to the Almighty, who in loue to both hath now at length made vs of two discording Nations one peaceable people vnder one Prince, not by conquest (the mother of confusion) but by an happy seede and off-spring proceeding from the successe of marriage, his holy ordinance: Whereby the memory of all fore-passed displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures and vnkindnesse is buried in perpetual ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuion. Many haue longed &amp; laboured to worke
<pb facs="6"/> this blessed Vnion. How many lost their liues in the ouer vehement pursute of the intended mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage betweene King <hi>Edward</hi> the sixt, and <hi>Mary</hi> the late Queene of <hi>Scottes:</hi> the successe whereof, if it had beene effected, was much to be doubted. But the Eternall <hi>God</hi> in his wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome reserued this notable worke to a more fit season, for the good especially of his Church, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing now not onely vnited vs vnder the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and ciuill gouernment of a terrestriall Monarchy, but also in a sincere obedience and right seruice of himselfe vnder the spirituall raigne of his eternall Sonne our Lord <hi>Iesus Christ,</hi> the Almighty Monarch ouer Heauen and Earth. What Nation now in the whole world hath generally intertayned and submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it selfe to the obedience of the written word (deliuered of more auncient time by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of <hi>God,</hi> and lasty by the Sonne of <hi>God</hi> him-selfe and his Apostles) but this our happy Island? These holy bookes we receiue for the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infallible Oracles of <hi>God,</hi> what is more (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Saluation) we reiect as Superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Derogatory to the euerlasting word of <hi>God:</hi> What is lesse wee hold ouer weake
<pb facs="7"/> and Imperfect: let <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Potentate,</hi> the whole power of <hi>Antichrist</hi> doe their worst, the Lord by this Vnion hath now established that peace to his Church within this Island, that it shal be a sanctuary to all the true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors of his name, euen (I doubt not) to the ende of the world. To whom there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bee giuen all honour and praise for euer and euer. And let all true subiects to King Iames our dread Soueraigne say there-to. <hi>Amen. Cotham in Lincolnshiere 24. Martii. 1606.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thy louing friend</hi> Edward Ayscu.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>