<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY MOST HONOVR'D FRIEND William Brouncker Es∣quier, This.</title>
           <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100999_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13264</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23563</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100999</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY MOST HONOVR'D FRIEND William Brouncker Es∣quier, This.</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Five sermons : upon severall occasions preach'd at Pauls Crosse, and at Saint Maries, in Oxford. By Humphry Sydenham, Mr. of Arts, and fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Sydenham, Humphrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Parker, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 43, 5, 38, 4, 35, 9, 26, 4, 26 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="29"/>
   <pb facs="29"/>
   <head>TO MY MOST HONOVR'D FRIEND <hi>William Brouncker</hi> Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier, This.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Sir:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here I owe a iust ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and would pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish it, I lesse feare the censure of vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, than of vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse; you know the age is both tart, and nimble, in her Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrase on those which would be <hi>Men in Print;</hi> I haue found it; yet will rather hazard the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of a weake man, than an vngratefull: Howeuer, I desire not so much to expose my <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi>
      <pb facs="30"/> to the world, as my <hi>loyaltie,</hi> that others might take notice how much you haue beene mine in your cherishing of <hi>those,</hi> and how I am euer yours in my expressions of <hi>this.</hi> He that doth but <hi>tacitely</hi> acknowledge the bounties of a <hi>noble</hi> friend, in a manner buries them, when he that proclaimes them, hath in a part requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; he hath repayed his honour, and therefore him, and so hath satisfied, though not restored. If this publike thankfulnesse of mine, for those daily fauours, shall meet with so mercifull an interpretation of yours, I esteeme not any rigid one of the times; I cannot gloze with them, nor you, yet shall endeuour to be reputed one of those who vnfeinedly honours you, and will doe, whilst I weare the name, and title of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your euer friend, and seruant HVM: SYDENHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>