<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface of the author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100621_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21448</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7754</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100621</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface of the author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An humble motion vvith submission vnto the right Honorable LL. of Hir Maiesties Priuie Counsell : VVherein is laid open to be considered, how necessarie it were for the good of this lande, and the Queenes Majesties safety, that ecclesiasticall discipline were reformed after the worde of God: and how easily there might be provision for a learned ministery</title>
                 <author>Penry, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>111, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The preface of the author.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere it not (gentle reader) that the truth of the cause, &amp; the want in the practise, had a long time called vnto me, in reading of Gods book, and by experience of former time, drawing out before me, in the dayly knowledge of my conscience, the manifold necessitye of Christs discipline: I would not haue aduentured, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mine own wants, to put pen to the paper in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of so great waight. But knowing that by this my motion, ther might be occasion to the learned &amp; wise, to think vpon very good things for the benefite of this realme, &amp; (if need be) to set forth more deepe &amp; setled demonstration, with far more exceding excellency: &amp; for that I see the wiles of Sathan, by works of disgrace to hinder the good of my country: I thought it my duty to our high God, to his holy church, the Queens most excellent Ma<seg rend="sup">tie</seg>, &amp; my natiue cuntrie, by such meanes as these troublesome times would giue me leaue, vnto my louing mother that bare me, &amp; my tender nurse y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> fedeth me, those good &amp; honest fruites wherwith God hath vouchsaued me for hir vse: beseeching al my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing cuntrimen, charitably, soberly &amp; wisely to think &amp; with sanctified affections to deale in these matters: that the hand of our God may bee with vs, to giue vs this honor, that at the length his cause may haue fauor and preuaile to the profit &amp; ioy of vs &amp; our posteritie. And I desire no other good wil of thee (gentle reader) whosoeuer thou be, in the christian accepting of this worke, than my very soule, in doing hereof, did with great care &amp; godly loue seeke the prosperous estate of this land, &amp; the flourishing of Gods church: for whose peace let vs pray night and day.</p>
   <p>Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>