<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface of thys boke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100594_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02599</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1273.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100594</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface of thys boke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first two parts of the Actes, or vnchast examples of the Englysh votaryes : gathered out of their owne legenades and chronycles by Iohan Bale, and dedycated to our most redoubted soueraigne kynge Edward the syxte</title>
                 <author>Bale, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 <publisher>Bale, John, Bishop.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, cxx, 4 leaves, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="91"/>
   <pb n="ij" facs="91"/>
   <head>The Preface of thys boke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or so much as Rome hath bene so syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefull a synke and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicyouse puddell, as hath all the worlde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by the sodome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouse vowe of their symulate chastyte, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary I thynke it in thys preface of the seconde part of my Englysh votaryes,<note place="margin">ij. part.</note> to shewe what foundacyon it hath had in the same. Xenophon sayth in hys boke of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, that Rhoma is the name of a dogge, &amp; Iohan Textor affirmeth the same both in hys Epithetes &amp; Officines. A dogge in the scripture is iudged a beast most vyle,<note place="margin">A dogge</note> hys pryce beyng all one wyth the rewarde or wages of an whore for her whoredome. Thou shalt (sayth the lord to Moses) ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brynge the hyre of an whore, nor the pryce of a dogge into the house of God in no maner of vowe, for both of them are abhominacyon vnto the Lorde thy God,<note place="margin">False teachers</note> Deuter. xxiij. They in the scriptures of the sacred Bible, are compared vnto dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whych both professe and teache the verite of God vnpurely, snarynge the sym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple sowles wyth the vnprofytable trady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons of men synnefull. Dogges are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentyll barkers, cruell byters, lascyuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouse lechours, gredy deuoure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, and insa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyable
<pb facs="92"/>
rauenours, much delyghtynge in bloude. The malycyouse and couetouse Romanes,<note place="margin">Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> wyth those vnpure Apostles, whych they from tyme to tyme haue sent vnto thys our nacyon, hath most apertly shewed themselues to be those vyle dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and swyne, whom Christ admonished vs to be ware of. Mathew. vij.</p>
   <p>¶ In the Bible text, S. Hierome sayth, that Roma was the wyfe of Nahor Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams brother.<note place="margin">Nahor.</note> Gene. xxij. Whose chyldren were afterward, obseruers of the Plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and so bycame Idolaters, after the mynde of Philo and other olde wryters. Cechim the sonne of Iauan,<note place="margin">Cechim.</note> Genesis. x. otherwyse called Italus, had a doughter named Roma, as testyfyeth Berosus the Chaldean, Fabius Pictor, &amp; Caius Sem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pronius, whom he constitute quene of the Aborygenes or people of an vnknowne be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynnynge. Whych quene first buylded the great cytie so named, Whom after longe tracte of tyme Romulus most gorgyously fynyshed.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Romulus.</hi>
      </note> Thys mencyoneth also <hi>Paulus Constantinus, Christianus Massaeus,</hi> and <hi>Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Functius</hi> in their Chronolagies, besydes that <hi>Ioannes Annius</hi> ded therin afore them. Now lete vs consydre how lady Lecherie the virgynall Goddesse of the Sodomyti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Papistes, hath compassed in, thys great cytie on euery syde with her fleshly fylthynesse. And fyrst let vs begynne with
<pb n="iij" facs="92"/>
Romulus and Remus, the first setters vp or aduauncers therof. These. ij. bloudy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne had an whore to their mother, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Rhea ilia,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ilia Rhea</hi>
      </note> whych beynge a professed nonne to Venus, committed whoredome both wayes, that is to saye, both in sowle and in bodye. For vndre the vowe of chas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyte she serued the ydolles, as the maner was that tyme, and so dallyed besydes in the darke, as was well perceyued by her game.</p>
   <p>¶After the myndes of Virgil, Ouide, and such other fabulouse Poetes, these. ij. cruell captaynes Romulus and Remus, receyued their first nurryshment of a she wolffe whom they sucked, in sygnyfyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the wonderfull tyranny whych shuld folowe in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> great cytie Rome, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they were the fyrst amplyfyers. Other authours report, that they were first nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of an harlot called <hi>Lupa,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lupa.</hi>
      </note> not farre frō the floude of Tyber, where as the Romish Pope holdeth now hys palace, of whome all brothel houses, stewes, or places where suche fylthynesse is wrought, haue their names, and are called to thys houre <hi>Lupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lupana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi>
      </note> Romulus thus preserued by a thefe called <hi>Paustulus,</hi> nurryshed by a wolfe, and brought vp by an whore, gyuē also of him selfe to outragyouse lecherie, couetyse, and ambycyon, bycame suche a traytour to his owne stocke, as in the ende most cruelly
<pb facs="93"/>
slewe hys naturall brother Remus, to establysh hys great buylded cytie in the wyckednesse of cursed Cain. Marke for thys storye Titus Liuius, Plutarchus, Bedas, and Iohan Boccatius. Chloris otherwyse called Flora,<note place="margin">Chloris.</note> a most notable harlot, obtaynynge infynyte ryches by her execrable whoredome, made Rome her heyer and the only inheritour of her fylthy possessyons, execrated of God, Deuter. xxiij. For the whych the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes admytted her for a great Goddesse, and dedycated vnto her ones in the yeare in Apryle, certayne feastes, called <hi>Flora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia sacra.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Floralia.</hi>
      </note> Thys hath <hi>Marcus Cicero,</hi> whych calleth her the mother of the Romanes, so hath <hi>Aulus Gellius,</hi> and Iohan Textor.</p>
   <p>¶Of these autoryte amonge these Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes were there many, both consuls and senatours, whych were named by thys vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comly worde <hi>Spurius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Spurij.</note> signifyēge a bastard, as is to be seane in the chronycles of <hi>Euse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius,</hi> and <hi>Paulus Constantinus,</hi> by <hi>Spurius Ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginius, Spurius Tarpeius, Spurius Carbilius, Spurius Posthumus, Spurius Scruilius, Spurius Largus, Spurius Cassius, Spurius Nautius, Spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Medullinus, Spurius Vectius, Spurius Furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Spurius Herminius, Spurius Paulus, Spurius Oppius, Spurius Crassus,</hi> &amp; a great sort more. By thys shuld it seme that vnchast liuing was not only vnpōnyshed: but also aduaū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced to great honoure amōg the Romanes.
<pb n="iiij" facs="93"/>
      <hi>Priapus</hi> called in the Byble,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Priapus</hi>
      </note> Miplezeth, iij. Reg. xv. and. ij. Parasip. xv. was suche a disformed chylde of Venus, and most execrable ydoll of the Cananytes, as had neuer the lyke (for in hys groues the bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of that lande, both wrought theyr fylthynesse, and also taught the fowle fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the same) hys storye is farre to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely to be rehearced. Yet was he so dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed of the Romanes, that he both became the God of theyr gardenes,<note place="margin">A God.</note> and had hys feastfull dayes euery yeare wyth solemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte obserued, a garlande of floures sett vpon hys heade, and an he asse alwayes offered in sacryfyce to hym. <hi>Ouidius primo libro fastorum, Textor, Althamerus, ac Cibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</hi> Non other were admitted in those dayes by the hygh senate of the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">Romysh goodes.</note> neyther yet by commaundement and custome worshypped, but suche lecherouse monsters as these were, of whom they had great nombre.</p>
   <p>¶Resort we now to the Empyre of thys Rome, after the ouerthrowe of the other thre generall monarchyes of the worlde, of the Assyreanes, Perseanes, and Grekes, and se what enteraunce and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse ladye lecherie had therin. With Cleopatra the quene of Aegipt, whych was a woman (as testifyeth <hi>Egesyppus</hi>) of a most corrupt lyfe, <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prour,<note place="margin">Iulius</note> had very longe occupyēge without
<pb facs="94"/>
all honestie. Loke Bedas <hi>de temporum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione. Iac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bus Bergomas,</hi> and other lyke au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours. Of <hi>Nero Domicius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Nero.</hi>
      </note> whose fleshely appetyte coulde not with women be fully satisfyed, the doynges were to execrable to be here rehear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed. As <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Aurelius.</hi>
      </note> for the debylyte of nature, coulde no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar folowe in that fylthye course of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, whych he had contynued in from hys youth, he caused his owne preuye par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to be cut awaye, and so dedicate hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe to Venus, takynge vpon hym from thens fourth the name and offyce of a wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man, to proue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t vncomely occupyenge in an other prodygyouse kynde. <hi>Freculphus</hi> hath thys in the first chaptre of hys secōde Tome, so hath <hi>Ado Viennensis</hi> with others more.<note place="margin">Clergy.</note> What acceptacy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n and fauer thys most deuylysh example hath obtayned in our Romysh spirytualte, geldynge excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the sequele of thys boke shall declare. Bede also reporteth in his former treatyse, <hi>de temporum ratione,</hi> that Constantius the Emperour begate greate Cōstantine here in Englande,<note place="margin">Constan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinus.</note> of Elene hys concubyne. Whych Constantine, as a great nombre of Romysh authours testyfyeth, was the first that buylded Christen temples at Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e,<note place="margin">Tēples.</note> &amp; that fournyshed the clergy ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e wyth such possessyons and body ease, as in processe brought them into all kyndes of wantonnesse in the fleshe.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="v" facs="94"/>¶In contynuaunce of yeares, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mysh Emprour became the elder sonne of Antichrist by professyon and othe,<note place="margin">ij. sōnes.</note> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the patrymony of S. Peter, as they call their theuysh possessyons, and so to maynteyne them in all ydelnesse, pryde, &amp; lecherie. The Frenche kynge also on the other syde, became hys yongar sonne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge sworne alwayes at hys coronacyon, with fyre and with swerde to support the same. Of our Englysh kynges I speake not, whych neuerthelesse were hys adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue chyldren from the dayes of kynge Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheede y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great, to the myddle age of kyng Henry the. viij. The Emprour after that,<note place="margin">Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</note> was appoynted by offyce to holde the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes styroppe whyls he leaped on hys mule, and the Frenche kyng to holde hys brydell and to wayte vpon hys Ienet of Spayne <hi>Ex Christophoro Marcello in ritibus Romanae Ecclesiae.</hi>
      <note place="margin">French kynge.</note> Tedyouse were it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare here the whole cyrcumstaunce, how lecherie reigned in this seconde sonne also. As how <hi>Childericus</hi> the Frenche kyng,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Childeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</hi>
      </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng expuls<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d for hys vnsacyable aduou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye, begate <hi>Clodoucus</hi> of an whore whych was an other mannys wyfe, of whom des<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cended (as they report) all their Christened kynges. Loke <hi>Gaguinus, Iohan Liectenber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> and <hi>Franciscus Bonadus</hi> in Anacepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leosi. Angisus the sonne of Arnolde by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopp of Metis,<note place="margin">Angisus</note> vsurpynge the hygh ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardshyp
<pb facs="95"/>
of Fraunce, at layser made the kynge to go pyke a salett, &amp; defeated hym of hys crowne by helpe of the prestes, as wytnessyth Abbas Vespergensis, <hi>Trite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius in compendio,</hi> and <hi>Ioannes Nauclerus.</hi> The kynges by that meanes (sayth <hi>Otho Phrisingensis</hi>) became very idyotes, <hi>Pipinus</hi> of a bastarde stocke in Alpaida the harlot,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Pipinus.</hi>
      </note> admytted by Pope Zachary to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> crowne, as testyfyeth <hi>Robertus Goulet in compendio sexaetation mundi.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>¶Necessary is it, that sumwhat be sayd here of their chast relygyon also. In Rome were and are yet certen temples,<note place="margin">Tēples.</note> into whō neyther honest matrone nor yet chast vyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyne were suffered to entre, what was permytted to commen whores, oppressers of the people, and Sodomytysh prestes in that behalfe, I thynke all the worlde kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth at thys daye. Thys madde supersty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon (sayth <hi>Iacobus Zieglerus in sua Syria</hi>) had her fyrst orygynall in the mounte of Olympus within the yle of Cypres,<note place="margin">Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus.</note> wher as a solempne temple was dedycate to Venus, into whom no woman was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to entre, and passed from thens to the Romanes, beynge there admytted for a most hygh relygyon. Neuerthelesse the commen whores had there allowed them for theyr lascyuyouse occupyenge,<note place="margin">Whores</note> most fayre mansyons in a strete called Suburrs, as both <hi>Martialis and Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus</hi>
      <pb n="vi" facs="95"/>
hath vttered. Neyther hath any mannys doctryne, sens the worldes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge, bene more hyghly accepted of the Romanes and theyr clergye, than the crafty and darke learnynge of bawdy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristotle,<note place="margin">Aristotle</note> whych not only besydes hys Sodometry kept a most fylthy whore, called Hermia, but also after her deathe, ded sacryfyce vnto her as to a great God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and made hymnes in her prayse. Thys sheweth Origene and Iohan Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in hys offycynes. Both Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus and hys whore Selenes,<note place="margin">Simon Magus</note> whych at Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>us a cytie of Phoenices had mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned the brothell howse or stues, were admytted of the Romanes for their exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable sorceryes, to be worshypped for Goddes wyth yearely sacryfyces. Loke Iustinus, Irenaeus, and <hi>Eusebius Caesarien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis,</hi> all auncyent writers.</p>
   <p>☞ In Englande here sumtyme, myght no byshop ryde,<note place="margin">Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes.</note> but vpon a mare, as testyfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Bedas li. ij. ca. xiij. Cestriēsis, li. v. ca. xij.</hi> &amp; Robbert Fabiane, Pa. v. ca. cxxx. Which holy obseruacyon they had from Rome, &amp; it is not without mystery of theyr bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerysh beastlynesse. The great aduou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer Pope Sergius,<note place="margin">Sergius</note> after certen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelacyons and myracles of the deuyll, broughte fourth a great chyste full of dead mennys bones, and caused the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple both to kysse them and to worshypp
<pb facs="96"/>
them in the heade church of Rome, to dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the whoredome there. Thys wytnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syth first Bedas <hi>de temporum ratione,</hi> and than both <hi>Platina</hi> and <hi>Petrus Equilinus.</hi> All these vncomely hystoryes consydered, Rome with her vnchast vowes and vota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes,<note place="margin">Rome.</note> is that blasphemouse Babylon, Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal. xvo. &amp; that Sodome and Aegypt, Apo. xi. whom all the scriptures detesteth. Her cytezens are they, whom God hath gyuen vp into most prodygyouse lustes of vnclennesse, for changynge hys truthe to a lye. For they vndre the professyon of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styte, leauyng the naturall vse of women (sayth S. Paule) haue brent in their owne lustes one to an other,<note place="margin">Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytes.</note> that man wyth mā, that is to saye, monke wyth monke, nonne with nonne, fryre with fryre, &amp; prest with prest, wrought fylthynesse. Roma. i. besy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that they ded with boyes bitches and apes with other beastes, yea, the holye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers of thē. If ye spell Roma backwarde,<note place="margin">Roma.</note> ye shall fynde it loue in thys prodygyouse kynde, for it is preposterus <hi>amor,</hi> a loue out of order or a loue agaynst kynde. I shame no more to tell thys to the Popes remnaūt here in England, than they shame to blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme marryage whych is Gods holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stytucyon,<note place="margin">Papis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> and to playe styll the whorema<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sters &amp; Sodomytes in euery corner. The eternall God ones clerely delyuer thys Christē laude frō that monstruouse genera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>