<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100099_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12709</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23026</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100099</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mystery of godlinesse : a generall discourse of the reason that is in Christian religion. By William Sparke divinity reader at Magd: Coll: in Oxford, and parson of Blechly in B [uck] ingham-shire</title>
                 <author>Sparke, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lichfield, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Webb, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 78, 2, 78 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>TRVTH proues it selfe, and disproues error. Which if it might bee fully, and fairely cleared in the great <hi>mystery</hi> of revealed <hi>grace,</hi> would soone put to silence the endlesse <hi>controuersies</hi> of religion, with all honest hearts. Wherein many haue at all times <hi>langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed away,</hi> &amp; which being now growne from <hi>words</hi> to <hi>blowes</hi> haue wasted the Churches, and <hi>shaken the faith</hi> of the most, insomuch that if Christ should now come
<note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Luke</hi> 18.8.</note>
      <hi>should hee finde faith on the earth, when
<note n="b" place="margin">
            <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.12.</note> the loue of so many is waxen cold?</hi> Religion hath beene so long <hi>disputed</hi> that now it may be <hi>questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> whether there be any or no, most men see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to bee resolued according to that of <hi>Nigidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in <hi>A Gellius, Religentem esse oportet,
<note n="c" place="margin">Noct. Attic. l. 4. c. 9.</note> religiosum nefas.</hi> Whose <hi>practise</hi> is either vanished into an <hi>empty speculation,</hi> or meerely pretended vnder an <hi>idle profession.</hi> Was ever chaste Virgin, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron so shamefully handled by the most debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed ruffians, as <hi>sacred trueth</hi> hath been by her loue making paramours whilst every faction ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her to themselues, they haue torne her peece-meale amongst them? That we neede not serue her now, as once the Levite did his concubine,
<note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Iudg.</hi> 19.29.</note>
      <hi>to cut her in peeces, and to send her into all the coasts of Israel.</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>Every tribe hath a <hi>part,</hi> and that they make much of, (more then of the <hi>whole</hi>) which best serues their owne turnes. How infinitely is the pretending <hi>head</hi> swolne bigger then the whole body, being long since fallen from it? Never was any Saints <hi>relique,</hi> so improved, and <hi>vbiquitated.</hi> How vast are the <hi>secular armes</hi> growne, being cemented to that monstrous head, without neck, or shoulders? A <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique head</hi> with <hi>Catholique armes.</hi> How farre are the <hi>legges</hi> divaricated beyond the stride of any <hi>Colossus,</hi> as if they would never come together againe, to walke one and the same way? How is the body pined the while, and vtterly wasted away, whilst every part stands apart, as in the
<note n="f" place="margin">Menen. Agrip. Liv. l. 2.</note>
      <hi>Apologue,</hi> refusing to labour or take care for the whole? Is not this the trueth? <hi>Thus hath shee beene vsed,</hi> whose life is Christ, whose body is the Church, <hi>in the house of hir friendes.</hi> They haue peirced my hands and my feete, yea my head, and my side, they may tell all my bones, there is no whole part in mee. And they who should haue taken downe her tortured body, imbalmed, and wrapped it vp in fine linnen, vntill it rose againe, haue playd the curious <hi>Anatomists,</hi> and <hi>dissected</hi> every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, with so many subtile <hi>quaeries</hi> and <hi>disputes</hi> that it is almost as hard to finde the trueth in their bookes, as in the others liues. Which could we see as faire as she is in her <hi>iust proportion,</hi> and <hi>comely feature,</hi> such is her <hi>grace</hi> that shee would even ravish our soules with vnsatiable
<pb facs="5"/>loue, and delight, and would make vs all <hi>of one minde,</hi> minding <hi>that one thing vvhich is necessary.</hi> There haue not wanted skilfull handes I confesse, to gather vp, and put together her dismembred <hi>limbs,</hi> to adorne and set her out in her <hi>liuely beauty,</hi> and I thinke many of them had the Spirit of God to reviue her againe, and to quicken her. Since shee hath brought forth many children vnto God. And now what more? No more, but the same a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, in an other manner, if by any meanes this <hi>vvayvvard age</hi> not pleased with varieties, may bee perswaded
<note n="g" place="margin">2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.10.</note>
      <hi>to receiue the loue of the truth that vvee may be saued. Likenesse</hi> begets <hi>liking,</hi> and <hi>lookes</hi> beget <hi>loue.</hi> I haue therefore indeavoured to present vnto <hi>rationall</hi> men a view of the <hi>reason</hi> that is in Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion. The reason I say, not <hi>of it,</hi> for it is of <hi>faith,</hi> which hath no <hi>vvorth</hi> if the truth bee <hi>obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> but the reason that <hi>is in it,</hi> how it is <hi>thus</hi> in the <hi>Analogie</hi> and <hi>Symmetrie</hi> of the whole, and euery part, not why euery particular is <hi>so</hi> or <hi>so.</hi> which being revealed from God, may bee <hi>apprehended</hi> by <hi>faith,</hi> can not be <hi>comprehended</hi> by any <hi>vvit</hi> of man. Suffice it vs who proceed in our knowledge vpon certaine <hi>principles,</hi> by <hi>comparing</hi> their issues, that we finde all things <hi>ansvverable</hi> to what we haue <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,</hi> and our <hi>faith</hi> in nothing deceiued, or <hi>deluded.</hi> My principall aime in this ensuing discourse, is to giue the Christian Reader a <hi>Synopsis</hi> or full view at once of our religion in the <hi>vvhole contexture</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for his better resolution. Which lest I should obscure, or confound by <hi>incident discourses,</hi> I haue
<pb facs="6"/>beene forced to passe (it may be too <hi>cursorily</hi>) tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough most particulars, which would require so many, and far larger <hi>tracts</hi> then this little <hi>model</hi> of the <hi>vvhole.</hi> And because I seeke not herein to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade or convince <hi>Infidels</hi> (which seemes to bee the <hi>scope</hi> of
<note n="h" place="margin">Iustin. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. Tertul. <hi>in their Apologies.</hi> Arnob. Aug. de Civit. Dei. Morn. Viues. Raimundus de Sabunde.</note> others, who haue written of this <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>) but to <hi>resolue,</hi> and confirme our selues in the <hi>present truth</hi> (with whom it were a folly not to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute <hi>ex praecognitis &amp; concessis</hi>) I haue laide the foundation of this little Fabricke, in the receiued principles of Religion. And lastly, that I may not build <hi>heterogeneous stuffe</hi> thereon,
<note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12.</note>
      <hi>wood, hay, stubble; but rather, gold, siluer, pretious stones,</hi> I haue vsed, so much as might be, the very wordes and phrases of Scripture, not onely for <hi>proofe,</hi> but for <hi>expression,</hi> which being the Word of GOD, can best speake his owne <hi>meaning,</hi> howsoeuer to some it may make the <hi>stile</hi> seeme not so <hi>aequable</hi> and pleasing. The Word of God is it not
<note n="k" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, the <hi>rationall milke</hi> of our reasonable soules, whereby they are nourished to eternall life? And our faith hath such force of <hi>reason</hi> thereby, that it is
<note n="l" place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, the <hi>cleare euidence,</hi> and most <hi>evicting argument</hi> of things not seene, most sublime &amp; abstruse. And it is able to convince and perswade
<note n="m" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.23. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>vnbeleeuers,</hi> neuer so <hi>vnlearned,</hi> and
<note n="n" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor,</hi> 10.5.</note>
      <hi>to cast downe all contrary rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonings</hi> of the most subtile adversaries, <hi>that exalt themselues against the knowledge of God, bringing into captivity euery thought to the obedience of Christ.</hi> The
<note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</note>
      <hi>service</hi> of God thereby prescribed vnto vs, is it not <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, a <hi>reasonable seruice</hi> to all that are not
<pb facs="6"/>
      <note n="p" place="margin">2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 3.2.</note>
      <hi>vnreasonable</hi> and wicked men? To whom how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer they take it, wee must and can giue
<note n="q" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</note> a <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the hope that is in vs.</hi> The <hi>Lineaments</hi> whereof I haue indeavoured to draw, and <hi>shadow</hi> out in a new, but I hope not vnnaturall, <hi>method,</hi> which bee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing done, seemes to mee rather a bare <hi>skeleton,</hi> then any compleat <hi>systeme</hi> of that solide body, which I tooke in hand. Yet it sufficeth mee, if as in
<note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.7.8.9</note>
      <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiels</hi> vision, in the valley of dead bones, <hi>the bones become together, bone to its bone. For the sinewes and the flesh shall come vpon them, and the skinne shall couer them about, when the breath of GOD shall come from the foure vvindes, and blovv vpon them, and they shall liue.</hi> Howsoeuer, I am willing to bee <hi>deliuered</hi> of this meditation as it is, after a longer, and more painefull <hi>travell,</hi> by <hi>fitts,</hi> then such an imperfect <hi>embrio,</hi> and <hi>vnshapen birth</hi> may seeme worthy of. And by his helpe
<note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.5.</note>
      <hi>vvithout vvhom vve can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> I may heereafter <hi>polish</hi> &amp; <hi>perfect</hi> what I haue now <hi>conceiued,</hi> not altogether, I hope, without his <hi>Spirit.</hi> When I shall haue better discerned thereof <hi>at a distance,</hi> and may happely haue gained some farther or clearer <hi>discouery</hi> by <hi>information,</hi> or <hi>obtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation</hi> of others. For although I haue no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to expect an <hi>adversary</hi> herein, hauing not willingly irritated, or <hi>provoked</hi> any, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>trueth</hi> many times <hi>findes foes, where it makes none,</hi> if any shall trouble themselues to quarrell this little peece, what shall be justly found amisse, I shall most willingly amend, easily neglecting
<pb facs="7"/>what shall bee petulantly carped, and submitting my selfe in all things to my blessed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this faithfull Church of <hi>CHRIST IESVS.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note n="†" place="margin">Tertul.</note>
      <hi>Difficilium facilis est venia.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>