<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Aduertisement.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100094_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16632</idno>
           <idno type="STC">354</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100094</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Aduertisement.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Almansor : the learned and victorious king that conquered Spaine. His life and death published by Robert Ashley, out of the librarie of the Uniuersitie of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Luna, Miguel de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Parker, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 79, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>An Aduertisement.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing during my younger yeares had some trayning in the Arts, and Learned Languages in the famous Vniuersitie of Oxford: and by aduice of experienced friends hauing after seriously sought to attaine the knowledge of the Lawes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which wee liue, in the place where they are professed: and hauing beene long since ingaged and denominated among the Professors thereof: yet finding the practise to haue ebbes and tydes; (as haue for the most part all other humane employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) I haue stolne and snatched at vacant times some oportunities; what by Trauaile, Bookes, and Conference; to get some knowledge of forreigne Countries, and vulgar Languages: especially those of our Neighbours (I meane the French and Dutch, the Spanish and Italian) that by the perusing of their Writings, I might also bee made partaker of the Wisdome of those Nations: hauing beene long of this opinion. That as no one
<pb facs="5"/>soyle or territorie, yeeldeth all fruits alike, so no one Climate or Region affordeth all kind of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in full measure.</p>
   <p>With this resolution, being not letted by other occasions, J spent the best houres of some few Weekes, not many yeeres sithence in a superficiall suruey of the famous <hi>Librarie</hi> of that flourishing <hi>Vniuersitie,</hi> where I had beene trayned: which I found richly replenished with Bookes of all Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Faculties: not only in the Learned Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, <hi>Latine, Greeke,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew:</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the vulgar Tongues of our Neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) but euen with some furniture as well of <hi>Manuscripts</hi> as of printed Copies in the <hi>Arabian, Aethiopian,</hi> and <hi>Armenian</hi> Languages; with the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Wisdome and Characters (not speaking of the <hi>Chaldaick,</hi> and <hi>Syriak;</hi> because they are accounted by many but as Hebrew-dialects). There are also some <hi>Turkish</hi> &amp; <hi>Persian Manuscripts; Indian, Malayan,</hi> and <hi>Mexican Characters and Writings.</hi> Yea, <hi>China</hi> it selfe (being thought by many to bee inaccessible to Strangers) though by sundry Seas and Lands it bee farre separated from vs, hath vouchsafed to inrich this great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazin, or Storehouse of Learning, with diuers and sundry parcels of her Wisdome imprinted in her strange Characters.</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>Amongst the rest I happened on an <hi>Arabian Historie</hi> concerning the losse of <hi>Spaine</hi> by <hi>Rode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigo King of the Gothes,</hi> which by command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>King</hi> Philip the Second, was translated into <hi>Spanish</hi> out of the <hi>Arabian Copie</hi> remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the <hi>Escurial:</hi> where I my selfe haue seene a <hi>glorious golden Librarie of Arabian Bookes.</hi> In the midst of that Historie, I found a Summarie Collection, or obsernation of the life and death of <hi>a Learned Arabian King Iacob Almansor</hi> the Conquerour of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Of the excellencie of this great King, some hauing heard and read that among other his vertues, hee was an infinite louer of Learning, hauing <hi>assembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in his Librarie fiftie fiue thousand Bookes in an ignorant Age: when long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Inuention of Printing, all Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Learning, were only preserued by the laborious industrie of the Writers hand and Pen.</hi> Weighing also his wise distribution of his time with his exact Iustice, Wisdome of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, his Temperance of Dyet, Fortitude, and Prudence in his Militarie affaires; with the Prosperitie of his Conquests; and successe of all his enterprizes: they became desirous to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted,
<pb facs="6"/>with the particulars of his life; and longed to haue it communicated vnto them, in a Tongue which they better vnderstood. To their honest desire, hauing oportunitie in my hand, I thought it conuenient to giue satisfaction by trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating it out of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Copie which was prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Saragoza 1603.</hi> remayning in that vnpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralleld rare <hi>Librarie</hi> of the Ʋniuersitie of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and therehence out of <hi>the larger Historie of the Conquest of Spaine by the Moores,</hi> (being then the Subiects of this <hi>Almansor</hi>) by me excerpted and published. I present it to publicke view, that Christians finding their vertuous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie to be equalled or ouermatched by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans</hi> may the rather be excited to a disdainfull emulation of their worthiest en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>