<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohan Bale to the Christen readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1546</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100286_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22076</idno>
           <idno type="STC">848</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100286</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohan Bale to the Christen readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first examinacyon of Anne Askewe : latelye martyred in Smythfelde, by the Romysh popes vpholders, with the elucydacyon of Iohan Bale</title>
                 <author>Askew, Anne</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Straten, Derick van der (Theodoricus Plateanus)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Wesel</pubPlace>
                    <date>1546</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 2, 46, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>Iohan Bale to the Christen readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Monge other most syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular offyces (dylygent reader) whych the lorde hath appoynted to be done in the ernest sprete of Belyas, by the forerō ners of hys la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tre aperaunce, thys is one verye specyall to be noted. They shall turne the hartes of their anncyēt elders into the chyldrē. Mala. 4. And the vnbe Ieuers of their tyme, to the wysdome of those ryghrouse fathers, as ded Iohan Baptyst afore hys first cōmynge, Luce 1. That is (sayth Bedas ca. 68. de tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum <note place="margin">Bede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> prophecy▪</note> ratione) the faythe and feruent zele of the prophetes and Vpostles shall they plant in their hartes, whych shall in tho se dayes lyne and be amonge men conuer saunt. &amp; than wyll breake fourth (sayth he as a verye true prophete) soche horry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble persecucyon, as wyll first of all take from the worlde, those myghtye helia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses by tryumphaunt martyrdome, to the terryfyenge of other in the same fayth.
<pb facs="3"/>
of whom some shall becom through that occasyon, most gloryouse martyrs vnto <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. sortes.</note> Christ also, &amp; some verye wycked Aposta taes for sakynge hys lyuelye doctryne. For by the seyd Bedas testymonye in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge of the same chaptre, two most certayne sygnes shall we thā haue that the lattre iudgement daye is at hande. The returne of Israels remnaunt vnto their lorde God, and the horryble perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucyon of Antichrist. <note place="margin">2. sygnes.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Conferre with thys treated scripture and former prophecye of that vertuouse man Bedas, the worldes alteracyon now, with the terryble turmoylyng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s of our tyme. And as in a most clere myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, ye shall wele perceyue them at thys present, to be in most quyck workynge. And as concernynge the Israelytes or <note place="margin">Israely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> Iewes, I haue both seane and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of them in Germanye, most fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Christen beleuers. Neyther is it in the prophecye (Osee 3.) that they shuld at that daye be all conuerted, no more than they were at Iohan Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tystes preachynge, Luce 1. For as Esaye reporteth, though the posteryte of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob be as the see sande (innumerable)
<pb n="3" facs="3"/>
yet shall but a remnaunt of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert than vnto their lorde God. Esaie 10. And though the lorde hath syfted that howse of Israel (as broused corne in a syffe) amonge all other nacyons, Amos 9. Yet shall not that remnaunt of theirs perysh, but at that daye be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, through the onlye eleccyon of <note place="margin">preachers</note> grace, Romano. 11. Now concernyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the afore seyd forerōners, in thys most wonderfull change of the worlde before the lattre ende therof. I thynke within thys realme of Englande, besydes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Tyndale. Barnes.</note> nacyons abroade, the sprete of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyas was not all a slepe in good Wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyam Tyndale, Robert Barnes, &amp; soche other more, whome Antichristes vyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence hath sent hens in fyre to heauen, as Belyas went afore in the frerye cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rett, 4. Regum 2.</p>
   <p>These turned the hartes of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers into the chyldren, soche tyme as they toke from a great nombre of our nacyon, by their godlye preachynges and writynges, the corrupted beleue of the pope &amp; hys mastrye workers (whych were no fathers, but cruell robbers &amp; de stroyers, Ioā. 10.) reducynge thē agayn
<pb facs="4"/>
to the true faythe of Abraham and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Gene. 15. and Math. 16. The pure beleue in Christes birthe and passyon, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch Adam and Noe sucked out of the <note place="margin">The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> first promes of God, Iacob and Moses out of the seconde, Dauid and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes out of the thirde, and so fourth the Apostles and fathers out of the other scriptures, so firmelye planted they in the consciences of manye, that no cruell kynde of deathe coulde auerte thē from it. As we haue for example their consta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt dyscyples, and now stronge witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Iesus Christ, Iohan Lassels and Anne Askewe, with their other. ij. com <note place="margin">Martyrs</note> panyons, verye gloryouse martyrs afore God, what though they be not so afore the wronge iudgynge eyes of the worlde whom the bloudye remnaunt of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ put vnto most cruell deathe in Smythfelde at London, in the yeare of our lorde, M. D. XLVI. in Iulye.</p>
   <p>If they be onlye (as was Iohan Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyst) great afore the lorde by the holye scriptures allowaunce, whych are stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelye adourned with the graces of hys sprete, as faythe, force, vnderstandynge, wysdome, pacyence, loue, longe susseraun
<pb n="4" facs="4"/>
ce and soche lyke. I dare boldelye affer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me these 4. myghtye witnesses also to be the same, so well as the martyrs of the prymatyue or Apostles churche. For so <note place="margin">Christen martyrs.</note> strongelye had these those vertues as they, and so boldelye obiected their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes to the deathe for the vndefyled Christen beleue, agaynst the malygnan̄t Synagoge of Sathan, as euer ded they, for no tyrannye admyttynge anye create or corruptyble substaunce for their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lyuynge god. If their blynde babyes <note place="margin">Breade.</note> to proue them vnlyke, do obiect agaynst me, the myracles shewed at their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes more than at these, as that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythfull generacyon is euer desyerouse of wonders, Math. 12. I wolde but kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of thē, what myracles were shewed whan Iohan Baptystes head was cut of in the preson? Marci 6. and whan Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes <note place="margin">myracles</note> the Apostle was byheaded at Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem? Aero. 12. These 2. were excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent afore God, what though they were but myserable wretches, lyght fellawes, sedycyouse heretykes, busye knaues, and lowsye beggers in the syght of noble kyng Herode and hys honorable counsell of <note place="margin">rochettes</note> prelates. For had not rochettes and syde
<pb facs="5"/>
gownes bene at hande, haplye they had not so lyghtlye dyed.</p>
   <p>If they allege Steuen, to maynteyne their purpose, that he at hys deathe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helde beauen open. I aske of thē agayne <note place="margin">Steuen.</note> what they were whych se it more than hys owne persone? Sure I am that their wycked predecessours there present, se it not. For they stopped their cares, whan he tolde them therof, Actorum 7. If they yet brynge fourth the other hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storyes <note place="margin">Legēdes.</note> of Apostles and martyrs. I ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were them, that all they are of no soche autoryte. as these here afore. The popes martyrs in dede, were moche fuller of myracles than euer were Christes, as hys selfe tolde vs they shulde be so, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thei 24. Yet wrought fryre Forest, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han Fisher, and Thomas More no myra cles, <note place="margin">Forest. Fysher. More.</note> what though manye be now rege stred in their lyues and legendes by the fryres of Fraunce, Italye, and Spayne. Besydes that Iohan Cochleus hath written of them, ad Paulum Pōtificem, ad regem Henricum, and also in their defence agaynst doctor Sampson. With that Erasmus ded also ad Hutrenū. P. <note place="margin">Writers.</note> M. ad Gasparem Agrippam, Albertus
<pb n="5" facs="5"/>
Pighius, Riuius, Fichardus, &amp; a great sort more. And as for the holye mayde of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ēt with Doctor Bockynge, though they wrought great wonders by their lyfe, yet aperednon at their deathes. Of hys owne chosen martyrs, Christ loketh for <note place="margin">Christen martyrs.</note> non other myracle, but that onlye they perseuer faythfull to the ende, Math. 10. And neuer denye hys veryte afore men. Luce 12. For that worthye vyctorye of the synncfull worlde, standeth in the inuyncyblenesse of faythe, and not in my racles and wonders, as those waueryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge wittes suppose, 1. Ioan. 5.</p>
   <p>Ryght wonderfullye wyll thys apere in the ij. myghtye conflyctes here after <note place="margin">Anne As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewe.</note> folowynge, whych the faythfull serua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt of Iesu Anue Askewe, a gentylwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man verye yonge, dayntye, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, had with that outragynge Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goge, in her ij. examynacyons. about the xxv. yeare of her age, whom she sent abroade by her owne hande wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge. The handelynges of her other iij. companyons, shall be shewed in other seuerall treatyses at layser. For the glorye and great power of the <note place="margin">Goddes power.</note>
      <pb facs="6"/>
lorde, so many festlye aperynge in hys e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect vessels, maye not now perysh at all handes, &amp; be vnthankefullye neglected but be spred the worlde ouer, as wele in Latyne as Englysh, to the perpetuall in famye of so wyll fullye cruell and spyght full tyrauntes. Nothynge at all shall it terryfye vs, nor yet in anye poynt lett vs of our purpose, that our bokes are now in Englande condempned and brent, by the Byshoppes and prestes with their <note place="margin">Bokes cō dempned.</note> frantyck affynyte, the great Antichristes vpholders, whych seke by all practyses possyble to turne ouer the kynges most no ble and godlye enterpryse. But it wyll from hens forth occasyon vs, to set fourth in the Latyne also, that afore we wrote onlye in the Englysh, and so make <note place="margin">Latyne.</note> their spirytuall wyckednesse and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son knowne moche farther of. What auayled it Ioakim to burne Bieremyes proyhecye by the vngracyouse counsell of hys prelates? Hiere. 36. Eyther yet An tiochus to set fyre on the other scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res? 1. Macha. 1.</p>
   <p>After the Apostles were brought afo <note place="margin">God wyll be know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> re the counsell and strayghilye cōmaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to cease from preachynge, they prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>
moche more than afore. Acto. 4. In most terryble persecucyons of the pryma tyue churche, were the examynacyons &amp; answers, tormentes and deathes of the constaunt martyrs written, and sent a broade all the whole worlde ouer, as testyfyeth Eusebius Cesariensis in hys ecclesyastyck hystorye. Their coppyes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde yet euerye where. Great slaugh ter &amp; burnynge hath bene here in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande for Iohan wycleues bokes, euer <note place="margin">Iohan wycleue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> bokes.</note> sens the yeare of our lorde. M. CCC. LXXXII. Yet haue not one of them throughlye peryshed. I haue at thys houre the tytles of a C. and XLIIII. of them, whych are manye more in nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre. For some of them vndre one tytle com prehendeth ii. bokes, some iij. some iiij. Yea, one of them contayneth xij. I thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke not the contrarye, but ere the worlde be at a full ende, God wyll so gloryfye that twentye tymes condempned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyke, <note place="margin">Canonyse</note> execrated, cursed, spytted, and spat led at, that all your popysh writers befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hys tyme and after, wyll be reckened but vyle swyneheardes to hym, for the good fauer he bare to Christes holye Gospell, A verye madnesse is it to stryue
<pb facs="7"/>
agaynst God, whan he wyll haue the lon ge hydden inyquytees knowne. As the godlye wyse man Gamaliel sayd, Acto. 5. If thys enterpryse that is now taken <note place="margin">gamaliel</note> agaynst yow, be of God, ye shall neuer be able with all your tyrannouse practyses to dyssolue it.</p>
   <p>Now concernynge that blessed wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Anne Askewe, whych latelye suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the tyrannye of thys worlde for ryght <note place="margin">Anne As kewe.</note> wisnesse sake. In Lyncolne shyre was she borne of a verye auncyent and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble stocke, Sir Wyllyam Askewe a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye knyght beynge her father, But no worthynesse in the flesh, neyther yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye worldlye noblenesse anayleth to god warde, afore whome is no acceptacyon of persone, Actorum 10. Onlye is it fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the with hys true loue and feare, whych <note place="margin">True no bylyte.</note> maketh vs the accept, noble and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye chyldren vnto God, Ioan. 1. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by hys gyft, she had wonderfull ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundaunce. Soch a won was she, as was Lydia the purple sellar, whose har <note place="margin">Lydia.</note> te the lorde opened by the godlye prea chynge of Paule at Thyatira, Acto. 16. for dylygent hede gaue she to hys wor de whan it was ones taught without su
<pb n="7" facs="7"/>
perstycyon, &amp; wolde no lōgar be a false worshypper orydolatour after the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed scole of Antichrist. But became frō thensfourth a true worshypper, worshyp pyng her lorde God (whych is a sprete &amp; not breade) in sprete &amp; in veryte, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to that worde of hys, Ioan. 4. The Gospell of Christ bare she in her harte, asded the holye mayde Cecilia, &amp; neuer after ceased frō the stodye therof, nor frō <note place="margin">Ceciliae?</note> godlye cōmunycacyon &amp; prayer, tyll she was clerlye by most cruell tormentes, ta ken from thys wretched worlde.</p>
   <p>By her do There (dere fryndes in the lorde) as ded the faythfull Bretherne in fraunce, at the cyties of Lyons and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna by a lyke faythfull yonge wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man called Blandina. Whych was there put to deathe with. in. myghtye <note place="margin">Bladina</note> companyons more amonge other (as thys was) for her Christē beleue, about the yeare of our lorde, C. and LXX. in the prymatyue sprynge of their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styanyte. They wrote vnto their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne in the landes of Asia &amp; Phrygia verye farre of, her myghtye stronge suffe rynges for Christes fayth, whych they kne we nothynge of afore. I write here vnto
<pb facs="8"/>
in Englande the double processe of thy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> noble woman, wherof ye are not ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, for so moche as it was there so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfestlye done amonge yow, Coupled I <note place="margin">Anne Askewe.</note> haue these ij. examples togyther, bycau se I fynde them in so manye poyntes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. Blandina was yonge and tender, So was Anne Askewe also. But that whych was frayle of nature in thē both, Christ made most stronge by hys grace. Blandina had iij. ernest companyons in Christ, Maturus, Sanctes, and Atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, <note place="margin">Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyons.</note> so feruentlye faythfull as her selfe. So had Anne Askewe iij. fyre fellawes, a gentylman called Iohan Lassels her instructour, a pres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, and a tayler called Iohan Adlam, men in Christes veryte vnto the ende most cōstaunt. With Blā dina were in preson, to the nombre of x. <note place="margin">Recāters</note> whych renyed the truthe and were cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relye forsaken of God for it. Howmanye fell frō Christ besydes Crome and Shax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, whan Anne Askewe stode fast by hym, I am vncerteyne. But I counsell them, as saynt Iohan counselled the Laodycyanes, in the myserable estate <note place="margin">Tryed Golde.</note> they are now in, to bye them through tryed golde of Christ, least they perysh
<pb n="8" facs="8"/>
all togyther. Apoca. 3. If they had not styll remayned in that chauncell, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Christ commaunded Iohan in no wyse to measure, Apoca. 11. They had <note place="margin">The cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uncell.</note> neuer so shamefullye blasphemed, lyke as Bedas also toucheth in hys former propheeye.</p>
   <p>Prompt was Blandina, and of most Iustye corage, in renderynge her lyfe for the lyberte of her faythe. No lesse lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye <note place="margin">Corage.</note> and quyck was Anne Askewe in all her enprysonynges and tormētes. Great was the loue, Blandina had to Christ. No lesse was the loue of Anne Askewe. Blandina neuer faynted in torment. No <note place="margin">Racked.</note> more ded Anne Askewe in sprete, whan she was so terrybly racked of Wrysleye the chaunceller and Ryche, that the stryn ges of her armes and eyes were peryshed Blandina deryded the cruelte of the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauntes. So ded Anne Askewe the mad nesse of the Byshoppes and their speche men. Reade burnynge plates of yron and of brasse had Blandina put to her sydes, <note place="margin">Burned.</note> So had Anne Askewe the flamynge brā des of fyre. Full of God and hys veryte was Blandina. So was Anne Askewe to the verye ende. Christ wonderfullye
<pb facs="9"/>
tryumphed in Blandina. So ded he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Anne Askewe, whan she made no noyse on the racke, and so cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>estlye afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de reioyced in hym. Blandina was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen fourth to wylde beastes to be deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. So was Anne Askewe to cruell Bys <note place="margin">Beastes.</note> hoppes &amp; prestes, whom Christ calleth rauenynge wolues, deuourers, and the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, Math. 7. &amp; Ioan. 10. Blandina vpon the scaffolde boldelye reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the pagane prestes of their errour. So ded Anne Askewe whan she was fast tyed to the stake, with stomack rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke that blasphemouse apostata Shaxtō with the Byshoppes and prestes genera <note place="margin">Shaxtō.</note> cyon, for their manyfest mayntenaunce of ydolatrye.</p>
   <p>Blandina at the stake shewed a vysa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge vnterryfyed. So ded Anne Askewe a countenaunce stowte, myghtye and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest Infatygable was the sprete of Blā dina. So was the sprete of Anne As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewe. The loue of Iesus Christ, the gyft of the holye Ghost, and hope of the crow <note place="margin">Graces.</note> ne of martyrdome, greatlye mytygated the paynem Blandina. So ded those iii. worthye graces, the terrour of all tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in Anne Askewe. The stronge
<pb n="9" facs="9"/>
sprete of Christ gaue stomack to Blandi na, both to laugh and daunce. The same myghtye sprete (&amp; not the popes despera te sprete) made Anne Askewe both to re <note place="margin">Sprete.</note> ioyce and synge in the preson. So bolde was Blandina (sayth Eusebius) that with a presumpcyō of stomack she cōmo ued with Christ vnseane. I suppose Anne Askewes lattre examynacyō, wyll shewe her, not to do moche lesse. Gentyll was <note place="margin">Hygh sto macke.</note> Blādina to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hristē beleuers, &amp; terry ble to their aduersaryes. So was Anne Askewe verye lowlye to true teachers, but scornefull and hygh stomaked to the enemyes of truthe. Manye were conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the sufferaunce of Blandina. A farre greatter nombre by the burnynge of Anne Askewe. Though Blandina we reyonge, yet was she called the mother <note place="margin">Mother.</note> of martyrs. Manye men haue supposed Anne Askewe, for her Christen constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye to be no lesse. Blandina prayed for her persecuters. So ded Anne Askewe most feruentlye. The ashes of Blandina <note place="margin">Ashes.</note> and of other martyrs, were throwne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the flood of Rhodanus. What was done with the Ashes of Anne Askewe &amp; her companyons, I can not yet tell.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>
All these former reportes of Blandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na and manye more besydes, hath Euse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius in Ecclesiastica historia, libro 5. cap. 1. 2. &amp; 3. Hugo Floriacensis, Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus <note place="margin">Autors.</note> Contractus, Uincentius, Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus, Petrus Equilinus, and other hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storyanes more. And as touchynge Anne Askewe. these ij. examynacyons, with her other knowne handelynges in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, are wytnesses for her suffycyent. Thus hath not the fyre taken Anne As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewe <note place="margin">Not all dead.</note> all whole from the worlde, but left her here vnto it more pure, perfyght, &amp; precyouse than a fore, as it wyll also Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han Lassels within short space. So that concernynge her, it maye wele be sayd, that Paule verefyeth, 2. Cor. 12. The strength of God is here made perfyght by weakenesse. Whan she semed most fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <note place="margin">Weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</note> than was she most strōge. And glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye she reioyced in that weakenesse, that Christes power myght strongelye dwell in her. Thus choseth the lorde, the folysh of thys worlde to confounde the wyse, &amp; the weake to deface the myghtye. Yea, thynges despysed &amp; thought verye vyle, to brynge thynges vnto nought whych the worlde hath in most hyght reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyō.
<pb n="10" facs="10"/>
I thynke yf thys martyr were ryght lye conferred, with those canonysed mar tyrs, whych haue had, and yet hath styll, sensynges and syngynges, massynges &amp; <note place="margin">Martyrs</note> ryngyngesi the popes Englysh churche, cause with cause and reason with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, (as haplye here after they shall) she shuld be a great blemysh vnto them. An example of stronge sufferaunce myght thys holye martyr be, vnto all them that the lorde shall after lyke maner put fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewarde <note place="margin">Example</note> in thys horryble furye of An tichrist, to the glorye of hys per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted churche.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>