<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right worship∣full Master William Killigrew Es∣quier, one of her Maiesties priuie Chamber and Mystresse Margerie Killigrew his wife, R. Some wisheth increase of Gods gifts to their euerlasting comfort.</title>
           <author>Some, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100971_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12590</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22907</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100971</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right worship∣full Master William Killigrew Es∣quier, one of her Maiesties priuie Chamber and Mystresse Margerie Killigrew his wife, R. Some wisheth increase of Gods gifts to their euerlasting comfort.</title>
                 <author>Some, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godly sermon preached in Latin at great S. Maries in Cambridge, in Marche 1580. by Robert Some: and translated by himselfe into English</title>
                 <author>Some, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bishop, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Master William Killigrew <hi>Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier, one of her Maiesties priuie Chamber</hi> and Mystresse Margerie Killigrew his wife, <hi>R. Some</hi> wisheth increase of Gods gifts to their euerlasting comfort.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleased your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships to vse me very frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I am verie mindefull of it, and for some proofe of my thankfulnesse, I offer to you that shorte Sermon in English, which I presented in Latine to the Right honourable the Earle of Leicester, my singular good Lorde and Master. It is, I confesse verie plaine, and my desire was so to haue it: but it will, I am sure, minister comfort by the grace of God to suche as haue a feeling of their sinnes. And this either is, or should be one prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall drifte of our sermons, especially in
<pb facs="3"/> these daies, wherein as many as are to be awaked out of the sleepe of sinne by Gods fearefull threatenings so other are to be raysed vp, and must haue life put into them by Gods sweete promises. I could easily, and would like well to goe on in this argument, if it were not both the butte and white that my Sermon principally doeth leuell at. Vnto the which because I referre your selfe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Killigrew, and your good bedfel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, I take my leaue and commend you both to Almightie Gods tuition. Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge the 20 of April. <hi>1580.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your worships to command in Christ,</hi> Robert Some.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>