<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS MVCH RESPECTED FRIENDS, Master PETER CVRTHOPE Gentleman, and Mistresse IANE, his most deare and beloued Wife: Grace in this world, and glory in the world to come, through Christ our com∣mon SAVIOVR.</title>
           <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100379_Fr6_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19474</idno>
           <idno type="STC">59</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100379</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS MVCH RESPECTED FRIENDS, Master PETER CVRTHOPE Gentleman, and Mistresse IANE, his most deare and beloued Wife: Grace in this world, and glory in the world to come, through Christ our com∣mon SAVIOVR.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A hand of fellovvship, to helpe keepe out sinne and Antichrist : In certaine sermons preached vpon seuerall occasions: by Robert Abbot</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 276 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="135"/>
   <pb facs="135"/>
   <head>TO HIS MVCH RESPECTED FRIENDS, Master PETER CVRTHOPE Gentleman, and Mistresse <hi>IANE,</hi> his <hi>most deare and beloued Wife: Grace</hi> in this world, and glory in the world <hi>to come, through Christ our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> SAVIOVR.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My right worthy friends:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW can I be vnmindfull of you, who finde you still mindfull both of me and mine? My studies are much refreshed by you both: if then amid my studies, I, acknowledging others kindnesses, should be forgetfull of yours, my thankfulnesse would bee neere a wracke. Receiue therefore this my poore Prese<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t: and if I cannot shew my selfe in what I would, I hope you
<pb facs="136"/> will accept of what I can. Bookes were neuer more plentifull; as knowledge, they doe abound as waters of the Sea: yet there was neuer more need of good ones, as being one speciall meanes to pull downe sinne and Antichrist. I cannot commend mine to be such: yet, as Gods gifts, I can commend my desires to be forward (as I am able) to doe God seruice both by tongue and pen. I see the iustice of God giuing ouer some, who had no loue to the truth, to beleeue the lies of the Man of Sinne. And God hauing made me a poore Watchman in his Church, I would willingly warne mine owne sheepe of the danger, both by word and writing; yet, before it goeth to others, it doth come vnto you both, acknowledging your furtherances of it, and crauing your fauours both to entertaine and vse it as your owne. We poore Schollers doe wearie our bodies many waies: by writing amongst the rest. But a valiant man will not stand vpon the breach of his weapon, so he may get the victorie: nor we vpon the wearying and wearing of our bodies, if we may gaine what we fight for, to wit, the acceptance of our labours by them to whom wee doe intend them, together with the saluation of their soules. How-euer the successe may be, my hope shall lift vp my head amid all my faintings. Neither doe I feare, but that good people will giue approbation to what I haue rather la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to doe, than done. My aime is but to striue for Religion, and for that Religion which will giue vs comfort before God. I haue considered many times the danger of Idolatrie: as first, that Idolaters are a sottish people, who, through Gods iust iudgement,<note place="margin">Esay 46.6, 7, 8. Esay. 54.9, &amp;c.</note> withhold the truth in vnrighteousnesse, and will not walke in the light of reason. Secondly, that they are a cruell people,<note place="margin">Dan 3.</note> like <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who garded his Idoll with a fiery fornace, <hi>and heat it seuen times hotter for the true worshippers of God;</hi> and like the ancient persecutors vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Romane</hi> Emperours, who put <hi>Christians</hi> vpon cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and stakes, who did teare and scratch their sides with nailes
<pb facs="136"/> and clawes, who cast them vnto beasts, and burnt and broyled them with fire, and the like. Thirdly, that they are an alluring people, who haue their vermilion Images, like those that temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Ierushalem,</hi> and their great rewards like the Deuill,<note place="margin">Matth. 4.</note>
      <hi>All this will I giue thee</hi> (saith he to Christ) <hi>if thou wilt fall downe and worship mee:</hi> In which respects as Images or <hi>Idols</hi> are called <hi>Louers,</hi> so Idolaters, Whore-mongers, who will spare for no cost or paine to satisfie their lusts; like <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar,</hi> who made his Image of gold,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> and countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it with varietie of musicke, to wooe the minds of the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to stirre vp superstitious affections. And hauing laid vp these things with my selfe, and seeing withall that Poperie cannot (with all its subtill euasions) wash it selfe from deepe staine in this kinde; equalling, if not excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding euen Heathenisme it selfe in varietie of Idolatrous lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, as we may see by comparing the multiplicitie of heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish and Romish Idols. When I haue considered, I say,<note place="margin">Ʋide Wolfgang. Muscul. in Psal. <hi>16.</hi> &amp; Episc. Der. in diat. de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichr. cap. <hi>7.</hi> l. b. <hi>3.</hi> cum multis alijs.</note> that as the <hi>Heathens</hi> had protecting Idols for Nations, as <hi>Belus</hi> for the <hi>Babylonians, Isis</hi> and <hi>Osyris</hi> for the <hi>Aegygtians, Neptune</hi> for the <hi>Africanes,</hi> the <hi>Sunne</hi> for <hi>Rhodes, Iuno</hi> for <hi>Samos, Venus</hi> for <hi>Paphos, Apollo for Delphos, Quirinus</hi> for <hi>Rome, Minerua</hi> for <hi>Athens,</hi> and <hi>Diana</hi> for <hi>Ephesus:</hi> So <hi>Rome</hi> hath Saint <hi>Iames</hi> for <hi>Spaine,</hi> Saint <hi>Dennis</hi> for <hi>France,</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> for <hi>Rome,</hi> Saint <hi>Ambrose</hi> for <hi>Millane,</hi> Saint <hi>Marke</hi> for <hi>Venice,</hi> the three <hi>Kings</hi> for <hi>Collen,</hi> Saint <hi>Lewis</hi> for <hi>Pannonia,</hi> and Saint <hi>Mary</hi> for <hi>Heluetia.</hi> And as the <hi>Heathens</hi> had guardians for the Elements, as <hi>Iupiter</hi> for the <hi>Heauen</hi> and <hi>Fire, Iuno</hi> for the <hi>Aire, Neptune</hi> for the <hi>Sea,</hi> and <hi>Pluto</hi> for the <hi>Earth:</hi> So <hi>Rome</hi> hath Saint <hi>Agatha</hi> for the <hi>Fire,</hi> Saint <hi>Nicholas</hi> for the <hi>Sea,</hi> and Saint <hi>Theodulus</hi> for <hi>Tempests.</hi> And as the <hi>Heathens</hi> had guardians for the <hi>Fruits</hi> of the earth, as <hi>Bacchus</hi> for <hi>Wine,</hi> and <hi>Ceres</hi> for <hi>Fruit:</hi> So <hi>Rome</hi> hath
<pb facs="137"/> Saint <hi>Iodocus</hi> for <hi>Fruits,</hi> and Saint <hi>Vrbanus</hi> for <hi>Wine.</hi> And as the <hi>Heathens</hi> had guardians for their <hi>Cattell,</hi> as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi> and <hi>Pan:</hi> So <hi>Rome</hi> hath Saint <hi>Wendaline</hi> for <hi>Sheepe,</hi> Saint <hi>Eulogius</hi> for <hi>Horse,</hi> Saint <hi>Pelagius</hi> for <hi>Oxen,</hi> and Saint <hi>Anthony</hi> for <hi>Swine.</hi> And as the <hi>Heathens</hi> had their protectors for <hi>Trades, Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi> as <hi>Minerua</hi> for <hi>Learning, Vulcan</hi> for <hi>Smiths, Aesculapius</hi> for <hi>Physitians, Mars</hi> for <hi>Warriours, Diana</hi> for <hi>Hunters, Castor</hi> and <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lux</hi> for <hi>Sea-faring-men,</hi> and <hi>Flora, Venus</hi> and <hi>Lupa</hi> for <hi>Harlots:</hi> So <hi>Rome</hi> hath Saint <hi>Catherine</hi> and <hi>Gregorie</hi> for <hi>Schollars,</hi> Saint <hi>Luke</hi> for <hi>Painters,</hi> Saint <hi>Cosmas</hi> for <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitians,</hi> Saint <hi>Maurice</hi> for <hi>Souldiers,</hi> Saint <hi>Eulogius</hi> for <hi>Carpenters,</hi> Saint <hi>Crispine</hi> for <hi>Shoo-makers,</hi> Saint <hi>Gut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> for <hi>Taylors,</hi> Saint <hi>Magdalen</hi> and <hi>Afra</hi> for <hi>Harlots.</hi> And lastly, as the <hi>Heathens</hi> had their guardians against <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases,</hi> as <hi>Apollo</hi> against the <hi>Plague, Lucina</hi> against the paines of <hi>Womens trauailes,</hi> and <hi>Hercules</hi> against the <hi>Falling-sicknesse:</hi> So <hi>Rome</hi> hath Saint <hi>Sebastian</hi> against the <hi>Plague,</hi> Saint <hi>Petronel</hi> against an <hi>Ague,</hi> Saint <hi>Marke</hi> against sudden <hi>Death,</hi> Saint <hi>Margaret</hi> against the paines of <hi>Womens la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, S. Otilia</hi> against the diseases of the <hi>Eyes, S. Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> against the <hi>Tooth-ache,</hi> and the like. The consideration of all these and many other obiects of Idolatrie (none of which were of Gods making) hath made me many times to search into the cause of Religion, and to striue both with my selfe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that all insinuating Idolatrie being laid aside and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the truth may take place both in our heads and hearts. I know that deepe decisions of controuersies are not so easily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in our ordinary assemblies. I haue sought therefore to bring the truth vnto the easiest triall, in remouing such ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry exceptions as it is subiect vnto by the wise men of the world. Whatsoeuer it be, I doe offer it vnto both your hands: desiring God that it may confirme you in the truth of our true Religion.
<pb facs="137"/> It shall be my reioycing to see you and yours alwaies walking in the truth, and so humbly resigning your selues to the diuine wisdome of Gods word, both for the direction of your soules and bodies, that God may neuer haue iust cause to giue you ouer to Schisme, Heresie, Vanitie, or any other wickednesse what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer. Euen so humbly prayeth he, who hath some few yeeres had experience of your great loue, and who desireth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your faithfull Shepherd, ROBERT ABBOT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>