<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE CVRTEOVS READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100511_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00887</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100511</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE CVRTEOVS READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life and gate of Christianitie : entreating of the sacrament of baptisme, deuided into five bookes. Contayning the effects, the mater, the forme, the baptiser, and the partie baptised: with the reasons and use of all the auntient rites and ceremonies. ... Composed, gathered, and written by O.A</title>
                 <author>Almond, Oliver</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Auroi (Ouroy), Pierre</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 202, 8 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE CVRTEOVS READER.</head>
   <p>COnsidering with my selfe (Gentle Reader) what should be the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall cause and most effectuall motiues, that should vrge the kings maiestie and most high Court of <hi>Parlament,</hi> to enacte and make that rigorous lawe and penall Statute concerning the <hi>Baptisme</hi> of <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes</hi> Children: <hi>First that they should not be Baptised by their owne Priests: nor anie Catholike Layman or Mydwife of their Profession in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: Secondlie that they must be forced contrar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e to their consciences vpon paine of forfeiture of an hundreth pounds, to bring or cause their Children to be brought to a Minister of a contrarie Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion in Religion, and that Publikely in Church or Chapell there to be Baptised; vnlesse the Child were in danger of death, then the Minister to be sent for home to the Catholikes house, and ther to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister this Sacrament.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The first reason or cause may be;<note place="margin">The first reason of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.</note> for that perchaunce they thought it could not be so sufficientlie performed by anie other then of their owne ministerie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession
<pb facs="3"/> and Religion. But if they imagined any such thing surely they were mighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceaued: and some of the learned amongst them (I meane the Lords Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall) might haue informed them, that this conceit or opinion inclined to the practise of the old <hi>Heretikes</hi> the <hi>Donatists,</hi> against whom <hi>S. Augustine</hi> writte many bookes aboue a thousand yeares agoe,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>1.</hi> con. Donat.</note> who were perswaded that the Children <hi>Baptised</hi> by anie other then them selues, were not sufficiently <hi>Baptised:</hi> but they <hi>Rebaptised</hi> againe euen <hi>Catholikes</hi> if any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned or came to be of their profession. Not much vnlike by reason of this statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te it is nowe practised. For if any <hi>Catholike</hi> doe present his Child at <hi>Church</hi> or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell for auoyding the penaltie with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation that the Child is all readie chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stined: yet not withstanding, say the most part of the vnlearned ministers, I will doe my dutie and office, and so rebaptise the Child, although this be expresslie contrarie to the constitutions of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law:<note place="margin">De Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secra. dist. <hi>4.</hi> can. qui bis.</note> and by the same Canon Law they incurre by the acte of <hi>Rebaptization Irregularitie.</hi> Some in deed of the Ciuiller and learneder sort of <hi>Ministers,</hi> doe not
<pb facs="3"/> absolutly <hi>Rebaptise,</hi> but with Condition: <hi>If thou arte not Baptised, I Baptise thee.</hi> But this will not serue their turne, but rather betrayeth their ignorance? For they ought not to <hi>Rebaptise,</hi> vpon Condition, but when there is probable doubt, that the partie presented vnto them is not <hi>Baptised.</hi> Here is no such matter, but protestation made by the parents or others that the Child is allready <hi>Baptised.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For a second reason<note place="margin">The Second reason.</note> I imagine they could not so much as thinke that the <hi>Baptisme</hi> practised in the <hi>Roman Catholike Church</hi> or by a <hi>Roman Catholike Priest</hi> was no <hi>Baptisme,</hi> was not auaylable, and therfore they made this statute and law. For if this doctrine were true, woe then to their <hi>Protestanticall</hi> congregation. For first, then many of them were not <hi>Christians.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they neuer had any head of their <hi>Church a Christian.</hi> They haue had but fower heads of their <hi>Church,</hi> and they of diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se sorts: An old man, a man of middle age, a woman, and a child; and these fower all different in age, or sexe, and all fower baptised <hi>Catholiklie</hi> by a <hi>Catholike Bishop</hi> or <hi>Priest</hi> according to the <hi>Roman</hi> vse. But if <hi>Baptisme</hi> acted and done by a
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Catholike Bishop</hi> or <hi>Priest</hi> according to the <hi>Roman</hi> vse were not auaylable, why then no <hi>Baptisme</hi> no <hi>Christianitie,</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentlie the head of their <hi>Church</hi> no <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian.</hi> For K. <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight the first head of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> was <hi>Catholikly Baptised</hi> before <hi>Protestancie</hi> was preached. King <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth a Chid a boy, he also was <hi>Baptised</hi> according to the <hi>Roman</hi> vse by <hi>Henry</hi> his Father. And for the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> she was baptised <hi>Catholiklie,</hi> &amp; God saue all good tokēs) as the report goeth, she berayed the font. And for our King Iames,<note place="margin">Premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition.</note> who now rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gneth, he reporteth him self that he was <hi>Baptised</hi> by a <hi>Catholike Bishop.</hi> And for the <hi>Circumstances</hi> I had rather an other should examine then my self. But what milke he sucked from his nurces breast I know not, but sure I am his mother, from whom he had his being and first entran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce into this world, was a Constant <hi>Roman Catholike</hi> and a worthie Queene and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</hi> But to conclud the statute sure was not acted vpon conceat that <hi>Catholikes</hi> did not trulie <hi>Baptise,</hi> and that by <hi>Catholike Baptisme</hi> they were not true <hi>Christians.</hi> Some other reason they had, and
<pb facs="4"/> what may that be?</p>
   <p>Thirdly their motiue surely might be to gette monie,<note place="margin">The third reason.</note> and begger and impouerish <hi>Catholikes.</hi> This in deed hath wrought some effect. For some Gentlemen haue bene brought in question by some Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters for not bringing their Children to the Church to be <hi>Baptised,</hi>
      <note place="margin">W. C. R. B.</note> and so for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to compound, or else by <hi>Publike</hi> Court to haue beene censured for the whole penaltie. The Composition hath cost, some twentie pounds, some ten pounds, some more, some lesse. We know that God doth suffer temptations, tribulations, miseries, wants, pouertie, and some tyme beggerie it self to fall vpon is seruants,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> yet we are instructed by the <hi>Apostle S. Paule: Deus autem fidelis est, qui non patietur vos tentari vltra id quod, &amp;c. That God is faithfull, and will not suffer vs to be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted aboue that which we are able. But will make also with tentation yssue,</hi> that we may be able to sustaine, and withall to take cheere and Comfort.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Tobi.</hi> 2.</note> We read that old <hi>Tobie</hi> by reason he did obserue his <hi>Religion,</hi> burie the dead, releeue and comfort the afflicted, who were persecuted for their Consciences (and this he did contrarie to
<pb facs="5"/> the lawes and commaundement of the <hi>King Sennacherib</hi>) he grewe into miseries, was stroken blind by mischaunce, had wants, became verie poore: yet afterward the <hi>Scripture</hi> sayeth: God sent his <hi>Angell</hi> restored him to his sight, and he became againe verie rich. In like manner God suffered Iob to be tryed in the losse of his wealth and goods,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.</note> in the death of his Children and sore punishment of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: yet afterward his welth was restored, his Children multiplied, and he recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his former health. Almightie God commaunded <hi>Abraham</hi> that he should with his own hand,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 22</note> sacrifice his owne Sonne: yet presently God sent his <hi>Angell</hi> who sayd: <hi>Ne extendas manum tuam in Pue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: Extend not thy hand against the Child.</hi> So I hope God will one day at his pleasure put you in a better mind to recall these Cruelties and penall exactions, incline you to mercie, send his Comforts to his afflicted, and giue to euerie one in the end their right.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>Intherim</hi> this must be our daylie prayer which the Church vseth on the <hi>Sabaothe of Quatuor Tempora in Lent:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Missa Rom.</note>
      <hi>Adesto quaesumus Domine supplicationibus, &amp;c. Be thou
<pb facs="5"/> Present ô Lord, we beseech thee to our supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that we may deserue thou being the giuer of all graces in prosperitie to be humble, and in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie secure and stedfast. And thou ô Lord our Protector looke vpon vs, that we who are pressed downe with the weight of our miseries, may, being partakers of thy mercie, serue thee with freedom of mind and courage.</hi> Some enuious or liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorious fellowe may say, that by these kind of words we should seeme to looke for a day and libertie of <hi>Conscience.</hi> I answere. Herein we must referre our selues to the goodnes and mercie of God. And thus farre we assure our selues, and this Confidence we haue vpon the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our cause, that if we haue no resti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, or relaxation of our miseries in this life, we hope to receaue <hi>Centuplum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 20.</note>
      <hi>an Hundred sold</hi> in the next, <hi>VVhere neither thiefe can steal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>; nor canker corrupt.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Fourthlie I thinke the principall cause and true motiue and intention of the <hi>Parlament</hi> might be, to with drawe the,<note place="margin">The fourth reason.</note>
      <hi>Lay Catholike People</hi> from all conuersation with their <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Cleargie,</hi> in that they should haue no vse of them in <hi>Sacraments and Ceremonies;</hi> and therfore they intended to forbid them all, and put a great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie
<pb facs="6"/> euen vpon <hi>Baptisme, Mariage</hi> and <hi>Buriall.</hi> For preach they must not, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the Statute of <hi>Persuation: say Masse</hi> they may not, you know the penaltie and daunger: heare <hi>Confession</hi> they may not, the Statute of <hi>Absoluing</hi> forbiddeth: nor bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the <hi>Dead: nor Baptise: nor marrie.</hi> So that they would haue them cast of as vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable seruants. What thinke you of the Counsell of <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Emperour?</hi> Was it not as graue, as wise, as politike as the <hi>Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to suppresse <hi>Catholike Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion?</hi> Did they not shed their bloud and martyr them? Did they not disarme them, take from them all their forces? Did they not by lawes and Statutes spoyle them of their Lands and goods and begger them? Yet <hi>Christianitie</hi> flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risheth, and <hi>Iulians Counsell</hi> confounded. Was not also the <hi>Counsell</hi> of the <hi>Iewes</hi> as politike, wise, carefull, and prouident to suppresse the <hi>Apostles</hi> and commaund they should not speake in the name of <hi>Iesus,</hi> as the <hi>Parlament</hi> is to expell <hi>Catholike Priests,</hi> and the vse of their <hi>Religion</hi> and function? I would to God they would hearken to the Counsell of <hi>Gamaliel</hi> a graue <hi>Counseller,</hi> a doctor of the law, honorable to all,
<pb facs="6"/> people, who brought vp and instructed.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 5.</note>
      <hi>S. Paule</hi> in the lawe, what was his Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>Let these men alone</hi> (sayeth he) <hi>for if this Counsell or worke they goe about be of men it will be dissolued: but if it be of God, you are not able to dissolue them, least perhaps you be found to resist God also.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Finallie and fifthly,<note place="margin">The fifth reason.</note> It may be I haue missed my ayme all this while in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons alleadged. For the true meaning and purpose in deed was to bring the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes</hi> to obedience and Conformitie with the <hi>Protestants</hi> in the Administration of this <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and other publike practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of their Religion. In verie deed there were great reason in making and ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting this lawe, and imposing these grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous penalties, if the <hi>Catholikes</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were <hi>innouators,</hi> bringers in or deuisers of nouelties; or in administration of this <hi>Sacrament</hi> should derogate or take away any essentiall parte, or should practise any rite or Ceremonie which they had not receaued from their Auncestours, euen from their first Conuersion to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianitie.</hi> But considering that the <hi>Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes</hi> are verie respectiue, and more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the due administration of this
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Sacrament,</hi> then <hi>Protestant</hi> or <hi>Puritan;</hi> there is small or no reason in my opinion for this seuere penall Statute and lawe, to vrge and force them to bring to the Church vpon so great a penaltie, their Children to be <hi>Baptised</hi> of <hi>Puritan</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant.</hi> For it is manifest to the whole world, where <hi>Christianitie</hi> hath bene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed, and may appeare by this small ensuing treatise, how obseruant and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant the <hi>Catholikes</hi> haue euer beene in the prouision of <hi>Baptisme,</hi> as well in tyme of necessitie in <hi>Priuate Baptisme,</hi> both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Minister,</hi> as also touching the matter &amp; the forme, which are the two principall partes: and also in publike and solemne Celebration, in obseruing the auntient rites and Ceremonies therof. Farther it is open and plaine to the eyes of all men, that the <hi>Catholikes</hi> doe not decline nor swarue one iote from the <hi>Institution</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> bur are guided by the <hi>Canon</hi> of holy <hi>Scripture,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>an.</hi> 3.</note> especialy concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the two essentiall parts, that is: that by the speciall ordinance of <hi>Christ</hi> the matter must be true elementall water: and the forme to be: <hi>In the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Sonne, and of the Holy Ghost:</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/> which was prescribed by no other then <hi>Christ</hi> himself after his glorious <hi>Resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth,</hi> 28.</note> when he gaue Commission to his <hi>Apostles</hi> to <hi>Baptise.</hi> And as for the rites &amp; Ceremonies which we <hi>Catholikes</hi> vse (as shall appeare in the 5. Booke of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise) they are not idle, nor superstitious, as the <hi>Protestants</hi> would haue them: but most honorable, significant, instructiue, profitable, and comfortable to Christian people. And for Confirmation of them we haue the practise of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> the <hi>Tradition</hi> of the auntient <hi>Primatiue Church,</hi> the testimonie of all ages, with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Fathers, and holie <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> And it is worth the noting and in particular to be obserued, that the <hi>Catholikes</hi> at this day in <hi>England,</hi> vse in the <hi>Celebration</hi> of this <hi>Sacrament</hi> no other matter, nor no other forme, nor Ceremonie then that which was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them by antiquitie euen from the first founders and Conuerters of this Iland to <hi>Christianitie,</hi> either among the <hi>Britons:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Beda. li. <hi>2.</hi> hist. Angl. cap. <hi>17.</hi>
      </note> partly by those who were sent from <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Pope Elutherius</hi> at the instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of <hi>King Lucius:</hi> or afterwarde by <hi>S. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus</hi> and <hi>S. Lupus</hi> appointed by <hi>Pope
<pb facs="8"/> Celestine</hi> for their <hi>Reformation</hi> concerning the <hi>Pelagian</hi> heresie: or amongst the <hi>Scots</hi> or <hi>Picts</hi> by <hi>S. Palladius:</hi> or finallie amongst vs <hi>English</hi> by <hi>S. Augustine</hi> the monke, sent by <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> the <hi>Great.</hi> All which consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered (Gentle <hi>Reader</hi>) I referre to thy owne Iudgement what great necessitie there should be so eagerlie and with such penaltie to vrge <hi>Catholikes</hi> to present their Children at <hi>Church</hi> or Chappell, to be <hi>Baptised</hi> of <hi>Puritan</hi> or <hi>Protestant.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now hauing diued into the viewe why the <hi>Parlament</hi> enacted so seuerely against <hi>Catholike Baptisme,</hi> by compelling all <hi>Catholikes</hi> vpon such penalties to <hi>Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ze</hi> publikely at their <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Chappell</hi> by their <hi>Ministers.</hi> I will briefly put downe the motiues that moued me to write this small ensuing treatise.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The motiues to write this treatise.</note>And first (Good <hi>Reader</hi>) I tooke this matter in hand to let thee vnderstand what <hi>Baptisme</hi> is, and the necessitie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to saluation. It is here on earth the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> first begining of <hi>Christianitie:</hi> the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> the house of God:<note place="margin">The reason of the title of the boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke.</note> the high-way to all other <hi>Sacraments,</hi> in so much that without this no other <hi>Sacrament</hi> is auaylable: a washing
<pb facs="8"/> and cleansing our soules from all sinne <hi>Originall</hi> and others: a <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for all paines due for sinne eternall or tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: a deliuerie from the bondage and power of the <hi>Diuell:</hi> a restorer of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie: an incorporation to <hi>Christ</hi> as members of his bodie mysticall: and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie a reconciliation vnto the grace &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God Almightie, wherby we are made the adopted Sonnes of God, Coheyres and inheritors with <hi>Christ</hi> of the kingdome of heauen. Hath it all these effects? Take heed then that thou lay the foundation sure of thy <hi>Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> that is: that thou be truely <hi>Baptised</hi> and Christened.</p>
   <p>The second motiue was to lay open <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and make plaine vnto thee by way of questions and doubts (which I suppose to be the easiest and plainest Course for thy better vnderstanding) the effects, the matter, the forme, the minister as well in necessitie as in publike Celebration, with the solemnitie and Ceremonies of this <hi>Sacrament;</hi> For that thou being more fullie herein instructed, thou mayest haue a more especiall care to haue it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlie effected and trulie performed in
<pb facs="9"/> these daungerous tymes of heresie. For assuredly this is the gate that openeth to heauen: which if it should be shutte and not duely ministred, there were no hope of saluation, but all open to hell and damnation.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly to giue thee a Caueat and warning of the daungerous opinions and assertions,<note place="margin">The daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous points of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</note> which are taught and spread abroad of this <hi>Sacrament</hi> by the <hi>Sectaries</hi> of this age. The first daungerous poynt of doctrine is, that the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptisme</hi> was institued by <hi>S. Iohn Baptist:</hi> and that the <hi>Baptisme</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>S. Iohns,</hi> is all one and the selfe same; which is against <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
      <hi>Scripture</hi> and reason. For then we must needs say, that the first and chiefe <hi>Sacramēt</hi> of the new <hi>Testament</hi> and <hi>Ghospell</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> should be instituted by a precedent <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> and not by <hi>Christ</hi> him self, which were absurde, seing all <hi>Sacraments</hi> of the <hi>New Testament,</hi> haue their institution by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
      <hi>Christ,</hi> and their force and vertue from his death and <hi>Passion.</hi> Secondly that this <hi>Sacrament</hi> doth not conferre grace, cleanse the soule from sinne as an effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient instrumentall cause by <hi>Christ</hi> insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and endued with that vertu; which
<pb facs="9"/> were to destroy <hi>Baptisme.</hi> Thirdlie that it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> doth not impresse in the soule a seale, signe, and Character of <hi>Christianitie</hi> inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible for euer; which is to make no distinction betweene Iewe, Gentill, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan and <hi>Christian.</hi> Fourthly that he, who <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> is once <hi>Baptised,</hi> can not be damned; which were to set all at libertie; and make men carelesse of all other <hi>Christian</hi> life. Fifthly that the only memorie of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
      <hi>Baptisme</hi> doth iustifie from our sinnes, which we shall commit after <hi>Baptisme,</hi> which were to take away all satisfaction, repentance and penance; and other such like absurdities, and daungerous poynts of <hi>Doctrine</hi> against <hi>Scripture, Councells, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and all antiquitie.</p>
   <p>Finallie I would haue thee to consider with what subtiltie the <hi>Deuill</hi> hath endeauoured in these latter tymes by his instruments the <hi>Heretikes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The fourth motiue.</note> to disgrace the beautie of <hi>Christs Spouse</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> to depopulate roote vp, and destroy like wild boares the vineyard of our Lord. And I compare the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Baptisme</hi> to the tree of life placed in the middest of <hi>Paradise;</hi> which the <hi>Heretikes</hi> of this age, some of them haue hacked and hewed at
<pb facs="10"/> the verie chiefe boughes and branches therof: some others haue pilled the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, and pulled of all the leaues, the beautie therof: and some others haue destroyed all the fruite and vertu therof, and put the axe euen to the verie roote to destroy all. <hi>Martin Luther</hi> endeauoured at one blowe to cutte of two of the essentiall parts of this tree of life; that is: the <hi>forme</hi> and <hi>mater</hi> of <hi>Baptisme;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luther in Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis collo. ca. <hi>17.</hi>
      </note> For (sayeth he) <hi>no forme of words is necessarie.</hi> It is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient with him: <hi>To Baptise in the name of the Lord.</hi> And as for the <hi>matter,</hi> anie li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor that is apte to washe, as Ale, beere, or milke, is sufficient. Thus this Impe and instrument of <hi>Sathan,</hi> maketh no scruple to destroy the two essentiall parts of this <hi>Sacrament</hi> to appoint anie li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor for matter, and no forme of words. Although this errour of <hi>Luthers</hi> be against <hi>Christs institution,</hi> and expresse Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, who hath ordayned water to be the matter: and the forme to be: <hi>In the name of the Father,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.</note>
      <hi>and of the Sonne, and of the Holy Ghost: M. Brentius</hi> will make himself so bould with <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Church,</hi> as to set downe an order of his owne, neuer heard of before: <hi>Let the Minister</hi> (sayeth
<pb facs="10"/> he) <hi>recite the Creed, and say:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius de Baptis.</note>
      <hi>In this faith I Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptise thee;</hi> and this shall passe for currant without anie other forme of words.</p>
   <p>But <hi>M. Iohn Caluin</hi> goeth farther, almost impudēt and blusheth not to say: <hi>That the forme of words in Sacraments are meere Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call charmes and enchauntments.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Caluin li. <hi>4.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitu. cap. <hi>17.</hi>
      </note> And thus you may see how these Agents for <hi>Sathan</hi> doe dismember the essentiall parts of this <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Baptisme,</hi> and doe cutte of the principall boughes of this tree of life.<note place="margin">Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants. Read S. Aug. li. <hi>2.</hi> de nup. &amp; Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pisc. ca. <hi>29.</hi>
      </note> Then come the <hi>Protestants</hi> in parte ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning yssue with the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> and pull of the leaues, and pill of the barke of this tree of life, that is: they deride, neglect and contēne the auncient Ceremonies of this <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Baptisme,</hi> as well the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Ceremonies, such as goe before the acte of <hi>Baptisme,</hi> as exorcismes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufflations, hallowing of the fonte &amp;c: as the Subsequent such as are after <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptisme,</hi> videlicet: holy vnction, with holy <hi>Chrisme,</hi> the vse of the waxe-candle or taper light, the cloathing with the white garment commonlie called the <hi>Chrisome.</hi> All which Ceremonies although they be auncient, profitable, significant, and deliuered by Tradition as from the
<pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>Apostles,</hi> as shall appeare in the sequell: yet are these derided, neglected, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned by the <hi>Protestants.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Last of all come the <hi>Puritans</hi>
      <note place="margin">Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans.</note> withe the axe of <hi>M. Caluin,</hi> laying load at the very roote of this tree of life, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all, to beat downe this gate and entrance to saluation. This <hi>Sacrament</hi> say they, is not necessarie to <hi>Saluation</hi> for all men, because Children borne of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Parents</hi> may be saued without <hi>Baptisme;</hi> either by <hi>Predestination,</hi> or by the fayth of their <hi>Parents;</hi> the elder sort being of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, may be sure of their <hi>Saluation</hi> only by faith. Also they extinguish and condemne the two principall effects of <hi>Baptisme</hi> that is <hi>Remission</hi> of sinnes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion of inherent grace wherby the sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le is cleansed and iustified. Although this be contrarie to <hi>Christs</hi> owne wordes, who expresseth the necessitie of <hi>Baptisme</hi> vnto all saying:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>Nisi quis renatus, &amp;c. Vnlesse euerie one be borne againe of water and the holy Ghost, he can not enter into the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> Also that <hi>Baptisme</hi> doth remit sinne the aunciēt Fathers when they compiled and made the <hi>Nycen Creed,</hi> which is one of the three <hi>Creeds</hi> beleeued of all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants,</hi> haue these wordes: <hi>Confiteor vnum
<pb facs="11"/> Baptisma in Remissionem Peccatorum: I Confesse one Baptisme vnto Remission of sinnes.</hi> Some will haue it onlie an externall washing, no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall cleansing. And the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clud all <hi>Infants</hi> and Childrē from <hi>Baptisme,</hi> and onlie will admit such as haue the vse of reason, are aged, &amp; mē of vnderstāding.</p>
   <p>Take heed therfore (Curteous Reader) of this daungerous doctrine, beware of these wicked brood, who hack and hewe, pill and poll, yea cut downe euen at the root this tree of life, planted in <hi>Paradise</hi> by God himself, instituted by <hi>Christ</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> as the onlie ordinarie meanes, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and entrie to saluation. They will haue it vsed onlie as a Commaunded Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to incorporate vs as the members of the <hi>Church,</hi> and as a bare sign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and seale of Iustice: not as the ordinarie meanes for all to saluation, not as conferring grace inherent, not as cleasing and washing the soule internallie, not as remitting sinne; And so cutting downe by the roote the efficacie, force, vertue and power of this <hi>Sacrament,</hi> which is to ayme at the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe of all <hi>Christianitie.</hi> For if no <hi>Baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me</hi> no <hi>Christianitie:</hi> no <hi>Christianitie,</hi> no <hi>Christ Vigila ergo &amp; Vale. Be watchfull ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> and so farewell. This 30 of Iulie, 1614.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thy true friend and well willer in Christ O. A.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <p>The generall Pointes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in this treatise are fiue.</p>
   <list>
      <item>1. <hi>First of the effects of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the necessitie therof to Saluation.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>2. <hi>Of the two essentiall Parts of Baptisme, that is: Concerning the matter and the forme, the water and the word.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>3. <hi>Of the Baptiser, that is of the ordinarie minister, to whom by office, function, or Commission it belongeth to Baptise: or the Extraordinarie who are allowed to Baptise in case of necessitie, as the layeman, midwife, or any other woman.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>4. <hi>Of the Parties who are to be Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptised, as Infants, and Children, and such as haue vse of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, as aged, and men of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>5. <hi>Of the reasons, vse, and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of the Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of this Sacrament.</hi>
      </item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>