<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Vertuous, Graue, Wise, and Religious Gentlewoman, Mris. Dorothey Dalby, Widow, his deare and naturall Mother: HARIM WHITE, her dutifull and onely Sonne, wisheth, in this life prosperity; and in that which is to come, eternall felicity.</title>
           <author>White, Harim</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100638_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B16321</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25387</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100638</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Vertuous, Graue, Wise, and Religious Gentlewoman, Mris. Dorothey Dalby, Widow, his deare and naturall Mother: HARIM WHITE, her dutifull and onely Sonne, wisheth, in this life prosperity; and in that which is to come, eternall felicity.</title>
                 <author>White, Harim</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ready vvay to true repentance: or a godly, and learned treatise, of the repentance of Mary Magdalen : opened in diuers sermons at the first; begun in little Alhallows vpon the wall, London, the 21. day of Septemb. 1616. and continued in S. Peters church in Sandwich; contayning doctrine of faith. By Harim White Bachelor of Diuinity, and chaplyn to his most excellent maiesty. Whereunto also, by request, are added certaine other sermons, preached by the same author, vpon diuers occasions, in his priuate cure</title>
                 <author>White, Harim</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Bushell, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 60 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Vertuous, Graue, Wise, <hi>and Religious Gentlewoman,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">ris</seg>. <hi>Dorothey Dalby,</hi> Widow, <hi>his deare and naturall Mother:</hi> HARIM WHITE, her dutifull <hi>and onely Sonne, wisheth, in</hi> this life prosperity; and in that which is to come, <hi>eternall felicity.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hings deferred, and long in expectation, afford the more ioy in the fruition. You haue (I acknowledge
<pb facs="3"/> most deare and louing Mother) hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto reaped nothing at all, for all that you haue so largely and long since sowne: but haue with the wise Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, still patiently waited for the fruitfull time of Haruest.</p>
   <p>Now therefore, in some measure to comfort you, (though at the last) as our Sauiour willeth his Disciples, so doe I you, <hi>To lift vp your eyes, for now the Regions are already</hi> Albae <hi>white, euen to the Haruest. Ioh. 4. 35.</hi> And although they bee not all <hi>Siccae,</hi> dry, and throughly ripe at once▪ yet let our small beginning bee acceptable, and encourage you with hope of the rest in due time. All Graines are not ripe together, but euery kinde hath it owne proper, and
<pb facs="3"/> fit season. Heere first we beginne with <hi>Faith,</hi> and purpose (God blessing vs) to goe on with <hi>Hope,</hi> and end with <hi>Loue,</hi> which threefold Cable shall neuer bee broken. I could finde none in right (amongst the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more fit then your selfe, to whose care and protection I might commit this shiftlesse and helplesse Orphan: it beeing originally, and properly your own Issue. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you shall bee pleased with these my first fruites, and fauourably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret these my first endeauours: you shall thereby encourage mee to tender to your view, workes of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter importance heereafter. And in the <hi>interim</hi> (as duty bindeth mee) I will not cease to solicite God by
<pb facs="4"/> prayer for your continuall prosperity; and that when hee shall please to take you from this earthly mansion, you may ascend into the euerlasting habitation of glorie. And thus in all filiall obsequy I humbly take my leaue this third of Ian. 1617.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your euer obedient, louing Sonne. HARIM WHITE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>