<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The poesie of Richard Tauer∣ner Gent.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100459_Fr1_12</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11035</idno>
           <idno type="STC">164</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100459</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The poesie of Richard Tauer∣ner Gent.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A registre of hystories : conteining martiall exploites of worthy warriours, politique practises of ciuil magistrates, wise sentences of famous philosophers, and other matters manifolde and memorable. Written in Greeke, by Ælianus a Romane: and deliuered in Englishe (as well, according to the truth of the Greeke text, as of the Latine) by Abraham Fleming. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Aelian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 178 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div xml:lang="eng" type="encomium">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The poesie of Richard Tauer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Gent.</hi>
   </head>
   <l>Yf stories should lye fainting vnder foote,</l>
   <l>(Synce foes with force marche on to foile their fame,</l>
   <l>VVhos buisy braines their flights of fury shoote,</l>
   <l>To impaire their praise, and nippe their noble name)</l>
   <l>If such I say should blotted be with blame,</l>
   <l>No witte would worke a way by penne to showe</l>
   <l>The state of such as liued longe agoe.</l>
   <l>Yf Homers hed had slept in slouthfull ease,</l>
   <l>VVhat wight had knowne Vlysses wandred wayes?</l>
   <l>VVhat coasts he scapte, whar syrts, and surgeing seas,</l>
   <l>Before he had in Ithac' happy dayes:</l>
   <l>The Poets penne his passage open layes,</l>
   <l>And many moe that diuersly indite,</l>
   <l>Haue lefte at lenghte their labours large in lighte.</l>
   <l>Such willinge wights in Englishe angle dwell,</l>
   <l>VVhose paineful pēns haue purchasd peereles praise,</l>
   <l>Obliuion blind their quiuering quills so quell,</l>
   <l>As once her hed, that Hagg, she dare not raise:</l>
   <l>Among the which in theis our drouping dayes,</l>
   <l>No will doth want to wring from wit a verse,</l>
   <l>Of Flemings praise the pension to rehearse.</l>
   <l>Through stories straunge and many a tretise triewe.</l>
   <l>Thy penne hath pearst, thy quill hath traced quite</l>
   <l>And left them vs in English glasse to viewe,</l>
   <l>As precious pearles and Diamonds of delighte.</l>
   <l>Let Sycophants assault with darts of spighte</l>
   <l>This planted plot: yet of this worke most wise,</l>
   <l>The fame shall flye from yearth to azur skyes.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>