<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his more than Honour'd Unckle
Adam Lawrence: Leonard Lawrence wisheth in∣crease
of happinesse, with the Yeares
of Nestor.</title>
           <author>Lawrence, Leonard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100242_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21479</idno>
           <idno type="STC">778</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100242</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his more than Honour'd Unckle
Adam Lawrence: Leonard Lawrence wisheth in∣crease
of happinesse, with the Yeares
of Nestor.</title>
                 <author>Lawrence, Leonard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A small treatise betwixt Arnalte and Lucenda entituled The evill-intreated lover, or the melancholy knight. Originally written in the Greeke tongue, by an unknowne author. Afterwards translated into Spanish; after that, for the excellency thereof, into the French tongue by N.H. next by B.M. into the Thuscan, and now turn'd into English verse by L.L. a well-wisher to the Muses</title>
                 <author>San Pedro, Diego de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Moseley, Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 108 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To his more than Honour'd Unckle
Adam Lawrence: Leonard Lawrence wisheth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
of happinesse, with the Yeares
of Nestor.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Sir,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen first I Translated this small
<hi>Treatise</hi> of <hi>Arnalte</hi> and <hi>Lucenda,</hi>
I was Resolv'd to have tender'd it
to Your Honour'd view, fairely
written in a well-pen'd Manuscript:
but since that time my Resolutions
are alter'd, yet not somuch through
my owne desires, as by the perswasion of some well-wishing
friends; who earnest to have some Copies of
(I must confesse) these my weake Endeavours, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged
me to send it to the Presse, thereby to avoyde
the tediousnesse of writing: To these their motions
I was easily perswaded, and that the rather, 'cause
my Subject had formerly beene a Printed Object:
(though in another tongue) Yet I protest no vaine am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition,
no phantastique desire, to be perspicuous to
the transparent eye of the world incited me, but onely
the importunity of friends: this I hope will excuse
my forwardnesse, either to Your worthy selfe, or any
indifferent Reader; the ingenious I am sure will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage
my resolutions; and as for the <hi>Hidra</hi>-headed
<pb facs="3"/>
multitude, let them spit the venome of their malicious
Envy, and spare not; for I have already prevented the
operation of their poyson, with an Antidote of suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
worth, which is, my neglect of such Criticall
dispositions: and if this be not sufficient, why the two
Capitall Letters of Your ever-honour'd name, is of
force enough to confound them with amazement. For
which reason, I knowing it to be customary to such as
write Bookes, to Dedicate their Labours to some one
or other; some tendring their Workes to the view of
Grand-Personages, (I will not say in hope of reward)
others to their speciall friends, (perhaps in respect
of love and familiarity) yet both (I am confident (with
intent, that they may be set forth to the perspicuous
eye of the world; have chose Your most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected
Selfe, to Patronize my post-ensuing Lines;
not knowing any so worthy, or more judicious,
or to whom I am more oblieg'd. Or have I dar'd
to tender them to the acceptance of any other, sith
they are Yours, and You may justly claime them,
I having Devoted all my Services to Your Candid
selfe. These if You daigne to protect, I'le not
care for Carping <hi>Momus,</hi> or Barking <hi>Zoylus,</hi>
though they should taxe me with a <hi>Westminsterian</hi>
Epitaph: albeit I confesse I was never such a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender
to Learning (though I know not much)
as to steale whole Verses, though it bee lawfull
to Quacke-salve Lame Lines with helping words,
and two Physitians use one and the selfe-same
Simples (though differently Compounded) but
to write <hi>Verbatim,</hi> I'de not affront any mans inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium,
so ignobly, or dishonour my selfe so basely,
though thousands know it not: one may come
<pb facs="3"/>
with <hi>Virgils</hi> Verse in his mouth, and say,
<q>
         <l>Hos ego versiculos feci, tulit alter honores.</l>
      </q>
But's no matter, such Censurers may use their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
I will not say of ignorance or envy, if
of either I care not: It's Your Honour'd selfe,
whom I observe: so you be pleased, it imports not
who's offended.</p>
   <p>My <hi>Genius</hi> having prompt me to present these
unpolisht Lines to Your judicious Censure; I shall
intreate You'ld pardon the faults my English Stile
affords; and attribute them to my unskilfulnesse;
I must confesse (and believe) there bee many, yet
since more sublimer Wits have had some, mine
may bee the more excusable; for if the finest
Lawne have an Iron-mould, (witnesse Your selfe)
it may bee borne withall in a courser piece.</p>
   <p>But what neede I direct the freenesse of Your
Noble Disposition, or the generosity of your su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-excellent
minde, since the Transcendency of
Your judgement, manifests that you'le have this
consideration; that a small haire cannot give so great
a shadow as a bigge Cable, nor a Needles poynt,
so large a circumference as a wide Circle. I neede
not unfold th'<hi>aenigma</hi> of my meaning, <hi>Car, au, bon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeur
ne fault que demy parolle.</hi> As Painters draw
a Counter-Figies by a living Object; so have I
enterpriz'd to translate a Booke, being a Printed
Subject; yet if I give not a true resemblance, or
lay my shadowes right, representing th'<hi>Idea</hi> of
my <hi>Prose,</hi> though Metamorphis'd into <hi>Verse,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
it to my want of Art, not of Desire:
Thus, if you please to protect these my imployments,
which kept my Wits busie for some spare houres, from
<pb facs="4"/>
the taxations of false-opinionate men, whose Criticall
Censures I may compare to <hi>Paris</hi> Darts, or <hi>Cephalus</hi>
Shafts, which transpierce the best Armour of proofe,
though of <hi>Vulcans</hi> owne forging. I'le promise, when as
I am growne more cunning, and can mixe my colours
better, to Present You with some more serious Piece:
In the interim I, tendring these to Your protection, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend
You to the tuition of the Vniversall <hi>Rector,</hi>
who Felicitate all Your Enterprizes; whilst I, with all
respect, and submissive Reverence, humbly kisse Your
hands, and remaine in hope of the continuance of Your
Favours,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your well-wishing, and most
affectionate Nephew:
<hi>Leonard Lawrence.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>