<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To Miles Mosse, Minister of the Word, and Bacheler of Diuinity</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100921_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10968</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21238</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100921</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To Miles Mosse, Minister of the Word, and Bacheler of Diuinity</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Miles Christianus or A iust apologie of all necessarie writings and writers : specialie of them which by their labored writings take paines to build vp the Church of Christ in this age and in a publique, and diffamatorie epistle lately set forth in print, are vniustly depraued. Allowed by auctority</title>
                 <author>Rogers, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>5, 2-36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="address">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To Miles Mosse, Minister of the <hi>Word, and Bacheler of Diuinity</hi>
   </head>
   <argument>
      <p>Miles Christianus wisheth more soundnes <hi>of iudgement, more substance of learning, with more</hi> wisedome and discretion in all his actions.</p>
   </argument>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou haue published of late, Maister Mosse, à little Treatise entituled, <hi>A short Catechisme, &amp;c.</hi> you fore-saw I doubt not, whither it shoulde go, from what, into whose hands it would come, how many eies woulde see, and how many eares heare it, and heare of the same: and therefore vpon mature deliberation (for may I thinke otherwise?) you commended it (<hi>yet the worke of other heads</hi>) and your selfe withal (<hi>the corrector and abridger thereof</hi>) with many titles and notable words vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the present age, and posterity to ensue. Of which Booke I haue nothing, or verie little, but of the Preface, or dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorie Epistle of yours (which I woulde to God had neuer beene written, or more Christianly, soberly, and aduisedly penned) I haue many thinges to say.</p>
   <p>Nowe that you may perceiue my quarrell against you is iust, not picked by mee, but ministred by your selfe, I haue sette-downe all your wordes, without either adding vnto, or taking from them any whit: and where you
<pb facs="3"/>
say well, you shall haue the praise due for good deseries, but where you haue slidde from the truth, and broached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sound and noisome assertions, I haue both laide them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and confuted them also, for your owne good, if admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished you will see your faultes, and reforme your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and for the common benefit of our Church and Countrey, to whose seruice, I haue dedicated my selfe and studies.</p>
   <p>And this haue I donne (as hee knoweth to whome the verie ground not of mine onely, but of your writing also is knowen) not of any setled ill-will to your selfe, to whome I wishe all good, but through an vtter detestation of your Paradoxes, which neither for mee had beene confuted in an open booke, had not they by your selfe to the great disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God in a publike writing, and vulgar tongue both in Towne and Countrey, beene dispersed.</p>
   <p>I am no aduersarie to your person, but to your opinions, which if you change, I am changed; if not, assure your selfe to heare that you would not, when you will persist to holde that you should not maintaine.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>