<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Noble-minded
READER.</title>
           <author>Lawrence, Leonard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100242_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21479</idno>
           <idno type="STC">778</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100242</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Noble-minded
READER.</title>
                 <author>Lawrence, Leonard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A small treatise betwixt Arnalte and Lucenda entituled The evill-intreated lover, or the melancholy knight. Originally written in the Greeke tongue, by an unknowne author. Afterwards translated into Spanish; after that, for the excellency thereof, into the French tongue by N.H. next by B.M. into the Thuscan, and now turn'd into English verse by L.L. a well-wisher to the Muses</title>
                 <author>San Pedro, Diego de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Moseley, Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 108 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_poem_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Noble-minded
READER.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, if my Lines should chance come unto</l>
   <l>The worthy prospect of your noble view,</l>
   <l>Although they are (I must confesse) unfit</l>
   <l>To walke in equipage with better Wit;</l>
   <l>Nor worth th'observance of your curious Eye,</l>
   <l>Yet read them pray, and passe their faults; for why</l>
   <l>A stocke ungrafted never yet could yeeld</l>
   <l>Such pleasant fruite as pruned Trees: the Field</l>
   <l>Vntill'd (you know) can nothing else produce,</l>
   <l>Vnlesse wilde weeds, good to no wholesome use.</l>
   <l>Wild Grapes, though prest, yeeld no such pleasant wines</l>
   <l>As the rich clusters of the manur'd Vines:</l>
   <l>Or can the Crab-tree such an Apple beare</l>
   <l>As the faire Pippin; then Sir, shall I dare</l>
   <l>Presume to thinke my Genius or my Braines</l>
   <l>Can Echo forth such high Cothurnick straines,</l>
   <l>As those ingenious Wits, who well may claime</l>
   <l>The sacred Title of a Poets name?</l>
   <l>Farre be't from me to harbour such a thought,</l>
   <l>Since in respect of such, I'me worse than nought</l>
   <l>By many thousands: thus your pardon daigne,</l>
   <l>Excuse my faults, 'twill recompense my paine:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="5"/>
For know some time my Muse and I have spent</l>
   <l>This Worke to finish, which I now have sent.</l>
   <l>For since Report had falsely blaz'd, that I</l>
   <l>Could steale whole Verses, but not versifie,</l>
   <l>I chose a Subject thereby to expresse</l>
   <l>The skill I have, how to compact a Verse.</l>
   <l>Yet Sirs, beare with me, though they doe not run</l>
   <l>With fluent straines most sweetly on your tongue▪</l>
   <l>I ne're was lull'd asleepe upon the lap</l>
   <l>Of some sweete <hi>Muse,</hi> I never tooke a nap</l>
   <l>Vnder the shadie Leaves of <hi>Phoebus</hi> Tree,</l>
   <l>The Groves of <hi>Tempe</hi> I did never see.</l>
   <l>Th' are the first blossomes of my unskill'd Braine,</l>
   <l>Which if you please to cherish and maintaine,</l>
   <l>With the bright Sun-shine of your favour, then</l>
   <l>The uipping Frosts of selfe-opinionate men,</l>
   <l>Nor Envies blasts shall never have the power</l>
   <l>To crop the Bud of this my growing Flower.</l>
   <l>This if you grant, 'twill tye me to remaine</l>
   <l>Your constant Friend, to which I signe my Name.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>L. LAVVRENCE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>