<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100771_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03284</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1340</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100771</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The confession of faith : conteining how the troubled man should seeke refuge at his God, thereto led by faith: with the declaratio [n] of the article of iustification at length. ... Compiled by M. Henry Balnaues of Halhill, &amp; one of the Lords of session, and Counsell of Scotland, being as prisoner within the old pallaice of Roane: in the yeare of our Lord. 1548. Direct to his faithfull brethren, being in like trouble or more</title>
                 <author>Balnaves, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 244, 32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="139"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>IF it please thee, good reader, of these ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant floures, amongst the which thou hast walked at large, again to take a taste, or smelling. Thou shalt read these short abbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiations subsequent. Exhorting thee, that where any obscuritie appeareth, that thou make recourse vnto the preceeding places, where euery thing is manifestly expressed. Thou shalt doe well, if earnestlie thou shalt pray that Lord onely, to whom the haruest perteineth, that it would please him send true workemen thereto: To the manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of his owne glorie before his congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, by Iesus Christ: whose omnipotent spirite, satiate the harts of them which thirst ryghteousnesse.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>