<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Letter of the Alcayde Ali Aben∣zusian in answer of the former by which hee dedicateth the Worke to King Ali Abencirix.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100094_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16632</idno>
           <idno type="STC">354</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100094</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Letter of the Alcayde Ali Aben∣zusian in answer of the former by which hee dedicateth the Worke to King Ali Abencirix.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Almansor : the learned and victorious king that conquered Spaine. His life and death published by Robert Ashley, out of the librarie of the Uniuersitie of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Luna, Miguel de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Parker, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 79, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="reply">
   <head>The Letter of the <hi>Alcayde Ali Aben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zusian</hi> in answer of the former by which hee dedicateth the Worke to King <hi>Ali Abencirix.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>PRayse be giuen to our Souereigne God. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> To the much renowmed and that with reason for hu great skill in Gouerning, Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in conseruing, and Fortitude in mayntayning his Subiects in Peace, the valiant Warrior, strong and couragious defender of <hi>Morisme,</hi> of high and famous Progeny and Race, the great <hi>Calipha,</hi> the rooter out of his Enemies, the King highly honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and of complete power, <hi>Ali Abeneirix;</hi> the highest God continue his good desires. And in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to his Letter dated in the Palace of <hi>Zarbal,</hi> the fourth day of the Moone of <hi>Moharram</hi> this present yeare; by which I was commanded to write a Booke of the customes, conditions and manner of life of his Predecessor King <hi>Abilgua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit
<pb facs="8"/>Iacob Almansor,</hi> and therewith also to set downe and declare what other Rules a good Prince ought to obserue: for the fulfilling whereof I haue stolne from other my great businesse, some parts of the night bereauing my selfe of that sleepe which for my weake and wearied bodie had beane requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site; and in these twelue briefe and compendious Chapters which accompany this my Letter I haue rehearsed and registred the life and customes, and the manner of Ruling and Gouerning with this great King and Gouernour vsed in the time of his prosperous Raigne: and I am also of this opinion that without any farther addition of those Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings which are written by the Phylosophers and other graue and learned Authors, one may gather out of this as much fruit as he desireth. I am an eye witnesse of all that I write, hauing serued him in his Chamber and other Offices in his Royall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, of no small importance, more then twentie yeares (as is well knowne to those that frequented the Court in his time) and haue seene and knowne his customes and conditions, vprightnesse and sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, Gouernment and manner of administring justice both in Peace and Warre. Now in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of writing I worke two effects, the accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of a Royall commandement; and the registring
<pb facs="9"/>of the vertuous and laudable morall customes of so good a King. Ʋouchsafe to accept my good will and pardon my faults and ouersights if there bee any in this Treatise (whereof I doubt not there may bee many) attributing them rather to my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulnesse, then to any wilfull imperfection, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesnesse or negligence, eyther against the fidelitie of an Historie, or the loyaltie which is due to his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Seruice; whom our Souereigne God, continue in his Protection.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From the Citie of <hi>Deuque</hi>
         <date>the fifteenth day of the Moone of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beh</hi> the first,<note place="margin">This date a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth with the month of Angust of the yeare of Christ, 731.</note> the one hundred and tenth yeere of the <hi>Hixera.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>