<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Introduction.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100049_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11601</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21842</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100049</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Introduction.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The quæstion of tythes reuised : Arguments for the moralitie of tything, enlarged, and cleared. Obiections more fully, and distinctly answered .Mr. Seldens historie, so farre as mistakers haue made it argumentatiue against the moralitie, ouer-ly viewed. By William Sclater, D.D. and minister of Pitmister, in Somerset</title>
                 <author>Sclater, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 33, 6, 34-35, 6, 36-59, 72-226, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Introduction.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince I began to smatter in <hi>iudgement</hi> of questions, thus I haue euer thought of the particular; that its amongst those, that may much more easily be <hi>defended,</hi> then <hi>eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</hi> So vtterly inconse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiall, are all arguments pretended against the diuine right of Tything, yet so blind is preiudice, so earelesse the belly, so stiffe and absurd couetousnesse, in denying principles, and in spight of all premises resolued to hold the conclusion of Sacriledge.</p>
   <p>Difficultie of euiction ariseth hence: first, that <hi>opposites take from vs appearing principles, and put vs to prooue them in our owne science:</hi> secondly, haue framed to themselues principles, which no man must dare to contradict, vnder perill of his<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing at for absurditie: A principle it seemes to my poore vnderstanding. First, that praecepts of God, neuer so ancient, hauing no appearing repeale, binde euer to the end of the world.
<pb facs="4"/> Secondly, that men willing to loose Conscience from bond of any diuine praecept, such especially as but lookes towards moralitie, must be able to shew, by soundest euidence, the abrogating of that, from which they pretend to be inlarged. For what our Sauiour disclaimes, dares any attempt?<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 5.17.</note>
      <hi>Dissoluing the Law in any Iot or title?</hi> without cleare signification of the Law-giuers will for cessation? Or suppose wee, hee speakes of the maine only after the letter, and not of particulars, and degrees of dutie, couched vnder the maine? Of particulars and degrees of sinne implyed in the grosse? who should not tremble at so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane arrogancie, that heares him protest <hi>his</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 5.19.</note>
      <hi>nullitie in Gods kingdome, who breakes, or tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth breach of the lest commandement.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Tis strange libertie these licentious times haue taken; to cancell at pleasure, what their fancie distasteth in the Law of God.</p>
   <p>How vrgent is the<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 4.15, 6.</note>
      <hi>caueat against Image ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> for representation, or worship of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head; how plentifully particularized, and backt with reasons? yet goes it for current doctrine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst some Papists, that the praecept was tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porarie, peculiar to Iewes; in respect of their grosse rudenesse, and strong propension to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Its a praecept in <hi>casu,</hi> to<note n="d" place="margin">Ier. 4.2.</note>
      <hi>sweare the Lord liueth in truth, in iudgement, and in righteousnesse.</hi> A toleration rather, say Anabaptists, limited to Iewes, in their estate of weakenesse, and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. No oath lawfull to Christians in new
<pb facs="4"/> Testament, in what cause soeuer, by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie soeuer imposed.</p>
   <p>Praecept of Sabbath, ancient, some thinke, as the world for the <hi>quota</hi> of time; we are sure, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled by Gods owne finger in the two Tables of stone; yet thought a meere Iewish ceremonie, to vanish with other shadows of heauenly things, in this time of reformation.</p>
   <p>Subiection to Christian Magistrates, inioyned<note n="e" place="margin">Eph. 6.2.</note>
      <hi>in the first commandement with promise,</hi> law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse Anabaptists make proper to the State, and politie of ruder Iewes.</p>
   <p>Vsury, so damned by <hi>Moses,</hi> Prophets, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, Churches, Heathens, is deemed a sinne pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar only to the people of Iewes.</p>
   <p>Were <hi>Nicholas</hi> of Antioch now aliue; or <hi>Nichols</hi> the Familist, approaching as neere to his heresie, as to his name; they would voyce it as strongly, that fornication was a sinne peculiar to Iewes; And that Christians may liue after the licence of <hi>Plato</hi> his Common-wealth, rather then astrict themselues to these lawes of <hi>Moses,</hi> made seuerall, as their opinion seemes, to the Iewish Nation.</p>
   <p>May not <hi>Dauids</hi> Apostrophe beseeme vs in these times,<note n="f" place="margin">Psal. 119.126.</note>
      <hi>Its time for thee, Lord, to lay to thy hand, for men haue destroyed thy Law.</hi> What praecept, with greatest instance pressed, may not a licentious Libertine plead to bee exempted from? If it may be lawfull, without ground to auouch it meerely Iudaicall? Yea, how would
<pb facs="5"/> my soule wish rather to be a Iew, that dissolute nature might be restrayned in mee by lawes, and my Conscience inioy the sweete comforts found in obedience, then to inioy such liberties of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, such lawlesse licence, to be Idolatrous, lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urious, impious, Sacrilegious?</p>
   <p>Should not Christian Conscience be well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised, how it slights any the praecepts of God? Had not the euidences need be praegnant, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce vs to beleeue our freedome from their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
   <p>Thinke of it seriously, you that put vs to plead our <hi>ius,</hi> while you keepe possession of Tythes: whither it lye not rather on your Conscience, to prooue repeale of that diuine Law-giuen for Tything. Least that taxe of our Sauiour laid on the Pharisees, light on you; <hi>full well haue you</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Math. 15.6.</note>
      <hi>abrogated Gods commandement to stablish your owne tradition,</hi> or rather fancy. And<note n="h" place="margin">Iude 12.</note>
      <hi>without feare to feed</hi> your owne couetousnesse, and luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, with Gods reserued portion. Once wee are sure, a law of Tything there was giuen of God: obserued by Patriarches, ancient Iewes, and Christians; maintained by Fathers, to stand still in force: how may any dare auouch it abrogated without clearest euidence of the word of God?</p>
   <p>Their principles, such as they are, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued amongst the <hi>vulgus</hi> and their Chaplens, let vs examine. 1. That is impregnable borrowed from Manichees, pointed at by <hi>Thomas;</hi> that <hi>Christians stand bound to no praecept of Moses, or
<pb facs="5"/> Prophets, which Christ, or his Apostles haue not, in Scriptures of New Testament, giuen life vnto.</hi> Would they, I trow, be so vnderstood? that all Mosaicall; and Propheticall praecepts, which are not <hi>totidem verbis</hi> reuiued in new Testament; are now <hi>mortua? Apagesis Antinome.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Or sufficeth the protestation of our Sauiour that he<note n="i" place="margin">Math. 5.17.</note>
      <hi>came not to destroy the lest title of</hi> Moses <hi>his morall Law;</hi> and that of <hi>Paul,</hi> that<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 3.31.</note>
      <hi>faith doth not abrogate the Law, but rather stablish it,</hi> to countenance whatsoeuer Law giuen by <hi>Moses,</hi> explicated by Prophets, which was not either particularly iudiciall, or amongst the shadowes of things to come. That yeelded, till that of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be euidenced to bee amongst the seuerals of the Iewes, life it hath sufficient put into it by Christ and his Apostles, in their protestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and auouchment for the generall.</p>
   <p>But who so is acquainted with their discreetest answers to arguments grounded on Scriptures of the new Testament, shall finde them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act a praecept, punctually there speaking for Tythes; with such scorne shall hee heare argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of most apparent consequence thence drawne, reiected; because the conclusion for Tythes, <hi>vnder that name,</hi> is not extant in our testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note>
      <hi>Make the instructer partaker of all thy goods,</hi> said the Apostle. Part-taker, said an Arch-presbyter amongst them, not Tenth-taker; and pleased himselfe much in the elegance.<note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.13, 14.</note>
      <hi>As Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui ministring about holy things, liues of the Temple,</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/> &amp;c. <hi>So hath Christ ordained for them that preach the Gospel, to liue of the Gospel.</hi> To liue of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, God forbid else; but had <hi>Paul</hi> meant Tythes, doubtlesse hee would haue named them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Their second Principle then is this, that Scriptures of new Testament meane to oblige vs to no duty, but what by name it commends vnto vs. Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists, I thinke, and our lay-Parsons, are, in the grounds of their Tenants, <hi>coniurati;</hi> sworne bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> Though Christ said,<note n="n" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.16</note>
      <hi>Baptize all nations;</hi> Though <hi>Paul baptized whole housholds;</hi> though<note n="o" place="margin">Act. 2.39.</note>
      <hi>Promises,</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 10.47.</note>
      <hi>spirit,</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">Mar. 10.14.</note>
      <hi>kingdome,</hi> belongs to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, yet, after Anabaptists, neuer meant Christ to admit Infants to his baptisme? for as easie had it beene for him to name them, had hee so inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as to leaue it determinable, by doubtfull consequetiall deductions. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 3. Their third ground they haue borrowed, vnwittingly it may be, from the schoole of <hi>Thomas;</hi> the best Patron, I dare say, of their opinion. That the ancient practise of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> before the law written, was arbitrary onely, without any iniunction, or prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of God. And yet, saith, <hi>Thomas, Abraham</hi> had his Propheticall instinct which was to him a law. And may wee thinke their sacrificing, and like deuotions, or pious offices, were done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iniunctions? <hi>By faith Abel offered.</hi> Heb. 11. Therefore not without a word of God<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 26.13.</note>. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham kept Gods charge, his commandements, his sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, his lawes.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>The names, the same, as of those lawes after giuen in writing, force vs to thinke, they had their rule of faith, of worship, of life, according to which they were bound to frame their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and life. Euen of the particular, <hi>Abrahams</hi> Tything, it shall after appeare, it was done of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of Iustice, by iniunction, and therefore not, as is supposed, arbitrarily.</p>
   <p>Thus the introduction to our intendment. How loth am I, that couetousnesse should grow impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, so impious, as without warrant, or sound rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, to abrogate any law of God, intended to bee perpetuall: how faine would I perswade consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, (and if there be any, it will be perswaded) to prooue, before it affirme, the law of Tything abrogated; to evidence, before it pleade exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from it; They erre, that thinke vs onely bound, by reasons to prooue such lawes perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: those that scize the Lords ancient inheritance to themselues, those that detaine any part of that portion, must prooue it temporary, before they can warrant conscience in such practise, Cleerely God gaue such a law; according to it, practised Patriarches, Iewes, Christians vpon perswasion of obligation; ancients, as many as treated it, iudge it to binde the Christian Church. The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, the reasons of none, except demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, shall sway my iudgement, nor ought to sway anies, to thinke it temporary, belonging onely to the time, and state of the Iewes.</p>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <p>A taste of Lay-mens reasons, much swaying their conscience, let me, though something out of place, giue you; A pidling Cauiller, willing to shew his witte, would needes frame argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Tything, of the text, which gaue mee first occasion to treate the question. After many quarrellings against choice of that text of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. to support the conclusion, thus hee <hi>quaerees.</hi> What if from this text hee could frame an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment against Tythes? <hi>Ans.</hi> He should bee to me <hi>Magnus Apollo.</hi> And if out of this, or any other holy text, you could handsomely but <hi>straine</hi> an argument, I would yeeld you the conclusion.</p>
   <p>Its well with you, my Lay-masters, you haue in our free hold the eleuen points of the law. I dare say, you shall sooner fetch water out of a flint, then argument out of Scripture, to prooue your <hi>ius</hi> to them.</p>
   <p>Yet this Text would afford some <hi>Sampson</hi> one. What, trow we, may that be? if hyre or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges bee the maintenance belonging to ministers, then not Tythes: for hire is a ciuill thing, and from men by ciuill contract. Tythes are challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from God, as a diuine donation. Therefore Tythes, and wages, being of diuers nature, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not both be the ministers maintenance. But the maintenance, belonging to ministers, is hyre or wages. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Ergo:</hi> not Tythes.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ans.</hi> Wittie too too: <hi>quasi dicam,</hi> if an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be the maintenance belonging to <hi>Leui,</hi> then
<pb facs="7"/> not Tythes: for inheritances are ciuill things, descending lineally from father to son, setled vpon posterity, by ciuill, or naturall, or nationall law. Tythes are challenged to <hi>Leui</hi> from God, as a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine donation; but the maintenance belonging to <hi>Leui,</hi> is an inheritance. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Ergo,</hi> not Tythes. How easie is it to answer, that Tythes was that inheritance, and Tythes is this wages? Will you rest in an answer when you haue it? The Apostle saith not, our maintenance, whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it is, is wages, or hyre giuen by ciuill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. But from proportion of wages giuen in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice to souldiors, &amp;c. proues a reward or recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, due to Ministers for preaching the Gospel. 2. Is euery hire or wages due by ciuill contract? The <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> or wages of sinne is death. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. by ciuill contract thinke you? betwixt whom, and the sinner. 3. Alters this the nature of things, to haue many efficients? Lastly, if hyre, then not Tythes? what if Tythes be this hyre? as it was <hi>Leuies</hi> inheritance. Then though hyre, yet Tythes. Hyre imports the generall, Tythes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the particular: hath not this <hi>Sampson</hi> puld the house vpon our heads.</p>
   <p>A second argument thence drawne, is from <hi>Pauls</hi> silencing of the particular, where hee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely treates of the generall. <hi>Paul</hi> purposely treating of Ministers maintenance for perpetuitie, mentions not Tythes, where one word yet had strooke the matter dead.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p>
      <hi>Ans.</hi> Will it please you to know, that <hi>Pauls</hi> principall scope is not, to treate of maintenance; but to perswade the people, to yeeld of right in things indifferent, in fauour of the weake, by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument drawne from his example. Hee yieldes in maintenance, therefore ought they in matters of lesse moment. His secondary intention is, to auow his right to maintenance: where, though grounds be laid that concerne posteritie, yet is not that his maine purpose.</p>
   <p>His conclusion in this second intention is, that he and <hi>Barnabas</hi> had right to maintenance: must he needes descend to expresse mention of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>quantum?</hi> especially it beeing else-where sufficiently determined? what if he thought the people well enough able, out of the old Scriptures to informe themselues of the particular? This once is apparent. Scriptures of new Testament deale lest particularly, in matters plainely, and plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly particularized in the old; as in those maine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities, of obseruing Sabbath, and forbearing v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury, &amp;c. is euident.</p>
   <p>But to this Argument, <hi>Paul</hi> purposing to speake of ministers maintenance, mentions not Tythes. <hi>Ergo</hi> what? they are not due? or no thought in <hi>Paul</hi> of Tythes, as if I should say:</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Moses</hi> purposing to set forth the<note n="s" place="margin">Gen. 1.</note>
      <hi>history of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> mentions not Angels: are they therefore not created? or had <hi>Moses</hi> no thought of their creation?</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p>Our Sauiour purposely treating of the<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 5.</note>
      <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall law,</hi> and continuance thereof, speaketh not particularly of the Sabbath. How much quaestion hath the Church beene pestered withall about that Subiect? Sure our Sauiour much forgot himselfe, especially hauing praescience of things to come, that he gaue not one touch at moralitie of Sabbath, where one word had stroke the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dead. Are ye satisfied? such arguments are the best, that these mens Logicke can frame;</p>
   <p>Proceede we now <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> to reuiew of the quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion; stating it after our old course, for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillers sake, who hath laboured to perplexe it; Who knowes whether God will more blesse our second indeauours?</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>