<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOƲRABLE GEORGE, MARQVIS BVCKINGHAM, Viscount VILLEIRS, Baron of Whaddon, Iustice in Eyre of all his Maiesties Forests, Parkes and Chases beyond TRENT; Mr. of his Maiesties Horse, and one of the Gentlemen of his Maiesties Bed-Chamber, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Majesties most Honourable Priuy Counsell of ENGLAND, and SCOTLAND.</title>
           <author>Baret, Michael</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100900_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04062</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1412</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100900</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOƲRABLE GEORGE, MARQVIS BVCKINGHAM, Viscount VILLEIRS, Baron of Whaddon, Iustice in Eyre of all his Maiesties Forests, Parkes and Chases beyond TRENT; Mr. of his Maiesties Horse, and one of the Gentlemen of his Maiesties Bed-Chamber, Knight of the most noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Majesties most Honourable Priuy Counsell of ENGLAND, and SCOTLAND.</title>
                 <author>Baret, Michael</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An hipponomie or the vineyard of horsemanship : deuided into three bookes. 1. The theorick part, intreating of the inward knowledge of the man.2. The first practicke part, shewing how to worke according to that knowledge. 3. The second practicke part, declaring how to apply both hunting and running horses to the true grounds of this art. In which is plainly laid open the art of breeding, riding, training and dieting of the said horses. Wherein also many errors in this art, heretofore published, are manifestly detected. By Michaell Baret</title>
                 <author>Baret, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 48, 51-122, 20, 139, 13, 101, 1, 23, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="78"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOƲRABLE</hi> GEORGE, MARQVIS BVCKINGHAM, Viscount VILLEIRS, Baron of Whaddon, <hi>Iustice in Eyre of all his Maiesties Forests,</hi> Parkes and Chases beyond TRENT; Mr. of <hi>his Maiesties Horse, and one of the Gentlemen</hi> of his Maiesties Bed-Chamber, Knight of <hi>the most noble Order of the Garter, and</hi> one of his Majesties most Honourable Priuy Counsell of ENGLAND, <hi>and</hi> SCOTLAND.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a maine infirmity (Right<note place="margin">Ephes. 4. 18.</note> Honourable) crept into all, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer cured in any, to bee (as the Apostle saith) darkened in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding; for experience tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that the blind man is inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to many miseries; though the path be straight, yet hee will wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and though the day be cleare, yet he either sees nothing, or if any thing, yet very darkely, and none are so enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned but they see obscurely: which is the cause that all Arts and Sciences are neuer truely purged from errors, but still experience bringeth the causes of them to light, whereby
<pb facs="79"/> Mens knowledges are more refined from the drosse of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. With the waight of which, this famous Art of <hi>Horsemanship</hi> is Turkishly burthened, mens apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors being so deluded by the false euidence of the senses, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y are blindly led by the seducing guide of traditions, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer seeking any other path, but that which Antiquity hath traced; thinking that former Ages haue discouered the whole World of Truth, and that there were no Islands vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detected, that were worthy the paines of discouery by any that should futurely attempt the same. Whereby this Age is so led by opinion, that whomsoeuer they shall see to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish themselues for a voyage, to finde more fruitfull Ports, they are generlly holden factious, and will either suffer Ship-wrack, or else bring counterfeit stuffe.</p>
   <p>Which conceding implication hath brought such a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion to the true knowledge of this Art, that many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Horses are branded with the infamous title of Iades, which are of a more predominate spirit, and potency then their knowledge can comprise to bring in subiection for seruiceable vse; they often times working vpon the effect for the cause, and so hold that which is contingent to bee absolute necessary; and that such Iadish and rebellious qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities as are produced (for want of iudgement how to bring them to true obedience) are so naturally ingrafted in those horses, that they necessarily proceed from their vile dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position: Whereby these worthy Creatures receiue most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy disgrace, (through mens abuses) and are loaden with the burthen of their faults.</p>
   <p>Whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h abortiue imputation (Right Honourable) when I seriously considered, and by diligent practise obserued to bee begotten by that monster (Custome) and nursed by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and forced, as necessity by the strength of error, for
<pb facs="79"/> that such restiffe qualities are but accidents, and so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were done, were contingent, and might either bee, or not be, being but the procliuity of their dispositions: I haue armed my selfe with the helmet of courage to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter combate with that vgly and triple-headed mons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er, (not being dismayed, for the poysonous stings, of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting tongues) to free these oppressed Creatures, from the torture of this burthen, (they being but sensitiue Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) and to retort it vpon the necke of ignorant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors, who are (or should bee) reasonable Creatures, and therefore command the vnreasonable. And for the better preseruation of their worthy esteeme, I haue planted this <hi>Vineyard</hi> of <hi>Horsemanship▪</hi> and fenced it about with Reason, to nourish such impes as desire to be grafted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Wherein is set forth (as in a glasse) the causes of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, that this generous Art might bee purged from the abuses thereof; and also to bring a Horse to his highest per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that this old and blind Age can effect, by the Art of breeding and riding, vtterly reiecting all violent means as enemy to the same, but onely to worke, by true order of motions, distinction by true time, and proportionating corrections, according to the Horses disposition, for the gaining of true obedience, to agree with the man both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward that they both may be one Subiect, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the scope and period of this Art.</p>
   <p>Which I haue presumed to present vnto your Lordship to be defended in its weaknesse vnder your protection, and to be graced with the countenance of so worthy a Personage: whom it hath pleased God to giue such fauour in the eyes of our Soueraigne as to grace you with many noble dignities; to bee Maister of his Maiesties Horse. Hoping your Lordship (who is of such mild nature and worthy desert)
<pb facs="80"/> will vouchsafe to accept of this poore present, as a token of my sincere good will, and will be as a tender nurse and louing father to the diligent and true practitioners of this worthy Hyponomie. For although the Stile be rude and oftentimes corrupt through an Icarius soaring, and transcending de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to amplifie it aboue my illiterated elocution; for <hi>dum numerus addatur, pondus detrahatur;</hi> yet the grounds I know to be so true, that I will approue any part which may be held Paradoxicall, with the hazard of my life, because I had rather Sillogise them <hi>operibus</hi> then <hi>verbis.</hi> And therefore I most humbly craue pardon for my presumptuous attempt, to set your name before so weake a Worke, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your milde censure thereof, for <hi>confusa disterminat consideratio.</hi> And thus, committing your Honourable estate to the Almighties Protection, and my selfe at your Honours command, I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>In most humble and dutifull Seruice, MICHAEL BARET.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>