<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100090_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16527</idno>
           <idno type="STC">344</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100090</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The monarchicke tragedies : Crosus, Darius, The Alexandræan, Iulius Cæsar. Newly enlarged by William Alexander, Gentleman of the Princes priuie chamber</title>
                 <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>406 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Argument.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T that time when the states of <hi>Greece</hi> began to growe great, and Philosophie to be thought pretious, <hi>Solon</hi> the first light of the Athenian common-wealth like a proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Bee gathering honnie ouer many fields, learning knowledge ouer many countries, was sent for by <hi>Croesus</hi> King of <hi>Lidia</hi> as famous for his Wealth, as the other was for his Wisedome. And not so much for any desire the King had to profit by the experience of so profound a Philosopher, as to haue the report of his (as he thought it) happines approoued by the testimonie of so renoumed a witnesse. But <hi>Solon</hi> always like himselfe entring the regall Pallace, and seeing the same very gloriously apparelled, but very incommodiouslie furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with Courtiers, more curious to haue their bodies deckt with a woma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishlie affected forme of rayment, and some superficiall complements of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended curtesies, then to haue their minds enriched with the true treasure of inestimable vertue, he had the same altogether in disdaine. Therefore after some conference had with <hi>Croesus</hi> concerning the felicitie of man, his opinion not seconding the Kings expectation, he was returned with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt as one of no vnderstanding. But yet comforted by <hi>Aesop</hi> (Authour of the wittie fables) who for the time was resident at Court, and in credit with the King.</p>
   <p>Immediately after the departure of <hi>Solon, Croesus</hi> hauing two Sonnes (whereof the eldest was dumbe, and the other a braue youth) dreamd that the yongest dyed by the wound of a dart, wherewith being maruellously troubled, he maried him to a Gentlewoman named <hi>Caelia,</hi> and for farther disapointing the suspected, though ineuitable destinie, he discharged the vsing of all such weapons as he had dreamed of. Yet who could cut away the occasion from the heauens of accomplishing that which they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signd. The spiritfull youth being long restraind from the fields, was inuited by some countrie-men to the chace of a wild Boare, yet could very hardlie impetrate leaue of his louinglie suspitious father.</p>
   <p>Now in the meane time there arriued at <hi>Sardis</hi> a youth named <hi>Adra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus,</hi> Sonne to the King of <hi>Phrigia,</hi> one no lesse infortunate then valourous,
<pb facs="3"/>he hauing lost his mistresse by a great disaster, and hauing kild his brother by a farre greater, came to <hi>Croesus,</hi> by whom he was courteously enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taind, and by the instancie of the King, and the instigation of others against his owne will, who feared the frowardnes of his infectious fortune, he got the custodie of <hi>Atis</hi> (so was the Prince called) whom in time of the sport thinking to kill the Boare, by a monstrous mishap he killed. After which disastrous accident standing aboue the dead corps after the inquirie of the truth being pardoned by <hi>Croesus,</hi> he punished himselfe by a violent death. There after, <hi>Croesus</hi> sorrowing exceedingly this exceeding misfortune, he was comforted by <hi>Sandanis,</hi> who laboured to disswade him from his vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary iourney against the <hi>Persians,</hi> yet he reposing on superstitious, and wrong interpreted responses of deceauing oracles, went against <hi>Cyrus,</hi> who hauing defeated his forces in the field, and taken himselfe in the Citie, tyed him to astake to be burned, where by the exclaiming diuers times on the name of <hi>Solon,</hi> mouing the Conquerour to compassion, he was set at libertie, and lamenting the death of his Sonne, and the losse of his Kingdome, makes the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strophe of this present Tragedie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>