<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Reuerende father in god Iohn by Gods permission, Bishop of London, my speciall good Lord, all humble dutye acknow∣ledged.</title>
           <author>Temple, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100993_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13578</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23869</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100993</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Reuerende father in god Iohn by Gods permission, Bishop of London, my speciall good Lord, all humble dutye acknow∣ledged.</title>
                 <author>Temple, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon teaching discretion in matters of religion, and touching certayne abuses nowe in the Churche : preached at Paules Crosse the 21. of Nouember by Robert Temple Bachelor in Diuinitie sometimes of Magdalene Colledge in Oxforde</title>
                 <author>Temple, Robert, Bachelor in Diuinitie</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <publisher>Aggas, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bourne, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the right Reuerende</hi> father in god <hi>Iohn</hi> by Gods permission, Bishop of London, <hi>my speciall good Lord, all</hi> humble dutye acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to youre Lo. pleasure (right reuerende Father) I haue copied out this Sermon, and let it go to the presse, remouing (at length though with much a do) a common reason that diswades verie many, and did for a time discourage my selfe: I meane the peruerse cauillatiō of such, as call into question other mens la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, a greate deale busier to finde a fault, then do any good, as in deede it is easier to reprehende then iudge arighte, and mislike then do the like. I am so farre (I protest) from selfe loue or lyking, that I am still affrayde least some thinge of other bee committed
<pb facs="3"/> whiche being sette out abroade, can not bee called in againe Manie may flatter themselues in a fonde conceite of there owne doings, and delight in the fauorable iudgemente of their friendes, but they shall finde it farre otherwise, when there workes come once to a vulgar protractation. I most humblie beseech your Lo. to defend with your accustomed fauour my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthye labour, and earnestlye praye my Bretheren in the Ministrie, to laie aside all former conceaued opinion againste the matter, and hartely desire euerie good reader besides to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strue euerie thing with a consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as I for his sake in euery point haue spoken my con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>science. At your L. Mannor house at Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: Aprill 22. 1592.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your L. in all humble dutie</hi> Robert Temple.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>