<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my very good &amp; louing friends, Iohn Bannister Gentlemam, Maister in Chi∣rurgerie, and practitioner in Phisicke. William Clowes, and William Pickering Gentle∣men, and Maisters in Chirurgerie, Ihon Reade wisheth prospe∣rous successe in your doe∣ings, health of body, &amp; after this life eter∣nall felicitie.</title>
           <author>Read, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100216_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20850</idno>
           <idno type="STC">723</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100216</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my very good &amp; louing friends, Iohn Bannister Gentlemam, Maister in Chi∣rurgerie, and practitioner in Phisicke. William Clowes, and William Pickering Gentle∣men, and Maisters in Chirurgerie, Ihon Reade wisheth prospe∣rous successe in your doe∣ings, health of body, &amp; after this life eter∣nall felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Read, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most excellent and compendious method of curing woundes in the head, and in other partes of the body : with other precepts of the same arte, practised and written by that famous man Franciscus Arceus, Doctor in phisicke &amp; chirurgery: and translated into English by Iohn Read, chirurgion. Whereunto is added the exact cure of the caruncle, neuer before set foorth in the English toung. With a treatise of the fistulae in the fundament, and other places of the body, translated out of Iohannes Ardern. And also the description of the emplaister called dia chalciteos, with his vse and vertues. With an apt table for the better finding of the perticular matters, contayned in this present worke</title>
                 <author>Arcaeus, Franciscus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cadman, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 119, 1 leave, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To my very good &amp; louing friends, Iohn Bannister Gentlemam, Maister in Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie, and practitioner in Phisicke. William Clowes, and William Pickering Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Maisters in Chirurgerie, Ihon Reade wisheth prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous successe in your doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, health of body, &amp; after this life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His part of Phisicke which is called Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia (my true and louing friends) is the most auciēt &amp; principal part of medicinal practise, so highly commended of Hippocrates, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, Celsus, and other learned men, that they accoūt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> a haynous matter for any man to meddle with the same, which in deede is not a Phisition. For Chirurgery is maymed, and vtterlie vnperfect, without the healpe of those other partes, which consisteth in prescribing of inward medicines, and conuenient diet.</p>
   <p>And is so neare linked with these in a lyance, that no man deserueth to be called a Chirurgion, that is ignorant in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke.</p>
   <p>For vlcers, Apostumes, or any other extreme affects of the skinne, haue their originall from some inward cause, and nature expelleth them from thence vnto the skinne, as vnto a naturall clensing place. Likewise in wounds that are inward, there happeneth oftentimes ebullicion of humours by meanes of anger, or some other passion of the minde, wherevnto if due regard be not giuen, the Chirurgians la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is in vaine, and his topicall medicines applyed to no purpose.
<pb facs="3"/> If this seeme obscure or false vnto any man, let him reade Hippocrates touching the stuffe which a phisition is to vse. For in that place he setteth downe most euidentlie, what emplaisters, Vnguents, and other instruments, are necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for the Phisition. Let him also consider that he sheweth that the very rootes of vlcers &amp; apostumes, ought first to bee plucked vp. Let him also weigh how he teacheth, that spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall regard is to be had, to the appointing of conuenient dyet. And so shall he well vnderstand that Chirurgians ought to be seene in phisicke, and that the Barbours crafte ought not to be tearmed chirurgerie.</p>
   <p>But why am I so tedious heerein? when as the verie difinition of phisicke, doth agree with chirurgirie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if chirurgerie be phisicke, no wise man will denie but that the chirurgians ought to be seene in phisicke, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering they worke both vppon one subiect. Wherefore they ought not to be tearmed chirurgians which haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nothing but the composition of two or three emplai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters out of Barbours shoppes, neither yet Barbours them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, nor vnskilfull women, besides a number of blinde bussardly bayardes, which maister Wiliam Clowes hath most properlie painted foorth in their right coulours, in his booke entituled de Morbo Gallico, wherefore I omit them, although they confidently cracke and bragge that they can cure any thing.</p>
   <p>And with great boldnesse doe take vppon them the practise of this science, insomuch that they deptiue men of learning of their due commodities heerein. Giueing out that such are phisitions and not chirurgians. As though the chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgian ought not to be seene in phisicke, or that he could be a phisition, that were ignorant in chirurgerie.</p>
   <p>But oh good God, is it tollerable that the auncient glorie and renoume of chirurgirie should be so defaced or that such men as haue spent all their time in it, should so iniuriously be put from the benefit of the same.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>If therefore these men that haue all their time bestowed their studies in chirurgerie for the reliefe of such as are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seased: doubtles they may freely (notwithstanding the gainesaying of carping crackers and blinde empericks) vndertake the practise of this part of phisick in any place. Considering the beginning of these ordinary chirurgians, which commonlie we call barbara chirurgians, reade Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salius in his epistle which he set foorth before his worke of the frame of mans body.</p>
   <p>In which place he setteth downe the reason whie in these our daies, chirurgerie is deuided from phisick, not without great hurt vnto mankinde. I write not these things vnto you (louing friends) for that I would in anie wise abolish the auncient priuiledge which hath beene graunted in times past vnto the Barbors of the Cittie of London, for there are in the saide Cittie (which also vse Barberie) that are verie expert and skilfull in chirurgerie.</p>
   <p>But for my part let them practise this arte such as will, and are disposed to keepe them from hunger and colde.</p>
   <p>Onely this I note, the abuses heerein of our present time, yeelding altogether the practise of this noble arte, (to the great hinderance of the common weale) vnto men vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and I doe withall affirme that all chirurgians ought to be seene in phisicke: and that the Barbors crafte ought to be a distinct mistery from chirurgery. I thought it good (louing friendes) to discourse vnto you something at large in this matter, that ye might understand how farre this arte in these our daies is fallen from the auncient and true chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and how much the beautie of the same is blemished and defaced, by these obscure and base emperickes. Neither is it without cause (louing patron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>) that I haue spent all this time with you in these matters.</p>
   <p>For you are they, which in most delighted in chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, you are they, by whom chirurgerie being decayed may hope for reformacion, you are they which for your singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb facs="4"/> skill heerein, are able to iudge of all such imperfections as lurke among these busardlie empericks. You are they that are able to defend the true &amp; sincere chirurgerie, against the false and corrupt. In consideration whereof I thought it not amisse heerein to publish vnto you (my courteous friends) these <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uctors which I haue translated, hoping there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that the ruder sorte being alured with the facilitie and easinesse of the same, will more earnestly apply their mindes to the learning thereof. And that many will bee moued hereby the sooner, whome otherwise conceit of difficultie might haue feared away.</p>
   <p>But I am assured that I shall hereby incurre the hatred of the enuious, and the reprehencions of carping quarrellers. But that some profite may come by this my paynes, vnto such as are studious in Chirurgerie, I esteeme nothing of them, for I know I shall be easilie able to put to silence those vnnaturall persons.</p>
   <p>It may be that some will thinke me of Antisthenes faction, that laide platformes of euery mans life, and yet the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher was more wise in his precepts, then wary of his owne gouernment and say, I haue reached aboue my skill, in limiting other mens doeings. But if I haue intermedled to farre, it is (curteous friends) not in censuring the actions of the good and vertuous, but in discouering the abuses of the lewde. For I reprehend not as one thinking generally all bad, hut perswade, as one wishing perticularlie euerie one should liue well, and dye better.</p>
   <p>And therefore (my curteous friends) I am most earnestly to craue your assistance (in protecting this rude worke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the first fruits of my trauaills. For Damydas caused his Parret to pearke vnder a Dragon of Brasse, to defend it from the vultures tyrannie.</p>
   <p>And I shrowde this simple worke, vnder your curteous patronages, that the malitious, whose toungs cut like swords, may like the Serpent feare to offende that hear be, whereon
<pb facs="4"/> the beames of the Sunne doth rest. And therefore doe your endeuours that this noble Arte of Chirurgerie (now lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing and decaying) may by your good meanes and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance, beginne againe to florish.</p>
   <p>And being as it were heretofore dead, recouer her life and decayed estate, and that by your good assistance, learned professours may be appointed in all conuenient places, to publish and set foorth the same. For so will it come to passe, that in short time this famous Arte will bee restored to her auncient perfection, vnto the great commoditie of the common weale.</p>
   <p>If anie that are enuious grudge at my doings, I straight for refuge flie to your good Cencure, which I count as a sufficient defensorie against such as loue to backebite. Committing therefore my bookes to your patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, least the gates being to bigge for the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the mountaine should seeme to swell and bring foorth a Mouse. Thus wishing you all such happie successe as you can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, and I imagine, I ende.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in curtesie bounden, IOHN READ Chirurgian.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>