<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worship∣full Sir John Stanhope Knight, the Father of the bridegroome Knight, my most louing and good Patron.</title>
           <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100549_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19091</idno>
           <idno type="STC">55</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100549</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worship∣full Sir John Stanhope Knight, the Father of the bridegroome Knight, my most louing and good Patron.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A vvedding sermon preached at Bentley in Darby-shire : vpon Michaelmasse day last past anno Domini. 1607. Wherein is set forth the bond and preseruation. ... By R. Abbot</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 67, 7 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sir <hi>John Stanhope</hi> Knight, the Father of the bridegroome Knight, my <hi>most louing and good Patron.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worshipfull Knight my verie good Patron, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I made a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion of vsing your name, for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing of so small a matter as this sermon is; yet I easily resolued that sith it had pleased you to craue the copy thereof, you would pardon mee to grace it with the dedication. I
<pb facs="3"/> might wel doubt to offer so little wher I owe so much, but that I considered that small offices sometimes are testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of great affectiōs, &amp; presumed that according to your wonted loue, you would take the wil in good worth, howsoeuer the worke seeme to bee of small import. Accept it therefore I humbly pray you, as a very thankfull acknowledgement of your great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour towards mee, both in calling me, first to the place where now I liue, and giuing me since such respect and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, as whereby I haue with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and contentment enioyed the same. And surely if therein I haue done in publicke any profitable ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to the Church of God, a great part thereof is to bee reputed to you, who so freely and graciously of your owne voluntary accord, and onely for the workes sake which I perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, being my selfe wholy strange and vnknowne to you, vouchsafed by
<pb facs="3"/> your gift to free mee of that incessant labour wherein I had beene imployed before, for the space of tenne yeares in reading and preaching in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Church and Citie of Worcestor, and to setle mee in a place, where I might more freely dispose of my selfe, though not to withdraw my selfe from the seruice to which I had deuoted my selfe, yet in some part to bestow my time to the common benefit of the whole Church, which before was limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to one onely congregation. Amidst which imployments, either publicke or priuate, if I attaine to doe any thing to yeeld you any helpe or furtherance in things appertaining to God, and in Gods behalfe to answer the end wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at you aimed in your first acceptance of me, I much reioyce therein, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer shal reioyce, and thinke that houre or time happily bestowed, wherein I shall be <hi>the helper of your ioy,</hi> and<note place="margin">2. Co 1. 24</note> of that faith wherby you shall stand in
<pb facs="4"/> the day of the Lord Iesus. As for this sermon, being but a countrey exercise, if any shall thinke it not so well po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished as that it should bee fit in this sort to goe abroad, your approbation shall be my excuse, and in that nature I commend it to you that haue desired it, wishing with it to you, and to your whole house, all happines and honour, and that the Oliue by my seruice im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted into your stocke, may yeeld many branches, to the enlarging and strengthning thereof, so resting al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all dutie, much bounden and deuoted, R. Abbot.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>