<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100538_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69095</idno>
           <idno type="STC">50.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100538</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The third part of the Defence of the Reformed Catholike : against Doct. Bishops Second part of the Reformation of a Catholike, as the same was first guilefully published vnder that name, conteining only a large and most malicious preface to the reader, and an answer to M. Perkins his aduertisement to Romane Catholicks, &amp;c. Whereunto is added an aduertisement for the time concerning the said Doct. Bishops reproofe, lately published against a little piece of the answer to his epistle to the King, with an answer to some few exceptions taken against the same, by M. T. Higgons lately become a proselyte of the Church of Rome. By R. Abbot Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 184, 183-385, 1, 80, 91-108, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE <hi>to the Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Christian Reader, thou shalt vnderstand, that vntill the greater part of this Booke was prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I thought I had giuen thee therein an answer to all that Doct. Bishop had published vnder the name of his Second part. But being at Southwell not long since to doe my dutie to the most Reuerend Father, the L. Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of Yorke, his Gr. being pleased to vse speech to me concerning a point in the said Second part, and shewing me thereof the booke it selfe, I perceiued a defect in that that I had answered, finding there handled the other questions of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Catholike which he had left vntouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his former booke, and whereof in the booke which I had receiued, there was
<pb facs="3"/>conteined nothing. In turning the booke I found a fault of the Print in the answer to the Aduertisement, corrected in the end of the questions, whereby I presently percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that he first printed his vngodly Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face here conteined, and the said answer, &amp; for some cunning deuice (what it might be I leaue to thee to ghesse) did thus publish the beginning and end of the booke, and left the middle part to be added at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure afterward. As it first came foorth, so I receiued it, enquiring after no more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I thought I had receiued all, and knowing of no more, I haue written to no more, and had I knowen of the rest before I had printed so much of this, I would haue suppressed this till I had confuted that as I haue done this. And heereby thou vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standest the cause why I haue in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this booke taxed M.
<note place="margin">
         <hi>Preface. sect.</hi> 22 <hi>pag.</hi> 190. <hi>Aduert. sect.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 193. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </note> Bishop for the omitting of those questions, because hee himselfe had then diuulged his book with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, neither had I heard that he had written any thing of them: which taxations though now I cannot alter, yet by this Preface I reuoke, and doe wish thee to passe
<pb facs="3"/>them ouer, as if they were not there at all. Albeit where I might alter them I haue so done, and therefore recalled from the Presse the copie of my Preface and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisement heere adioyued, wherein I had further noted that omission; by meanes whereof, and for the adding of an answer to some few exceptions taken against mee by M. Higgons, lately reuolted from vs, so soone as I could get the sight thereof, this booke hath been somwhat longer in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming foorth than otherwise it should haue beene. To which, being, though not by my default, thus maimed and vnperfect, I haue done some disgrace by withdrawing from it the Dedication which I had intended; being notwithstanding, good Reader, to intreat thy gentle patience to take this in good part, till God shall giue me opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie heereafter to adde the rest. Heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I say, because it shall first be necessarie for mee to returne a Counterproofe to Doct. Bishops Reproofe, lately published against a little peece of my answer to his Epistle. Concerning which worke of his, (being such as I presume will in the end
<pb facs="4"/>make him odious and hatefull to all men that will take knowledge of it) I haue heere added some aduertisement for the time, and giuen an answer to his Preface, wherein he hath taken vpon him to haue said so much <hi>as may suffice to discredit me with all indifferent men,</hi> that whereas it will require some longer time to examine his Reproofe in that sort as I intend it, I may notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing in the meane time somewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the edge, and remooue the scandall of it, whilest by discouery of some of his iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings (if at least being so grosse and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they deserue to be called iuglings) the Reader shall be able to conceiue what he is in all the rest. I will heere amplifie nothing further, but refer thee to those obseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that I haue giuen thee thereof. God giue his blessing both to my writing and to thy reading, that we may both grow in hatred of Antichristian error, and in the knowledge and loue of the trueth of God.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord</hi> R. ABBOT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>