<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The preface of thys boke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100594_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02599</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1273.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100594</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The preface of thys boke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first two parts of the Actes, or vnchast examples of the Englysh votaryes : gathered out of their owne legenades and chronycles by Iohan Bale, and dedycated to our most redoubted soueraigne kynge Edward the syxte</title>
                 <author>Bale, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 <publisher>Bale, John, Bishop.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, cxx, 4 leaves, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <pb n="2" facs="11"/>
   <head>¶ The preface of thys boke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ildas that aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyent Brytayne, in hys fyrst treatyse of the dolorouse destruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of hys contreye, hath this worthyesen thence agaynste them which were the chefe cause therof. And borowed it is of the. xxiiij. chaptre of Salomons prouerbes. Whosoeuer cōmendeth the wicked (saieth he) and reporteth them righteouse or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye,<note place="margin">Pro. 24</note> the same shall ones haue the course of the people, and the comminalte shall ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre hym. Plentuouse hath the Popes clergie bene in his poynt, speciallye in the churche here of Englande. Not onlye haue they commaunded vnto vs whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, bawdes, brybers, Idolaters,<note place="margin">Romish sayntes.</note> hy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pocrytes, trayters, and most fylthy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morreanes, as Godlye men and women, but also they haue canonysed thē for most holye sayntes, set them vp gylt Images in their temples, commaunded their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gils to be fasted, appoynted them holy da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yes and the peoples to do them honoure with euensonges, howres, processiōs, ligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, masses, ryngynges, synginges, sensyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, and the deuyll and al of suche heyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshe wares. They haue done by vs as
<pb facs="12"/>
theyr olde predecessours the Idolatrouse prestes ded by the auncyent Romanes. They haue set vs vp a sorte of lecherouse Goddes to be worshypped in oure tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,<note place="margin">Olde goddes &amp; newe.</note> to be our aduocates, and to helpe vs in our nedes. In stede of Iupiter, Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, Mercurye, Mars, Iuno, Proserpina, Diana, and Venus, whiche ded all their feates in whoredome, as the poetes vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth, they haue geuen vs Wenefryde, Cuthbert, Dunstane, Oswalde, Ansel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tket, Brigyde, Audrye, Modwen, Edith, Osith, Ethelburge, and a greate sort more of vnpure workers out of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryage.</p>
   <p>Marke the lyues of their Englyshe sayntes, almoste from the begynnynge, &amp; ye shall not fynde one of them canonysed for preachynge Christes veryte a ryghte, neyther yet for leadynge a lyfe after the perfyght rules of the Gospell. Not one commende they for worshyppynge God wythoute mennys tradycyons, nor yet for executynge the workes of Mercye, vnles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se yt were to their aduauntage. Neuer rec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kened they wedlock anye Godlye esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of lyuynge, thoughe yt were an onlye ordre instytuted of God in the begynnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, yea, for hys prestes also. Commonlie they haue dyswaded bothe men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from yt, as from a most pernycyou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se euyll,<note place="margin">Dyffa-</note> or from a myschefe of all mysche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes,
<pb facs="12"/>
callynge yt folyshnesse, fylthynesse, beastlynesse, a walkynge in darkenesse,<note place="margin">Maciōs of Marri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>age.</note> a mayntenaūce of lechery, a fulfillinge of fleshlye desyres, a grounde of all vyce, an entraunce of deathe, a corruptynge of maydenhode, a lake of myserye, a clay pytt of vnclennesse, a thraldome of Egipt a ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>te of Sathan, a snare of the deuyll, &amp; a ponde of perdicyon, loke Iohan Cap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>graue <hi>in Catalago sanctorum Anglie,</hi> special<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye in the lyues or legendes of Clarus, Eanswyde. kyneswyde, Etheldrede, we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefrede, Mylburge,<note place="margin">Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mye.</note> and Myldrede wyth suche other lyke, and ye shall fynde my wordes moste true. In the hystorye of Saynt Vrsula haue they named thē An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of darkenesse whiche hath persuaded marryage laufull. Of whose nōbre was firste God the eternall Father, and than Moses and the Prophetes for the olde la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we. And afterwarde Iesus Christe hys eternall Sonne, wyth Peter Paule, &amp; the other apostles, for the newe lawe. Were not the men (thynke yow) wele ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seane?</p>
   <p>So peruerse stomakes haue they bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to women, that the more par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of their temptynge spretes they haue made she deuyls (loke their Saintes legendes) but he that tempted Christ was an he deuyll, a relygyouse deuyll, and a prestlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll. Whā they haue bene tempted wyth
<pb facs="13"/>
lecherouse spretes in the lykenesse of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, they haue (they saye) by the suffren vertu of holy water,<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyls.</note> turned them into deuyls agayne. But neuer were they yet so connynge with all their holye water, as to make of theyr whores honest mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed women. No, yt is not their ordre, to do suche myracles. In the lyfe of Saynt Godrick is mencyon of a she, deuyll, but in the conclusion, he apereth with han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge ware of no small quantyte, hauin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge hys yonge ones folowynge hym wyth shauen crownes. Of a lykelyhode ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for he was some spirituall he tempted, &amp; hys chyldren wythin holye orders. Such power had Saynt Guthlake ouer those watchinge wormes, that he made them to tarry with hym, and to buylde hym vp a monastery at Ascendyck, now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Crowlande, some saye. To be short in thys matter. Their sayntes in a maner were all vnmaried.<note place="margin">Sayntes vnmari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> If anye were mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that wolde nedes be sayntes, they we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re anon compelled by othe, or by the waye of penaunce, to leaue their makes to the occupieng of others, the man his wyfe, and the woman her husbande, as ye shal beholde in this boke by most plentuouse examples. For matrimony hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bene suche a blacke bugge in their si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoge and churche, that neuer wolde canonysacyon serue yet, where as was
<pb n="4" facs="13"/>
in place.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding we are throughly as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertayned by innumerable scripturs and argumentes, that matrimonye is of God, and by their innumerable examples of fylthynesse, that their vowed wyueles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se and husbandelesse chastyte is altogy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the deuyll. Sens the gloriouse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce of the Gospell haue that Sodo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miticall swarme or brode of Antichrist (that ye call the spiritualte) bene oft ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes admonyshed of their fleshlye er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours by the manyfest scripturs therof. that they shulde ones repente theyr most horryble myschefes,<note place="margin">Votari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es.</note> and graunt vnto ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryage the fredome due therunto. And what haue they done, thynke you? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge els at all but laughed them to scorne, reportynge them to be but fables and lyes. The learned allegacyons, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and argumentes of Philyp Melāch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton, Luther, Lambert, Pomerane, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and suche other, they haue hearde,<note place="margin">Christen doctors.</note> but the answere is yet to make. They mocke and mowe at them like Iack a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes or lyke them which went vp &amp; dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne by the crosse whan Christ was crucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, and that is ynough for them. For they haue it of their popes lawe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere no man, yea although they wryte their abhominacions to the vttermoste,
<pb facs="14"/>
vnlesse they haue hym in preson. I haue therfor thought yt best,<note place="margin">The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour.</note> seynge they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde not the sacred scrypturs, to laye before them their abhomynable practy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and examples of fylthynesse, by their owne legendes, Chronicles, and sayntes Liues, that all men maye knowe what legerdemaynes they haue vsed, and what lecherouse liues they haue led here in Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande▪ sens the worldes beginninge. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te them now be ashamed of their beastly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, or els put on their mothers face al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither.</p>
   <p>In the first part of this boke, maye men breuelie beholde how and by whome this realme was firste inhabited, which thynge hath bene hytherto in all Englysh Chronicles,<note place="margin">Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</note> doubtfullie, vnagreablye, yea, and vntrulie treated, vpon coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs, fantasies, and lies onlye, by reason of ignoraunce in the scripturs and moste auctorised histories. They shall also per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue, what peoples haue here by all ages remained, what doctrines hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne thaught by their true and false prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, what worshippinges of God they haue vsed, and what lawes in religion they haue folowed. Finallie they shall knowe clerelie, the deceytfull workeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of the instrumentes of Sathan, their Bishoppes, prestes,<note place="margin">Prestes</note> &amp; monkes, with other disgised locustes of the same generacion.
<pb facs="14"/>
Whose contynuall stodye, labour, and seking was alwaies to blinde them by a colour of chast lyuynge / makinge them to beleue, that their maryenge of wiues was a prophane layte / a brutishe beastly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse / and a thynge which greatlye dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased God / Their owne vowynge of vyrgynyte was againe (they said) a spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ordre, a lyfe of Angels,<note place="margin">Marria<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge.</note> and an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye religon which pleased God aboue all other, what though they neuer had it in their liues. For true virginite is a fayth vncorrupted,<note place="margin">Virgini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te.</note> or a beleue gouerned by the onlye worde of God without all supersticions of men. This was the onlye virginite that Marye was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended of / <hi>Lucc.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Faythe</note> This virginite per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth chefely to marriage, as testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth Saynt Paule. 2. Cor. 11.<note place="margin">2. Cor 11</note> And as ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in Abraham and other iust fathers which had faythfull wiues. No people are lesse acquaynted with this virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te than sectaries, or they that vowe vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginite / for they chefelye depende vpon mennis tradicions and rules.</p>
   <p>But if a tre maie be knowne by his frutes, and a man by hys dedes, as oure sauer sayth they maye, <hi>Math.</hi> 7,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> ye shall easely perceyue by their actes, that these virginall votaries hath bene the verye Angels of darkenesse. Marke their gost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye conueyauntes, and their other good
<pb facs="15"/>
workes (as they will haue them yet cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) like as they are here regestred in course. And ye shall finde them more fyt for hell than for heauen. Yea must they be canonised sayntes, and do most won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull miracles. But those miracles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the stronge delusions (saynt Paule sayth) that the Lord will sende vnto them that shall perish for their vnbeleues sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke.<note place="margin">Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</note> 2. <hi>Thessalon,</hi> 2. I doubt not but this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of mine, though it be very sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, will ministre some light as wele to the learned as vnlearned. At the least it shall teache them to iudge false mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, that they be no more so deuylishly de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued. Lete not the oft citing of autours be greuouse to the readers,<note place="margin">Autours</note> my occasion iustly considered. For therby shall the papistes haue shame alwayes, if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them fables, or els me a liar for the tellynge of them, beynge in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges so manyfest. And as concernin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge those autours, they were their owne dere fryndes, and wrote the best they coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of them. If they had bene their enemy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, and so shewed the worst of them, or els but indyfferent wryters as they were most parcyall witnesses, it hadde bene a farre other shew of their mischefes than here will apere.</p>
   <p>Men trusted they wolde haue seane them selues in this clere lyght of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell,
<pb n="6" facs="15"/>
and so haue repented their former factes of falsehede. But truly they are of a farre other kynde than so.<note place="margin">Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes.</note> Their nature is not to repent. do they neuer so manye mischefes. Rather stody they out newe practyses of tyrannye and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels of cruelte, to adde myschefe to mys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe, tyll the great vengeaunce promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed lyght fullye vpon them. Who so euer hath promoted forewarde Gods ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryte (they thanke God of it) they haue bene non of them as yet.<note place="margin">Gospell</note> Yf they shuld make their boastes with Paule. 1. Corin. 15. that they haue done therin more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours than the other discyples, men of knowlege wolde by and by saye, that they lyed most falselye. In dede they ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue wyth Menelaus, Alchimus, Auantas, and with Cayphas gone afore all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye tyrauntes in the murtheringe vp of them whice hath done it. And for er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rours,<note place="margin">Errour.</note> they saye. But wha euer erred as they haue done, sens the worldes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge? Trulye non as yet. Neyther, Turke, Iewe, Saracene, Pagane, nor deuyll, as the examples herafter wylll shewe,, they shall not be able to auoyde yt, vnlesse they dyspute with fyer and faggottes as they haue done hytherto. For starke nought are they in dysputacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ōs, where as they are not at hād. For this boke. I shall haue their common lyuery,
<pb facs="16"/>
and be called a thousande tymes herety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. But neyther loke I for reasonable an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere of them, nor yet for amendement of their knaueryes.</p>
   <p>In this boke of mine, is one face of An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tichrist chefelye disclosed (parauenture iij. vndre one) wherwyth he hath of longe tyme paynted out hys whore,<note place="margin">Face of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaist.</note> the Rome churche that she mighte to the world ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a gloriouse madame. That face is her vowed chastyte, wherby she hath deceyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye boasted herself spirituall, beynge but whore and thefe, and dysdayned mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryage as a vyle draffe sacke,<note place="margin">Narria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth lay</note> and dyrtye dyshe cloute, callynge all them but lewde laye persones that were vndre yt, though they were kynges and quenes, Lordes, &amp; ladies. Ye noble gouerners and learned lawers, vnto whom God hath in thys a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge delyuered the measurynge rodde of hys worde, as he ded to Iohan. Apocal. 11. that ye shulde measure all thynges right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Be not now slacke in your offyces, as in the blind tyme, but thorow fourth that wretched bonde woman with her dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, that Rome churche with her whorish<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse. No poynt of nobylyte were it,<note place="margin">nobilite</note> nor yet of learned worthinesse, to be as ye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue bene of late yeares, styll seruaunte sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to a moste filthye whore, and to her whoredome and whoremongers. Our most christen Emperour of Englande, kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="16"/>
Hērye the. viij. of that name,<note place="margin">Kynge Henry.</note> &amp; now his most learned &amp; graciouse sonne kynge Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the .vi. a moste worthye ministre of God, hath gone before yow in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. They haue made open vnto ye the way, and dryuen away from your gates the great aduersarie that shuld most haue noyed yow. Disdayne not than yow to fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe. Take from your true subiectes, the popes false Christ with his belles and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blinges, with his miters &amp; mastries,<note place="margin">Christ.</note> with his fannoms and fopperyes, and lete them haue frely the true Christ again that their heauenlie father sent them from aboue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shioned out vnto thē in the Gospell. For much more bewtifull is he in the sighte of true beleuers, than are all the corrupt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men, with all their gorgiouse apa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>relinges. Loke you therunto with earnest<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse, for nothinge will be at the lattre day more straightly required of you than that.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>