<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The Praeface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100580_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00753</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1088</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100580</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The Praeface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Comfortable notes vpon the bookes of Exodus and Leuiticus, as before vpon Genesis : Gathered and laid downe still in this plaine manner, for the good of them that cannot vse better helpes, and yet are carefull to read the Scriptures, and verie desirous to finde the comfort in them. By the Reuerend Father in God Geruase Babington ... With a table of the principall matters contained in this booke</title>
                 <author>Babington, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Chard (Chare, Chayre), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 428, 427-446, 445-466, 2, 12, 223, 1 page, folded table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="244"/>
   <head>❧ The Praeface.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> his speech in one place, <hi>That almost</hi>
         <note place="margin">Singulas fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re syllabas spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare Coelestia sacramenta.</note>
         <hi>euery syllable of this Booke of Leuiticus conteyneth a myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi> A great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to stirre vp all God his people, both to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it, and to a verie great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer we read in it. We see by experience, that, if a man happen to finde any old and ancient Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of some Famous man, that liued many yeeres ago, with any inscription of old Letters or Characters, how he reioiceth at it, keepeth it, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it to his friends, and is neuer wearie of it. Much more should it please vs to view and marke the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Figures of this Booke, wherin (as in pictures) Iesus Christ, the great King of all Kings, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Sonne of almightie God was set-out and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed to the world before he came, and still most
<pb facs="245"/>
profitably noted and knowne now, when hee is come. Let vs therefore begin to read this heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Booke with comfort, &amp; continue the same with constancie, to the end. And (most gracious Father) for thy deere Sonnes sake, I beseech thee, throw my sins out of thy sight, that make me vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to come nere thy word, much more, both to taste the sweetnes of it my selfe, and to be a means that others may doe the like with mee. And as it hath pleased thee to vouchsafe mee a place of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in thy Church, with many and many mercies more, &amp; to stir my heart vp to this course of doing some part of my dutie in the same; so vouchsafe to giue power to my will, and to enable me with thy grace, that I may see and set downe, obserue and note what may bee to this end; namely, to worke, both in mine owne soule, and in the hearts of thy deere Chosen, knowledge and feeling of thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly truth, that may bee to the praise of thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable goodnesse and our owne aeternall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for euermore. O grant it, (sweet Lord) grant it, and be strong in weakenesse, as thou hast promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to be. Let no sinne of mine, or of thy people that shall euer vse my poore labours, hinder and hold this mercie from vs.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>Amen, Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>