<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100164_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7419</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100164</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mischiefe and miserie of scandals both taken, and giuen. By Ier. Dyke, minister of Epping in Essex</title>
                 <author>Dyke, Jeremiah</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 192, 191-242 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is not any one thing that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan the professed enemie of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind labours, and endeauours more, then the hindrance of the saluation of man. There is but one way to Heauen, that which <hi>Peter</hi> cals the <hi>way of Truth,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2. which <hi>Salomon</hi> cals <hi>the way of good men, Prou.</hi> 2. 20. which <hi>Isaie</hi> cals <hi>the way of Holinesse, Isai.</hi> 35. 8. which <hi>Ieremie</hi> cals <hi>the old, and the good way,</hi> and <hi>the ancient pathes, Ier.</hi> 6. 16, 18, 15. Now Sathan to
<pb facs="5"/> keepe men from Heauen, doth his vtmost to make men stumble at, and <hi>from the ancient pathes,</hi> that by taking offence at the waies of God, disliking, and distasting them, the saluation of their soules might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come impossible.</p>
   <p>To effect their stumbling at those wayes Sathan layes many and sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie kinds of stumbling blockes in the wayes of men. But yet amongst those many ones, I find there bee some more dangerous then others, and by which the Deuill preuayles much more then by the rest. And those I obserue and conceiue to be specially these three.</p>
   <p n="1">1. The Reproach, Contempt, and Obloquie, that by some men is vsually cast vpon Religion and the conscionable profession, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessours thereof. Sathan tels men that if they will needs goe this way they shall haue a deale of filth and dirt flung in the faces of them, that
<pb facs="6"/> they must looke to be scorned, and Reproached, as if they were the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Of-scourings of the earth.</hi> And this very thing starts and stumbles not a few. Some will better abide a stake, then some others can a mocke. <hi>Zedekiah</hi> could happily haue found in his heart to haue hearkened to the Prophets coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, but that this lay in the way, <hi>I am afraid of the Iewes, least they deliuer me into the Caldaeans hands, and they mocke me, Ier.</hi> 38. 19. It was death to him to be mocked. But all considered, we shall see how little reason any haue for this to stumble at Religion. For doe but consider who they are commonly that mock at Godlinesse. Doe but obserue their Character in the Scriptures, and you shall finde them such as these. A company of Hypocrites. <hi>Hypocriticall mockers, Psal.</hi> 35. 16. A crue of Drunkards, <hi>Psal.</hi> 69. 12. <hi>I am the song of Drunkards.</hi> A sort
<pb facs="6"/> of vitious persons, following their lusts, <hi>There shall come scoffers wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after their owne lusts,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 3. A company of <hi>Abiect persons, Psal.</hi> 35. 15. Like those enemies, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 5. <hi>Lewd fellowes of the baser sort.</hi> A rout of prophane godlesse irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Atheists that do no more know the Power, then Turkes, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens know the truth, of Godlines, <hi>The foole hath said in his heart there is no God, you haue made</hi> a mocke <hi>at the counsell of the poore, because the Lord is his trust, Ps.</hi> 14. 1, 6. It is a shrewd suspition, that he that is a Mocker is an Atheist, It well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes him to mocke at Religion that denies a God, and it is a signe that he denies a God, that mockes at Godlinesse. And will any wise man stumble at Religion for such mens Mockes and Reproaches? What can be expected better from them? It was a good answere that that Oratour gaue <hi>Salust, Neque e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim</hi>
      <note place="margin">Orat. in Salust.</note>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>qui, ita vt tu, vixit aliter, quam tu loqui potest,</hi> It cannot be but that he that liues thy life, should speake thy language, and it is an answere will serue the turne in this case; To looke for other language from men of so ill lifes, were to expect to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grapes of thornes. Let no man for such mens mockes and reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches bee stumbled at Religion, or thinke euer the worse of it. A man would choose his Religion by such mens enmitie, and it is the great honour of Religion that it hath such Aduersaries. <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Consulito comme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>s vestros, ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perietis primum Neronem in hanc sectam tum maximae Romae orientem Caesariano gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio ferocisse. Sed tali dedicatore damnationis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strae gloriamur. Qui enim scit illum, intellige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re potest non nisi aliquod bonum grande à Nero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne damnatum. Tentauerunt &amp; Domitian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s, &amp;c.—Tales nobis semper In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutores, Iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti, Impij, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes quos &amp; ipsi damnare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suestis, à quibus damnatos resti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuere soliti estis.</hi> Tertull. Apol. cap. 5.</note> It was that wherein the Primitiue Christians vsed to glorie that they had <hi>Nero</hi> their first Persecutor, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their persons and Religion, <hi>Inasmuch as they that knew him could not but know that it must needs bee some great good which</hi> Nero <hi>did condemne.</hi> It was the honour of Christians, and their Religion that <hi>Nero</hi> and such as he was, <hi>vniust, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>filthy persons,</hi> whom the Heathen themselues condemned were the sorest, and bitterest ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies they had. No wise man would haue stumbled at Christian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, because it had such an enemie as <hi>Nero</hi> was, A wiseman would haue loued it the better. The case is the same here, It is the honour of Godlinesse, and Religion, that it hath <hi>Hypocrites, Drunkards, viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous followers of their lusts, base and lewd fellowes, godlesse Atheists,</hi> for her scoffing Aduersaries. It must needs bee some great good which they hate, and scorne, I know scarce a better argument to perswade men to loue and embrace it, then that such men hate and deride it.</p>
   <p n="2">2. The Pouertie, the meane, and homely outside of such for the most part, as receiue &amp; professe Christ, and his Gospel. What should you doe looking this way, sayes Satan; <hi>Haue any of the Rulers, or of the</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>Pharisees beleeued on him? But this people, &amp;c. Iohn</hi> 7. 48. What a fond thing is it to follow this Christ whom none but a company of the meaner sort of people fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low? The greater, and richer sort of the world they like not, nor look not this way, but onely a few of the lower ranke, and condition of men. And how-euer many are stumbled at this, yet indeed little reason is there that any should in such a case be scandalized. So much the lesse reason because our Sauiour hath so fore-armed and fenced vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this Scandal, <hi>Math.</hi> 11. 5, 6. <hi>The poore receiue the Gospel.</hi> Why then, might some say, wee will not receiue this Christ, and this Gospell, which for the most part onely the poorer sort receiue. Therefore see what our Sauiour addes to preuent such scandal. <hi>And blessed is hee that is not offended in me,</hi> that is <hi>in mee</hi> a Christ recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="8"/> and professed by the poorer sort. How could men like well of Godlines in <hi>gay apparell,</hi> and with <hi>a gold ring,</hi> but the vile rayment makes it vile in their eyes, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider not that God hath chosen the vile things of this world, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the things that are mighty, that God hath chosen <hi>the poore of this world</hi> rich in faith, heyres of the kingdom which he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. 5. When <note n="*" place="margin">Iulian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> dixit, <hi>&amp; si Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losoph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>rum ego Senatū aduo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> tu continuo s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>dularios opifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, omne{que} in nos vulgus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cēdas,</hi> Augusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus dixit. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumeliosus es in infirma mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di quae elegi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> deus vt confun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret fortia,</hi> Aug. contr. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>g. li. 1,</note>
      <hi>Iulian</hi> the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagian gibed <hi>Augustine</hi> that he had not the wise sages, nor the learned Senate of Philosophers, <hi>but onely a company of meane tradesmen, handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craftes men of the vulgar sort,</hi> that tooke part with him, he sweetly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers, <hi>Thou reproachest the weake things of the world, which God hath chosen to confound the things that are mighty.</hi> That one thing may suffice to keepe men from stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling at homely outsides. Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if men had but an eye of faith
<pb facs="9"/> in their heads. Carnal eyes that are dazeled with the glittering out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides of worldly glories are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at such seeming basenesse, but faith blindes it selfe against such fleshly Scandals, and will not see them, when it sees them, but lookes thorough them, and sees glory thorough them. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 14. <hi>And the word was made flesh, and wee beheld his glory, as the glory of the onely begotten sonne of the father,</hi> though his glory were obscured with the vaile of the flesh, yet this vaile hides not glory from the eye of faith, faith did looke thorough this vaile and easily discerned him the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and only begotten sonne of the father, euen in the abasement of his Incarnation. The wisemen that came from the East, when they saw <hi>Herod</hi> at <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> happily in all his royall Robes, yet fall not downe not worship him; They come to <hi>Bethlehem</hi> and finde Christ in a
<pb facs="9"/> poore fashiō, happily in little better then rags, &amp; yet they fall downe &amp; worship him. Why fall they downe before a meane poore Christ, and not before a Magnificent, &amp; glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Herod?</hi> Why rather are they not scandalized at Christs base<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and pouerty? This is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of faith, In Christs Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy it saw Antiquity, in his base<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse beauty, in his meannesse ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, and more glory in Christs rags, then in <hi>Herods</hi> Robes. So surely if men did liue and walke by faith, and not by sight, neuer would Christ nor his Truth be stumbled at for the homely and poore out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side of those that professe him. The purblind eye of flesh cannot pierce through these vayles and cloudes, And what wonder is it to see a blinde man stumble?</p>
   <p n="3">3. But yet the sorest and greatest stumbling blocke of all, is the scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous sinnes and falles of such as
<pb facs="10"/> professe religion: certaine it is that these of all others are the most pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous stumbling blockes by which Satan causes multitudes of men to stumble at religion, and workes them to the dislike of the wayes of saluation. Afflictions and Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions for the Gospells sake are dangerous stumbling blockes, and by reason of them many are so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at religion, as that they turne their backes vpon it, <hi>Math.</hi> 13. 21. <hi>When tribulation, or persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion arises because of the word by and by, he is scandalized.</hi> So that Persecutions cause Scandal. But yet the Scandals that come by the euill lifes of professours are in some sense farre more dangerous and hurtfull then those Scandals that come from Persecutions. Though the scandal of persecution stumble &amp; beate off many, yet haue very many beene gayned to a loue, and liking of Religion, by the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb facs="10"/> Courage, &amp; Constancy of the Saints of God in Persecution. But neuer were, nor wilbe any gayned thereunto by the scandalous falles of professours. Persecutions keepe men off by feare, but Scandalous sinnes by Hardening mens hearts. There is far more hope, and possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of gayning a man that is kept off by feare, then of such as are kept off by a setled, resolued Hardnes of Heart. In scandals of the Crosse men may haue some secret likings of the Truth, may haue secret pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses in better times to owne it, but in scandals of euill example, men grow to an open, and professed dislike thereof. In scandals of the crosse, there is not alwayes a dislike of Religion it selfe, but onely of the hard termes, with which it must bee receiued, but from scandals of euill life growes a dislike of Religion it selfe. Notwithstanding the scandal of the crosse men may haue an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable,
<pb facs="11"/> and a good conceit of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but scandals of euill life breede, and nourish a base and a vile esteeme thereof in the hearts of men. So that persecutions doe not doe that mischiefe that scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous falles doe. <hi>Malicious persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours</hi> in some sense doe not that hurt that <hi>scandalous professours doe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now scandalous euents being so mischieous and pernitious, and yet withall so common, &amp; so frequent, why may it not be a worke of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to counterworke Satan, and to remoue out of the way these dangerous stumbling blockes, at which so many fall to their vtter ruine, and destruction.</p>
   <p>As Satan <hi>Balaam-</hi>like <hi>easts</hi> stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocks in, so should it be our care to <hi>take</hi> vp these stumbling blockes out of mens wayes. It is not enough for vs that wee <hi>put not a stumbling blocke,</hi> or an occasion to fall in another mans way, as the
<pb facs="11"/> Apostle aduises <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 12. But when others haue done it, our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour should be, to take such a stumbling blocke out of the way. It is Gods owne commandement we should so doe, <hi>Isay</hi> 57. 14. <hi>Take vp the stumbling blocke out of the way of my people.</hi> It were happy if wee could preuent scandals, but since that cannot bee <hi>(for it must needs be that offences come)</hi> the next happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is to preuent their mischiefe, that though they doe come, yet they may come with as little hurt as may be. <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Esto quod a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>erit scandalum, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto compescere vos potestis. Nolle compes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e culpa erit? Aut velle compescere sine gloria erit?—Si ergo vos scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum cum possitis non tollitis pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne non impletis ministerium ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum.</hi> Bernard. Epist. 200. ad vulger. Episco. Audegav.</note> The which thing who so will not, nor cares not to doe, shall not bee without blame, and who so endeauours to doe shall not be without his reward. The which worke who so doth not when oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion serues, fulfils not his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry, and the which worke who so doth, he doth an excellent and a worthy worke, euen the worke of Angels. <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Annon deni{que} ministerium est Angelorum tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere scandala de regno Dei. Si dixeriti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> quid ad nos, &amp;c.</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard. ibid.</note>
      <hi>Is it not the worke of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/> sayes <hi>Bernard, to take scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals out of the Kingdome of God?</hi> Yea we find it to be so, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 41. <hi>The sonne of man shall send forth his Angels and they shall gather out of his Kingdome all scandals.</hi> It is therefore not onely a <hi>Charitable,</hi> but an <hi>Angelicall</hi> worke to gather out scandals, and take vp the stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blockes that Satan casts in mens way to heauen.</p>
   <p>The same spirit should be in all Gods ministers which was in <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 29. <hi>Who is offended, or Scandalized, and I burne not?</hi> In cases of scandal hee was all on fire, not only in regard of his griefe for, but in regard of his zeale against them. Hee burned with an holy zeale, to remoue the scandal and to preuent the mischiefe it might doe. Hee burned with an holy fire of zeale to keepe others from burning in the fire of Hell, wherewith scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals did endanger them.</p>
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <p> Vpon these grounds haue I bin moued, &amp; encouraged to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing of this following treatise, to try if by any meanes, either prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, or printing, I might preuent the mischiefe of scandals. Were it that the fame of them did spred no farther then the places where they happen, this labour might haue beene spared, but <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Sicut quod de alto cadit gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>num facit vt ita audiant omnes, sic &amp; qui de alto gradu ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit ruina illius vbicun{que} audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> Chrysost. in Matth.</note> as that which falles from an high place (it is <hi>Chrysostomes</hi> comparison) makes a great noise, so that all heare it; so men that fall from an high degree of profession, their falles are not without such a noise as is heard farre, and neere. It was needefull therefore to proportion the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to the disease, that the playster should be as broad as the sore, and the medicine goe as far as the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. <hi>When I saw,</hi> saies <hi>Paul, that they walked not vprightly, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the truth of the Gospell, I said vnto</hi> Peter <hi>before them all. Gal.</hi> 2.
<pb facs="13"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="14"/> 14. But why <hi>before them all?</hi> Why had hee no more regard to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Peter?</hi> Why was it not spo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken to <hi>Peter</hi> priuately, and by him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selfe alone? Why speakes hee tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> which might bee to the discred it o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Peter before them all? Hierome</hi> giue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> a good answer, <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Dixi Cephae-Publicum scandalum non potuit priuate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>rari,</hi> Hieron. in Gal. 2.</note>
      <hi>A publique scanda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> could not bee healed priuately.</hi> It i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> very fit that publique euills, shoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> haue publique remedies. If these endeauours of mine, such as they bee, shall thorough Gods blessing haue such effect as to preuent any scandals for the time to come, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> saue any from the danger of such a are already come, or to bring any t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> repentance by whom offences haue come, I shall haue cause to thinke my time and paines happily bestowed.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>