<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100400_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20388</idno>
           <idno type="STC">68.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100400</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ansvveres of some brethren of the ministerie, to the replyes of the ministers and professours of divinitie in Aberdeene : concerning the late covenant</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wreittoun (Scribonius), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>THat you maye know our Proceedings, how wee are brought upon the Stage, and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rie to our expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are put in print. Comming to <hi>Abe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>dede</hi> on Fryday the afternoone, wee received, the <hi>Demands</hi> of our <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Brethren</hi> that night late: and, for the greater expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without delay, wee returned our summarie <hi>Answers</hi> on Saturday at night. On the <hi>Lords Day</hi> following, wee desired to expresse our-selves to the People in presence of the Ministerie, but the Pulpits and Kirks were altogether refused; and therefore in the most convenient place wee could have, <hi>sub dio,</hi> and at such houres as were vacant from the ordinarie exercises of publicke Worship; wee delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our Message in the Audience of manie. After our last Sermon, towards Evening, wee found that our labour was not in vaine in the LORD, for diverse persons, of speciall note, both for place and wisedome, with willing heart, &amp; great readinesse of minde did publickly put their hands to the <hi>COUENANT.</hi> Having the weeke following seene some parts of the Countrey, (where besides the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries <hi>Alford</hi> and <hi>Deare,</hi> who had subscribed before, the Moderator, &amp; diverse of the Presbyterie of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> the Presbyterie of <hi>Turreff,</hi> after they were satisfied in some scruples, did also subscribe) wee returned the next Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day to <hi>Aberdene;</hi> where finding that some others had sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed that week, we resolved to preach upon the morne. That night wee received a <hi>Reply,</hi> unto which before our returne home, wee have made an <hi>Answere.</hi> All these we desire may bee unpartially considered: and if it shall please the LODD, that any light shall come from our labour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy minde, let it bee ascribed not unto us, (who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had time nor helps for such a taske) but to the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Trueth, and Cause it selfe, and to the Father of Lights: to whom bee all Glorie.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="2"/>
VVHat did prodeed from our Penne in our <hi>Answ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> to the D. D. of <hi>Aberdeene,</hi> concerning the late Declaration given to his Majesties <hi>Commissioner,</hi> did flow from minds filled with a zeale to the peace of this Kirk &amp; Kingdome, and from our earnest desires of a perfect har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, betwixt the King and his Subjects against all <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings.</hi> This zeale of ours wee confesse made us studie more, how to decline and to keepe our selves from touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such of the D. D. demands as were thornie, than howe to walke safely through them. And likewise to make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest to his Majesties good Subjects in all places whether the D. D. demands, and our answeres should happen to come. That matters inclined to pacification, and were in a faire way off setling: for which peaceable intentions we could conceive nothing to bee more behovefull, than by word and write to make knowne to all men the forsaid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, which his Majesties loyall Subjects presented to his Majesties <hi>Commissionar,</hi> for clearing their <hi>Covenant</hi> of all unlawfull Combination against <hi>Authoritie.</hi> And by so doing, to stoppe the mouthes of our <hi>Adversaries,</hi> and to stay all their obloquies. In using of this meane, it was far from our thoughts to wound anye man, or to write anye word, which might give the smallest offence to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest of his Majesties Subjects, Hoping rather that these our proceedings should have beene more acceptable to <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,</hi> more approven of the wife and men of understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and more aggreable unto the minds of such as are for peace; than rashly and unadvisedly to have gone on in a Dispute of <hi>State questions,</hi> which hardly at any time hath beene profitable for peace, and which at this time seemed to us (to say no further) most unseasonable &amp; impertinent. Yet knowing that it were not only base and shamefull, but in our persons, and in our proceedings in this cause, a very great incongruitie, and in it selfe sinfull, to speake wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly for GOD, and to talke deceitfullie for him, for that were as one man mocketh another so to mocke him. <hi>Iob.</hi> 13. 7. 9. and to make iniquitie a meane to promove <hi>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
(a policie which wee have not learned,) as if GOD could bee served with our sinnes. Wee have made heere a briefe relation of the reasons &amp; grounds, where-upon wee have in our answeres confidently affirmed, that his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties <hi>Commissionar</hi> did accept, and was well pleased with the late Declaration.</p>
   <p n="1">1. His G. was most earnest to have the late <hi>Covenant</hi> so solemnely sworne, and so universally subscribed to bee rendred, or rescinded, and did propone plausible reasons for that effect. But this by such strong impediments as were at that time represented, and are now extant in print, being impossible to us to doe, except wee wold sin highly against God. His G. afterward declared that the Kings Majesty was most willing to indict an Assembly &amp; call a <hi>Parliament,</hi> but that our <hi>Covenant</hi> in the clause of mutuall defence, was a combination against <hi>Authoritie,</hi> and that we had sworne to defend one another in our owne private quarrells, aswel as in the cause of Religion. This his G. desired to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, as a maine hinderance of the obtaining of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, and without the removall whereof an Assembly, and <hi>Parliament</hi> could not be indicted. When this motion of a Declaration was first proponed to the severall meetings the greater part was against it: because no Declaration, containing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ye thing contrarie to the <hi>Covenant</hi> could bee granted, and an explanation of the Covenant, the meaning whereof seemed to be plaine enough, would no more please than the Covenant it self: but by the earnest dealing of some Noblemen of his Majesties Counsell sent from the <hi>Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioner,</hi> with some Commissioners sent from everie meeting, It was thought meet in end, that a Supplication containing a Declaration should bee formed, which at last his G. did receive at the hands of the Supplicants, and upon the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thereof promised to deale with the Kings Majestie for obtaining a free Assembly and Parliament, which he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to undertake without this Declaration. Thus by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nature and course of our Proceedings about this point, it
<pb facs="3"/>
is manifest that the Declaration was, at least in this farre sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactorie to the <hi>Commissioner</hi> himselfe, that hee did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to mediate for an Assembly and Parliament, which was both the summe of our desires, and the onely end of this Declaration. So that no man could in any reason think that we should have wronged him in affirming that his G. did accept, and was well pleased with that Declaration since upon the sight, receiving, and hearing thereof, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to doe his best endeavours with his Majestie for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining what was petitioned by us, which before and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, his G. had utterly refused to doe.</p>
   <p n="2">2. The three Noble-men of his Majesties Counsell who were imployed by his G. about this Declaration, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ordinarly to him for advysing what forme of Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration would best please, and give best satisfaction. And we had great reason to think that the forme which pleased their Lorships should not be displeasing, or unacceptable to his G.</p>
   <p n="3">3. After that diverse formes of Declaration were drawn up, and none of them was found to give satisfaction: at last it was thought good, that one should bee formed by waye of Supplication for a generall Assembly and Parliament.</p>
   <p>And because the maine hinderance of obtaining thereof, was that our <hi>Covenant</hi> was suspect to be a combination a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Authoritie,</hi> it was found necessare that this impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment should bee removed by declaring that no such thing was intended in the <hi>Covenant.</hi> This forme of Supplication did first please the three Noble-men, and thereafter, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse parts and expressions of it were corrected by his G. particular direction, which are still keeped in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, &amp; in the notes of the Noblemen and others at that time imployed about this work frō their several meetings. This made us to think that his G. was well pleased with so much as was corrected by himself, and that his G. would have also corrected other parts &amp; expressions thereof, if hee had not bene well pleased with them: and therfore made
<pb facs="4"/>
us secure that his G. would no have offended that we or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, shuld have affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> so much.</p>
   <p n="4">4. Wee have reason to think that the first Declaration which was showne to the Petitioners by the three Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men sent from his G. to negotiate with them, would have given satisfaction; why then shall wee not think, that the Supplication mended by his owne particular direction, not in the Petitorie part, but in the Declaration which it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, might in like manner satisfie.</p>
   <p n="5">5. Among other partes of the Declaration which were mended by the Commissioners direction, One was in the beginning thereof, where, in place of that which was first written <hi>That the Kings Majestie bad conceived the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of Fayth</hi> and <hi>Covenant lately renewed by us his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Subjects to bee an unlawfull combination against Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie:</hi> His G. would have it changed thus, <hi>That his Majesties Commissioner hath conceived the Confession of Faith,</hi> &amp;c. Wee might therefore have imagined that the Kings Majestie possibly would not have beene pleased with our Declaration, but it could not so much as enter in our minds that his Majesties <hi>Commissioner,</hi> who would have the words to expresse his owne dislike, and not the Kings, should not for his owne part beene pleased with it, or bee offended with us, for affirming so much.</p>
   <p n="6">6. There was some reasoning between the three Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellers and the Petitioners, whether the words of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration should bee thus conceived, <hi>amaine Hinderance,</hi> or, <hi>the mains Hinderance,</hi> for which later conception the Petitioners did plead, That this which was the maine hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance being removed by their declaration, for which end they were moved to make it, ther might bee no more hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derances afterward, or at lest so small ones, that they might easily be put out of the way; and the trueth is, that since the removall of that main hinderance, we have heard of no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulare hinderance from the contents of the <hi>Covenant.</hi> This also did make us to say with the greater confidence that the Declaration did please.</p>
   <p n="7">
      <pb facs="4"/>
7. When the Declaration was received by his Majesties Commissioner, was read openly, and was confirmed hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the oath of the petitioner. His G. declared that hee verily believed that they meaned what they spake, that hee hoped what they had written should prove satisfactorie to his Majestie, and that hee would against the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted do his best endeavours with his Majestie for obtaining our desires, which could not but make us conceive that his G. was satisfied with it himself.</p>
   <p n="8">8. Although all the companies of petitioners could not bee present to hear with their own eares, the words that were spoken, yet all of them had so much as we have written, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported unto them, not by uncertaine rumour, but by the faithfulnesse of their Commissioners; and upon the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this report, and certaine evidences of the trueth, they rested satisfied, and were put in hope of a generall Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly at the <hi>Commissioner</hi> his returne. Which hath made them also now in their answers to the last of the late propositions made unto them by his Majesties <hi>Commissioner</hi> after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, to affirme, that his G. accepted their Declaration as the most ready &amp; powerfull mean, which could come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compasse of their thoughts, for clearing them of that objected Combination, lykeas they have testified no lesse in their letters to others. So that if wee have erred in our affirmation, we have not erred alone, but have beene car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried awaye with the common errour of so many as were heere conveened, without exception of any one.</p>
   <p n="9">9. As it is verie unbeseeming our profession &amp; calling, so was it verie far from our minde &amp; desire, in our answers to touch the honourable Lords of Counsell, or any in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie under his sacred Majestie. If the Act of approbation with the Subscriptions thereof, (the ground of the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive) was torne and rescinded and the missive it selfe, once thought fitte to bee sent, was returned and promise given, that it should not be sent, there was no lesse done than was assevered by us. What reason wee had to affirme that this
<pb facs="5"/>
was done upon the Supplication &amp; complaint of the lieges, may appeare, if it be remembred, First, that some of the honourable Lords of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>unsell after they were informed by the supplicants what p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>udices were done to their cause by the Act approving the Proclamation, were passionatly desirous to have the Act rescinded, and did declare that they would not spare to deale with the Commissioner for that effect. 2. When it was requyred by the Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, that another Act should bee made bearing, that by their subscribing the Proclamation they had not given their Approbation to it, It was often and at large answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that they did not by their Subscription approve the Proclamation, but onely gave warrant thereby to the Clerke for registration, and to the Herauld for publishing the same. And thirdly the Supplicants presented a petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on containing the reasons of their desires, and could not bee satisfied, except upon these reasons the Act were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scinded, and the missive stayed. This Supplication was received by the <hi>Commissioner,</hi> was openly reade, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere was given by his G. that their desire should be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. All this in substance was knowne to many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands before any word was seene from our penne, neither had anye thing written by us come to the sight of the world, if it had not beene put to the Presse by the D. D.</p>
   <p>So much have wee beene constrained to say for vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our selves, who esteeme it to bee our chiefest comfort and greatest glory, that wee plead for the cause of God, and trueth of Religion and desire neither in our plea nor in our preaching for the defence of the trueth to alledge any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ueth. We have written nothing before, or at this time, from an humour to contradict any man, or to wrong the meanest far lesse any of the honorable Lords of his Majesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Counsell, &amp; least of all his Maiesties high Commissioner But doe confesse that there was much insisting great wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on both sides; &amp; many meetings▪ before the forme of Declaration could bee agreed upon, and received: And wee
<pb facs="5"/>
doe believe also that the rescinding of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> so ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently urged, was that which would have given him, as his Majesties Commissioner, greatest satisfaction, Neither are wee ignorant that <hi>Partly</hi> through the malignancie of Sycophants watching all opportunities to promove their owne projects; <hi>Partly</hi> through the rubs and difficulties which occurre in working of great maters to their wished ends; and <hi>Partly</hi> through the busie and overweaning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of some who would seeme to bee somewhat that they may warme themselves at a combustion, and who are readie to raise suspitions against the wisest and best affected to <hi>Authoritie;</hi> much must beewritten and spoken <hi>per ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioni di stato,</hi> which otherwise would not bee thought so necessarie. Yet cannot wee conceive but the acceptance of the Declaration of the loyaltie of his Majesties subjects set down in writ, and seconded by oath, was good service to the King, and that labouring with his Majestie to possesse his royall heart with the best conceptions and constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the actions of his well meaning, and honest hearted Subjects, deser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>eth from them the increase of that respect, and honour which they owe to all whom God honoureth to bee instruments of good and happinesse to this Kirke and Kingdome, which the LORD establish under his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties long and prosperous reigne.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>