<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Errata.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100548_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18981</idno>
           <idno type="STC">54</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100548</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Errata.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The trve ancient Roman Catholike : Being an apology or covnterproofe against Doctor Bishops Reproofe of the defence of the Reformed Catholike. The first part. Wherein the name of Catholikes is vindicated from popish abuse, and thence is shewed that the faith of the Church of Rome as now it is, is not the Catholike faith, nor the same with the faith commended in the Epistles of St. Peter and St. Paul, and that confirmed by the testimony of the ancient Bishops of Rome, and other writers of that church. By Robert Abbot Doctor of Diuinity, Master of Balioll Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Garbrand, Ambrose</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Adams, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 402, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="212"/>
   <head>Errata.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>PAge 18. line 24. so, reade to. p. 19. l. 11., for all, r. for all, ibid. l. 33. you, r. your. p. 27. l. 11. accordeth, r. accorded. p. 28. l. 2. in marg.</hi> scrip. sit. <hi>r.</hi> scripsit. <hi>p. 66. l. 19. in marg.</hi> Part. 1. <hi>r.</hi> Chapt. 1. <hi>p. 144. l. 2. Achan, only, r Achan only. p. 179. l. 10. in marg.</hi> cedite. <hi>r.</hi> incedite. <hi>p. 214. l. 33. these Kings? to whom haue they, r. these Kings to whom they haue. p. 245. l. 34. in marg.</hi> creatum, quae, <hi>r.</hi> creatum se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum piam fidem, quae. <hi>p. 291. l. 21. they they, r. then they. p. 334. l. 19. widomes, r. widowes. p. 363. l. 21. a matter, r. matters.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>