<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONO∣rable Gentleman, Sir Charles Morrison, Knight Baronet.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100391_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00564</idno>
           <idno type="STC">107</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100391</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONO∣rable Gentleman, Sir Charles Morrison, Knight Baronet.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blacke devill or the apostate : Together with the wolfe worrying the lambes. And the spirituall navigator, bound for the Holy Land. In three sermons. By Thomas Adams</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 78, 2, 4, 34, 2, 4, 58, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Gentleman, Sir <hi>Charles Morrison, Knight Baronet.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy Sir,</hi> I haue beene bold, vpon better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with your vertues then with your selfe, to send a short Treatise to your view. I know whose iudgement it must passe, yet am feare-lesse: not in any arrogant stupidity of my owne weakenesse; but in a confident presumption of your goodnesse; a weighty habite, not paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel but transcendent to your Greatnesse. Perhaps Nature hath taught you, that to be Generous is to be vertuous: but I am
<pb facs="3"/>
sure, wisedome hath perfected naturall disposition in you; &amp; giuen you not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an excellent theoricall discourse, but an actuall reducing of those things into practise; which are better then you shall finde here. Though you haue happier Contemplations of your own, yet accept these, as the slender presents of a poore man giuen to the rich. Weake I confesse it: for how should the child be strong, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got in the fathers weaknesse! It hath the more need of your Protection; &amp; knows the better to expresse it selfe and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour euer ready at</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honourable command</hi> to doe you seruice,
Tho: Adams.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>