<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧To the Right Worshipfull,
Sir Henry Mountague Knight,
the Kings Maiesties Serieant for the
Law, and Recorder of the Honourable
Citie of London.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100425_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02367</idno>
           <idno type="STC">125</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100425</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧To the Right Worshipfull,
Sir Henry Mountague Knight,
the Kings Maiesties Serieant for the
Law, and Recorder of the Honourable
Citie of London.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sacrifice of thankefulnesse : A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, the third of December, being the first Aduentuall Sunday, anno 1615. By Tho. Adams. Whereunto are annexed fiue other of his sermons preached in London, and else-where; neuer before printed</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Knight, Clement</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 94, 93-103, 1, 2, 25, 1, 2, 45, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧To the Right Worshipfull,
Sir Henry Mountague Knight,
the Kings Maiesties Serieant for the
Law, and Recorder of the Honourable
Citie of London.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Worthy Sir;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here there is diuersitie of helpes, leading to
one Intention of good, the variety may well be
tolerated. Who findes fault with a Garden,
for the multitude of flowers? You shall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
heere different kinds; whereof (if some
to some seeme bitter) there is none vnwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some.
It takes fire at the Altar of God, and beginnes with the
Christians <hi>Sacrifice:</hi> the flame wherof (by the operation of the
blessed <hi>Spirit</hi>) may both enlighten the vnderstanding, and
warme the affections of good men: and in others consumingly
waste the drosse and rust of sinne,<note place="margin">Mat. 3. 11. 12.</note> which must eyther be <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi>
by the <hi>fire</hi> of Grace heere; or sent to the euerlasting <hi>fire</hi>
to be <hi>burned.</hi> The <hi>Wisemens Oblation</hi> seconds it: what
is formerly commaunded in Precept, is heere commended in
Practise. The <hi>Politicke Hunters</hi> of the world are discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:
and <hi>Plaine-Dealing</hi> encouraged. One (almost forgotten
vertue) <hi>Charitie</hi> is praised; and a busie vice is taxed. In all
is intended <hi>Lux Scientiae, Pax Conscientiae; Peccati ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ina,
aedificatio Iustitiae.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Your noble endeuours are obserued by all eyes, to bee distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished
<pb facs="3"/>
into this method: from your vertues there is a resultance
of shining Light to information, from your Office to reformation
of others. Goe forward so still, to menage your Place in that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
Citie: and let the fire of correction eate out the rust
of corruption. You may punish, euen whiles you pitie. The good
Magistrate, like a good Chirurgion, doth with a shaking hand
search vlcers; more earnestly desiring <hi>Non inuenire quod
quaerit, quàm inuenire quod puniat.</hi> The God of mercie
and saluation wrappe vp your soule in the bundle of Life; and
(when the Lust of the earth shall to the Dust of the earth) fixe
you in the blessed Orbe of Glory.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all faithfull
obseruance.
THO. ADAMS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>