<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Worshipfull, Maister Richard Wistow, Gentleman, one of the assistants of the Companie of the Barbors and Surgions: Iohn Partridge, wisheth increase of knowledge by his worthy trauell.</title>
           <author>Partridge, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100351_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09117</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19429</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100351</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Worshipfull, Maister Richard Wistow, Gentleman, one of the assistants of the Companie of the Barbors and Surgions: Iohn Partridge, wisheth increase of knowledge by his worthy trauell.</title>
                 <author>Partridge, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The treasurie of commodious conceits, and hidden secretes : Commonlie called The good huswiues closet of prouision, for the health of her houshold. Meete and necessarie for the profitable vse of all estates. Gathered out of sundry experiments, lately practised by men of great knowledge: and now newly corrected, and inlarged, with diuers necessary phisicke helpes, not impertinent to euery good huswife to vse in her house amongst her own famelie</title>
                 <author>Partridge, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Culinary arts</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Worshipfull, Maister Richard Wistow, Gentleman, one of the assistants of the Companie of the Barbors and Surgions: Iohn Partridge, wisheth increase of knowledge by his worthy trauell.</head>
   <p>AFter that I had (worshipfull Sir) taken some paine, in collecting certaine hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den secretes together, &amp; reduced them into a necessary litle booke, for my owne behoofe &amp; my familiar friends: yet at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of a certain Gentlewoman, being my deare and speciall friend, I was constrained to publish the same, &amp; considered with my selfe the saieng of the wise, which is: That good is best, which to all indifferently is of like goodnes, or effect: or which without respect of person, is good to all indifferētly. The cōsideration of which, &amp; her importu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacye together, instiged me to cōmunicate vnto the view &amp; publike benefit of al men, this smal book: the contents whereof doth instruct &amp; teach all maner of persons &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, to know perfectly how to make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers &amp; sundry sorts of new conceits, aswel of meats, conserues, and Marmalades, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
<pb facs="3"/>
of sweet and pleasant VVaters, of woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Odors, Operations &amp; Vertues: with diuers other things, that haue not hitherto bene publiquely knowne: VVhich fact of mine (I knowe) will be, not only, disliked of some, but altogether condemned: not for that it is euil: but that their fine heades can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not disgest that any other beside themselues should inioy the benefit thereof, hauing for their Maxime, that such things are of small price, as are common to al men: much after our English prouerbs, Quainty &amp; Dainty, Far fetcht &amp; deare bought is good for great estates. But I account that person foolish, &amp; vnworthy help of any Phisitian or Surge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that will refuse to receiue, or gain health by the medicine of any such Phisitian or Surgeon, who by learning the same out of Galen, Auicen, Hipocrates, or any other such like, hath oftentimes cured the diseases in sundrie and many persons, for that the same hath bene commonly vsed: but rather most willingly and curteously to imbrace the same (for present remedie) as a thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently well experimented and prooued.
<pb facs="3"/>
I need not (Right Worshipful) to vse these woordes for the defence of this litle Booke, considering that your VVorship doth very wel accept such things, as vniuersally bring with them a publike profite and vtilitie whence consisteth your delight, rewarding liberally the traueile of such, who haue and doo traueile therein. VVherefore, for that I among all other persons, doo thinke my selfe most beholden vnto your woship, to gratifie your goodnesse, and to satisfie the request of my friend, I haue compiled this litle booke: which I haue put foorth vnder your worships name and protection: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testing, that if I shal see this woorke, which with some cost and charge I haue brought to perfectiō, be wel accepted at your hands, I shall shortly exhibite vnto your worship, a thing of greater value &amp; estimation. And thus committing your good worship vnto God, I end: who send you your desire of vnderstanding and knowledge.</p>
   <signed>Your Worships to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund. I. Part.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>