<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To as many as long for true happinesse.</title>
           <author>N., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100057_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07678</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18608</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100057</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To as many as long for true happinesse.</title>
                 <author>N., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godlie mans guide to happinesse : A manuell of necessary motiues, holy meditations, and godly prayers, to stirre vp the hearts of men vnapt to pray. To the great comfort of all, that with due and holy attention will practise this most godly and Christian dutie. Written for his owne, and published for the comfort of them that long for trv [e] happinesse. by I.N</title>
                 <author>Norden, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 234, 4 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To as many as long for true happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but that euery man that liueth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sireth to liue a happie life: but euery man taketh not the right course to be truly happy. For, as there is in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man a double life, the one in this world, the other in another; the one perish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the other permanent: so are men carnally or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinely qualified, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly bend their indeuors, to visible, or inuisible things &amp; are commonly most af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fected to things visibly seene, and sencibly felt, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, or heard. But as for


<pb facs="7"/>
inuisible things, few attaine to know them, much lesse to seeke them, least of all to enioy them. No, although their bodies bee ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with millions of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies, &amp; their minds, with cares, griefs, &amp; infinite pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions; which nothing can cure, or releeue; but some speciall inward spirituall working, yet seldome or neuer looke they vp aboue these earthly things; but in whatsoeuer outward, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hard estate they are, they seeke helpe here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, if they finde it, they ascribe it, to the visible meanes and acknowledge them happie in finding it; in sicknesse to finde a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition to heale them, in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie


<pb facs="7"/>
to haue a friend to enrich them, is imputed happinesse: how much more happinesse were it then for a man neuer to be sicke, to be rich, to be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in the eyes of all men, to be reputed the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest man in the world, and to enioy what his heart could thinke here? Would not all men admire this mans happinesse? And would not all men desire, and couet to bee in his like estate? And admit hee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto it, is this the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse he aymes at? No, hee must haue peace and long life to enioy it, else the very consideration of death, and to forgoe this faigned happinesse would


<pb facs="8"/>
be vnto him as if a sword hung ouer his head by the haire of a horse taile; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie minute readie to fall on his head. Alas, what shall a man then so much strug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle and striue for the hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pinesse of this life, that consisteth onely of such things as the getting of them requires labour, som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lies; the hauing of of them, enuie; the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them feare, and the losse of them sorrow? Which yet is not all: there must bee finally <hi>a redde rationem,</hi> an account; a fearefull reckoning; which, if men would dulie consider, in the time of their greatest supposed happinesse, it would make


<pb facs="8"/>
their hearts to tremble, and their knees to knock one against another like <hi>Balteshars,</hi> for feare of the infelicitie to come. If then the greatest happinesse that man can attaine vnto in this life, be thus accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, where is that true happinesse, that absolute felicitie finally promised? Such a happinesse there is, but what it is, no man can declare it; for <hi>the eye hath not seene it, the eare hath not heard, neither can it enter to mans heart, what God hath prepared, for those that loue him:</hi> But by examination of the chiefe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in man in this life can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute himselfe most happie, and comparing them with


<pb facs="9"/>
what things wee shall fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely enioy, it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that mans happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse doth not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in the enioying of good things, but in the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from euill things. The happiest man in this life hath causes of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, griefe and vexation of spirit, his life requireth labour, labour brings wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinesse; wearinesse couets rest, and rest presupposeth the bodies infirmitie; and consequently decay and death: And death prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth eternall saluation, the happinesse of the soule and bodie, or damnation of both. This is the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all men mortall, how happie soeuer hee


<pb facs="9"/>
seeme to liue heere, where they haue hunger; thirst; heate and cold, want of things desired: and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand discontents; from which wee can neuer bee freed, vntill wee come to our heauenly Country, where Christ is ready to receiue vs, where the holy Angels and Saints are euer expecting the increase of that heauēly cōpany, whose ioy and happinesse increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth by the increase of sanctified soules, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie them; where the seruitude, which in this life oppresseth vs, shall bee turned into ioyfull li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, where we shall haue no more cause of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, of sorrow, or griefe;


<pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>God himselfe will wipe away our teares,</hi> which the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations which we heere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure haue prouoked, death shall haue no more power ouer vs; wee shall haue there no night, nor darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; we shall neede there neither sleepe, nor corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall sustinance; wee shall be free from sicknesse; we shall feare there no enuie, or malice of neighbours; wee shall neither buy nor sell; we shall neede neither gold nor siluer; wee shall want no garments, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne and couer our base bodies, as heere wee need; wee shall not be oppressed with the euills wherewith we are here infested; But bee replenished and made


<pb facs="10"/>
rich in euery delightfull thing; wee shall be there imbraced of our God, as his deere Children; our happinesse shall be so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakeable, as it cannot be manifested here, what and how glorious it shall be there; but <hi>we shal haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure at Gods right hand for euermore:</hi> If men there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that now delight themselues in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their riches; in their siluer and gold▪ and boast themselues of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse &amp; largenesse of their possessions, of their mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Mansions, of their rare iewels, the abundance of their plate, and sump<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous feasts, wherein they repose their felicitie and


<pb facs="11"/>
happinesse, did duely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the shortnesse and inconstancie of these de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nities, and other inferiours that delight themselues in all kindes of vices, would but call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to minde, what they lose by these false baytes of Sathan; they would cast their most precious things ouer-boord into the sea of contempt, as dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayning this worlds ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>best things,</hi> and their dearest sinnes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they finde a kinde of counterfeit content, and felicitie, which shall bee futurely requited, with future infelicitie and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. Happie then shall that man bee euen heere,


<pb facs="11"/>
(seeme he neuer so vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie) that for this pearle wil sell all his carnall and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall delights, to buy such a precious purchase, and so permanent, which hee shall hold to himselfe for euer, freely without r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt, without feare of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, and without any other mans claime: for euery man shall haue so competent a portion, as none shall couet another mans. The purchase in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the value is not deere. And the Lord, of whom he shall hold it, will neuer expose his tennant, nor exact any seruile ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice at his hands, but such as shall bee vnto himselfe, more glorious and sweet,


<pb facs="12"/>
then the most honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble attendance of the greatest Potentate of the World. Hee that hath a heart to conceiue the least portion of this vnexpres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible happinesse; let him seeke it while hee hath time; let him aske Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of him, that giueth it freely; let him heare, and consider what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable words, and seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promises are spoken of in the Scriptures, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this happinesse by the Prophets, by CHRIST who is Truth it selfe, and by his Apostles, who beare witnesse of the same Truth; that so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ed of the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this happinesse to


<pb facs="12"/>
come; hee may labour to attaine it, hungering and thirsting for it, with continuall prayer to him that giues it.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in Christian good will, <hi>I. N.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>