<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Terry, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100547_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13632</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23915.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100547</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Terry, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The defence of protestancie proving that the Protestant religion hath the promise of salvation : VVith the twelue apostles martyrdome; and the tenn persecutions under the Roman emperours The true scope of this ensuing treatise, is to proue by theologicall logicke both the excellency and equity of the Christian faith, and how to attaine the same. Written by that worthy and famouse minister of the gospell of Iesus Christ I.T. and published for the good of all those which desire to know the true religion</title>
                 <author>Terry, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Millard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 6-229, 9 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>CHristian and Religious Reader, this treatise was compiled for thy good, and is very necessary for these Preposterous times, wherein are such sound Proofes handled, which is to the overthrow of Popish errours and schismaticall superstition, and tends to the mainetenance of true Protestancye with their faith and quality therof.</p>
   <p>Faith in holy Scripture is taken either for the quality and habit of Faith, or for the doctrine of Faith. The holy Scripture deciphereth the quality and habit of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb n="6" facs="5"/> Faith by arguments taken out of all Theologicall places as followeth.</p>
   <p>The principall efficient cause of the quality or habit of Faith, is God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 29. The instrumentall cause is the word of God, <hi>Rom</hi> 10. 17. The material cause is an assent vpon knowledge, <hi>Ioh,</hi> 6. 69. The formall cause is a sure and settled assent, grounded vpon a sure &amp; setled kgow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. 8. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 6. The finall cause is the exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of all glorying in our selues, and the ascribing of all glory vnto God <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 27. The effects of Faith are, as all other divine graces and fruits of the spirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 18. so an holy considence, and an assurance of God's loue, and a comfortable boldnesse to come vnto God as vnto a gracious and loving Father, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 12. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10. The subiect wherin it is seated, is the mind. For the mind is the eye of the soule, and Faith is the true sight thereof, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. 56. <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 18. the object thereof is all diuine truths. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 4. especially the Covenant of grace, foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded vpon Christ, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20. 31. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 21. the attributes are, that it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ound, orthodoxe, and Catholicke; that is, one and the same in all the true servants of God, which haue bin, are, or shall be to the end of the world, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 5. Things divers are a sleight opinion, <hi>Act</hi> 26. 28. and a temporary Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 20. Things contrary are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption, &amp; fleshly security either bred by confidence in tēporall prosperity, <hi>Isa.</hi> 28. 15. or in the outward pledges of God's loue, <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rm.</hi> 7. 4. or in the outward shew of good workes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 32. &amp; 10. 3. Things privately op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite are ignorance, <hi>Eph,</hi> 4. 18. a blind Faith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 19. &amp; sophisticall infidelity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 23. That which is plain contradictory, is flat Atheisme, <hi>Sap.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 23. 8, things like are a bodily eye, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9. 39. a bodily hand, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6 12.
<pb n="7" facs="5"/> a bodily mouth, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 53. a bodily foot, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 7. &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily wings, <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 37. Things vnlike are vnstable chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dishnesse, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 14, and wauering doubtfulnes, <hi>Iac.</hi> 1. 6. The coniugates are to beleeue in God, and in Christ. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. 1: and to be one of the houshold of Faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 10: the notation or interpretation of the name, is a sure and <note place="margin">
         <hi>Vides, quia fiet quod dictum est.</hi>
      </note> certaine accomplishment of that which Faith beleeueth, <hi>Math.</hi> 8. 8. The definition or description thereof is this; Saui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g Faith is diuine wisdome, or a certain knowledge, and a settled assent, and adhaerence to all diuine verities, necessary to saluatiō, especially to the couenant of grace, as to the meanes of the chiefest good and highest happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15. the diuision thereof is into a weake and strong Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 2. The testimonies are the confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Martyrs and Confessors that haue liued, doe and shall liue to the end of the world. <hi>Apocal.</hi> 7. 10.</p>
   <p>This is the delineation of the whole body of Faith, as it is drawne out by the pensill of the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles: the parts &amp; members whereof which are most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersed, are further lightned and cleared in the first part of this Treatise. As in the second part thereof, the reasons and arguments produced to open and iustifie the seueral doctrines of Faith, are referred to all the Topick places, as being the rich mines out of which they are digged.</p>
   <p>The doctrines of Faith, set down in the bookes of the Prophets and Apostles, are Logicall, reasonable &amp; wise; and the very first principles and grounds thereof are <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 2</note> without any mixture of sophisticall deceit. The high Priests pectorall, wherein the Vrim and Thummim was put, and by the which God gaue answer vnto his peo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le, was called by the Hebrewes <hi>Hosen,</hi> and by the Greekes <note place="margin">See <hi>Alsted. Praecog Theolog. fol.</hi> 230.</note>
      <hi>Logeïon,</hi> and by the Latines <hi>Rationale,</hi> for that the Lord's
<pb n="8" facs="6"/> doctrines had in them the most pure holines of most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Logick, or reason.</p>
   <p>The Logick places which I follow in this Treatise, are deliuered by <hi>Petrus Ramus,</hi> who concerning the vse of Logick hath very much cleared the rules of <hi>Aristotle</hi> our grand Master.</p>
   <p>The exempli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ying of Logick places by the Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call positions, I haue taken from <hi>Amandus Polanus,</hi> but with this difference: in that he setteth downe his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments declaratiue and demonstratiue, in bare sentences and propositions, without further discourse; whereas in this Treatise they are further opened by other arguments and reasons. For as learned and iudicious Doctour <hi>Feild</hi> anouncheth in his Dedicatory Epistle to his first Booke of the Church, the doctrines wherein we differ from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are grounded not only vpon the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test authority that is, but also vpon the most preuailing reasons that euer perswaded men. And verily, if that most famous Oratours iudgment be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ound, there is no reason to giue credit to that reason, whereof there cannot bee yeelded a sufficient reason. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>. lib. 4. ad Herennium.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The great Antichrist of these last times, (as testifieth <note place="margin">2 Thess. 2. 8.</note> the Apostle) which hath brought in a great Apostacy frō the Faith, shalbe consumed with the Spirit of the Lord's mouth, and shalbe abolished with the brightnesse of his comming: and so shall his Armies also, which (as <hi>Chryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Chrys. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>om.</hi> 49. <hi>in Mat.</hi>
      </note> saith) are impious Heresies. For whereas the time of miracles is now long since expired, whereby the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles and their successours in the Primitiue Church, got credit to the diuine doctrine of the Gospel of Christ, and <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 4. 2 Cor. 10. 4.</note> made it most powerfull to the ouerthrowing of all Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenish Idolatries, and impious Heresies, it remaineth
<pb n="9" facs="6"/> now that the Professours of the Gospel by the glorious light of powerfull arguments, taken out of God's booke, and iustifiable by the exact rules of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ound reason, make Truth victorious against Antichrist, and all his impious Heresies: For where Truth is clearely demonstrated, and rightly apprehended, it cannot otherwise be, but that it <note place="margin">1 Esd. 3, 12.</note> will mightily preuaile.</p>
   <p>Our most wise and learned <hi>Solomon,</hi> hath already by his penne begun this regall and Princely worke, and hath iustified by cleare and demonstratiue arguments, that the supreme authority to command aswell in Ecclesiasticall as in ciuill causes, resteth in the ciuill Magistrate in his own Dominions and Countries, and hath sent his Booke to all Christian Princes, the which (no doubt) shall preuail at that time, when he that hath the hearts of all Kings in his own hand, shall know it to be most <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>it.</p>
   <p>And why should it not then highly please, especially the Ecclesiastick Peeres of his Kingdomes, to follow so worthy &amp; supereminent an example, in causing all The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologicall doctrines in this our renowned Church, to be confirmed by cleare and demonstratiue arguments, iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficable by all the rules of sound reason, and the sophismes opposed against them, reduced to the elenches, as in part they haue bin already by that famous late publike Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Doctor <hi>Whitaker.</hi> And if worthy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>samples of famous men of their own ranke be not to be neglected herein, haue they not to be their Precedents the singular Patrons of the Christian Faith, that liued in the Primitiue Church, that penned their learned Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and deliuered them vp into the hands euen of the Heathenish persecuting Emperours?</p>
   <p>And albeit that reprobate <hi>Iulian</hi> did say of these A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologies,
<pb n="10" facs="7"/> I haue read them, vnderstood them, and despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them: yet the learned Bishops were not disma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>de therewith, but gaue him this answere; thou hast read thē <note place="margin">
         <hi>Zozom. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</note> perhaps, but thou hast not vnderstood them; for if thou hast vnderstood them, thou wouldst not haue despised them.</p>
   <p>And verily whereas the vpholders of the Kingdome of Antichrist come with strong delusion, and with all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuablenes of vnrighteousnesse, why should not all such as are set in the defence of the Gospell of Christ, striue earnestly, as the Apostle S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <hi>Iude</hi> exhorteth, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance <note place="margin">Iude 4.</note> of the Faith which was once giuen to the Saints? yea, why should they not striue for truth euen vnto death and defend Iustice for li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, seeing if they doe so, they shall <note place="margin">Eccl 4. 28.</note> haue God to fight for them against their enemies? <hi>Meroz</hi> hath a double curse for omitting this duty, and <hi>Iael</hi> hath a double blessing for performing the same, pronounced by an Angell of God from Heauen. Curse yee <hi>Meroz,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iud. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 22.</note> said the Angell of the Lord, curse the inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, because they came not out to helpe the Lord; to helpe the Lord against the mighty. <hi>Iael</hi> the wife of <hi>Heber</hi> the Kenite, shalbe blessed aboue other women dwelling in tents: for she put her hand to the naile, &amp; her right hand to the workemans hammer; with the hammer smote she <hi>Sisera,</hi> yea she smote off his head, after that she had woū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and pierced his temples.</p>
   <p>So let the words of the wise, which are like goads and <note place="margin">Eccl. 12. 11.</note> like nailes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>astned by the masters of the assemblies which are giuen by one Pastour, bee as it were driuen into the heads of all spirituall <hi>Siseraes,</hi> that all Heresie and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try may be pierced and wounded, and in the end vtterly destroyed. And so now also let all thine enemies perish
<pb n="11" facs="7"/> O Lord, and let all that loue thee and thy Truth, be as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> he riseth in his might.</p>
   <p>And let all true Christian hearted Englishmen conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually pray, that the Sunne of righteousnesse would neuer goe down vnder the Horizon of this our Church of great <hi>Brittaine;</hi> but that he would alwayes shine ouer it by the bright beames of his glorious Gospell; and blesse it with the heauenly influence of his holy Spirit, holding still the starres thereof in his right hand, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing the Candle of his Word in the Candlesticke thereof vnto the world's end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord IOHN TERRY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>