<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE ROBERT Viscount Rochester, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of his Majesties most honourable priuy Councell.</title>
           <author>Alexander, S. William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100488_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16469</idno>
           <idno type="STC">338</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100488</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE ROBERT Viscount Rochester, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of his Majesties most honourable priuy Councell.</title>
                 <author>Alexander, S. William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Doomes-Day, or, the great day of the Lords iudgement : By Sr. William Alexander Knight</title>
                 <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hart, Andro</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE ROBERT Viscount <hi>Rochester,</hi> Knight of the most noble order of the <hi>Garter, and one of his Majesties most</hi> honourable priuy Councell.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT the World may haue some publicke testimonie of that priuat loue, which your Vertues long since had begotten with my thoughts (my Lord) this is a small sparke flowne from a great Flame towardes you, whose glory is, that you onely of all the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Isle haue the Altar of your honour adorned with offrings from both the Nations in this kind, as if your Worth were the Center where both our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections should meete, making an vnion in minds, a course both worthy of the credite of your place, and of your estimation with the world. Who more great with <hi>Augustus</hi> then <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coenas?</hi> none so great with the Muses. This subject may be
<pb facs="3"/>thought by some of too melancholicke a Nature for your youth, and state, but yet is vnnecessarie for neither, it may serue for that <hi>Macedonians</hi> Page who vsed euery Morning to call to him, <hi>PHILIP thou must die,</hi> though not so importunatly vrging, yet when looked on, it is a dumbe remembrer both of death, &amp; judgement, of all what was in the World, &amp; of what is likely to be when it ends: But long may you liue, your Fortune still striuing to equall your Worth, your Worth to exceed your Fortune, and the World to admire both, both being ripe before your yeares. This for the present is but [like vnripe fruits] an imperfect piece wrested from a mind many wayes distracted, &amp; involued in doubtfull designes, the successe of some whereof, I hope hereafter hauing purchased me fame from the World (who for that effect will leaue no way of worth within the compasse of my power vnattempted) may make me the more able to communicat it with another, for none can giue what he hath not himselfe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes I purpose when my mind is more calme to end this Worke, but neuer that desire which I haue</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>To serue your Honour. S. WILLIAM ALEXANDER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>