<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Thompson, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100563_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13732</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24024</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100563</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Thompson, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The soules alarum-bell : Wherein the sicke soule (through the horror of conscience) being awakened from security by the sight of sinne, hath recourse to God by meditation and prayer. By H. Thompson</title>
                 <author>Thompson, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 462, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eligious Reader, amongst other there bee two seuerall causes which haue instigated me to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise and publish this worke of Meditation: partly because of mine owne exercise and commodity, for the health of my soule in the World to come, and the good ordering of my body here in this present troublesome Pilgrimage; and partly for the vtility and profit of my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Countrey, the aduancement and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit whereof euery Man is bound both by nature and conscience to studie by all meanes possible to the vttermost of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, for the true leading of the soule into the right path of righteousnesse. And for that purpose euery Man is bound to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stribute according to the greatnes or smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Talent ministred and lent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, bee it neuer so little, if it may any way profit; and see it doe not remaine in
<pb facs="6"/> him as dead and frustrate, but rather that it bee bestowed forth to encrease and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie But (gentle Reader) the manifold miseries and calamities of this our wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched life, which are incident to our fraile flesh, being duly considered, doe enforce vs to seeke out the right way of Meditation for the comfort of our weake and oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed soules, ouer growne with the deluge of sinne Now if we did rightly know the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of benefits which true Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, being poured forth to GOD in zeale of heart doth bring; wee would bee farre more industrious to find it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once found, and surely lodged in the secret chamber of our hearts, we would be farre more des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rous to keepe it: the thoghts of our hearts are as so many spectacles to demonstrate and make apparant vnto vs the benefit, necessity, force, and vse of holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>editation, inciting vs both to frequency and feruency therein: without which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides many other benefits, which thereby wee either obtaine or lose) neither can Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than be resisted, nor our faith manifested, nor GOD daily honoured. There be many considerations likewise therunto mouing, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the shortnesse of our life, (which is but a span) and the vanity thereof, the sudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="7"/> of Christs comming in a moment, the strict and fearefull account that must bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>dered at the day of his appearance for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, vngodly, vncharitable, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian liuing and behauiour. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause holy Meditation is a mourning and desire of the Spirit to God for that which is lacking (euen as the sicke man sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for his health) whereby being reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to God by faith, he may enioy the thing he doth expect and craue, or hath need of: In what a desperate danger may wee bee thought to bee in, if wee shall shew our selues slacke or carelesse in this so auaila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a dutie? Let vs therefore meditate in all places, and at all times, calling to mind the largenesse of Gods gracious loue, and his louing kindnesse in Christ Iesus our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, who biddeth vs aske, and it shall be giuen, knocke and it shall be opened: And whensoeuer thou art burthened or oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with thy sinnes, or any other misery, or calamity in the World, vse godly and holy meditation, and be thou then fully as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured, the Lord will offer himselfe to be reconciled to thee, if thou thy selfe be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and faithfull to call for the same at his hands. To the furthering whereof, and (as it were) the tracing a path thereto,
<pb facs="7"/> consider that life it selfe is but the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benger of death, and we liue to die. GOD that numbred the haires of our head, hath unmbered our yeeres also, which we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not passe, whether in middle age, or in old age, or in Infancy; when, and where, and how, we know not: for the issue of death is in the hands of God. Our end and finall dissolution is therefore concealed from vs, because we should be alwayes meditating, and prepared for our end, and thinke eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moment vpon death, which is the ende of all flesh. <hi>Dauid</hi> teacheth vs to looke backe into our liues by holy meditation, whereby wee may learne to redeeme the time by timely repentance, <hi>Psal. 90.</hi> As a Bird guideth her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>light with her traine, so the life of man is best directed by a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall meditating recourse vnto his ende. Here (good Reader) is both the manner &amp; the method, the forme &amp; the fashion how to meditate, and what to meditate, as time and necessity shall require, with a requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site regard and serious consideration, that our holy meditations may bee the more gracious in the eyes of God, and successe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in our desires and occasions, that God may blesse both them and vs with an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Earnest in this World, of the eternity in
<pb facs="8"/> the World to come; whether by his blessed will so prospering this intended meanes, that it may be able to bring vs to the bles<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed Hauen of rest and endlesse ioy. The Lord of life and death (in whose hands is the breath of euery liuing thing) so direct vs, that wee may learne to number our dayes, that wee may run out the short race of our sinfull Pilgrimage in godlinesse of holy meditation, with much patience, loo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king to Christ Iesus the Authour and fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sher of our faith; that when we shall haue finished these dayes of sinne, wee may bee translated to a better life in the Kingdome of Glory, which GOD hath purchased to vs in the blood-shedding of his beloue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Sonne. To whom with the Father and the Holy Ghost, be rendered all glory, maiesty, power, and dominion, now &amp; euer. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, Henry Thompson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>