<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100096_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16809</idno>
           <idno type="STC">371</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100096</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defense and declaration of the Catholike Churchies [sic] doctrine, touching purgatory, and prayers for the soules departed. by William Allen Master of Arte and student in diuinitye</title>
                 <author>Allen, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Laet (Latius), Hans (Jan) de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>289, 6 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Frend of myne, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry studious of the truethe and zelous of Goddes hovvse, one that learned to beleue first, and then sought to vnderstand aftervvard (vvhiche I take to be the natural ordre of a Christian schoole, vvhere faith must in most matters directe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n, and leade the vvay to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding) asked of me, as of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e vvhome he hartely loued, and knevv to be studious in such matters by my trade of lyfe, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vvhat grovvndes the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches doctrine, and the Christian
<pb facs="3"/> peoples faith of Purgatory, ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> prayers for the departed, stoode I ansvvered him then presently, as I coulde, and shortly after (as his further request vvas) in vvrityng, sumvvhat more at la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. The vvhich my doing thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghe it vvas both rude and shor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> yet he so measured it, ethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> loue, as it commonly happet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> or elles by a singulare facility vvherby he mislykethe nothing that is meante vvell, that he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it common to many moe, then I vvoulde my selfe. For thoughe I vvas vvell contented, that the simple people or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther should take profite or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure by my paine, yet cōsidering the matter to be ful of difficulty,
<pb n="3" facs="3"/> and to reache to Goddes iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the vvorlde to coom, I called to my minde the saing of Nebridius, vvho (as S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine reporteth of him,<note place="margin">August. epist. <hi>23.</hi>
      </note> vvithe vvhome he vvas very familiare,) being muche studious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tiue of the secret pointes of our faith, vvoulde be excedingly offended, to heare a man aske of a matter of importaunce, a briefe declaration: his saying vvas, that he loued not a shorte ansvver to a longe quaestion. VVherby, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>as me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hought in a maner ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished, that my treatise though it satisfied my frend, and displeaced not other, yet coulde not, vvriten bothe hastely and briefely, serue so longe and large
<pb facs="4"/> a matter. I did feare vvith all, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> entre, in this my lacke of yeres iudgement, and knouledge, in to the searche of suche secretes, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I knevve, by that light vevve tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I made of the matter before, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> orderly proceding in the ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vvoulde driue me vnto: I did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> arne of auncient Irenaeus, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> suche doctrine and mysteries may be safely had, and vvithe ovvte all feare of erroure, taught by holy Priestes and Bisshoppes <hi>Qui cum episcopatus successione,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Libr.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 43.</note>
      <hi>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>risma veritatis certum, secundum p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citum patris acceperunt.</hi> VVho haue receiued vvith theire ordinary succession in theire pastoral sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>, the gracious gifte of vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding the truethe. <hi>And these are they
<pb n="4" facs="4"/> (saith he in the same place) which may with owte all daunger to theime selues and theire hearers, expound vnto vs the holy scriptures.</hi> Other men doubtlesse (vvhich, this miserable age of oures seeth not, that measureth all thinges by a fonde flourishe of learning, vvhereof yett there vvas neuer lesse store) can not, nor must not be so bovvld, thoughe their giftes vvere many moe, and stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy much longer then mine. And to confesse the truethe in deede, 1 vvas sum vvhat lothe (suche vvas my foolishe feare then) to faule in hande vvith that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vvhiche being vvell and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he bottom ripped, I perceiued, of al other causies in the vvorld, most to touche the very sore of
<pb facs="5"/> haeresye, and therfore might to me procure the hatered of suche, vvhose loue othervvise I coulde be cōtent, ether to kepe or vvin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Besides that, I savve the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the contrary parte, seeking to make som ansvver to such thinges as might in this cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se most greeue theire mindes, or marre their matter, should driue me from that course of studye, vvhich other vvise in quietnesse I vvould most gladly kepe, to ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue trueth and defende my cause, vvhich once of fredō and good vvil takē in hād, must aftervvard of duety and necessity be vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dē. Not vvithstāding al these thī<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, good reader, vvhich might most iustly hould me backe, yet
<pb n="5" facs="5"/> novv my frēdes request, the case and cōditiō of this praesent time, and my duety tovvardes my mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>che, may of good reason, and must of necessity chaunge my former intent, and remoue my priuate study to the benefite of the cōmō cause. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore being at lenghth by iuste occasiō vvholy minded to serue as vvell as I coulde that vvay, <hi>I</hi> thought good these late moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, to make a more full decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that thing, vvhiche at my sayde frendes request, I had so briefely touched before. That as then vvhen he first had it of me, it onely serued him for his ovvne contentation, the pleasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his singulare and secrete
<pb facs="6"/> frendes, and the helpe of som simple vvhome he knevve de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by ouer light looking on so graue matters, so novv (Good Christian reader) I trust it may helpe in commō, not onely such as haue bene caryed a vvay by the gile of haeresye, but other that are muche subiecte to the daungerous flatterly of this prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent time: vvith vvhome, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure euer ioyned to the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stātes doctrine, often more prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleth, then the preachers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suasion. Be bovvlde to charge any of oure aduersaries, make he neuer so greate accompte of him self, vvith the force of trueth here expressely proued both by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and authority: if it hovvld
<pb n="6" facs="6"/> him not, he shall (I am sure) brast ovvte vvith impudency, and nott louse him sellfe by reason, iuste dealing, or honesty. And if it be prooued to touche vvith safety the poysen it self, let no man doubte to vse it for a preseruatiue, in this commō in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiō of our time and country. For it vvere no reason, any man should practise vvithe the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re people priuyly, in such thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as he vvere not hable to maynteyn before their pilloures and preachers openly. And for that hatered vvhiche I may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to my selfe by myne ovvne trauell, it shall not muche moue me: for <hi>I</hi> shall ether be partaker therof, as a common prayse in
<pb facs="7"/> these euill dayes to most good men: or elles if <hi>I</hi> be not vvorthy so muche, <hi>I</hi> vvill learne to beare it as sum parte of punishment and satisfaction for my sinnes. <hi>I</hi> may not bye frendship vvithe flattery, nor mannes loue vvith forsaking Goddes truethe. Of suche thinges then <hi>I</hi> vvill not make muche reckeninge: but my principal care is, that in vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or vvading in so deepe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>I</hi> kepe the streght lyne of the Churchies truethe, vvhiche, in the exceding rashnesse of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se darke daies, a man may quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lose. And therefore to make sure, <hi>I</hi> humbly submit my selfe, to the iudgement of suche oure masters in faithe and religion, as
<pb n="7" facs="7"/> by Goddes callinge are made the lavvful pastors of our soules. Of vvhome <hi>I</hi> had rather learne my self, thē teach other: if ether they had occasion and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to speake, or <hi>I</hi> might of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and duety in these miserable times hould my peace. Fare vvell gētle Reader, and if <hi>I</hi> pleasure thee by my paynes, lett me for Christes sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke be partaker of thy pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>At Antvverp <date>the Second of May. 1565.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>