<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Aluarus Nonnius, to the renowmed preacher Benedict Aria Montanus.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100216_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20850</idno>
           <idno type="STC">723</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100216</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Aluarus Nonnius, to the renowmed preacher Benedict Aria Montanus.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most excellent and compendious method of curing woundes in the head, and in other partes of the body : with other precepts of the same arte, practised and written by that famous man Franciscus Arceus, Doctor in phisicke &amp; chirurgery: and translated into English by Iohn Read, chirurgion. Whereunto is added the exact cure of the caruncle, neuer before set foorth in the English toung. With a treatise of the fistulae in the fundament, and other places of the body, translated out of Iohannes Ardern. And also the description of the emplaister called dia chalciteos, with his vse and vertues. With an apt table for the better finding of the perticular matters, contayned in this present worke</title>
                 <author>Arcaeus, Franciscus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cadman, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 119, 1 leave, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>Aluarus Nonnius, to the renowmed preacher Benedict Aria Montanus.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F, according to the olde saying of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ickes (most learned Aria) men are begotten for mens sakes, then are those to be esteemed greatest, and had in highest accompt, that which daylie most doe profite the common health of man. Which, though by sundrie skills, it may be performed, yet by none more amply then that of curing diseases, the Art whereof, hath made her studentes immortall, or of eternall memorie.</p>
   <p>And seeing your Arcaeus is of this number, and one who in following, and exercising this arte, hath made himselfe so famous in his countrie, as no man liuing the like: howe much more renowmed (thinke you) shall he bee, if those thinges he hath practised with his hands amongst the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, may in writing be testified also vnto the learned? surelie (as one saith) he should aduaunce his head among the starres. But this glorie gotten by such industrie, diligence, labour, and incredible cunning, shall together with the auctor, languish &amp; perish in obliuion, vnlesse by your meanes it be brought abroad into the light.</p>
   <p>Make common therefore that which the common Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgians know not, and let not such healthfull remedies lye secret by you, least your readinesse in communicating the benefite, should seeme lesse, then was the aucthors willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in bestowing it. And that I may not seeme as of no force to begge it, but euen by good right to demaund it at your hands, thus doe I iudge, that the booke of wounds, is not onely profitable, but also necessarie. For it not onelye teacheth those thinges, which with many faultes, and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous
<pb facs="12"/> errours, are vnlearnedly, and vnskilfully written off by the barbarous, but also so reselleth the ignoraunce of our Chirurgions, <note place="margin">As vvell in Englande as in spain.</note> that hee seemeth vnto me, to haue deliuered mortall men from their tyrannie, whome Galen rightly compared vnto theeues.</p>
   <p>Moreouer our age shall learne some thinges, which other antiquitie knowe not, or left as impossible to be set down, namely to cure happelie, and with an easie method: yea and that with remedies either gotten by muche practise and iudgement, or else fetched from Hippocrates and Gallens fountaines.</p>
   <p>As for his order, though it be not so exact, because of his continuall practise and curing the sicke, yet is it likewise, for a great comprehension of Arte, to bee commended, for the distribution is perpetuall whereby hee deuideth woundes into their generall differences, and into simple and compound, as into their braunches.</p>
   <p>Also the proper prognostications are noted, and lastlye the perticuler method of curing added. Then which order none coulde (in my iudgement) haue beene sette downe, or deuised better.</p>
   <p>After this generall Chapter, followeth that of wounds in the head. For this, because of the greatnesse of the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and worthienesse of the partie, offereth it selfe first.</p>
   <p>Next to that, are the wounds of the breast and bellie, in such sort deliuered, that nothing can bee further wished, to the knowledge, either of their daunger or healing. The rest of wounds inflicted vppon other partes then those, are either comprehended vnder his simple wound, or else o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of the aucthor as ouer light to bee written off. The temperature, placing, knitting, substance, figure, action, and vse of euerie affected part, he handleth in a certaine additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of phisicke to the end of this booke.</p>
   <p>Which is notable in this, that almost no accident can happen to a wound, but from thence may bee found a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb facs="12"/> way of curing the same.</p>
   <p>But to come againe to his chirurgerie, his wounds being finished, he propoundeth the curing of vlcers, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in one onely Chapter.<note place="margin">Heere vvas some ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight, for there are ii. or three Chapters thereof.</note>
   </p>
   <p>And heere I thinke good to admonish, that the same Chapter is all but a matter of remembrance, and as a thing taken out of his table, notes of memorie in like sort, as are also most bookes of Hippocrates that are carried about. Where hence it commeth that neither all things are defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nor yet enclosed in the walles of method, and yet euerie where a perfect curation shineth foorth. But this breuitie is recompenced with a fine curation of the french disease: in which this is notable, that he sheweth the true man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of decocting Salsa Parilla, taught heretofore by no man. All which things are declared with a briefe exposition vpon euerie Chapter. But to ende my Epistle as I began, you shall do a worke worthie your condition, if, as you are example to others in wisedome and holy life, you doe also helpe mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men in this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie.</p>
   <trailer>Fare ye well.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>