<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100621_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21448</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7754</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100621</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An humble motion vvith submission vnto the right Honorable LL. of Hir Maiesties Priuie Counsell : VVherein is laid open to be considered, how necessarie it were for the good of this lande, and the Queenes Majesties safety, that ecclesiasticall discipline were reformed after the worde of God: and how easily there might be provision for a learned ministery</title>
                 <author>Penry, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>111, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I had read ouer this treatise (which by the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God light into my handes) and considered not onely the declaration of Christes discipline in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof, though briefly, yet plainely set down, and plentifully proued by those testimonies of Scripture, that (after many assaults) doth confirme the cause vnanswe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably but also the aequity, easines, the benefit and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity thereof euen in reason and policy, for the safty of hir Maiesty, the peace of the Land, the rooting out of popery and al other vngodlines; and that by such reasons as answere the foolish obiections of ignorant politikes: and in such maner layde open and vrged, as may satisfy al that bee not be sotted with wilful ignorance, and sturre the turbulent affection of none: as I took just occasion to praise God for his labors, whosoeuer was the penner of it: so did it giue me matter to encrease my perswasiō in that which long before I had conceaued, to wit that the Lorde meaneth certainlye either to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish this same scepter of his sonne Christ Iesus in a glorious manner among vs, or to make England an example of his vengeance for the reiecting of it. For first it is euident that God hath cleared it so euidently, &amp; that by so dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and sundry sorts of handling the same, as no man of what state soeuer (if he desire to know it,) can want wherwith to satisfy his expectation. For if thou desire to haue it disputed against a professed and bitter enemy ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, thou hast the first and second reply of T. C. against D. VV. If thou wouldst heare it handled in a sweet and pleasant latine style, the Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal discipline is able to content thee, if thou be vnlearned &amp; desire the same course in thy mother tongue, beholde the Learned discourse (whiche D. Bridges assaying to confute hath confirmed) the sermon vpon Rom. 12. &amp;c. If thou desire to see it layd open and concluded in scholastical manner, the demonstration doeth that way satisfy thee and lastly, if thou wouldst see it freed from the sclander that are against it, answere the obiections that may be, and are coyned to disgrace it, and vnderstand how it ouerturneth not, neither (in the substance) altereth any tollerable common-wealth; but is the onely stay and prop of euery good policy: besides the forenamed, and many other worthye writings, this present treatise professeth &amp; notablye performeth the same: so that there is no man, learned or vnlearned, feruent or myld, imployed or at leasure, but God hath prepared some of these books (except he be as the deafe adder) euery way to iustify the truth of his disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline vnto him: which causeth me to gather vnto my self a comfortable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion, that these seueral guiftes, bestowed vpon diuers men, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested vnto the Church in so diuers a manner, and al to one end; are not in vaine: But for the great good and comfort of those that shal striue for this cause in this age, and for their certane direction that shall reap the benefite of it, in the ages to come. But (alas) if we diligently wey on the other side, how this glorious and heauenly offer of the Lord vnto vs hath beene and is reiectcd, and shamfully disgraced by al estates and conditions. How greate ones cast of the yoak &amp; break the bands: yea, &amp; how that many who should haue commended the same vnto the prince with Helkijah, haue imploied al their wit and learning to traduce it with Amasiah yea and spent al their time in converting, sclaundering, displacing &amp; imprysoning those that haue bene but suspected to fauor this truth: &amp; lastlye when the increase of Gods dishonour that ary seth from hence is dulie weyed, it giueth vs rather cause
<pb facs="3"/>to feare, that God hath cleared his own light thus manifestly vnto vs, rather to make vs the more without excuse, than to make vs pertakers of so heauē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a condition. For we see how it commeth, that our great Cleargye may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters spend al their time, in vexing of Gods people, and set themselues to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sgrace all that fauor this way: the ministers of God that should be alwayes busied in studying Gods word, and teaching their people, ar constrained to spēd the most of their tyme, in seeking to be quite of those intollerable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestations wherwith they ar daily vexed: the nobles &amp; gentlemē take occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hereby to doe what they list: and the people seing the ministers in such disgrace, care not a button for their doctrine, so that if any of them bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued for their sinnes, they can be thus reuenged, complain of him to the Bishop that he is a mislyker of the state of L. Bishops: and they are so jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of their honor, that they admit the information of knowne Papistes, or any other notorious wicked wretches, &amp; wil (yea do vsually) giue more countenance to the veriest varlet in the Land that commeth with such a com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plaint; than to the most learned minister in al their diocese, if he be thought to lyke of the discipline, and (which is the greater argument of Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance not far off) ignorance and contempt of Gods word, and al kinde of sinne aboundeth in euery place, and in al estates and conditions: so that as the consideration of Gods mercies towards vs in offering vs this blessing, giueth vs some cause to trust that he wil perfect his good worke begun in this Land: so the regard of the encrease of al kindes of monstrous transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions doth justly occasion vs to fear that the land hath prepared (whiche without speedy reformation we shal shortly feele) such a scourge as shal mak vs more wondered at for our punishment, then wee haue bene admired for our peace: yet may none of these things discourage the seekers of this holye Reformation, for if they look to be crowned, they must stryue to the end. And let the aduersaries of the same know, that it may be their wickednesse shal being thus much to passe, as to keep it from vs for a tyme: but if they think either to weary the defenders, or lessen their nomber, or ouerthrow the cause: the mistres of fooles, their owne experience doth shew them that they deceaue themselues. For is not the cause far more cleared, and the nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them that fauor and seeke to aduance it, since they haue waged war against it vnder their last general, mightely multiplied aboue that which was to be sene before? Yes doutles, &amp; so it must be stil: for it being a portion of the Gospel, must needs be of the nature of the Gospel, even to spring wher it is cut down, and to spread where it is troden vpon: and though the loue of Egipt cause this generation never to know what so heauenly a conditiō meaneth, yea and Moses his ill managing of the matter be the cause that he shal onely see it: yet certainly the dayes wil come, when our posterity shal no more be gainsaid for desiring &amp; practising Christs discipline, (for which we ar so many wayes abused) then we ar for professing of the doctrine, for which our fathers shed their blood. Let this be the conclusion of al, thogh the Lord do not vouchsafe this generation an honor so excellent, yet take thou heed that thou be no meanes of keeping it back: for if thou be a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, &amp; giue thy hart, hand or countenance against it; if a magistrate, &amp; do any way discountenance it, if a priuat person, &amp; cease to pray for it or liue a life vnworthy of it: thou shalt answere at the day of judgement, &amp; be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted as an enemye to the kingdome of Christ Iesus, and an occasion that in thy time be raigned not over that generation: &amp; therefore by this book &amp; such others informe thy selfe in the trueth of it: &amp; when thou knowest it, be in loue with it &amp; so labour by al the meanes of thy calling to aduaunce it: so shalt thou be comforted whether with it, or without it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>