<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translator to the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Some, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100436_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14610</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16814</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100436</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translator to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Some, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A familiar and Christian instruction : Containing a collection of diuerse and sundrie places of Scripture, seruinge for an exposition vpon the Lordes prayer, the Creede, the tenne commaundementes, the Sacraments, together with the offices and duties of eche Christian towardes another. Translated out of the french by G.C</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Vautrollier, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Maunsell (Mansell), Andrew 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 336 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Translator to the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His treatise and famylyar instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiō translated out of the french, for mine own priuate excercise onelie: beinge by my friendes, against my will diuul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated: I am to request thee (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader) friendlie to accept the same. VVhich as it is briefe, and short: so is it sweete &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable: containing a faithfull, and true exposition of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest pointes of the pure, aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and Christian religion: set downe in such maner, that the simple, &amp; ruder sort, may easely vnderstand, and beare it away. So that it should seeme in verie deede, that for them it was first
<pb facs="4"/> framed by the author him selfe, as hauinge an especiall care of them. As for the learned, and skilfull, they haue farre better, and greater helpes, &amp; therefore lesse neede it: yet may they profit them selues somewhat, if they will vouchsafe to looke so lowe, and consider the compendiouse, true, and right way of exposition therein vsed. For they shall see how one place of scripture is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the other: the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and darke, by the more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest, and cleare: and euery ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle so fully confirmed by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies of Gods word, that we neede not once doubt, or stagger in the principles of our faith, which ought to be firme &amp; sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fast, being grounded, and built on so good, and sure a foundatiō. But the intent and purpose of the authour, (as I saide,) was
<pb facs="5"/> chiefly to benefit, and pleasure by this his paines, the ignoraunt, vnlearned, and poorer sort, and therefore labored to be shorte, and plaine. Short, partly least it should deterre the most part from reading of it, which are soone wearie of well doing: part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly also that the volume being but smale, they might the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be induced to buy the same. Thus laboring to be briefe, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding he hath so well tē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered his stile, that he is not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure: &amp; indeuoring to be plaine, he is not ouer tedious: which should not seeme so easie a thing, seeing that the most part in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting do herein offend. Wherfore (gentle reader) I doubt not but thou wilt giue him thāks, which hath taken this paines for thy profit, and hath shewed thee so readie away to the attaining of
<pb facs="5"/> all spirituall knowledge, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding in heauenlie wisdōe. Thus wishing thee so to read, and regard the same, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing an earnest desire to practise that in thy workes, which here is taught thee in wordes: and to seeke for those things which are most necessarie, and needefull for the leading of a good &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life: God may so guide the in this world by his grace: that thou maiest in the world to come be partaker of his glorie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> G. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>