<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE EDVVARD, Earle of DORSET, of His Majesties most Hono∣rable Privie Counsell; Lord Chamberlaine to the Queene; and Knight of the most Noble Order of the GARTER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100560_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02170</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1231</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100560</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE EDVVARD, Earle of DORSET, of His Majesties most Hono∣rable Privie Counsell; Lord Chamberlaine to the Queene; and Knight of the most Noble Order of the GARTER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Meditations and disquisitions upon the one and fiftieth Psalme of Dauid : Miserere mei Deus. By Sr. Richard Baker, Knight</title>
                 <author>Baker, Richard, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Boler, Anne</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Eglesfield, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 75, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE EDVVARD, Earle of DORSET, of His Majesties most Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Privie Counsell; Lord Chamberlaine to the Queene; and Knight of the most Noble Order of the GARTER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Honoured Lord, I know, you neither like, nor have leisure, to looke upon trifles; but I know also, you account not discourses of Piety, in the number of trifles: This makes
<pb facs="3"/>
mee bold to present your Lordship, with this short Treatise of Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; that being short, it may not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert you long; being Pious, not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert you at all. J so much honour your Lordship, for your publicke ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; so much am bound to you, for your private; that J cannot forbeare to present you with something, as a testimony of my service in both: and a richer present I could not thinke of, than Meditations upon this Psalme of <hi>David;</hi> which is indeede, the Master-piece of his Repentance, as his Repentance the Master-piece of all his Vertues. The Jewell it selfe is from <hi>David,</hi> onely the Case from me; and though the Jewell deserve a more Illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Case; and your Person a more
<pb facs="3"/>
Jllustrious present; yet there is colour to hope I may bee pardoned in both; seeing, the Jewels splendour, gives a lustre to any case; and your Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, to any present. And though it might bee presented with a better hand; yet it cannot with a better heart; seeing he presents it, that is</p>
   <p>Your Lordships humble and devoted servant,</p>
   <p>RICHARD BAKER.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>