<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE PRINCE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100059_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14801</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17987</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100059</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE PRINCE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Free trade. Or, the meanes to make trade florish : Wherein, the causes of the decay of trade in this kingdome, are discouered: and the remedies also to remooue the same, are represented</title>
                 <author>Misselden, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 134, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE PRINCE.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OVR HIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES</hi> is no lesse <hi>Happy</hi> to bee the <hi>SONNE</hi> of so great a <hi>KING,</hi> then to be the <hi>Heire apparent</hi> of so many <hi>Kingdomes.</hi> In
<pb facs="3"/> the <hi>one,</hi> rare endowments of <hi>Maiesty</hi> and <hi>Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity,</hi> are <hi>Yours</hi> by <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration:</hi> In the <hi>other,</hi> a <hi>Royall Monarchy by inheritance and succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</hi> The <hi>one</hi> doth fit <hi>You</hi> for the <hi>other,</hi> and <hi>Your Royall FATHERS footsteps</hi> for them <hi>both.</hi> In <hi>those</hi> are <hi>Peerelesse prints: You</hi> cannot cast <hi>Your Eie,</hi> but they are present to <hi>You,</hi> and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented in <hi>You. You</hi> see in <hi>HIS Religion, Piety:</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> in <hi>HIS Sacred Person, Tranquility:</hi> in <hi>HIS Gouernment, Policy.</hi> In euery <hi>one</hi> of these, <hi>all</hi> these: and <hi>all</hi> in <hi>You.</hi> In that last, <hi>HIS Maiesty</hi> hath carried a quick <hi>Eie,</hi> ouer the <hi>Commerce</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome:</hi> because it hath relation both to the <hi>Reuenue of the Crowne,</hi> and the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> of all <hi>HIS Kingdomes.</hi> It is said in <hi>Ezechiels Vision,</hi> that <hi>One wheele ran within
<pb facs="4"/> the other,</hi> which hath an <hi>Emphasis</hi> in that tongue, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and surely matters of <hi>STATE</hi> and of <hi>TRADE,</hi> are involued and wrapt vp together. Which latter, because it is at this time in agitation, and there are, notwithout cause, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Quaere's</hi> about the <hi>Causes</hi> of the generall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay thereof; hath caused me to put my selfe on this <hi>Enquiry,</hi> to <hi>philosophize</hi> if I could, in these <hi>Causes</hi> and <hi>Remedies.</hi> Not
<pb facs="4"/> that I would seeme with <hi>Phormio,</hi> to reade a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture to <hi>Hannibal:</hi> No, I haue only <hi>mustered</hi> and <hi>marshalled</hi> these <hi>men</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their <hi>Rancks</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> it is <hi>Yours</hi> to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them. Great <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> suffered a meane musition to say vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, <hi>Absit, vt haec tu me melius scias.</hi> But for my part, I dare not in any thing, put <hi>such</hi> an <hi>absit,</hi> to a <hi>PRINCE so absolute.</hi> Euery thing mooues it selfe
<pb facs="5"/> to its <hi>Center.</hi> These little lucubrations present them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to your <hi>HIGHNES,</hi> as vnto their proper <hi>Orb.</hi> For as they <hi>looke</hi> vp to the <hi>KING,</hi> or as they <hi>looke downe</hi> to the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> In both they looke on <hi>YOV,</hi> with a double aspect. <hi>YOV</hi> are the <hi>Ioy</hi> of the <hi>KING,</hi> the <hi>Hope</hi> of all these <hi>Kingdomes.</hi> The <hi>Only Sonne YOV</hi> are, of the <hi>Only KING:</hi> An hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py<note n="*" place="margin">Ex <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> prospexit, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidit, quasi portò-vidit.</note>
      <hi>SEER,</hi> of a blessed <hi>SIRE:</hi> A <hi>Princely
<pb facs="5"/> CONSVL,</hi> of <hi>the Priuy Councel: A watchman, A worthy,</hi> of <hi>DAVID</hi> and of <hi>IACOB.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These Meditations of <hi>mine,</hi> are very <hi>meane:</hi> an vnfit obiect for a <hi>Princes</hi> sight: vnlesse as <hi>YOV</hi> are <hi>a God on Earth;</hi> in this also <hi>YOV</hi> represent <hi>the GOD of Heauen;</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in your <hi>Princely</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and patience, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. The Cause is great, your Wisedom's deep, and my <hi>Lord the KING</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/> is as an <hi>Angell of GOD. YOV</hi> are <hi>HIS, HE</hi> is<note n="*" place="margin">Not <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> too.</note>
      <hi>CHRIST,</hi> and <hi>CHRIST</hi> is <hi>GODS.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Oh GOD,</hi> be thou still the <hi>KING</hi> and <hi>CHRIST,</hi> of this <hi>CHRIST</hi> Our <hi>KING: Euangelize</hi> vnto this <hi>Angel:</hi> double the Spirit of Our <hi>ELIAH,</hi> on Our <hi>ELISHA:</hi> that <hi>HE</hi> may flourish like our <hi>Palme Tree,</hi> and grow vp like our <hi>Cedar</hi> of<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Libanon</hi> per Litterarum Metathesm, <hi>Albion.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Albion.</hi> Giue thy <hi>Iudgements</hi> to the <hi>KING,</hi> and thy <hi>Iustice</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/> to the <hi>KINGS SONNE:</hi> And let all the <hi>People</hi> offer these sweete <hi>Odours</hi> to <hi>Thee</hi> the <hi>God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> and pray for the life of the <hi>KING</hi> and <hi>HIS SONNE.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>So prayeth, for HIS Maiestie, And your Highnesse,</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, <hi>EDW. MISSELDEN,</hi> Merchant.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my House at</hi> Hackney <hi>on</hi> Whatson Eue,
<date>
            <hi>the 8 of</hi> Iune <hi>In the yeare of</hi> Grace, <hi>M.DC.XXII. And of the KING of</hi> Peace, <hi>XX.LV.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>