<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Barlow, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100949_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04434</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1456.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100949</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Barlow, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The summe and substance of the conference : which, it pleased his excellent Maiestie to haue with the lords, bishops, and other of his clergie, (at vvhich the most of the lordes of the councell were present) in his Maiesties priuy-chamber, at Hampton Court. Ianuary 14. 1603. Contracted by VVilliam Barlovv, Doctor of Diuinity, and Deane of Chester. Whereunto are added, some copies, (scattered abroad,) vnsauory, and vntrue</title>
                 <author>Barlow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Law (Lawe), Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 103, 9 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Copy of the <hi>Conferēce</hi> in <hi>Ianuary</hi> last, hath beene long expected; and long since it was finished; impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of the diuulging, were many; too, main, aboue<note place="margin">Archiep. Can tuar.</note> the rest: one, his <hi>vntimely death,</hi> who first imposed it vpon me; with whome is buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the famousest glory of our English Church, and the most kind incouragement to paines and study: <hi>A man happie in his life &amp; death; loued of the best, while he liued; &amp; hearde of God for his decease; most earnestly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring, not many dayes before hee was stroken, that he might not, yet, liue to see this Parliament, as neare as it vvas.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The other, an expectation of this late <hi>Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall</hi>
      <note place="margin">2</note>
      <hi>Conference,</hi> much threatned before, and
<pb facs="3"/>
triumphed in by many; as if that <hi>Regall</hi> and most <hi>honourable</hi> preceding, shoulde thereby haue receiued his <hi>Counter-blast,</hi> for being too forward: But his Maiesties <hi>Constancy</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, by the last, added comfort and strength to this former, which now, at length, comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; therein, <hi>good Reader,</hi> thou mayest both see those <hi>huge</hi> pretended <hi>Scandales</hi> (for which our flourishing Church hath, beene so long disturbed) obiected and remoued; &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, behold the expresse and viue image of a most learned and iudicious King: whose manifolde giftes of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> my skant measure of gift is not able to delineate, nor am I willing to enumerate, because, I haue euer accounted the personall commendations of <hi>Liuing Princes.</hi> in men of our sort, a <hi>Verball Symony,</hi> Such <hi>Flies</hi> there are too many, which puffe the skinne, but taint the flesh. His Maiesties hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deportment in those sublimities, will be the eternizing of his memory: the rather, because, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>to digest so great Felicity, without surfet</hi> of surquedry is a <hi>vertue</hi> rare in great personages, &amp; <hi>that,</hi> which the K. of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uē
<pb facs="3"/>
feared, euen the King of his own choice would want. The more eminent he is, in all princely qualities, the happier shall we be: our duty, as we are Christians, is <hi>Prayer</hi> for him; as wee are Subiectes, <hi>Obedience</hi> to him; as we are men, <hi>acknowledgement of our setled state</hi> in him. Our vnthankfulnes may remoue him as it did, the <hi>mirrour</hi> of Princes, our late famous <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth.</hi> Shee rests with God, the <hi>Phaenix</hi> of her ashes raignes ouer vs; and long may he so doe to Gods glory, and the Churches good, which his excellent knowledge be wtifieth, and good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement adioyned will beatifie it. An hope of this last, we conceiue by his written <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: a <hi>Specimen</hi> of the other, in this <hi>Interlocutory Conference:</hi> whereof take this, which is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but as an <hi>Extract,</hi> wherein is the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance</hi> of the whole; intercourse of speeches, there occasioned, would cause prolixity without profit: what euery man said, <hi>point deuise,</hi> I neither could, nor cared to obserue; the vigour of euery <hi>obiection,</hi> with the summe of each <hi>answer,</hi> I gesse, I misse not: For the first day, I had no helpe, beyond mine owne; yet some of good place
<pb facs="4"/>
and vnderstanding, haue seene it, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troled it, except for the <hi>breuity:</hi> for the two last, out of diuers<note place="margin">Deanes of Ep. Londl. Christchur. VVinchest. VVindsor. Archdeac. Nottinghā. and mine owne.</note> copies, I haue selected and ordered what you here see: in them all, next vnto God, the Kinges Maiestie alone, must haue the glory: Yet, to say, that the present state of our Church, is very much obliged to the Reuerend Fathers, my Lordes of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Winton,</hi> their paines &amp; dexterity in this busines, were neither <hi>detraction</hi> from other, nor <hi>flattery</hi> of them. His <hi>Highnes</hi> purposed to compose all quarrels of this kind, hereby, and supposing he had setled all matters of the Church, it pleased him so to sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie by <hi>Proclamation</hi> after it was done: but there is a <hi>triple generation</hi> in the worlde, of<note place="margin">Prou. 30, 1<gap reason="illegible: over-inked" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 13. 14</note> whome the <hi>wiseman</hi> speaketh, marry, I say nothing, (for, euen, priuate speeches cannot, now passe without the smeare of a <hi>Blacke Cole.</hi> In one ranke whereof, you may place our <hi>Hercules Limbo▪ mastix,</hi> whome it might haue pleased, without his <hi>Gnathonical</hi> appeale, to haue rested his Maiesties determinatiō; &amp; being a <hi>Synopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Theolog</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>; and <hi>angry,</hi> that he was not, so, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, haue learned, the difference
<pb facs="4"/>
Diuinitie, betweene <hi>Viam Regis, &amp; viam gregis.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Many copies, of diuerse sorts haue been scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and sent abroad, some partiall, some vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, some slanderous; what is here set downe, for the <hi>truth thereof,</hi> shall be iustified: the onelie wrong, therein, is to his excellent Maiestie, a syllable of whose admirable speeches, it was pitty to loose, his wordes as they were vttered by him, being as <hi>Salomon</hi> speaketh, <hi>Like Apples of</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pro. 25. 11</note>
      <hi>gold, vvith pictures of siluer;</hi> and therefore, I request thee good Reader, when thou commest to any of his Highnes speeches, to turne <hi>Martial</hi> his Apostrophe vpon me;</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Tu malé iam recitas, incipit esse tuus,</hi> and I will take it kindly. If thou bee honest and courteous, thou wilt rest satisfied, and that is my content: to lay a pillow for a dog, sortes neither with my leysure, nor purpose. <hi>Farevvell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesu, <hi>W.</hi> Barlow.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>