<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100520_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01847</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1199</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100520</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short discourse of the three kindes of peppers in common vse : and certaine special medicines made of the same, tending to the preseruation of health</title>
                 <author>Baley, Walter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in former yeeres at
this season I haue been
alwaies careful to shew
my special affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
by offering som present,
appertaining to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruatiō
of your health:
so at this time, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> in token of a
good and prosperous newe yeere, (God grant you
many) I haue emboldened my selfe to exhibite to
<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> in our vulgar toong, this short
discourse of the three kindes of Peppers, and of
three medicines cōpounded of the same, greatly
commended by Galen in his books <hi>De sanitate
tuenda;</hi> which being vsed in right order, with
discretion, will vndoubtedly bring three waies
commoditie to the continuance of your heath.
For it is certaine that most men in this our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
through our maner of feeding, do gather in
<pb facs="3"/>
the stomacke and in the first veines many crude
and vndigested humours, which do often occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
lacke of appetite, grosse windines, distentions
in the sides, and many waies greeuous paines; and
sometimes vnnaturall vomits: which crudities
carried farther into the body, doo breede ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions,
tympanies, feuers, and other dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
diseases. The due consideration hereof, may
easily inferre how necessary to health in this our
region the vse of pepper is, and what commodity
may accrew by conuenient vse of the three me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines
made thereof. For first the medicine ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<hi>diatrion pipereon,</hi> by consent of all wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
hath facultie to warme the stomacke, to dry
superfluous moisture, to further concoction, to
discusse winde, to ripen crude humours, and is
cōmended aboue all other medicaments, that in
performing of these actions it doth no way ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heate
the liuer, nor distemper the bloud. The
second medicine termed <hi>diaspoliticon,</hi> keepeth
the belly loose, and doth carry by the stoole, crude,
corrupt, and naughtie humours, cut grosse and
thicke phlegme, keepeth cleane the belly and
guts. The third medicine termed <hi>diacalamin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the,</hi>
hauing more subtiltie in substance doth pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate
farther, and so doth concoct and expell
not onely the crudities of the belly and of the first
veines, but also doth digest, extenuate, discusse,
and by vrine carieth the excrementes of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="3"/>
veines, clenseth the bloud, and keepeth clean
the habite of the body by sweate and perspiration
through the skin. That in very truth Galen had
iust cause so greatly to commende these three
medicines as most conuenient to preserue health.
For I do not reade in all our authors of a more
conuenient meanes to continue health, than the
apte and due vse of these three medicines, which
in propulsing of diseases, and in reforming of the
state of the body, may be resembled to the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umuiri
in the common-wealth of Rome. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I remaine to the almightie a daily ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
so to prosper the effects of these medicines,
that the same commodities may come vnto your
<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> which our authors do attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
vnto them, that your yeeres
may be inlarged to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame
age.
{inverted ⁂}</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>