<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, LANCELLOT ANDREWES, Lord Bishop of Win∣chester, and Counsellour of Estate to his MAIESTIE.</title>
           <author>Alban, Fr. St.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100333_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01128</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1124</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100333</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, LANCELLOT ANDREWES, Lord Bishop of Win∣chester, and Counsellour of Estate to his MAIESTIE.</title>
                 <author>Alban, Fr. St.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine miscellany vvorks of the Right Honourable Francis Lo. Verulam, Viscount S. Alban : Published by William Rawley</title>
                 <author>Bacon, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Robinson, Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 166 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="44"/>
   <pb n="79" facs="44"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, LANCELLOT ANDREWES, Lord Bishop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester,</hi> and Counsellour of Estate to his MAIESTIE.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst Consolations, it is not the least, to represent to a Mans selfe, like <hi>Examples</hi> of Calamitie in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For <hi>Examples</hi> giue a quicker Jmpression, than <hi>Arguments;</hi> And
<pb n="80" facs="45"/> besides they certifie vs that, which the <hi>Scripture</hi> also tendreth for satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; <hi>That no new Thing is happened vnto vs.</hi> This they doe the better, by how much the <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> are liker in circumstances, to our owne Case; And more especially, if they fall vpon <hi>Persons,</hi> that are greater, and worthier, than our selues. For as it sauoureth of Ʋanity, to match our selues highly, in our owne conceit; So on the otherside, it is a good sound Conclusion, that if our Betters haue sustained the like Euents, wee haue the lesse cause to be grieued.</p>
   <p>Jn this kinde of Consolation, I haue not beene wanting to my Selfe; Though as a <hi>Christian,</hi> I haue tasted (through <hi>Gods</hi> great goodnesse,) of higher Remedies. Hauing therefore,
<pb n="81" facs="45"/> through the Ʋarietie of my Reading, set before me, many <hi>Examples,</hi> both of Ancient and Later Times, my Thoughts (I confesse) haue chiefly stayed vpon three <hi>Particulars,</hi> as the most Eminent, and the most Resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. All three <hi>Persons,</hi> that had held chiefe place of Authority in their Countries; All three ruined, not by Warre, or by any other Disaster, but by Justice, and Sentence, as Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, and Criminalls; All three famous Writers, insomuch as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their Calamity, is now as to Posterity, but as a little Picture of Night-worke, remaining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the faire, and excellent Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, of their Acts, and Works. And all three (if that were any thing to the matter,) fit <hi>Examples</hi> to quench
<pb n="82" facs="46"/> any Mans Ambition of Rising a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; For that they were euery one of them restored with great glory, but to their further Ruine and Destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ending in a violent Death. The <hi>Men</hi> were, <hi>Demosthenes, Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Seneca;</hi> Persons, that J durst not claime Affinity with, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Similitude of our Fortunes had contracted it. When I had cast mine Eyes vpon these <hi>Examples,</hi> J was carried on further to obserue, how they did beare their Fortunes, and principally, how they did employ their Times, being banished, and disabled for Publike Businesse; To the end, that J might learne by them; And that they might be, as well my Counsellours, as my Comforters. Wherupon I happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to note, how diuersly, their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes
<pb n="83" facs="46"/> wrought vpon them, especially in that point, at which I did most aime, which was the employing of their Times, and Pens. Jn <hi>Cicero,</hi> I saw, that during his Banishment, (which was almost two yeares,) he was so soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and deiected, as he wrote nothing, but a few Womanish <hi>Epistles.</hi> And yet, in mine opinion, he had least reason of the Three, to be discouraged: For that although it was iudged, and iudged by the highest kinde of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in forme of a <hi>Statute,</hi> or <hi>Law,</hi> that he should be banished; And his whole Estate confiscated, and seized; And his houses pulled downe; And that it should be highly penall, for any Man, to propound his Repeale; Yet his Case, euen then, had no great Blot of Ignominy, but it was thought,
<pb n="84" facs="47"/> but a Tempest of Popularitie, which ouerthrew him. <hi>Demosthenes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwise, though his Case was foule, being condemned for <hi>Bribery;</hi> And not simple <hi>Bribery,</hi> but <hi>Bribery</hi> in the Nature of Treason, and Disloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; yet neuerthelesse tooke so little knowledge of his Fortune, as during his Banishment, hee did much busie himselfe, and entermeddle with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>State;</hi> And tooke vpon him to Counsell the <hi>State,</hi> (as if he had beene still at the Helme,) by letters; As ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by some <hi>Epistles</hi> of his, which are extant. <hi>Seneca</hi> indeed, who was condemned, for many <hi>Corruptions,</hi> and <hi>Crimes,</hi> and banished into a solitary <hi>Island,</hi> kept a Meane; And though his penne did not freese, yet he abstained from intruding into Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="85" facs="47"/> of Businesse; But spent his time, in writing <hi>Books,</hi> of excellent Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Vse, for all Ages; Though he might haue made better Choyce, (sometimes) of his <hi>Dedications.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These <hi>Examples</hi> confirmed mee much in a Resolution, (whereunto J was otherwise inclined,) to spend my Time wholly in Writing; And to put forth that poore <hi>Talent,</hi> or halfe <hi>Talent,</hi> or what it is, that God hath giuen me, not as heretofore to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Exchanges,</hi> but to <hi>Banks,</hi> or <hi>Mounts</hi> of Perpetuity, which will not breake. Therefore hauing not long since, set forth a part of my <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stauration;</hi> Which is the Worke, that in mine owne iudgement, <hi>(Si nunquam fallit Imago,)</hi> J doe most esteeme; I thinke to proceed in some
<pb n="86" facs="48"/> new parts thereof. And although J haue receiued from many Parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, Testimonies touching that Worke, such as beyond which J could not expect at the first, in so ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struse an Argument; yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse J haue iust cause to doubt, that it flies too high ouer Mens Heads: I haue a purpose therefore, (though I breake the order of Time,) to draw it downe to the sense, by some Patternes of a <hi>Naturall Story,</hi> and <hi>Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And againe, for that my <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Aduancement of Learning,</hi> may be some Preparatiue, or Key, for the better opening of the <hi>Instau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> Because it exhibit's a Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of new Conceits, and old; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Instauration,</hi> giues the new vnmixed, otherwise than with some
<pb n="87" facs="48"/> little Aspersion of the old, for tastes sake; J haue thought good to procure a <hi>Translation</hi> of that <hi>Booke,</hi> into the <hi>Generall Language,</hi> not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great and ample Additions, and Enrichment thereof; Especially in the <hi>Second Booke,</hi> which handleth the <hi>Partition</hi> of <hi>Sciences:</hi> In such sort, as I hold it may serue, in lieu of the <hi>First Part,</hi> of the <hi>Instauration,</hi> and acquit my promise in that part. Againe, because I cannot altogether desert, the Ciuill Person, that I haue borne; Which if I should forget, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough would remember; J haue also entred into a worke touching <hi>Lawes;</hi> Propounding a Character of <hi>Iustice,</hi> in a middle terme, betweene the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatiue, and Reuerend discourses of Philosophers, and the Writings of
<pb n="88" facs="49"/>
      <hi>Lawyers,</hi> which are tied, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to their particular <hi>Lawes.</hi> And although it be true, that J had a purpose, to make a particular <hi>Digest,</hi> or Recompilement, of the <hi>Lawes,</hi> of mine owne Nation; Yet because it is a Worke of Assistance, and that, that I cannot master by mine owne Forces, and Penne, J haue laid it aside. Now hauing in the <hi>Worke</hi> of my <hi>Instauration,</hi> had in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, the generall Good of <hi>Men,</hi> in their very Being, and the Dowries of Nature; And in my <hi>Worke</hi> of <hi>Lawes,</hi> the generall good of <hi>Men</hi> likewise, in Society, and the Dowries of Gouernment; I thought in duty I owed somewhat vnto mine owne <hi>Country,</hi> which J euer loued; Jnso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as although my Place, hath
<pb n="89" facs="49"/> beene farre aboue my desert, yet my Thoughts, and Cares concerning the Good thereof, were beyond, and ouer, and aboue my place: So now being (as I am) no more able to doe my <hi>Countrey</hi> Seruice, it remained vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, to doe it Honour: Which J haue endeuoured to doe, in my <hi>VVorke,</hi> of the <hi>Raigne,</hi> of <hi>King HENRY</hi> the <hi>Seuenth.</hi> As for my <hi>Essayes,</hi> and some other Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of that nature, I count them, but as the Recreations of my other Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and in that sort purpose to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue them; Though J am not ignorant, that those kind of <hi>VVritings,</hi> would, with lesse paines, and embracement, (perhaps,) yeeld more Lustre, and Reputation to my Name, than those other, which I haue in hand. But J
<pb n="90" facs="50"/> account the Ʋse, that a Man should seeke, of the publishing of his owne <hi>VVritings</hi> before his Death, to be but an vntimely Anticipation of that, which is proper to follow a Man, and not to goe along with him.</p>
   <p>But reuoluing with my selfe, my <hi>Writings,</hi> as well those which I haue published, as those, which I had in hand, me thought they went all into the <hi>City,</hi> and none into the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> Where because I haue found, so great Consolation, J desire likewise to make some poore Oblation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore J haue chosen an Argument, mixt of <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Ciuill</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations; And likewise mixt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Contemplatiue,</hi> and <hi>Actiue.</hi> For who can tell, whether there may not be an <hi>Exoriere aliquis?</hi> Great
<pb n="91" facs="50"/> Matters (especially if they be <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi>) haue (many times) small be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings; And the Platforme, may draw on the Building. This <hi>Worke,</hi> because I was euer an Enemy to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring <hi>Dedications,</hi> I haue dedicated to your Lordship; Jn respect of our ancient, and priuate Acquaintance; And because amongst the Men of our Times, I hold you in especiall Reuerence.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships louing Friend Fr. S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. ALBAN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>