<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADMIRABLE METHOD TO LOVE, SERVE and Reuerence the Glorious Virgin Mary our B. Aduocate.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100011_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11368</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21628</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100011</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADMIRABLE METHOD TO LOVE, SERVE and Reuerence the Glorious Virgin Mary our B. Aduocate.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An admirable method to loue, serue and honour the B. Virgin Mary : With diuers practicable exercises thereof. Al inriched with choice examples. Written in Italian by the R. F. Alexis de Salo, Capuchin. And Englished by R.F</title>
                 <author>Salo, Alessio Segala de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cousturier (Le Cousturier), Jean</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 607, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="exhortation">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>AN ADMIRABLE METHOD TO LOVE, SERVE and Reuerence the Glorious Virgin Mary our B. Aduocate.</head>
   <head type="sub">Or a pious Exhortation to be deuoted to the Queene of Heauen.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>VERY faithful Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian is to Indeauour to his vtermost to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come deuot and duly resighned to the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the Glorious Queene of Heauen whom the Angels serue
<pb facs="11"/>the Arch-Angels adore, the Thrones honour, the Cherubins and Seraphins respect, and in fine the highest aduāced in the Court of Heauen account it their Glory to make Court vnto Knowing how aduantagious her fauour would be to them, for if a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier heer accounts it for so high a felicity, to haue the glory of possessing the heard of some great Princesse as promissing himselfe great honours and dignities from thence, and how much more, if besides al this he were assured of that dearer place in her me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory as shee could refuse him nothing but if he chaunced to fal into disgrace, would vndertake his defence &amp; reconcile him with his Prince againe free him from the punishments he had merited,
<pb facs="12"/>obtaine his repeal if he were ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished from the Court, and not only restore him to his former estate againe, but aduance him higher then euer he was before, what a blessing what an excesse of Ioy would this fortunat fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit receiue from thence what would he do, or rather what nor do in gratitud for so great an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation? what meanes what sort of seruices would he most inuent to honour her withal! assueredly both night &amp; day, he would haue no other thought then how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse his thankfulnes to her in some particular manner, and then would be no danger so great, no seruice so painful he would not, go through with al, to maintaine himself in her better graces stil.</p>
   <p>And yet farr more happy a
<pb facs="12"/>thousand times are the seruants &amp; fauourits of the Queene of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, in that they are assured she is perpetually mindful of them that she beares them an vnequald loue, that they may hope the Greatest of fauours from her and that she cannot be wanting to them in their afflictions that as a faithful Aduocate she doth Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace their protection in al oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, that she preuails her self of al occasiōs to render the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal king her B. Sōne propitious to them, and what is most of al deliuers thē from eternal paines, &amp; brings them in fine to the pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesion of the glory and happines of the Kingdome of Heauen.</p>
   <p>From al which we may gather fiue rare Priuiledges those truely deuote vnto the Mother of God
<pb facs="13"/>Inioy thereby the first is that she loues them with a profound and cordial affection; the second that she honours them with diuers particular fauours; the third that she is alwayes ready to assist them in their necessities as after as they implore her aide; the fourth that as a most careful Aduocate with particular solicitud she vndertake their deffence and renders them propitious the eternal King of Heauen, reconciling them into him, when they haue offended him; the fifth and last that she de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuers them from eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Let vs consider then and examine them on by on which great exactnes to animat euery soule to the affection of so deare and great a Lady.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>