<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Faults Escaped.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100389_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15315</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25603</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100389</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Faults Escaped.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A theologicall disputation concerning the oath of allegiance : dedicated to the most holy father Pope Paul the fifth. Wherein all the principall arguments which haue hitherto beene brought by Cardinall Bellarmine, Iacobus Gretzer, Leonard Lessius, Martin Becanus, and diuers others, against the new oath of allegiance, lately established in England by act of Parliament, are sincerely, perspicuously, and exactly examined. By Roger Widdrington, an English Catholike. Translated out of Latin into English by the author himselfe,whereunto hee hath also added an appendix, wherein all the arguments, whach that most learned diuine Franciscus Suarez, hath lately brought for the Popes power to depose princes, and against the aforesaid oath of allegiance, are sincerely rehearsed, and answered</title>
                 <author>Preston, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60, 421, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="246"/>
   <head>Faults Escaped.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>In the Epistle</hi> nu. 2. line 33. reade, <hi>as that.</hi> nu. 6. against line 81. put in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent c <hi>Cap.</hi> 10. <hi>sec.</hi> 2. <hi>nu.</hi> 13. nu. 7. l. 39 reade, <hi>do thinke.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In the Admonition</hi> nu. 8. l. 44. reade, <hi>shamefully.</hi> nu. 27 l. 15. <hi>eiectus.</hi> nu. 29. l. 36. <hi>was not thrust.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In the Disputation</hi> pag. 31. lin. 22. reade, <hi>actually</hi> l. 23. <hi>actuall.</hi> p. 60. l. 31. <hi>Realme.</hi> p. 78. l. 20. <hi>of [<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r].</hi> p. 103. l. 6. <hi>absolued.</hi> p 105. l 9 <hi>hath authoritie.</hi> p. 174. l. 19. <hi>this oath.</hi> p. 181. l. 35. 36. <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>urtold.</hi> p. 186. l. 13. <hi>what action.</hi> p. 192 l. 19. <hi>in this.</hi> p. 207. l. 1. <hi>that as it.</hi> p. 209. l. 12 <hi>can erre.</hi> p. 211 l. 11. <hi>no more.</hi> p. 214. l. 35. <hi>enormious.</hi> p. 229. l. 35. <hi>name Monke.</hi> p. 232. l. 1. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>positors.</hi> p. 240. l. 35. <hi>vtterly.</hi> p. 241. l. 30. <hi>appearance.</hi> p. 243. l. 16. <hi>refraine.</hi> p. 255. l. 18. <hi>no iust.</hi> p. 260. l. 15. 16. <hi>infinite.</hi> p. 262. l. 27. <hi>day and day.</hi> p. 266. l. 33. <hi>Cassianus.</hi> p. 288. in the last line of the margentread <hi>and</hi> 21. p. 293. l. 16. <hi>coercion</hi> p. 296. l. 25. <hi>coercion.</hi> pag. 399. l. 4. in the margent <hi>grant.</hi> and lin. 31. dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. p. 302. l. 34. <hi>coerciue.</hi> p. 334. l. 19. <hi>contract.</hi> from the page 341. to 349. put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue in the first line <hi>Against the Oath of Allegiance.</hi> p. 345. l. 28. read <hi>the last of Ianuary.</hi> p. 366. l. 11. <hi>forbid.</hi> p. 370. l. 28. <hi>this Disp.</hi> p. 371. l. 10. <hi>doe make.</hi> p. 374. l. 35. <hi>will not.</hi> p. 375. lin. 13. <hi>to himselfe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In the preface.</hi> nu. 10. reade <hi>had not.</hi> p. 404. l. 2. <hi>Censurers.</hi> p. 410. l. 3. <hi>will come.</hi> p. 416. l. 39. originall.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The other faults I beseech the curteous Reader to correct.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="246"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>