<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Translator.</title>
           <author>Roui, Fr.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100406_Fr1_15</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22622</idno>
           <idno type="STC">91</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100406</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Translator.</title>
                 <author>Roui, Fr.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The loves of Clitophon and Leucippe : A most elegant history, written in Greeke by Achilles Tatius: and now Englished</title>
                 <author>Achilles Tatius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Allam, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 255, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>To the Translator.</head>
   <l>AS richer Grapes bloud often rackt, at last</l>
   <l>Loses the former, pleasant, rasie tast;</l>
   <l>Nor <hi>Rhodian</hi> art can to the life expresse</l>
   <l>At second draught the Archetype: No lesse</l>
   <l>Presume we in Translation, where we seeke</l>
   <l>With English pencill to pourtraict the Greeke;</l>
   <l>Whose ev'ry pondrous word in ballance set,</l>
   <l>Drawes sixe of ours: Which striving t'interpret</l>
   <l>We torture language, making the intent</l>
   <l>Of Authors such as what they never meant.</l>
   <l>Mistake me not; I blame not this in thee,</l>
   <l>That rendrest all in pure integritie,</l>
   <l>And faithfulnesse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Nor gives thy 'Edition place</l>
   <l>To that in Latine, or the Tuscan phrase.</l>
   <l>Though some may lash these labours, and repine</l>
   <l>They were not spent on subject more divine;</l>
   <l>Whom nought but Pulpit-travels please: We say</l>
   <l>Who made time to be serious, made to play▪</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="13"/>Did not sweet <hi>Heliodore</hi> and <hi>Eustath</hi> lend</l>
   <l>Stolne houres to Fancies, and made condiscend</l>
   <l>The Venerable Mitre, for to prove</l>
   <l>To handle pen drawne from the wings of Love,</l>
   <l>The sacred Crozier laid aside, whereby</l>
   <l>Lives <hi>Chariclea</hi> to eternitie,</l>
   <l>And faire <hi>Ismene?</hi> Sage, and grave, and wise,</l>
   <l>Who pitcht their contemplations on the skies,</l>
   <l>And liv'd among the Starres; whose nimble braines</l>
   <l>Ran o're the Pole, such as thine Authors, deignes</l>
   <l>To decke our thoughts in amorous slavery,</l>
   <l>Offering no force or rape to modesty:</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Longus</hi> his Shepheards stories, and, not knowne</l>
   <l>Yet, <hi>Aristaenetus,</hi> with cleare <hi>Alciphron,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>May safely still be handled; and above</l>
   <l>All learned Worthies of the schoole of Love</l>
   <l>The godlike <hi>Sydneys</hi> workes. It doth not skill</l>
   <l>Though <hi>Cato</hi> Florals see, he's <hi>Cato</hi> still.</l>
   <l>May not I, honest too, great <hi>love</hi> behold</l>
   <l>Slide into <hi>Danaes</hi> lap in drops of gold?</l>
   <l>May we not from the windowes of our hearts</l>
   <l>View <hi>Cupid</hi> ayming with sweet-bitter darts,</l>
   <l>And still be shot-free? or discerne the fire</l>
   <l>His flaming torches yeeld, and scape his ire?</l>
   <l>Bookes are like bogs; heed with what foot we tread,</l>
   <l>We may not sinke; so with what minde we reade.</l>
   <l>Iudge others what they please: what you have done,</l>
   <l>Certes 'tis good: shew it the glaring Sunne.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Fr: Roui.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>