<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honorable my verie good Lord, Robert Deuoreux, Earle of Essex and Ewe, Vicount of Hereford, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, &amp;c. Master of the Queenes Maiesties horse, knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most ho∣nourable priuie Counsel, the continuall encrease of Gods euerlasting fauour, peace and comfort in this, and in the world to come.</title>
           <author>Linaker, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100280_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05517</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15638</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100280</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honorable my verie good Lord, Robert Deuoreux, Earle of Essex and Ewe, Vicount of Hereford, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, &amp;c. Master of the Queenes Maiesties horse, knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most ho∣nourable priuie Counsel, the continuall encrease of Gods euerlasting fauour, peace and comfort in this, and in the world to come.</title>
                 <author>Linaker, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A comfortable treatise for the reliefe of such as are afflicted in conscience</title>
                 <author>Linaker, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Boyle, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 71, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>To the right honorable my verie good Lord, Robert Deuoreux, Earle of Essex and Ewe, <hi>Vicount of Hereford, Lord Ferrers of</hi> Chartley, &amp;c. Master of the Queenes Maiesties horse, knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable priuie Counsel, the continuall encrease of Gods euerlasting fauour, peace and comfort in this, and in the world to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Anie men (right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) when they intend some euil, I meane when they haue resolued free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and boldly to trade in some sinne without check and control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doe seeke to shroude themselues vnder the cloth and countenaunce of some great persons of Worship and Honour. If my purpose or practise were such, I might iustly feare to bee
<pb facs="2"/>crossed and cursed in this my enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise. The searcher of all hearts know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that my purpose, prayers, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours (through his gracious assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance) are, and shall bee, to keepe a good conscience in my ministerie, to walke in the vprightnesse of my heart, and to bee kept blamelesse to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Iesus Christ. In this resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may it seeme good vnto your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as you haue alreadie (at the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest and humble sute of manie my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good and worshipfull friends) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued me to fauour: so still to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue your most honourable protection for my further encouragement in well doing. May it also please your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and religious disposition, to comfort and countenaunce this Mite, and small measure of comfort, which according to grace receiued, I haue once addressed, and now the second time published, and enlarged for the reliefe of such as grieue and groane vnder the heauie but then of their sinnes. Behold I presume to present it vnto your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as the best present I haue, to testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my humble dutie, seruice, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse.
<pb facs="2"/>And if by Gods good fauour and blessing there shall be ame one sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, worde, syllable, or letter, which may bring, or adde comfort to you or yours, I shall be occasioned the rather, heartily to blesse God for so great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and to pray more instantly, that your Honour may be blessed for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your honours most humble and bounden seruant in the Lord,</hi>
Robert Linaker.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>