<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLY Iudicious, and worthily eminent in his Profession, Mr. WILLIAM RANDOLPH, Doctor of Physicke.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100388_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00777</idno>
           <idno type="STC">109</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100388</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLY Iudicious, and worthily eminent in his Profession, Mr. WILLIAM RANDOLPH, Doctor of Physicke.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Diseases of the sovle: a discovrse diuine, morall, and physicall. By Tho. Adams.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>[8], 74, [2] p. ;  4⁰</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>No match</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY Iudicious, and worthily eminent <hi>in his Profession, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>.</hi> WILLIAM RANDOLPH, <hi>Doctor of Physicke.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T will seeme strange to those, that better know my <hi>vnworthinesse</hi> then your <hi>merits,</hi> that I should admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Physicke</hi> to a <hi>Physician.</hi> But my <hi>Apologie</hi> is iust; conuincing rather them of <hi>ignorance,</hi> then my selfe of <hi>presumption.</hi> It is not a <hi>Potion,</hi> I send, but a <hi>Prescript</hi> in paper; which the foolish Patient did eate vp, when he read in it written, <hi>Take this.</hi> Neither do I send it, to direct you, but that you should rectifie it. So the poore <hi>Painter</hi> sent <hi>Appelles</hi> a <hi>Picture,</hi> to mend it, not to commend it. That which tastes of <hi>Philosophie</hi> in it, is but so much of those <hi>axiomes</hi> and <hi>rudiments,</hi> as I gather'd in the <hi>Vniuersitie</hi> in a short time, and haue had much opportunity to lose since. Somewhat is chym'd out of <hi>experience;</hi> wherein I may say, <hi>Neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit as</hi> was <hi>ingenii largitor:</hi> as <hi>Plinie</hi> writes of the Rauen; who labouring of thirst, and spying a vessell with
<pb facs="3"/>
some little water in it, but so deepe as she could not reach, filled the vessell with stones; till the heauier matter sinking downewards, raysed vp the lighter to her easie apprehension. My owne ill health forced me to looke into that poore <hi>Cisterne</hi> of <hi>knowledge,</hi> which I had: and finding it almost <hi>drie,</hi> I assayed by some new <hi>contemplations,</hi> to raise it vp to experience; which now, behold, runnes ouer, and (without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution to it selfe) is communicatiuely dispersed to others. Only doe you vse it, as I desire you should my selfe: if it be in health, conserue it: if foule purge it. For my owne part, I am content, that no happie <hi>meditation</hi> of mine should be <hi>vt Curia Martis Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis;</hi> or like some precious <hi>mysterie,</hi> which a Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioner will get money by, whiles hee liues; but suffer none els to vse, when hee is dead: for hee resolues, it shall die with him. It is more <hi>Morall,</hi> then <hi>Physicall;</hi> and yet the greater part <hi>Theologicall.</hi> wherein I haue most satisfied my owne conscience, in ayming at that punctuall <hi>Center,</hi> and blessed <hi>Scope,</hi> whither all endeuours should looke; the straitening our warped <hi>Affections,</hi> and directing the <hi>Soule</hi> to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And in this passage, (you must pardon mee) I feare not to say your <hi>memory</hi> at least, if not your <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding,</hi> may hereby be helped. My <hi>Medicines</hi> are not very <hi>bitter;</hi> but nothing at all <hi>sweete</hi> to a <hi>sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall</hi> palate: learning from <hi>Saluian;</hi> that <hi>Quae petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantium auribus placent, aegrotantium animis non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunt.</hi> For my <hi>soule,</hi> I prescribe to others that, which I desire euer to take my selfe; such sauing <hi>Recipe's,</hi> as Gods holy <hi>Writ</hi> hath directed mee. For my <hi>Body,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
though I would not haue it lamed by my owne neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, that it might leane vpon the staffe of <hi>Physicke;</hi> hauing not so much <hi>health</hi> to spare, as might allow some vnthrifty expence of it on surfets: yet when it is <hi>sicke,</hi> I desire no other <hi>Phisician</hi> then your selfe. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a great number of men are of my mind, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent are the knocks at your <hi>Study-</hi>dore: but I am sure that all those desires are not enflamed with that light of knowledge, which I haue of your sufficiency, through much priuate conference. Rudenesse or prolixitie do ill in an <hi>Epistle,</hi> and worse when both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and may perhaps please a mans selfe, and none els. I haue done, when I haue (yet once againe) chaleng'd your promised <hi>Iudiciall</hi> of <hi>vrines:</hi> which if you make publike, you shall haue the like addition to my singular thankes. Till a good gale of oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity waft my self ouer to your <hi>Sudbury,</hi> I haue sent you this <hi>Messenger</hi> of that loue and seruice, shall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ready to attend you; desiring that, as it hath found the way to you, you would giue it your <hi>Passe</hi> to the World; and (if it grow poore with contempt) your <hi>Legacie</hi> of <hi>approbation.</hi> Wingraue <hi>in Buck. May vlt.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all iust referen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of loue,
THO. ADAMS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>