<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A Preface vnto the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100582_Fr2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02872</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1301</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100582</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A Preface vnto the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The image of both Churches : after the most wonderfull and heauenly Reuelation of sainct Iohn the Euangelist, contayning a very fruitfull exposition or paraphrase vpon the same. Wherin it is conferred vvith the other scriptures, and most auctorised histories. Compyled by Iohn Bale an exyle also in thys lyfe, for the faithfull testimony of Iesu</title>
                 <author>Bale, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>151, 1, 48, 112, 140 leaves, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ A Preface vnto the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O highly necessary (good Christian Reader) is the knowledge of S. Iohns Apocalips or Reuelation,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12</note> whether thou wilt, to him that is a true member of Christes church, as of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other booke of the sacred Byble. For in none of them all are y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faythfull diligent hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and readers more blessed, nor more liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly so declared obseruing the contentes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, thē in this one booke.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.</note> No wher is it more clerely specified, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghost to bee one euerlastyng God, and Iesus Christ to be the eternall sonne of that lyuing Father (which are the fyrst and chiefe groundes of our Christian faith) then here. No where is the durable kingdome and priesthoode of the sayde Iesus Christ more plentuously spred,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.</note> more playnly proued and more largely vttered, thē in this holy oracle. No where is the doctryne of healthe more purely taught,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 7. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.</note> fayth more throughly commē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor yet rightuousnesse more highlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, then heere. No where are heresies more earnestly condempned, blasphemous vices more vehemētly rebuked,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 15.</note> nor yet their iuste plagues more fiercelye threatened, then in this compendious worke. Herein is the true christian church (which is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meeke
<pb facs="3"/>
spouse of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lambe without spot) in hir right fashyoned colours discribed.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.</note> So is the proud church of hypocrites, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rose coloured whore, the paramour of Antichrist, and the sinfull sinagoge of Sathan, in hir iuste proporcion depaynted, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mercifull forewarning of the Lordes electes.<note place="margin">
         <hi>VVhy this booke is called the Image of both chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi>
      </note> And that is the cause why I haue here intituled thys booke, the <hi>Image of both Churches.</hi> Neyther heere spareth the holy Ghost theyr hypocrisie nor pryde, their Idolatrie nor whoredome, theyr couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, nor most cruell tyranny, with theyr o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther outragious myscheues. No, he toucheth them so nyghly that we should y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> better know them, and be the more ware of them, that he sheweth them to be such a spirituall sorte as maketh dayly marchaundise of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bodyes and soules of men.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 11. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</note> Let vs neuer looke to haue a more open marke of that wicked generation, take heede of them if we lust. He that will lyue godly in Christ, and be a pacyent suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. He that will stande in Gods feare, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare him selfe to temptacyon. He that will be stronge when aduersitie shall come &amp; auoyde all assaultes of Antichrist,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 3. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>Pet</hi> 5. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.</note> and the diuill, let him giue him selfe wholly to the study of this prophecy.</p>
   <p>Not one necessary poynt of beleife is in all the other scriptures,<note place="margin">
         <hi>A brief sum is this boke of the whol scriptures.</hi>
      </note> that is not heere also in one place or other. The very complet summe and whole knitting vp is this heauēly booke of the vnyuersall verities of the Bible. All that Moyses taught in the lawe, Dauid in
<pb facs="3"/>
the Psalmes, and the Prophetes in theyr wrytinges concernyng Christes spyrituall kyngdome both here &amp; aboue,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luc.</hi> 24. <hi>Esay.</hi> 9. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.</note> meete for thys present knowledge are heerein briefly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 16. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18.</note> So is hys eternall vyctory for vs, ouer sinne, death, hell, and the dyuill, with hys perpetuall cleerenesse, aucthoritie, and empyre world without ende, compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously here expressed. Hee that knoweth not thys booke, knoweth not what the church is whereof he is a member.</p>
   <p>For herein is the estate thereof from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes ascention to the ende of the world,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Col.</hi> 1. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 4. <hi>Apoc</hi> 12. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.</note> vnder pleasaunte figures and elegant tropes decy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp; no where els throughly but heere, the tymes alwayes respected. He that delighteth not to beholde the condition of his own citie, is therevnto no louing citizen. And after the true opinion of sainct Austen,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3. <hi>August. Apoc.</hi> 21. <hi>Hier.</hi> 50.</note> eyther wee are citizens in the new Hierusalem with Iesus Christ, or els in the old supersticious Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon with Antichrist y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vicar of sathā. He that with diligēce shall serch y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> matter, specially in this presēt reuelatiō shal throughly perceiue the certaintie thereof.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.</note> Consider the dignytie and worthinesse of this most precious Iewel that the Lord hath left here to our cōsolatiō. Fyrst God the eternall father gaue it vnto Christ his welbeloued sonne in our māhood.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>Luce.</hi> 10. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 21. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 12. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.</note> Christ now glorified committed it vnto the holy Ghost, which is here called an Angell or messenger. The holy Ghost deliuered it vnto <hi>Iohn</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> peculiarly beloued disciple of Iesu.
<pb facs="4"/>
And <hi>Iohn</hi> last of all lefte it with the vnyuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall church to theyr christian eruditiō. Mark now if any other treatise of the sacred Bible had euer so worthy a foreward setting forth.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gilbertus porre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>a. Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>Lucc.</hi> 11▪</note> This is not that it should be altogither neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and not looked vpon▪ No man lighteth a candle (sayth Christ) and conueyeth it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a bushell that men should not see therby.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Mark.</hi> 4.</note> Neuer was this gracious gift giuen of God to be hidden as it hath bene of longe tyme, but to be opened to all the congregations. A more necessary doctrine to the christian eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is not in the whole scriptures; all cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstaunces considered. For besides all that is afore expressed,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iacobus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber super Dionisium.</hi>
      </note> it containeth the vniuersal troubles, persecutions and crosses, that the church suffred in the primatyue spring, what it suffreth now, and what it shall suffer in the latter tymes by the subtile satellytes of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist which are y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cruell mēbers of Sathā.<note place="margin">
         <hi>VVhat this booke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth.</hi>
      </note>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>VVhat it openeth to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
      </note>It manifesteth also what premyes, what crownes, and what glory the sayd cōgregatiō shall haue after this present conflict with the enimyes, that the promysed rewardes myght quicken the hartes of those that the tormēts feareth.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Dyosius A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexādrinus in chiliaste.</hi>
      </note> A prophecye is this <hi>Apocalips</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and is much more excellent thē all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prophecies. Lyke as the lyght is more precious then the shadowe, the veritie then the figure, the new testament then the olde, and the gospell then the lawe, so is this holy oracle more precyous then they. That <hi>Esay, Hieremie, Ezechiell, Danyell, Oseas,</hi> with all
<pb facs="4"/>
the other Prophets warneth afore hande to follow concerning Christ, and hys churche,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Robertus Tuiciensis et Haymo.</hi>
      </note> this mystery declareth effectually fulfilled. It is a full clerenesse to all the cronicles and most notable histories which hath bene writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten since Christes ascension,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Sebastianus mayer in prefacione.</hi>
      </note> opening the true natures of their ages, tymes, and seasons. He that hath store of them, and shall diligentlye serch them ouer conferring the one with the other, time with tyme, and age with age, shal perceyue most wonderfull causes. For in the text are they onely proponed in effecte, and promised to folow in their seasons, and so ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with the other scriptures, but in the cronicles they are euidently seene by all ages fulfilled. Yet is the text a lyght to the crony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and not the cronicles to the text.</p>
   <p>Unto sainct <hi>Iohn</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Euangelist were these<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gilbertus porreta in prologo A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seos.</hi>
      </note> mysteries of the whole Trinitie reueled (as I shewed afore) such tyme as he was of the Emperour <hi>Domicianus</hi> exyled for his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching into the yle of <hi>Pathmos</hi> at the cruell complayntes of the Idolatrous priestes and bishops, &amp; of him so written &amp; sent out of the same exile into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> congregations. In one day were all these marueils seene and in the same written,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Haymo in libro.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note> as witnesseth <hi>Haymo</hi> with dyuers other expositours, and as seemeth agreeable to the text (which is a great wonder) in tokē y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the Lord as <hi>Dauid</hi> reporteth hym,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 44. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.</note> is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry swift writer, which at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same time earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occupied y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hand of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayd <hi>Iohn</hi> Of suche a nature is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> message of this boke w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the other
<pb facs="5"/>
contentes therof, that from no place is it sent more freely,<note place="margin">
         <hi>August. Bedas.</hi>
      </note> opened more cleerely, nor tolde foorth more boldely, than out of exyle. And this should seeme to be the cause thereof. In exyle was it first written, as a little before is mencyoned. In exyle are the powers thereof most earnestly proued of thē that hath faith.<note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>Rabanus et alii docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Hieroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro deviris illustribus.</hi>
         </p>
      </note> As appeareth yet by <hi>Iustinus</hi> the martyr. <hi>Militon</hi> the <hi>Asiane, Hireneus, Hipolytus, Victorinus,</hi> and other which were there of the first expositours in the primatiue church, and in the ende suffered for it y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> death of their bodyes. And though it were than the laste booke of the Byble,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Franciscus Titelman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de aue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poca.</hi>
      </note> and hath bene euer since fardest from knowledge &amp; least regarded of them all, yet was it the first that receiued any mans expositiō, as a booke thought most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to be knowne of the Christians.</p>
   <p>Into the deserte sendeth the Lorde hys church,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12. <hi>Georgius Aemilius.</hi>
      </note> when the filthy spirite by his spight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful spiritualtie speweth out his execrable wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, throwyng the thyrd parte of the starres into the earth with his tayle. He giueth hyr two Egles wings to flye thither with,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 54. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 13. <hi>Luke.</hi> 4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.12.</note> which are the light precepts &amp; examples of Christ to declyne their mischieues. For he both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ed his selfe when occasions were giuen him, and commaunded hys disciples to flee from citie to citie in time of their persecutions. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth hir there a resting place for iij. yeares and an halfe, which are the dayes of <hi>Helyas, Danyell,</hi> and <hi>Iohn.</hi> And all this is not that shee should there be ydle.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17. <hi>Dani.</hi> 12. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 11.</note> Flattery dwellyng
<pb facs="5"/>
at home, and sucking there styll his mothers brestes, may neuer tell out the truth, he seeth so many daūgers on euery side, as displeasur of frindes, decaye of name, losse of goodes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Flattery may neuer tell forth the truth.</hi>
      </note> offence of great men, punishment of body, &amp; ieopardy of lyfe, wyth such other lyke. The forsaken wretched sort, hath the Lorde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided alwayes to rebuke the worlde of sinne for want of true fayth, of hipocrisie,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Math.</hi> 4. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 16.</note> for want of perfect ryghtuousnesse, &amp; of blyndnesse, for lacke of Godly iudgement.</p>
   <p>For nought is it not therfore y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he hath exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a certen number of beleuing brethren the realme of Englande, of the which afflicted family my fayth is that I am one.<note place="margin">
         <hi>VVhy god exileth the faythfull brethren,</hi>
      </note> Where vpon I haue considered it no lesse then my bounde dutie vnder payne of damnation, to admonyshe Christes flocke by thys present reuelation of theyr perills past, and the daū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to come for contempt of the Gospell whych now reygneth there aboue all in the clergy.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Protestaciō of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hereof</hi>
      </note>
   </p>
   <p>I am not the fyrst which hath attempted thys offyce, or taken vpon mee thys ody<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enterpryse, full of rebukes and slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and that maketh mee the boulder. <hi>Iustinus</hi> becomming of a prophane philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher a perfect chrystian,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Franciscus Titelman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus libro.</hi> 2. <hi>de auth. apoc.</hi>
      </note> wrote an exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion vpon this Apocalips, and was slayne for the veritie in the yeare from Christs incarnatyon a. C. and liiii. <hi>Melyton</hi> the Byshoppe of <hi>Sardis</hi> in <hi>Asia</hi> (which was one of the vii. congregatiōs vnto whome Iohn wrote) made also a booke of the same,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hieronimus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. in libro de ilustribus, viris.</hi>
      </note> &amp; lyued
<pb facs="6"/>
about the same tyme in the yeare of our lord a .c.lx. <hi>Hyreneus</hi> a discyple of Polycarpe byshope of Smyrna (which was also one of the sayde congregations) left behinde hym a commentary vpon the same booke,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Sebastianus meier et frā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciscus Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celmannus.</hi>
      </note> and suffred stronge martyrdome for the truth in the yeare of our lorde a c.lxxv. Hypolytus a byshope in Aphrica,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Petrus equi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynus &amp; so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phronius Grecus.</hi>
      </note> a man of much godly wysdome and learning wrote vpon the same about the yeare of our lorde .cc. &amp; .xx. In lyke maner Uictorinus the byshop of Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauis about the yeare of our lorde cc &amp; .lxx. Ticonius the Aphricane, anno. dom. ccc. &amp;, xc. Saynct <hi>Hierome</hi> to <hi>Anatholius Anno. Dom.</hi> cccc. &amp; .x. And saynt <hi>Austin</hi> also,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioannes tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cemius de scriptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eccles<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>sticus.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Anno</hi> dom. cccc. &amp; .xx. with dyuerse other more. <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masius</hi> byshoppe of <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>icina</hi> wrote .v. lytle bookes vpō this Apocalyps vnto <hi>Castorius</hi> whereof this is the beginning.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ambrosius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>usbertus.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Tuis vir il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustris et religiose castori</hi> (which volume I haue redde) and he lyued in the yeare of our Lord .cccc. &amp; .xl.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Redas et Meyerus</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Aprigius</hi> byshop of Pacē in <hi>Spayne,</hi> made a notable work vpon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same about y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yeare of our lorde .ccccc. &amp; .xxx. So did <hi>Cassiodorus Apulus,</hi> as <hi>Petrus Equilinus</hi> calleth him, anno. dom. ccccc.lxx. &amp; called his booke <hi>complexiones in Apocalipsim.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>So did <hi>Isidorus iunior</hi> the bishop of <hi>Hispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioannes. Tritemius de scriptori hus Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticis.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Anno Do. DC.xxx.</hi> with all those that here foloweth. Of whom I haue sene almost so many, as haue there begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings here registred.
<list>
         <head>Ex benedictinis monachis.</head>
         <pb facs="6"/>
         <item>
            <hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edas presbiter Anglus. li. iii apocalipsis sane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti Iohannis inqua.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Alcuinus monachus Anglus. li. i.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Haymo Hirsueldēsis Germanus,</hi>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>Petrus equilinus et Hermannus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>edell.</hi>
            </note>
            <hi>li. vii.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Legimus in ecclesiastica historia.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Strabus fuldensis Germanus, lib. i. Sicut in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularibus literis.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Rabanus maurus, Germanus, li. i.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ambrosius Ansbertus Gallus, li, x. de illustra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione afflatus.</hi>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>Ioannes Tritenuus Spanhemē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> abba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </note>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Robertus Tuiciensis Germanus, lib. xii. Vt tu quoque venerabilis colo.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioachim Abbas Calaber. li. viii. Quia profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da libri huius.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Monachus quidam Cantuariensis, li. i. Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Genesis .xxviii. Vidit.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Easterton monachus Anglus lib. i. Posuit ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra sua in medio.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <head>Ex Canonicis regularibus.</head>
         <item>
            <hi>Richardus de sancto Victore, Scotus,</hi>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>Franciscus citelmānus &amp; Sebastia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus meyer.</hi>
            </note>
            <hi>libro primo.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Gaufredus Antisiodorensis, Gallus, lib. i.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <head>Ex Carthusianis monachis.</head>
         <item>
            <hi>Henricus de Hassia, Germanus, lib. i,</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Dionisius Rikel Germanus, lib. i. Ecce puer meus electus.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <head>Ex sacerdotibus prophaenis.</head>
         <item>
            <hi>Ambrosius de septem tubis, li. i. Tempus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem arbitror.</hi>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>Thomas vvalde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Ranulphus c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>strensis.</hi>
            </note>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Berengarius Thuronensis, Gallus, lib. i.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Gilbertus porreta, Gallus. li. i. Omnes qui pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> volunt viuere.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Author a centum annis, Anglus, libro. i.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <pb facs="7"/>
            <hi>Ioannes Hus, Bohemus, li. i. Cum finierin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> testimonium.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Paulus Burgensis, Iudeus, lib. i. Licet opinio expositorum.</hi>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>Otho brun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius et Conradus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ontorius</hi>
            </note>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Mathias Dorinck, Germanus. lib. i. Costasie doctor Anglus, lib. i. Ecce de scripsieam tibi triplic.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Iacobus Stralen, Germanus, lib. i. Vidit Iacob in somno schalam.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <head>Ex Carmelitanis.</head>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioannes Baconthorpe, Anglus, lib. i. Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipsis Iesu Christi. &amp;c.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioannes Tytleshale,</hi>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>Iohannes Tritemius. Arnoldus Bostius</hi>
            </note>
            <hi>Anglus. li. i. Est autem A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalipsis, Grecus sermo.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Thomas de ylleya, Anglus li. i. Apocalipsis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelacio dicitur.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioannes Barath, Hannonius, lib. i. Ego Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vidi ostium.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioannes de Vernone, Gallus, lib. i. Nicolaus de Alsacia, Germanus, lib. i. Ioannes Bloxam, Anglus, lib. i. De apparicione septem sigillo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioannes Elyne,</hi>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>Anglorum Heliades Iohannes Balei libro.</hi> 2.</note>
            <hi>Anglus, li, i. Secundum Isido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ethimolo.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioannes Tilneye, Anglus, li. i. Septem ecclesijs in Asya.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Henricus Winchingham, Anglus, li. i. Aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum est templum Dei.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioannes Thorpe, Anglus, lib. i.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioannes Egidius, Gallus, lib. i. Apocalip. &amp;c. Ioanni Euangeliste.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioannes Haynton, Anglus, lib. i. Beatus qui legit verba.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <pb facs="7"/>
         <head>Ex Augustinianis.</head>
         <item>Augustinus de Auchona, Italus,<note place="margin">Ambrosius choriolanus Nicolaus. Bertrandus</note> lib. i.</item>
         <item>Iordanes Saxo, Germanus, lib, primo. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trandus parayte, Tholosanus, lib, i. Augusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de Roma, Italus. li, primo, Philippus de Mantua, Italus, li. primo. Ioannes Capgraue, Anglus, li. primo. Syluester Meoccius, Venet. lib. i, Promaiori intelligentia.</item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <head>Ex dominycanis.</head>
         <item>Iordanes Botergius, Germenus.<note place="margin">Leander Bonouien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis. Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Archie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piscopus.</note> li. i. Hugo Bar chinonensis, Gaillus lib. i.</item>
         <item>Asser pinguis panis eius &amp;c.</item>
         <item>Albertus Magnus Germanus lib. i. Confiteor tibi pater.</item>
         <item>Stephanus Bisuntinus, Gallus lib. i. Nicolaus Gorham, Gallus li. i.</item>
         <item>Bernardus de Trilia. Narbonensis, li. i.</item>
         <item>Paganus Bergomensis, lumbardus. li. i.</item>
         <item>Aluarus de Caturco, Tholosanus.<note place="margin">Nicolaus Bertrandus Sebastianus me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erus.</note> lib. i.</item>
         <item>Fredericus de Venecijs, Italus lib, pri,</item>
         <item>Ioannes Annius, Viterbiensis li, prim.</item>
         <item>Hieronymus Sauanarola, Italus, lib. i</item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <head>Ex Franciscanis,</head>
         <item>Alexander de Hales, Anglus, lib. primo.<note place="margin">Titelmanus Bernardus Lutzenbur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gus. Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an. Tritemius.</note>
         </item>
         <item>Helias de Hanibalis, Italus, lib primo,</item>
         <item>Petrus Ioannis Cathalanus. li. primo,</item>
         <item>Ioannes Walleys, Anglus, lib. primo,</item>
         <item>Petrus Aureolus, Tholosanus. libro. 1.</item>
         <item>Nicolaus Lyranus, Germanus. libro. ij.</item>
         <item>Oportet te iterum prophetare.</item>
         <item>Astesanus Astensis, Lumbardus, li. i.</item>
         <item>
            <pb facs="8"/>Bernardinus Senensis, Italus, li. i. Beatus qui legit et audit.</item>
         <item>Theodoricus Andree. Tholosanus, lib. i.</item>
         <item>Ioannes de Rupe scissa. lib. i.</item>
         <item>Franciscus Titelmannus, Germanus, li. ii. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioribus diebus eruditis.</item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <head>Ex neotericis.</head>
         <item>
            <hi>Martinus Lutherus, Germanus. lib. i.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Varias prophecias inuenimus in.</hi>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>The wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our tyme vpon the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips.</hi>
            </note>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Sebastianus Meyer, Bernensis. li. i.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>De lib. Apocalipseos cum.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Georgius Aemilius, Germanus lib. i.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Mira quedam inest auiditas.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Franciscus Lambertus, Gallus. li. vii. Israeliti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Mose Dei lege.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Huldricus Zwinglius, Heluecius lib. i.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioannis Brencius, Sueuus lib. i.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Ioannes Caluinus, Gallus. li. i.</hi>
         </item>
         <item>
            <hi>Melchior Hofman, Germanus. lib. i.</hi>
         </item>
      </list>
And many other more.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Doctors are folowed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with the scriptures.</hi>
      </note>Of these Commentaries haue I taken both example to doe this thing, and also coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell to vnderstande the text, to none of them wholly addict, but as I perceiued them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes agreinge to the Scriptures. What chronographers &amp; historianes I haue herein folowed for the tymes and ages of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian church, besides the Scriptures, it will euidently apeare to the reader in the margēt of this volume.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoca.</hi> 8 <hi>Apoca.</hi> 11 <hi>Apoca.</hi> 14. <hi>Esay.</hi> 1. <hi>Gene.</hi> 10. <hi>Hiere.</hi> 23.</note> I know there will be great thonderings, lyghtninges, and earthquakes at the comminge foorth thereof, for so is it here oft promised of the holy ghost.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>The boystuous tyrauntes of Sodoma with theyr great Nemroth <hi>Wynchester,</hi> and the execrable citizens of Gomorra, with theyr shorne sinered captaines, wyll sturre aboute them. Much payne haue they of long tyme taken, and many haue they cruelly burned, as was seene of late yeares in <hi>Couentrie, London,</hi> &amp; in other places more,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Fabianu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> et alij in chronicis.</hi>
      </note> to obscure the knowledge thereof. Who can suppose thē that they wyll now sit styll theyr mischeues made so manifest? Our worldly wyse bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren also, which are neither hote nor colde, wyll starcle a course at the matter.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoca.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Eccle.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>0. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> I know somewhat is to be suffred at theyr handes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so. For they alwayes tarry theyr tymes, &amp; wyll not wake the shrewed curre for hurting themselues.</p>
   <p>Graciously hath the Lorde called them, specially now of late,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gala.</hi> 1. <hi>Esa.</hi> 60. <hi>Math.</hi> 22.</note> but his voyce is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing regarded. His seruauntes haue they imprisoned, tormented, and slayne, hauinge his veritie in muche more contempt then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. We loked for peace (sayth Hieremye the Prophet) and we fare not the better at all. We wayted for a tyme of health,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hiere.</hi> 8. <hi>Hiere.</hi> 14▪ <hi>Psalm.</hi> 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Apoca.</hi> 13.</note> and we fynde here nothing els but trouble. And no marucile, consideringe the beastes head that was wounded, is now healed vp againe so workemanly, as the .xiii. chapter here mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioneth. The abhominable hipocrisie,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esaie.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Math.</hi> 23▪ <hi>Apoca.</hi> 13. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>Apoca.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, pryde, &amp; fylthinesse of those terrible ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magaūts of antichrists holy household, those two horned whoremoūgers, those cōiurers
<pb facs="9"/>
of Egipt,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Iude.</hi> 1.</note> and lecherous locustes leapynge out of the smoke of the pitte bottomlesse, which dayly deceyueth the ignoraunt mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tytude wyth theyr sorceryes and charmes, must be shewed to the worlde to theyr vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter shame and confusion.</p>
   <p>They knowe as dyd Balaam the sorcerer, that ouer a gorgious glittering whore euery fleshely man is inordynatly wanton,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Nu.</hi> 24. <hi>Iude.</hi> 1. <hi>Proue.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 6. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2. <hi>Osce.</hi> 8. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18.</note> ferce, &amp; greedy. Folowinge hys wayes therefore, they haue alwayes for lucres sake, gloriously garnished theyr holy mother, the madame of myschife, and proude sinagoge of Sathan, wyth golde, siluer, pearle, precious stone, veluets, silkes, miters, copes, crosses, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etes, ceremonies, sensinges, blessinges, bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gala.</hi> 4. <hi>Osce.</hi> 4. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16, <hi>Psal.</hi> 102. <hi>Hiere.</hi> 6.</note> brawlynges, processions, popetts, and such other madde mastryes (whereof the church that Christ left here behinde him knewe not one iote) to prouoke the carnal idyotes to hir whoredome in the spyryte. The Lorde hath longe suffered them of mercy,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esay.</hi> 58. <hi>Psal.</hi> 54. <hi>Gene.</hi> 12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> and wythhoulden from thē his right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hande of theyr deserued vengeaunce, yet wyll they not fall to repentaunce nor amende theyr dayly mischifes.</p>
   <p>To tell them freely of theyr wycked workes by the scriptures, I haue exyled my selfe for euer from myne owne natiue countrie, kyndred, fryndes, acquaintaunce (which are the great delyghtes of this lyfe) &amp; am well contented for Iesus Chrystes sake and for the comforte of my brethren there,
<pb facs="9"/>
to suffer pouertie, penury, abiection, reprofe, and all that shall come besides. A commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement the Lorde hath giuen in this booke vnto them whome hee hath called of mercye from their wretched beggeries,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18. <hi>Hier.</hi> 50. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17.</note> to spare no rebukes, but to powre out double vpon that bloudy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>awde &amp; malicious mother of theirs. Neuer was this commaundement more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to be folowed then now, hys holye worde of saluation so presently set at nought, despised, and persecuted of hir madde moodie mynisters.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.</note> Unto heauen are hir sinnes gone vp in these latter dayes, as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> heere witnesseth, requiring vengeaunce for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents bloud that shee hath so cruelly shed. And the Lord hath remembred hir wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse accordyng to his promyse,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18. <hi>Luce.</hi> 13.</note> as partlye hath bene seene in this realme, and in diuers other more.</p>
   <p>I doubt not but within short space she shal be wholly turned ouer into the bottomlesse pit again with all hir heathenish ceremonies,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 9. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.</note> superstitions and sorceries, and neuer return hetherwarde no more then the great mightie mylstone y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is throwne into the seas bottom, Christ so restored vnto his right spouse. Wō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders wil appeare cōcerning this &amp; such other matters, to him that shall diligently examine the scriptures &amp; historyes alleged in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. For only minister I an occasion heere vnto them of a farther serch.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. <hi>Mar.</hi> 9. <hi>Luce.</hi> 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.</note> Nothing wil be hidden from him, that asketh with meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, seeketh in fayth, and in prayer desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="10"/>
the glory of the Lorde. Euident will those secrete mysteries be vnto him, whiche are priuely hidde vnto other vnder dark am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bages and parables.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Esay.</hi> 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 10. <hi>Luce.</hi> 8.</note> Though this heauenly treasure of health be vnder locke and keye of vnknowne similitudes, and so bee shutte vp from the vntowarde and wicked generation for their vnbeleuers sake, yet will it be playn ynough to the faithfull beleuers instauntlye calling vpon him which hath the key of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> to open vnto them the dore of his infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble verities.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iacob.</hi> 1. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3. <hi>Col.</hi> 4. <hi>Iacob.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Psal.</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Ephe.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> They shall be sure to finde there that shall richly delyght them, and that will greatly replenishe the most wholesome desire of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oules, concerning their necessary saluation in Christ.</p>
   <p>The more the figuratiue speech aboundeth heere,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Franciscus La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>bertus in prefaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one.</hi>
      </note> the more let them conferre it with the other scriptures without all honyed colours of retoricke or of crafted philosophy, specially with those which of their owne nature ioint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreeth to the same. Nothing ought heere to be sought of curiositie,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Georgius Aemilius in prefaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one.</hi>
      </note> but of loue towards God, for defence of his most pure doctryne, and for auoydance of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> craftie snares of the viuel. A perfect preparation is it to a cōstant soule when the battayle is seene afore, the ende thereof knowne, and the remedies lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Heere are we admonished afore hande of two most daungerous euils,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gilbertus porreta, &amp; Georgius Aemilius.</hi>
      </note> neyther to agree to those tyrantes which battayleth with the Lambe in his elect members, nor yet to obey those deceiptful bishops y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in hipocrisie vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth
<pb facs="10"/>
the churches tytles. Of suche tirryble plagues of vengeaunce as were comming to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Israelites,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esay.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <hi>Hiere,</hi> 8. 1. <hi>Mac.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> the Lorde euer war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them afore by his Prophets. And none was there that escaped them so cleerely, as they dyd whiche regarded those warninges, watching euermore the conclusions of them. Much lesse harme felte they of <hi>Antiochus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanes</hi> that had redde <hi>Daniels</hi> prophecy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and marked it,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 1. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. 1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 6, <hi>Luc,</hi> 2.</note> then they which knewe it not when the Tyraunte came vpon them. Through dyligent expecration in the fayth of Gods promises, receyued iust <hi>Symeon</hi> and <hi>Anna</hi> the sauiour of the world in hys tender infancie.</p>
   <p>Mencion maketh the holy Ghost heere of <hi>Gog</hi> and of <hi>Magog</hi> two tirryble fierce eny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Christes congregation,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apoc,</hi> 20, <hi>Ezech,</hi> 38▪</note> and sheweth afore hande their purposed mischieues. Let vs not suppose it to be a fable,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ezec,</hi> 39, <hi>Apoc,</hi> 13. <hi>Num.</hi> 23, 1. <hi>Ioh,</hi> 4,</note> that he so ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly telleth vs. Neyther let vs thinke but this warning is of loue, if we liste so to take it, and accept it for a trueth. Immedyately after the Apostles preaching▪ was this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie giuen to the Christian church (which hath bene alwayes a smal congregation) least they shoulde vnbewares at the subtile sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestions of these two enimyes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>VVha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> this prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and to what ende.</hi>
      </note> throwe asyde the sinceritie of Christes Gospell. So glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous are the pretenses of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Romysh Pope and <hi>Mahomete,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioannes Oecolāpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius in▪</hi>
      </note> that they seeme vnto them whyche regarde not these warnings, the verye Angelles of lyghte, and theyr
<pb facs="11"/>
churches most holy congregations, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diuels with their filthy dregges of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. The Pope in his church hath ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes without number.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>miam &amp; Danielē.</hi>
      </note> None ende is there of their babling prayers, their portases, beads, temples, aulters, songes, houres, belles, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Popish ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies without number,</hi>
      </note> Organes, ornamēts, Iewels, lights, oylings, shauings, religions, disguisings, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie of feasts, cōstrained vowes, fastings, processions, and pratlings, that a man would think they wer proctours of Paradise. On y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other side <hi>Mahomet</hi> in his church is plentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous also in holy obseruations.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Guihelmus Tripolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tusaraceno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
      </note> They washe them selues oft, they frequent their temples, they pray fiue tymes in the day, they reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently inclyne, they lye prostrate vpon the grounde, they feruently call to God, they are temperate in feedyng, not curious in theyr buyldynges,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioannes Cuspinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine turca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
      </note> they abstayne from wyne, they abhorre Idolles, they hate them that are proude, and commende all sobernesse. And these vertuys haue they to appeare most in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent liuers. But vnto what ende thys holynesse leadeth, the sequele heereof decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. <hi>Daniell</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aketh these two but one, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are both of one wicked spirite,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. <hi>Oecolāpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padius in Danielem.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13.</note> and reporteth his blasphemous mouthe to vtter presumptuous things. Sainct <hi>Iohn</hi> sayeth also that the Dragon speaketh blasphemyes against God in them both. Marke both their voyces, and ye shall fynde these sayings most true. The Pope maketh hys boast, hee is the highe priest, hee is of equall power with
<pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>Peter,</hi> he can not erre,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioannes Oecolāpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius in Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nielem. Theodorus Bibliander in christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na consulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</hi>
      </note> he is heade and spouse of the church, and he is Christes immedyate vicar. By this braulyng boaste hee maketh men to beleue, he may constitute lawes, kepe vnder the Gospell, distribute kyngdoms, sell promocions and benifices, set vp a Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, prouyde satisfactions, make new bodyes to Christ, redeme dead mens soules, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit sinne for money.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Mahomete</hi> braggeth also,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioannes Oecolāpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius in Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nielē.</hi>
      </note> that he is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great prophet, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> promises <hi>Messias</hi>▪ y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Apostle of both testamēts, abled both by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> law &amp; the gospel, &amp; that he hath his name frō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eternall throne of God. He is well contented that Christ be an holy Prophet, and a most worthie creature,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioannes Cuspinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus et Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliander.</hi>
      </note> yea▪ the word of God▪ the soule of God▪ and the spirit of God, conceiued of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> holy ghost, and borne of Mary the virgin, but he will in no case graunt hym to be the sonne of God, nor that he dyed here for mans redemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ion. Both these two mayntayners of mischief al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth <hi>Moyses</hi> lawe, the Psalter,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioannes Oecolāpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius in Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nielē.</hi>
      </note> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and the Gospell, yea, they commende them, auaunce them, sing them, reade them, honour them, and reuerently vse them in all their doyngs.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Theodorus Bibliander in christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na consul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione.</hi>
      </note> Yet will they haue their owne filthy lawes preferred aboue them, the Pope his execrable decrees, &amp; <hi>Mahomete</hi> his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Alchorane,</hi> els will they murther men without measure. Thus though they out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly appeare very vertuous (yet are they the malignaunt ministers of Sathan, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord which hath redenied them. By
<pb facs="12"/>
these may wee measure their inferiour mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandies,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mat,</hi> 23, <hi>Apoc,</hi> 13, 2, <hi>Tim,</hi> 4, <hi>Apoc,</hi> 18, <hi>Hier,</hi> 50,</note> hauing their lyuery and marke.</p>
   <p>Of these hath our louing Lord premony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed vs in this heauenly worke of his, and graciously called vs away from their abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, least we shoulde bee partakers of theyr sinnes, and so receyue of their plagues. If we vnthankfully neglect it, the more daū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is ours. Let no man take the corrections of this booke to mallice.<note place="margin">
         <hi>A christian request of the Author</hi>
      </note> But if hee chaunce in it as in a cleare glasse to perceiue him selfe spotted, let him washe away the deformities, for Gods worde spareth no mans iniquytie. Read my whole Commentary, els iudge me not. In no wyse rebell I heere agaynst any princely power, or aucthoritie giuen of God, but agaynst Antichristes filthy tytles.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Antichristes titles are not of God,</hi>
      </note> The grace of our Lorde Iesus Christ bee euer more with thee (good faythfull Reader) and with all those good men that intierly hunger for his rightuousnesse, Amen.</p>
   <trailer>Thus endeth the Preface of the Image of both Churches, out of Sainct Iohns Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calips.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>