<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE, CONTEININGE A iuste complaint of the disobediēce that now is towardes the spiritual gouer∣nours, and of the pitiful lacke of suche necessarie reliefe of our soules, as by them wee shoulde haue, with the argument of the treatise fo∣lowinge.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100097_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16820</idno>
           <idno type="STC">372</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100097</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE, CONTEININGE A iuste complaint of the disobediēce that now is towardes the spiritual gouer∣nours, and of the pitiful lacke of suche necessarie reliefe of our soules, as by them wee shoulde haue, with the argument of the treatise fo∣lowinge.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise made in defence of the lauful power and authoritie of priesthod to remitte sinnes : of the peoples duetie for confession of their sinnes to Gods ministers: and of the Churches meaning concerning indulgences, commonlie called the Popes pardo [n] s. By William Alle M. of Arte, and student in diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Allen, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fowler (Fouler), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 412, 8 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE, <hi>CONTEININGE A</hi> iuste complaint of the disobediēce that now is towardes the spiritual gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and of the pitiful lacke of suche necessarie reliefe of our soules, as by them wee shoulde haue, with the argument of the treatise fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowinge.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecause y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vniust clayme &amp; chalēge of any power not geuen doth highly displease God, frō whō only al preheminence of mā procedeth, no doubt al priestes and Bishopes, who haue so lōg practised pardoning and punishing of sin, if they hold not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> right of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lēt function by Gods own graunt, they haue buyld this many hundreth yeares towardes hel, &amp; can neither auoyde the heauy indignation of God, in whose of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and prerogatiue they haue vniustly intermedled, not yet marueile at their disdayne amōgest men, seing it is sayd,<note place="margin">Eccl. 20.</note> that the vsurper of power is woorthely
<pb facs="5"/> hated: <hi>Qui potestatē sibi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>umitiniustè, odietur.</hi> But if that most high &amp; holy order do by good right &amp; reason, &amp; by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> son of God Christ Iesus his own warrāt &amp; special cōmission, occupy y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> seate of iudgemēt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Church for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gouermēt of our souls &amp; neadful search of our secret sins thē it stādeth lamētably w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> disobedient captayns of this cōtēpt, through whose cōtinual call to seditiō, so many haue bē caried away, frō y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> obeysāce y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is due to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> soueraing power geuē to gods ānoited.</p>
   <p>They remember well (such is theyr exercise in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> woord) how y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> disdayne of Moyses &amp; Aarons prelacy ouer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thē God chose to be his peculiar, moued his maiestie to so great indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiō, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he droue downe Core &amp; al his cōfederacie to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> depth of hel both bodie &amp; soule thē selues a lyue, &amp; al the people looking on their fal so fearful. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample had bē of lesse respect, if his heuy hand had stayed vpō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> principal of that prowde sort, but it did not. for ther pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished, by straunge fire of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> accessaries to that Schisme, two hundreth &amp; fiftie moe. And the grudge, alas, of the people
<pb facs="5"/> not ceassing so, God sent fier frō heauē, &amp; wasted xiiij m. &amp; vij c. of thē at ōce. And al this saith Moyses: <hi>Vt sciatis quia blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemauerint Dominum,</hi> that you may be well assured,<note place="margin">Iosepus saith that Dathā ād Abyron perished at the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peninge of the earth ād Cores by the fier af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tervvard amongst those that offered incense. Lib. 4. c. 2 Antiq.</note> that they blasphemed oure Lord God. So nere dooth the cōtempt of Goddes ministers, touche his owne person, that in disdaine of the one, there is accompt made of most horrible blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of the other. This Cores, as Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ephus writeth, <hi>was a man that had a cast in talke to please the people,</hi> as the seditious often haue: and this was a great flowre of his perswasiō of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple to seditiō &amp; disobediēce, as holy writ reporteth: <hi>Cur eleuamini, sup populū Domini? <hi>It is sufficciēt for our purpose, that the whol multitude is sanctified, and the Lord is in thē, why do you exalt your selues aboue the people of God?</hi>
      </hi> Thus said y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> seditious against Gods priestes thē: &amp; now truly, both y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cher do pipe Cores note, of <hi>our eleuamini</hi> in euery play &amp; pulpit, neuer hauing in mind their lamētable fal, whose steppes they like so wel to folowe.</p>
   <p>Mary I cā not tel wel, whether y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cases
<pb facs="6"/> be cōparable, though I nothing doubt but oures is much woorse:<note place="margin">De sacer. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> For. S. Chrysostome sayth, that the disobediēce of Dathon and the rest of that confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie, rose rather vpon the affectation of so high a function, wyth admiration of their dignitie, then vpon any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of that power, in which the prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes of God were placed: but the disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure and the derogation that now is doen to the much more excellent office, standeth vpon vnfaythfulnes, mistrust of Gods promisse, loue of sinne, liking of libertie, lothsommes of truth, and vnmyndfulnes of saluation. In which case though neyther the heauens yeld fier for ther present punishment, nor y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth open for theyr spedie passage to eternal payne, yet the perpetuall fight whiche they kepe agaynst Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, there disordered life, and diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, there darknesse of vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in such light of approued trueth, and the continuall course of the Church whiche in marueylouse myserie they doo willingly susteyn, doth, me thinke, fully resemble the lamentable state of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <pb facs="6"/> damned and forsakē sorte, and therefore beinge yet a lyue, in good lykinge, and lybertie, I feare they wyttingly &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lullie perishe.</p>
   <p>And yet I am not so voyd of al hope of their recouery, that I would refuse to conferre wyth them, touching that authoritie of remissiō of sinnes or other preheminence, which the Priestes of Christes Church doo clayme, and they so earnestlie controll. Though the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I would doo it, for the helpe of the more hūble sorte, which in these dayes of disobedience, be rather dryuen out of the way by force of the common tēpest, then by malice or misbehauiour towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the ministerie, whom in Christes name I must aduertise to cōsider care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, in what doubt and daunger they and all ther dearest doo stande, in this pitifull vacation and long lacke of the practise of priesthoode for the remission of their sinnes &amp; other nedeful succour of ther soules. For if Christ,<note place="margin">Cōtempt of mans ministeri for remis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sion of synnes bringeth dānatiō.</note> by whose bloud we obteyne pardon of our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, haue by his ordinance made man y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> minister of our recōciliation to God &amp;
<pb facs="7"/> the bestower of his mercy in remissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of sinnes, then doubtlesse who so euer neglecteth, to walke the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en waye of saluation, and refuseth the ordinarie meanes of mercye, whiche Christe meaneth to be applied to oure vse none otherwise, but by the office of mortall men, he lyueth in sinne perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, he dieth in sinne wythout hope of recouerie, &amp; for sinne wythout doubt shall perish euerlastingly.</p>
   <p>Therefore the matter of so great importance, standing on so doubtfull termes, it were no wisdome to sleepe so soundly in suche present peril, nor to continue wythout care and singular respect of most dredful state, In which, if we passe our dayes wthout hope or possibilitie of Goddes mercie, by cause we refuse mans ministery, then all our life and studies, all our paynes or pleasures, all our woorkes and wayes do nothinge ells, but driue vs in diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to extreme death and despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
   <p>I make the more matter hereof, for that not onely such as be ledde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="7"/> folye and falshode by the perswasiō of some, to whose teachinge and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge they haue vnaduisedly addicted them selues, but also diuerse euen of the faythfull, that be not fallen (than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be geauen to God) so farre, as to contemne the Churche, and Christes appoynted ordinance, are not yet so touched, as in such case of extreme miserie, Christen men should be.<note place="margin">Heresy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nfecteth daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uē vvher she Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not.</note> For heresie is such a creeping and conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouse canker, that, albeit she vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie (through mercy and Goddes gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce) kill not all, yet she dulleth the conscience, dryeth vppe the zeale, and enfecteth the mindes of most.</p>
   <p>The lyke lacke of Christian comforte hath bene often ells amongest the people in suche stormes of the Churche: but so lytle care and consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration thereof, I doo not lightly remember.</p>
   <p>In the persecution of the Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalles and Arian Gothes in Affrike the people of God were seuered from theyre pastours, and thereby wanted
<pb facs="8"/> succoure of their soules as we nowe doo, but therof they conceiued such greif &amp; heauines, that it is surely lamentable to remember:<note place="margin">Li. 2. de persecut. Vandal.</note> The story is recorded by Victor &amp; the woordes of the sorowfull people vttered in the waies, as their ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Bishopes did passe towardes theire banishment, be reported thus: A mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous preasse of faithful people, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> highe wayes coulde not receiue, came downe the hills with tapers in their handes, and laid their deare children at the Martyrs feet (so they termed the witnesses of Goddes truth then) and pitifully complayned thus.<note place="margin">The so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovve of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple for their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopes bannish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
      <hi>Alas too whom doo you leaue vs so desolate, whiles your selfes goe to the croune of martyrdome? who shal nowe baptise these poore babes, in the fountes of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely water? who shall loose vs tied in the bandes of our offenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es, by pardon and reconciliation? who shal prescribe to vs the due of penaunce for our sins past? For to you it was surely said: what so euer you loose in earth, it shal like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise be loosed in heauen.</hi> Such you see was the carefulnes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people thā,
<pb facs="8"/> in that litle lack of so necessary a thing: where now in so long desolatiō of most holy thinges, and our greatest comfort, fewe there be that take any greif of so much miserie at al, and that hartely la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the case, almost none. If we assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly beleeued (as it is surely true) that al whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h passe this present life in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bōds of mortal sin, should euerlastingly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishe without al hope of mercy, and thē to be vndoubtedly bound in theire of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, whom the priestes of the holy Church had not loosed in this life (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting only the case of extrem necessity where by no means possible mans mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery can be obteined) then truly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the feare of our owne dangerous state, our hartes would bleed for pity &amp; compassion of so many that depart this present world, in the det of eternal dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, not only of our Christiā brethrē commonly, but of our deerest and best beloued peculiarly. It is not my time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conscience, nor scrupulous cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that rayseth this feare: but it is the graue sentence of Goddes ordinance, it is S. Augustines owne iudgemēt that
<pb facs="9"/> moueth me of pitie to moue, &amp; of duetie to admonish my brethrē &amp; friendes, of a thing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> perteineth to them all so neare. S. Augustin, cōceiuing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> manifold mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Christiā people in thabsence of their true Pastours in times of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutiō, doth liuely set furth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> godly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuors of faithful folks in these words: Doe we not cōsider, whē the matter is brought to such ā extreme ishue, &amp; wher it can not be by flight auoyded, what a wōderful cūcurse of christiā mē of euery kind, state, &amp; age, is vnto the Church? <hi>wher som cry out for baptim, some for recōciliatiō or absolutiō</hi> (for so I inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prete, <hi>ipsius poenitentiae actionē,</hi> which also may meane a request to haue penāce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> priest) <hi>and al generally cal for cōfort, cōfession, and bestowing of the holy sacramēts? In which extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, if ther lack such as should minister these thinges vnto thē. <hi>Quantū exitiū se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetur eos, {quod} de isto seculo vel nō regenerati ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eūt, vel ligati? quātus estetiā luctus fideliū suo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rū, {quod} eos secū in vitae aeternae requie nō habebūt?</hi>
      </hi> What vtter destructiō shall fal on thē, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> must passe this life, either not christened
<pb facs="9"/> or elles fast bounde in sinne? And what passing sorowe will it be for their faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full frendes,<note place="margin">Of olde the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stours did in times of heresy oftē for a sake their flock, but novve the flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>k hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aken their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours.</note> which shal not haue their company in eternal rest and ioy? Thus far, sayd he for proof that the Pastoures should not forsake their flock, &amp; thus say we nowe, where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flocke haue forsaken their pastours: y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lacke is lyke in both. But ours is so much woorse, because it was procuted willingly, &amp; theirs the more of excusable, because it was both born necessity, &amp; lamented christianly.</p>
   <p>Neither may we think our selues here much to be relieued, by them, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> pretend y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> like practise of such thinges as nowe we lack.<note place="margin">Note.</note> For y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> euer augmented y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sorow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> iust dolour of the faithful. Much it is, God knoweth, to want their Pastours &amp; priestes so dear, &amp; with them for most part all the due of Christianity: but to susteine in stead therof, a kind of apishe imitation of such holy functions, which in deed, by what pretence of holynes so euer it be vsed, is &amp; alwayes hath bene accompted most detestable, that is the great calamity which wasteth most in al tempesteous times of Gods religiō.
<pb facs="10"/> For the only vse, acquaintance, &amp; fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity of this false face or resemblance of trueth &amp; holy actions of the Church, driueth many into a kind of contētaciō &amp; rest in such things, as thēselues, other wise do abhor, or at least, turneth away their earnest appetite &amp; desire of those matters,<note place="margin">Ther is no neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie that should driue any man to take any sacramēt at an he retikes hande, sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and penaunce and that not vvith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie, vhhich only is in present peril of death.</note> which no mā cā without peril of damnation misse. It is not yet ment hereby, that euery sacrament is frustrat alwayes that be by such made, or mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred, although for moste they be so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned, that they be not onely nothing beneficial, but also damnable both to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> geuer &amp; receiuer: but my meaning is, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euē those sacramēts, which be of necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that by Gods special mercy thei may be receiued of such as be not otherwise cōpetent ministers, where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> present pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril of any mans life forceth therevnto, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euē then whē they may be beneficiall to other y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> without schism cal for the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēts, yet they shalbe dānable vnto thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. For hereof let euery mā be bold, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> taketh vpō him any ministery in scism &amp; disorder, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> so oftē as he hath practised it, so often hath he prouoked Gods ire
<pb facs="10"/> towardes himself, &amp; procured, as much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s in him lyeth, his indignation to al y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re partakers therof. S. Basil the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>omplaineth hereof very much in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ayes, by these wordes:<note place="margin">Epist. 70.</note>
      <hi>in the doctrine of impiety ād wickednes the churches babes be now brought vp. For how cā <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t be otherwise? Baptisme is ministered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y heretikes, they helpe forth, such as passe hence, they kepe visitation of the sicke they haue comfortinge of the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>owful, they take on them the ease of such as be burdeyned in all cases, and to be short,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The hurt of heresie to youth.</note>
      <hi>they minister the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of holy communiō: so that, in time though the libertie of Christes religiō be restored againe, the youth shal take such likinge in heretikes practises, to whom by loue and custome, they are so fast knit, that it will be hard to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce thē home to truth againe.</hi> Thus farre spake S. Basil of his dayes: and right good cause haue we no lesse to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne of ours. They were thā incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with Arians, and we with a legiō of newe deuises and bold practisioners of such high &amp; heauēly functiōs, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="11"/> by God nor mā, they are rightly &amp; orderly called vnto.<note place="margin">The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit that vve re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by our nevv ministers</note> By these nowe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our soules seme to liue, but by these alone we surely dye euerlastingly. In al which great desolation of Christian cōfort &amp; all spiritual functiōs this were some solace, if eyther y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> older sort could cōsider what they haue lost, or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> poore children, which are nurced in these no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties, might learne what they lacked.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in this boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>My meaninge is therfore, to moue al partyes to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> necessary care &amp; heed of the matter, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> treatise folowing: trusting that some one or other of my good bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who all be to me most deare, will awake at my earnest call: and consider of the matter deapely, howe it fareth wyth him and other, touchinge theyr soules, since the sacrament of penance hath bene banished and the priesthood of Gods Church spoyled of iuridictiō &amp; right in remission of sins, &amp; to help him in so necessarie &amp; fructeful aduise of him self<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, &amp; other, whō in such cases I meane always to serue, I wil seek out y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> groūd of this authority, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hath bene so longe practised of the priest, &amp; honoured of the
<pb facs="11"/> people, to the singular glory of God, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> notorious encrease of vertue, &amp; weale publik of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole Christian world, that both y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> good catholike may haue reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable prouf of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which to his immortal weal he hath so lōg both loued &amp; reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rēced in Christes ministers, &amp; also y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tēners of so heauēly power may learne in hūblenes of hart to like &amp; feare y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellēt functiō, which by pride they did before vnaduisedly disproue. If it may please any man, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is doubtful of this ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticle, which is so necessari to be knowē, to consider, &amp; giue good attēdance to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole course of my talk, I promise him as afore God (who wil sharpli iudge al sinister endeuours in causes of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I wil deal sincerly in al poynts &amp; faythfully: I wil not couer my selfe nor y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> light of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cause in cloud of words, neither by any artificial sleight (as new doctours now a daies oftē doo) circū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uēt y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sense of him y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is most simple, such indifferēcy shalbe vsed euery where in trial of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> truth, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I wil seme for his sak, to doubt of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> matter my selfe, Though in deede (so God saue me in my commō
<pb facs="12"/> sense, &amp; so god speare me for my sinnes) I can neuer mistrust any poynt of that fayth in which I was newe borne and baptised. But that notwith, standing I wil not spare to rippe vppe that, which men most reproue in Goddes Church and ministers, that all the disobedient children may see, howe free they be frō falshood, &amp; farre frō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> beguiling y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flock of Christe to them cōmited to kepe, we will cal y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> high magistrates (though yt be exceding vnsemely for subiectes to accōpt of their gouernmēt) y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> principall pastour must giue a reason of his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, &amp; awnswer for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> limitatiō of his indulgences by yeares, dayes and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, both he and all other Bishops shalbe accomptable for such graue cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures exercised vpō mens soules, wyth them all inferiours priestes must be posed for searchinge the secretes of our cōsciences, for releassing mās misdedes, ēioyning penance, &amp; requiring satisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō for syns. Thus bold wil we be with trueth, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rather therby to deface falshod.</p>
   <p>And al this in that order, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> may in lest roome conteyne most matter, wyth
<pb facs="12"/> both breuity &amp; light, so much, as so depe &amp; large a cause cā beare, frō al cōtentiō I will so far refrayn, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euē y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries them selues of Christes trueth and doctrine, albeit they be persons infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, by lawe, &amp; consent of all nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ōs, shall not yet without meane &amp; resona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble moderatiō be touched or talked of, requiring of them this curtesie againe, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they reprehend nothing in this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course pryuilie, which they can not, nor dare not awnswer to opēly.<note place="margin">A reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable request.</note> And of my louing brethrē y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> be Catholike I must farder require one thing (the sute is for thē selues) that, when in a maner they sensibly feele y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> truth, they would not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuse to folowe the same: y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> by outeward worke they may declare theire inward wil. Herof I am now more careful, for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I see heresy &amp; falshood to be of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenāce &amp; colour, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it is oftē liked, before yt be beleued: wher gods trueth, for ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rour &amp; bitternes y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it beareth, is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways folowed, wher it is wel knowen &amp; trusted. But surely trueth is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably vnderstanded, til it be willingly practised.</p>
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <p>Therefore who soeuer acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in his cōscience the power of Gods Church &amp; ministery for the remission of sinnes, &amp; vseth not humbly cōfession of his sinnes, that that power may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to his saluatiō, he is so much far<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der from God, by how much more he knoweth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> right way to come to God. Mans wil must in al such cases of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror &amp; difficultie, geue ouer to Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dināce, whose cōmādementes, though they seme to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worldly burdenous, yet to the good &amp; ghostlie,<note place="margin">De do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Cap. 41.</note>
      <hi>&amp; paucis amāti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us</hi> (sayth. S. Augustin) they are sweet and exceding pleasant. And this let euerie mā assuredly know, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> who soeuer cōp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth confession so heauy, he neither fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> weight of sinne, nor yet sufficiēt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feareth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> appoynted payn for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same. Al these vntowardly affections, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sinne and the worlde haue planted in vs all, lette vs seke by loue and zeale of Gods truth and ordinance, to amend: &amp; ioyne with me (gentle Reader) I besech thee in prayers, that our endeuours may please God, &amp; profite his people.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>