<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100227_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14212</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24527</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100227</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A collection of certaine learned discovrses, written by that famovs man of memory Zachary Vrsine; doctor and professor of divinitie in the noble and flourishing schools of Nevstad. For explication of divers difficult points, laide downe by that author in his catechisme. Lately put in print in Latin by the last labour of D. David Parry: and now newlie translated into English, by I.H. for the benefit and behoofe of our Christian country-man</title>
                 <author>Ursinus, Zacharias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Broome (Brome), Joan</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 179, 192-235, 238-341, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous &amp; Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
Reader: at their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
request whom it
most concerned, and
of mine owne inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
which shall (I
professe) bee ever ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile
to thy godly desi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, I did sixe moneths
since begin (and only beginne) to teach this
stranger to speake English (A strāger indeed
for language, but for consent in doctrine our
natural country-man, and fellow-citizen in
the heavenly Hierusalem.) This course vpon
special occasion interrupted, I haue now the
second time attempted and perfited, at the
importunity of my friend this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rinter, whose
commodity had otherwise beene much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiced
by prevention.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>
If I haue truely expressed the Authors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
it is as much as I can desire, or thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect.
Jf I haue failed thereof, I hope it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ordinarily, nor groslie; wherefore being
vnworthy of pardon, much more of praise, I
humbly pleade for thy favourable censure.
Hast is the enemie of circumspection, and
seldome meetes a swift and wise resolution.
Thou wilt (I presume) the rather beare with
me, if thou remember but this, that I was
compelled to make a three weekes worke of
it, in a time when (besides this) I did of dutie
dispatch more businesse, and of necessity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
more griefe and heavinesse, then in so
small a space did ever afore befall me. Some
proofe hereof may be this, that for certaine
howers I was enforced to imploy others,
whose stile (I know) thy quicke re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ish can iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciously
distinguish.</p>
   <p>Touching the Author, all I can say is too
little, and of that little (least thou surfette on
me, eare thou come to him) take only this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.
He was in his life laborious, religious, &amp;
like an Angell amongst men; in his stile
princely, pure, and plentifull like a sweeping
torrent; in his learning (which was of all
sortes, especially in Divinity) sound, subtile,
<pb facs="3"/>
and profound as the deepe <hi>Ocean.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The difficulty and obscurity which must
needs be where is great depth, naturall bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,
and necessitie of schoole-termes should
haue beene plained and cleered (as farre as
my weake vnderstanding could perfourme)
had not the niggardly shortnesse of time, &amp;
envious occurrent of businesse, and disquiet
of minde beene a barre to my honest intent.
Time may minister occasion of supplying
these and all other defectes: In the meane
while for mine encouragement and thine
owne good, accept these first fruites of my
studies in this kinde; and remember to read,
not for contention, but instruction. And so I
leaue thee to God; whom I desire a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> well to
enable thee to the conceaving, as he did this
his servant to the vnfolding of the most deep
mysteries and subtle controversies of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>