<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100232_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21074</idno>
           <idno type="STC">744</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100232</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ariosto's satyres : in seuen famous discourses, shewing the state, 1 Of the Court, and courtiers. 2 Of libertie, and the clergie in generall. 3 Of the Romane clergie. 4 Of marriage. 5 Of soldiers, musitians, and louers. 6 Of schoolmasters and scholers. 7 Of honour, and the happiest life. In English, by Garuis Markham</title>
                 <author>Arisoto, Lodovico</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 108 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, the vertuous, with their owne, hauing alwaies regard to an others good, do painfully bestow houres, daies, and yeares, to make that easie to others, which they with great labour haue obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; in their places, vsing all meanes, to reclaime all persons, from all manner vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to furnish them with such gifts of grace, as make the possessors all iointly happy. From the man of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which hath learning and wisedome, thou mayest bee sure to receiue good instruction. I know my selfe vnable to giue the Author of this booke, his due commendation: if I were, and did, yet should I seeme to some, to flatter, to others not to haue sayd inough: wherefore for thy content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let this suffice thee, the author had his education with the learned, his liuing among the greatest concourse of people, and his life vnreproueable. For his gifts, the world hath already had sufficient experience, in that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous worke of <hi>Orlando Furioso.</hi> Whosoeuer thou art, I dare assure thee, thou mayest in this discourse (as in a glasse) see thy present estate, and so not misse to iudge rightly of thy end. In reading thou shalt finde pleasure, both in the matter and forme; by considerng thou shalt be able to instruct thy selfe and others; but by practising as thou ought, thou shalt find setled happinesse. Let the example
<pb facs="3"/>
of others be thy instruction, to flie that euill which hath bin their ouerthrow, and to embrace that good which was their aduancement. Be thankful first to God, then to the author, and lastly to thy Country-man, who for thy sake, without any other recompence, hath taken the paines in most exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site manner, to be thy interpreter.</p>
   <closer>Vale.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>