<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Wor∣shipfull, Sir William Alexander, Knight, Se∣cretarie, and one of his Maiesties most hone∣rable priuy Coun∣cell in Scot∣land.</title>
           <author>Robinson, Bartholomew</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100444_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10824</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21096</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100444</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Wor∣shipfull, Sir William Alexander, Knight, Se∣cretarie, and one of his Maiesties most hone∣rable priuy Coun∣cell in Scot∣land.</title>
                 <author>Robinson, Bartholomew</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The anatomie of a distressed soule : Wherein, the faults of the elect,are discerned from the sinnes of the wicked, spirituall defections cured, confused consciences resolued, all meanes of presumption and desperation remoued, the sicknesse, dulnesse, and deadnesse of the spirit releeued, crosses and temptations inward, and afflictions outward remedied, for the benefite of all that groane vnder the burthen of sinne, and feeling of Gods anger, thirsting for the sense of reconciliation in the blood of the lambe</title>
                 <author>Robertson, Bartholomew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Speed, Daniel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 280 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="127"/>
   <pb facs="127"/>
   <head>To the Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, Sir <hi>William Alexander,</hi> Knight, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretarie, and one of his <hi>Maiesties most hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable priuy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>En to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues as it were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, they write their names on their houses; <hi>Absolon</hi> reared a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, is not this (said one) <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuie</hi> which I builded for my glory, &amp; <hi>Ninus</hi> to immortalise his father <hi>Belus,</hi> made for him an Idoll, in whose dominions while <hi>Terrah Abrahams</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did dwell, he became with the rest an Idolater, these
<pb facs="128"/>
would haue their fame &amp; time ending together, but they haue shot short, of the seauen won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the world, nothing but naked names remaine: all these are mutilate inuentions, to the <hi>Iew</hi> departed, his brother or nearest kinsman must raise seed to continue his name in <hi>Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,</hi> but children beeing the Lords gift, could not bee had when &amp; as they would: books, with time that eates all, doth often smoother, may successiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by concatenation of ages in the Presse as a new <hi>Phoenix</hi> reuiue, but all these to perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity are set apart as faulty. For as they all, monuments, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and bookes, are of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, so shall with the same al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though neuer so olde bee dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the godly man only and
<pb facs="128"/>
his name doth euer indure, who hath it, and himselfe also writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in heauen, and registered in the booke of life, for all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming oblusion hath no place, your vertues and graces make you liue longer then any of these post-running records: but your goodnes for euer, with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of daies, to whō I heartily pray that after your period shall bee faithfully finished here, you may be partaker of glory: thus I rest euer your Worships,</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>In all Christian duty to be commanded,</salute>
      <signed>Barthol. Robinson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>