<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authors advertisement to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100394_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22928</idno>
           <idno type="STC">94</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100394</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authors advertisement to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The naturall and morall historie of the East and West Indies : Intreating of the remarkeable things of heaven, of the elements, mettalls, plants and beasts which are proper to that country: together with the manners, ceremonies, lawes, governements, and warres of the Indians. Written in Spanish by the R.F. Ioseph Acosta, and translated into English by E.G</title>
                 <author>Acosta, José de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 <distributor>Aspley, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 188, 187-590, 16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Authors advertisement to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ANY have written sundry bookes and discourses of the <hi>New World</hi> at the <hi>West Indies,</hi> wherein they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe new and strange things disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in those partes, with the actes and adventures of the Spaniards, which have conquered and peopled those Countries. But hitherto I have not seene any other Author which treates of the causes and reasons of these novelties and wonders of nature, or that hath made any search thereof. Neither have I read any booke which maketh mention of the histories of the antient Indians, and naturall inhabitants of the <hi>New World.</hi> In truth these two things are difficult; The first being the works of Nature, contrarie to the antient and received Philosophy, as to shew that the region which they call the burning Zone, is very moist, and in many places very temperate, and that it raines there, whenas the Sunne is neerest, with such like things. For such as have written of the West <hi>Indies,</hi> have not made profession of so deepe Philosophie; yea, the greatest part of those Writers have had no knowledge thereof. The second thing it treats of, is, of the proper historie of the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the which required much conference and travaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb facs="3"/>
the Indians themselves: the which most of them that have treated of the <hi>Indies</hi> could not doe, either not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the language, or not curious in the search of their Antiquities: so as they have beene contented to handle those things which have beene most common and superficiall. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring therefore to have some more particular knowledge thereof, I have beene carefull to learne from men of greatest experience and best seene in these matters, and to gather from their discourses and relations, what I have thought sit to give knowledge of the deedes and custome of these people. And for that which concernes the nature of those Countries, and their properties, I have learned it by the experience of many friends, and by my dilligence to search, discover, and conferre with men of iudgement and knowledge. In my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion there are many advertisements, which may serve and benefit better wits for the searching out of the truth, or to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede farther, in finding that pleasing which is conteined heerein. So as although this new <hi>World</hi> be not new, but old, in respect of the much which hath beene written thereof; yet this historie may in some sort be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ld for new; for it is partly historicall, and partly philosophicall, as well for that they are the workes of nature, as of free-will; which are the deedes and customes of men, the which hath caused mee to name it the Naturall and Morall Historie of the <hi>Indies.</hi> Containing these two things: In the first two bookes mention is made of that which concernes the heavens temperature, and habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, which books I had first written in Latine, &amp; now I have translated them into Spanish, vsing more the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of an author, then the strict bonds of a translator, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my self the better to those for whom it is written in the vul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gar tong. In the two following books, is treated of that which concernes the Elements and naturall mixtures, as Mettalls, Plants, Beasts, and what else is remarkable at the <hi>Indies.</hi> The
<pb facs="4"/>
rest of the bookes relate what I could certainely discover, and what I thought worthie memory of the Indians themselves, their Ceremonies, Customs, Governments, Wars, &amp; Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. In the same Historie shall be spoken (as I could learne and comprehend,) of the figures of the antient Indians, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had no writing nor characters as we have, which is no small industry to have preserved their Antiquities, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the vse of letters. To conclude, the scope of this worke is, that having knowledge of the workes of nature, which the wise Author of all nature made, we may praise and glorifie the high God, who is wonderfull in all things and all places. And having knowledge of the Indians customes, we may helpe them more easily to follow and persever in the high vocation of the Gospel; to the knowledge whereof, the Lord would draw this blinde nation in these latter daies. Besides al these things, every one may sucke out some profit for himselfe; for that the wise do alwaies draw forth some good out of the smalest sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, as we finde deepe Philosophie in the least and basest crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. I must onely advertise the Reader, that the two first bookes of this historie or discourse, were written in <hi>Peru,</hi> and the other five, since in <hi>Europe,</hi> dutie binding me to returne into these partes: so as some speake of matters of the <hi>Indies,</hi> as of things present, and others, as being absent. And therefore I have thought it good to advertise the Reader heereof, that this diversitie of speach may not be troublesome vnto him.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Farewell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>