<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100396_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69202</idno>
           <idno type="STC">66</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100396</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Generall demands concerning the late covenant : propounded by the ministers and professors of divinity in Aberdene, to some reverend brethren, who came thither to recommend the late covenant to them, and to those who are committed to their charge. Together with the answers of those reverend brethren to the said demands. As also the replyes of the foresaid ministers and professors to their answers</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>King’s Printer in (for) Scotland.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 37, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T will, no doubt, seeme strange to see my name in print, standing so neare these men who are Interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors in the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding pages, their profession and mine being of such different natures; But I shall entreat the ingenuous rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to take notice of the necessitie of this my doing.</p>
   <p>I am by the three Answerers to these Demands wronged, and that by an injurie of an high nature, chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged in writing to have done that, which God doth know never entred
<pb facs="3"/>
into my thoughts; and for any thing the answerers did or doe know, never came into my minde. And though by the law of challenges, they having challenged me, I may choose the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons (which certainely should have beene in another kinde, had the chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengers beene of another profession) yet being men of so holy a function, I have thought good to make choyce of their own weapons; and by my pen to doe out that blot, which they by their pen have laid upon me. And I have thought it fit to doe it in a scedule an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to this booke (which for that cause only I have caused to be here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed) that where mens mindes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may be poysoned by swallowing an untruth in their answers, so deeply wounding my honour and loyaltie;
<pb facs="3"/>
this antidote might be ready at hand to cure them, before they should be fully tainted with it: As likewise sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing that if they should be printed severally, many might meet with their answers alone, which might leave in them a bad impression of me; if they should not be attended with this just and true expression of mine.</p>
   <p>The injuries wherewith I am viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the three answerers, are of two sorts: One of them strikes me alone, as his sacred MAJESTIES high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioner; The other wounds me as his MAJESTIES Counsellour; and with me all of that honourable boord. The former is this,</p>
   <p>They deliver affirmatively, That the declaration which they tendered mee of their late Covenant, was such as I
<pb facs="4"/>
accepted, and was well pleased with. And this they set down twice for fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; In their answer to the first de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand towards the end, and in their answer to the third demand a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the middle of it; and that with such confidence, as truly I cannot with any justice blame the reader for belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of it, when it fell from the pens of these men, whose profession is the teaching of truth.</p>
   <p>But I shall desire the readers to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themselves (notwithstanding the prejudice of these mens persons) to be undeceived by a plaine averment of truth.</p>
   <p>I am confident none of these three answerers ever heard me say so, nor will they say they did. If they but heard it from others (which I do veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="4"/>
beleeve they did not, and shall do so still, till they avouch their authors) sure no man can choose but misse in them that civill prudence, which will not allow any discreet man to affirme that of any other; much lesse of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of my qualitie, and at this time of my place; the foundation whereof shall be so frail and slipperie, as report, which is alwaies uncertaine, and most times false.</p>
   <p>For clearing the truth, I doe averre upon mine Honour that I never said so, I never thought so. And though that that Declaration was much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the industrie of some well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected (from what was first intended) yet it gave me not satisfaction: and I dare boldly affirme, I never said it would give my Master the KINGS
<pb facs="5"/>
MAJESTY any. My justifiers in this, shall be these Noblemen, Gentlemen, and others to whom I ever spoke, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther publickly, or in private. I was indeed content to catch at any thing I could, when I could not obtaine what I would; as being willing to doe my countrey-men that respect, as to the utmost of my power to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to my gracious Master, with all favourable construction, even that which I then thought, and did know fell short of just and home satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <note n="†" place="margin">Nor is there any ground for their opinion of my accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse they call receiving, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting; and that was not in my power to refuse, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conceived in formall words of a supplication, and so tendered to me, who by my royall Master his instructions was commanded to receive the petitions of all his good and loyall subjects.</note> And here, I doe confesse, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not charge it for a faultie mistake up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the readers of these asseverations of the three answerers, if they should, before this my declaration, conceive that his MAJESTIE were in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilitie
<pb facs="5"/>
like to rest satisfied with that declaration of the Covenant; having it delivered to them from men whom they have in all this businesse beleeved as much as themselves, that his MAJESTIES Commissioner, who in all likelihood did know his MAJESTIES minde best, did rest satisfied with it.</p>
   <p>But his MAJESTY hath just reason to charge me, if these asseverations were true; as I have good reason to vindicate my selfe, they being not true. The truth is, if these asseverations be true, I doe professe to the whole world, that his MAJESTY hath a most just cause to discharge himselfe of mee, and my service, and to discharge mee of all trust in this, or any other nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation For I professe, that I know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his MAJESTIES constant mislike of
<pb facs="6"/>
the said Covenant, it must bewray in me, either breach of trust, or want of judgement; if I should goe about to make either my self, or the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that my Master could receive satisfaction by such an explanation.</p>
   <p>And here I cannot dissemble, but must ask leave to vent my self thus far. Had these wrongs beene put upon me by the pens of other men, and not of these whose professions I am forward and willing to beleeve (because I would have it so) will not suffer them to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace wilfull and malicious designes: I should justly have doubted, that there had been some men in this kingdome, who being afraid of a setling and peaceable conclusion of this businesse, had gone about to raise in my royall and gracious Master a jelousie of my
<pb facs="6"/>
slacknesse in my King and Countries service, that so I might be called back, <hi>re infecta.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If any such enemies there be to the peace of this miserable distracted Church and State, I beseech God in time to discover them, and that all may end, in covering them with shame and confusion. The summe of all I will say of this personall wrong offered to my self, is this; If these reverend and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gentlemen, the Answerers, in these untrue aspersions intended any harme to me, I shall only now requite them with a cast of their own calling; I pray God forgive them. If they intended me no harm, then I do expect that they will give my self and the world satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in clearing me that I gave them no ground for these their asseverati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb facs="7"/>
And so being confident of his MAJESTIES goodnesse to all his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters; amongst the rest, to the meanest of them, my self, especially in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, that he will never be shaken in the opinion of my loyall and constant service, upon such slight, light, and groundlesse reports: I will say no more of that first point.</p>
   <p>For that which concerneth my selfe as a Counsellour, and the rest of that honourable Boord, averred by the three answerers, in their answers to the third and fourteenth demand; I do here protest before Almighty God, that none of the allegations alledged by the three answerers, nor any petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on given me by the supplicants, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me to give way, that the order of the Councell table should not passe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="7"/>
an act: for I did then, and doe now avow, that I then was, and now am ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly satisfied with his MAJESTIES most gracious declaration; and that in my opinion all ought to have thought themselves sufficiently freed from fears of innovations. But the true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son was this, I was so tenderly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned towards the peace of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that I gave way to that, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of honourable qualitie assured me, if it were not done, a present rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture might follow, and so consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ruine of this Kingdome; which I was resolved to keep off so long as possibly I could, retaining my fidelitie to my Master. VVhich care of mine I finde but slenderly required, when it is made an argument to perswade his MAJESTIES good subjects to do that
<pb facs="8"/>
which is so displeasing to him, and so unsafe for them. And yet even in this passage, it would have beene expected from men of that profession, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing should have passed but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth. In which point too they have failed, either as I hope by a mistaking, or a mis-informing. For the Missive once thought fit to be sent to his MAJESTY was never rent, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth yet as it was: and wee did not send it, because wee did not thinke, thanks to his MAJESTY would be sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable in the name of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, when we knew his MAJESTIE, by the last proceedings of many, and protestations made against his royall declaration (pretended in the name of the whole country) could not receive satisfaction.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>To conclude, notwithstanding this personall wrong offered to me his MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTIES high Commissioner, I will carefully; cheerfully, and constantly go on with this great businesse, wherewith he hath intrusted me. VVhich as I pray God that it may prosper under my hands; so I praise God that he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me so cheerfull and willing a heart to go on in it; that if my life could procure the peace of this torn Church and Kingdome, to the contentment of my royall Master, and comfort of his distracted subjects; he who knoweth all things, knoweth likewise this truth; It is the sacrifice of the world, in which I would most glorie, and which I would most sincerely offer up to God, my King and Countrey.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>HAMMILTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>