<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Matter.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100623_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11769</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22063</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100623</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Matter.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The philosophers banquet : Newly furnished and decked forth with much variety of many severall dishes, that in the former service were neglected. Where now not only meats and drinks of all natures and kinds are serued in, but the natures and kinds of all disputed of. As further, dilated by table-conference, alteration and changes of states, diminution of the stature of man, barrennesse of the earth, with the effects and causes thereof, phisically and philosophically. Newly corrected and inlarged, to almost as much more. By W.B. Esquire</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Vavasour, Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 364, that is 362 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Culinary arts</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>The Preface to the <hi>Matter.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>THat <hi>Health is abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> Gold, and a sound bodie above infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Riches; is a</hi> Text of Truth, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved with most joyfull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, to their comforts that entirely possesse it, and know the worth by the use, not by the want: as doe those poore and life-weari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>d wretches, whose pleasures by sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses perplext, and dayes spunn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> out in griefe and misery by the contrary; yet what is this precious stone to the Dunghill-cocke, or the richest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ifts of <hi>bodie</hi> or <hi>mind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> fortune,</hi> to him
<pb facs="14"/>
that is not <hi>Gemmarius;</hi> one that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderstandeth their value, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lueth them according to his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing: The <hi>Crab,</hi> the <hi>Gangrene,</hi> or the <hi>Stone,</hi> that put the knife to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scition, or the sawe to abscition, and Traytor-like, racke the body with tortures, not inferiour to death: cry out in him that is patient of this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery: Happy man that art borne from these woes, that art free from these maladies. Cherish therfore that good which is so precious in life (thou that enjoyest it) which keepes off death, and sweetens all the affictions that oppose us in life, and abuse it not in Riots, in surf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ts and disorders, things so apt to deprive it; the losse being so great, and the pleasures so small, and without which, all humane so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace is but sorrow; all rejoycing is but mourning, and life it selfe is but death. For to him that hath the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est titles, the largest honours, the fairest reuenues, nay, all the pleasures that the earth and Sea to boot can affoord; yet what are all these pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ne is wanting?
<pb facs="14"/>
Therefore to the preservation of that which is, and redeeming of that which hath beene, but is not, our <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers</hi> propose certaine Rules and directions, for the ordering, reducing, and maintaining of mans body in health; which like a Clocke, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the many severall particles and connexions thereunto belonging is ever subject to diversion and error. For as <hi>Galen,</hi> the Light of Physicians writeth, of that little window, or light of <hi>Man,</hi> the delicacie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, not the least creature, or attomic in the world, but by accident, may sore offend, yet that there are subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory and pertinent peremptory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities besides thereunto belonging ingendred, by <hi>Rheumes, Convulsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and other operations of the brain, and strings thereunto officiall, 52. diseases: If then so many disastrous Planets reigne over one little mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, had it not need of sight and light to prevent them? And if to this one, so many to the whole body of man, how many are incident, and what cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riosity therefore is to be given to our
<pb facs="15"/>
steps, when without their limits they are so many enemies of Nature, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to seize upon us? And which dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and direction being observed we may lengthen out our dayes with joy and delight to the last period of their prefixment, when either sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse or casualty, one Accident or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall fall upon us, to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment of that Sentence which was never yet frustrated by any, nor ever shall, whilest the foure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> indes blow one against another. For against that, here is no prevention, <hi>(Contra vim mortis, non esc medicam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> in her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis)</hi> although some, and no meane Clarks, have thought and written to the contrary, that Age might be kept backe, and sicknesse kept by, which if it may be for a time, wee conclude, it cannot be for ever.</p>
   <p>That Age may not be kept backe, though sometimes tardied in his speed.</p>
   <p>FRyer <hi>Bacon,</hi> a man of infinit lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, study, capabilitie and Art
<pb facs="15"/>
in his time, amongst many other his strange and impossible endevours, published a booke <hi>De retardanda Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necture;</hi> or the keeping backe of old age, the which whilst he himselfe in observing and prescribing the Rules, Orders, Observations, and Retarda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation thereof, grew old in the act, and himselfe was overtaken with age: Let the ayre in her wholsom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mest kinde, with the most nicest ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies that <hi>Physicke</hi> or curiosity observed, Fennes and Marishes, and the low and unwholsome vapors of the earth unsuckt up thereby, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>savory breath whereof may breathe contagion into windowes: In stead thereof, brush over Rockes and Hils, and Fields and Fountaines, with the wholsommest perfumes that the best matters may give it to worke upon, bring health through the Crannies, and receptacles of our houses, and breathe it in at the nostrils of the most healthfull creature living; let him rise early, not walke late, be tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in Dyet, moderate in exercise, wary in lust, cheerefull of disposition,
<pb facs="16"/>
sit not much, walke not sildome, sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet never, know the disposition and state of his owne body, from the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest content, to the least particular: be a Physician himselfe, on himselfe; use the art and direction of all the world, and all the Colledges and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians therein: yet notwithstanding shall age creepe upon him, and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den him with her weight, and the unnecessary luggage of her carriage, which is strength in peevishnesse, weaknesse in performances, will to desire, yet want to execute, as help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly is daily experienced. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, who would weare his head white, and his beard gray, his eyes hollow, and his eares deafe, blacke veines, and dry braines, a dropping nose, a wrinckled brow, shaking hands, and toothlesse gummes, feeble legs, and shrunke sinewes, that might ransome himselfe, either by paine or price. The old Courtier, inamored of his young mistris, sleighted more for his want, then his will, having some sparkes of heat, not yet extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished by antiquity, would offer (if
<pb facs="16"/>
it might be) more then the portion of his supple hammes, to enjoy the one, but to obtaine the other: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the face once adorned with beauty, and more adored th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n the <hi>Indian</hi> sunne, now crept into wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, and folded up in the pleats of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, and more ecclipsed then the Sunne (for this I say) what paine or price so heavy, that these creatures of lightnesse would not undertake, but that this ceaselesse lackey to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, trouped with Kings to his pages, never turnes backe to make amends in his regresse, for any injury hee effects in his progresse; which makes one complaine in a Sonnet to this effect as followeth.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>Could age like dayes as nights ensue,</l>
      <l>Each morning sresh her selfe renue:</l>
      <l>What Lady then at nights decay,</l>
      <l>But would i'th morne begin her day?</l>
      <l>For where's a face so much declinde,</l>
      <l>That beares not youthfull thoughts in minde?</l>
      <l>That often peepe with oylie eyes,</l>
      <l>Through doctor'd strange adulteries,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="17"/>
Vpon the world in silke and Gold,</l>
      <l>That grieve to thinke they are so old:</l>
      <l>The Matrons in their rip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>st age,</l>
      <l>That should have wisdome as their Page,</l>
      <l>So much inclin'd to this Devotion,</l>
      <l>That to obtain't would give an Otian;</l>
      <l>Old age, bad cloat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>es, such griefe imparts,</l>
      <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>y break or wound al womens harts</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Therefore the Phylosophers, not to perswade impossibilities, would have no man thinke but they must be old; but would have no man old be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee be wise, yet somewhat to runne with the current of humour, have here added certaine linkes or lengthenings to these <hi>Summa Desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deria,</hi> and as much as may be done by art, or precept, laboured to keepe backe these aged wrinkles, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive our beauty and strength, and nip the flower of all worldly delight, and therefore doe here at their Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, disccurse of <hi>Seriacum jocis,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules of wisedome, which saith, Mingle thy cares with
<pb facs="17"/>
joyes, and thy sorrowes with delight: crowne the morsels of thy labour with the height of thy contentment, and reserve some times for thy va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancie and freedome: For the bowe that is alwayes bent, must needs be weakened, and unapt for use. And where sorrow, griefe, and vexation, which sucke veines dry, and rowle up the countenance in wrinkles like a scrowle of scorched parchment, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lye tugging, what can be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted but the wast ruine, and deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the whole body? and therefore at thy Table, in thy Chamber, in thy places of rest and retirement, lay thy cares and affaires, and worldly thoughts aside, till time of conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent deliberation or prosecution re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them. For as saith <hi>Macrobius,</hi> Moderate mirth at our tables, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the body, enlightneth the mind, and causeth a good digestion in the stomacke, delighteth our selves and our company, and increaseth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: and with his opinion likewise, it seemes altogether convenient and fitting, that our discourse at the table
<pb facs="18"/>
should either concerne the natures of those meats and drinkes wee furnish our tables with; or the natures and conditions of those that accompany us at our Tables, or ingenious positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and questions, to exercise our wits at our Tables, or of such pleasant conceits and jests as doe exhillerate our company, and cause mirth at our Tables.</p>
   <p>And therefore I have determined to call this present worke, <hi>The Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers Banquet;</hi> dividing it into foure equall parts or Bookes, as the nature of the foure subjects wee chiefly handle, conveniently require.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>