<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>St, M.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100969_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68781</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23228</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100969</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>St, M.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nevves out of York-shire: or, an account of a iovrney, in the true discovery of a soueraigne minerall, medicinall water, in the West-Riding of Yorke-shire, neere an ancient towne called Knaresbrough, not inferiour to the spa in Germany : Also a taste of other minerall water of seuerall natures adioyning. By M.S</title>
                 <author>Stanhope, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Gibbs, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T what time this relation of our English <hi>Spa</hi> was (though cursorily) composed, the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Newes out of Yorke-shire</hi> (which like a Signe I fixed at the Portall of the discourse) was not improper. That many Moneths are past, since it was capable of the Character of the Presse, and ready drest to encounter the publike view, it shall suffice there are diuers can witnesse, with the casualty of its protraction. There are (I confesse) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by-circumstances enterlaced, which though they aime at lapsed time, yet are they not altogether misap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliable to the present. In substance I differ not much from the <hi>Spadacrene</hi> lately published by a graue Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, the garbe onely of my particularising I challenge as mine. As for such pedanticke Formalists, who hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may tax mee for digressing from the proposed sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,
<pb facs="5"/> let such know I hold it the greatest slauery in the world to be tied to their vnnecessary rules. But for thee (gentle Reader) be but pleased to obserue the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of the liberty I take, and then I hope (the dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the times considered, which had need of a lash to be rowzed) thou wilt not think I roaue very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently. Yet before I leaue thee, I must craue thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience (as one tendering the common good) whilest I offer to thy consideration some cautions in the vse of these Waters, which (if I mistake not) are of such re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all consequence, that neglected, their expected effects are made frustrate.</p>
   <p>That the worth and excellency of Physicall helpes consisteth not in the remedies themselues (as one well obserueth) but in their wise and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent dispensation, is so vndoubted a position, as none but such as scorne the clew of reason should guide their vnderstanding in the Labyrinth of so many vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties as are abroach in the world, will deny. And hence it is, that Medicines iudiciously dispensed, are said to be as Angels of God sent for the good of men; but inconsiderately vsed, they are Messengers of death. Yet such is the giddy precipitation of many, especially the meaner sort of people, that they no sooner heare of a secret, (be it a medicinall Water, or what else that promiseth health) but (all fit circumstances set apart)
<pb facs="5"/> they violently rush vpon it, perswading themselues (out of a passionate desire to be refreshed) a sudden laying hold vpon any nouelty, to be the most aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious course. Nay, how many are there who vpon notice of a new-found medicinall Spring like this of ours, question not the infallibility of its curing all manner of diseases? the sottishnesse of which fancy is so grosse, that I will not doe it the grace of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position.</p>
   <p>Nor are the vulgar onely bleared with this misty conceit, for I haue heard of our Empericall hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists (who take a pride (as one saith) to Monopolize cures vnto the prerogatiue of one Secret) who haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouched it as a thing feasable, to compose a medicine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to cure any disturbance incident to Nature. But I leaue these with their quaint cratchets to themselues, and worse company I know not how to wish them; and come to the obseruances I desire may duely be conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of such as intend the vse of this our Water. And first I wish, that whosoeuer the parties be, before they attempt the vse of the water, they repaire to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Physitian, especially such as haue been conuersant in the vse and quality of the water, and make knowne to him their distemper, that so consideration may be had of the aptnesse of the waters faculty, how it stands
<pb facs="6"/> qualified to the affected part, which is of such condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing sequele, that the omitting hereof hath proued fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall to many. For who but the Physitian (whose pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession it is) is fit to iudge of the multitude of causes in diseases, what varying differences arise in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, quality, quantity, and times of remedies? wherein the party either ignorant, or mistaken, medicines of sauing and curing power, out of time and place dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, bring forth mischiefe, and many inconueniences instead of helpe.</p>
   <p>It being granted then in the first place that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is of probable vse, in the next succeeds a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of body, according to the nature, quality, and seate (as I may say) of each humor, which obseruance how much it auaileth, let the common experience of those, who submit themselues to aduise, testifie in the difference of the effects found from irregulars. For the manner of vsing the Water, there is no question but a sudden glutting of the stomake, with a surcharge of any thing, wherewith Nature is not acquainted, is a most preposterous course; yet that this is ordinary also (especially amongst the vulgar) who knowes not, that hath obserued the pressing of people to these like waters? Soft fire (saith the old prouerbe) makes sweet Malt, and a gentle acquainting of Nature by degrees
<pb facs="6"/> with any thing makes it more gratefull, and steales as it were a kinde of familiarity with Nature. The time of the yeare by the obseruance of the learned as most proper, is thought to be <hi>Iune, Iuly,</hi> and <hi>August,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, the morning best allowed for the circumstance of the day. Ordinary repasts, and the liberty at other times taken of eating and drinking, would now be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, for three or foure houres space after the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the water, that so Nature may finish her taske with more ease, hauing the water onely for a subiect to grapple withall.</p>
   <p>A temperate diet by abstaining from meates of grosse and melancholicke substance, must take place as a rule amongst the rest worthy of remembrance, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto as a fit companion moderate exercise would be ioyned. Nor let such thinke (whose bodies especially are the seats of radicated ancient diseases) to finde ease suddenly by the vse of these watters; such must come armed with a well-grounded patience, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect by degrees a lessening of their maladies, who though haply they haue staied the ordinary prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed time of the waters vse, and yet are not sensible of any great change, yet let them not despaire, for that a second yeres, triall may bring forth an happy issue of their desires, whereunto this had onely the power to
<pb facs="7"/> make the way. And (which is strange) it hath beene obserued, that some who haue by graue aduise beene induced to drinke of these waters, and haue not in any fit circumstance digressed from the Physitians rule, though during the time of their abode at the place, they haue not perceiued any apparant amendment, yet after their departure haue beene restored to perfect health. The reason hereof the learned giue to be, that (after the drinking of the Water) there remaineth in the more sollide parts of the body (by which the water did passe) the hidden faculties and powers thereof, which commonly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the effects within the space of <hi>40.</hi> dayes. This hath beene obserued as a thing of frequent experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
   <p>I had not embarked my selfe into these cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onarie aduertisements at all, (knowing they are more punctually set downe by others, especially in the late <hi>Spadacrene</hi>) but that at my being this Summer at our new <hi>Spa,</hi> I did obserue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers to take a most preposterous course in drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Water. Some came thither, rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting a Miracle than a cure; hauing beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperately diseased for many yeares, and yet concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued hope of a perfect recouerie by two or three
<pb facs="7"/> dayes stay. Others at the first approach to the water sticke not to drinke (besides the omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of preparation) as large a quantity as would require (by due order) the rising to of ten or twelue daies, and it may be within an houre forbeare not to please the pallate with any ordinary refection. Hence (omitting a world of other errours) comes these waters (which in themselues methodically vsed are of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent effects) to be so much disparaged, their worth traduced, and their admirall operations obscured by the brutish precipitation of most that haue recourse to them; whereof if others warned will not take heed, let the failing of their desire in the cure, nay perhaps the disease made more desperate, or extraordinary symptomes hapning, be the iust reward and guerdon of their wilfull vnaduisednesse.</p>
   <p>I am loth to leaue thee before (for thy encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement) I adde an experiment or two which (amongst others) this Summer <hi>1626.</hi> brought forth at this our new <hi>Spa.</hi> A man about the age of <hi>50.</hi> yeres (being of an extraordinary bulke of body, but especially his belly of an vnseene great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse) who partly by the surcharge of that great
<pb facs="8"/> masse of flesh he carried, and partly through a stoppage of the passages of respiration, could not of twenty yeares before goe many paces without a pause, and the benefit of a seate, hauing drunke of this Water orderly about a fortnight, his belly did fall to a competent size, and hee was able to goe from the Towne of <hi>Knaresbrough</hi> to the fountain (which is little lesse than two miles) and most of it vp the hill) without any desire of rest, or easing. I also saw a Youth, and spake with him, about the age of twentie yeares who for the space of three yeares before had been miserably afflicted with a kinde of Epilepsie, yet differing from the ordinary manner of that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease, in some strange and violent distortions which for the most part affected his right side. It was ordinary for him to fall three or foure times in a day, in which fits he lay groueling vpon the ground, a miserable spectacle. This poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had continued the vse of the water not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue ten dayes, during which time hee had but two fits, and those exceedingly moderated. A strange alteration, and not easily admitting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, and shewes that this Water is of an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble composure, and transcendent faculties, and
<pb facs="8"/> worthy the curious indagation of the learned. I hold my selfe much to blame, that I did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire their names, and abode, for the more full satisfaction of those who are of nice beleefe. It remaines, that of what is past, and doth follow, if thy obseruance procure thee any benefit, that thou blesse the Fountaine of all fountains, from whom all Creatures deriue both being, and whatsoeuer is in them of worth and efficacy.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>M. St.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>