<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRI∣STIAN READER, encrease of all good gifts.</title>
           <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100366_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09024</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19312</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100366</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRI∣STIAN READER, encrease of all good gifts.</title>
                 <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Abba father: or, a plaine and short direction concerning priuate prayer : Also, sundry godly admonitions concerning time, and the well vsing of it. By Elnathan Parr, minister of the word</title>
                 <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Samuel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 132 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN READER, encrease of all good gifts.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O condemne a set forme of prayer, argues want of sobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and wisdome. In pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prayers in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation it is necessary to haue a prescribed forme called Liturgy, or Diuine Seruice, which for more ease of memory is to be read out of the booke. The anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entest Fathers (in the peace
<pb facs="5"/>of the Church) haue by their practice so iudged it: many Councels haue appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it, and the best refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches follow it.</p>
   <p>As for priuate prayer of one Christian alone, it is more expedient that it bee vttered without a booke; and the most compleat per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that duty is, when a Christian is able not onely to repeate and apply to his owne soule and conscience a prayer concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by another, but also vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fit matter, and heads suteable to the occasion, to conceiue and vtter prayers of his own. Yet seeing there are many to whom God
<pb facs="5"/>hath not giuen memory and vnderstanding fitting, to expresse in a continued speech the desires of their hearts; for such haue I written this direction.</p>
   <p>The reason why I haue vndertaken this businesse, considering there are so many good Prayer-bookes in euery mans hand, is, first, because, though it bee cōmendable to vse a booke, yet it is more comfortable to pray of our selues, whose wants may be such, as that we shall hardly finde them sufficiently expressed in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny booke: for euery man is best acquainted with his owne heart.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Secondly, a man may be cast into prison, and his booke taken from him: how vncomfortably must he needs passe his time, if he cannot pray without his booke. The booke cannot be vsed in the darke, when we may haue iust occasion to pray. The booke may bee forgotten, or lost: but if thou attainest this gift, thou canst neuer loose it, vnlesse thou loosest thy selfe.</p>
   <p>For these reasons I commend this Treatise to thee, which I could haue amplified further, and it may be, clothed it with a more elegant stile. But I
<pb facs="6"/>aimed at thy profit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that I directed beginners, for whom short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and plainnesse are most fitting.</p>
   <p>If thou profitest by this which I heere propound to thee; praise God: and in thy prayers forget not him, who hath at least en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoured to further thee. If thou profitest not; yet I haue done my good will, for the which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire thee to loue</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy true friend in Iesus Christ, <hi>Eln. Parr.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>