<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100110_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16828</idno>
           <idno type="STC">373</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100110</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true sincere and modest defence of English Catholiques that suffer for their faith both at home and abrode : against a false, seditious and slaunderous libel intituled; The execution of iustice in England. VVherein is declared, hovv vniustlie the Protestants doe charge Catholiques vvith treason</title>
                 <author>Allen, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fr. Parsons’ Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 219, 5 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBEIT the late pamphlet, intituled <hi>The execution of Iustice,</hi> put forth in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers languages, for defence or excuse of the violent proceeding against Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques in England, and for accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as wel of them at home as of vs their felowes in faith abrode, passing forth without priuilege and name ether of writer or printer (euen thence where such matter is speciallie cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and might easilie haue bene authorized): &amp; mouing indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, odious, and dangerous disputes of estate, replenished with manifest vntruthes, open slaunders of innocent persons, and namelie with immodest malediction and seditious motions against the cheefe Bishop, the Prince of Gods people; though (I say) it might rightlie haue bene reputed an infamous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, ether to be contemned, or with such freedome of speech refelled, as that maner of writing doth deserue: yet conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the matter, meaning, and phrase therof to be agreable to the humour and liking of some in authoritie;<note place="margin">The causes of ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvere.</note> and the booke not onelie not suppressed (as diuers others of that argument seeming ouer simple to the wiser Protestants, of late haue bene) but often printed, much recommended, diligentlie diuul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and sought to be priuileged in<note n="*" place="margin">In Frāce.</note> forreine places, where for shame they durst not publiquelie allowe it at home: yea, and in a maner thrust into the handes of strangers, and therfore like to proceed (though in close sort) from authoritie: we are forced, and in truth verie wel contented and glad it hath pleased God to giue this occasion, or rather necessitie, to yeeld (for the answere of the said booke) our more particular accompt, in the behalf of our Catholique brethren dead and aliue, at home and in banishment.</p>
   <p>Which we wil doe sincerlie as in the sight of <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> the iust iudge of the world, and al his <hi>Saints:</hi> in such humble, milde, and temperate maner, as beseemeth our profession, and
<pb facs="3"/> the audience: which audience we craue with teares of the whole Church and Christian world, and of al that are placed in power and sublimitie ouer vs in our owne Countrie or els where: that so our cause may be discerned both by God and man; and our vnspeakable calamities, ether by the intercession of manie, releeued; or by the general compassion of al our faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful brethrē, made to vs more tollerable. Loth we are, and odious it may be compted to speake in such matter as must needes in some sort touch our superiours: but Gods truth and mans inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cēcie are priuileged, and may in humble seemelie wise be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, against whomsoeuer. And our pen (God willing) shalbe so tempered herein, that it shal displease no reasonable reader, nor surelie skarce them (if it may be) against whom in our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culpable defence we are forced to write.</p>
   <p>We haue in this case examples inough of Christian modestie in the ancient apologies of holie Fathers in Christ his Church; as of S. <hi>Iustin,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Examples of vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie.</note>
      <hi>Tertulian, Athanasius, Hylarius</hi> and other, writing to their Princes, that persecuted ether by errour or infidelitie, the faithful people. Whos stile and steppes so long as we folowe, we shalbe blameles in the sight of al wise and good men; and offēd none, to whom the plaine truth it self is not odious. As on the other side, we haue in our aduersaries late bookes, for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modest railing,<note place="margin">The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants stile.</note> contemptuous phrase, slaunderous speach, blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous wordes, false, reprochful, seditious matter, and al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honest scurrilitie, what to abhorre and detest, and what to auoide in thes our writings; which we would haue most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like theirs, and not onelie allowable to our frendes, but (if it were possible, and so pleased our merciful Lord to giue vs grace in their sight) not ingrateful to our persecutours: whos salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as Christ knoweth) we seeke in al thes our endeuours, together with the maintenance of truth, more then our owne defence and purgation.</p>
   <p>Wherupon otherwise, for our owne onelie honour and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, we would not so formallie stand, against so honorable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries in this world; if we thought ether their hartes (which are in Gods handes) were not vpon euident reason and remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance of our innocencie, inclinable to mercie and better consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of their owne state and ours: or that their accusation of vs afflicted Catholiques, were not ioined to the general repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension of the whole Church and the principal pastours therof; whom by the lawe of our Christian religion we ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect more then our owne liues; and in causes of our soule and conscience, to obey aboue anie earthlie Prince, by what other obligation so euer we be bound vnto him.</p>
   <p>And as we would gladlie passe in this our answere, with such
<pb facs="3"/> equabilitie and indifferencie, that in defence of the spiritual power (which by our aduersaries importunitie, we are driuen in maner against our wils to treat of) we might not iustlie offend the temporal, acknowledging in diuers respects al hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dutie to them both: so writing nothing that anie man shalbe able to proue vntrue ether in fact or faith; we trust in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders equitie, be he Catholique or Protestant, that in so fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and necessarie a defence of our selues, and of our Superiours, as also of the common cause of our Christian faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, he wil not iudge our writing seditious, slaunderous or infamous libelling (as the nameles author of this inuectiue, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whom we treat, vnchristianlie and vncourteouslie calleth other our brethrens bookes) recording onelie the heauie perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, torments and deathes of Catholiques, in such sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, plaine and sincere sort, as indeed al thinges were done:<note place="margin">The bookes of English persecution most true.</note> and so as no man liuing can trulie ether charge the reporters of fiction or falshood, or of anie euil intention of diffaming to strangers their superiours dealings, in making relation of our deare Countries most doleful calamities. For the thinges there done dailie in publique, cannot otherwise be hidden from the world: and seing they are passed by lawe and order of pretended iustice, ther can be no cause why them selues should mislike the diuulging therof; except they acknowledge in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science some iniquitie, and dishonorable defect in their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, against the most innocent persons whom daily they tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and make away.</p>
   <p>We are not so peruerslie affected (God be praised) as pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poselie to dishonour our Prince and Countrie,<note place="margin">The true causes of publishing our mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> for whos loue in Christ, so manie haue so meeklie lost their liues: or to reueale their turpitude, which we would rather couer (if it were possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) from the eyes of the world with our owne blood: but we set forth the truth of al thes actions, for the honour of our nation, which otherwise to her infinite shame and reproche, would be thought wholie and generallie to haue reuolted from the Catholique faith, and consented to al the absurdities and iniquities of this new regiment and religion, if none with zeale and extreme indeuour resisted such pernitious innouations. Wher now as wel our owne people, as al strangers in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian world, perceauing the disorder to proceed but of the partialitie of a few powerable persons abusing her Maiesties clemencie and credulitie; doe glorifie our Lord God, that in so great a tentation, al the Cleargie in maner, and so manie of the laitie of al sortes constantlie persist in their fathers faith, to the losse of goods, landes, liues, honours, and what soeuer besi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: and that the whole state (excepting the authoritie of the
<pb facs="4"/> Prince) may yet be rather counted Catholique, then heretical: this is the honour of our nation in al places, which otherwise (for dooble reuolt and recidiuatiō into Schisme, and for extreme persecution) would be compted remediles, hopeles, and of al other places most infamous.</p>
   <p>Secondlie; we set forth thes thinges for the memorie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of such notable Martirs, as haue testified the truth of the Catholique faith by their pretious death.<note place="margin">See S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian.</note> Which was an ancient <hi>Canon</hi> and custome of the primitiue Church, which appointed certaine special persons or skil and learning, to note the daies of euerie ones glorious confession and combat, that their memories might afterward be solemlie celebrated for euer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Christians.</p>
   <p>Thirdlie; we doe it to communicate our calamities with our brethren in faith, and the Churches of other prouinces stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding free from this miserie, both for their warning, and our comfort, and to excite in them Christian compassion towardes vs; that therbie and by their councel and praiers, we may find mercie and releef at Gods hand: by the example of the Oriental Churches afflicted by the <hi>Arrians,</hi>
      <note place="margin">See S. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sile. Epist. 69. &amp; 70.</note> which as we may read in <hi>S. Basile,</hi> in their like distresses, made their general complaints by often letters and messingers, to the west Churches, standing more entire and void of that Heresie and persecution.</p>
   <p>Finallie; we are forced to publish thes thinges so particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlie and diligentlie, to defend the doings of the said holie Confessors and their felowes in faith, against the manifold slaunders and calumniations of certaine Heretiques or Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, vniustlie charging them with treason, and other great trespasses against the Common-wealth, to auert the eyes of the simple from the true causes of their suffering; and to disapoint the holie personages (if they could) of the honour done to Martirs in Gods Church. For, that is one special cause among manie, why they had rather make them away for forged treason, or other feigned offences, then for profession of the truth; which in their hart they hate more then anie crime in the world. <hi>S. Gregorie Nazianzene</hi> liuelie expresseth the condition of al Heretiques, in the behauiour of <hi>Iulianus the Apostata,</hi> thus writing of him:<note place="margin">Oratione in laudē Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saris.</note>
      <hi>He openlie and boldlie professing impietie, yet by coulor of clemencie couered his crueltie; and lest vve should atteine to the honours done customablie to Martirs (vvhich he disdeined to the Christians) he vsed namelie this fraude and deceipt, that such as he caused to be tormented for Christs cause, should be thought and reported to be punished not for their faith, but as malefactours.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For discouerie therfore of this sinful and deceiptful dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="4"/> of our aduersaries (who not contented with the death and torments of Gods Saints, would punish them by ignominie after their life) we are driuen to this dutiful office of their and the holie Churches defence; whos honour and innocencie we may not bewray for a thousand deathes.</p>
   <p>Wherin we are not much terrified by the vaine and vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar exordium of the Author of this inuectiue which we now must refute:<note place="margin">The Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellers vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium.</note> who beginneth aboue al arte (after their maner) with a common sentence, as meet for vs and our matter, as for him and his cause: telling vs, that it is a common vsage of al offendours, and speciallie rebels and traitors, to make defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of their lend and vnlauful factes, by couering their deedes with pretence of other causes. Which speech, as it might be vsed where anie such trespasse could be proued; so is it fondlie said where no crime can be auouched: as in the processe of this treatise, shalbe (by Gods grace) most clearlie conuinced. And it might not onelie be applied by the olde heathen or heretical persecutors, against the first <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>Martirs</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> being falslie charged with the same crimes as we be now, and answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for them selues, as we doe: but may much more be verified and found in publique persons and common-wealthes, when they erre or commit iniquitie, then in anie poore, priuate,<note place="margin">States Princes and common-vvealthes haue more pretēces for couering their mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes thē priuate mē.</note> or afflicted persons, be they neuer so guiltie. For Princes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities in disorder haue a thousand pretences, excuses, and coulors, of their iniust actions: they haue the name of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, the shadowe of lawes, the pennes and tongues of infinite at their commaundement: they may print or publish what they like, suppresse what they list: wherof priuate men, be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so wicked or good, haue not so great commoditie.</p>
   <p>For examples we need not to goe farre out of our owne Countrie and memorie. For, when <hi>Richard</hi> the third, intending to vsurpe the Croune of <hi>England,</hi> slew diuers of the Nobilitie first most cruelly,<note place="margin">Richard Duke of Glocester.</note> and afterward murthered vnnaturallie his owne innocent nephewes: what solemne Libels, proclamations, orations, were put foorth to iustifie his abhominable iniquitie? When the last Duke of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> for the like ambitious purpose, would haue dishabled and defeated traiterouslie,<note place="margin">Iohn Dud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Duke of Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland.</note> both the noble daughters of his owne Soueraigne and Maister; and by the title of his daughter in lawe, possessed him self of the Croune: what a number of pamphlets and edicts were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished on the sodaine, for couloring of that foule treacherie and intollerable treason? When <hi>Orange</hi>
      <note place="margin">Orange.</note> and his confederats re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolted not long since, from their natural Prince; the Scottish Heretiques from their lauful Soueraine,<note place="margin">Iamy, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, &amp;c.</note> and other Prouinces for the same cause, from the vnitie and common faith of the
<pb facs="5"/> Church; who hath not seene the infinite Libels for their excuse in wickednes? That therfore, that may sometimes fal in priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te mens causes for couering their sinne and shame, happeneth farre oftener and much more dangerouslie in powerable and publique persons. And so it maketh no more against vs, then this writer him self, whether he hath published his Libel by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie (as he wil not seeme) or of his owne peculiar head and affection, which rather we are content to suppose.</p>
   <p>Howsoeuer it be, we wilbe bould to examine in the treatise folowing, with such modesty and indifferency as is requisite in Gods cause, his whole reprehension: and in the meane time til he can proue vs, or our brethren guiltie of anie crime, other then the exercise and profession of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique faith:<note place="margin">Ioa. 10.32 Act. 23.6. Act. 28.20.</note> we wil say with our Sauiour, <hi>De bono opere lapidamur;</hi> and with the Apostle, <hi>De spe &amp; resurrectione mortuorum iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicamur, &amp; propter spem Israel his catenis circunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti sumus.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>