<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLY-Religious M. Crashavv, M. Milward, M. Dauyes, M. Heling, with other worthy Citizens, my very good Friends.</title>
           <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100391_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00564</idno>
           <idno type="STC">107</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100391</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLY-Religious M. Crashavv, M. Milward, M. Dauyes, M. Heling, with other worthy Citizens, my very good Friends.</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blacke devill or the apostate : Together with the wolfe worrying the lambes. And the spirituall navigator, bound for the Holy Land. In three sermons. By Thomas Adams</title>
                 <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 78, 2, 4, 34, 2, 4, 58, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="64"/>
   <pb facs="64"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY-Religious M. Crashavv, <hi>M. Milward, M. Dauyes, M.</hi> Heling, with other worthy <hi>Citizens, my very good</hi> Friends.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen,</hi> Because you haue iust occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion in your callings to deale often with Merchandise, I haue beene bold to call you a little from your Temporall, to a <hi>Spirituall</hi> Traffique: and haue sent you a Christian <hi>Nauigatour, bound for the Holy Land;</hi> who without question will giue you some relations of his Trauells, worthy two houres perusing. You shall finde a whole <hi>Sea</hi> sailed through in a short time; and that a large <hi>Sea,</hi> not a foote lesse then the World. You will say, the description lyes in a little volume: Why, you haue seene the whole world narrow'd vp into a small Mappe. They that haue beene said, after many yeares, at last to compasse it, haue not described all coasts and corners of it. Euen their silence hath giuen succee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="65"/>
generations hope to find out new Lands; and you know, they haue found them. You cannot expect more of two houres discouery, then of seauen yeares. I leaue many things to be descried by others: yet dare promise this, that I haue giuen you some necessary directions for your happiest voyage. Ouer this <hi>glassy Sea</hi> you must saile, you are now sayling. <hi>Truth</hi> be your Card, &amp; the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> your Pilot. Your Course being well direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, you cannot possibly make a happier iourney. The Hauen is before your eyes, where your Sauiour sits with the hand of mercy wafting you to him. You cannot bee <hi>Sea-sicke,</hi> but he will comfort, and restore you. If the Tempest comes, call on him with <hi>Peter, Lord saue vs;</hi> and he will <hi>rebuke the windes and the Seas;</hi> they shal not hurt you. <hi>Storme and tempest,</hi> winds and waters obey his voyce. What Rocks, Gulfes, Swallowes, and the danger (worse then that is called the Terror of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> the Pyrate; one plague which the Deuill hath added to the Sea, more then Nature gaue it) of that great <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> Satan; and other perils that may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger you, are marked out. Decline them so well as you may; and consider what Prouidence guides your course: this <hi>Sea</hi> is <hi>Before</hi> Gods <hi>Throne.</hi> Keepe you the Cape of <hi>good Hope</hi> in your eye: and what euer becomes of this weake Vessell, your <hi>Body;</hi> make sure to saue the Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger, your <hi>Soule,</hi> in the day of the Lord <hi>Iesus.</hi> What is here directed you, shall be faithfully prayed for, by him</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>That vnfainedly desires your Saluation,
Tho: Adams.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>