<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100521_Bo1_10_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16485</idno>
           <idno type="STC">34</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100521</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition vpon the prophet Ionah : Contained in certaine sermons, preached in S. Maries church in Oxford. By George Abbot professor of diuinitie, and maister of Vniuersitie Colledge</title>
                 <author>Abbot, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Garbrand (Harkes), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 638, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>GOOD Reader, the words of the text in the former Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, ministred me occasion to shew, who it is to whom our prayers are to be directed, that is God alone; and consequently, that we should not vse any inuocation of Saints. But in the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling of that question so largely, out of the Fathers of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church, my purpose was not onely to settle the ignorant for their beliefe concerning that point, but withall by example there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to let the simpler sort see, what is to be conceiued in other que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions disputed betweene vs and the Church of Rome. For the same may be said concerning the Primacie of Peter, the merite of
<pb n="225" facs="116"/>
works, free will, prayer for the dead, Purgatorie, &amp; the most part of those controuersies which now a daies are handled. They take on them to maintaine many of their positions if not directly out of the Scriptures, yet from probable shewes out of some of the old Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who were great lights after the time of the Apostles. But first, many bookes pretended to belong to that reuerend age, are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> counterfeits, and start vp since the liues of those graue and godly writers; and from these are many of the allegations taken. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the very auncient Fathers receiued some things as true with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out discussing, whereinto when themselues vpon speciall occasions did iudiciously looke, they were either of a contrarie opinion to their former, or spake faintly and doubtfully. Thirdly, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> which some of them taught was contradicted by other, and so one part must needs erre. Fourthly, they were not so led by the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Spirit of God, as those Secretaries of the holy Ghost, who deliuered the canonicall Scriptures to the world: &amp; therfore they are no farther to be allowed, then where they consent with the most sacred written word; and that is their owne iudgement of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. Lastly, there are many places cited by Bellarmine, Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and other the aduersaries of the Gospell, which when they are diligently looked into, and weighed by all circumstances, do not purport that for the which they are produced. Of all which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations it is easie to giue diuerse examples. This I thought good to note, lest weake brethren or credulous preiudicate persons shold be too much abused, with the misapplied name of the old and most renoumed Church.</p>
   <p>And whereas I haue shewed my opinion concerning the suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed strange shapes of men in many quarters of the world, if anie should vrge any authour of former or later age against that my assertion, in one word I account them all in that point to be fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and onely to haue receiued such rumours and vniustifiable traditions from hand to hand: although some of them, thinking thereby to procure to themselues the fame of men farre tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled, do aduouch that they haue seene such. In our dayes God hath giuen light, &amp; therfore let vs not still delight to be in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Onely this one scruple is to be remooued away, that whereas cōstant report hath auerred this to be so, in some one part of <hi>Peru,</hi>
      <pb n="226" facs="117"/>
is the South portion of the West and lately found Indies; &amp; some men of good iudgement, whose aduentures for nauigation that way, haue nobilitated the discoueries performed or attempted by our English nation, haue with firme credence entertained that for a very truth; yet as I esteeme, they may easily satisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in that behalfe, by the full and sufficient report of <hi>Pedro de Cieca</hi> in his first part of the Chronicles of <hi>Peru,</hi> chapter <hi>26.</hi> who being a Spaniard borne, and now more then fiftie yeares agone hauing spent seuenteene yeares in his personall peregrination ouer that countrey, sheweth that not farre from the Line, yea in more places of <hi>Peru</hi> then one, there are people who being borne in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall shape as other men, yet do take their infants when they are but a few dayes old, and by certaine deuises which they haue, as with frames of wood and binding or swathing do make the head of such fashion as they would, as some to be very long, and some to be so crushed together that they haue no neckes, but their heads seeme to be immediate parts of the trunke of their bodies. And this contenteth me for the veritie of that matter, and I doubt not but so it will to all other, who desire in their minds to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded of things as indeed they be, and not as sometimes they seeme.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>