<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST RE∣VEREND FATHER IN God, the Lord Archbishop of CANTER∣BVRIE his Grace, Primate and Metropolitane of all ENGLAND, Chauncelour of the Vniuersitie of OXFORD, one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Counsell, my verie good LORD.</title>
           <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100540_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18831</idno>
           <idno type="STC">53</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100540</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST RE∣VEREND FATHER IN God, the Lord Archbishop of CANTER∣BVRIE his Grace, Primate and Metropolitane of all ENGLAND, Chauncelour of the Vniuersitie of OXFORD, one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Counsell, my verie good LORD.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The old vvaye : A sermon preached at Oxford, the eight day of Iuly, being the Act Sunday. 1610. By Robert Abbott</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <distributor>Edgar, Eleazar</distributor>
                            <distributor>Garbrand, Ambrose</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 59, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND FATHER IN God, the Lord Archbishop of CANTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BVRIE his Grace, Primate and Metropolitane of all ENGLAND, Chauncelour of the Vniuersitie of OXFORD, one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Counsell, my verie good LORD.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost Reuerend Father, albeit it be somewhat beside custom to make Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sermons, yet it is not beside dutie in me to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="3"/> to your Grace, the first fruits of my returne to this famous Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie, wherof the chiefest protection vnder his most Excellent Maiestre, belongeth to your Grace, &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in through your Grace his cōmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, though to a forward and wel-willing companie, I am now become a Head, where I liued som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times an inferior member. Which place, as by your Grace his fauour it hath befallen mee, without my expectation or seeking, so I desire to vse it being befallen mee in such sort, as to satisfie your Grace his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation and good conceipt of me. In the entrance whereof, if I haue done a seruice so acceptable and so likly to profit many; as the desire of many for the publishing of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="3"/> would import, it shal (I hope) ominate further good in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse of my abode here, which I wish to be no longer thē shalbe for the glorie of God, the seruice of his Maiesty, &amp; the benefit both in spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and in generall of the Church of God. To which I shall bee the more encouraged, if it shall please your Grace to accept in good part, this small worke as a token of my thankefull minde, which in all due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie I recommend to your Grace his fauour, and your selfe in all your affaires, to the mercie and blessing of Almightie GOD, who euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more so assist &amp; guide you in your Pastoral care and Gouernement of his CHVRCH, as that when the chiefe Pastour shall appeare, you
<pb facs="4"/> may in lieu of present toyle and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, receiue an incorruptible Crowne of glorie in that life that is for euer. So resting,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces in all most humble affection and duetie, R. ABBOTT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>