<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100100_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12284</idno>
           <idno type="STC">226</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100100</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A censure upon a dialogue of the Anabaptists : intituled, A description of what God hath predestinated concerning man ... By Henry Ainsworth</title>
                 <author>Ainsworth, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles, Successors of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>CHristian Reader, howbeit the continued infirmitie of this authors body, wherwith it pleased God to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise him, might iustly haue excused him from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king pen in hand to write, especially in businesses of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, his desire being as himselfe testified in his life time, to finish this last period of his life with more comfortable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations then to follow controversies: yet did he labour to his power, yea and (as I may say) beyond his power, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force himselfe even in his decayed health, together with his other necessarie labours, to discover the fraud and falshood of the adversaries: amongst others he iudged these Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists not the least, which occasioned this ensuing Censure; Another nearer inhabitant then the former author, was one Mr. <hi>Paget</hi> that lived in the same citie by him▪ being a chiefe leader to another congregation there, who being of a quarrelsome disposition, and envious hearted towards Mr. <hi>Ainsworth,</hi> and the truth professed by him, having un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iustly picked quarrels against him: afterward without his privitie while matters were in debating (not imitating D. <hi>Reynolds</hi> to <hi>Hart</hi> although he highly commends him pag. <hi>367.</hi>) published a book against him, laying to his charge things which he knew not, even grosse vntruths, and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reproches, making divers false charges upon him, as if he neither shamed nor feared to be Sathans instrument to blow abroad whatsoever envie and malice had scraped to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in likelihood expecting no other reward then grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the world, by the Gospells disgrace in our subversion; yea labouring through his sides to smite the text it selfe,
<pb facs="3"/>
which I trust M. <hi>Ainsworth</hi> hath well cleared in that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle advertisement published in his life time with those books of Moses, besides a particular answer to his book he had well begun, and had finished long before his death had not his infirmitie of body hindered. But now time permits not to instance particulars, but leaving so unneighbourly, yea so unchristian an opposite to the Lord for iudgement, I will add a word or two touching the occasion of this treatise en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing, which was at the request of some, (whose minds the Anabaptists would cumber with their errours) to shew his iudgment on the foresayd book. Now as some were assaulted that yet would giue no way or entertainment to those errors, yet othersome that had stood in the truth a long time, were perverted. The knowledge of these things comming to this reverend and iudicious man, Mr. <hi>Henry Ainsworth,</hi> hee soone drew out this answer, and sent it by a friend into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, to reclaime (if God saw it good) such as had erred herein, and gone astrray by rash and inconsiderate zeale beyond knowledge, and through the grace of God to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue such from falling as yet stood: this he sent for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, purposing if the Lord continued some competent health and strength, to revise and so to make more perfect this which then shortnesse of time in respect of the Messengers great haste, could not be affoorded, and so to make it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick in this spring; but the Lord having prevented this his purpose, by taking him to himselfe, hee now resteth from his labours. Yet finding the matter may, through the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of God, be profitable to his people, it is thought fit not to keepe these his last labours in matters of this nature in silence, but that it come to the publick view for the good of them that are ordained to life. And so I wish thee to fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in the Lord.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>