<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100190_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01490</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11617.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100190</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apology against the defence of schisme : Lately written by an English diuine at Doway, for answere to a letter of a lapsed Catholicke in England his frend: who hauing in the late co [m] mission gone to to [sic] the Church, defended his fall. Wherin is plainly declared, and manifestlye proued, the generall doctrine of the diuines, &amp; of the Church of Christ, which hitherto hath been taught and followed in England, concerning this pointe</title>
                 <author>Garnet, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fr. Garnet’s First Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 202, that is 200 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>HAuing made readye for thy necessary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation against all contagion of Schisme, so present an Electuary, (Gentle Reader) I thought it very profitable for thy better vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and the easier reading of this Treatise, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertise the of the generall order and methode ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The wholle booke therfore is fittely deuided into fiue partes. The first answereth in order the obiections, which are vsually made in defence of Schisme: and were the principall cause of writing this Treatise, according to the occasion ministred by the letter here confuted although afterward al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, through the wholle booke, many obiections be aunswered: either propounded by the author him selfe, or touched in the aforsaide letter.</p>
   <p>The second parte, out of Theologicall grounds and reasons,<note place="margin">§. 13.</note> declareth the vnlawfullnes of this kind of Schisme.</p>
   <p>The third parte, intreateth of some thinges an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed vnto this Schismaticall action.<note place="margin">§. 32.</note> as daunger of infection: the greeuousnes of the sinne, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison with other sinnes: and the neglecting of our dewty towardes our neighbours in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation therof.</p>
   <p>The fourth parte deduceth out of that which went before,<note place="margin">§. 35.</note> that this action was vnlawfull and a signe distinctiue before any statute of the realme, or late Canon of holy Church: and largely entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the nature and variety of signes distinctiue of religion.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>The fifth,<note place="margin">§. 36.</note> examineth the auncient practise of Gods Church: and out of the same doth euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude the determined purpose.</p>
   <p>This, gentle Reader, did I thinke good to warne thee of: desiring in recompence of all my labour, that thou wilt courteously pardon the faultes esca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: which although they be more than I would, yet considering many difficulties of a straunge lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, a straunge countrey, absence of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> authour, and an vnready copy: are notwithstanding fewer than I expected. Other faultes thou maiest lett a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, vntill in reading thou be at a stay: yet in two places there wanting wholle lines: take the paines at the beginning to amend them. that so both thy owne course in reading may be easied: and those which shall come afrer thee, may be furthered.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>