<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE COVRTEOVS AND CHRISTIAN READERS, ESPECIALLY TO HIS OWNE Parishioners, grace, and truth, and peace, with the Churches of God in CHRIST.</title>
           <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100380_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19569</idno>
           <idno type="STC">60</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100380</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE COVRTEOVS AND CHRISTIAN READERS, ESPECIALLY TO HIS OWNE Parishioners, grace, and truth, and peace, with the Churches of God in CHRIST.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A triall of our church-forsakers. Or A meditation tending to still the passions of unquiet Brownists, upon Heb.10.25 : Wherein is iustified, against them, that the blessed Church of England 1 Is a true Church. 2 Hath a true ministry. 3 Hath a true worship. By Robert Abbot</title>
                 <author>Abbot, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Paine (Payne), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <distributor>Meredith, Christopher</distributor>
                            <distributor>Stephens, Philemon</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 223, 222-249, 5 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE COVRTEOVS AND CHRISTIAN READERS, ESPECIALLY TO HIS OWNE Parishioners, <hi>grace,</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> with the Churches of God in CHRIST.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Earely beloved) I have lived now by Gods gratious dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, above fifty yeares; and in the place of my allotment two and twenty full. How unprofitably so ever in the dayes of my vanity, when the world, the flesh, and the Devill, bore sway; yet, through undeserved grace, painefully, ever since the weight of a peoples care was noticed to my consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. I have had <hi>great labours, some watchings, many strifes,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions,
<pb facs="6"/>
with my selfe, and others, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout truth, and godlinesse. And though I have earnestly contended that <hi>the mouth of the oxe might not be muzled, that treadeth out the corne,</hi> but that J, and others of Gods labourers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ight live honorable of the gospell, and at the Altar, at which we serve, as Christ hath ordained: yet (with a good conscience) I can say as the Apostle, <hi>I have coveted no mans gold, or silver, or apparrell:</hi> I have loved, and <hi>desired to spend, and to be spent, though the more I love, the lesse I am loved</hi> of some few</p>
   <p>I know that J must <hi>lay downe this tabernacle,</hi> and the time of my dissolution is not farre off. Therefore doe I more seriously beginne to thinke of my state: and doe set upon it to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine how I am like to be presented <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tribunall seate of God.</hi> Whē I thinke of my sinnes, and manifold
<pb facs="6"/>
infirmities <hi>I feare &amp; quake,</hi> through the sight of the maiesty purity and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of God: but when I think of Christ the <hi>mediator of the new testament,</hi> and of the infinite value of his bloud of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in the dearenesse of Gods love, and applyed &amp; rested on by faith, which the holy Ghost in a saving measure hath given me; <hi>I approach with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and the lifting up of my head.</p>
   <p>But, till that time come I lie under the expectation of flouds of sorrowes, streames of temptations, and other hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane infirmities. I pray that J may doe nothing that may dishonour Christ my master, and that I may suffer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that may drive me from him and his service. J know that the wasters of grace are strong, and many, and that no goodnesse is entayled to us without great care and vigilancy. I know that sinnes and afflictions are the two great enemies of perseverance.
<pb facs="7"/>
And though sinne be the most power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which yet (through grace) I have learned to trample upon with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant acts of piety and charity, <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my measure,</hi> yet afflictions are my next care, which if they bee slighted, will make secret inrodes to hind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r peace with God</p>
   <p>My afflictions have not beene so weighty as millions of Gods deare saints have felt. In this Gods grace hath beene marvellous, because hee knowes my weakenesse to beare, and my unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse to bee a souldier in that war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare: yet have they not beene so lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, as that they have not made me work enough. It is grievous to bee slighted of them whom a man dearely loves and to have contempt powred upon that which comes in fulnesse of strength, and tendernesse of affection to doe good. Jt is hard not once scarce to be thanked, for constant travels to
<pb facs="7"/>
edifie and save soules. It is something to see respects fly abroad in full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to strangers, when nearer relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are forgotten.</p>
   <p>But to bee <hi>persecuted by the tongues</hi> of those a man deserves well of, and to be <hi>privily smitten</hi> of those from whom best incouragements are due, will wound the heart of a <hi>David</hi> though he be after Gods owne heart. J have of long suffered words of dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution and disparagement. They have beene my meate, drinke, and cloathing. Though when I have beene downe the wind of weakenes, feeblenesse of spirit ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> given advantage for a deepe impression, yet (blessed be God) as strength hath appeared I have kicked at them with chearefulnesse, though pride and folly hath sometimes mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpreted this also.</p>
   <p>I have often looked into the cause. Lord, what have I done? Have I
<pb facs="8"/>
not lived like thy servant, though with much sensible weakenesse? have <hi>I not laboured in thy vineyard</hi> with all my strength? have J not taught thy truth by <hi>taking heede to reading and doctrine?</hi> yes surely, saith my conscience I have <hi>kept back none of thy counsell,</hi> I have not <hi>strengthened the hands of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednesse.</hi> I have loved the godly, as such, though I have hated their indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretions, as well as my owne. J have been kinde and courteous to those that have ill rewarded me. Onely, this is the truth, J have loved the Church of God amongst us, and the whole go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement ecclesiasticall, and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall If any thing have appeared harsh, I have excused it a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I was bound. I have not indured to heare publike scandalls to bee layed upon them. I have opposed gainesayers with earnestnesse of spirit, others will
<pb facs="8"/>
say, like a man, but J will say, and J am sure, like a minister.</p>
   <p>This hath fallen upon darke melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholick, high lookt, and sowre natures, and so hath suffered a disgust. Some have beene sowred, but sweetned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with the trade of the good word of God, and the practise of affability. Some have beene estranged till this contracted folly hath beene digested. Some have complayned of chiding, when my nature can chide nothing but sinne and disorder: and some have hardned themselves in error, and schisme. To crosse me (I feare) and my tenets for the Church, they have revenged upon themselves.</p>
   <p>What these few will gaine in the issue I doe not know. This (I doubt) that they will repent, if greatnesse of sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack will let them looke backe againe, when it is too late. But for you (my good people) <hi>in whose hearts God
<pb facs="9"/>
hath writ mee</hi> by the preaching of Christ, and his truth, ye have not <hi>so runne in vaine.</hi> Ye will not be delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with their pretences and sweet words. Yee have heard formerly from me all these grounds, and oppositions of Brownisme, which here J present unto you: and here have J thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressed them for you, that they may keepe you from that snare of <hi>simple ones,</hi> and that they may ever lie by you, when J am dead, and with my Christ, to keepe you upright in the waies of our blessed Church.</p>
   <p>I know that some of you beare a deare and tender affection to these few seduced ones, though now they will not heare you. Ye have lived in the same Church together like friends: ye have delighted in the same word of God, prayer, and sacraments: yee have sweetly comforted one another in the private communion of Saints: and
<pb facs="9"/>
ye see that still they seeme to live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable lives towards men, and that they pretend to delight still in the word of Christ, which <hi>is the onely rule of salvation.</hi> These things will give great advantage to them to worke upon you, and to you to keepe intimate familiarity with them. But (in the feare of God I beseech you) take heede: weigh well what in this discourse J say, and <hi>God give you understanding in all things.</hi> Jt is no small charge to unchurch a church, to unminister a ministery, and to unworship a worship. They must be sure of their hands, that they can, and will answer it to Christ with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence when they have done it. To doe it with a trembling heart, is to doe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst conscience. To doe it <hi>with full assurance of understanding,</hi> is to doe it with sure warrants, and precepts of Christ. If they have such against our
<pb facs="10"/>
Church, I am sure we shall finde them: if not let them goe, if they will, but follow not them in the breach.</p>
   <p>To keepe you out of it, I have done as J doe: and to gaine them too, if they will not bee resolved without grounds. J am sure they shall have no iust cause to except against my dealing with them. They may except against me, as an <hi>English Priest,</hi> and <hi>Bishops creature,</hi> as I heare, but shall never against my course with them. I have dealt with them with matter more then with words: and because they pretend to two things, to the <hi>scriptures,</hi> and to <hi>conscience,</hi> and I know a third thing in them, <hi>weakenesse.</hi> Therefore have J dealt with them accordingly. J have compared scripture with scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to finde out the truth, but cannot finde theirs. I have dealt
<pb facs="10"/>
conscionably with them in fighting with that onely weapon against them, of their owne choosing, the word of Christ. And because they are weake, I have not shewed my selfe a man in giving them any bitter language, or exasperating termes. As the barking of one dogge begets the barking of another, though it bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Moone: so is it with high words, and therefore it were glorious, and above a man, if it were layed downe on all sides, and partakings. But as the waves of the sea, when they meete not with a rocke, but with the sands, they returne backe-againe with a wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry flash: so have J done by them, <hi>that all our matters may be done in love.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Indeede I have taken their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted name out of their mouthes, <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratists;</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
and given their right one unto them, <hi>Brownists;</hi> and this J have done out <hi>of conscience.</hi> I finde by experience that the word, <hi>Separation,</hi> doth winne to their cause: For, when people of strong affections, and weaker Iudgements, doe reade of the necessity of separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the scriptures; and can not discerne how we have made separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from heathenisme, and when we have beene thrust out of <hi>Rome (because wee were unwilling to bee so bad as shee)</hi> have maintayned our just standing from her in a divided way; they have beene willing to hearken to a separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting plott. Therefore Browne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leader amongst us, to this breach, (if now time hath not made it worse then he intended it) J can not nickname, but inconscience call
<pb facs="11"/>
the childe after the fathers name. Jt was Christs course, <hi>ye are of your father the Devill, his children ye are,</hi> and so must I.</p>
   <p>Jt is true also, that afterwards, yee may finde some opinions gone against, that are held by some that keepe Communion with our Church, as of a true Church. But I am sure they are the <hi>Brownists</hi> opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons also, to whom I speake. All that I can say therefore for that, is this. Jt may bee, that some of you know, or have heard of that Noble Moralizers fable of <hi>Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olus,</hi> who when hee was in all his military accoutraments to give combate (as hee thought) to <hi>Argalus</hi> a Knight of the Sunne. This mans wife dressed her selfe in her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands armour, and gave her husbands enemy meeting. <hi>Amphiolus</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters
<pb facs="12"/>
valiantly, gave a wound in the necke, closeth, overthrowes, and gives a mortall wound in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. But when hee opened the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, viewes his Conquest, and saw it was faire <hi>Parthenia, Arga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> his wife, he could have no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the day, it became not a man so to ruine a woman. Such is my case heere. J say as a father of old, <hi>I dare not write against a Bishop of my communion;</hi> the love of brotherly peace is glorious in the Church, even among men that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise differ in opinion. But if they put on the armes of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, (because they will bee so) with whom I fight for truth, I cannot helpe it, if they meete with a blow, though I glory not in it, yea am sorry that there should be any such cause.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>I have now done, and commend you all <hi>to the word of Gods grace which is able to save your soules,</hi> though no Bownist, nor Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist had ever beene hatched. <hi>Live in peace, and the God of peace shall bee with you.</hi> Give not way to any opinion whereby the <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of spirit, and the bond of love</hi> may be broken. <hi>Play the men, be strong and of a good courage.</hi> Have prepared hearts to dye for Christs cause: but, to bee sticklers in such poore quarrels, as can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bring peace to the Church, nor comfort to you at last, abhorre. <hi>Wee must all appeare before the Iudgement seate of God,</hi> where colours shall doe us no good, because we shall be iudged naked: where pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences shall doe us no good, because <hi>the bookes shall bee opened:</hi>
      <pb facs="13"/>
and where no authors or favourers of Sects, or Schismes shall shelter us, because we must stand before <hi>the man Christ Iesus:</hi> to whom I ever leave you, and in whose name ye shall have the prayers of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to be used in the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Gospel ROBERT ABBOT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>