<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Philanthropus, Theophilus</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100760_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06160</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16651</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100760</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Philanthropus, Theophilus</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christs communion with his church militant : First preached, and now published, for the good of Gods church in generall. By Nicholas Lockyer, Mr. of Arts</title>
                 <author>Lockyer, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rothwell, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 194 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ommunion with Christ, is our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines in this world, and in
the world to come: that which makes every bitter thing sweet, and every
sweet thing sweeter. With this sweet subject is this little tract, now
come to thy hand, taken up. Poore fallen man is still complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one
want or other; and when the thing is given which he longed for, yet his soule
is as far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as before; like to a childe that cries for this and
that, and yet when he hath what he cryed for, continues crying still, and
cannot tell well what he would have. All our want <pb facs="6"/>is this, the want
of Communion with Christ: this is the cause of all complaints; the
infelicity of the soule; the summe of mans misery, here and hereafter;
but poore blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man sees it not, and therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of twenty things,
twenty miles a this side his disease; and so spends his dayes in
labour and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and yet loses happinesse, both here and hereafter
too. A full fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of Christ, is full felicity: a full fruition of any
thing below Christ, without Christ, is but vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and vexation of
spirit. The more then, O fallen man, thou canst get into communion with thy
God, the more will thy great losse bee repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, thy complaining soule
satisfied, &amp; thy tranquillity setled upon thee againe. Hunt not then
after rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, honours, pleasures, and suchlike low delights of the
sonnes of men, with this deluded mistaken world, which lyes in
wickednesse; for feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city <pb facs="6"/>is not in these: but study and
strive after a nearer communion with Christ: the next way to get most in
with him, is the speedy way unto all happinesse: so much as thou
canst get of his company, so much art thou in Heaven. <hi>How preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are
thy thoughts unto mee, O God,</hi> (saith David?) <hi>how great is the
summe of them? If I should count them, they are more in number then the
sand: when I awake I am still with thee.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal.
139.17,18.</note> This is Heaven upon Earth; and that true nobility and honour,
which wee should all bee ambitious after; to lose our spirits in God.
What an unspeakable felicity is it, to bee still with God in our thoughts?
This ennobles the spirit of man, and makes it a companion to the King of
Kings: this gives evennesse and steadinesse to a mans course; and
makes him walke in all the wayes of God blamelesse: this gives
transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant <pb facs="7"/>peace &amp; tranquility to a mans spirit; and
makes him unmoveable in the midst of feares: this gives bread, in famine;
drink in drought; peace, in warre; health, in sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; life, in death.
Devote thy selfe therefore to Christ, that he may devote himselfe to
thee: and as a poore <hi>medium</hi> of communion, make use (if you please)
of this ensuing Treatise. If thou get any good, give glory to God; and make
the poore Pen-man, a constant sharer in thy prayers.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ. <hi>Theophilus
Philanthropus.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>