<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREPARATIVE TO THE TRIPLE CORD. WHEREIN Is proued the Dignity &amp; Infallibility of the written Word of God, or Sacred Scriptures: As also the necessity of finding out their true sense intended by the Holy Ghost: With certaine infallible Rules for the finding out of the sayd Sense.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100159_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19373</idno>
           <idno type="STC">580</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100159</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREPARATIVE TO THE TRIPLE CORD. WHEREIN Is proued the Dignity &amp; Infallibility of the written Word of God, or Sacred Scriptures: As also the necessity of finding out their true sense intended by the Holy Ghost: With certaine infallible Rules for the finding out of the sayd Sense.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triple cord or a treatise proving the truth of the Roman religion, by sacred scriptures taken in the literall sense : expounded by ancient fathers. interpreted by Protestant writers. With a discouery of sundry subtile sleights vsed by Protestants, for euading the forc of strongest arguments, taken from cleerest texts of the foresaid scriptures</title>
                 <author>Anderton, Lawrence</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72, 24, 33-801, 11 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="1" facs="37"/>
   <head>A PREPARATIVE TO THE TRIPLE CORD. WHEREIN Is proued the Dignity &amp; Infallibility of the written Word of God, or Sacred Scriptures: As also the necessity of finding out their true sense intended by the Holy Ghost: With certaine infallible Rules for the finding out of the sayd Sense.</head>
   <div n="1" type="section">
      <head>SECT. I. The true State of the Question, concerning the verity of the Sacred Scriptures. Whether the Scriptures contained in the Bible be the word of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe truly Diuine and Infallible in euery least parcell or text ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? And therefore for such are by all the faythfull to be receaued, belieued, and obeyed.</head>
      <div n="Catholic" type="doctrine">
         <head>Catholike Doctrine.</head>
         <p>
            <hi>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ACRED Scripture being a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ground of Christian fayth and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the dignity and infallible truth thereof must necessarily be acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; and therfore the Catholike Church</hi>
            <note n="(1)" place="margin">Conc Trid sess. <hi>4.</hi> Decret. de Canonicis Scripturis.</note> Receaueth and honoureth with like affect ō of Piety and reuerence all the bookes as well of
<pb n="2" facs="38"/> the Old as New Testament, seeing one God is Authour of both &amp;c. <hi>The Councell Senonense decreeth, that</hi>
            <note n="(2)" place="margin">
               <hi>Decret.</hi> 4.</note> Great hath been &amp; euer is to be the Authority of sacred Scripture, in which nothing can be false, nothing idle. <hi>Our Catholike Doctours teach, that</hi>
            <note n="(3)" place="margin">Rhem. Test. in Gal. <hi>6.</hi>
            </note> The Scriptures which are indeed wholly of the holy Ghosts indyting, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put to the Churches tryall, are found proued, and testifyed vnto the world to be such, and not made true, altered, and amended by the same. Without which attestation of the Church, the holy Scriptures in themselues, were alwayes true before, but not so knowne to be to all Christians, nor they so bound to take them. Cardinall Bellarmine <hi>proueth seuerall wayes, that the</hi>
            <note n="(4)" place="margin">De verbo Dei l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
            </note> Canonicall Bookes of Scripture are the word of God. So that according to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, there is not any one Sentence or text of Scripture which we are not bound to belieue for most true &amp; diuine.</p>
      </div>
      <div n="Protestant" type="doctrine">
         <head>Protestant Doctrine.</head>
         <p>
            <hi>Some</hi> Prot.<note n="(5)" place="margin">Harm. of Confess. p. 1.</note> belieue &amp; confesse the Canonicall Scriptures of the holy Prophets, and Apostles of both Testaments, to be the very true word of God &amp;c. <hi>And they</hi>
            <note n="(6)" place="margin">Ibid. pag. <hi>3</hi>
            </note>
            <hi>detest all the heresies of Artemon, the Manichees, Valentinians, of Cerdon, and the Marcionistes, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed that the Scriptures proceeded from the holy Ghost, or els receaued not, or &amp;c. corrupted some of them.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>Others of more sublimated spirits do so little esteeme of the written Word, that they affirme the</hi>
            <note n="(7)" place="margin">See heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after Chap. 1. Sect. 1. fig 53.</note> Old Testament and the New to be contrary and to fight altogeather. <hi>Others vtterly reiect</hi>
            <note n="(8)" place="margin">Luth. tom. <hi>3.</hi> VVittemb. in Psalm. <hi>45.</hi> f. <hi>423. 422.</hi> &amp; tom. <hi>3.</hi> Ger. f. <hi>40. 41.</hi>
            </note>
            <hi>Moyses and his writings, as being (as they conceit)</hi> in the sight of God either Idolatry, or Hipocriticall wisdome. <hi>Others</hi>
            <note n="(9)" place="margin">Swingl. tom. <hi>2.</hi> cont. Anabap. f. <hi>10.</hi>
            </note>
            <hi>charge the Anabaptistes with ignorance, for that they thinke the Commentaries of the Euangelists, and the Epistles of the Apostles, to haue bene then in Authority, when Paul did write these things, as though Paul did attribute so much to his Epistles, that whatsoeuer was contained in them was sacred &amp;c. Which thing</hi> (sayth Swinglius) were to attribute immoderate arrogancy to the Apostle.<note n="(10)" place="margin">VVhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tak. de Eccl. cont. Bel. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trou. <hi>2.</hi> q <hi>4.</hi> pag. <hi>213.</hi> Fulke ag. the Rhem. Test. in Gal. <hi>2.</hi> f. <hi>322.</hi>
            </note>
            <hi>Others condemne</hi> S. Peter to haue erred in matters of fayth, euen after the Holy Ghostes descending vpon the Apostles. <hi>But these things once admitted, how then can we be secure that the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listes and Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tles were the Scribes of the holy Ghost, and erred not also in their writings?</hi>
         </p>
         <pb n="3" facs="38"/>
         <p>
            <hi>And if it be true which</hi> D. Fulke <hi>sayth,</hi>
            <note n="(11)" place="margin">In Confut. of Purgat. p. <hi>214.</hi>
            </note> Whosoeuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth the authority of the holy Scriptures, therby bewraieth himselfe to be an hereticke; <hi>what is then to be thought of Luther, Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Swinglius, Fulke himselfe, and sundry other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes, who thus impudently detract from the authority of Moyses, the Euangelistes, the Apostles, and their writings.</hi>
         </p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="section">
      <head>
         <hi>SECT. II.</hi> That the sacred Scriptures are the true word of God, diuine &amp; infallible, the Scriptures themselues do testify.</head>
      <p>I Do not intend these proofes from Scriptures with any expectation that they should be approued by such as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect their authority, relying only vpon their priuate Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, but only in this regard, that the world may know, that we Catholikes do so highly esteeme them for diuine and infallible, as whatsoeuer is spoken, taught, or to be read ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, we in all Disputes and Controuersies of Religion, do humbly submit our selues to the doctrine thereof.</p>
      <p>First then we belieue that the Author of the Scriptures, is only God himselfe, dictating them to his Prophets, Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelistes, and Apostles, as his Scribes; of whom <hi>S. Peter</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that,<note n="(1)" place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.</note>
         <hi>The holy men of God spake, inspired with the Holy Ghost.</hi> And S. Paul affirmeth that,<note n="(2)" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</note>
         <hi>All Scripture inspired by God is profitable to teach &amp;c.</hi> Agreably to which the Prophets were said to be <hi>the mouth of our Lord:</hi>
         <note n="(3)" place="margin">
            <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.20.</note>
         <hi>The mouth of our Lord hath Spoken.</hi>
         <note n="(4)" place="margin">
            <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.70.</note>
         <hi>As he spoke by the mouth of his holy Prophets, that are from the beginning.</hi>
         <note n="(5)" place="margin">
            <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1.</note>
         <hi>In tymes past God speaking to the Fathers in the Prophets, last of all in these dayes hath spoken to vs in his Son.</hi> This speach whether vttered by the Prophets, or by Christ himselfe, is here said to proceed from God, as the first Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. And so God is said to speake by the mouth of man, &amp; the Prophets and other sacred writers by the mouth of God. And wheras Moises writeth that<note n="(6)" place="margin">
            <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.16.</note>
         <hi>God said to Pharao,</hi> S. Paul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>elating the same thing writeth that, <hi>The</hi>
         <note n="(7)" place="margin">
            <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.17.</note>
         <hi>Scripture sayth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>harao:</hi> so m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>king Gods speaking and the Scriptures spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ing all one. And to the same purpose speaketh <hi>S. Paul</hi> of
<pb n="4" facs="39"/> himselfe,<note n="(8)" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3.</note>
         <hi>Seeke you an experiment of him, that speaketh in me, Christ?</hi> Yea the selfe same vvritings are said to be written by God, &amp; by Moises. So God said to Moises.<note n="(9)" place="margin">
            <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.1. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.1.2.4.</note>
         <hi>Cut thee two ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of stone like vnto the former, and I will write vpon them the words which the tables had, which thou hast broken.</hi>
         <note n="(10)" place="margin">
            <hi>Deut</hi> 10.4.</note>
         <hi>And he wrote in the tables according as he had written before, the</hi> 10. <hi>wordes. And yet</hi>
         <note n="(11)" place="margin">
            <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.27.28.</note>
         <hi>our Lord said to Moises, write thou these words &amp;c. And he wrote in the Tables the words of the Couenant, ten.</hi> Now how could the Tables of the law be said to be written by God &amp; by Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, but that Moises as a schollar did hould the pen, and God as maister did direct, that so all that writing might be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to Moises as the Instrument, and to God as the chiefe author.</p>
      <p>A further proofe heer of may be taken from the frequent practise of the holy men of God, who vsually confirmed their callings, as also the Doctrine which they wrote or preached by testimonies of the Scripture. So S. Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiste alleadged the Prophet I say as a witnesse of his Embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, for being asked who he was, he answered,<note n="(12)" place="margin">
            <hi>Io.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Esa.</hi> 40.3.</note>
         <hi>I am the voyce of one crying in the desert, make straight the way of our Lord, as I say the Prophet said.</hi> The Apostles Peter, Paul, Iohn, Iames, Iude, in all their Epistles do frequently alleadge the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the law and Prophets. Yea Christ himselfe first of all confirmed his owne Embassage by testimony of the Prophet Esay saying,<note n="(13)" place="margin">
            <hi>Luc.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Esa.</hi> 61.1.</note>
         <hi>The spirit of the Lord vpon me, for which he annointed me &amp;c.</hi> He confuteth the Saduces out of the Scriptures, when he said,<note n="(14)" place="margin">
            <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.24.26.</note>
         <hi>Do you not therfore erre, not knowing the Scriptures?</hi> And a little after, <hi>As concerning the dead that they do ryse againe, haue you not read in the booke of Moises &amp;c?</hi> Finally he<note n="(15)" place="margin">
            <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.43. <hi>Psal</hi> 109.1.</note> confuteth the Pharisees by the testimony of Dauid, and directeth them thus,<note n="(16)" place="margin">
            <hi>Io.</hi> 5.39.</note>
         <hi>Search the Scriptures for you thinke in them to haue life Euerlasting, and the same are they that giue testimony of me.</hi> This alleadging of the Scriptures by the Prophets, Apostles, and Christ himselfe in proofe of their Callings and Doctrine, doth cleerly suppose their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine infallibility.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="section">
      <pb n="5" facs="39"/>
      <head>
         <hi>SECT. III.</hi> That the Ancient Fathers do teach and belieue the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cred Scriptures to be the true word of God, of diuine, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Authoritie.</head>
      <p>THE Ancient Fathers teach, that the sacred Scriptures are Letters, or Epistles sent from God to man. So S. Chriso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome,<note n="(1)" place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>m. <hi>2.</hi> in Gen.</note>
         <hi>God from the beginning spoke with man by himself for so he came to Adam so he blamed Cain, so he spoke with Noë, so he lodged with Abrahā. But after all mankind had degenerated into great malice, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then did the maker of all withdraw himselfe wholly from man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind but willing to renew his friendship with them, he sent letters as to men absent, to reconcile vnto him all men, and these Letters God gaue, but Moises brought them.</hi> S. Austine affirmeth that,<note n="(2)" place="margin">In Ps. <hi>90.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Letters came to vs from that Citie</hi> (to wit Heauen) <hi>where we are Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: they are the Scriptures, which do exhort vs to liue well.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note n="(3)" place="margin">Ser. <hi>16.</hi> ad frat. in Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo.</note>
         <hi>The diuine Scriptures, are as Letters sent to vs from our Country. Because our King more pious and mercifull then can be thought or spoken, hath vouchsafed to send vnto vs by Patriarches and Prophetes the diuine inuiting Scriptures by which he would inuite vs to our eternall Country.</hi>
         <note n="(4)" place="margin">L <hi>4.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. Ep. <hi>84.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>What is sacred Scripture</hi> (saith S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory) <hi>but a certaine Epistle of Almighty God to his Creature?</hi>
      </p>
      <p>S. Austine teacheth, that Christ God and man<note n="(5)" place="margin">De ciuit. Dei. l. <hi>11.</hi> c <hi>3.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Spoke first by the Prophets, then by himselfe, after by the Apostles as much as he iudged sufficient: yea he made a writing</hi> (or Scripture) <hi>which is called Canonicall, of most eminent Authority which we belieue of these things, which it is not expedient to be ignorant of, nor are able of our selues to know.</hi> And writing to S. Hierome,<note n="(6)" place="margin">
            <hi>Ep.</hi> 19.</note>
         <hi>I acknowledge</hi> (saith he) <hi>to thy Charity that I haue learned to giue that feare and honour to those bookes onely of the Scriptures, which are now called Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, that I most firmely belieue no Author of them to haue erred any thing in writing. And if I shall find any thing in those writings, which seemeth contrary to truth, I will nothing doubt, but that either the Book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> is corrupted, or that the Interpreter hath not conceiued what is spoken, or that my selfe doth not vnderstand it.</hi> So Religious a respect did S. Austine beare to the Scriptures. Yea he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly
<pb n="6" facs="40"/> auoucheth that,<note n="(7)" place="margin">De doct. Christ. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>37.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>faith it selfe will stragger, if the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of diuine Scriptures do not stand sure.</hi> In which respect pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering it before all the writings of men, he further saith:<note n="(8)" place="margin">De Bapt. Cont. Don. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Who knoweth not, that the holy Canonicall Scripture as well of the old as new Testament is contained in its owne certaine Bounds, and that the same is so to be preferred before all the later writings of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopes, that no doubt or disputation may be had thereof, whether it be true or right whatsoeuer shall appeare to be written therin.</hi> Thus S. Austine, and thus all Catholikes at this day.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="section">
      <head>
         <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> That Sundry Protestants doe acknowledge the sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be the word of God, of diuine and infallible au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</head>
      <p>MAny Protestāts seeme to giue so much credit vnto the sacred Scriptures, as that they pretend to belieue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for certaine, but the holy Scriptures only. So <hi>M.</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let teacheth that,<note n="(1)" place="margin">Synop. p. <hi>38</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>The Scripture is not one of the meanes, but the sole, whole, and only meanes to worke faith.</hi> And agreably our English Church hath decred that the<note n="(2)" place="margin">
            <hi>Art.</hi> 6,</note>
         <hi>Holy scripture cōtaineth all things necessary to Saluation: So that whatsoeuer is not read ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, nor may be proued therby, is not to be required of any man, that it should be belieued as an Article of the faith, or be thought requisite or necessary to Saluation.</hi> The Heluetian reformed Church ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that,<note n="(3)" place="margin">In the Harm of Confess <hi>p.</hi> 4.</note>
         <hi>In controuersies of Religion or matters of faith, we cannot admit any other Iudge then God himselfe, pronouncing by the holy Scriptures what is true, what is false, what is to be followed, or what to be auoyded.</hi> And againe,<note n="(4)" place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>5.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>The Canonicall Scripture being she word of God, and deliuered by the holy Ghoste, and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed to the world by the Prophets and Apostles, being of all other the most perfect and ancient Philosophy, doth alone perfectly containe all Piety &amp;c.</hi>
         <note n="(5)" place="margin">In the Harm. <hi>pa.</hi> 6.</note> The Bohemiā Ministers reach with one cōsent, <hi>cōcerning the holy Scriptures of the new &amp; old Testament, which is cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Byble &amp;c. that it is true, certaine, and worthy to be belieued &amp;c It is inspired and taught of the holy Ghost, and vttered by the mouth of holy men, written by them, and confirmed by heauenly
<pb n="7" facs="40"/> and diuine testimonies &amp;c.</hi>
         <note n="(6)" place="margin">Ib. p. <hi>7.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Wherfore euery one ought very highly to esteeme of the diuine writings of the holy Prophets and Apostles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely to belieue them, and religiously to yield vnto them in all things.</hi> The French Protest. auouch,<note n="(7)" place="margin">
            <hi>Harm. pa.</hi> 8. 9.</note>
         <hi>That God reueiled himselfe &amp;c. farre more plainly in his word: which word in the begining he reueiled to the fathers by certaine visions and Oracles, and then caused it to be written in these Bookes we call holy Scripture. All this holy Scripture is contayned in the Canonicall Bookes of the old and new Testament.</hi> And then making the Catalogue therof, they say, <hi>we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge these Bookes to be Canonicall, that is, we account them as the Rule and square of our faith &amp;c. and we belieue that the Word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in these bookes, came from one God &amp;c.</hi> The Prot. of Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia<note n="(8)" place="margin">Harm pa. <hi>10.</hi>
         </note> confesse that, <hi>this word of God was not brought or deliuered by any will of man but that holy men of God inspired by Gods spirit spake it as S. Peter witnesseth &amp;c.</hi> And they<note n="(9)" place="margin">Ib p. <hi>11.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>without any doubt belieue also those things, which are contained in them &amp;c. As also that this holy Scripture doth most perfectly contayne the will of God, and that in it all things are abundantly taught, whatsoeuer is necessary to be belieued of man to attaine saluation.</hi> The Prot. of Wittemberge say,<note n="(10)" place="margin">Ib. p. <hi>13.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>This Scripture we belieue and confesse to be the Oracle of the Holy Ghost, so confirmed by heauenly Testimonies, that if an Angel from heauen preach any other thing, let him be accursed.</hi> The Prot. of Scotland decree thus:<note n="(11)" place="margin">Harm. p. <hi>19.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>As we belieue and confesse the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God sufficient to instruct, and make the man of God prefect; so doe we affirme and auow the authority of the same to be of God, and neither to depend on men or Angels.</hi> In regard of these premisses and sundry other such like acknowledgments, D Fulke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth and concludeth as before, that<note n="(12)" place="margin">Against <hi>Purgat. pag.</hi> 214.</note>
         <hi>whosoeuer denyeth the Authority of the Holy Scriptures, therby bewraieth himselfe to be an heretike.</hi> And in this truth all Catholikes doe accord with D. Fulke.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="5" type="section">
      <head>
         <hi>SECT. V.</hi> That it is impious to corrupt, or reiect any part of Canonicall Scripture.</head>
      <p>ALL sides agree, that it is most impious to corrupt the wordes, or true sense of Scripture, by adding, or sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting,
<pb n="8" facs="41"/> mistranslating, or false interpreting; this being, as S. Paul saith,<note n="(1)" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 2.</note>
         <hi>to adulterate the word of God:</hi> and these Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters according to Origen, are,<note n="(2)" place="margin">In Rom. <hi>2.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Theeues and adulterers of the Scriptures.</hi> And S. Cyprian calleth them,<note n="(3)" place="margin">De vnit. Eccl. nu. <hi>7.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>false Interpreters, art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ficers. &amp; craftsmaisters in corrupting the truth.</hi> The anc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ēt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes were obserued by the<note n="(4)" place="margin">Iren. l <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
         </note> Fathers, to be often guilty of this haynous crime, but none more frequently &amp; palpably then our moderne Prot. haue offended herin, as will cleerly appeare vpon sundry occasions in this Treatise following. But this they haue learned from their first Father Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to whom Swinglius said,<note n="(5)" place="margin">Swingl. tom <hi>2.</hi> ad Luth l. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram. p. <hi>412. 413.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Thou dost corrupt the word of God, thou art seene to be a manifest and common corrupter and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerter of the holy Seriptures: how much are we ashamed of thee, who haue hitherto esteemed thee beyond all measure, &amp; now proue thee to be such a man.</hi> Wheras on the other side, for speciall reuerence &amp; sincerity of dealing in those matters, the Fathers and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like expositors are those whom S. Paul styleth<note n="(6)" place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15.</note>
         <hi>Right hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the word of truth:</hi> These making Conscience and estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it most sacrilegious to corrupt, alter, adde, or subtract the least word or sillable indited by the holy Ghost, &amp; writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the booke of God.</p>
      <p>It is no lesse criminall to deny or reiect the sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures when they seeme to make against them: which S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome obserueth to be the custome of ancient heretikes, who,<note n="(7)" place="margin">In Proaem, Comment. in ep ad Tit.</note>
         <hi>whatsoeuer they saw contrary to their opinion, they either scraped out, or reiected the whole.</hi> Or, as S. Austine saith of them.<note n="(8)" place="margin">L. <hi>18</hi> cont. Faust. Man. c <hi>7.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>That which doth not hinder their heresy, that they receiue: but tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> which hindreth, that they reeeiue not.</hi> So the Manichees denyed all the old Testament, and many parts of the new, as S. Austine<note n="(9)" place="margin">Haer. <hi>46.</hi> &amp; cont. Faust. l. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; <hi>81.</hi>
         </note> witnesseth; the Nicolaires and Gnostikes discarded cut of the Canon the Psalter, as Philastrius<note n="(10)" place="margin">L. de hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res c. <hi>117.</hi>
         </note> testifieth. The Ebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onites plainly reiected the Ghospell of S. Mathew, as S. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius<note n="(11)" place="margin">
            <hi>Haer.</hi> 30.</note> recordeth: And<note n="(12)" place="margin">
            <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 21.</note> according to Eusebius, they made smal account of the rest of the Ghospels. Marcion receiued only the Ghospell of S. Luke, as Tertullian<note n="(13)" place="margin">L de Praescrip. Iren. l <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi>
         </note> and Irenaeus auouch: And the same maimed in aboue 20. places,<note n="(14)" place="margin">
            <hi>Haer.</hi> 42.</note> as S. Epiphanius proueth, and confuteth. The Alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians contemned the Ghospell of S. Iohn, and the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyps,
<pb n="9" facs="41"/> witnesse <hi>Epiphanius.</hi>
         <note n="(15)" place="margin">
            <hi>Haer</hi> 51.</note> The Seuerians admitted not the Actes of the Apostles, as <hi>Eusebius</hi>
         <note n="(16)" place="margin">
            <hi>L.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> declareth, &amp; the same affirmeth <hi>S. Austine</hi>
         <note n="(17)" place="margin">L. de vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. cred c. <hi>2.</hi>
         </note> of the Manichees. The Ebionites re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected all the Epistles of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> as witnesse <hi>S. Irenaeus</hi>
         <note n="(18)" place="margin">L. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>26.</hi> Epiph. haer. <hi>30.</hi>
         </note> and <hi>S. Epiphanius.</hi> Now that our moderne Prot. doe no little of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in this kind of reiecting the Scriptures, whē they seeme to make against them, I shall sundry wayes make cleere, in this<note n="(19)" place="margin">See hereafter.</note> subsequent Treatise.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="6" type="section">
      <head>
         <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> The necessity of finding out the true Sense of the sacred Scriptures.</head>
      <p>SEeing all things naturally desire that which is good, and the mind cannot incline to any euill, which may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the vnderstanding or the will frō that which is right, vnles it be vnder the pretext and colour of that which is true &amp; good; euen as the Deuill to deceyue men,<note n="(1)" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note>
         <hi>doth trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure himselfe into an Angell of light:</hi> So in matter of faith, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being more true thē the sacred Scriptures, all heretikes vnder the specious title of the Scriptures, do deceiue others and are deceiued themselues. Now because falshood cannot receiue proofe from truth, and Scripture rightly vnderstood can produce or nourish no errour; therfore from Scriptures falsely vnderstood doe all Heretikes defend themselues and their cause. But against this fraud Christ himselfe forwarneth vs,<note n="(2)" place="margin">
            <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15.</note>
         <hi>to take great heede of false Prophets, which come in the cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of sheep, but inwardly are rauening wolues.</hi> This cloathing of sheep are the words of the Prophets and Apostles, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by heretikes, but inwardly, that is, in the Sense of the words, they are reuening wolues and robbers of Soules. To which purpose saith most excellently the eloquent Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,<note n="(3)" place="margin">L. Cont. proph. haer. Nouitates. c. <hi>36.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>what is the cloathing of sheep, but the sentences of Prophets and Apostles? Who are the rauening wolues, but the wild and rauenous senses of heretiks, who alwaies trouble the foulds of the Church, and teare in peaces the flocke of Christ by what meanes they can? But that they may more deceiptfully steale vpon the vnwary sheepe, the cruelty of wolues remayning, they cast of the shape of wolues, and wrappe
<pb n="10" facs="42"/> thēselues within the sentences of Gods law, as within certaine fleeces of sheep.</hi> In like sort wheras our Sauiour biddeth vs not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue false Prophets who wil cry,<note n="(4)" place="margin">
            <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.23.</note>
         <hi>Lo heer is Christ, or there,</hi> old Origen expoundeth this of heretikes detorting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:<note n="(5)" place="margin">In Mat. hom. <hi>29</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>He that would deceiue vs saith, Behold heere is Christ, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for example this place of the Gospell: but the Author of another error will say, Behold Christ is heere, offering for example another text.</hi> So that the text of Scripture is made to serue the turne of all he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiks, though neuer so opposite one to another: Euery one, as S. Peter saith,<note n="(6)" place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</note>
         <hi>deprauing the Scriptures to their owne perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <note n="(7)" place="margin">Tract. <hi>18.</hi> in Ioan.</note>In this respect it is, that the sacred Scriptures are said to be the bookes of Hereticks. <hi>Heresies</hi> (saith S. Austine) <hi>and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine opinions insnaring the soules of the peruerse, and plunging them into the depth</hi> (of Errour) <hi>haue no other roote but when Scriptures are not well vnderstood, and what is not wel vnderstood in them, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so rashly and audaciously defended.</hi> Yea,<note n="(8)" place="margin">De Gen. &amp; lit. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>They are Heretickes for no other cause, but because not rightly vnderstanding the Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, they obstinatly maintaine their false opinions, against the truth of them.</hi> And according to S. Hilary,<note n="(9)" place="margin">L. <hi>2.</hi> de Trinit. &amp; l. de Synodis extremo.</note>
         <hi>Heresy is</hi> (or aryseth) <hi>of the vnderstanding not of the Scripture</hi> (it selfe,) <hi>the fault is in the sense, not in the wordes.</hi> And then naming diuers Heretickes, he sayth, <hi>they all speake Scriptures without sense, they all pretend fayth, without faith: for the Scriptures are not in the reading, but in the vnderstanding.</hi> Agreably to which, Christ our Lord repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Sadduces in these words:<note n="(10)" place="margin">
            <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.29.</note>
         <hi>You do erre, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God.</hi> The Sadduces did read the texte of Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e, but therfore they are said <hi>to erre,</hi> because they did not know, that is, they did not vnderstand the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: teaching therby that the cause of Error, is the not right vnderstanding, although we haue the wordes vpon our fingers ends.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>S. Irenaeus</hi>
         <note n="(11)" place="margin">
            <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> disputing against heretickes auoucheth that their monstrous Doctrines and phantasies of opinion, are wholly framed of Scriptures not well ioyned together; As If a man should breake asunder the Kings Image made of precious stones, and changing the figure, should make ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Foxes &amp; Lions, and by reason of the identity of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="11" facs="42"/> should endeauour to persuade the simple, that this is the true Image of the king: such like monsters make Heretickes of the word of God it selfe. This is so certaine a truth, that D. Luther himselfe auoucheth that,<note n="(12)" place="margin">In Postil. VVitt. in <hi>2.</hi> con. <hi>8.</hi> Dom. post Trinit. fol. <hi>118.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>It is true that the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture is the booke of Heretickes, because Heretickes are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed to prouoke to that booke: neither did there aryse at any time any Heresy so pestiferous, and so foolish, which did not endeauour to hyde it selfe vnder the veile of Scripture.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>That then, which importeth for the final and Infallible deciding of Controuersies arysing from the Scripture, is to fynd out the true sense therof intended by the holy Ghost: to which all parties will professe without any tergiuersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to yield and subscribe. And so prescribed S. Hierome,<note n="(13)" place="margin">In Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. ad Gal. <hi>1.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Let vs not thinke</hi> (sayth he) <hi>that the Ghospel is in the wordes of Scripture but in the sense, not in the superficies, but in the marrow, not in the leaues of words, but in the roote of reason.</hi> Againe,<note n="(14)" place="margin">In c <hi>1.</hi> ad Gal. Ep. ad Nepot. &amp; in l. <hi>3.</hi> reg. c. <hi>1.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Then the Scripture is profitable to the hearers, when it is not expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded without Christ (that is to say, not contrary to the Rule of faith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered by Christ to his Church &amp;c.) otherwise the Diuel which allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Scriptures, and all heretickes (according to Ezechiel) of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures make Cushions which they may put vnder the elbow of men of all ages.</hi> Wherfore S. Austine aduiseth wel,<note n="(15)" place="margin">
            <hi>Ep.</hi> 221.</note>
         <hi>Loue exceedingly the vnderstanding, because the Scriptures themselues, except they be rightly vnderstood, cannot be profitable vnto thee.</hi> Tertullian telleth vs,<note n="(16)" place="margin">De Eraescript. c. <hi>17.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>That the sense of holy Scripture adulterated, doth impugne the truth, as much as the style corrupted.</hi> And answerably herun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Prot. themselues teach, that<note n="(17)" place="margin">Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds in his Confer. <hi>p.</hi> 68.</note>
         <hi>It is not the shew, but the sense of words</hi> (of Scripture) <hi>that must decyde controuersies.</hi> Now how this true sense is to be found without all Error and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, these few Sections next following will cleerly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="7" type="section">
      <pb n="12" facs="43"/>
      <head>
         <hi>SECT. VII.</hi> That the sacred Scriptures do admit seuerall true and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent senses, but not contrary, as wel Literall as Mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call: &amp; of the force of such Arguments as are taken from any of the forsaid senses.</head>
      <p>SAint Gregory<note n="(1)" place="margin">L. <hi>21.</hi> mor. c. <hi>1.</hi>
         </note> teacheth that, It is a thing proper to the sacred Scriptures, hauing God for their Author, to be of that fecundity, as to affoard seueral true senses, in one &amp; the same sentence, as the literall or historical, and the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual or mystical. The literal is that which the words of themselues do immediatly beare: the spiritual relateth to some thing else, then that which the words do immediatly signify. The literal againe is twofold, the one simple or plaine, which consisteth in the propriety of wordes: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther figuratiue, wherby the wordes are transferred from their natiue signification to another: and of this there be so many kinds, as there are seueral kinds of figures. The spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual sense also is deuided into Allegoricall, Tropologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and Anagogical. Now of these senses, the literall is found to be in euery Text both of the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament: And though the Spiritual be often to be had in both Testaments, yet not in euery sentence of both. So those wordes, Thou shalt loue thy Lord thy God with all thy hart, haue but one sense, and that is Literal. These things supposed, that which may seeme somwhat questionable, is, whether one Text of Scripture may admit seuerall true &amp; different Senses, either literal or spiritual? In which though I fynd<note n="(2)" place="margin">
            <hi>Fulk ag. Purg. pa.</hi> 151. Wil. in Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nop. <hi>p.</hi> 26.</note> D. Fulke and M. Willet to hold the Negatiue; yet S. Austine<note n="(3)" place="margin">L. <hi>12.</hi> Confess. c. <hi>20.</hi> &amp; <hi>23. 27. 31.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> de doct. Christ. c. <hi>27.</hi> l. <hi>11.</hi> de Ciu. Dei. c. <hi>19.</hi>
         </note> proueth by many examples, that in one sentence may often be found seueral true literall senses. And further sayth,<note n="(4)" place="margin">L. <hi>12.</hi> Confess. c. <hi>31.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>When one shal say, Moyses meant that which I do, and another, nay that which I do; I thinke I speake more religiously, why not rather both, if both be true? Or if any third or fourth, or any other truth any man shall see in these wordes; why may not he be thought to haue seene all those truthes, by whom God, to those that see
<pb n="13" facs="43"/> true and diuerse things, hath tempered the Scriptures with many senses?</hi> In another place he affirmeth, that such is the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures obscurity, that<note n="(5)" place="margin">De Ciu. Det. l. <hi>11.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>It bringeth forth diuers senses of truth &amp;c. whiles one vnderstandeth it after this manner, another after that.</hi>
         <note n="(6)" place="margin">L. <hi>12.</hi> Conf. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; de G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>n. ad lit. l. <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>21.</hi> de doct. Chr. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>36.</hi> de Ciu. Dei. l. <hi>15</hi> c. <hi>16,</hi> de vtil. cred. c. <hi>3.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Yea one text of Scripture may wel haue so many vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings, as may stand with truth, and be not repugnant to lyfe and good māners.</hi> And the like he teacheth in sundry other places. And indeed it is the general Doctrine of the Anciēt Fathers.</p>
      <p>A truth so euident that sundry Prot. writers do teach the same. <hi>Zanchius</hi> auoucheth that,<note n="(8)" place="margin">De Sacra Script. fol. <hi>421. 424. 425.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Besydes the literal Sense, the Allegorical sense is often needful: to which are reduced the Anago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical, and Tropological, or Moral sense; and that these are deliuered from the Holy Ghost:</hi>
         <note n="(7)" place="margin">Orig. in Gen. ho <hi>11.</hi> Greg. Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. l. <hi>20.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sost. ho <hi>21</hi> in Gen. Fulg. l. <hi>2.</hi> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ad Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim. c. <hi>14.</hi> Lyra. in Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel. c <hi>8.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>and are sometymes collected as pertayning to fayth or to manners, and according to the mynd of the Holy Ghost.</hi> The Translatour of the Bible into English published Anno 1576. speaking of the diuersity of Translations, sayth,<note n="(9)" place="margin">Ep. to the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of Engl. Scot. and Irel. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Seeing some Translations read after one sort, and some after another, wheras all may serue to good purpose and edification, we haue in the Margent noted that diuersity of speach or reading, which may also seeme agreable to the mynd of the Holy Ghost.</hi> Aretius thinketh,<note n="(10)" place="margin">Loc. com. loc. <hi>59.</hi> fol. <hi>187.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>As concerning the variable Exposition of Scripture, it is light which they</hi> (the Anabaptistes) <hi>do obiect: for they ought to consider that the Guiftes in the Church be diuerse, namly in Interpretation, wherin whiles the Rule of fayth and sincerity be obserued, there is no cause why the diuersity of opinions should hurt.</hi> And somewhat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he sayth,<note n="(11)" place="margin">Ibid. fol. <hi>177.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Concerning the variable interpretation</hi> (of the Scriptures) <hi>I affirme euery one to enioy their seueral Guift, and do somtymes profitably vary: And that so long as it is not erred from the scope of fayth, we ought not to be offended with the diuersity of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</hi> But to alleadge many witnesses in one, the Prot. of Geneua in their <hi>Principles of diuinity propounded and disputed by certaine Students there,</hi> vnder M. Theodore Beza, and M. Anthony Faius, and by them published, affirme and reach that,<note n="(12)" place="margin">
            <hi>L.</hi> 52. <hi>fol.</hi> 149.</note>
         <hi>The Scripture is so plentiful, that one and the selfesame place can admit d uers Interpretations, and yet all agreable with the Doctrine of fayth.</hi> So that both Scriptures, Fathers, and Prot. do all teach this Catholicke Doctrine, that the wordes and sentences of Scripture do contayne in them seuerall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="14" facs="44"/> Expositions and vnderstandings, and yet all true, and intended by the Holy Ghost.</p>
      <p>The next thing to be examined, is, which of these Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses do affoard a forcible Argument for the establishing any truth in matter of fayth and Religion. And first it cannot be denyed, that a firme Argument may be taken from any sense, litterall or mysticall, so long as it appeareth that Sense to be true and intended by the holy Ghost: But because it is most difficult to know and discerne when these mysticall &amp; spirituall senses are true, and so intended by the holy Ghost, therefore ordinarily speaking, arguments drawne from this Sense are weake, vncertayne, and not sufficient absolutely to determine a Point of fayth. And so it is generally taught by Diuines, that, <hi>Theologia Symbolica non est argumentatiua, symbolicall or mysticall Diuinity doth not yield a strong Argument:</hi> which truth they haue learned from S. Denis in his Epistle to Titus. And S. Austine demaundeth<note n="(13)" place="margin">
            <hi>Ep.</hi> 43.</note>
         <hi>who but mest im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently will endeauour to interprete by himselfe any thing that is Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legoricall, vnles he haue most manifest testimonies by whose light ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure things may be illustrated.</hi> And with him agreeth S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome teaching<note n="(14)" place="margin">In. c. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</hi> Mat.</note>
         <hi>That neuer can Parables and doubtfull vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings of riddles</hi> (or hard questions) <hi>profit to the Authority of Decrees.</hi> And the reason of this is, because the mysticall and spirituall Senses are many; and although they may edify, when they are not agaynst fayth or good manners, yet it doth not alwayes appeare, that they were intended by the holy Ghost: wherefore<note n="(15)" place="margin">Ep. <hi>48.</hi> ad Vincent.</note> S. Austine deseruedly derideth the Donatistes, who from these words mystically interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Shew me where thou feedest, where thou lyest in the noone day?</hi> did gather that the Church of Christ did only remayne in Affrick.</p>
      <p>Seeing then a good Argument cannot ordinarily be framed from the mysticall or spirituall Sense; Let vs now see what authority beareth the Litterall: In which, it is our generall doctrine, that seeing it is certayne, that Sense which is immediatly gathered from the wordes to be Sense of the holy Ghost, that therfore from the literal sense are we to take Arguments that will be efficacious: And so accordingly
<pb n="15" facs="44"/>
         <hi>Chemnitius</hi> concludeth, from seueral sayings of <hi>S. Irenaeus</hi>
         <note n="(16)" place="margin">
            <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 47.</note> that<note n="(17)" place="margin">Exam. part. <hi>1.</hi> fol. <hi>74. 48.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>That is the sound sense, and which is without danger, which plainely and without ambiguity is set downe in the Scripture in the same words.</hi> That then which is necessary to be knowne, is, how infailibly to find out the true Literall Sense frō whēce Arguments of force may be taken, &amp; truly to discerne when and wherein it differeth from the figuratiue.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="8" type="section">
      <head>
         <hi>SECT. VIII.</hi> Certaine Rules prescribed for the discerning of the simple Literall Sense from the figuratiue. And for the finding out of the true sense intended by the Holy Ghost.</head>
      <p>VVE find by dayly experience that often doubtes do arise cōcerning the very literall sense of Scripture: And this sometimes through the ambiguity of words, as where it is said, <hi>Drinke ye all of this;</hi> heeresome think it vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine whether the word, <hi>All,</hi> signifieth all men without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, or only all the faithfull, or only all the Apostles. Sometimes the doubtes arise through the propriety of words: for seeing the literall sense (as hath bene said) is som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times simple, and sometimes figuratiue, it is doubtfull in many places whether the true sense be proper and simple, or figuratiue. All Catholikes vnderstand these words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> simply and plainely, according to propriety of the words: Protestāts expound them figuratiuely. Through this difficulty some haue fallen into grieuous errors, as Origen, taking<note n="(1)" place="margin">Hier. ep. ad Pama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>h.</note> the words of Scripture figuratiuely, when they should haue bene taken simply. And on the contrary, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias,<note n="(2)" place="margin">Hier. Praefat. l <hi>18.</hi> in Isa. &amp;. in c. <hi>36.</hi> Ezech. Aug. l <hi>20.</hi> de Ciu Dei. c. <hi>7.</hi>
         </note> Tertullian, and others, by taking the words proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when they should haue bene taken figuratiuely.</p>
      <p>For the auoyding therfore of these extremes, S. Austine giueth vs this good Rule.<note n="(3)" place="margin">L. <hi>3</hi> de Doct. Christ. c. <hi>10.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Whatsoeuer can neither be referred to the honesty of manners, nor the truth of faith, that is to be taken fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiuely and Metaphorically.</hi> Againe,<note n="(4)" place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>b. c. <hi>6.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>If any speach of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be commanding as forbidding sinne, or commanding Beneficence, then it is to be taken properly: But if it should seeme to command
<pb n="16" facs="45"/> sinne, or forbid Beneficence, it is a figurative speach.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>The 2. Rule giuē by S. Austine is,<note n="(5)" place="margin">De vnit. Eccl c. <hi>16.</hi> &amp; cont. lit Pet. c. <hi>5.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>16.</hi>
         </note> that obscure &amp; doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full places may not be vrged against those which are more plaine, but are to be vnderstood &amp; expounded by them. This is so reasonable, that Chemnitius accepteth of it for good, saying;<note n="(6)" place="margin">Exam. part. 1. fol. <hi>48. 74.</hi> et. part. <hi>3.</hi> fol. <hi>49.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>We affirme that obscure places of Scripture are not to be expounded against that opinion which is expressed in plaine and euident places of Scripture.</hi> And he alledgeth S. Hierome to teach, that<note n="(7)" place="margin">Exam. part. <hi>3.</hi> fol. <hi>127.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>doctrine may not be gathered out of obscure, doubtfull, aenigmaticall, and allegoricall places of Scriptures.</hi> In regard where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that figuratiue layings afford no certaine proofe or Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in matters of faith, it is taught by most Protestants, as<note n="(8)" place="margin">Chem. Ex. part. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>127.</hi> Aret. loc com loc. <hi>51.</hi> p <hi>162.</hi> &amp; loc. <hi>81.</hi> p. <hi>261. Wil. in Syn.</hi> p. <hi>27.</hi> Oecol. l. ep. Oecol. &amp; Swingl. l. <hi>1</hi> p. <hi>223.</hi> Lub. de Princip. p. <hi>409. Down. of Antich.</hi> p. <hi>169.</hi>
         </note> Chemnitius, Aretius, M. Willet, Oecolampadius, Lub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus, and M. Downham, who affirmeth it to be <hi>a Rule in Diuinity, that, Theologia Symbolica non est argumentatiua.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>A third Rule is, that the wordes of Scripture are euer to be taken in their playne, proper, and litterall sense, and not to be changed into figures, vnles that Sense be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to other plainer places of Scripture, or make against some knowne Article of fayth, or be opposite to the common Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the whole Church, or inferre some absurdity. This is also acknowledged by Protestāts: for D. Bilson affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it to<note n="(9)" place="margin">In his true Differ. <hi>fol.</hi> 568.</note>
         <hi>Be rightly sayd, that, in the Scriptures so long as the letter may possibly be true, and not agaynst fayth and good manners, we may not fly to figures.</hi> Chemnitius thinketh that,<note n="(10)" place="margin">Era. part. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>71.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>when the Holy Ghost would haue any sentence in the Scriptures to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood otherwise then as the wordes do simply and properly signify, he plainly expresseth and sheweth so much, eyther in the same or some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place.</hi> M. Hooker<note n="(11)" place="margin">Eccl. Pol l. <hi>5.</hi> Ser. <hi>59.</hi> p. <hi>130.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>holdeth it for a most infallible Rule in Exposition of Scripture, that where a Litterall construction will stand, the furthest from the Letter is commonly the worst.</hi> And the very same is taught by<note n="(12)" place="margin">Against the Plea of the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. <hi>pa</hi> 194.</note> D. Couell. And this with great reason, for if those textes of Scripture which being literally taken, are not directly against any other playner Scripture or Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of faith, may be peruerted and turned into Tropes and figures, then as Melancthon well obserueth,<note n="(13)" place="margin">L. Ep. Oe col. &amp; Swingl. ep. ad Prider. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con p. <hi>645.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>All things may be peruerted:</hi> Yea faith it selfe will perish, and all diuine Mysteries depend only vpon opinion, and so the way laid
<pb n="17" facs="45"/> open to infinite errours.</p>
      <p>A fourth Rule approued by Catholikes &amp; Protestants is this: that, when the Scripture doth specially instruct vs in the Doctrine of the Holy Sacraments, in the institution or publishing of Gods peculiar Commandements, or in any principall Article of faith, then that sense is to be holden good, for proofe of which the words are most plaine and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall. But for the right vnderstanding of this, it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, that although our Sauiour in his ordinary Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or preaching to the people, which did imply a Cōman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, did sometimes to stirre them vp to greater attētion, remember them in figuratiue words of some generall duty or Commandment, not then first prescribed, but formerly knowne and commanded; yet the first promulgation of euery peculiar Commandement is euer deliuered in words plaine, not figuratiue or obscure. And as touching doctrines, it is not meant hereby, that euery sentence or opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God is euer to be vnderstood according to the literall words, but onely that such as comprehend in them a speciall difficulty or necessity for vs to beleiue, or practise; such as are the Articles of our faith, which are set downe and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered in plaine words, and so to be vnderstood. Wherefore such examples of God being a <hi>Consuming fire,</hi> of Christ being a <hi>stone, a lyon, a vyne, a doore,</hi> and the like, are of another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not importing any principle or Article of faith or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
      <p>Againe, in the secluding of Tropes and figures, it is not intended that euery figuratiue locution should be secluded, but onely such as is obscure and darke, for there be some which are in themselues no lesse easie and manifest then the other: As for example to say, <hi>The Cup is shed,</hi> Euery one knoweth (as Beza<note n="(14)" place="margin">In Mat. <hi>26.28.</hi>
         </note> cōfesseth) that thereby is meāt not the Cup it selfe, but the thing contayned in the Cup. And this, and such like are sometimes vsuall, but yet their sense is knowne and manifest.</p>
      <p>This Rule thus vnderstood, is acknowledged by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants to be good: so Vrsinus prescribeth that,<note n="(15)" place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Catech. fol. <hi>416.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Articles of faith ought to be vnderstood properly, vnles some Article so taken proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="18" facs="46"/> do disagree with other places of Scripture.</hi> Whitaker teacheth that,<note n="(16)" place="margin">De Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra Script. fol. <hi>391 395.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Although in the words</hi> (of Scriptures) <hi>many things be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure, and in many places, yet all Articles of faith are manifest.</hi> Chē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius affirmeth that,<note n="(17)" place="margin">Ex. part. <hi>1.</hi> fol. <hi>48.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>The Scripture when it deliuereth do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or Commandements, to be certaine, &amp; nothing obscure.</hi> Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton discoursing of this matter cōfesseth that,<note n="(18)" place="margin">L. de ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Corp. &amp; sing Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, <hi>and see</hi> L. Epist. Oecol. &amp; Swingl. fol. <hi>132. 140. And Confess. Aug. tract. de Euchar.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Although the phrase of Scripture be full of figures in narratiō of things done, yet</hi> saith he, <hi>If in the Commandements or Doctrines which containe the nature or will of God, we goe about to doe the like, what shall f, ollow, learned men may easily iudge.</hi> Whereupon he concludeth that in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of faith, the Scriptures ought to be taken properly, as the words do vsually signifie, vnles therby, <hi>An absurdity doe light vpon other plainer places of Scripture:</hi> Which if it doe, then, saith he, <hi>It is to be redressed by the benefite of figures: But if the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdity light only vpon reason, and not vpon the Scripture,</hi> then, as he teacheth, <hi>must the word of God be preferred before the Iudgment of reason.</hi> And he further auoucheth that <hi>It is needfull that the meaning of those places be certaine, from whence Doctrine, or Articles</hi> (of faith) <hi>be taken:</hi> otherwise saith he, <hi>when the rite of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision was instituted, it had bene lawfull for Abraham to haue ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined some other thing then that which the words signifie:</hi> And, <hi>a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile man might haue disputed, a thing</hi> (seeming) <hi>so ridiculous, to be in no sort commanded of God: But</hi> (thereby only) <hi>to be signified, that lusts were to be restrained and bridled.</hi> Thus fully Philip Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon. Lastly Carion thinketh it needfull,<note n="(19)" place="margin">Chron. p. <hi>237.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>that in the Articles of faith, in themorall law, and in the Promise of Grace, that we be restrayned with the natiue signification of the words.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And as this Rule standeth good for the vnderstanding of such Scriptures as instruct vs in the Institution of Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and Commandementes, and in the necessary Article of fayth: So also may it serue for the fynding out of the true sense of any other Text, in which the vsuall and Literal sense is euer true; if so the said sense make not against some other plainer places of Scripture, or be contrary to some Article of fayth, or opposite to the general vnderstanding of the Church, or therwith it inferre some grosse and plaine absurdity. These Rules prescribed and approued both by Catholickes and Prot. if they likewise be obserued in the
<pb n="19" facs="46"/> Exposition of the Scriptures, they wil certainly discouer the literal sense from the figuratiue, and therby preuent Prot. of their frequent flying to figures, when they are conuinced by the Letter.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="9" type="section">
      <head>
         <hi>SECT. IX.</hi> An Examination of such Rules as Prot. ordinarily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe, and obserue for fynding out of the true Sense of the sacred Scriptures.</head>
      <p>THe first Rule that I fynd to be vsed and taught by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Sectaries, for the fynding out of the true Sense &amp; meaning of the Scriptures, is the Scripture it selfe.<note n="(1)" place="margin">
            <hi>Harm.</hi> of Conf <hi>p.</hi> 5.</note>
         <hi>The Interpretation wherof</hi> (say they) <hi>is to be taken only from herselfe, that herselfe may be the Interpreter of herselfe &amp;c.</hi> And,<note n="(2)" place="margin">Ib. p. <hi>3.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>We ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that Interpretation of Scriptures for authentical and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which being taken from the Scriptures themselues &amp;c. accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with the Rule of faith &amp; Charity. Yea</hi>
         <note n="(3)" place="margin">Ib. p. <hi>14.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>the true meaning of the Scripture is to be sought in the Scripture it selfe, and among those, that being raysed vp by the Spirit of God, expound Scripture by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>This Rule to be most imperfect and false, I proue at large<note n="(4)" place="margin">See hereafter.</note> heerafter; for the present, M. Hooker shall confute it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouching that,<note n="(5)" place="margin">Eccl. Pol, l. <hi>2.</hi> pa. <hi>116.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>The Scripture could not teach vs the things that are of God, vnles we did credit mē, who haue taught vs, that the words of Scripture doe signifie these things.</hi> And seeing, as D. Whitakers cōfesseth<note n="(6)" place="margin">De sacra Script. pag. <hi>521.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>the Scripture hath no liuely voyce which we may heare,</hi> but is a thing without all life: It is impossible to imagine that her selfe alone can make knowne to her Readers, the true vnderstanding of so many and so difficult passages as are contayned in her.</p>
      <p>Others perceyuing the insufficiency of this, doe giue for their Rule, not the Scripture it selfe sole, and alone, but as<note n="(7)" place="margin">Whitak. de Eccles. Contr. <hi>2</hi> q. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>221.</hi> &amp; de script. pag. <hi>521.</hi>
         </note> it is diligently read, conferred one place with another, the Circumstances weighed, and much prayer vsed. But these studies and Conferences are but humane endeauours, and such wherein euery man, without extraordinary Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge from God, is subiect to error, ouersight, and mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity,
<pb n="20" facs="47"/> all his prayer and possible diligence notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: and therefore cannot make and infallible Rule, as shalbe further sundry waies euicted, in this<note n="(8)" place="margin">See hereafter.</note> Treatise following. Onely I will now obserue what D. Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, who prescrybed the foresaid Rule, as the best meanes of Interpretation, thinketh of it himselfe.<note n="(9)" place="margin">De Eccl. Controu. <hi>2.</hi> q. <hi>4</hi> p. <hi>221.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Such as the meanes are</hi> (saith he) <hi>such of necessitie must be the Interpretation: but the meanes of interpreting darke places, are vncertaine, doubtfull, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous, therefore it cannot be but that the Interpretation also must be vncertaine, but if vncertaine, then it may be false &amp;c.</hi> So confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedly false is the foresaid Rule.</p>
      <p>The last Rule then, which indeed they chiefly rely vpon, is the interpretation made by the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> and giuen as they imagine, to euery Priuate man. So D. Whitaker af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth euen of such as are <hi>ignorant in tongues,</hi> that,<note n="(10)" place="margin">De sacra Script. p. <hi>127.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>They acknowledge and allow the Doctrine, being instructed by the Holy Ghost.</hi> But Lubbertus saith more plainely that,<note n="(11)" place="margin">De Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipijs &amp;c. p. <hi>573.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>God hath giuen to euery faithfull person, not only the Spirit of vnderstanding, but also of discerning false Dostrine from true.</hi> Yea say Brentius &amp; D. Whyte,<note n="(12)" place="margin">
            <hi>Brent. Prolog. Cont. Petr. Sot.</hi> Whit. in the way to the Church. <hi>pa.</hi> 6. 27.</note>
         <hi>As the priuate man hath priuate Authority of Iudging and decyding Doctrine of Religion, so the Prince hath Publike.</hi> But though it be most true, that the Scriptures are to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood by the same spirit by which they were written, and giuen vnto vs, to wit, the Holy Ghost, and that by the Holy Ghost the Guift of Interpretation is sometimes giuen to particular men: yet that neither the said guift is giuen to euery one of the faithfull, nor they to whom it is giuē, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out speciall Reuelation, can infallibly be assured thereof; &amp; much lesse can it giue any assurance to others of the right expounding of Scripture or decyding any Controuersie, as I shal at large declare herafter<note n="(13)" place="margin">See hereafter.</note>. In the meane time, it is not vnworthy of obseruation, that Protestants appointing these Rules for the finding out of the true sense of Scripture, doe thereby intend no other, but to make themselues, euen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Priuate man, to be absolute Iudge and Interpreter of the sense of the Scripture: and so to exempt themselues from all other Interpretations, though made by Auncient Fathers, Generall Councels, and the vniuersall Church.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="10" type="section">
      <pb n="21" facs="47"/>
      <head>
         <hi>SECT. X.</hi> That the certaine and Infallible Rule, for the fynding out of the true Sense of the Scriptures, is the Church of Christ.</head>
      <p>ALthough Prot. ordinarily professe that they<note n="(14)" place="margin">Harm. of Confess. <hi>p.</hi> 3.</note>
         <hi>Do not acknowledge that, which they call the meaning of the Church of Rome, for the true and natural Interpretation of the Scriptures:</hi> Yet the Church of Christ in General Councel hath Decreed that,<note n="(15)" place="margin">Conc. Trid. Sess. <hi>4.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>No man dare to Interprete the sacred Scripture contrary to that Sense, which the Holy Mother the Church hath and doth hold, to whom it belongeth to Iudge of the true Sense and Interpretation of holy Scriptures.</hi> And this with greatest reason, for if the Church hath power from Christ to discerne the word of God from the wordes of men as shalbe cleerly proued<note n="(16)" place="margin">See hereafter.</note> hereafter, doubtles she hath the like power of discerning in the words the sense and meaning of God, from the sense and vnderstanding of men, both these being committed to the Church, that the may faithfully preserue them, and giue them to others, to wit, the true Scriptures and true vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing therof. This God promised to his Church by the Prophet Esay in these wordes,<note n="(17)" place="margin">
            <hi>Isa.</hi> 59.21.</note>
         <hi>My spirit that is in thee, and my words that I haue put in thy mouth, shall not depart out of thy mouth, and out of the mouth of thy seed, and out of the mouth of thy seeds seed, sayth our Lord, from this present and for euer.</hi> Which is also confirmed by Christ our Sauiour promising<note n="(18)" place="margin">
            <hi>Io.</hi> 14.16.17.</note>
         <hi>The spirit of truth, which should abyde for euer, and should</hi>
         <note n="(19)" place="margin">
            <hi>Io.</hi> 16.13.</note>
         <hi>teach all truth</hi> And indeed seeing the true Ghospel of God, doth not consist in the writings or words, but in the sense; if the Church had only the written word, and not the true sense therof, she had not the true Ghospel of God, and so neither faith in Christ which is had by the true Ghospel; Fayth ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing relation not to the words but to the sense. Wherefore H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>retickes and Deuils though they can alledge Scriptures, yet not hauing the true sense, they haue not a true, but a false &amp; Diabolical Ghospel.</p>
      <pb n="22" facs="48"/>
      <p>Besydes <hi>Christ opened</hi>
         <note n="(20)" place="margin">
            <hi>Luc.</hi> 14.45.</note> (the Apostles) <hi>vnderstanding, that they might vnderstand the Scriptures,</hi> which certainly he did not for them alone, but much more for his Church: and so ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the Apostles deliuered to the Church the true sense of them: for if they had deliuered the wordes and not the sense, they had not preached the Ghospel, nor taught all Nations to keep all things that were cōmanded to them by Christ. What preaching or doctrine would that be, which were deliuered without the meaning? certainly no other then of Children, or Parrots who can giue the sound of wordes without the sense.</p>
      <p>Lastly, seeing the Church is <hi>the Pillar and ground of truth;</hi> and truth properly and truly is in the vnderstanding of the Scriptures, not in the writings or words, but improperly &amp; as in a signe; it euidently followeth, that she hath a certaine knowledge of the truths which are contayned in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
      <p>This truth is so certaine, that S. Austine for the true vnderstanding of the Scriptures, directeth all men to the Church, saying,<note n="(21)" place="margin">L. <hi>1.</hi> Cont. Cres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. c. <hi>33.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>The truth of Scriptures is holden by vs, when we doe that which now hath pleased the vniuersall Church, which the authority of the same Scriptures doth commend, that seeing the holy Scripture cannot deceyue, whosoeuer feareth to be deceiued by the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scurity of this question, let him take Coūsaile therof from the Church, which without any ambiguity the holy Scripture doth demōstrate.</hi> But to omit sundry other Fathers very cleare for thh purpose, many of the learnedst Protestants teach the same Doctrine, as I shall<note n="(22)" place="margin">See hereafter.</note> shew hereafter: onely for the present, heare what D. Whitaker saith to Dureus his Catholike Aduersary,<note n="(23)" place="margin">Cont. Dur. l. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>134.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>Thou dost affirme that to be the sense of the word, which the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church hath receiued frō the Holy Ghost; I confesse so much for the Church is taught the true sense of Scripture from the Holy Ghost: she is the keeper of faith, the ground and Pillar of truth.</hi> So confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and cleare it is that the true and vndoubted sense and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Scriptures, is to be learned from the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church. Wherefore all Catholiks in their Disputes, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and Comments vpon the Scripture, doe euer place this as a sure ground and vndeniable Principle, that the true
<pb n="23" facs="48"/> and sincere sense of the Scriptures, is to be taken from the Interpretation of the Catholike Church.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="11" type="section">
      <head>
         <hi>SECT. XI.</hi> An explication of what we meane by the Church, when we say, that the true vnderstanding of the Scripture, and the finall Decision of all Controuersies in Religion, is to be taken from the Church.</head>
      <p>FIrst then<note n="(1)" place="margin">Canus loc. com. l. <hi>12.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> et. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> Bellar de Concil. l <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> Et de verb. Dei. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Rhem. Test. in Mat. <hi>18.</hi>
         </note> Catholikes do heere vnderstand by the Church, the supreme Pastour thereof with a Councell of other Bishops, Pastours and Doctours. In so much that whatsoeuer by these in matters of fayth and manners is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, and proposed to the whole Church to be belieued, that we all firmly belieue to be most true and infallible, &amp; wholy agreeing with the true sense of Gods word inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Holy Ghost.</p>
      <p>Secondly, we<note n="(2)" place="margin">Val. <hi>T. 3.</hi> Disp. <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> Punct. <hi>7.</hi> §. <hi>44.</hi> Bellar. de verb. Dei l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> &amp;c. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus loc. com. l. <hi>12.</hi> ca. <hi>6.</hi>
         </note> vnderstand by the Doctrine of the Church, such Points of Faith also, as not being written in the Scriptures, haue bene deliuered by the Apostles by word of mouth, the Holy Ghost inspiring them, or Christ being the Author of them: And these we belieue to haue as infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble authority of truth, as if they had bene written in the Scriptures.</p>
      <p>Thirdly<note n="(3)" place="margin">Staplet. de Princip. l. <hi>11.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
         </note> we likewise teach, that the vniuersall &amp; Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall practise of the Catholike Church, is a sure and Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Interpreter of the Scriptures. In so much that if any Question shall arise concerning any difficult place of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, the general obseruation and Practise of the Church concerning the matter treated in that place is to be inquired, and to be held and followed, as the best Interpretation, and a truth Infallible.</p>
      <p>Fourthly, Protestants<note n="(4)" place="margin">Iewel in his Sermon at Paules Crosse. Fulk in his Ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were to a Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faite Catho. <hi>p.</hi> 27. 33. 36. <hi>Whitak. cont. Camp. Rat.</hi>
         </note> themselues confesse, that the Church during the first 600. yeares after Christ, was pure, sincere, and truly Catholicke; to the holy Fathers then of those times we appeale, firmly belieuing<note n="(5)" place="margin">Staplet. de Princip l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
         </note> that what they with vnanimous cōsent did teach, or the greatest part of thē,
<pb n="24" facs="49"/> without contradiction of others, cōcerning pointes of faith, or what vnanimous Interpretation of Scripture they made concerning Articles of faith, that the same is by vs receiued and beleiued, as the true meaning of the holy Ghost, and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of faith.</p>
      <p>Lastly, the Church of Christ hath florished and shyned in all Ages, with true and vndoubted Miracles, which being Truth, cannot giue Testimony to a falshood; these also are sure and infallible proofes of all such Doctrine, in Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation whereof they are done.</p>
      <p>These are the Principles and firme grounds vpon which the Catholike Church doth build her faith and Religion: which I doe not heare goe about to confirme, with many such Arguments as might be easily produced in proofe of them, because the same wilbe done at large vpon seuerall occasions in this Treatise following, to which therefore in this respect I referre the Reader.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>