<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ARGVMENT.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100090_Fr3_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16527</idno>
           <idno type="STC">344</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100090</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ARGVMENT.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The monarchicke tragedies : Crosus, Darius, The Alexandræan, Iulius Cæsar. Newly enlarged by William Alexander, Gentleman of the Princes priuie chamber</title>
                 <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>406 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="52"/>
   <head>THE ARGVMENT.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>ARIVS,</hi> the fourteenth from <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Persia,</hi> being after the death of <hi>Occhus</hi> for his singular valour from the gouernment of <hi>Armenia</hi> aavanc'd to the <hi>Persian</hi> empyre, became so arrogant (Fortune, as it were, setting him forward to confusion) as he sent to demand tribute of <hi>Phillip,</hi> then King of <hi>Macedonia:</hi> who being of a hautie nature, and inferiour to none of that age in courage, or mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie discipline, requited this contumelius message with as disdainfull an answere; threatning that he would come and deliuer it in <hi>Persepolis.</hi> But being preuented by death he left the execution of his designe to his sonne <hi>Alexander,</hi> who for the great victories which thereafter he obtained was sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the great. He inheriting the hatred of his Father to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Darius,</hi> and far surmounting him in ambition, past in person to <hi>Asia</hi> with an armie of thirtie thousand only.</p>
   <p>After his arriuall, <hi>Darius</hi> wrote to him in a proud and contemptible manner, ascribing to himselfe the title of the King of Kings, and kinsman of the Gods, and naming <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> his seruant. Hee also in vaunting manner boasted that he would haue that mad boy, the sonne <hi>Philip</hi> (for so in derision he tearmed him) bound, and beaten with rods, and after brought to his presence apparrelled like a Prince. For performance whereof he directed one of his Minions with fourtie thousand, to make impediment to his passage at the riuer of <hi>Granick;</hi> where by the wonderfull valour of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi>
      <pb facs="53"/>they were ouer-throwne. <hi>Darius</hi> being aduertised of this, came himselfe in proper person, accompanied with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, (but euill ordered) nomhers; and encountred <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> beside <hi>Isso,</hi> in the straites of <hi>Cilicia:</hi> where hauing fought a doubtfull and bloody battell, in ende by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible valour, and neuer-fayling Fortune of <hi>Alexander</hi> his armie was defeated, himselfe put to flight, and his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wife, and children made captiues. They were most cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouslie entertained by <hi>Alexander:</hi> who notwithstanding their exceeding great beautie yet would not abuse them, or suffer them to be abused by others: nor visited he them more oft then once (and that to comfort them) all the time of their imprisonment.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Darius,</hi> notwithstanding of all his losses (his courage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the full, whilst his Fortune was in the waine) wrote very proudly to <hi>Alexander,</hi> taking still the title of a King to himselfe, but not giuing it him, offering him as much gold, as <hi>Macedon</hi> could containe, for ransome of the Captiues. Which being very disdainfully refused by <hi>Alexander,</hi> he hauing re-enforced his troupes, &amp; comming forwarder to fight with greater force then before, was enformed how his wife had died in prison, whose death he bewaild with excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great sorrowe. And vnderstanding what courtesie <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> had vsed towards her, he sent to sue for peace, not for any feare of his force, but allured (as he alledged) by his courtesie. This sute being likewise reiected, he fought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side <hi>Arbella</hi> with no better Fortune then before. Yet for all these misfortunes being of an inuincible courage, and dispay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of peace, he re-assembled all his forces, which were aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the comming of the <hi>Bactrians,</hi> &amp; was comming forward with intention at last either to die, or preuaile. But
<pb facs="53"/>in the meane time two traiterous subiects of his owne, to wit, <hi>Bessus</hi> whom he had promoted to be gouernour of <hi>Bactria,</hi> &amp; <hi>Nabarzanes</hi> one in speciall credite with him, conspired his death. VVhich danger, though it was reuealed to him by <hi>Patron,</hi> Captaine of the Greekes, yet he could not, or rather would not eschue. At length, those two traitours tooke and bound him with golden chaines, and cast him in an olde Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, with purpose to present him to <hi>Alexander.</hi> But they hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how he would not accept their present, and how he was comming to inuade them, threw their darts at <hi>Darius,</hi> and left him for dead. In this estate he was found by <hi>Polistratus,</hi> and after the deliuery of some fewe words dyed. <hi>Alexander</hi> hauing exceedinglie lamented his miserable and vndeserued end, directed his bodie to his mother <hi>Sisigambis</hi> to be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably buried.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>