<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Introduction taken out of this our Fathers booke of Para∣dise, and third chapter. What succours the soule, which is figured by Paradise, hath in suffering of dangers; For by the fountaine there, divided into foure rivers, the foure Cardinall vertues are ex∣pressed.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100171_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19065</idno>
           <idno type="STC">548</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100171</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Introduction taken out of this our Fathers booke of Para∣dise, and third chapter. What succours the soule, which is figured by Paradise, hath in suffering of dangers; For by the fountaine there, divided into foure rivers, the foure Cardinall vertues are ex∣pressed.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christian offices crystall glasse : In three bookes. First written in Latine, by that famous and renowned Father, Saint Ambrose Bishop of Millane. Whereunto is added his conuiction of Symmachus the Gentile. A worke tending to the advancement of vertue, and of holinesse: and to shew how much the morality of the Gentiles, is exceeded by the doctrine of Christianity. Translated into English by Richard Humfrey</title>
                 <author>Ambrose, Saint, Bishop of Milan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Greene, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dawson, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>66, 126, 2, 127-142, 10, 75, 9, 64, 38, 20, 41, 1 page, folded table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="31"/>
   <head>An Introduction taken out of this our Fathers booke of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise, and third chapter. What succours the soule, which is figured by Paradise, hath in suffering of dangers; For by the fountaine there, divided into foure rivers, the foure Cardinall vertues are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aradise is a certaine fertile ground, that is, a fruitfull soule planted in <hi>Eden,</hi> that is, in a certaine pleasant place for exercise and recreation, in which the soule taketh her solace and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. Also <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> which is the mind, is as <hi>Adam,</hi> the sense likewise is as <hi>Evah.</hi> And lest thou mightest have something to object against the infirmity of nature, or against her misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition, as too too obnoxious to the dint of dangers, consider what succours this soule hath to susteine and support her in this her estate. There was a Fountaine which did water Paradise: what Fountaine was it, but the Lord Iesus, the Fountaine of eternall life, like as is the Father? Because it is written
<pb facs="32"/>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Psal. 6.9.</note>
      <hi>with thee is the fountaine of life;</hi> and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 7.38.</note>
      <hi>out of his belly shall flow even rivers of water of life.</hi> Both the Fountaine is red,<note n="*" place="margin">Legitur.</note> and the River is red, which watereth the fruitfull wood of Paradise bringing forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease to eternall life. This<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 2.10.11.12.</note> fountaine is divided into foure heads, <hi>Pishon, Tigris, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates.</hi> But as the wisdome of God is called in the Gospell the fountaine of life, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of<note n="d" place="margin">John 7.37.38.</note> spirituall grace, <hi>if any man thirst let him come unto mee, and drinke;</hi> and in the Prophet<note n="e" place="margin">Prov. 5.15. &amp; 9.5.</note>
      <hi>come eate of the bread, and drinke of the wine that I have drawne:</hi> so is it the fountaine of all vertues, which direct our course to everlasting life, the chiefe whereof, and upon the which the rest depend, are pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, temperance, fortitude, and justice. The Lord is as the fountaine comming out of <hi>Eden,</hi> the soule as Paradise; as those foure Rivers watering the same. <hi>Pishon</hi> is Wisdome, and therefore it hath good gold, shining Carbuncle, greene<note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>Praefertur gemmis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridantibus. Chrysopra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, porri succum &amp; ipsa referens Plin.</hi> 37. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Vnde color prasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus:</hi> A leeke greene colour: the stone is such <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, rare, and pretious Rev. 21.20. Exo. 28.18. <hi>Hebr. Nophec Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro. in Es.</hi> 45.12. <hi>relegat ad Epiph.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Prasius,</hi> pretious Pearle, the Onix stone; for wee oftentimes take<note n="g" place="margin">Zach. 6.11. &amp; 4.2. &amp; 13.9. Rev. 1.12. Ps. 45.9.</note> gold for wise inventions, hence the Lord by the<note n="h" place="margin">Dani. 11.43. Zach. 14.14. Ezech 21.26. <hi>Platoes</hi> golden and silver wits, &amp;c. Like as <hi>Es.</hi> 3.1. by bread meant the prudent, and so by crowne of glory and diademe of beauty, <hi>Es</hi> 28.5. consisting of gold, the same as the consequent words make evident, <hi>v.</hi> 6.</note> Prophet; <hi>I have given them gold and silver;</hi> and<note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 68.13.</note>
      <hi>David</hi> of the wise, <hi>though yee have lien among the pots, yet shall yee bee as the wings of a Dove that is covered with sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and whose feathers are like yellow gold.</hi>
      <pb facs="32"/> It hath the Carbuncle, for prudence is as bright sparkles kindling the light of the soule, and therefore as the orient Onix, and the pretious Pearle; for what more pretious then Wisdome, and what more greene and flourishing then it? and like to the <hi>Prasius</hi> jasper or<note n="k" place="margin">Smaragdus.</note> Emeraud. According to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes</hi> it is called <hi>feoison,</hi> that is a chaining of the mouth flowing about <hi>Lydia,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther countries, yea all countries for prudence is not streight and narrow, but large, and rich of commodities. This<note n="l" place="margin">
         <hi>Pishon</hi> the same which <hi>Pasis,</hi> and <hi>Pasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigris,</hi> the chanell of <hi>Euphrates</hi> called <hi>Basi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> this falling into the red sea was a neighbour to the Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites.</note> river is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented of many, as appeareth most of all in Christs comming, his well-head flowing in. Therefore it is the prime, and first of the foure. The second is<note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Nilus.</hi> Rameses a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Goshen,</hi> fit for pasture bordered upon it. From thence the Israelites departed out of Egypt, and then when they were about the celebrating of the Passeover and so pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed forth with their loynes girded, <hi>Exodus</hi> 12.1.11.37.</note>
      <hi>Gihon,</hi> by which the commandement was given to the children of Israel, when they were in <hi>Egypt:</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part with their loynes girded, which betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth temperance. It signifieth a gaping of the earth. As the earth therefore gaping swalloweth up whatsoever ordure, and off-scowring: so doth temperance abolish what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever inordinate lusts of the body. It com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passeth about the whole land of<note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Ab</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>cremo, &amp;</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> of a burnt countenance, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>stultus, Maurus, &amp; Mauritaria à</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>quod est nigrum. Hebr. Chus</hi> as <hi>Cusi</hi> 2 Sam. 18.21. black. <hi>Saul</hi> so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the title of <hi>Psal.</hi> 7. because hee changed not his heart from the hatred of <hi>David,</hi> but remained as unchangeable therein, as the skinne of the <hi>Aethiopian.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> which is by interpretation vile. What so like <hi>Ethiopia</hi> blacke with the blacknesse of sinne? The third is<note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Tigris</hi> is a Persian word signifying <hi>swift,</hi> and is called also <hi>Tiglah,</hi> sharpe or straight <hi>Iosephus</hi> In the fountaine <hi>Plinie</hi> affirmeth it to be termed <hi>Diglito, Hidelito,</hi> and meeting after it hath made many chanels <hi>Pasitigris</hi> or <hi>Pisitigris. Munster</hi> fetcheth <hi>Hiddekel</hi> from the roote <hi>Hadal,</hi> signifying sometimes not <hi>desijt,</hi> but <hi>deseruit,</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Tigris,</hi> which goeth opposite
<pb facs="33"/> to <hi>Ashur,</hi> where prevaricating <hi>Israel</hi> was held under captivitie. This is the swiftest of all. The<note n="p" place="margin">Ashur <hi>of Ashri</hi> Hebr. beatus.</note> Assyrians by interpretation, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors inhabite upon it. He which directing his course to higher projects, and by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his mind captivating his vices, hee is in estimation as this river. Fortitude by his strong, and swift course repulseth and beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth backe the obstacles, neither can any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions debarre his passage. For courage will goe through with her worke, and scornes whatsoever confronting encounter. The fourth is <hi>Euphrates,</hi> which in <hi>English</hi> is fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundity, and abundance of fruites, carrying before it a certaine flagge, or ensigne of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice feeding with comfortable hope every soule. For no vertue doth flow with more plenty, and store of all good fruites then doth justice and equity. For it seeketh to profit others above it selfe, and neglecting her owne in private, preferreth the publike, and common emolument and good. The most deeme <hi>Euphrates</hi> to be deduced <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, that is to say<note n="q" place="margin">Perath Hebr. <hi>which is</hi> Euphrates, <hi>seemeth to come from</hi> parash ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pandere, &amp; pison <hi>from</hi> pasah crescere.</note> rejoycing, because man-kind rejoyceth in nothing more then in justice and equity. But the cause why the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, and passages of the other rivers are described, and not of this, is according to the received opinion, for that the water hereof is affirmed to bee vitall, and is of a fostering and augmenting nature. Whence the Sages of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> and <hi>Assyrians</hi> have termed
<pb facs="33"/> it <hi>Auxe:</hi> It runnes in a contrary course, and is the confluence of other waters; For where prudence is, there is malice; where fortitude there is anger; where temperance, there is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance, for the most part, or other vices: but where is justice, there is a confluence of the sweet land and fresh waters, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordancy of all the rest of the vertues stript of all their repugnant vices. In respect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the way of her journey, and chanell shee is unknowne; for justice is no piece of any other vertues, but is compleate of her selfe, and the mother of them all.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>