<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Letter written by King Aben∣cirix to the Alcayde Ali Abenzufian Viceroy and Gouernour of the Pro∣uinces of Deuque in Arabia, by which he commandeth him to write the life of King Iacob Almansor.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100094_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16632</idno>
           <idno type="STC">354</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100094</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Letter written by King Aben∣cirix to the Alcayde Ali Abenzufian Viceroy and Gouernour of the Pro∣uinces of Deuque in Arabia, by which he commandeth him to write the life of King Iacob Almansor.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Almansor : the learned and victorious king that conquered Spaine. His life and death published by Robert Ashley, out of the librarie of the Uniuersitie of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Luna, Miguel de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Parker, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 79, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Letter written by King <hi>Aben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cirix</hi> to the <hi>Alcayde Ali Abenzufian</hi> Viceroy and Gouernour of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces of <hi>Deuque</hi> in <hi>Arabia,</hi> by which he commandeth him to write the life of King <hi>Iacob Almansor.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>PRayse bee giuen to God alone, <hi>Amen.</hi> The high and highly honoured King Gouernour of the Moores, of noble dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, defender of Mahometisme, who shiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himselfe vnder the protection of the most high God, <hi>Ali Abencirix:</hi> To the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, Noble, Wise, Discreet, Learned, and Generous Gentleman the <hi>Alcayde Ali Aben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zufian</hi> our Vice-roy and Gouernour of the Prouinces of <hi>Deuque:</hi> wee send greeting. And after our salutation, wee say that consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the great wisedome with which the King <hi>Abilgualit Miramamolin Iacob Almansor,</hi> our great Grandfather and Lord gouerned his Kingdomes in peace; and the fortitude with which hee preserued his Subiects, and rooted out their Enemies; and the Iustice with which he conserued his Estates; and the
<pb facs="7"/>Temperance, vsed by him in all his actions and deeds, which of all the World are admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and all the Bookes replenished with his Sayings and Sentences in all Sciences; and his notable Deeds of Armes, with his great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and good customes to bee such as all the Princes of the World may take an example and patterne thereby to rule and gouerne their Common-weales, and to liue in tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie. We haue thought meete and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient that the Discourse of his Life should be gathered together, and orderly compiled and written in one Booke, (and not be left as it is now scattered in many parts:) as well for our owne consolation, as for the Imitation of this great King in his customes and manner of liuing: to make our profit and vse of them in matters that concerne our Gouernment and our Common-weales; and to this effect hauing that regard which wee haue of your person, abilitie, and learning, together with your trayning and continuall attendance and seruice in his Royall Palace from your child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, being alwayes inward with him, in such sort that no other how learned soeuer can better set forth and write his life and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb facs="7"/>then you. Wee charge and command you that with conuenient breuitie auoyding prolixitie, and writing the Truth with that obligation which is due to the fidelitie of an Historie: (whereof by reason of your good zeale and punctuall manner of writing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued by you, we rest assured) you write a Booke of his life and customes, together with the manner and order how this good King ruled and gouerned his Kingdomes till his life ended by death: which you shall entitle the bright Mirrour of Princes; whereby you shall doe vs acceptable seruice. In this Booke you shall also doe well to set downe what especiall things a good King is to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue, to make himselfe beloued of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and feared of his enemies. All which may serue vs in steed of a Guide or a Light with the fauour and helpe of our Souereigne God for the ruling and gouerning of our Kingdomes and Common-weales, that they may enioy Peace and tranquillitie; and our selues quietnesse of minde and clearnesse of Conscience. Whereof through that confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence we haue in your worthinesse we make no doubt. God haue you in his keeping.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From our Royall Palace of <hi>Zarbal;</hi>
         <date>the fourth day of the Moone of <hi>Mobarram,</hi>
            <note place="margin">The date is answerable to the yeare <hi>An. Christi</hi> 731.</note>
            <hi>the hundred and tenth yeare of the Hixera.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>