<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The argument of the whole worke, and the reasons why Lodouico Ariosto writ these Seauen Satyres.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100232_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21074</idno>
           <idno type="STC">744</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100232</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The argument of the whole worke, and the reasons why Lodouico Ariosto writ these Seauen Satyres.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ariosto's satyres : in seuen famous discourses, shewing the state, 1 Of the Court, and courtiers. 2 Of libertie, and the clergie in generall. 3 Of the Romane clergie. 4 Of marriage. 5 Of soldiers, musitians, and louers. 6 Of schoolmasters and scholers. 7 Of honour, and the happiest life. In English, by Garuis Markham</title>
                 <author>Arisoto, Lodovico</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 108 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The argument of the whole worke, and the reasons why <hi>Lodouico Ariosto</hi> writ these Seauen Satyres.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE reasons why Master <hi>Lodouico Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osto</hi> writ these seauen Satyres, so much renowned and esteemed amongst all the Italians, were grounded vpon these fiue principles or discontentments.</p>
   <p>First, the Poet being giuen wholly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his booke and study, was in the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth year of his age (at what time he began to write his <hi>Oriando Furioso</hi>) entertained into the seruice of <hi>Don Hypolito,</hi> Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of Esta, a greate fauourer of learning and good wits; where he continued certaine yeares at his study, being imployed by his Lord in many matters of greate importance, vntill this strange accident hapned, which was the first occasion why he fell into dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace with his Lord and master; and this it was.</p>
   <p>The Cardinall <hi>Hypolito</hi> Master vnto <hi>Ariosto,</hi> falling in loue with a young Lady his kinswoman (who for her owne part was no lesse in amored of <hi>Don Iulio</hi> the naturall brother vnto the Cardinall) she confessed vnto him, that the only thing which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned her (aboue all other) to affect his brother, was the sweet as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect and beauty of his eies; vpon which the Cardinall grew into so great a hatred against his owne brother, that by iealousie turning his loue into too violent fury, he set espialls ouer <hi>Don Iulio</hi> when he should goe out of the towne on hunting, and set vpon him with a company of villaines, whome the Cardinall commanded in
<pb facs="4"/>
his owne presence to thrust out the eyes of his brother, because they onely were the choyce companions of his loue; an acte no lesse infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous to the Cardinall, then intollerable to all humane gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Whereupon the Cardinall to escape all punishment that might happen to be inflicted vpon him, hee presently fledde to <hi>Agria</hi> a Citty in <hi>Hungary,</hi> whereof he was Archbishop, &amp; liued there vntill the death of <hi>Iulio</hi> the second then Pope of Rome, to auoyde his fury, who was much incensed against him. And because <hi>Ariosto</hi> would not followe him thither, as other of his seruants in his ranke did, he tooke it maruellously ill at his hands, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting him from fauour vpon so sleight an occasion, gaue the Poet a ground for his inuention.</p>
   <p>The second cause of his discontentment was, that he being of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry familiar and inward acquaintance with the Medices of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> of which family two were Popes in his time, the one <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, the other <hi>Clement</hi> the seuenth, both which he follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in good will, and stood them in greate stead as well when they were banished their country, as when they liued as priuate men in their owne citty: but when he sawe his expectation was deceiued, and that he found them not so ready to requite his seruice as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe imagined he had (and that rightly) deserued, he gaue them ouer quickly, and left the Romane Court, retyring himselfe to liue priuatly in Florence. For aboue all things he loued not to daunce long attendance at the Court for any preferment, neither would he be bound (longer then he pleased) vnto any man, although hee might haue had neuer so much, he prizing his liberty at so high a rate, as he esteemed the same more then the best Cardinals hat in Rome, as himselfe in his second Satyre affirmeth more plainly.</p>
   <p>The third cause which made him passionate, was this: his father dying, left him a greate charge and very little liuing, there being fiue brothers of them, and as many sisters (besides his old mother) all which lay vpon his hands to prouide for them; which was no
<pb facs="4"/>
small corsiue vnto him, to be troubled with so many worldly busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, he beeing giuen by nature to ease and to sit quietly at his booke; and this greeued him so much, as oftentimes he was giuing ouer his study cleane, meaning to follow the world another while, had it not beene that he was perswaded to the contrary by a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>are friend and kinsman of his, whom he dearely loued, called <hi>Pandolfo Ariosto,</hi> whose death afterward he very much lamented.</p>
   <p>The fourth cause of discontentment was, he was much galled with the loue of women, whereunto he was a little too much gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, it being a veniall sinne amongst the Italians; yet is he the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be pardoned, in that he often confesseth his fault, and shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himselfe to be sorry for the same, wishing that he could haue amended it: and also because he deuoted himselfe vnto the seruice of such as were honorable, as was that most faire and vertuous wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow descended of the noble family of the <hi>Lapi</hi> in Florence, as hee himself testifieth in one of his Canzons, in which he celebrateth the beauties and honors of his Mistrisse, setting downe therein the time when, and the place where he first was inamored of her; which was in Florence, in the yeare <hi>1513.</hi> vpon Saint <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> day in Iune: at what time the Florentines vnder the conduct of their chiefe Captaynes, <hi>Iulian</hi> and <hi>Peter di Medices</hi> did solemnize many great feasts, and presented diuers rich showes and playes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the people, in honor of their brother <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, who then was newly chosen Pope. But after Cardinall <hi>Hypolito</hi> dyed, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fonzo</hi> Duke of Ferrara allured <hi>Ariosto</hi> by al the meanes he could vnto his Court, offering him great offices and preferments to haue serued him in ordinary, but he louing his liberty more then any treasure refused his proffer, &amp; yet not altogether in such sort, but that in some fashion he was content to retaine vnto him. Againe, had he beene giuen to haue sought wealth and to haue heaped riches together, he could no way haue been without them for diuers great
<pb facs="5"/>
Princes being willing to haue had him liue in their Courtes with them, made tender of many great pensions vnto him, but he accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of none: only he was content to offer his seruice (as I sayde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for̄e) to the aforesayd Duke <hi>Alfonso,</hi> whome he chose rather for country sake, and of meere loue to the place wherein he was borne, then for any great gaine or promotion which he expected.</p>
   <p>Fiftly and lestly to conclude, he wrote these Satyres in Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Hypolytoes</hi> time, and whilst he continued with <hi>Alfonso</hi> Duke of Ferrara; who amōgst other fauours done vnto him, made him president or lieutenant of acountry called Grassignana (sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto his Dukedome) but because the people were very facticus and the country rebellious, and therefore he troubled ouer much with them, he tooke small pleasure in that gouernment, but rather mightily complaineth thereof, as is to be seene in the fourth and seuenth Satyre:</p>
   <p>He was borne in Anno <hi>1474:</hi> in the Castle of <hi>Reggio,</hi> which standeth in Lumbardy, his father at that time being gouernour thereof: He dyed of a payne he had in his stomacke, and was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Saint <hi>Bennets</hi> Church in Ferrara, hauing a fayre monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of marble with his statue placed thereupon, and an Epytaph which a gentleman a friend of his bestowed vpon him.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>