<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A SVMMARY of the whole contense of this present Booke, for the Readers better compre∣hension thereof.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100011_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11368</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21628</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100011</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A SVMMARY of the whole contense of this present Booke, for the Readers better compre∣hension thereof.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An admirable method to loue, serue and honour the B. Virgin Mary : With diuers practicable exercises thereof. Al inriched with choice examples. Written in Italian by the R. F. Alexis de Salo, Capuchin. And Englished by R.F</title>
                 <author>Salo, Alessio Segala de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cousturier (Le Cousturier), Jean</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 607, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A SVMMARY of the whole contense of this present Booke, for the Readers better compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension thereof.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE whole scope of this present Treatise is no other then to teach in a deuout and excellēt manner how to Reuerence and adore with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Inclinations our B. Lady and mistrisse the Queene of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; as a preparatiue to which, we haue indeauoured to declare,
<pb facs="4"/>her heroical vertues, greatnesses, excellencies and sublime prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues: And by the way is to be considered that although Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be peculiar to God alone, yet according to diuines distinction thereof, it also may be appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the B. Virgin, to Angels, and other Saints and thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come common to God &amp; Man. As we may cleerly gather from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers passages of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as namely in Paralip. chap. 26. when it is sayd; <hi>And they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined and adored first God, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the King.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These Adorations then admit a three-fould distinction of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria, Dulia, and Hyperdulia, where of the first is proper vnto God alone, in regard of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit and increated Greatnes; the
<pb facs="4"/>second hath reference to such creatures as aduance in sanctity and glory aboue the rest, which sanctity and glory arriuing in any on to more sublimity (as in the B. Virgin) with the more sublime honour of Hyperdulia, cōsequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we are to reuerence them: But before we proceed to the exercise of this Adoration we prefix an exhortation to deuotion towards her, and declare fiue Priuiledges, her seruants are indowed with al, setting down (as preamble to the worke) those conditions and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities which are requisit in her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uots. Then we pass to the expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of these Adorations, in the first Chapter, declaring their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, in the second how gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teful and acceptable they are to the B. Virgin, and in the fower
<pb facs="5"/>following ones, fower forcible argumēts are established to proue her deseruing that adoration. The first deduced from her being the Mother of Almighty God. The next for her being elected aboue al other Saints, and al the Quires of Heauen. The third for her so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraine power and authority, ouer al Creatures: And the fourth and last for her being an affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat Mother vnto vs al. Then we come to the practise of these Adorations, (or Genuflexions) shewing how they are deuoutly to be performed, as wel in the interiour as exteriour, and heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon we take occasion to inlarge our discourse touching the Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations due to God, to his Blessed Saints and Angels, &amp;c. Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the remaine of the following
<pb facs="5"/>Chapters, in setting down diuers practical wayes of honouring the B. Virgin applying to euery on its proper Reuerence and Adoratiōs: but principally we insist vpon those twelue sublime prerogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of hers, prefigured by the twelue Starres, in her crowne of which S. Iohn in his Apocalips make mention.</p>
   <p>Now this aduertisement is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to al that although the choice of many exercises of adoratiōs be proposed in this present worke, notwithstanding they are only to fix on, which they may find most gust and comfort in, and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to beware-of entergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to much at once least they become thereby but more negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in performance of them, and a too precipitious desir of cōming
<pb facs="6"/>soon to end, make them but hast too much vpon the way, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them without fruit and deuotion.</p>
   <p>Wherefore we councel rather to make choice of some few we may performe with mediocrity of deuotion, then of many with danger of tepidity &amp; distraction. Notwithstanding when any feast occurs, vnto which we haue a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular deuotion (as those of our Blessed Sauiour his Mother or the like) we may then multiply our Genuflexions to a hundred a day, (for example) or a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand distributed equally to seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral dayes or nights of the octaue as we please, as we shal more largely declare in the following Treatise by the assistance of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, and the fauour of
<pb facs="6"/>his holy Mother, al which we dedicat to the praise of God from whom al Good proceeds, to the Blessed Virgin his most holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to Saint Francis our Glorious Patriarch.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>