<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Aduertisement.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100174_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11172</idno>
           <idno type="STC">575</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100174</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Aduertisement.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ground of the Catholike and Roman religion in the word of God : With the antiquity and continuance therof, throughout all kingdomes and ages. Collected out of diuers conferences, discourses, and disputes, which M. Patricke Anderson of the Society of Iesus, had at seuerall tymes, with sundry bishops and ministers of Scotland, at his last imprisonment in Edenburgh, for the Catholike faith, in the yeares of our Lord 1620. and 1621. Sent vnto an honourable personage, by the complyer, and prisoner himselfe. The first part, or introduction</title>
                 <author>Anderson, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 60, 6, 552, that is 152, 6, 174, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="203"/>
   <head>Aduertisement.</head>
   <p>By reason that these bookes were printed by men who had no great skil in the Scottish language, sundry small errours haue escaped, which the learned and charitable Reader will, I hope, the more easily excuse, and correct.</p>
   <p>
      <label>Errata.</label> IN the first Part, in the Preface to the Reader, read <hi>Carpere vel noli.</hi> In the second Part, line 28. read, <hi>these.</hi> Pag. 22. in the margent, <hi>dele</hi> these words, <hi>See these words in the Bible.</hi> Pag. 23. lin. 3. read, <hi>which hath byn vsed.</hi> Pag. 27. l. 12. <hi>dele</hi> these words, <hi>Quem &amp; citat Beza.</hi> Pag. 44. l. 1. read, <hi>these.</hi> Ibid. in the margent, <hi>dele</hi> these words, <hi>Serm. de Annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiat.</hi> Pag. 45. l. 3. read, <hi>Carne sola.</hi> Pag. 72. l. 3. read, <hi>recludunt.</hi> Ibid. l. 7. read <hi>additus.</hi> Pag. 73. l. 3. read <hi>Bruma.</hi> Ibid. l. 34. read <hi>solo.</hi> Pag. 81. l. 30. read <hi>Bibles.</hi> Pag. 93. l. 30. read <hi>meritorious.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Errours of the third Part, if any haue escaped, the Courteous Reader, I trust, will of himselfe correct.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="204"/>
   <pb facs="204"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>