<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>REVERENDISSIMO in Christo Patri, Guilielmo, Providen∣tia divina Archiepiscopo Cantuariensi, totius Angliae Primati &amp; Metropolitano, Regiae Majestatis à sa∣cratioribus Concilijs: &amp; Academiae Oxoniensis Cancellario dignissimo. HONORATISSIMO ETIAM DO∣mino, Thomae Domino Coventrie Baroni de Ales∣borough, magni sigilli Angliae Custodi; Serenis∣simo Regi à Concilijs, &amp;c. NEC NON MVLTIS NOMINIBVS Honorando, Domino Francisco Windebanck Equiti Aurate; Caroli Regis Consiliario, &amp; Secretario Principali.</title>
           <author>Humfrey, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100171_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19065</idno>
           <idno type="STC">548</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100171</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>REVERENDISSIMO in Christo Patri, Guilielmo, Providen∣tia divina Archiepiscopo Cantuariensi, totius Angliae Primati &amp; Metropolitano, Regiae Majestatis à sa∣cratioribus Concilijs: &amp; Academiae Oxoniensis Cancellario dignissimo. HONORATISSIMO ETIAM DO∣mino, Thomae Domino Coventrie Baroni de Ales∣borough, magni sigilli Angliae Custodi; Serenis∣simo Regi à Concilijs, &amp;c. NEC NON MVLTIS NOMINIBVS Honorando, Domino Francisco Windebanck Equiti Aurate; Caroli Regis Consiliario, &amp; Secretario Principali.</title>
                 <author>Humfrey, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christian offices crystall glasse : In three bookes. First written in Latine, by that famous and renowned Father, Saint Ambrose Bishop of Millane. Whereunto is added his conuiction of Symmachus the Gentile. A worke tending to the advancement of vertue, and of holinesse: and to shew how much the morality of the Gentiles, is exceeded by the doctrine of Christianity. Translated into English by Richard Humfrey</title>
                 <author>Ambrose, Saint, Bishop of Milan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Greene, Charles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dawson, John 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>66, 126, 2, 127-142, 10, 75, 9, 64, 38, 20, 41, 1 page, folded table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>REVERENDISSIMO in Christo Patri, Guilielmo, Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia divina Archiepiscopo Cantuariensi, totius Angliae Primati &amp; Metropolitano, Regiae Majestatis à sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratioribus Concilijs: &amp; Academiae Oxoniensis Cancellario dignissimo. HONORATISSIMO ETIAM DO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino, Thomae Domino Coventrie Baroni de Ales<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough, magni sigilli Angliae Custodi; Serenis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>simo Regi à Concilijs, &amp;c. NEC NON MVLTIS NOMINIBVS Honorando, Domino Francisco Windebanck Equiti Aurate; Caroli Regis Consiliario, &amp; Secretario Principali.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ompetency (most <hi>Reverend Father</hi> in God,<note place="margin">Maximè sae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdoti hoc convenit, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare Dei tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum decore corgruo, ut e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam hoc cultu aula Domini resplendeat: Ne restrictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem erga cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, aut indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiorem se prabeat. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terū enim in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanum, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum, si aut sumptus desit necessitati eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quos à sordidis nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiationis aucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pijs retrahere debeas, aut vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptati super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stuat, Ambros. Offic. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>21</hi>
      </note> and <hi>Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable</hi>) for the suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient maintenance of the <hi>Clergie,</hi> to whom the <hi>Cure</hi> of <hi>Soules</hi> is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;
<pb facs="3"/> is neither the last nor the least, of your <hi>Graces</hi> godly <hi>cares</hi> and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devours.</hi> For which <hi>pious intention</hi> of your <hi>Graces,</hi> my selfe amongst many others of my <hi>Brethren,</hi> stand in no small degree obliged and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged: To your <hi>Grace,</hi> I say, and to the <hi>Right Honorable</hi> my ever hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red good Lord, the <hi>Lord Keeper;</hi> and the <hi>Right Honorable</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Windebanck, Principall Secretary</hi> of <hi>estate</hi> unto his <hi>Majestie.</hi> All your <hi>Honors</hi> great <hi>favours, paines,</hi> and <hi>pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:</hi> I were most <hi>unthankefull</hi> not to acknowledge, as bestowed upon my selfe; in your <hi>endevours</hi> (upon my petition) to induce some <hi>Improprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries</hi> whom I lately had to doe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, to an <hi>enlargement</hi> of my poore <hi>maintenance.</hi> Which, though for want of <hi>devotion,</hi> perhaps, in <hi>some</hi> of
<pb facs="3"/> them, it tooke not the <hi>effect</hi> desired: yet is my <hi>selfe</hi> and <hi>familie,</hi> and in me, all of my <hi>Ranke</hi> and <hi>profession;</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthelesse beholding unto your <hi>Honors,</hi> for your noble <hi>encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to our studies. Seeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>thankefulnesse</hi> is ever more testified by <hi>Tokens</hi> then by <hi>words:</hi> I advised with my selfe how to make the best expression of it. But finding my greatest <hi>Riches,</hi> to be my <hi>Paines:</hi> I here make bold most humbly to present it to your <hi>Honours;</hi> And that in a <hi>better</hi> mans performance then mine <hi>owne:</hi> even of the most holy and admired <hi>St. Ambrose.</hi> This hath beene the prime motive to mee (<hi>most Reverend,</hi> and <hi>Right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>) to present this my <hi>Translation;</hi> first to your <hi>Honors;</hi> and by you, to the rest of <hi>Gods people.</hi> And your
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Grace,</hi> verely, in this your most pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Government,</hi> joyned with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted <hi>courage</hi> for <hi>Gods cause:</hi> is (mee thinkes) the neerest resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of this most renowned <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop.</hi> And whereas hee also was a Lieutenant of the Citie of <hi>Millane,</hi> a Consul, and <hi>principall Officer</hi> of the <hi>Emperours</hi> in his time; I hope hee shall find the fairer <hi>entertainment:</hi> and if you please, <hi>imitation</hi> too, with your <hi>Honors.</hi> The <hi>matter</hi> is of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Offices</hi> and <hi>morality:</hi> of <hi>Iustice, Magnanimitie, Prudence</hi> and <hi>tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> joyned with <hi>pietie:</hi> great <hi>stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> and <hi>practises</hi> of your <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Honours.</hi> Now most humbly desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my poore performance in the <hi>Translation,</hi> may both bee <hi>excused</hi> and <hi>accepted:</hi> I in all humilitie and thankfulnesse, make tender of it to
<pb facs="4"/> your <hi>noble</hi> hands: desiring leave that under the <hi>patronage</hi> of your much <hi>honored</hi> and <hi>beloved names,</hi> it may bee recommended unto the <hi>people.</hi> For which <hi>Second Favour,</hi> I shall ever remaine, the daily <hi>Orator</hi> for</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces and Honors happinesse and salvation, RICHARD HVMFREY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>