<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To our verie louing Companions, and fellowes in Armes, hir Maiesties Gentlemen Pensioners: and to the gentle Reader whosoeuer.</title>
           <author>Fitzwilliams, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100278_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22422</idno>
           <idno type="STC">884</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100278</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To our verie louing Companions, and fellowes in Armes, hir Maiesties Gentlemen Pensioners: and to the gentle Reader whosoeuer.</title>
                 <author>Fitzwilliams, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The art of riding : set foorth in a breefe treatise, with a due interpretation of certeine places alledged out of Xenophon, and Gryson, verie expert and excellent horssemen: wherein also the true vse of the hand by the said Grysons rules and precepts is speciallie touched and how the author of this present worke hath put the same in practise, also what profit men maie reape thereby: without the knowledge whereof, all the residue of the order of riding is but vaine. Lastlie, is added a short discourse of the chaine or cauezzan, the trench, and the martingale: writte by a gentleman of great skill and long experience in the said art</title>
                 <author>Astley, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 79, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To our verie louing Companions, <hi>and fellowes in Armes, hir Maiesties</hi> Gentlemen Pensioners: and to the <hi>gentle Reader whosoeuer.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene practised by many excellent men in sundrie professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to forbeare the publishing of their owne names with such workes, as they haue set foorth with singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar skill for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Their intent wherein (as we conceiue) hath beene onelie this, to profit and benefit others, without regarding anie waie to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase praise or commendation vnto themselues. VVhich franke and liberall kind of dealing, as it proceedeth (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les) of a noble disposition of mind, which seeketh rather to doo, than to be seene in doing, and passeth not for so meane a reward, as is commonlie due for speach, or for a mans tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell by his pen: so were it a kinde of iniurie, to suffer the names of such excellent persons (worthie to beare name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad aboue others) to rest in that sort drowned in silence and darknes, and not rather to indeuor (though contrarie to their likings in that behalfe) to aduance their doings, and to make them openlie knowne vnto the world, thereby to receiue part of that honor which is due vnto them. For
<pb facs="4"/>praise and renowne is vnto none so iustlie due, as vnto those, which in anie vertuous action doo least affect it. In this number, which is but rare, must we note vnto you (though perchance not without some offense vnto him) the worthie Gentleman M. Iohn Astley, maister of hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Iewell house, and Gentleman of hir priuie chamber, a man, besides his reputation and countenance in Court, knowne to be of singular shill in the Art of Riding: who (in truth) being the Author of this treatise, and yet either for modesties sake, or otherwise carelesse, that the world should yeeld praise and commendation vnto him for his trauell therein taken, hath sought by all the meanes he could (as maie appeare by the Epistle, vnder the Cipher of two letters herevnto prefixed) to suppresse, and in no wise to haue his owne name seene in the same; rather conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that anie other should carrie the opinion thereof, than he himselfe: where as (by his fauor be it spoken) he ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue doone the contrarie, and to haue entituled his name vnto his owne worke, whereby the same should haue receiued both credit and reputation. Howbeit, this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being handled with such exquisite skill and iudgement, as by the perusing of this booke you shall perceiue it is, it was an easie matter, thereby to haue knowen M. Astley, though his name had beene neuer so much dissembled, or the same not otherwise notified vnto you: for the matter it selfe (no doubt) would soone haue lead you to iudge that to be his, which (happilie) few men els could haue doone but he. Therefore (for our partes) being loath that so worthie a Gentleman, who hath trauelled so carefullie, and so kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for the good of his countrie, and was the onelie-man, that persuaded Maister Blundeuill to take first in hand his
<pb facs="5"/>worke of Frederike Gryson (which we all haue receiued no small benefit by) should be defrauded of his due commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though he himselfe doo litle regard it. And because the worke it selfe is such, as may boldlie abide the censure of the most precise and skilfull in this profession, and withall beseeme his owne name verie well: we haue aduentured (as you see) not fearing anie blame for our boldnes herein, (because in so dooing, we meane nothing but all loue and honor vnto him) to declare thus much vnto you, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the verie Author of this present worke, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth now of his friendlie liberalitie into your hands, to the end you maie reape both profit and pleasure thereof, for both are verie largelie comprized in it. Vse it, we praie you, with like kindnesse as it is offered vnto you, and take benefit of it without cauill, or ouer-curious reprehension; wherein as you shall doo the Author himselfe but iustice, and also make vs his faithfull true friends much behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, so shall you happilie encourage him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, to endeuor himselfe againe to your fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and greater benefit hereafter. From the Court, at VVhite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, the last of March. 1584.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <list>
            <item>
               <hi>H. Mackwilliam.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi>W. Fitzwilliams.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>