<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An apologie of the Author, done as by the Mourner, to the Lovers of Learning.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100435_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03379</idno>
           <idno type="STC">135</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100435</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An apologie of the Author, done as by the Mourner, to the Lovers of Learning.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The muses threnodie, or, mirthfull mournings, on the death of Master Gall : Containing varietie of pleasant poëticall descriptions, morall instructions, historicall narrations, and divine observations, with the most remarkable antiquities of Scotland, especially at Perth By Mr. H. Adamson</title>
                 <author>Adamson, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Anderson, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 87, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>
      <hi>An apologie of the Author,</hi> done as by the Mourner, to the Lovers of Learning.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>LET none offend, though in mine age I sing</l>
      <l>Swan-like, some lawfull joyes youthead did bring:</l>
      <l>My songs are mournings, which may clearly shew</l>
      <l>Th'inconstant course of all things here below:</l>
      <l>Yet guided by that steadfast hand alwayes</l>
      <l>Which, midst confusions great, the ballance stayes:</l>
      <l>Thus <hi>Heraclitus-</hi>like sometimes I mourne</l>
      <l>At giddie Fortunes reelings: thence I turne</l>
      <l>Like to <hi>Democritus</hi> in laughter wholly</l>
      <l>To see th'inconstant changes of her folly.</l>
      <l>Thus do I mourne, and laugh oftimes, by course,</l>
      <l>As giddie Fortune reeles from good to worse:</l>
      <l>For neither is the battell to the strong, <note place="margin">Eccles. 9. 11.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Nor doth unto the swift the race belong,</l>
      <l>Nor bread to these whose wit should have commanding,</l>
      <l>Nor riches to the men of understanding:</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="7"/>
Nor favour doth to men of knowledge fall,</l>
      <l>But chance (as would appear) doth order all.</l>
      <l>So, if the second causes we do view,</l>
      <l>We shall finde out a paradoxe most true.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But O thou prime and supreme cause of all,</l>
      <l>Nothing to thee by fortune doth befall,</l>
      <l>For Thou, in midst of all these great confusions</l>
      <l>Fores<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s, and workes most permanent conclusions,</l>
      <l>Keeping most comely order in varieties,</l>
      <l>And making concord in all contrarieties.</l>
      <l>Hence doth it come to passe of thy benignitie,</l>
      <l>That wicked men possesse both wealth and dignitie.</l>
      <l>But, as its written, riches are preserv'd, <note place="margin">Eccles. 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </note>
      </l>
      <l>And for the evill of th'owners are reserv'd:</l>
      <l>And as a mightie load the bearers smothers,</l>
      <l>So some to their owne burt rule over others,</l>
      <l>Not looking to th'account they must needs make, <note place="margin">Eccles. 8. 9.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Nor bow their smiling fortune may turn back,</l>
      <l>Whose honour like the sea doth ebbe and flow,</l>
      <l>Whose beautie hath the time to fade and grew,</l>
      <l>Whose riches, like the Eagle, hath their wings,</l>
      <l>Now lighting down on earth, to Heaven then springs. <note place="margin">Prover. 23. 5.</note>
      </l>
      <l>The body's Summer rose is quickly gone,</l>
      <l>By winters stormie age all overblowne,</l>
      <l>To shew earths constant changes: and that all</l>
      <l>Which here on earth do spring must likewise fall.</l>
      <l>Thrise happie he that state who quickly findes,</l>
      <l>Which is not shaken with earths contrare windes!</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Hence <hi>Solitarie</hi> and <hi>poore</hi> content I live,</l>
      <l>Sith bitter hap blind fortune doth not give:</l>
      <l>And, like <hi>Diogenes,</hi> contemplate all,</l>
      <l>Within my Cabine, that here doth befall:</l>
      <l>Which gives me subject both to sing and mourne,</l>
      <l>The times ov'rpast, which never shall returne.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>
I praise the worthie deedes of Martiall men,</l>
      <l>And I do wish the whole world might them ken:</l>
      <l>I praise their vertues: No, their Vertuous deeds</l>
      <l>Do praise themselves, and as most lively seeds</l>
      <l>Beget like children: so commemoration</l>
      <l>Begets them native sons by imitation.</l>
      <l>Native! more native than by blood descended,</l>
      <l>Who with their fame their fortunes have mispened.</l>
      <l>For what availes to point a noble race</l>
      <l>By long descent of branches, if in face <note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. Sat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Like vertue doth not shine, and equall worth</l>
      <l>Ignoble deeds belie a noble birth;</l>
      <l>Maugre all contrare thoughts, this true shall trie</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Vertue alone is true nobilitie.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If one most vitious in my line should be</l>
      <l>Five hundred years ago, what is't to me,</l>
      <l>Who vertuous am;? What? can it derogate</l>
      <l>To my good name? or violate my state?</l>
      <l>Or if antcestors brave shall me preceed,</l>
      <l>And I do prove the knave, what shall proceed</l>
      <l>By their Heroick vertues unto me,</l>
      <l>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>se vitious life denies my progenie?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For linage and forebears, <hi>Naso</hi> said,</l>
      <l>Are not cal'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> ours, nor what our selves not made. <note place="margin">Meta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. 13.</note>
      </l>
      <l>To prove this paradoxe I durst be bold <note place="margin">Arist. Ethic. lib. 1. cap. 11</note>
      </l>
      <l>With judgement of the learned but I hold</l>
      <l>My pen: for all do know of old what's said,</l>
      <l>I rather that <hi>Thersites</hi> were my daid,</l>
      <l>And I <hi>Achilles-</hi>like, most noble, rather <note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>. Sat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Then I <hi>Thersites,</hi> he to be my father:</l>
      <l>True generositie doth so esteeme,</l>
      <l>Though ignorance the contrare would maintaine.</l>
      <l>But <hi>Momus</hi> must needs carp, and <hi>Misanthrópos</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Be <hi>Ariopagita-</hi>like Scythropos.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <pb facs="8"/>
Scarce were these lines as yet come to the birth</l>
      <l>When some false flattering sycoph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nt gave forth</l>
      <l>Most foule aspersions, making rumors spread,</l>
      <l>That citing of some auncient stories bred</l>
      <l>No small disgrace unto the present times,</l>
      <l>Places, and persons of most auncient stemmes.</l>
      <l>And that I write of purpose to attaint them;</l>
      <l>I wish of this their wrong it might repent them:</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>or as the contrare's true, so I protest</l>
      <l>I never bad a purpose to infest</l>
      <l>The meanest, far lesse these of better sort,</l>
      <l>Where birth and grace do make a sweet consort.</l>
      <l>Yea, more I do protest, against my will</l>
      <l>These lines were reft from under my rude quill:</l>
      <l>I never did intend so great a height</l>
      <l>That they should touch the presse, or come to light:</l>
      <l>But now, sith more there is then my designe,</l>
      <l>I forced am my just defence to bring</l>
      <l>Gainst my traducers, who maliciouslie,</l>
      <l>With banefull invie's tooth, have snatch'd at me</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But I appeale to all judicious learning,</l>
      <l>Whose wits are exercised in decerning,</l>
      <l>If I your approbation do finde,</l>
      <l>I care nought these <hi>Ardelio's</hi> catching winde;</l>
      <l>Nor other Patrons do I seek but you,</l>
      <l>To take of this small piece a litle view,</l>
      <l>And give just censure joyn'd with your protection,</l>
      <l>More worth then <hi>Zoilus</hi> hate <hi>Gnatho's</hi> affection;</l>
      <l>Your favours shall me shelter and defend</l>
      <l>Against all invies rage to live to end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>Trusting in God to keepe my conscience pure,</l>
      <l>Whose favour most of all shall me secure.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>