<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my Honoura∣ble and Worthy Friends in Par∣liament.</title>
           <author>Knight, P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100356_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09491</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19774</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100356</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my Honoura∣ble and Worthy Friends in Par∣liament.</title>
                 <author>Knight, P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An inuitation vnto prayer, and the practise of piety, directing the way to true happinesse : Wherein is principally to be considered, these foure things. 1. What prayer vnto God is. 2. The necessity of it. 3. The profit we receiue by this holy exercise. 4. The maner and vse of it</title>
                 <author>Perrott, James, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Bird, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, Isaac</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 129, that is 127, 5 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To my Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Worthy Friends in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL good counsell comes from God. Humane consul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are as fraile; as themselues are feeble. Nature hath her cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and corruptions in all the accidents of this world. Mans aduice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng onely on it selfe, is
<pb facs="4"/> like his actions, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times prosperous, often perillous, &amp; many times pernitious. The most sure and sase helpe that vvee haue, comes from the gouernour of Heauen &amp; Earth. The defence of his truth is our best buckler, and his seruice our chiefest safety. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Petitions vnto God, are the Harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which prepares a place for our heauenly habitation, and makes firme our earthly posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions. This small and
<pb facs="4"/> slender Treatise, which J haue now puhlished concerning Prayer, was first written ahout <hi>27.</hi> yeares since, then penned for mine owne practise: since which time, it hath beene concealed, and in a manner cast away, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst many my other loose Papers, vntill of late finding it vnlooked for, J shewed it to some of my priuate Friends, whose desires vvere; it should be made publicke. To that J yeelded, not for any worth J could
<pb facs="5"/> conceiue to bee in the worke, comming from one so weake, but to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy those who J knew would beare with my faults. Of all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the world is as it were the Theater, our selues the Actors; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in some play their partes with skill, others in sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, most with errors: the greater part are cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surers, more ready to finde fault with others, then to search into them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues: whatsoeuer they are, or J am, J see my
<pb facs="5"/> selfe subiect to censure▪ This subiect is Prayer, the pathway to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: the handling and carriage of rich Roabes by poore men, makes not the garments meane, but it may be more meanely valewed, it is that in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre as in Physicke; the Materials of the one, and ingredients of Medicines in the other, beeing of themselues good, yet not well by the workers ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, composed, and mixed; makes their shew of lesse esteeme; and
<pb facs="6"/> indeede their substance of lesse vse. Such may be the state of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise touching prayers, the subiect in it selfe holy &amp; heauenly; but by mee not well handled; may so fall out to be lesse valewed, then the dignity of it wel set forth, would shew it selfe to be. Howsoeuer, I offer this small Widowes Myte into that Treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie where true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by Prayer and Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, makes their oblations and tribute in the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary of GOD, vnto
<pb facs="6"/> whose gracious and good guidance, I commend all your good consultations, with all others that by faithfull prayer and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent deuotion, desire to serue his Diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours in him, who can make vs all his, and to enioy all happines.</hi> I. P. Knight.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>