<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>S., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1008_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13119</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23412.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1008</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>S., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A receite for grace· : In a sermon preached in the parish church of Westminster. By Christopher Styles</title>
                 <author>Styles, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 18 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, (I confesse, the Presse is oppressed) and there is no end in making of bookes, (and euery Preacher is not fit to be a Writer) I doe also humbly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my defect in both: what bold presumption then doth spurre me forwards to so dangerous aduentures? Onely these weake reasons:</p>
   <p>First, a diligent desire not to bee idle, as also to vse it for a better meanes whereby to shun idle and euill company.</p>
   <p>Secondly, writing maketh our knowledge more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and our speech more ready and perfect.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, because we are called to teach the Word of God, as well by writing, as by word; by pen, as by voice; therefore the Prophets wrote hidden mysteries; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles profound doctrines; and <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangelist, a whole booke of Diuine Reuelations; and not without command.</p>
   <p>What if my plainnesse be not well taken of the enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? (let them that are gald, kicke) my faithfull mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heerein, is for the common good of the multitude; and yet I know, the most good will redound vnto my selfe. Therefore (good Christian) though I write not excellently, pleasing things to delight thee, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit all: yet if I write honestly plaine truth, which no
<pb facs="4"/>doubt will comfort many, especially my friends, and all such as feare God without dissembling: Straine not thy conscience to cauill at words, and to wrest them contrary to good meaning: if any small fault hath escaped me, consider thy selfe (in another, or the like kind) maist commit a worse: for <hi>Humanum est er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare:</hi> It were beyond humane nature not to erre; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let thy charity couer that, which thy enuie would disclose: for <hi>Diuinum est amare:</hi> it makes vs like vnto God, to loue: for God is loue. Vse thy discretion: and so farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>C. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>