<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ARGUMENT.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100508_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17248</idno>
           <idno type="STC">41</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100508</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ARGUMENT.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The whole booke of Iob paraphrased : or, made easie for any to understand. By George Abbott</title>
                 <author>Abbot, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2</publisher>
                    <distributor>Overton, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 271, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD, for whose pleasure all things<note place="margin">Rev. 4. 11.</note> are, and were created,</hi> having made <hi>Job</hi> fit for use, resolveth to imploy him, and having first tried him in a calme sea of prosperity, and not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him to leake, at last launcheth him into the deep, and ingageth him in a long and dangerous voiage of adversity, where hee must undergoe many a fight and storme, to prove God a Master-builder.</p>
   <p>Hereupon, because Satan knew not Gods designe, God himselfe hints it to him by commending <hi>Job,</hi> which his malice not abiding to heare, and desiring to contradict, presently becomes a sutor, to God, to have the winnowing of him, which God for many reasons granteth to him: Partly, in respect to shew him that hee is the onely <hi>discerner of the heart:</hi> Partly, in<note place="margin">heb. 4. 12.</note> respect of the errour of those times wherein it was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally received, that God afflicted not in soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but onely for, and according to the proportion of sinne: Partly, in respect of <hi>Job,</hi> for his after-honour and preferment: And lastly, in respect of after-times, to leave upon record a paterne of patience, and a seale
<pb facs="6"/>
of Gods power and faithfulnesse in upholding the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and in delivering them out of all their troubles.</p>
   <p>Satan having received his commission to worke he goeth, and dischargeth all his Ordinance at once upon <hi>Job,</hi> thinking through force and policy, to wring some discontented blasphemy from him, and so to disprove God, but <hi>Job</hi> abid the shocke, and uttered not a mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beseeming word, till at last his sores began to smart, and therewith also the light of Gods countenance through the thicke cloud of those many afflictions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to shine dim upon his spirit, and then hee opened his mouth, not as Satan hoped, to blaspheme, but to ease his forrwfull soule, with breathing forth a dolefull wish or two; as that either he had never seene life, or might now see death.</p>
   <p>Which impatiency of <hi>Jobs,</hi> his friends standing by, tooke fire at, and thereupon they being ignorantly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced of God, that hee afflicted not but in proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable punishment to sin committed, and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were opinionated of <hi>Job,</hi> that for all his faire shew, he must needs be but a hollowhearted hypocrite; they with vehement importunity, pressed these sore upon him as infallible maximes, thereby to have disarmed him both of his sword of faith, and shield of sincerity, but <hi>Job,</hi> though conscious to his owne infirmities which he ingenuously confesseth, yet was also privie to his owne uprightnesse, which he as manfully maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth against all his opposites, and the more they laboured to loose his hold on God, the faster he clung unto him, yea, though God himselfe seemed to take their part, by suffering Satan afresh to face him with his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>past sinnes accompanied with present terrours, and
<pb facs="6"/>
himselfe too utterly benighted his soule with an abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute sun-set of all present sight and sense of immediate favour: yet in this great desertion God gave him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand for his secret support, a little chinke of light whereby he was able to see, and sustainingly to remind himselfe of Gods former favours (though hee felt none present) which made him able to leane upon his God, yea, and which enlightned him clearely to see also his owne sincerity, though it were sore shot at by his friends, which did drive him to appeale from man to God (the onely Judge of secret things) with whom he desired to plead his cause (with some exceedings) in that behalfe, provided he would substitute one that was his equall in his stead.</p>
   <p>Which <hi>Elihu</hi> hearing, when his time came to speak accordingly addressed himselfe unto him in Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, wisely, both justifying <hi>Job</hi> against his friends, and cond<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mning their ungrounded opinion in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him an hypocrite, because of his great afflictions; and also justifying God against <hi>Job,</hi> who, through his friends unadvised spurring him on, had overreached. Wherefore <hi>Elihu</hi> sheweth <hi>Iob</hi> his fault which God strucke at by his affliction, to wit, pride, whereof hee convinceth him by his saufie capitulating with God, who both in right of prerogative, over his creature, yea and in justice for his sinne, (though not for his hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie) might justifie all he did against him, and was by no means to be disputed withall touching any thing he did, because of his excelling power, unsearehable wisdome, and undeniable justice.</p>
   <p>Which <hi>Elihu</hi> having spoken, God himselfe secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him with a large expression of his owne tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendent
<pb facs="7"/>
greatnesse in wisedome and power beyond <hi>Jobs</hi> capacity, consequently shewing him his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption and solly, and his owne unquestionable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in all his workes, however they appeare to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane reason.</p>
   <p>Which, when <hi>Job</hi> understood from God himselfe, his mouth was stopped, saving in abasing himselfe and confessing of his fault, which was no sooner done, but God shaketh hands with <hi>Job, Brings forth his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse<note place="margin">Psal. 37, 6.</note> as the light, and his judgement as the noone-day,</hi> in the sight of all his accusers; prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him to be Mediatour for his friends, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally maketh him a large amends, even double to all hee lost.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>