<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGT WORSHIPFVLL AND his most deare respected friend Maister IOHN MASSY of Codington in Cheshire.</title>
           <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100657_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06957</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17381</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100657</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGT WORSHIPFVLL AND his most deare respected friend Maister IOHN MASSY of Codington in Cheshire.</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Markhams methode or epitome (wherein is shewed his aprooued remedies for all diseases whatsoeuer incident to horses, oxen, kine, bulls, calues, sheep, lambs, goats, swine, dogs of all kind, conies, all sorts of poultrye, all water-foule, as geese, ducks, swans, and the like) pigeons, all singing birds, hawks of all kind; and other creatures seruice-able for the vse of man: deuided into twelue generall points or heads. By Gervase Markham. Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Markham, Gervase</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Langley, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 75, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGT WORSHIPFVLL AND his most deare respected friend Maister IOHN MASSY of Codington in Cheshire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Sir, Hee that much doth, may much miscarry, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause danger euer is the Companion with labour: and in these dayes mens braines are so sickly and subiect to
<pb facs="3"/>
take surfaits, especially where either the feast is (in their owne conceits) too full, or the dishes not drest an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to their stomacks, that, to bee a Cook to please all mens varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, were to ascribe a cunning har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly bestowed vppon Angels; from which consideration I haue beene many times induced to haue obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this small and inrespeccted Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, as willing to hold from mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking mindes (which poyson with false construction) a benefit so good and certaine, as I know they will be fruitfull in diuulging my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praise, and finding knots in smooth rushes, adding to my title, vaine prate and ostentation; But by many
<pb facs="3"/>
of my better friendes, and some whose approued wisedomes are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and some whose knowne loues doe and euer shall gouerne mee, I am inforced to disesteeme the vaine battery of the enuious, and boldly publish this Treatise, which I doubt not but will bee a generall good to all the whole Kingdome, for whose seruice I was onely cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated. As for your worthy selfe who was the first that euer beheld it, and to whose handes it flew before it had taken any perfit or true forme, as knowing how able you were both to iudge of the defects, and to crowne the perfections, not a Gentleman in this Kingdome of
<pb facs="4"/>
your ranke going one steppe before you, either in loue or knowledge of Horsemanship: To whom I say but you should I send this my last In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant; to bee nourished and defended, since it pleased you to accept it with much loue, when it was vnlikely of life any where but in your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some. Then worthy Sir, let mee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you to take it to Protection, and whilst nothing but enuy as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saults it, bee you its constant guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian; But when eyther a stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or better skill proues ie vaine, then leaue it againe to my selfe, and wee will both dye inrespec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; till when, (which will not bee whilst any thing is) at least
<pb facs="4"/>
not whilst Men ride on Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, I will euer rest a faithfull and true Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, full of your Goodnes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>GERVASE MARKHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>