<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all Faire Ladies,
Famous for their Vertues,
L. L. wisheth the enjoyment of their
Desires; whether Coelestiall, or
Terrestriall, but most especially to
that Paragon of Perfection, the ve∣ry
Non-such of her Sexe, famous
by the Name of Mistris
M. S.</title>
           <author>L., L.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100242_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21479</idno>
           <idno type="STC">778</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100242</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all Faire Ladies,
Famous for their Vertues,
L. L. wisheth the enjoyment of their
Desires; whether Coelestiall, or
Terrestriall, but most especially to
that Paragon of Perfection, the ve∣ry
Non-such of her Sexe, famous
by the Name of Mistris
M. S.</title>
                 <author>L., L.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A small treatise betwixt Arnalte and Lucenda entituled The evill-intreated lover, or the melancholy knight. Originally written in the Greeke tongue, by an unknowne author. Afterwards translated into Spanish; after that, for the excellency thereof, into the French tongue by N.H. next by B.M. into the Thuscan, and now turn'd into English verse by L.L. a well-wisher to the Muses</title>
                 <author>San Pedro, Diego de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Moseley, Humphrey</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 108 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To all Faire Ladies,
Famous for their Vertues,
L. L. wisheth the enjoyment of their
Desires; whether Coelestiall, or
Terrestriall, but most especially to
that Paragon of Perfection, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Non-such of her Sexe, famous
by the Name of Mistris
M. S.</head>
   <l>OH stand my Friends yee sacred Treble-trine</l>
   <l>Of divine Sisters, oh yee Muses Nine,</l>
   <l>Inflame my <hi>Genius,</hi> and my thoughts inspire</l>
   <l>With the bright beames of your Aetheriall fire:</l>
   <l>Oh teach me words which yet were never knowne,</l>
   <l>The choisest Straines that flow from <hi>Helicon,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And rape me up with Raptures 'yond the pitch</l>
   <l>Of vulgar thought; my obtuse minde enrich</l>
   <l>With quick Invention, for I have a taske</l>
   <l>Beyond my skill, therefore your ayde I aske.</l>
   <l>Be then propitious unto my designes,</l>
   <l>And prompt my thoughts, that I in <hi>strenuous Lines,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>
And words compacted by your proper paine,</l>
   <l>May gaine excuse; yet lest I should prophane</l>
   <l>The sacred worth of those <hi>Faire Ladies,</hi> who</l>
   <l>May claime all honour as their proper due,</l>
   <l>What <hi>Attributes,</hi> what <hi>honour'd Titles</hi> shall</l>
   <l>My trembling <hi>Tongue,</hi> my <hi>Faculties,</hi> and all</l>
   <l>My lab'ring <hi>Senses</hi> study to conferre</l>
   <l>On their Rare worths, who scarce know how to erre?</l>
   <l>Call I them Ladies? why their Sexe doth claime</l>
   <l>The proper Title of that Gentile Name:</l>
   <l>Stile I them <hi>faire ones?</hi> of an <hi>Angels</hi> hue,</l>
   <l>That's but their right, I give them but their due:</l>
   <l>Say I th'are vertuous? why their actions show</l>
   <l>It most apparent, and the world doth know</l>
   <l>I should but flatter, if I should confine</l>
   <l>My Tongue to style them <hi>Goddesses divine:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Though others use it, pardon me, not I,</l>
   <l>I have no power for to <hi>Deifie,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Though I adore yee, and would sacrifice</l>
   <l>My Life to serve yee: what shall I devise,</l>
   <l>What shall I adde, or what shall I expresse</l>
   <l>To sound your praises? Oh I must confesse</l>
   <l>It is a Subject for an <hi>Homers</hi> Quill,</l>
   <l>By farre transcending my unlearned skill:</l>
   <l>M' Invention's dull, or is it so sublime,</l>
   <l>To touch your worths, you being most divine:</l>
   <l>What new-coyn'd Titles, what unheard of straines</l>
   <l>Shall I then frame, to blazon forth your fames?</l>
   <l>Alas, I'de best strike saile, waft to the shore,</l>
   <l>And Anchor there, not dare to venture o're</l>
   <l>This Sea of Honour, 'lesse I had the Art</l>
   <l>Of <hi>Heraldry,</hi> your Titles to impart,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Or skill to blaze them in their sev'rall Tables</l>
   <l>Drawne out with <hi>Or,</hi> with <hi>Argent,</hi> and with <hi>Sables;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Gules, Furres,</hi> &amp; <hi>Azure, Bands, Barres, Chev'rons, crosses,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Bulls, Beares,</hi> and <hi>Lyons,</hi> with the well-shap't <hi>Horses:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Or that my <hi>Barke</hi> were better rigg'd and trim'd,</l>
   <l>Or that I had a fairer gale of winde</l>
   <l>T' embreath the sailes of my most slake Invention,</l>
   <l>And so transport me with quick apprehension.</l>
   <l>And now more than my Tongue can style yee, know</l>
   <l>I am oblieg'd and eke engag'd to show</l>
   <l>Unto the prospect of your glorious eyes,</l>
   <l>The sighs, the sobs, the woes, the miseries</l>
   <l>Of tortur'd <hi>Arnalt,</hi> who doth living dye</l>
   <l>Through th' unkindnesse and strange cruelty</l>
   <l>Which faire <hi>Lucenda</hi> shews him: this his Fate</l>
   <l>He doth intreate you to compassionate,</l>
   <l>And to bewayle his suff'rings, to complaine</l>
   <l>Of her neglect and tyrant-like disdaine,</l>
   <l>Which is the cause of his afflicting smart,</l>
   <l>And of the tortures which infest his heart.</l>
   <l>Oh if you chance but ever to distill</l>
   <l>A Pearle-like teare, he doth beleeve it will</l>
   <l>Be of such force, that it will mollifie</l>
   <l>Her flinty heart, convert her cruelty</l>
   <l>To courteous kindnesse, move her to repent</l>
   <l>Her peevish coynesse, cause him sweet content.</l>
   <l>Then oh yee Rare ones, since yee thus may save</l>
   <l>Our ill-intreated Lover from the grave,</l>
   <l>Expresse your pitty, oh bewaile his fate,</l>
   <l>Taxe the unkindnesse and invet'rate hate</l>
   <l>Of coy <hi>Lucenda,</hi> blame her for neglect:</l>
   <l>Oh tell her, tell her, that such true respect</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="7"/>
She doth not merit, since she still disdaines</l>
   <l>His profer'd love, his service, and his paines:</l>
   <l>And let the beames of your bright goodnesse shine</l>
   <l>Also faire Ladies on these Lines of mine,</l>
   <l>Which though unworthy of your gracious view,</l>
   <l>Vouchsafe to read, they being sent to you;</l>
   <l>'Twill please sad <hi>Arnalt,</hi> and exhilarate</l>
   <l>His pensive thoughts; perhaps 't may recreate</l>
   <l>Your fancies wearied with excesse of pleasure,</l>
   <l>But 'twill reward me with too rich a Treasure,</l>
   <l>And so engage me, that I shall not know</l>
   <l>How to obsolve the Debts the which I owe</l>
   <l>Unto your worths, for why, they cannot be</l>
   <l>Repay'd without some new-coyn'd Mystery:</l>
   <l>Thus with my Booke I kisse your faire white hand,</l>
   <l>And at the Barre of your just knowledge stand</l>
   <l>To heare our Doome; it's you must Judgment give</l>
   <l>If by Oblivion we shall dye, or live</l>
   <l>With Fame eterniz'd: give your <hi>Verdict</hi> then,</l>
   <l>And with it life in spight of envious men.</l>
   <l>Say you'l protect it, say 't shall take a nap,</l>
   <l>Encurtain'd closely in your silken laps:</l>
   <l>Grant this sweet Ladies unto him who stil</l>
   <l>VVill be obsequious to your honour'd wills,</l>
   <l>Yea, unto him, who ever will remaine</l>
   <l>More than your servant, well knowne by the name</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>of <hi>L. L.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>