<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The first Preface to the friendlie Reader.</title>
           <author>Read, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100216_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20850</idno>
           <idno type="STC">723</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100216</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The first Preface to the friendlie Reader.</title>
                 <author>Read, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most excellent and compendious method of curing woundes in the head, and in other partes of the body : with other precepts of the same arte, practised and written by that famous man Franciscus Arceus, Doctor in phisicke &amp; chirurgery: and translated into English by Iohn Read, chirurgion. Whereunto is added the exact cure of the caruncle, neuer before set foorth in the English toung. With a treatise of the fistulae in the fundament, and other places of the body, translated out of Iohannes Ardern. And also the description of the emplaister called dia chalciteos, with his vse and vertues. With an apt table for the better finding of the perticular matters, contayned in this present worke</title>
                 <author>Arcaeus, Franciscus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cadman, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 119, 1 leave, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The first Preface to the friendlie Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough (as I doubt not) euerie good mā will enterpret this worke to none other ende, but to be for the cōfort of them that are wounded, sore, and diseased, and will esteeme no lesse of mee, by whome they profite, then they will be glad to receaue the benefits. Yet forasmuch as it is impossible to auoyde the teeth of malitious enuie, I thought it not vnnecessarie to preuent the furies of some, which are euer gnawing and byting vpon them that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any good sciences. To those I protest, that in all my labours and studies, I neuer entended or yet do entend to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the mindes of any such picke-faultes, which will doe nothing but detract and iudge others, snuffing at all that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth the nōses of their momish affections, how laudable soeuer it be otherwaies.</p>
   <p>But as M. Hunton in his Epistle to M. Bannester saide most true, that enuie lieth alwaies at vertues gate, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n on her heeles whē she goeth abroad. And as the deafe cannot discerne the sweetnesse of Musicke: so the ignorant cannot looke into the excellencie of knowledge. For there is in these daies many that are so wilfull in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, that being reproued for their ignoraunce, sticke not to threaten with woords, swordes, Curtelases, and Daggers, to wounde, cut, slash, yea and kill such good men who are painefull studients and labourers in the Arte.</p>
   <p>As I red of that good man Maister Iohn Hall of Maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, who although he were a skillful man, and of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertues in the Arte of Chirurgerie, yet for speaking against the deceiptfull sorcery of one Robart Harris, in An. Dom. 1556. He had a dagger drawen at him, as himselfe doth declare in his expostulations.
<pb facs="5"/> And also it is credibly reported, that in Anno domini 1574. One Master Bactor a man of good knowledge, both in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke and Chirurgery, for the reprouing of the great abuses of one Fower Akers, he had a sword drawen at him as hee trauailed on the waie, and likelie to haue beene spoyled, had not other trauailers asisted him. I may well veryfie the sayings of good Master Bannister, who doth explaine their diuelish practises, hauing neither learning, knowledge, modestie, nor honistie. And yet practise abroad their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed deceipts vnder the colour of admittance from the Hall of London, and some from others being in aucthory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, of which sort I could name a great number, which for modesties sake, I omit. A thing greatly to be lamented that those which are or should be the fathers of arte, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders of good artists, should so slightly passe their license to such ignoraunt asses, to maintaine them, not onely in coosining her Maiesties subiects of their monie, but often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times depriue them of their lims, yea and also their liues. But it is no meruaile, for monie is sweete, and what is it but Lucre may doe? for I my selfe talking with one of the same companie and felowship, complayning vppon the abuses thereof, in passing their licenses to such, made me this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere. In deed quoth he it is not well, but we were as good to take their monie, for they would play the knaues neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse. Surely his aunswere was truer then he wist, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a matter most lamentable. For whereas by the good and godly lawes of the realme, they are prohibited from practising or medling in the arte without license, (before the which should goe and approbation as well as examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) now for sooth for monie they may buy them a cloake to coeuer them from the lawe, and to play their partes at will. Yet among the rest, I know some one of small lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and lesse knowledge, who hauing trauailed 180. miels to fetch a seale weying fower pound besides the a purtenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces therevnto belonging, whereby he is growen so farre in
<pb facs="6"/> loue with himselfe, and so vndiscretlie doteth ouer his owne doinges, at his returne, that he maketh is trauell and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest as he thinketh, ordinary table talke, for he walked from Tauerne to Tauerne, and from Alehouse, to Alehouse, with his licence at his girdle closed in a boxe, as though hee had beene the proctor of some spitefull house) aggrauating the matter so monstrouslie, as if he had endured the verie labours of olde Hercules, and no meruaile, for when hee had made his market, and receaued his letters of marte, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in companie wth some others, and grewe in speeches of practise (for there vppon he standeth, but his method is small) did not sticke to confirme, that Arsenick and rusty Bacon, was a present remedie for wounds made with goon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shot. And being an other time demaunded by a learned Doctor in Phisicke how a wound came to be an vlcer, was stricken dum. And yet of like he might aunswere his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations well. For that (as he saith) he was vsed so fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly, and plast amongest the best. A meane surely to embolden him well. For he was but bashfull when he was before the worshipfull Doctor. And yet will not sticke to make himselfe comparable to any, and will impudentlie cracke, that any man shal neuer attaine to do the like cures as he hath don, with a great deale more of shameles cōparisōs. There are others of the kinde of young Cuckoose, or as nuseled Snakes, which flie with Isops Crowe, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pluct the winges, would faine deuoure the bird.</p>
   <p>But leauing them to their blindnesses, and praying vnto God for their amendment, my purpose is heere to do them good that haue neede, that is to distribute in english to them that are vnlearned, parte of the treasure that is in other lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uages, to prouoke them that are of better learning, to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their knowledge in such like attemptes: finally to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that to the vse of many, which ought not to be secret for lucre of a few, and to communicate the fruite of my labours, to them that will gentlly and thankefullie receiue
<pb facs="6"/> them, which if any be so proud or supercilious, that they immediatlie will despise, I shall friendlie desire them, with the wordes of Horace: Quod si meliora nouisti candide im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perti, si non his vtere mecum.</p>
   <p>If they know better, let vs haue part: If they doe not, why repine they at those which meane well? why condemne they the thinges that they cannot amend. Or if they can, why dissemble they their cunning? How long would they haue people ignorant?</p>
   <p>Why grutch they Chirurgerie should come foorth in English? would they haue no man to know but onely they? or what make they themselues? for if Galen the Prince of this arte being a Grecian wrote in the Greeke: King Aui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene of Arabia in the speech of the Arayans: If Plinius, Celsus, Serenus, &amp; other of the Latines wrote to the people in the Latin tongue: Mercellus Ficinus (who all men assent to be singulerly learned) disdained not to write in the Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an tongue: generally, if the intent of all that euer set foorth any noble studie, haue beene to be read, of as many as woulde: what reason is it, that we should huther muther heere among a few, the thing that was made common to all? Christ sayeth: no man lighteth a Candell to couer it with a Bushell, but setteth it to serue euery mans turne; and these goe about, not onelie to couer it when it is lighted, but to quench it afore it bee kindled (if they might by mallice) which verie well veryfieth the sayings of Maister William CLOWES in his last edicion De Morbo Gallico, whose wordes are these.
<q>
         <l>No man can lead so iust a lyfe,</l>
         <l>No worke be writ so true:</l>
         <l>That can escape their sqinting eyes,</l>
         <l>Or passe their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>luish view.</l>
      </q>
      <pb facs="7"/> which as it is a detestable thing in any godly science: so me thinketh in this so necessarie an arte, it is exceeding damnable and diuelish, to debarre the fruition of so inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable benefites, which our heauenly father hath prepared for our comfort and innumerable vses, wherewith he hath armed our impotent nature, against the assaultes of so many sickenesses, whereby his infinite mercy and abundant good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is no thing els more apparantly confessed, by the which benefites, as it were with most sencible argumentes, spoken out of heauen, he constraineth vs to thinke vpon our owne weakenesse, and to knowledge that in all flesh is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but miserie, sickenesse, sorrowes, sinne, affliction, and death: no not so much strength as by our owne power, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue one member of our bodies diseased. As for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of medicines, comfort of hearbes, mayntenance of health, prosperitie and life, they be his benefites, and proceed of him, to the ende that wee should in common, helpe one another, and so liue together in his lawes and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in the which doing, we shall declare our selues to haue worthelie employed them, and as fruitefull seruaunts, be liberally rewarded. Otherwise, vndoubtedly the talent which we haue hidden, shall be digged vp, and distributed to them that shalbe more diligent, a terrible confusion before so high a Iustice, and at such a court, where no wager of lawe shall be taken, no proctour limited to defend the cause, none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception allowed to reproue the witnesse, no councell admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to quallifie the gloses, the verie bare text shall bee there alleadged.</p>
   <p>Cur non posuisti talentum in fenus? Why hast thou not bestowed my talent to the vauntage. These and such other examples haue enforced me being oftentimes exercised in the studie and practise of Chirurgerie, to follow the good endeuours of other good men, who haue tasted of the same cuppe of enuie, as their predecessours haue done. And shall I perswade my selfe to escape the same? No, for as I am cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly
<pb facs="7"/> enformed by my verie good friends, that my booke was not so soone at the presse, as enuie euen readie to repine at the same. But being warned, I will be the better armed, &amp; with my friends and predecessours, stande to the brunt of their brutish and malitious tongues. And nothing bee discouraged at them, for I know those that are godly and well disposed, will curteously except of euerie good and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable attempt. And for the malitious, small regard is to bee giuen, for I doe perceaue that now in our time, no good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise can be gone about, but false detraction and enuie is readie to ouerthrow the same. For what are they that haue written both in auncient and later times, but they haue tasted of this beastly broode, and enuious sect? Yea and of such men that haue as it were dandled them in their lappes.</p>
   <p>For I cannot onely speake by experience of my selfe, but also by certaine knowledge of some others, that breding vp vnder our selues such impes, who we did not onely giue sufficient maintenance vnto, but also did impart vnto them those things which we by long studie and chargeable labour had found out. But when (as they thought) there was no more to be gotten, and them selues sufficiently furnished, being gone from their Maisters, were presently puffed vp in pride, and being better perswaded of them selues, then of their carefull teachers, forgetting from whence they sucked their milke, goe about by all meanes (as much as in them lieth, to the aduauncement of their owne glorie) to seeke the ouerthrow of their Maisters credits.</p>
   <p>But vnhappie are those men which nusell such whelpes, or hath such fire brands, but surely they doe but kindle coles to burne them selues, for their rewarde shalbe to haue the like seruaunts, to serue their owne turnes.</p>
   <p>For as our Sauiour Christ saith: <hi>such bread as we breake, shalbe broken to vs againe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But no douht as we hatched euill seruaunts, so some haue bred good.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <p>And as in reproouing the euill, I wish not the good to bee offended, contrariewise, in praysing the good, I wish the euill no parte thereof. For if good menne in times past haue beeue mooued with good concience, for knowledge sake, and for the better maintenance of their common wealth in setting foorth this Arte (in our vulger tounge) for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, comfort, succour, helpe, and health of such as are sicke, deseased, or otherwise wounded and hurt in the warres, or by some mischaunce, why should they be so enuied at, yea euen of those which haue pluckt fetherse from their winges, and hath not been ashamed to vse them among their owne. But these that haue so learned of Dedalus, to frame wings by Arte, which could not be had by nature, let them take heede least by playing with other birds fethers, not skilful to vse the same, they receaue the reward of Icarus.</p>
   <p>But as the wise man saith, it is a skabbe of the world, to bee enuious at vertue: for enuie groweth vp among ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</p>
   <p>The poyson which Serpents continually doe keepe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any harme to themselues, they spewe out to others destruction. But the malitious contrariewise, hurteth no man so much as themselues.</p>
   <p>But I count him most wicked, that it malitious against his friend. But enuie walketh not alone, but is commonlie conioyned with his associates, as slaunder, ignoraunce, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishnesse, lying, and flatterie, which I will knyt together in these verses following, in as briefe manner as I can, hoping that when they shall feele their imperfections touched, they will the sooner forsake that vnchristian-like vices, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the godlie and vertuous.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <lg>
      <l>Enuie and slaunder, are two mischieuous vices,</l>
      <l>And knit still in vnitie to a wicked ende,</l>
      <l>To defame or kill, they are full of deuices,</l>
      <l>They regard no estate, be he foe or friend.</l>
      <l>Enuie all empayreth, and doth nothing amend,</l>
      <l>Dignitie, welth, and worldly felicitie,</l>
      <l>Doth cause cruell enuie to be in many.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Ignoraunce of the soule, is verie madnesse,</l>
      <l>Which while it alboureth, the trueth to attayne,</l>
      <l>Is confounded and wrapped in heauinesse,</l>
      <l>Through selfe knowledge and feeblenesse of brayne.</l>
      <l>Yea, this is also mosT euident and playne,</l>
      <l>That as ignoraunce is bred by idlenesse,</l>
      <l>Euen so is errour by ignoraunce doubtlesse.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>There is to mankind, no greater enemie,</l>
      <l>And that more hindereth his estimation,</l>
      <l>Than the lothsome burthen of beastly follie,</l>
      <l>Which plainely appeareth in ech condition.</l>
      <l>Fooles are ouerthrowen with their light affection,</l>
      <l>And as Corne vpon stones is sowen in vayne,</l>
      <l>Euen so are good counsailers to a foolish brayne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The soule with lying is often infected,</l>
      <l>As with a pestilent and hurtfull maladie,</l>
      <l>The soule in that state is knowen to be wicked,</l>
      <l>Wherof shame or reason is thonelie remedie,</l>
      <l>And as great tellers of newes are seldome credited,</l>
      <l>So lyers and bosters, are alwaies despised.</l>
   </lg>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <lg>
      <l>Of slaunderers and flatterers take heede if you will,</l>
      <l>For neither tame, nor wilde beasts can bitte vs so ill,</l>
      <l>But of all wilde beastes slaunder is the most bitter,</l>
      <l>And of the tame, most biteth a flatterer,</l>
      <l>For a man much better is among raueners,</l>
      <l>To fall, and betaken, then among flatterers,</l>
      <l>For Rauens but of flesh dead bodies doe depriue,</l>
      <l>but flatterers deuore men while they be aliue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Flattery from friendship is hardlie disseuered,</l>
      <l>Being mutuallie knit with the affects of the minde,</l>
      <l>Busie bodies and pickthankes are not to be trusted,</l>
      <l>As wise men their subteltie will quicklie out finde.</l>
      <l>Nobles by flatterie are often made blinde,</l>
      <l>And as wormes in soft wood doe breed most gladly,</l>
      <l>So gentell and noble wittes, are hurt by flatterie.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Irefulnes or wrath is a most cruell vice,</l>
      <l>Accursed of good men hatefull and ouglie,</l>
      <l>Repugning peace that sweete vertue of price,</l>
      <l>Which knitteth both God and man in amitie,</l>
      <l>It is contrary also to humanitie,</l>
      <l>And as the Godlie and wise doth detetest it,</l>
      <l>So the wicked and foolish doth embrace it.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>But enuie is so sprung vp in these our dayes, that it greu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the enuiouse to see another doe well, and lesse doth their owne mishappes trouble them then their neighbours good sucsesse. And therefore the Philosopher Archelaus saide vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an enuious man which was verie sorowfull. I know not well whether euill haue chaunced to thee or good to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: signifying thereby, that enuiouse men are as sorofull for others prosperitie, as for their owne aduersitie. Well, I can but lament the abuses of these dayes, for as soone as
<pb facs="9"/> God layeth his visitacion on vs, we foorthwith runne to some witch, or sorcerer, who forthwith affirmeth the parties are taken, or else if they can hearer of a runnagate straunger skumming ouer the Countrie, although they neither know from whence he came, nor whether he will. He shalbe soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner trusted of them then their owne countrie men, be they neuer so learned or skilfull. Yea, and will rather trust them with their liues, then with an obligation of xx. pound. And no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e trulie so welcome now as they. As for example in this yeere 1587. There came a flemming into the Cittie of Gloceter named Woolfgange Frolicke, and there hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foorth his picture, his flagges, his instrumēts, &amp; his letters of marte with long lybells, great tossells, broad seales clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in boxes, with such counterfet showes and knackes of knauerie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oosening the people of their monie, without either learning or knowledge.</p>
   <p>And yet for mony got him a license to practise at Bristow: But whē he came to Gloceter &amp; being cald before some be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in aucthoritie, by my selfe &amp; others, he was not able to aunswere to any one poynt in Chirurgerie, which being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and the man knowen, the matter was excused by way of Charitie, to be good to straungers. And besides as I vnderstand there is in the Cittie of London one Peter Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, a Duch man borne, an impudent bragger, for by chaūce he was called to a Gentilman to cure a Gangrena, &amp; for that he would haue straunge remedies, in stede of others, he applied to the greeued place Butter, small Ale or stronge beare, a medicine sure fit vnto his skill. And no meruaile it is, for I had thought the flemmings ad either deuoured in their owne bellies, or send it some other way, our eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Beare and Butter, but I perceiue as it is good foode, so it is with them wholesome medicine.</p>
   <p>And that maketh it with vs so deere, and especially where they dwell.</p>
   <p>But let any of vs goe about to practise among them in
<pb facs="10"/> their countrie, they would sone expell vs either by lawe or by sword.</p>
   <p>But we cherish them, that deuour vs. There is an other springing vp, who degressing from his countrie guise im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitating the Spaniard, and leaning so nere the same, that he got the healpe of a French man to be his Barbar, who studied so long in the schoole of falshood, that by his deepe insight in mineralls, he obtained such knowledge, that hee passed Paracelsus, for by his skill, hee framed such a Pill, that as many as receaueth the same, hee shall neuer more after be sicke nor lame.</p>
   <p>And for the great vertue thereof, I thought it good to set downe the composicion, because all men shall either vse or shun the same: &amp; it is this Rec Turbith Simple, g.iii. antimonij Preparati, g.30. Mercuri Sublimati, g.j.ss. this was apointed to be giuen in conserua Roses, for all diseases, the pestilence excepted.</p>
   <p>And then to giue it in Theriaca and Romachi. The experiēce of this pill cost some full deere. Wel I say no more but a paire of good Peters, which pearce Plowman neuer knew. But these abuses raignes not in Chirurgery onely, but also in Phisicke.</p>
   <p>For now whether he be scholler, or scholler not, Bache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, or Bacheler not, Master, or Master not, Doctor, or Doctor not, all is one, and as much is the one excepted as the other.</p>
   <p>For if he hath but serued any worshipfull Doctours, or other learned men in Phisicke, will not be ashamed to take vnto himselfe as good a title as his learned Master, yea although he were a Conny keper. As I hard the iudgement (of one that taketh vppon him the highest title of a Phisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) that he gaue in the vrine of a woman that was deafe, that she had about her heart, an impostume, or a peece of flesh hrowing which stopped her gearing, and therefore she was not to be cured, but he could ease her.</p>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <p>This I leaue to the learned to iudge, whether he bee a Doctour, or Doctour not. I will therefore forsake the prouing of so manyfest a thinge as this vice is, and returne vnto thee (god reader) whom I haue already offended in exceeding the length of a preface, like vnto a wayfaring man, who when he had vndertaken a long iourney, stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled euen in the very threshold of his doore.</p>
   <p>But I know not how it commeth to passe, yet we see it daylie, that ridiculous toyes, and absurd pamphlets being put foorth, are very pleasantly excepted. Whereas a man being moued with honest care to profit his countrie, and to leaue some testimony of the same behind him, doe publish any worke, it behoueth him to show some reason for his doinges, or else it will not yeelde his hoped for benefit.</p>
   <p>Which is to be construed and perused with humanitie, so that if a man couet to haue his bookes fauorablie excepted and read, he must behaue himselfe in writing, as Solon did in framing his lawes.</p>
   <p>Who (as Plutarch saith) did not fashion them according to the true line of equitie, but set downe such as he thought the people would willinglie obserue: euen so the iniquitie of the time hath brough to passe, that those bookes which are generally perused and read throughout, must not serue the time, but satisfie the opinions of men.</p>
   <p>A man may easilie discourse of this, but the fantasies of men are to variant to peruaile a whit in diswading them.</p>
   <p>But if it might, I would perswade some one from his purpose.</p>
   <p>For it is secretlie giuen out, and wih no little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe, that CALMETEVS shall in hast bee publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in ENGLISH, but I would the good man who hath taken the pains, had at his conuenient leysure, first haue read Maister Bannisters bookes of vlcers, &amp; of tumors
<pb facs="11"/> against nature are wounds, and conferred them together with Calmetius, might so haue saued his laobur, for there shall hee see the flowers of Calmeteus so cleane gathered, that he which comes after shalbe faine to brouse vppon the bare shrubbs. Vnlesse he do it againe for tery-fiyng the good olde Gentleman (who hath alredy taken the paines) and to bring him out of conceite with that he hath done, which I thinke will hardly bee. But for mine owne parte that I may now ende, I haue not sought or hunted after vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie by the publishing of this my labour, but onely I haue endured by this meanes being vnable any waye else to doe some good to my Countrie, which desire of mine shall sufficientlie comfort me, though I want the outward approbation of the world. And yet this one thing I would craue at the hāds of the learned, that if my boks by chaunce come vnder their censure, they wil either giue it their good word, or else suffer themselues to bee Iudged off by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourming the lyke labour.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Vale Iohn Reade Chirurgian.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>