<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100623_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11769</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22063</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100623</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The philosophers banquet : Newly furnished and decked forth with much variety of many severall dishes, that in the former service were neglected. Where now not only meats and drinks of all natures and kinds are serued in, but the natures and kinds of all disputed of. As further, dilated by table-conference, alteration and changes of states, diminution of the stature of man, barrennesse of the earth, with the effects and causes thereof, phisically and philosophically. Newly corrected and inlarged, to almost as much more. By W.B. Esquire</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Vavasour, Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 364, that is 362 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Culinary arts</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <l>THe <hi>Back</hi> and <hi>Belly,</hi> two unsounded seas</l>
   <l>Oreslow al goodnesse of these later daies,</l>
   <l>The new Saints worship'd since the old went downe,</l>
   <l>In Church, in Court, in Citie, and in Towne:</l>
   <l>With such devotion, that men now attend</l>
   <l>Not houres appointed, but whole ages spend</l>
   <l>In these Idolatries rendring more due</l>
   <l>Then blindfold zeale e're tendred to the true.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Sloth, Pride,</hi> and <hi>Pleasure</hi> cleave so neare the skin,</l>
   <l>They make each single birth a trebletwin:</l>
   <l>Incorporate so in body and in blood,</l>
   <l>To thousand vices, but small grains of good:</l>
   <l>Let but conceit thrast forth a strange attire</l>
   <l>In <hi>France,</hi> it sets three kingdomes straight a fire;</l>
   <l>Which leave not burning till they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted downe</l>
   <l>Lordships and patrimonies of renowne:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
Melted the earth, and Chimick't into gold,</l>
   <l>Done that which none e're did, but one wee hold</l>
   <l>Proceeded further in more strict degree,</l>
   <l>Conuerted Gold in't Gards of Gallentree:</l>
   <l>And still like <hi>Alchimists</hi> toyling the <hi>Stone,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ll <hi>gold,</hi> and <hi>silk,</hi> and <hi>earth</hi> and all is gone.</l>
   <l>Let but a <hi>Hellen</hi> of some meane degree,</l>
   <l>Of farre lesse beuty, more vnchast than shee,</l>
   <l>Inhabit <hi>wildernesses</hi> under ground,</l>
   <l>If shee be false and faire, she shall be found:</l>
   <l>Let <hi>Gluttony</hi> at howres neare so unmeet,</l>
   <l>Slighted all Circumstance weight by discreet,</l>
   <l>Whilst wary <hi>Cautions,</hi> with most strictest heed,</l>
   <l>Being all observ'd, are lesse oft then we need,</l>
   <l>Sit downe full charg'd to overcharge it more▪</l>
   <l>A thousand dangers waiting at the doore:</l>
   <l>Yet notwithstanding all her fearefull guard</l>
   <l>There she arrives, and will not be debard:</l>
   <l>Let <hi>Bacchus</hi> keepe his <hi>Cyder</hi> in a cell,</l>
   <l>Resort shall croud him wheresve're he dwell</l>
   <l>Let him dig <hi>mountains,</hi> be they ne'r so high</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
Vnto the roots where there soundations lye,</l>
   <l>And like to artfull <hi>Pioners</hi> worke deeper,</l>
   <l>To keepe their liquor stronger, cooler, sweeter;</l>
   <l>Industrious <hi>Porters, Coblers, Tinkers,</hi> Swaine,</l>
   <l>Will wind it vp with their eternall paines,</l>
   <l>With <hi>Wheeles</hi> and <hi>Buckets,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ch not night nor day,</l>
   <l>Shall even rest going up or downe the way,</l>
   <l>Whilst paths vntraced, former steps vni rod,</l>
   <l>Become as <hi>Dunstable,</hi> more worne, more broad:</l>
   <l>But should an <hi>Angell</hi> to no other end</l>
   <l>But only this, from heauen to earth descend,</l>
   <l>To tell the world of sicknes in her health,</l>
   <l>T'informe her that shee's poore for all her wealth,</l>
   <l>To give new <hi>Rules,</hi> and contradict the old,</l>
   <l>Though ne'r so bad his Custome should be col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>,</l>
   <l>And though his doctrine should confute the crimes</l>
   <l>That have consum'd whole ages in their times</l>
   <l>Noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ng it were, his paines should bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="4"/>
With crouds most strangely wondring, not regarded:</l>
   <l>Let Vertue courted in her best array,</l>
   <l>By learning with all titles that she may,</l>
   <l>Appeare so glorious, that the Suns bright eye</l>
   <l>Suffer ecclipse in her resemblancy:</l>
   <l>Vpon whose glorious person and attire,</l>
   <l>Heaven might looke gracious, and the earth admire</l>
   <l>Yet this sweet virgin vertue, <hi>learning art,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Deck'd with the marrow of the world, &amp; art</l>
   <l>Not not crept into in least particular sense,</l>
   <l>In skirts and Borders of small consequence</l>
   <l>But by some signe of man, and proofe of wit,</l>
   <l>When after many yeares o're-take not it;</l>
   <l>Yet after tedious houres, and toyled braines,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Dayes, nights, &amp; Books, Costs, thoughts</hi> and endlesse paines.</l>
   <l>It being arrested, and laid hold upon,</l>
   <l>At the whole suit of mankind should be none</l>
   <l>To joyne in action to maintaine a Tryall,</l>
   <l>In joynt approuement 'gainst so strong denyall</l>
   <l>He that could seite in likenesse of a face,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="4"/>
Being well accoultred and set out to grace</l>
   <l>The meanest matter, thought e're bred in braine,</l>
   <l>It should be descanted and read againe.</l>
   <l>Making his comma's (in his portrait w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>fe)</l>
   <l>Some pretty nose, his per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ods l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ke to eyes:</l>
   <l>If that prevaile not, what would then be better</l>
   <l>To hang <hi>Bacchus</hi> clusters, sparkling ore each letter?</l>
   <l>Or both together, sure that would not misse,</l>
   <l>For they are twins, embrace, and love to k sse:</l>
   <l>And all our hot bloods, both with strength and might,</l>
   <l>Pursue them endlesly both day and night.</l>
   <l>Bidding vs crosse all <hi>Bookes</hi> and <hi>Lines</hi> deface,</l>
   <l>Blot out our <hi>Sentences,</hi> and give them place:</l>
   <l>And then successe our Labor shall attend,</l>
   <l>Crowning our undertakings with good end.</l>
   <l>These though wee know impossible to doe,</l>
   <l>To run with humor we jumpe neare unto.</l>
   <l>Placing some part of <hi>Venice</hi> in our booke,</l>
   <l>As of <hi>Geneva</hi> we have tane a nooke.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="5"/>
Here's wicked women, as the one hath so;</l>
   <l>And here are vertues as the others show:</l>
   <l>Here are strong drinkes, your <hi>Beere,</hi> your <hi>Ale,</hi> your <hi>Wine,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Your choyce of <hi>meats,</hi> your <hi>grosser</hi> and your <hi>fine:</hi>
   </l>
   <l>And <hi>widowes</hi> with their heapes of hoarded gold,</l>
   <l>That would beo Lad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ed, though a month to hold:</l>
   <l>And here's good company, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>scourse at will,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Phylosophers, Physicians,</hi> arguing still:</l>
   <l>Sociates for every man, meanes for digestion;</l>
   <l>Can we want custome then, who makes a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion?</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>