<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE FRENCH STATIONER TO the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100002_Ba2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20993</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7367</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100002</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE FRENCH STATIONER TO the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the court or Instructions for courtiers : Digested into two books. Written in French by the noble, and learned iuris-consull Monsr Denys de Refuges, Councellor of Estate, and many tymes ambassador (in foraigne parts) for ye two last French kings his masters* Done into English by Iohn Reynolds</title>
                 <author>Refuge, Monsieur de (Eustache)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lee, William 2</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 189, 21, 189, 63 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="227"/>
   <pb facs="227"/>
   <head>THE FRENCH STATIONER TO the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riendly Reader, here I giue thee the third Edition of this excellent Treatise of the Court, sith I haue found it very pleasing and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to thee, except onely to some who found fault, that they were frustra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as they say) of the Marginall Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the second Edition, which indeede the Author himselfe had carefully and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inserted, rather by graue Authorities to confirme his opinion in the matters he alleaged and treated of, then that it was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise needfull. Wherefore to content both the wise and curious, I haue imprinted and anexed them by themselues at the end of the last booke informe of Annotations; assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my selfe, that if thou prie narrowly into them, thou shalt find them more corrected</hi>
      <pb facs="228"/>
      <hi>and reformed, and better rangd and ranck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their proper places, with their true col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of passages, then they were in the first Originall which I recouered, and also in many places augmented and illustrated far richer, then in any of the precedent Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereof I thought good to aduertise thee, that thereby thou accept and take in good part the care and diligence which I haue had to please thee, and to giue, thee full satisfaction in all points which concerne my selfe.</hi>
   </p>
   <trailer>Farwell.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>