<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE FOVNDATION and spring of all holy prayers and christian meditatiōs ought to be faith. Behold where fore we shall set heere in the entrie, the ar∣ticles of our faith, which some call the sym∣bole of the Apostles, as in deede they con∣teine a summarie of the Apostles doctrin, as is to be sene of that which is written in the 15. Chap. of the 1. vnto the Cor. vers. 3. &amp; elswhere: &amp; it is to be seene by the writings of the elders (as by the cathechisme of Cy∣rill, and the treatise of S. Ambrose, of Cayne and Abell, and in the 8. Chap. of S. Augustines booke named Enchiridion that is to say Manuel) that these Articles of the faith were holden amongest them as the true beginninges, and foundation of Christian religion.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S100748_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13837</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24144</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S100748</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE FOVNDATION and spring of all holy prayers and christian meditatiōs ought to be faith. Behold where fore we shall set heere in the entrie, the ar∣ticles of our faith, which some call the sym∣bole of the Apostles, as in deede they con∣teine a summarie of the Apostles doctrin, as is to be sene of that which is written in the 15. Chap. of the 1. vnto the Cor. vers. 3. &amp; elswhere: &amp; it is to be seene by the writings of the elders (as by the cathechisme of Cy∣rill, and the treatise of S. Ambrose, of Cayne and Abell, and in the 8. Chap. of S. Augustines booke named Enchiridion that is to say Manuel) that these Articles of the faith were holden amongest them as the true beginninges, and foundation of Christian religion.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The exercise of the faithfull soule : that is to say, prayers and meditations for one to comfort himselfe in all maner of afflictions, and specially to strengthen himselfe in faith: set in order according to the articles of our faith, by Daniell Toussain, minister of the worde of God: with a comfortable preface of the author, vnto the poore remnant of the Church of Orlians; containing a short recitall of extreme and great afflictions which the said church hath suffered. Englished out of French, almost word for word, by Ferdenando Filding</title>
                 <author>Tossanus, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Denham, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>56, 338, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="articles">
   <pb facs="22"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THE FOVNDATION</hi> and spring of all holy prayers and christian meditatiōs ought to be faith. Behold where fore we shall set heere in the entrie, the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our faith, which some call the sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole of the Apostles, as in deede they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine a summarie of the Apostles doctrin, as is to be sene of that which is written in the 15. Chap. of the 1. vnto the <hi>Cor.</hi> vers. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; elswhere: &amp; it is to be seene by the writings of the elders (as by the cathechisme of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill,</hi> and the treatise of <hi>S. Ambrose,</hi> of <hi>Cayne</hi> and <hi>Abell,</hi> and in the 8. Chap. of <hi>S. Augustines</hi> booke named <hi>Enchiridion</hi> that is to say <hi>Manuel</hi>) that these Articles of the faith were holden amongest them as the true beginninges, and foundation of Christian religion.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beleeue in God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther almightie, maker of heauen and earth. And in Iesus Christ his onelie
<pb facs="23"/> sonne our Lord. Which was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the Holie Ghost, borne of the virgine Marie. Suffered vnder Ponce Pilate, was crucified, dead &amp; buried, he descended into hell. The thirde day he rose againe from the dead. He ascended into heauen, and sitteth on the right hand of God the Father Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie. From thence shall he come to iudge the quicke and the dead. I beleeue in the Holie Ghost. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Catholike Church. The commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints. The forgiuenesse of sinnes. The resurrection of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. And the life euerlasting. Amen.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>IN the yeare of our Lord</hi> 273. <hi>in the Synode of</hi> Antioch, <hi>was condemned the heresie of</hi> Samosatenus, <hi>who would not auowe Iesus Christ to be the worde subsisting: but made thereof a sound or decree of God, not a seconde person of his diuinity: in such sort as against his errours was published a confession by</hi> George Neocoefariensis, <hi>as is to be seene in the</hi> 3. <hi>booke of</hi> Eusebius.</p>
   <pb facs="23"/>
   <p>
      <hi>IN the yeare of our Lord about</hi> 332.<note place="margin">1. Synode called vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall.</note>
      <hi>was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> Constantine <hi>the Great assembled a Synode, or Councel, to the assisting whereof there were</hi> 328. <hi>Bishoppes at</hi> Nice <hi>a citie in</hi> Bythinia, <hi>there where was chieflie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the heresie of</hi> Arrius: <hi>who dinied the true sonne of God equall with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the same substance. In this Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node were made plaine and cleare against</hi> Arrius <hi>the Articles of faith which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Iesus Christ by a confession as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beleeue in one God,<note place="margin">The Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol of Nice.</note> the Father Almightie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of heauen and earth, and of all things visible and inuisible.</p>
   <p n="2">2 And in one Lorde Iesu Christ, the onely begotten sonne of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of his Father before all worldes.</p>
   <p n="3">3 God of God, light of light, verie God of verie God: begotten, not made, beeing of one substance with the Father, by whome all thinges were made.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <pb facs="24"/>4 Who for vs men, and for our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, came downe from heauen.</p>
   <p n="5">5 And was incarnate by the Holie Ghost, of the virgin Marie, and was made man.</p>
   <p n="6">6 And was crucified also for vs, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Poncius Pilate, he suffered and was buried.</p>
   <p n="7">7 And the thirde day he arose againe according to the Scriptures, and ascended into heauen, and sitteth at the right hand of the Father.</p>
   <p n="8">8 And he shal come againe with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to iudge both the quicke and the dead, whose kingdome shall haue none ende.</p>
   <p n="9">9 And I beleeue in the holie Ghost, the Lorde and giuer of life, who proceedeth from the Father and the Sonne, who with the Father and the Sonne together, is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped and glorified, who spake by the Prophets.</p>
   <p n="10">10 And I beleeue one Catholike and Apostolike Church.</p>
   <p n="11">11 I acknowledge one Baptisme, for
<pb facs="24"/> the remission of sinnes.</p>
   <p n="12">12 And I looke for the resurrection of the dead, &amp; the life of the world to come. Amen.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>IN the yeare of our Lorde</hi> 386.<note place="margin">Seconde Councell.</note>
      <hi>there assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at</hi> Constantinople <hi>the second Synode called vniuersall, which confirmed and ratified the confession made at</hi> Nice, <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding onely that which followeth against the heretike</hi> Macedonius, <hi>who denied the true diuinitie of the holie Ghost:</hi>
   </p>
   <p>We beleeue in the holy Ghost Lorde and giuer of life, proceeding from the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the sonne, who with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; the sonne together is worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and glorified.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>HEere followeth the Symbole or confession of</hi> Athanasius <hi>Bishoppe of</hi> Alexandria, <hi>being chosen fiue monthes after the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell held at</hi> Niece, <hi>who hath abiden great combats for the pure doctrine of the sonne of God against the</hi> Arrians.</p>
   <pb facs="25"/>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hosoeuer will be saued: before all things it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie that he holde the Catholike faith.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Which faith except euerie one doe keepe holy and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed: without doubt hee shall perish euerlastingly.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And the Catholike faith is this: that we worship one God in Trinitie, and Trinitie in vnitie.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Neither confounding the persons: nor diuiding the substance.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> For there is one person of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, another of the Sonne: and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Holie Ghost.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> But the Godhead of the Father, of the Sonne, and of the Holie Ghost is all one: the glorie equall, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie coeternall.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Such as the Father is, such is the Sonne: and such is the Holie Ghost.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The Father vncreate, the Sonne vncreate: and the Holie Ghost vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create.</p>
   <pb facs="25"/>
   <p>The Father incomprehensible, the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Sonne incomprehensible: and the Holie Ghost incomprehensible.</p>
   <p>The Father eternall, the Sonne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> eternall: and the Holie Ghost eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
   <p>And yet they are not three eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> but one eternall.</p>
   <p>As also there bee not three incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensibles, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> nor three vncreated: but one vncreated, and one incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible.</p>
   <p>So likewise the Father is almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> the Sonne almightie: and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghost almightie.</p>
   <p>And yet they are not three almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> but one almightie.</p>
   <p>So the Father is God, the Sonne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> is God: and the Holie Ghost is God.</p>
   <p>And yet are they not three Gods: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> but one God.</p>
   <p>So likewise the Father is Lord, the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> Sonne Lorde: and the Holie Ghost Lorde.</p>
   <p>And yet not three Lordes: but one <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/>
      <pb facs="26"/> Lorde.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> For like as wee be compelled by the Christian veritie, to acknowledge euerie person by him selfe, to be God and Lorde: So are wee forbidden by the Catholike religion to say there be three Gods or three Lords.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> The Father is made of none: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther created nor begotten.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> The Sonne is of the Father alone: not made nor created, but begotten.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> The Holie Ghost is of the Father and of the Sonne: neither made, nor created, nor begotten, but procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> So there is one Father, not three fathers: one Sonne, not three sonnes: one Holie Ghost, not three holy Ghostes.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> And in this Trinitie, none is afore or after other: none is greater, nor lesse than another.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> But the whole three persons bee coeternall together and coequall.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> So that in al things, as is aforesaid:
<pb facs="26"/> the vnitie in Trinitie, and the Trinitie in vnitie, is to be worshipped.</p>
   <p>He therefore that will bee saued, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> must thus thinke of the Trinitie.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, it is necessarie to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> euerlasting saluation: that hee also beleeue rightly in the incarnation of our Lord Iesu Christ.</p>
   <p>For the right faith is, that wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> and confesse, that our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, the sonne of God, is God and man.</p>
   <p>God of the substance of the father, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> begotten before the worldes: and man of the substance of his mother, borne in the world.</p>
   <p>Perfect God, and perfect man: of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> a reasonable soule: and humane flesh subsisting.</p>
   <p>Equall to the Father, as touching <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> his Godhead: and inferiour to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, touching his manhoode.</p>
   <p>Who although he be God &amp; man, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> yet he is not two, but one Christ.</p>
   <p>One, not by conuersion of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/>
      <pb facs="27"/> Godhead into flesh: but by taking of the manhoode into God.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> One altogether, not by confusion of substance, but by vnitie of person.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/> For as the reasonable soule &amp; flesh is one man: so God and man is one Christ.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/> Who suffered for our saluation, descended into hell, rose againe the third day from the dead.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> He ascended into heauen, he sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on the right hande of the father, God almightie.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/> From whence hee shall come to iudge the quicke &amp; the dead.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> At whose comming all men shall rise againe with their bodies.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="41"/> And shall giue account for their owne workes.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/> And they that haue done good, shal goe into life euerlasting: and they y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> haue done euil, into euerlasting fire.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="43"/> This is the Catholike faith, which except a man beleeue faithfully, hee cannot be saued.</p>
   <pb facs="27"/>
   <p>
      <hi>IN the thirde generall Councell which was assembled at</hi> Ephesus <hi>vnder the Emperour</hi> Theodosius <hi>the younger about the yeare of our Lorde Iesus Christ</hi> 450.<note place="margin">The third counsell.</note>
      <hi>was refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and condemned the errour of the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike</hi> Nestorius: <hi>the which would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with the Christian Church, whē as the worde became flesh, that the two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs diuine &amp; humane were knit in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or substance, and that vnseparablie: But did teach howe they were onely knit by an assistaunce or dwelling together: whereof he would not auowe that the virgin hadde borne the sonne of God, or that the sonne of God had suffered for vs. That which was to make nothing euen all the mysterie of our redemption: if he which was borne of a virgin, and hath suffered for vs, had not beene true God: hauing personally knit vnto himselfe our nature, after the which hee was borne of the virgin and hath suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on the crosse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>In the fourth generall Councell, in which did the Emperour</hi> Martianus <hi>assist at</hi> Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon: <hi>was condemned the heresie of</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiches <hi>the monke: the which monke fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another extreme errour contrarie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that of</hi> Nestorius: <hi>in such sort knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="28"/> the two natures in Christ as hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeth them, and in place of a person, he leaueth as it were but a nature: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Fathers of the councell to make cleare this matter, did set out the confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion which followeth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Wee confesse and acknowledge one one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Iesus Christ our Lorde: perfect in diuinitie and also in humanitie, verie God, and verie man, of a reasonable bodie and soule: equall to the Father as touching his Godhead, and coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with vs as touching his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode, and like vnto vs in all thinges sinne excepted: begotten of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before the worldes according to his Diuinitie, and in the latter dayes begotten of the virgine <hi>Marie</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Lord, for our sakes and for our saluation as concerning his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: One onelie and also Sauiour in two natures, without confusion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion, diuision, and separation: The differēce of natures be not takē away through the vnion, but rather the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of both natures being kept con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring in one person or substance: not to diuide them into two persons, but
<pb facs="28"/> to the end that hee alone might be our onelie Sauiour: as the Prophetes haue prophesied thereof, and he hath taught vs, and the Symboles of the Fathers confesse him.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>It is to bee noted that although the said Symbols and confessions are amongest the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes, yet notwithstanding they cease not to persecute to the vttermost those which with all their heartes beleeue the alone comprised Doctrine: Wherein is to bee seene that they haue not those confessions but vpon the paper, for they doe not beleeue in them: and that in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stead to be the true Catholikes, they persecute them. For as wee see in the</hi> Code <hi>of</hi> Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian <hi>and in the</hi> 9. <hi>booke of his tripartite histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the</hi> 7. Chap. <hi>The</hi> Gretian <hi>Emperours,</hi> Valentinian <hi>and</hi> Theodosius <hi>made an Edict and declaration, that they would hold those for good Christians and good Catholikes, which followed the Doctrine that was taught by</hi> S. Peter, <hi>and did beleeue in the Trinitie and of Iesus Christ according as it is here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore said. Nowe men doe not hold them for Catholikes, vnlesse one beleeue the blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Pope and of his traine, who sitteth in the Temple of God, as a God, making lawes at his pleasure, and profaning the pure ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the Lorde.</hi>
   </p>
   <list>
      <pb facs="29"/>
      <head>Here follovveth the consideration of the first Article of our faith, conteining manie goodlie Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</head>
      <item>Of Faith.</item>
      <item>Of the Trinitie.</item>
      <item>Of the Creation.</item>
      <item>Of the Prouidence.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>