<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translator of this Spanish Dialogue to his Honest louing learned Friend A. V.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101792_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14254</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24569</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101792</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translator of this Spanish Dialogue to his Honest louing learned Friend A. V.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sacke of Roome : exsequuted by the Emperour Charles armie euen at the natiuitie of this Spanish Kinge Philip. Notablie described in a Spanish dialogue, with all the horrible accidents of this sacke, and abhominable sinnes, superstitions &amp; diseases of that cittie, whic prouoked these iust iudgements of God. Translated latelie into the English tounge, neuer fitter to bee read nor deeplier considered, then euen now at this present time</title>
                 <author>Valdés, Alfonso de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jeffes, Abel</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ward, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Translator of this Spanish Dialogue <hi>to his Honest louing learned Friend</hi> A. V.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing in some publique imploimēts not long since so ouertoyled my selfe, as I found my liberty of returne to my former delectable studies and recreations, a very Paradize in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the Hel of Enuy and Mallice wherein I had beene long iniurious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with many stormes turmoiled: among other histories and pleasant discourses that at idlest times I read for recreation, this Spanish Dialogue receiued from you, so pleased me, as partlie for exercise of that toong, but chieflie for the singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar good liking I had of the matter, and to passe ouer some melancolye conceipts (wherinto the ingratitude of some persons, at whose handes I had but to well deserued, had throwne me) I began to translate the same into English, following as nigh as I could the verie Spanish letter, sauing in such phrases as in our toong haue neyther grace nor sence.</p>
   <p>The Treatise surelie is such, as being read of our nation, could not but worke singular good effects, euen in our most obstinate moderne peruerse Papists, seeing it so pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pablie reuealeth the horrible errors and abuses of that their corrupted Romane religion, or rather putrified super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition (most vniustlie by them misnamed Catholike or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicall) and that by a couple of their owne Spanish partie: notsomuch by scriptures sacred, where vnto they generally beare so small reuerence, as by euident demonstrations &amp; such inuincible reasons as were able to reduce very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Paynims to a better sence: and the Method and stile such, as if I could deliuer it in English with that grace it
<pb facs="3"/> hath in the Spanish, were no lesse delectable then profitable and not vnfit for other due respects to be printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished euen in this our time: that as euen at the natiuitie of this aspiring <hi>Philip</hi> King of Spaine, their cheefe Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Almightie God miraculouslie stirred vp a little armie of their owne religion, iustlie to chastice the hatefull pride of that Babilonicall Sea, when her treacherie was not growne to that heigth of hellish wickednesse, it hath since aspired: So the memorie thereof reuiued by the due consideration of euery perticuler accident, cause, and circumstance, so wittily discussed and liuely represented in this discourse, (conferred with the horrible treasons and villanies in this age, before our eyes committed by that Sea, euer sithence hatching continually new rebellions of subiects, murthers of annointed Kings and Princes, Massacres of Christian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, destruction and subuersion of kingdomes, &amp; common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales, tending finallie to the vtter dispeopling &amp; desolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Christendome, being mounted euen to the heigth of her impietie, and ripe for ruine) may nowe likewise ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate &amp; stir vp againe some noble spirits of our time before or at the death of the same <hi>Phillip</hi> their chiefe Abbettour,<note place="margin">Instat Clima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctericus eius &amp; babilonica Clades.</note> and mainteiner, to attempt and atchieue the like, or a more glorious godly honourable enterprise, causing all men of right sence, no lesse to abhorre these diuelish practises and practisers, then their damnable wickednesse indeed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serues: the which my traduction now finished, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to your correction and disposition: and so leaue you to your Theologicall or Metaphysicall muses, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full protection of the Almightie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>