<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101694_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19560</idno>
           <idno type="STC">599</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101694</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Institutiones piæ or directions to pray : also a short exposition of the Lords Prayer the Creed the 10 Com [m] andements Seauen Penitentiall Psalmes and Seauen Psalmes of thanksgiuing. by HI</title>
                 <author>Andrewes, Lancelot</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 405, 5 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous and Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, accept I pray thee, these
few obseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of <hi>Meditations</hi> and
<hi>Deuotions;</hi> which at the first, I intended for my owne priuate vse:
but since, considering with my selfe, that <hi>Bonum quò communius
eò melius,</hi> Euery good thing is the better for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing communicated.
I thought to publish it for the publique vse of them, who shall affoord
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues so much time, as to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme<pb facs="3"/>those Duties, which
are contained in it. The Heathen man could say, <hi>A Ioue prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium:</hi>
to the shame of many (I will not say) of those, who professe
themselues, and would be called <hi>Christians:</hi> who are so farre
from beginning all their actions with <hi>Gods</hi> ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, as that it is a
rare thing, to see them attend it at all.</p>
   <p>It is no maruell then, if <hi>God</hi> with-hold his hand of
goodnesse from our Land, or if (according to the <hi>Prophet</hi>) <hi>He
hide his face from vs.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 88 14.</note>when we are
so remisse, so dull, either in seruing him with <hi>the Dutie</hi> of
<hi>Praise</hi> and <hi>Thankesgiuing</hi> for his <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits</hi>
past, or with the <hi>Seruice</hi> of <hi>Prayer,</hi> for his
<hi>Prouidence</hi> and <hi>Goodnesse to</hi> come.</p>
   <p>Wee can talke of <hi>Comets</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>and
<hi>apparitions</hi> in the ayre, and be stricken with <hi>wonder:</hi> we
can speake of <hi>vnseasonable</hi> and <hi>tempestuous</hi> times, and
bethinke our selues of what dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, famine, and the like iudgements,
may ensue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, with <hi>griefe:</hi> wee can discourse of
<hi>warres, rumors of warres,</hi> and mightie prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations abroad, with
<hi>feare:</hi> and yet wee are so stupid, and sencelesse, that wee
cannot see or discerne, the true cause of all these occasions <hi>of
wonder, griefe, and feare,</hi> namely our <hi>sinnes:</hi> at least if we
doe, yet we set not our selues, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the cause, by that
whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some remedy, which <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe hath prescribed to
remooue it, if wee would but apply and vse it. We thinke it enough, if wee
can talke of the <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>(and it is somewhat if we doe
that) and haue the <hi>specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> how to rid our selues of the
<hi>disease:</hi> but for the <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise</hi> of it, it fares with vs,
as with those, who haue an infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie growing vpon them, and know the
remedy; but either for <hi>wāt of leasure, or for the queasinesse of
the stomach,</hi> or the <hi>bitter</hi> or vnpleasing taste of the
<hi>medicine,</hi> they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the taking of it, till the disease
<hi>grow incurable.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>We are content to heare, what <hi>the Phisician of our
soules</hi> prescribeth vs, but wee neglect the <hi>Diet,</hi> which hee
enioyneth vs. All our <hi>Religion</hi> depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on the <hi>Eare:</hi> and
(so it had pleased <hi>God</hi> to haue giuen vs but an <hi>Eare</hi> to
heare) hee might haue spared the <hi>tongue</hi> and <hi>lippes</hi> to
praise him, and<pb facs="4"/>all the other parts to worship, and reuerence
him: wee could haue beene well enough con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, with that member a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
   <p>But <hi>(beloued) let vs not deceiue our selues:</hi> for hee
that hath made the <hi>Eare</hi> to heare, what good hee hath done vnto vs,
hath made the <hi>tongue</hi> also, to confesse, his due praises, for
that which he hath so done. And if wee neglect to giue him due thankes for
his <hi>Mercie;</hi> it will come to passe, and that (to bee feared) very
speedily, that wee shall bee forced, in bitternesse of soule, to
confesse his <hi>Iustice,</hi> when we shall finde, that hee iustly
tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his <hi>Blessings</hi> into <hi>Curses</hi> and
<hi>plagues,</hi> and be compelled to acknowledge and say, <hi>Iust art
thou O Lord, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,<pb facs="5"/>and iust are thy
Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And therefore in time, let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of vs recollect himselfe,
and in his priuate <hi>closset</hi> or chamber with himselfe, and in the
<hi>Church</hi> with the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation humbly confesse his sinnes to
<hi>God,</hi> desire pardon for them, praise him for his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings,
pray him to continue them, and deprecate his iust anger from vs: and then no
doubt, but he will be graciously pleased, to bee mercifull to vs, and heare
vs, and auert those Iudgements from vs, which we most iustly haue
deserued. Which let vs all, againe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, beseech him to doe, for the
merits and intercession of his Blessed <hi>Sonne,</hi> and our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
<hi>Sauiour, Iesus Christ.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>