<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND
MIGHTIE PRINCE,
HENRY, Prince of Great
BRITAINE.</title>
           <author>C., J.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101746_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00430</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10561</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101746</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND
MIGHTIE PRINCE,
HENRY, Prince of Great
BRITAINE.</title>
                 <author>C., J.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Catholique traditions. Or A treatise of the beliefe of the Christians of Asia, Europa, and Africa, in the principall controuersies of our time : In fauour of the louers of the catholicke trueth, and the peace of the Church. Written in French by Th. A.I.C. and translated int English, by L.O</title>
                 <author>Eudes, Morton</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Morrant, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 96, 99-235, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND
MIGHTIE PRINCE,
HENRY, Prince of Great
BRITAINE.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MY GRACIOVS LORD.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat Attempts become great
Princes. And is there a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
or a more worthy enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise,
more holy in it selfe,
and more comfortable to the
world, then the re-establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of peace in the Church,
and the refreshing of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome,
through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement
of the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
which ignorance, auarice
and ambition haue hatched,
and which passion and stomacke doe as yet maintaine? And is
there any Prince more worthy for the sincerity of his life, more
capable for his solide iudgement, and rare knowledge in all
good sciences, especially in those that belong to God, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse,
<pb facs="3"/>
then that great King your father, the nurs-father of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning?
Who I say, more fit for this great businesse then Hee, as
well for his eminent dignitie, power, credite and authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst
the Christian Princes of the West, as also for the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
which he hath in the managing of the like affaires, hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
already well nigh pacified those diuisions, which the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
scruple of some, and the too too much libertie of others
had brought into the Church of England; vnto the which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,
he hath also most happily reduced the Church of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
to be conioyned and re-vnited both in discipline, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies;
that he may attainne to that marke which he aimes
at, that is, a holy and strict vnion, as well in the religion, as in
the state of all the people and Countries vnder his obedience?
Who I say, can with more hope of good successe vndertake so
excellent a peece of worke, then he, whom the heauens haue
so richly endowed with such rare qualities, as I haue sayed, and
other perfections truely heroique, and admirable! And you my
renowned Lord, after him, and with him for to second him in
such a goodly and honourable enterprise, seeing that already
by reason of the generosity of your spirit, the happy education
of your youth, the imitation of so rare an example, and that at
home, and of your owne Father: and aboue all the rest, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of the bountie and courage of your nature; you are the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
hope of great Britane, and make men expect great and
mighty desseignes at your hands, and such shal be profitable to
all Christendome: and (if it please God) to be one day a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall
instrument to tame these damnable Monsters of wicked
factions and pernitious sects, which haue almost made a spoile
of the body of Christ his Church; yet not so much doubtlesse
through the diuersity of beleefes in the matter of faith, which
is the soule and essence of religion (for the which we are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to praise God) As for the differences of Ecclesiasticall rytes
and ceremonies, whereof your highnesse shall see here a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne
or plat-forme, established only to shew to the world, that
in the three other Clymates, yea euen among the blind Pagans
and impious Mahometists, the name of the Sonne of God is
<pb facs="3"/>
knowne and called vpon, if not with so much puritie, yet sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
with more pietie (although that their doctrine is not so sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly
expounded) then amongst vs: and shall be more and more
(God willing) toward the end of the world, according to the
Propheticall and Euangelicall promises; and in the issue to
conuince and confound those which doe empale and enclose
the Church of Iesus Christ, within the circuite of their walles,
or within the limits of one Prouince, or else within the regions
of those people, who hold one selfe same opinion, and are obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
to one chiefe or head aboue all other. Iesus Christ is
the grand Soueraigne, and vniuersal Patriarch of al his Church:
and the holy Ghost saith, that it neither hath, nor shall haue
any other bounds or limits, then the whole compasse of the
round world: and which is more, that it shall haue his presence
and assistance for euer; although (for the ingratitude of men)
not at all times, nor in all places with like glorie, and efficacie.
The Sunne neuer ceaseth to shine vpon the earth, but not euery
day and in euery place, with the like brightnesse. This enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise
of Reconciliation (my gratious Lord) hath been attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
not once or twice, but often in ages past, as well by calling
of Councells, as by publicke conferences; as for example, that
with the Donatists, through the mediation of Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> at
Carthage, where the end was happie enough, and might in
some sort serue for a paterne in the differences of this age; as
also the conference at Ratisbon, vnder the authority of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour
<hi>Charles</hi> the fift, for Germanie: and for Fraunce that
at Poisi in the raigne of <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth.</p>
   <p>And besides these publicke meetings and conferences, there
haue beene found learned, iudicious and moderate men, not a
a few from time to time, who bearing a great zeale to the
peace of the Church, haue opened and shewed certaine meanes
and wayes, euery one according to his knowledge and consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:
But these discoueries of the trueth, haue found no place
in the hearts of them that were lead with passion; but will (by
all possibilitie) bring foorth better fruit hereafter in their due
season; that is to say. When as God being first ouercomeby
<pb facs="4"/>
our Repentance, Cries and Prayers, shall cause that lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Schisme to cease, being one of the greatest Plagues that
euer happned or could happen among Christians. Your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
shal see by marking that which I haue here compiled out
of them and their writings, how the difficultie of reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
for a great part of our controuersies, whether it be with
the East or South Churches, or between our selues of the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterne
Churches, lies not so much in the things themselues
which fall in question, as in the peruerse opinion of the dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants:
and that those things wherein we agree, are a thousand
times of more importance, to the glorie of God, and our salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
then those things wherein we varie and disagree; and
shall haue farre more reason to loue vs for those things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
we agree, then for to hate and persecute vs cruelly for those
things, which remaine as yet to be auoided from among vs:
yea seeing the greater part of our disputations, happen for
want of vnderstanding the state of the controuersies in questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
or els by reason of our termes and fashion of speaking:
but farre more for want of conceiuing the true sense of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Scripture; which also some great men of our time haue she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
manifestly, in certain points of doctrine, which were iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
irreconcileable: wherein was manifested Gods iustice against
our sinnes of presumption, curiosity, vaine-glory, enuie, auarice
and ambition. I say the more, because Princes and Soueraigne
Magistrates should beare sole authority, and by their abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
commaundement should testifie their good will therein,
and employ the prudent aduise of their Ecclesiasticall subiects,
not the wisest onely, but the best and godliest also, not so much
to dispute and winne the victory, as to conferre, and amiably
to agree: The God of peace will giue the fruit of peace, to his
glory and our good. But I know not by what Inchantment or
destinie, Kings for the most part know not their forces, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
do dispoyle themselues of a greate part of their owne
Authoritie, and many times perceiue it too late. As for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,
many doe know and see the euill, but doe perswade
themselues, that the remedie is most dangerous of all: or else
<pb facs="4"/>
for feare, will not bee singular in opinion, be it neuer so good,
louing rather to suffer themselues to bee caried away with the
torrent and streame of diuision, and to be of the common fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion,
that they may the better follow their priuate affaires. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
one doth bragge and vaunt himselfe of his faith, but few
or none will practise charitie, and what is faith without chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
more then a tree without fruite? or a body without a soule?
I haue beene here emboldened to addresse my selfe to your
Highnesse, for the reasons aboue said; and to the end that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the lustre of your name, this little Treatise, written onely
for the publike vtilitie, might be the more fauourably receiued
and respected of all men, especially of the subiects of the kings
Maiestie your father; amongst whom are more learned Diuines
well practised in the art of disputation, in the reading of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
and in all the Histories of the Church, then (peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture)
in three or foure other as great Countries. Their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
doe testifie it, insomuch that wee doe admire thereat in
these parts; and the English Liturgie gathered according to
the modell of the Auncients, the purest of them; in the which
through the aduise of so many excellent men in learning and
pietie, English men and others, hath beene reserued for reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
of Antiquitie, all which might be left with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science.
Also it is very likely that it shall endure perpetually,
and serue for a patterne or example for those which are not
as yet reformed: The praise whereof (next vnto God) shall be
to the good and wise Kings of Great Britane; the Predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors
whereof haue receiued and embraced with the first, the
faith of Iesus Christ, and not with the last, the Reformation
which was necessary in the Church: The principal cause truely,
or rather the only cause of this long peace &amp; prosperity, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
God hath blessed the Kingdomes of your Iland, besides
many benedictions wherewith he hath fauoured your Royall
house, and your Highnesse in particular, who haue after his
Maiestie the first place in age, in valour, and dignitie, and who
for the gratious respect which naturally you doe shew vnto all
<pb facs="5"/>
men, which through any merite or seruice doe seeke the honor
of your fauour, will mooue you (I am assured) to receiue
this little present, as from him, who will thinke himselfe
happy all the dayes of his life to say,
({inverted ⁂})</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Highnesse
most humble, and most
obedient seruant,
Th. A. J. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>