<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>M., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101429_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07224</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17621</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101429</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>M., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Reasons monarchie. Set forth by Robert Mason of Lincolnes Inne Gent</title>
                 <author>Mason, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 136, 8 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He farre traueller by Sea, vseth his Carde and Instruments, &amp; all his indeuoure, to finde out the course of a long and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous voiage. Wherein, the vncertaintie of the thing hee seeketh, causeth him often to faile his purpose. But in this course which I direct, the Reader shall not haue occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to aduenture any such ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, albeit the matter sought, be as precious, as whatsoeuer. Reason, which euerie man
<pb facs="5"/>should lodge in his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, is it which I aduise to be enquired; whereof, as men, by their originall natures doo participate, so ought they, by their reasonable Discretions, gouerne the whole course of their liues. Her excellencie can not in wordes bee expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, which causeth her rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to bee so slenderly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed: Reason is in the son of God, perfect, pure, &amp; true: But in men, corrupted: what is there that she doeth not in some measure search into? Her viewe pearceth into the
<pb facs="5"/>earth, and all the Elements. The powers of heauen and Angels, into all things that may be comprehended with vnderstanding; And farther, euen into things that are my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall, &amp; aboue the compasse of her selfe: For though shee cannot reach into the depth of eternitie, and the sauing of soules: yet she bringeth to the knowledge of God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe in his mercies (whereby this saluation is wrought) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a mysterie farre aboue the capacitie of men. Whatsoeuer concerneth vs, either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb facs="6"/>of this present world, or otherwise, Reason sheweth, that it was possible to Gods power, agreeable to his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, and mercie, answerable to his will and promises, and beseeming his glory, behoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to manifest our basenesse, &amp; necessarie for our welfare. By her powerfull argument, she is able to put vngodlines it selfe to silence; wherupon it is fitly concluded, that credit is not to be giuen to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward person, but to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine thing within the person: whereby is meant, Reason,
<pb facs="6"/>whose originall purenes, is in some measure hereafter dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered.</p>
   <p>That this right Reason is corrupted in men, none can doubt, if they behold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues truely what they are, in respect of what they should be. Wherfore, if Salomon therby found out the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of his life, and hath not spared to leaue to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like view of the worlde, his errors manifested, and the striuing hee had to reforme the same, no man hath Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to be ashamed, secretly,
<pb facs="7"/>and priuately, in the closet of his owne hart, to view his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions and slidings from reason; and indeuor the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing of his actions to the rule and order of Reason. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating of these things, I haue rather bent my selfe, to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Reader out of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the learned, &amp; Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son her selfe, then vpon any i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations of mine owne. I pray thee therefore take in good part my labor, &amp; good will, &amp; giue the subiect wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I intreate, thy furtherance, howsoeuer thou mayest bee
<pb facs="7"/>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with the maner of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. And let me desire (as Iustus Lipsius in his booke of Constancie) that thou wilt reade twise before thou once censure it; and I shall be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding for thy paines, and wish part of all Gods good blessings towards thee. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy euer wel willing friend, R. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>