<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>E</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101928_Bo1_2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14319</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24636.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101928</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>E</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Englands ioy</title>
                 <author>R. V. (Richard Vennard)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="acrostic_introductory_encomium">
   <lg>
      <head>E</head>
      <l>
         <hi>E</hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Nglands blisse, and blessed <hi>Queene,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>
         <hi>L</hi> Liue your praises in perfection,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>I</hi> In your Subiects hearts bee seene</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Z</hi> Zeale in humble loues subiection:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>A</hi> Angels in your loue attend you:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>B</hi> Blessed <hi>IESVS</hi> euer blesse you,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>E</hi> Euer so his hand defend you:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>T</hi> That no harmfull thought distresse you:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>H</hi> Holy powers of Heau'n preserue you:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>A</hi> And, all faithfull subiects serue you.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>R</head>
      <l>
         <hi>R</hi> Royall Graces euer grace you,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>E</hi> Euer true Loue liue about you,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>G</hi> Glorious Angels armes embrace you:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>I</hi> Ioy in England none without you,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>N</hi> None but Grace, and Vertue note you,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>A</hi> And the world for wonder Cote you.</l>
   </lg>
   <div type="body_of_poem">
      <lg>
         <pb facs="3"/>
         <l>REioyce O England, sing, and clap thy hands:</l>
         <l>For, God himselfe, doth for thy safetie fight:</l>
         <l>No foe so great, but that thy force withstands:</l>
         <l>It is so strengthened by the heauenly might.</l>
         <l>The Irish Rebell and the Spaniardes pride:</l>
         <l>Before thy face doe fall on euery side.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>The Noble Lord, <hi>Mount Ioy</hi> that Champion true<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Of honours choise, in Vertues Chiualrie:</l>
         <l>Hath put to flight, that coward Rebell Crue</l>
         <l>Of proude <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and made the Spaniards flie.</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Don Iohn de Aquila</hi> with all his traine<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>With little comfort are return'd to <hi>Spaine.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>The Irish Rebells, now doe keepe their Caues:</l>
         <l>Amidde the woods; like Wolues or rauening beasts:</l>
         <l>Where all like out-lawes, or vnciuill slaues:</l>
         <l>on grasse and shamrocks, now they make their feasts:</l>
         <l>O England, neuer, better newes can be:</l>
         <l>Then thus to heare, how God doth fight for thee.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Now shalt thou heare of nothing but confusion:</l>
         <l>Vpon the head of all thy harmefull foes:</l>
         <l>Now shall the Rebells finde the full conclusion,</l>
         <l>That in the end of all Rebellion growes.</l>
         <l>And Spaine shall fret, to see his pride puld downe:</l>
         <l>And God preserue, thy Soueraigne &amp; her Crowne.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <pb facs="3"/>
         <l>Now shall the Pope with all his practise faile:</l>
         <l>The hope of Traitors all be ouerthrowne:</l>
         <l>Nor Pope, nor Spaniard now shall none preuaile:</l>
         <l>To doe thee hurt, that but defend'st thine owne<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Now serue thy God, and giue him thanks for all:</l>
         <l>And keepe thy faith, and thou shalt neuer fall.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Be true I say, and faithfull to thy God<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>And euer loyall to thy Soueraigne Queene:</l>
         <l>For whose loues sake, he doth forbeare his rod.</l>
         <l>That hath been long in other countries seene:</l>
         <l>He will not suffer any to destroy thee<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>But ouerthrow their forces that annoy thee.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>In Eighty Eight, how did he by his hand,</l>
         <l>Scatter the Nauie of the Spanish fleete?</l>
         <l>And now in Ireland, in their hoped land,</l>
         <l>How hath he troden their forces vnder feet?</l>
         <l>Where noble <hi>Mount Ioy</hi> in deserued fame<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Eterniz'd hath the honour of his name.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>He beares the Sunne, and like the Sunne he driues:</l>
         <l>Proud swelling cloudes to wander with the winde:</l>
         <l>And vnder our bright Sunne of light he liues:</l>
         <l>Who giues a gratious light to such a minde.</l>
         <l>As, so deserues her Grace, to giue him light<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>That he be euer gracious in her sight.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <pb facs="4"/>
         <l>Now let all harts of happie England praie:</l>
         <l>Vnto our God of glorious mercies power,</l>
         <l>That he will still be our almightie staie:</l>
         <l>Our Rock, our Castle, and our heauenly tower:</l>
         <l>That in his mercie, we may fearelesse liue:</l>
         <l>And to his gratious loue all glorie giue.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Let vs still praie, that he will still preserue<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Our gracious Queene in his eternall grace:</l>
         <l>And giue vs grace both him and her to serue:</l>
         <l>And all vnfaithfull Traitours to deface:</l>
         <l>To spend our liues, but in our countries cause:</l>
         <l>And be obedient, to her blessed lawes.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Rebellion is the sinne of witch-craft nam'd,</l>
         <l>And witches are but Diuells in their natures,</l>
         <l>Oh hellish fiends, to the deuill fram'd.</l>
         <l>Which so deceiue but the accursed creatures.</l>
         <l>Oh cursed sinne that euer man should know thee,</l>
         <l>God blesse all English, and good Christians fro thee.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>And, since that truth, doth trie out euery thought,</l>
         <l>Wherein the depth of euery sence is sounded,</l>
         <l>Against that truth, who hath the Treason wrought,</l>
         <l>That, on vngratious reason hath been grounded.</l>
         <l>What euer fortune for a time doe fall,</l>
         <l>Confusions shame will be the end of all.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <pb facs="4"/>
         <l>Which shamefull end the God of endlesse glory,</l>
         <l>Hath giuen the Rebels and their wicked friends:</l>
         <l>While valiant <hi>Mountioyes</hi> noble victory,</l>
         <l>Truth blowes abroad in fame that neuer ends.</l>
         <l>While <hi>Irish</hi> shrugs, and <hi>Spaniards</hi> frownes doe proue,</l>
         <l>The blisse of <hi>England</hi> in the heauens aboue.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>What shall I saie? the Irish Rebells fled:</l>
         <l>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> gone, with sorrow, shame and losse:</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Tyrone</hi> I hope will shortly loose his head:</l>
         <l>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> glad, to put vp all their crosse:</l>
         <l>Hath tane an oath, to hye them home to <hi>Spaine:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>And neuer wish to bring their Armes againe.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Thus in the Rebell, all hie ruins point<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>The <hi>Spaniard,</hi> staying but a winde for <hi>Spaine:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>
            <hi>Tyrone</hi> in hourely daunger of a ioynt<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>And <hi>Irelands</hi> peace, I hope will growe againe:</l>
         <l>God surely pleas'd in this worke of peace,</l>
         <l>Where <hi>Truth</hi> shall flourish, and <hi>Rebellion</hi> cease.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>God graunt it so, and in his Gracious hand:</l>
         <l>Long blesse the daies, of our deere Soueraigne <hi>Queene:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>And make her Empresse of this blessed land:</l>
         <l>Till no more land within the world be seene:</l>
         <l>And make her Armies, euermore victorious:</l>
         <l>And all her Kingdomes, in thy mercie glorious.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <pb facs="5"/>
         <l>Blesse her Lord <hi>Mount-ioy,</hi> with that <hi>Mount</hi> of Ioy:</l>
         <l>That Noble Truth, in truest Noblenesse:</l>
         <l>May stand so stronge, as nothing may destroy:</l>
         <l>But, in the height of honours happinesse:</l>
         <l>May by the vertue of best valour proued,</l>
         <l>Of God and man, be blessed and beloued.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Blesse all her armie with those fearelesse harts:</l>
         <l>I hat soone may bring the Rebell in subiection:</l>
         <l>And make a iest of all those woodden dartes:</l>
         <l>That doe not loue a steeled coates complexion<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>And quaile the harts, or cut off all the heads<hi>:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>That so the pathe of proud Rebellion treads.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Blesse all her Counsaile, and her faithfull friends.</l>
         <l>Court, Citties, Countries all in such a peace:</l>
         <l>As all the world, that sees proude Traytors ends,</l>
         <l>May cause the root, of all rebellion cease:</l>
         <l>Such peace, and plentie, loue, and concord send:</l>
         <l>That we may sing thy Glorie without end.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Blesse still I pray our gratious Soueraigne <hi>Queene:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>With all the blessings of thy holy Grace:</l>
         <l>And let it neuer in our Land be seene:</l>
         <l>But in thy Mercie we may haue a place:</l>
         <l>Nor <hi>Mount-ioyes</hi> fame die in obliuions penne:</l>
         <l>To all of these, all England say, <hi>Amen.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>