<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST VERTVOVS, DISCREET, AND Noble; the Lady DORO∣THY CRANE, daughter to the right Honorable, and Religious, the Lord HOBART.</title>
           <author>Feltham, Owen</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101827_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00619</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10755</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101827</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST VERTVOVS, DISCREET, AND Noble; the Lady DORO∣THY CRANE, daughter to the right Honorable, and Religious, the Lord HOBART.</title>
                 <author>Feltham, Owen</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Resolues, diuine, morall, politicall b Owin Felltham</title>
                 <author>Felltham, Owen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 327, 3 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST VERTVOVS, DISCREET, AND Noble; the Lady DORO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THY CRANE, <hi>daughter</hi> to the right Honorable, and Religious, the Lord HOBART.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAME,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F euer Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions were needfull, I thinke they
<pb facs="3"/>
be in this Age of loose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; wherein, 'twere some vnhappinesse to bee good, did not the Consciousnesse of her owne worth, set vertue firme, against all dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartnings. This makes her of so specious a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that though shee need not the applause of any, to adde to her happinesse; yet she at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts the hearts of all that know her, to Loue, Seruice, Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.
<pb facs="3"/>
That I haue sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred this offertory of my thoughts to your Ladyship, this is reason inough; if not, your Loue to my dearest friend, may second it. To apparell any more in these paper vest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I should multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply impertinents; and perhaps displease. For I haue euer found face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation to dye Wisedomes cheeke of a blush-colour. Discreet
<pb facs="4"/>
Nature is alway mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest, and deseruing best, loues least to heare on't. This onely I will truely adde: that I know not the thing of that value, should make me shrine vp a worke of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to any, in whom I could obserue, the pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibility of a faile in Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Such a Dedication were to put Vertue to a Stepdame, that would not nurse, but stifle her. With your Goodnesse, I
<pb facs="4"/>
am sure, shee shall finde the tendernesse of a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall loue. And if in these weake extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, your Iudicious eye light you to ought, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creasing that affection (all by-respects put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way) my next Petition will bee: that it may please you to command</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your immutable seruant, OW. FELTHAM.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>