<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>F., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101585_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06065</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1648</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101585</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>F., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The trial of a Christians estate: or a discouerie of the causes, degrees, signes and differences of the apostasie both of the true Christians and false : in a sermon preached in London by Master Paul Bayne, and afterward sent in writing by him to his friend W.F</title>
                 <author>Baynes, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 23, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, good Wine needeth no garland, it will praise it selfe: so (I perswade my selfe) will this ensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermon, which a learned, holy and faithfull seruant of God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <hi>viuâ voce</hi> in publique, soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the eares of me and many, and afterwards, as a token of his Christian loue to me, bestowed vpon me in writing, which being so fruitfull and necessarie a labour, in the iudgement of the godly and learned that haue seene it, and so specially befitting these luke-warme and backsliding times, I thought I could not, without preiudice to thee, suffer it to lie by me for my priuate instruction and benefit alone, and therefore for thy good, the keeping in precious memorie the Preacher thereof, whom the Lord hath gathered into his barne, and for the glorie of God especially, I haue consented that it be made more publique and common, by comming vnder the presse. The Lord grant, that it may haue that successe in mee and thee, which hee that gaue first life vnto it in study<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and brought it foorth by preaching, intended, and I in consenting and causing to haue it printed, desire: so shall the feeble, weake and doubting Christian, be taken by the hand, staied and comforted against the feares of totall back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sliding,
<pb facs="3"/>
and we all shall be of the number of them which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low faith to the conseruation of our soules: which the Lord for Iesus Christ his sake grant. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in his best desires, <hi>W. F.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>