<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all the Reverend Fathers, the Bishops of this lande, &amp; to all the godly learned Ministers of Iesus Christ, &amp; to all the true and faithful favourers of the ho∣lie faith and religion, now publikelie pro∣fessed and maintayned in Englande: IOSIAS NICHOLS the least of the least of all Gods Saintes, wisheth all grace, peace and ioye in belee∣uing.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101326_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08206</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18541</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101326</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all the Reverend Fathers, the Bishops of this lande, &amp; to all the godly learned Ministers of Iesus Christ, &amp; to all the true and faithful favourers of the ho∣lie faith and religion, now publikelie pro∣fessed and maintayned in Englande: IOSIAS NICHOLS the least of the least of all Gods Saintes, wisheth all grace, peace and ioye in belee∣uing.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The plea of the innocent : wherein is auerred; that the ministers &amp; people falslie termed puritanes, are iniuriouslie slaundered for enemies or troublers of the state. Published for the common good of the Church and common wealth of this realme of England as a countermure against all sycophantising papsts, statising priestes, neutralising atheistes, and satanising scorners of all godlinesse, trueth and honestie. Written: by Iosias Nichols, a faithfull minister of the Ghospell of Christ: and an humble seruant, of the English Church</title>
                 <author>Nichols, Josias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 229, that is 241, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To all the Reverend Fathers, the Bishops of this lande, &amp; to all the godly learned Ministers of Iesus Christ, &amp; to all the true and faithful favourers of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie faith and religion, now publikelie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed and maintayned in Englande: IOSIAS NICHOLS the least of the least of all Gods Saintes, wisheth all grace, peace and ioye in belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Good name <hi>(sayeth Salomon)</hi> is to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen aboue greate ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,<note place="margin">Prou. 22.1.</note> and louing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour is aboue siluer, &amp; aboue gold. <hi>Which then is most excellent, when it is founde in the feare of God,</hi>
      <note place="margin">A good report &amp; namely of a minister, is a precius thing.</note>
      <hi>and our light shineth to the glorie and praise of God. But the name of a Minister is yet of more regarde, by whose standing and falling many are drawne, and the reproach of such men reacheth nerest to the heauens, and God is most dishonoured by their dishonour: for he hath said,</hi> I vvill be sanctified in thē that come neere me:<note place="margin">Leuit. 10.3.</note>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>and before all the people I vvill bee glorified.</hi> Howbeit, the Gospell proclaimeth all them blessed, who for Christes sake are reuiled, and against whome, men doe falslie say all maner of euill. For wicked men and infidels speak euill of them, which runne not with them to the same excesse of riotte: and beastlie men will vtter lewd wordes, against those thinges they know not. Heereof it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that many men fall away, beeing not able to be are the reproach: yet he which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth as he speaketh, &amp; knoweth what he beleeueth: he suffereth as a Christian, and is not ashamed, but glorifieth God in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. Notwithstanding when a brother shall reproach his brother,<note place="margin">Christians to reproach one the other, hurtful to the Church.</note> and one Christian ill an other, and the house of God shall be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: then is it most dangerous. For there will the enemie of mankinde, cast in many bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fire brandes and heape on much drye wood, that we might be all consumed one of another. And such (my most reuerend and beloued brethren) hath beene our case and condition:<note place="margin">The state of manie godlie Ministers</note> because we haue desired &amp; sought after the good proceeding and perfection of our Church, in the seruice and worship of Christ, and withholden our hands from doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and allowing of some thinges, in our iudgement, hurtfull to the same, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariant
<pb facs="7"/>to the Ghospell of trueth: Wee haue suffered &amp; endured much reproach and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt: which we haue patientlie borne, and with great silence, for diuers yeares sustay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: that on our part, the sacred worde of righteousnes, might not be ill spoken of and as much as in vs lyeth, wee might cut of all occasions to the common aduersarie, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile against the holy church of Christ, which is among vs. But now it seemeth to me, that notwithstanding all this,<note place="margin">The causes of this treatise.</note> the state of thinges is worse then euer before: and I can not tell whether our conniuence in suffering all euill speeches against vs, hath done the Church harme. For nowe the Papist beginne to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort themselues, yea they challeng vnto them the name of honest and true men and good subiectes: and by the reproachfullname of Puritan, al godlie Protestants are most cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninglie depraued. To haue beene called pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisian, Puritane hoatheaded, proud, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, schismatickes and troublers of the Church, wee haue borne it patientlie (God knowing our innocencie) and could yet be are it more; so as by our suffring of contempt, the Church of England, might receaue honour, and Gods people reioyce vnder good guiding pastoures. But when it is growne so far, that we are called &amp; accounted worse then Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,
<pb facs="8"/>enemies to the state, worse then Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie priestes, like Iesuites, subuerters of the common wealth &amp; enemies to her Maiesties most royall Crowne and dignitie (for whose safetie wee doe continuallie and instantlie pray) and that this is so farre growne, that the traiterous priestes doe brag of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie fauour, and vnder the name of Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans most frandulentlie and with most grosse and palpable lying and slaundring, traduce all Christian Churches: so that wee verely thinke that if such thinges goe forward, they will in a short time cause a most wofull ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the whole state &amp; of the Christian Church among vs: we cannot now forbeare any longer, but that wee must needes shew vnto all the worlde our innocencie: that the wrong which by ill &amp; false report hath bene done vnto vs, thorow our negligēce &amp; want of honest defence, be not made a strong forge and a close mightie engine, to destroy all the happie and godlie proceedinges of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, turning vp side downe the ioyfull flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing of the Christian religion &amp; Ghospell. And we cannot now heale this soare by any priuate doing; for it is spread abroad so vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall, and mens mindes are so vniuersallie possessed therewith, that we haue no way to doe good but to come into the open theater of
<pb facs="8"/>the worlde to pleade for our selues and to make manifest the vprightnes of our cause, against all these most false, vniust and slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous imputations. Let me therefore intreate you all (Reuerend Fathers and Brethren) in godly charitie to receaue this our most iust a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie &amp; with Christian equitie to consider of it, and with heauenlie wisedome waying the estate of the Church, and the present ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie, take euerie thing in that meaning as it is written. And I doe not doubt, but all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the knowne and professed enemie of all goodnes the popish faction, (which nowe these three and fortie yeares haue vsed all cunning treacherie and treasonable plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes, to bereaue her Maiestie (whome God almightie preserue still among vs of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent light and life of this worlde, and all this Realm by that meanes, of the heauenly light and life of the world to come) though I say, these vowed enemies of the Ghospell and of this land, doe freat, chafe and fume; yet shall not you my de are brethren, neither anie ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest Christian and faithful subiect, haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie iust cause, to mislike this manner of writing: but rather (thorow the hande of my God vpon me) finde and think it necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie at this tyme to be published to al Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an people of this English nation. For I doe
<pb facs="9"/>heerein declare and shew, what hath beene our cause and maner of proceeding, and that as plainelie without concealement,<note place="margin">The contents of this booke.</note> and as faithfullie, without partialitie to our selues, as I may boldly auoutch euery thing, to any mans conscience, which wilbe content with trueth and all the trueth: and secondlie how agreing al our cause &amp; doings from time to time, hath bene to the present estate, and her Maiesties proceedings in the Ghospell: Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in clearing our cause and doings of the greatest accusations and imputations, I make it plaine how vnequall and vniust the comparison is, betweene vs and the Papist: and lastlie I doe a little tourch, some other things necessaritie appertaining to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses. Now it may bee that heerein I shall not satisfie all men:<note place="margin">Hard satisfie all men.</note> paraduenture I shall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend some of the reuerend Bishoppes and some other learned Prelates standing for conformitie: and it may bee I shall not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlie answer the expectatation of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ministers, who desire reformation, or of some other wise &amp; learned Christians. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doubtles I haue cause to suspect myne owne insufficiencie. For who can tell how to walk perfectly with the Lord, and yet auoid all occasions of offence, where both the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties haue beene at so hote warre, and where
<pb facs="9"/>there are men of so many contrarie iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and affections? much lesse a man of so little helpes and so small giftes as I haue. How be it I craue the patience and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble taking of this my writing of them both; and I hope they will accept my good will. For in an especiall loue toward both parties I haue taken this in hand: and haue set God before mine eies before them both, that so neere as I coulde and as far as I knowe and am able, I vtter that which is right in his sight, not seeking to please ame man of either side: but endeuouring to doe a worke pleasing to God, and good for his Church, I might mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister occasion of profit to them both. Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that nowe is the time that eyther side shoulde cast of the loue of themselues, and turning their eies from the sweete reflex of their owne prayse, ioyne in one hart against the common enemies, for the peace, increase, perfection and honour of the Church of God in this land. Which my good &amp; honest mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, if I haue not so fully accomplished as I desire, I humble my selfe vnto God, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell heerein vnder his mercie: and I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, vpon good demonstration of my faulte, to make a mends and to satisfie eather par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie. But if their be anye of the reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hers, or of the learned Prelates (which God
<pb facs="10"/>forbid) that bee proude,<note place="margin">I appeale from the proude.</note> froward or malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and will stande stiffe vpon their concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued purpose, seeking them selues and their owne things, and not the glory of God, and the things which are Christs: I esteeme them no further then they deserue; I pray GOD amende them, and turne their heartes. So on the other side,<note place="margin">&amp; renounce all hypocrits.</note> if their bee anye man who seemeth to like reformation, who yet beeing an hypocrite and false hearted, hath anye hidden poyson in him (for it is no rare thing to haue a Iudas among twelue, and false creeping brethren, who woulde bring the Church into bondage, and make a praye of the same) as I knowe none such, so I doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce them in this Apologie, and all other what so euer, that doe not loue her M. with al their hart, and are not true and vpright fauourers of the Ghospell, as it is taught in England by publicke authoritie, or haue in him anye treacherous or wicked purpose a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the same, any maner of way. And I pray God to make them to be knowne: yea if any man bee guilty in his conscience of any euill, let him be ashamed, and let him hide him selfe &amp; seeke the shiftes of wicked men in darknesse.</p>
   <p>But as for vs, our cause is iuste before God, and we haue done no hurt to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie,
<pb facs="10"/>and we know and beleeue, that when the appointed time of God shall come, and his counsell hath sufficientlie tried vs: hee will bring foorth our righteousnesse as the light, and our iudgement as the noone day. Therefore I thinke it my duety without all feare, to open to all the world, what maner of trespassers we are, and to commend to the conscience of all wise, learned, and godlie Christians (when they shall throughlie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand rightly weigh euerie thing as it is) the righteousnes of our cause, and the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightnes of our meaning. O God and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Father, thou iudge of all flesh and sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the heart and raines, send forth thy light and thy trueth, iudge thou the cause of thy seruants, and take it into thy thine owne handes: And cause thy people to returne &amp; discerne betweene the righteous and the wicked, betweene him that serueth God and him that serueth him not. And let thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious countenance shine alwaies vpon this land and vpon thine anointed handmaide, our Soueraigne Queene Elizabeth: defend, protect and guid her, establish thy couenant of peace with her and this English nation for euer, euen the sure mercies of Dauid. For thy holy Sonnes sake Iesus Christ, Amen,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>At Eastwell in Kent</hi>
         <date> this <hi>4. of Iune. 1602.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>