<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE SVMME AND PARTI∣TION OF THE HOLIE BIBLE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101944_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11777</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2207</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101944</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE SVMME AND PARTI∣TION OF THE HOLIE BIBLE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The holie Bible faithfully translated into English, out of the authentical Latin. Diligently conferred with the Hebrew, Greeke, and other editions in diuers languages. With arguments of the bookes, and chapters: annotations. tables: and other helpes ... By the English College of Doway</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2 volumes (20, 1115, 1, 1004, 1, 1002-1124, 4 pages), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>THE SVMME AND PARTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE HOLIE BIBLE.</head>
   <head type="sub">With a brife note of the Canonical and Apochryphal Bookes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>y the vniforme consent of al learned Diuines, the holie Bible,<note place="margin">S. Ierom. Epist. ad Paulin. de omnib S. Scipt. libris. S. Aug. prefat in specul. li. 2. dc doct christ. ca. 9. li. I. de Gen. cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nich. ca. 4. li. de catechiz rudib. c. 3. &amp; 4. l. 2. qq. su per Exod q. 73. li. 15. cont. Faust. Manich. cap. 2. li 18. ciuit. ca 54. de vera re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. c. 27. li. 4. cōt. Faust. ca. 2. S. Greg. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 6. in Ezech. I.</note>
      <note place="margin">How the holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures conteine al knowlege neceslarie to saluation. The old and the new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment shew the same God, Christ, Church and other My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. The old more obscurely, with lesle helpes. The new more expresly and yeldeth more grace.</note> or written word of God, conteyneth Expressed orimplied, al thinges that man is to beleue, to obserue, &amp; to auoid, for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of aeternal saluation. That is, al matters of faith &amp; maners, by which we may know and serue <hi>God,</hi> and so be spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually ioyned with him, in this life, &amp; in eternitie. For both the old &amp; new Testament propose and testifie vnto vs, one and the same God, the same Christ, the same Church, and other Mysteries of our beleefe, not differing in substance, but in maner of vttering; the old more obscurely in figures and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies foretelling those thinges, which the New declareth (in great part) as donne and performed. VVherupon saith S. Augustin: <hi>In the Old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the New lieth hidden: &amp; in the New the Old lieth open.</hi> And touching their names, wherein appareth difference, <hi>the one</hi> (saith the same Doctor) <hi>is called the old Testament, either because it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pofeth promises of temporal thinges</hi> (VVherwith our old corruptnes is allured) <hi>Or in respect of the New, by which it is fulfilled, and in some part abolished. The other is called the New, because by it man is renewed, and hath promise of eternal life:</hi> VVhich shal neuer waxe old nor decay. Likewise S. Gregorie the great testifieth this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie, and correspondence betwen the Old and New Testament, affirming that the same is signified by the prophet Esccbiels vision of an hcele, which had foure faces, or apparence of foure whiles, the shape whereof <hi>was, as it were, a wheele in the middes of a wheele. What is this</hi> saith he, <hi>nisi quod in Testamenti veteris litera Testamentum nouum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit per Allegoriam? but that in the letter of the old Testament, the New lay hidden by an Allegorie?</hi>
      <note place="margin">In both Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are foure sortes of Bookes.</note>
   </p>
   <p>And as the same is the summe and subject of both Testaments: so both are diuided (for the more principal partes therof) into foure sortes of Bookes: <hi>Legal, Historical, Sapiential, &amp; Prophetical.</hi> The Legal bookes of the old Testament are the fiue Bookes of Moises; <hi>Genesis, Exodus, Leuiticus,<note place="margin">Legal.</note>
         <pb facs="9"/>
Numeri, &amp; Deuteronomie;</hi> whereto answer in the new Testament, the foure <hi>Gospels</hi> of <hi>S. Matthew, S. Marke, S. Luke, &amp; S. Iohn.</hi> Historical bookes of the old Testament, are the Bookes of <hi>Iosue, Iudges,<note place="margin">Historical.</note> Ruth,</hi> foure bookes of <hi>Kinges,</hi> two of <hi>Paralipomenon, Esdras</hi> with <hi>Nehemias, Tobias, Iudith, Hester, Iob,</hi> &amp; two of the <hi>Machabees;</hi> vnto which, in the new Testament, answer <hi>the Actes of the Apostles.<note place="margin">Sapiential.</note> Sapiential,</hi> of the old Testament, are the <hi>Prouerbes, Ecclesiastes, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, Booke of wisdome, &amp; Ecclesiasticus;</hi> and of like sorte are in the new Testament, the Epistles of S. Paul &amp; of other Apostles. <hi>Prophetical</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prophetical</note> bookes are <hi>Dauids Psalter</hi> (which is also <hi>Sapiential,</hi> yea like wise <hi>Legal</hi> and <hi>Historical)</hi> the Bookes of <hi>Isaias, Ieremias</hi> with <hi>Baruch, Ezechiel, Daniel,</hi> the twelue lesse Prophetes, <hi>Osea, Ioel, Amos, Abdias, Ionas, Michaeas, Nahum, Abacuc, Sophonias, Aggaeus, Zacharias, Malachias.</hi> And in the new Testament, <hi>the Apocalips</hi> of S. Iohn the Apostle.</p>
   <p>Al these Bookes are vndoubtedly Canonical, as the Authores cited in<note place="margin">Al these books recited are Canonical, and of infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble truth.</note>
      <note place="margin">Cone. Carth. An. Dni 419. Conc. Laodic cap. 59. Florent Instruct. Armen. decret. 7. Trident Sess. 4. S. Atha. in Synop. S. Aug. li. 2. doct Christ c. 8 Isider. li. 6. Ely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mol c. I. &amp; alibi. Nicep. li. li. 4. cap. 15. Euseb li. 5. c. 8.</note> the inner margent testifie. And consequently al, and al the partes therof; are of infallible truth. For otherwise as S. Augustin teacheth, if anie part were false, or doubtful, al were vncertaine. <hi>once admittiug falsehood</hi> (saith he, Epist, 8. ad Ieroni) <hi>in such soueraigne authoritie, no parcel of these bookes should remaine, which anie way should seme hard to maners, or incredible to beleue, but it might by this most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious rule be turned to an officious fiction of the author.</hi> That is: If anie error could be committed by the authores of Scriptures, either through ignorance, obliuion, or anie other humane frailtie, what soeuer were produced, exception might be taken, and question made, whether the author had e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>red, or no? True it is, that <hi>some of these bookes</hi> (as we shal par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly<note place="margin">Apochryphal of two sortes. 1. Not decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red canonical. 2. Reiected as erronious.</note> discusse in their places) were sometimes doubted of by some Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, and <hi>called Apochrypal,</hi> in that sense, as the word properly signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>hidden,</hi> or <hi>not apparent.</hi> So <hi>S. Ierom</hi> (in his Prologue before the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Bible) <hi>calleth diuers bookes Apochryphal,</hi> being not so euident, whether they were Diuine scripture, because they were not in the lewes Canon, nor at first in the Churches Canon, but were neuer reiected, as false or erronious. In which sense <hi>the Prayer of Manasses,</hi> the <hi>third</hi> booke of <hi>Esdras, and</hi> third of <hi>Machabees are yet called Apochryphal.</hi> As for the fourth of Esdras, and fourth of Machabees there is more doubt. But diuers others, as the <hi>booke ascribed to Enoch,</hi> the <hi>Gospels</hi> of <hi>S. Andrew, S. Thomas, S. Bartholmew,</hi> and the like recited by S. Gelasius (Decreto de libris Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticis dist. 15. Can. Sancta Romana) S. Innocentius the first (Epist. 3.) S. Ierom, Ep ad Laetam, S. Augustin li. 15. cap. 23. de ciuit. Dei. Origen homis. 2. in Cantica. <hi>are in a worse sense</hi> called Apochryphal, &amp; are reiected as
<pb facs="9"/>
conteyning manifest errors, or fained by Heretikes. Neither can a Christian<note place="margin">The Holie Ghost decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the Church which Bookes are Diuine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> Catholique he otherwise assured, Which Bookes are Diuine and Canonical Scriptures, but by declaration of the Catholique Church, which without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption<note place="margin">Mat. 28. Ioan. 14. 16. Act. 2. 20 1. Tim. 3.</note> succedeth the Apostles, to whom <hi>our Sauiour promised, and sent the Holie Ghost, to teach al truth.</hi> For if in anie thing more then others, assuredly one chief and most necessarie point is, to know and declare, which Bookes are Gods holie Word: being of most singular importance.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>THE SVMME OF THE OLD TESTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it is distinguished from the new.</head>
      <p>Not withstanding the subiect, &amp; general argument of both Testaments<note place="margin">The old and new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment differ in time. In maner of vttering. Varietie of Precepss. Promises. Meanes.</note> is one &amp; the same in substance, as is already said, yet they differ in time, in maner of vttering of Mysteries, in varietie of precepts, &amp; promises, also in meanes to obserue the thinges exacted, &amp; to attayne to the end pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed,<note place="margin">Temo. 3. quest. 10 Algasiae.</note> In regard wherof S. Ierome saith: <hi>Lex Moysi &amp; omne vetus instrumentum elementa mundi intelliguntur, quibus quasi ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis, &amp; Religionis exordijs Deum discimus. The law of Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and al the old Testament are vnderstood the elements of the world, by which, as by first rudiments &amp; beginnings, we lerne to know God.</hi> For that in it we haue first the Law of nature: and aster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a law written, with promises of temporal rewardes; as long life, land flowiug with milke &amp; honie, &amp; the like; but <hi>it brought nothing<note place="margin">Heb. 7. 9. 10. Gal. 4.</note> to perfection,</hi> as S. Paul saith, <hi>when giftes &amp; hostes were offered, which could not according to conscience, make the obseruer perfect.</hi> For the helpes of that time, were but <hi>infirma &amp; egena elemēta: Weake &amp; poore elements.</hi> Likewise in general, touching the punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments<note place="margin">The old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the new. A continual visible Church from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world to Christ. The same My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical bodie, but different in state. Diuided into six ages. The first age continued. 1656. yeares.</note> that sometimes happened to the people of the old Testament, when they transgressed, the same Apostle affirmeth, that <hi>al the same chanced to<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10</note> them in figure, &amp; are written for our correption, vpon whom the ends of the world are come.</hi> so that the old Testament, or <hi>Law was<note place="margin">Gal. 3:</note> but our pedagogue in Christ.</hi> Yet it setteth forth to vs the whole course of Gods Church, for the space of foure thousand yeares, that is, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world vntil Christ our Redemer. which Diuines diuide into six ages, wherein was varietie &amp; change of her state, three vnder the Law of nature, and three others vnder the written Law. The seuenth &amp; last age being this time of grace (wherin we now are) from Christ, to the day of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Iudgement: as the world was made in six dayes, and in the seuenth God is said to haue rested, and therfore sanctified it, in other sort, then the former six. The eight wil be after the Resurrection, during for al eternitie.</p>
      <p>VVhich six ages of the ancient Church, &amp; old Testament, are thus distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted.<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> The first from the Creation to Noes floud, conteyning the space of 1656.
<pb facs="10"/>
yeares. The second from the floud to the going of Abraham out of his countrie,<note place="margin">The second 368. or 398. The third. about. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>0.</note>
         <note place="margin">Gen. 8. Gen 12. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brard Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolog. S. Aug. li. 15. c. 8. ciuit. Gal. 3. Exo. 16. 3. Reg. 6. 3 Reg. 7. 1. Esdiae 1.</note> 368. or counting Cainan (Gen. 11. iuxta 72. &amp; Luc. 3.) 398. yeares. The third from Abraham his going forth of his countrie, to the parting of the children of Israel out of Aegypt. VVhich-some count to haue continued 720. yeares, others (whom we folow) but 430. And thus farre in the law of nature before the written law. The fourth age dured, 480. yeares, from<note place="margin">The fourth 480.</note> the deliuerie of the children of Israel forth of Aegypt, to the fundation of the Temple in Ierusalem. The fifth age was from the fundation of the Temple, to<note place="margin">The fifth 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>0. The sixth, nere 640. Al the time from the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Christ aboue. 4000. yeares.</note> the captiuitie &amp; transmigration of the Iewes into Babylon, about 430. yeares. And the sixth age dured about 640. yeares, from the Captiuitie of Babylon to Christ. In al which times God was acknowledged and rightly serued, by a continual visible Church, with true Religion; the same &amp; no other, which now that Church holdeth, that is called and knowen by she name of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique. As we intend, by Gods assistance, to shew by briefe Annotations, concerning diuers particular points now in Controuersie, as the holie Text geueth occasion. And especially by way of Recapitulation after euerie one of the six ages, when we come to those passages in the Historie, where the same are ended.</p>
      <div type="section">
         <head>OF MOYSES THE AVTHOR OF THE fiue first bookes.</head>
         <p>
            <hi>MOyses</hi> (so called because he was taken from the water, as the name<note place="margin">MOYSES. signifieth, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the water.</note>
            <note place="margin">Exod. 6. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m. 26. 1. Par. 6. Ioseph li. 2 Antiq. cap. 9. S. Aug▪ ser. 88. de temp. S. Greg. oratio. in laudem Basilij magni. S. Aug. li. 18. ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. c. 39.</note> signifieth) was borne in Aegypt, the sonne of <hi>Amram,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Caath,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Leui</hi> the Patriarch, and so of <hi>Iacob, Isaac,</hi> and <hi>Abraham.</hi> His maruelous deliuerie from drowning, his education, excellent forme, singular wisdome, heroical vertues, rare dexteritie in al affayres, &amp; whole life most admirable, are gathered out of holie Scriptures, by S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie Bishop of Nissen, into a briefe Summe, most worthie to be read, but to large for this place. He was borne about the yeare of the world two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand<note place="margin">The excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Moyses</note> foure hundred, long before al prophane writers, yea before manie of the Painimes false goddes, as S. Augustin declareth in diuers places of his most excellent booke intituled <hi>of the Citie of God.</hi> He liued in this world 120. yeares▪ Of which 40. were in Pharaos court, as the adopted sonne of Pharaos daughter: fourtie in banishment from Aegypt in Madian: and fourtie more he gouerned the people of Israel. His singular prayses are also briefly touched in the last chapter of Deuteromie, added by Iosue. and in the booke of<note place="margin">Deut. 34. Eccli 45. Glos. ord</note> Ecclesi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>sticus. He died in the desert, and was buried in the va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>le of Moab, so<note place="margin">His sepulchre not knowen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o anie man.</note> secretly that no mortal man knew his sepulchre, lest the Iewes, who were very prone to Idolatrie, should haue adored his bodie with diuine honour, for the greatnes and multitude of his miracles, and for the singular estimation, they had of him for the same.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>