<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>A., F. W. P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101863_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09147</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19461</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101863</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>A., F. W. P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Protestants theologie : containing the true solutions, and groundes of religion, this daye mainteyned, and intreated, betwixt the Protestants, and Catholicks. Writen, by the R. F. F. VVilliame Patersoune religious priest, Conuentuall of Antwerpe, preacher of Gods word and Vicar generall of the holy order of S. Augustin, through the kingdome of Scotland. The 1. Part</title>
                 <author>Paterson, F. William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaye (Jaey), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Mechelen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 309, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Preface TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Blessed Apostle S. Paul not without instruction of the Holy Ghost, doe forsee the troubles and calamities of the Church of Christ, Prognosticates saying, <hi>1. cor. 11. There must be Heresies amōgst you, to that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente, that they who are perfeict and approued amongst you, might be knowne.</hi> In which graue predictiō two things is to be obserued, the one is for our comfort, and the other is for our instruction: that by the one, to wit Heresie, we be not dismayed or much offended when we see in the holy profession of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion, Heresies Sectes, and Schismes to arise, that then we foresaeke not the field of our faith; wherin we warefare to God, <hi>1. cor. 9.</hi> and runnes not, as at an vncertaine thing, neyther fightes, as 'an that beateth the windes but runnes to obtaine, and fightes to vinne the reward. And lykewise that we late not goe the steadfast hold of our hope, but holding it sure, and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fast to the Rock of our faith, against which the
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>gates of Hell cannot preuaile neyther infidelity to haue accesse, Cyp. Epist. 55. ad comm. PP.</hi> If therefore we see by the verdict of the Apostle, that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies must be, which in effect brust out in the dayes of the Apostles, as bade weeades springs vp amongst the cornes in the good husbandrie of our Lord, and as cockle owersowede of the enemy in the good feild of God. For in the dayes of the Apostles there wāted not most wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heretickes, as <hi>Simon Magus, Her nogines, Philectus, Hymenaeus, Alexander, &amp; Nicolaus:</hi> who are mentioned in the Scripture, to haue wauered, and been inconstant in the faith: and after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of righteousnes to haue turned back from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: and to haue maintayned erroneous opinions, and teached false doctrine for lucre cause. VVith those also brust out others as the <hi>Ebionists, Cerinthus, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciō,</hi> against whom S. Paul, S. Peter, S. Iohn, and S. Iude, hath writen discouring thē, &amp; their doctrin, vv<seg rend="sup">th</seg> there manners, the which wicked persones were so drūned in the sees of Heresies, and delighted themselues in their poysonable opinions of errors, yealous and fyrie to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the same with their blood. So that to this presēt day, there hath been no age free of Heresie, neyther was the world so perfect in Faith and Religion in the dayes
<pb facs="8"/>of the Apostles more then now: neyther is the world so perfect yet, as not to haue many simple people in it; neyther is the simple people so happy, as to keepe themselues secur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humble, and in the obedience of the doctrine of the Church; neyther is the obedient fully secure not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, of subtill and crafty men; neyther is the subtill &amp; crafty Heretick so carefull of his credit &amp; honesty to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derat his peruerse opiniō and malice, to spare and forbeare to maintain opē falshoods, &amp; old dampned opinions, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle, and snare the ignorantes, and simple people. VVher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apostle prognosticates Heresies to be that mē ben forewarnde and fortold, that as Heresies must be, &amp; with it subtility and malice that whē men beholde the one, to be circumspect not to be deceaued, and trapped in the other, against whom Christ our Saluiour exhortes vs totake head of false Prophets who are clothed in sheape skinnes and are inwardly reaweing wolues, Matth. 7. And S. Iohn biddes not belieue euery spirit, but try them, and decerne them whether they be of God, or no? But who is this prudent, and wyse, that can not be deceaued? and who hath that gift to decerne spirits? seing Heresie it selfe is of the Scripture, and deceit and malice is of the diuell, that old serpent, for made not Sathan this potion out of Scripture, when he said Gen. <hi>3. Eritis sicut dij,</hi> his deceat and malice is
<pb facs="9"/>discouered in calling him an Serpent, as it is writen: <hi>&amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat serpēs calidior, cunctis animantib{us} terrae gen 3.</hi> Therefore how shall men of good iudgement know thē, &amp; farelesse how shall the ignorant and lai-persones try truth, from falshood: sounde doctrine, from error: heresie, frō true Religion: seing it is cōmon in this age, and taught euery man to read the Scriptures and by them to decerne spirites truth and falshood, heresie and true Religion. I wish frō my hart (if it please God) that as holy Scripture is the true tryall therof, that it were as euident and plaine to all men to seike the tryall therin, which the whole learned▪ &amp; holy men frō the Apostles tymes, hath iudged the contrary, that the Scripture is a book of difficulties as S Aust. saith, <hi>lib. 2. de doct. Christi cap. 6.</hi> Many things are darke and obscure in the Scriptures, and it hath been so prouyded of God, to the intēt that our pryd may be taymed with tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill, and our knowledge not cloyed with facility, which quickly contemneth, what hath been easily learned. In this same mynd is <hi>S Hier. in Ezech. cap. 45.</hi> saying, All pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie and interpretation of the Scriptute containes the truth in darknes and obscurity, to the intent that the scol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers &amp; learned within, may vuderstād, but the rude people without, may not know what is said, least we should cast precious perles before hoges, if the treasure of Gods secrets,
<pb facs="9"/>should be opened to euery mā. To amplifie at more lenght, the difficultie therof, <hi>Epiph. in Anchoratu,</hi> saies, The Scripture telleth all truth, but we haue need of a good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, and perseuerance to know God, and his word. Lykewyse, <hi>Orig lib. 7. in leuit.</hi> There is in the Gospel, saith he, the letter that killeth; and this destroying letre is not only in the old, buc also in the new Testamēt to him that vnderstandes it not spiritually what is said. VVhich difficultie <hi>Tert. in praesc</hi> affirmes, saying, I am not a fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to say, that the Scriptures themselues haue been so dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by the will of God, that they might minister matter vnto Heretickes. And therfore seing the Apostle progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticates that Heresie must be, which could not be without the Scripture, which is an ample field for all sectes, the greater should be our prudence and wisdome to beweere of their deceat and subtilities, lest they bring to passe which S. Paul feared saying, that as the Serpent deceaued Eua through his subtility, euen so your senses may be corrupted and to fall away from the simplicity vvhich is in Christ Iesu. For such false Apostles are decetfull workers trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figurating themselues in the Apostles of Christ. Neyther is it marueil that they so appeare, for their master Sathan can transfigure himselfe in an Angell of light, therfore it is not a great matter, if his ministers can transfigurat thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in the apparance of ministers of righteousnes, vvhose
<pb facs="10"/>end shalbe according to their vvorks. Secondly to deceat, and craft is neuer anexed malice, enuy, ialousie, calūnies, vvhich must, proceed from Heresie, as Christ himself defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes saying: <hi>ex fructib{us} eorū cognoscetis eos, mat. 7.</hi> vvhich fruicts are so manifest and euident, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be obscured, and denyed: is their slanderous reportes, inuections, lyes, skooffs, and blasphemies against God, and his Church, vnknown to the vvorld: no? in vvhich doing they haue follovved and imitated the Manicheis as, vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <hi>S Aug. lib. de vtilit. cred. c. 1.</hi> vvho exceeded all other Hereticks before them, that vvith open mouth selā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Church of Christ, and charging her vvith sensles &amp; prodigious dostrines and errours, outfaceing their bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemies vvith bitter inuections, and calumnies, to affray the ignorant people frō the bosome of the Catholik Church, and by setting them selues in the stoll, as fearfull bogelles to affray children, that they might not knovv the verity, through ther deceat and malice, neyther vvhether the Church is, but their synagogue, manasseing and treatning to ioyne all to there cōuentickle, lyke foullars vvho hauing layd the lyme vvands by the spring and vvater syde, go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to stope all other vvaters roūd about, and doe set skar crowes ouer them, that the poore birdes, not knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vvher to make succourse to find vvaters, not of chose, but of very necessity, at last most light in their snayres,
<pb facs="10"/>vvhich euidently appeare in the Hereticks of this age, euer vvith Heresie to haue malice adioyned vvith it: as experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath proued in Scotland, that in the beginning, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie was so delectable to the vvhole estait of the land, after, vvith vvhat subtility, policy, and craft, it is established, in so far, that it is pointly registred in the books of Parlamét, &amp; the professiō of their faith is acted vvord to vvord for a perpetual memorie &amp; the vvholl bodie of the kingdome is coacted to svveir, &amp; to subscriue this new faith, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuses, eyther Protestant, or Catholik: thē malice, inuy, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and blasphemy must force then, what by excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication &amp; horning: or by prisonement, confiscation of goods, exill, or death; they belieue no man whom onse they conceaue iealousie of, their malice is in reconciliable, that they are in will, &amp; desire after the mynd of Caligula, who wished the heades of all the Romās to stand on mās body, that at one blooe he may beheade them al. And therfore to effectuat their malicious desyres, and that the poyson of their hart may be made knowne, they evvomat clamorous raillings, and blasphemies against the Pope of Rome &amp; al Catholike people, that thereby the ignorāt being onse sna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in their heresie, anone are droūk with the same poysō of blasphmy, fury, hatred and malice against Catholicks and Priests, that they are lyke made, and frented people: and that they cam home from their sermonds no lesse feirce and
<pb facs="11"/>fyrie then sogeres frō the warlyke speaches of their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain exhorting them to the fight: or as it is said of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizins of Abdera that onse hearing a furious Tragedie in a heate sommer day, they were so stroken with such a fit of frenesie, through the vehemēt heat of the soune, that many days they did nothing but act the same Tragedie, vvith fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious gestures in there straites. VVas not the lyk tragedie acted in S. Iohnstoun; and through all Scotland: in vvhat frenesie and madnes were the people that in one yeare they raysed, throwdown, and demolised all the abbayes, Churchs, Chappells, and Hospitalls in the whole land, with perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance in blaspheming, condemning, skoffing, freting, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging▪ and moking God &amp; his Church. These holy puritāe Sancts are full of zeall, to evomat such haynous &amp; abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable blasphemies for poor and sound doctrine, dissembling credit and honesty, who are known enemies, they want in their sermons and make ample disgressions, to geet with men of small iudgement the name of a great preachour, &amp; to be called a cunning clerk, that as S. Austen saith, Any man of very small learning may doe the same, to prate v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon palpable follies, and to be inuectiue, which custome is deduced frō the Manicheis, who made long sermons with much grauity, long graces &amp;c. against whom <hi>S. Aug. lib. 1. de morib. eccl. c. 10.</hi> writes adiudging suchlyke toyes vvicked, vvhich doe no way concerne vs, for they speake
<pb facs="11"/>vpon old wyfes tailles, and childish bables, for in that, in which they are most earnest in approuing, and confuting matter of Religion against tht Catholickes, the more they show themselues to want iudgment, and whosoeuer is se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and deceaued of them to follow Heresie, condēneth not the Catholik Church, but showeth himself ignorant &amp; to lack iudgement. For the nature of Heresie, is to blinde the vnderstanding, and induce ignorance. And therefore as <hi>S. Cyp. lib. 1 epist. 3 saith that of thē, who are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane &amp; out of the Church,</hi> no things is to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted but a deprauat mynd, a deceitfull tongue, cankered malice, and sacrilegious lyes, whosoeuer shall giue credit to these professors, shall suffer with them the sentence of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, at Christ comming to iudg the world. In lyke mā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner S. Austē serm. <hi>22.</hi> de verb. Apost. declaring the cause of the peruersitie of heretiks &amp; with what malice and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred satan hath spyred them, that they so continue in their wicked course against conscience &amp; all morall reason, is more the feare of the shame of the world, then the feare of God, or loue of their soule. Lest there religion being dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and discouered it should be said to them, why haue you deceaued vs so long? why did you seduce vs? wherfore told yee vs so many fals things? regarding more the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of men to reprehend their folly, then the inuinciblenes of the truth, which must preuaile. VVhose description of
<pb facs="12"/>doctrine and manner is not neadfull to be produced of vs Catholiks, when sufficiently of Luther, &amp; others, they are described, as ane Anatomie to the obiect of all beholders, as reportes <hi>Theod. Fabrit. in locis comm. in art. Luth. pag. 4. &amp; 5</hi> saying, The natures of these Viperes are such, that they can cauill deceatfully with wordes: making the Scriptures a noise of wax, they show their impious &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious spirit to turne, and alter the sense by the meaning of the Apostles, in which they are admirable doctors, surpas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing in skill, &amp; wite of al the learned and profound men of this world. For they are gouerned by a malignāt spirit w<seg rend="sup">h</seg> doth possesse &amp; be wich their wits, &amp; are inradged with sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanicall virulēcy against Gods Church, and her professors. They cānot eshew but must interpret the Scripturs wrōg, for in this they are for all the world lyke spidders that suck poyson out of fayre and fragāt flours the venome not being in the flours but in thēselues. And therfore as heresie must be: It is not without our profit, to wit for our instructiō, seing that heresies are, and suffered to be, to that intent y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they who are perfect in his Church, might be known: for by Heresies the▪ Church is tryed as gold be the fyre, &amp; as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sea y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is moued with tēpests, casts out his froth &amp; filth (y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> poor waters keep his bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ds &amp; course) soe the Church in tyme of tribulatiō, and stormes of heresie voydes away the fooll &amp; vncleane mēbers out of her, the soūd and faithfull remaine
<pb facs="12"/>vnder her Catholicke rowfe, &amp; abydeth in the faith onse receaued, and belieued. For in tyme of Heresie &amp; Schisme, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> part of euery good Christian man must be, to doe as good sogers, to rūne to their captain &amp; generall, lookīg to him, &amp; expecting to be directed, how, and whē to stryke: &amp; as the modest and gētle passager, whē y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tēpest &amp; stormes ariseth to disordre their passage, sufferes with hartly mynd, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster to ruell the sterne, medling not with that, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which he hath not skill of▪ Euen so when priuie rebelles, and wicked members of Christian religion, sowe seditious schismes, and preaches heresie, troublīg therby y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> quiet &amp; setled cōsciēces of true belieuers: euery Christiā man, &amp; especially the lai &amp; inferior sort ought to cleaue to their heades, and ruelers in Christ Church, medling not vvith any point of religion called in controuersie, but lock to be directed, as they haue been alwayes, in all former ages by there Catholik Pastors, to vvhō they are cōmanded by the Apostle to obey, &amp; sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thēselues, no lesse thē the soger to his captain, or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sager to the schipper, &amp; master of the shippe. Therfore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the exāple of the Apostle, I haue set down the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantes opinion &amp; sound doctrine, that the modest and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Reader may iudge with equity, that their profession is reall heresie and containes nothing but filthy abominable assertions, without any good grounds eyther of Scripture, or reasone. That in vveighing the balance in thy hand of
<pb facs="13"/>iudgement and vnderstanding thow may saue thy soule which is lost if thow remaine in the profession with them, who will goe about to saue his soule, will learne the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And therefore Gentle Reader, I haue set downe in this Protestant Theologie there owne wordes lest some would say, that I doe belye them, which to doe I am very loth, but to obserue charity, as I would they should doe the lyke to me: and whereas Gentil Reader, that thow hadst not the full work accomplished, blame me not, I lippened to mens promises who hath failled, when I haue brought this booke so farre on the way, for my owne part I am so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that it is manked, or abriged if pouerty hath not been my impediment, notwithstanding to my ability with the curtosie of some goodes friends out of the zeall of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion. This first part of my booke is commed to light ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting opportunatie and frienship to effectuat the other part, which God-willing in his owne tyme shall be seene. Therefore inioy this for the present, and pitie my pouerty bidding the hartly fairewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy friend in Christ F. VV. P. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>