<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface generall to the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101549_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07929</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1830</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101549</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface generall to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Thomas Bels motiues : concerning Romish faith and religion</title>
                 <author>Bell, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 <publisher>Kitson, Abraham.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 157, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>The Preface generall to the Christian</hi> Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit <hi>I</hi> will not now dispute, whether the Bishops of Rome be that Antichrist, of whome the Apostle spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <note place="margin">2. Thess. 2. v. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> to the Thessalonians, or no? (notwithstanding the affirmative be the iudgement of sundry great learned men;) yet dare <hi>I,</hi> and doe I boldly avouch, that Bishops of Rome have for many yeres past, bene the precursors and fore-runners of that very Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, whereof mention is alreadie made: which to hold and thinke, many weightie and important reasons have mooved me. For first, <note place="margin">1</note> who but Antichrist, or his precursor, will either ascribe, or suffer to be ascribed unto him: such power of maiestie, and titles of Deietic, as are proper and peculiar to God aloue? And yet is this to be verified of the pope undoubtedlie, by the popes owne doctrine, and his popish doctors. The pope (if we will beleeve him) telleth us: that God, when he instituted two great lights in the firmament: to wit, the Sunne and the Moone: signified thereby, the autoritie of popes and of kings: gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us to understand, that the pope is as farre above a king in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as is the Sunne above the Moone in excellencie: yea, he addeth further; that Kings and Emperors have no power, to draw the sword against popish bishops &amp; priestes: as who forsooth, are not subiect to their iurisdiction. And least I should be thought, to father untruthes upon the pope: I will (which is my wonted manner throughout my whole booke,) alledge his owne wordes, which are these: <hi>Ad fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mamentum</hi>
      <note place="margin">Greg. 9. lib. 1. decret. tit. 33. cap. 6.</note>
      <hi>coeli, hoc est, universalis ecclesiae, fecit Deus duo magna luminaria, id est, duas instituit dignitates, quae sunt, Pontificalis autoritas, &amp; Regalis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testas: sed illa, quae praeest diebus, id est, spiritualibus, maior est: quae vero carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus, minor: ut, quanta est inter solem &amp; lunam, tanta inter Pontifices &amp; Reges differentia cognoscatur.</hi> To the firmament of heaven, that is, of the universall Church, God made two great lightes: to wit, ordeined two great dignities, which are the authoritie of the Pope, and the power of the King: but that power, which ruleth spiritual things, is greater: and that which ruleth things carnal, is lesser: that so great difference may be knowen betweene Popes and kings, as is betweene the sunne and the moone. The popish glosse in the same place, setteth downe <note place="margin">Glossa. ibid.</note> precisely, how farre the King is inferiour to the Pope, in these words: <hi>Restat, ut Pontificalis dignitas quadragesies septies sit maior regali dignitate.</hi> It therefore remaineth, that the pontificality of the Pope is seven &amp; fourtie times greater, then is the regalitie of the king. Pope Gregory <note place="margin">Gregor. ubi supra.</note> saith further, in this expresse maner: <hi>Intelligendum non est, quòd Rex vel Imperator super bonos &amp; malos gladii acceperit potestatem; sed in eos solum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modò, qui utentes gladio eius sunt iurisdictioni commissi.</hi> We must not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that the King or Emperour hath receiued power of the sworde
<pb facs="4"/>
over the good and the evill; but onely over them, who using the sword are committed to his iurisdiction. Behold, how the Scripture is tossed and wrested: to take from kings, that power which God hath given them. The popish parasites, the glossators of the Canons, ascribe more magnificall and plaine divine titles unto the Pope; even such as no way can be denied, to be proper and peculiar to God alone. These are their expresse words: <hi>Sic (Papa) dicitur habere coeleste arbitrium, &amp; ideò</hi>
      <note place="margin">Glossat. lib. 1. decretat. tit. 7. cap. 3.</note>
      <hi>etiam naturam rerum immutat, substantialia unius rei applicando alij; &amp; de ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilo potest aliquid facere.</hi> So the pope is said to have celestial arbitremēt, and therefore doeth he alter the nature of things, by application of the substantiall partes of one thing to another; &amp; he can make of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing something. Thus verily do they write, and yet no greater blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy can be uttered. Ioannes Gerson, though otherwise a great pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist, maketh rehearsal of intollerable dignities, and titles ascribed to the pope; which notwithstanding the pope himselfe hath acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged as pertaining to him, but the said Gerson them reprooveth &amp; derideth. These be his expresse words: <hi>Consurgit ex adver so blandiens &amp;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gerson. de potestat. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. consider. 12. part. 3.</note>
      <hi>subdola adulatio; &amp; ad aures Ecclesiasticorum praecipuè summi Pontificis insu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrans; ô quanta quanta est sublimitas ecclesiasticae potestatis tuae? quonians sicut Christo collata est omnis potest as in coelo &amp; in terra, sic eam Christus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim Petro suisque successoribus dereliquit. Vnde nec Constantinus quicquam Sylvestro papae contulit, quod non esset priùs suum; sedreddidit iniustè detentum. Porrò, sicut non est potest as nisià Deo, sicnec aliqua temporalis velecclesiastica, imperialis, velregalis, nisià Papa: in cuius foemore scripsit Christus, Rex regum, Dominus dominantium; de cuius potestate disputare, instar sacrilegij est; cui neque quisquam dicere potest, cur ita facis? mentior si non inveniantur haec scripta, ab illis etiam qui sapientes sunt in oculis suis.</hi> There starteth up on the contrarie side faire-spoken and craftie adulation: whispering in the eares of Clergie men, especially of the pope; Oh how great, how great is the Maiestie of thine Ecclesiasticall power? for as all povver vvas given to Christ, in heaven and on earth; So Christ left all the same power, to Peter and his Successours. VVherefore the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Constantine gave nothing to Pope Sylvester, which was not his owne before; but onely restored that, which was uniustly deteined from him. Further, as there is no power but of God, so is there nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any temporall or Ecclesiasticall, Imperiall or Regall, but of the Pope; in vvhose thigh Christ hath vvritten, the King of Kinges, and Lord of Lordes; of whose power to dispute, is as meere sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge; to whome no man may say, VVhy doest thou so? I am a lyar, if these thinges be not written: even of them, who are vvise in their owne conceites. These are Doctor Gersons wordes: vvho though he vvere a great Papist, yet could he not digest these Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian blasphemies, neither hide or conceale them vvithin his
<pb facs="4"/>
breast. Neverthelesse Pope Bonifacius did not onely acknovvledge them, but vvith great pleasure practised the same, as vvitnesseth the said Gerson in these vvordes: <hi>Hanc existimationem habuisse, visus est Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifacius</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gerson ubi supra.</note>
      <hi>octavus in quadam decretali: putatur ab alijs, depositio unius Regis Franciae per Papam Zachariam hic esse fundata; tanquam Papa sit, qui tras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre possit Reges &amp; regna.</hi> Pope Bonifacius the eight of that name, seemeth in a certaine decretall, to have had this opinion of his ovvn authoritie. Others thinke, that the deposition of (Childericus) the French King by Pope Zacharias, vvas grounded in this (Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian and godlesse conceit:) as if for soothe the Pope vvere he, that coulde depose Princes, and translate their kingdomes. And our Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suite Bellarminus, is so farre from blushing at this most detestable fact of Pope Zacharie: that he yeeldeth the reason <hi>si dijs placet,</hi> for the iustification thereof. <hi>Childericum (inquit) deposuit Papa, &amp; in eius</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bellarminus de Rom. Pont. lib. 5. cap. 8</note>
      <hi>locum Pipinum Caroli magni patrem Regem creari iussit: cuius causa fuit, quia propter socordiam Childerici, &amp; Religioni, &amp; Regno in Gallia, extrema ruina imminere videbatur.</hi> The Pope (saith our Iesuite) deposed Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericus, and commaunded to place Pipinus father to Charles the great, in his throne. The cause vvhereof was this; because forsooth through the negligent governement of Childericus, the Kingdome and Religion of Fraunce seemed to be in great daunger. Thus saith the Popes vassall; out of vvhose vvordes I gather first, that so much may be truely verified of Popes, as Gerson hath avovvched. <note place="margin">1</note>
   </p>
   <p>I gather secondly, that the Pope chalengeth both svvordes, and himselfe to be not onely universall Bishoppe, but universall King <note place="margin">2</note> also over all the vvorld.</p>
   <p>I gather thirdly, that the Iesuites (hovvsoever they dissemble by their fondly imagined aequivocation,) thinke of our most gratious <note place="margin">3</note> Soveraigne Queene Elizabeth, and meane to doe vvith her most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maiestie, as the Pope thought and did vvith Childericus; and for that end <hi>saltem secundariò,</hi> are so many Iesuites sent seditiously in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Secundò principalitèr.</note> this land.</p>
   <p>Secondly, my L. Abbot their ovvne deare Bernard, savve in his time such tyrannie and Antichristian dealing in the Church of Rome, as hee vvas thereby and therevvith enforced to exclame in these wordes: <hi>Tempus faciendinunc, quia dissipaverunt legem. bestia illa de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalypsi,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bernar. ad Gaufridum, epist. 125.</note>
      <hi>cui datum est os loquens blasphemias, &amp; bellum gerere cum Sanctis, Petri Cathedram occupat, tanquam Leo paratus ad praedam.</hi> It is novve high time to doe good, for they have troden under foote Gods Lavve. That beast mentioned in the Revelation, to vvhome vvas gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a mouth speaking blasphemies, and to make vvarres vvith the Saintes: sitteth in the chaire of Peter, as a Lyon ready to take his praye.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
Thirdly, the Pope doeth not onely take upon him, to depose kings and Emperours him selfe; but he avovvcheth further, that Subiectes <note place="margin">3</note> may and are bounden to depose their dread Soveraignes, vvhensoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they decline to infidelity: which certes is by popish interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vvhen any King or Queene embraceth syncerely the holy Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Christ, and denyeth Romish poperie. For thus vvriteth Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larminus, vvhose doctrine the Pope hath lately approoved; <hi>At si isti ijdem principes conantur avertere populum a fide, omnium consensu possunt</hi>
      <note place="margin">Robertus Bellarminus lib. 5. de Rom. Pontif. cap. 7.</note> &amp; <hi>debent privari suo dominio.</hi> But if these Princes goe about, to avert the people from the faith (of the Church of Rome:) then by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of all, they may and must be dispossessed, of their Scepters and Regalities.</p>
   <p>Againe, in the second Chapter he saith thus: <hi>Quòd si Christiani olim</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bellarm. cod. cap.</note>
      <hi>non deposuerunt Neronem, &amp; Diocletianum, &amp; Iulianum apostatam, ac Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentem Arianum, &amp; similes; id fuit, quia deerant vires temporales Christianis.</hi> If the Christians in times past, deposed not Nero, Diocletian, Iulian, Valens, and such like Emperours; the cause thereof was, for that they wanted povver and force, and vvere not strong ynough for that attempt. Againe, a little after he hath these vvordes: <hi>At non tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Christiani, immò nec debent cum evidenti periculo religionis, toler are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bellarm. cap. codem.</note>
      <hi>infidelom.</hi> But Christians are not bounde to tolerate a King, that is an Infidell, (or not a Papist;) nay, they must not tolerate such a one, vvith the evident daunger of Religion. And our said Iesuite yeeldeth this reason hereof; because forsooth saith he, <hi>De iure humanoest, quod hunc aut illum habeamus Regem.</hi> For it is by the Lavve of man, that vve <note place="margin">Bellarm. ubi supra.</note> have this or that man to our King. This is the doctrine of our Popes, and lately hatched Iesuites: out of vvhich most disloyall and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian assertion;</p>
   <p>I inferre first, that the Pope and Iesuites vvould most vvillingly, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive our most gratious Soveraigne of her Royall throne and Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; <note place="margin">1</note> if they vvere of force and povver so to doe.</p>
   <p>I inferre secōdly, that our Iesuite doth here approve peremptorily. <note place="margin">2</note>
   </p>
   <p>First, the diabolical excommunication of Pope Pius.</p>
   <p>Secondly, the disloyal fact of Murton, vvho brought the same into this Realme.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, the publishing thereof by Felton.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, the practising of the curse by Sanders, Fitz-morice, Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lard, and others their seditious complices.</p>
   <p>Fiftly, the renevving of the print, and dispersing of the copies in Rome, by our Iesuites, Persons, and Campion; as a compendious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative, for their commodious entrance into this land.</p>
   <p>I inferre thirdly, that all subiects are by this doctrine, stirred up and encouraged to manifest rebellion; &amp; to have no scruple of conscience <note place="margin">3</note>
      <pb facs="5"/>
therein. The reason hereof is evident, because if kinges receive their authoritie frō man, as this Iesuit auoucheth: then may kings indeed be displaced by man, as Romish parasites, and irreligious politikes beare the world in hand. yet Salomon the vvise replenished vvith ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie inspiration, teacheth vs another doctrine: <hi>Per me inquit, reges reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prou. c. 8. 15.</note> &amp; <hi>legum conditores iusta decernunt. per me principes imperant, &amp; poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes decernunt iustitiam.</hi> By mee (saith God in Salōmon) kings reigne, and princes decree iustice. By me princes rule, and all nobles, and iudges of the earth. And the Apostle saith: <hi>Omnts anima potestatibus</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. c. 13. v. 1.</note>
      <hi>sublimioribus subdita sit: non est enim potestas nisia Deo.</hi> Let everie soule bee subiect to higher powers: for ther is no power but of God. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of more at large, in the sixt chapter and third conclusion of the second booke. Fourthlie, Sylvester Pryeras that great popish Thomist, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <note place="margin">4</note> vs roundlie and malepertlie: that empires and regalities are not from God immediatlie, but from God by meanes of the pope. And he saith further, that royall power is so subordinate to poperie, or papacie: as is the Moone vnto the Sunne. These are his owne wordes: <hi>Nec obstat, quod potestas imperialis est a deo concessa secundum mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sylvest. de papa. para. 2.</note>
      <hi>iura: quia est a Deo, mediante papa: quia eam concedit non vt homo, sed vt vicarius Det. Nec sunt sic distinctae potestates, spiritualis scilicet &amp; temporalis: quin vna alteri subalternetur, ad instar lunae &amp; solis: nec sunt distinctae, quasi semper sint in diversis: sed quia sunt ordinatae ad distincta, scilicet spiritualia &amp; temporalia: &amp; in vno eodem{que} summo pontifiee, est vtraque in summo.</hi> It skilleth not, that manie lawes affirme imperiall power to be of God. For it is from God, the Pope being the meane, who graunteth it not as man, but as the vicar of God. Neither are the two powers, (the spirituall and the temporall,) so distinct: but that they remaine sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate the one to the other, after the resemblance of the sunne &amp; moone. neither are they distinct as being alwaies in diuerse subiects, but as ordeined to distinct thinges, spiritual and temporall. For they both are in one and the selfe same pope, even in the highest degree. Fiftlie, such as is the ruler of the citie, (saith Bellarminus our Iesuit,) <note place="margin">5</note> such are the inhabitants thereof: But pope Boniface the eight entred <note place="margin">Bellar. derom. pontif. lib. 5. cap. 7.</note> into his popedome as a Foxe, reigned in it as a woolfe, and died out of it as a dogge, as I haue proved in my 2. booke, in the 3. chapter &amp; second conclusion: <hi>ergo</hi> all the citizens of Rome in his time began as foxes, continued as wolves, and ended their daies as dogges: and consequentlie, the whole church of Rome during the time of Pope Boniface: was wicked, diabolicall, and meere antichristian. what shall I say of kissing the popes foote? of bearing the pope vpon mens shoulders? of the popes dispensing with the law humane, the lawe of nature, and the law divine? these may suffice, to teach vs to walke warelie, to looke about vs withall circumspection, to be verie care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full what doctrine we embrace: and ever to set before our eies, the
<pb facs="6"/>
admonitions and premonitions of our sauiour Iesus Christ. <hi>Attendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, inquit Dominus, a fermento Pharisaeorum quodest hypocrisis.</hi> Beware saith our Lord, of the leven of the Pharises, that is, their false doctrine, infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <note place="margin">Luc. 12. 2.</note> and infatuated vvith the traditions of men: as it is expounded in another place of the gospel. VVe must therefore here observe, that in the scribes and Pharisees rested in those daies the ordinarie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall face, power, regiment, and iurisdiction of the church. For so saith our saviour, in another place of the gospell: <hi>In cathedra Mosis</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 13.</note>
      <hi>sedent Scribae &amp; Pharisaei: omnia ergo quaecunque praeceperint vobis servare, servate &amp; facite.</hi> The Scribes and Pharisees sit in the chaire of Moses: therefore, whatsoever they shall commaund you to keepe, that keepe <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 3.</note> and doe. VVherefore since our Lord commaundeth vs, to beware of the hypocriticall doctrine of the Pharisees, who had the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in the visible Church of that age: and since Christ commaunded this for no other end, but because they had corrupted the sacred &amp; pure word of God, with the mixture of their owne foolish traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for that Christ obiected against them, saying: <hi>Quare &amp; vostrans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredimini mandatum Dei, propter traditiouem vestram:</hi> why doe you trās<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse Gods commaundement, for the accomplishment of your own <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 3.</note> tradition? and in another place: <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: But in vaine doe they worship mee, teaching <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 9.</note> doctrines the commaundements of men: since I say, our saviour thus commaundeth vs: it followeth, that we must refuse, reiect, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne, all prelates, all bishops, all priestes, and all whosoever have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie administration in the church, by what name or title soever they be called: if they deliver to vs the word of God impurelie, or mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with traditions of men: and consequentlie, that we must reiect and renounce, the pope, and all the rable of popish cleargie-men: as who do either not deliver the word of God at all, or at least so min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, so pestered, so corrupted, so adulterated with mans traditions: as no part there of remaineth sound, pure, and intire. It then standeth vs vpon, to employ our whole care, studie, and industrie, that we may liue secure from the leaven of these Pharisees: that is, of these popes and popish vassalles: who in steede of christian doctrine, doe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticallie deliver vnto vs, yea with threats of fire and faggot enforce vpon vs, the present poison of our soules. For if he that sitteth in Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters chaire be Antichrist, as vvitnesseth their owne Bernard: if the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of Rome have written in their thighes, the king of kinges and Lord of Lords, as their Gerson avoucheth: if all power asvvell civill as ecclesiasticall be chalenged of popes, as their Silvester affirmeth: if popes can place and displace kinges and Emperours, and dispossesse them of their regalities, and royall seats, as their Iesuit Bellarmine boasteth: if the bishops of Rome be as farre above kinges in auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as is the Sunne above the Moone in excellencie, as pope Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="6"/>
teacheth: if no king can draw the sword against any of his subiects, being cleargie-men without the popes good licence and favour, as the said Gregorie telleth vs: if the pope bee taken to be greater then any king by seaven and fourtie fold, as the popish glosse proclaimeth, nay, if the pope applie the substantial parts of one subiect to another: if the pope take vpon him to make of nothing somthing, as affirmeth another glosse: then doubtles doth it necessarilie follow, that if the pope be not that Antichrist, whereof S. Paul. speaketh to the Thessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians: yet is he perforce that Antichrist, where of Saint Iohn wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in these wordes: <hi>Omnis spiritus qui solvit Iesum, ex Deo non est: &amp; hic est antichristus, de quo audistis quoniam venit, &amp; iam in mundo est.</hi> Everie spirit that dissolveth Iesus, is not of God: and this is Antichrist, of <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4. 3.</note> whom you haue heard, that he is alreadie come, and is even now in the world. For not onely they dissolve Iesus, that denie his divinity, or his humanitie, or the hypostaticall vnion of the same: but they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so that derogate in anie point from the office auctoritie, and power of Christ, (who is our eternal king, our head, our prophet, our priest:) and in like maner, all they that by any meanes depresse or obscure the same: as doe the papistes, in innumerable particulars: to wit, in their reall inherent iustice, in their condigne merites of workes, in their congruent dispositions, in their massing sacrifice, in their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall presence, in their accidents without subiectes, in their lordlie papall primacie, in their purgatorie-purifications, in their satisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie supplements, in their disholie supererogations, in their phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saical flagellations: &amp; in many other like superstitiōs, fondly reputed holines. these things are partly proved already: but more fully &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, throughout the whole discourse following, pervse it therfore gē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reader willingly, marke it attentively, iudge of it friendly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne nothing rashly, revolve the authorities seriously, approove the trueth constantly, reiect falshood zealously; and if thou shalt perceiue thyselfe, to reape any spirituall commoditie by this my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: then vouchsafe to commend me in thy heartie praiers, to the father of all mercie: to vvhom vvith the sonne and the holie ghost, be all honour, povver, glorie, and dominion, novv and evermore,</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>