<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, FRANCIS, LORD VERVLAM, LORD High Chancellour of England, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Venner, Tobias</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101771_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14328</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24643</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101771</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, FRANCIS, LORD VERVLAM, LORD High Chancellour of England, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Venner, Tobias</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Via recta ad vitam longam, or A plaine philosophical discourse of the nature, faculties, and effects, of all such things, as by way of nourishments, and dieteticall obseruations, make for the preseruation of health : with their iust applications vnto euery age, constitution of bodie, and time of yeare. Wherein also, by way of introduction, the nature and choise of habitable places, with the true vse of our famous bathes of Bathe is perspicuously demonstrated. By To: Venner, Doctor of Physicke, at Bathe in the spring, and fall, and at other times in the burrough of North-Petherton neere to the ancient hauen-towne of Bridgewater in Somerset-shire</title>
                 <author>Venner, Tobias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Moore (More), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 195, 9 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, FRANCIS, LORD VERVLAM, LORD High Chancellour of England, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Often meditating with my self, to whom I should (according to the ancient and well approued cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of the best learned of all ages) consecrate these my labours, I at length resolued, in te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonie, of my deuoted affections to your Honour, as also in regard of the worthines and vtilitie of the subiect (which is the Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teticall part of Physicke, that for preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of health appertaines to all men, but to none, as I suppose, more then to your Honour, who vnder his Maiestie, doth cheifly weild the state of our Reipublique)
<pb facs="3"/>
to commit them to your Honours prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Whereunto, your benigne Nature, excellent learning, and singular respect to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards learned men, haue not a litle also en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged me. If the worke shall yeeld any manner of delight or profit to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, I haue my ayme and contentment. The God of Heauen grant you a long and healthy life, with a prosperous fruition of your Place and Dignities, to his Glory, your owne Comfort, and the Good of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties subiects. Thus referring both my self, and this worke to your fauourable accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, I in all obseruance humbly rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>At your Honours seruice and command,
TOBIAS VENNER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>