<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Correction of faultes, &amp; supplie of omissions.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101974_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13322</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23630</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101974</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Correction of faultes, &amp; supplie of omissions.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhetstone of reproofe : A reprouing censure of the misintituled safe way: declaring it by discouerie of the authors fraudulent proceeding, &amp; captious cauilling, to be a miere by-way drawing pore trauellers out of the royall &amp; common streete, &amp; leading them deceitfull in to a path of perdition. With a postscript of advertisements, especially touching the homilie &amp; epistles attributed to Alfric: &amp; a compendious retortiue discussion of the misapplyed by-way. Author T.T. Sacristan &amp; Catholike Romanist</title>
                 <author>T. T., Sacristan &amp; Catholike Romanist</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyon, Marc, Widow of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 570, that is 540, 2, 198, that is 197, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>Correction of faultes, &amp; supplie of omissions.</head>
   <p>PAge 60. line 13. reade Church Apostacie. p. 114. l. 18. for them, reade it. p. 116. for be reade were. &amp; for there formers reade the Reformers. p 127. omit real presence. l. 134. for sainte reade smarte. p. 142. for to dissent reade not to consent. p. 154. for to such contrarie reade contratie to such &amp; in the same page l. 23. for which is true, reade which in his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is true. &amp; p. 155. touching the same matter. l. 15. for none of which is contrarie, reade none of which abstracting from the institution is contrarie. p. 145. for but hath, reade but since it &amp; the rest were there included hath. pag. 156. line 2. for the manner reade the whole &amp; intire manner. p. 158. for declaredly &amp; vniuersally reade, so declaredly &amp; vniuersally. page 226. for the worde of God, reade either the vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten worde of God, &amp; in the same p. l. 14. adde althou' there were no other Councell for it. pag. 208. l. 20. to people, adde as euer so to receiue it by Christs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde. p. 265. for thrice, reade once. p. 240. lin. 6. to Christ, adde humane nature. p. 239. for reconciliatiōs, reade <hi>reconciliationis.</hi> p. 287. for dignitie reade <hi>decorum.</hi> p. 202. l. 7. omit other. l. 27. to exhibited add by it selfe. page 307. to not determined by the Church, adde in euerie particular. pag. 317. to illegitimate, adde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the doctrine of images. p. 371. to diuine wors<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hip, add in spirit. pa. 447. l. 16. for in, reade since. pa. 463. for thim, reade him. &amp; in the next l. 10. for may chalenge, reade may in that respect chalenge. p. 467. l. 17. adde in respecte of the people. p. 433. lin. 16. for able, reade agreable. &amp; omit su. pag. 438. lin. 13. for to whome reade, &amp; yet. p. 475. for conference reade cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence. p. 485. l. 16. for heresie, reade material heresie. p. 480. for martyrs reade examples. p. 493. l. 26. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence. adde to this purpose. p. 566. l. 24. to soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, adde including the prayers. p 546. l. 8. to glorious,
<pb facs="9"/> adde flashe. &amp; l. 26. for gaspell, reade Gospell. p. 545. l. 2. reade Pamphleter. p. 421. l. 18. omit in a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible maner.</p>
   <p>In the introduction to the Appendix.</p>
   <p>Page 73. line 10. adde defined. l. 3. for false, reade safe. p. 19. l. 20. omit either, &amp; in the next. l. reade wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. &amp; l. 24. to some of, adde them.</p>
   <p>Besides these neglects I aduertise the reader of an other faulte committed in the omission of titles for the distinct matters. Neuerthelesse this defect is sufficiently supplied in regarde that in the commencement or entrance of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie seuerall period, the contents are breefely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. There be manie other errors of lesse im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance committed by the printer as being a strāger as Nice with a great letter &amp; the like, which the discretion and iudgement of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will easily correct. In like manner he will perdone the rudnes of the style as penned by one whoe by reason of his absence &amp; daylie conuersation with strangers ignoreth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of his natiue language. As also he will conniue his tardance in the publication of the worke, which if it had not incountered vnima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined impediments might haue appeared manie monethes paste.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>