<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>W., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101310_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14989</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25296</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101310</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>W., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A bride-bush, or A vvedding sermon : compendiously describing the duties of married persons: by performing whereof, marriage shall be to them a great helpe, which now finde it a little hell</title>
                 <author>Whately, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 49, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader; Marriage</hi> hath scarse more that vse, then that accuse it. Most men enter into this estate, and beeing entred complaine therof. They should rather complaine of themselues. It is an vniust thing, and a fruit of ignorant pride, to cast the blame of our greeuances vpon Gods ordinances. I had bene happie (saith one) had I not bene married. Then wast thou foolish both before and since thy marriage. Ʋse it well, it shall adde to thine happinesse. We make bitter sawce, and cry out that the meate is bitter. Thou liuest in Matrimony not after Gods direction, but the rules (crooked rules they be) of thine owne lusts, and then say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, Oh that I had neuer married, Oh that I were vnmarried. For shame keepe silence, thy crying shewes thy disease. Thou art indeed married to an ill companion (thy wicked flesh, that body of death, that old husband) and art pestered with its brood, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther seekest a diuorce from this tyrant, nor endeauourest to crucify the wicked off-spring thereof. Hence are thy woes; not thy Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, not thy Wife, but thy pride, thy passion, cause all this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance, all this discontentment. I labour in this little Treatise to plead the cause of marriage: not so much directly in speech, as indeede actually, by directing the married to the knowledge and practise of their duties, which would mend all. These what soeuer man and woman indeuour to follow, if they prooue not marriage a solace to their soules, and refreshing to their other greefes, let mee neuer but greeue.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>These things I commend to thine vnderstanding, to thy life: vse them, and then say how thou speedest. I intended them at first for a few, and now communicate them to many. It is no vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table (I am sure) I hope, no vnprofitable deed. I desire thou shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest make some vse of them, therefore I make them publicke: if not, bee ignorant and complaine still. I meane them not to the learned, that can finde out better directions for themselues, but to those whose place is not too good to learne of the meanest Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: euen vnto men of the same ranke, as they for the most part were, to whom I spake them. If this worke profite, I am glad, then I know it shall please: howsoeuer, thou hast it Reader, and better shouldst haue had, if my store affoorded any better. I hope thou wilt not blame me for meaning well, and doing no harme. So I commend thee to the Lord.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Banburie,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>August 20. 1608.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> W. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>