<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Worshipfull, Sir Edward Wingfield, Knight.</title>
           <author>Beard, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101119_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06108</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1659</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101119</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Worshipfull, Sir Edward Wingfield, Knight.</title>
                 <author>Beard, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The theatre of Gods iudgements: or, A collection of histories out of sacred, ecclesiasticall, and prophane authours : concerning the admirable iudgements of God vpon the transgressours of his commandements. Translated out of French, and augmented by more than three hundred examples, by Th. Beard</title>
                 <author>Beard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 79, 90-472, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Worshipfull, Sir <hi>Edward Wingfield,</hi> Knight.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a principle in natural philosophy (right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) that in euerie naturall bodie, as well the Elephant as the gnat, there is some propertie or other to be admired and wondred at: and not only in philosophie, but also in Diuinitie; for euen the diuine Singer of Israel anoucheth the same, when hee saith, That the workes of God are wonderfull, and his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments past finding out: and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great reason; for if we turne ouer euery leafe of Gods creatures from the tenth sphere to the centre of the earth, we shall find, that euery leafe and letter of this great volume, is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable and wonderfull: and such as
<pb facs="3"/> doth not onely demonstrate a diuine power to sit at the stern of the world, but also our owne weaknes, which is not able to comprehend the least part thereof. This wonderfull workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship as it doth set forth the power of God as he is the creator, and his wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome as he is the gouernor of it; so es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially his mercie &amp; iustice appeare therein, as he is a father in preseruing his children, and a iudge in punishing sinners, and those that rebell against him: and these two are fitly called the armes of the Almighty, of which one is not longer &amp; larger than the other; but he is so far mercifull that he is iust withall, and so far iust, that his mercie doth also shew it selfe in the middest therof: the right consideratiō wherof if it were ingrafted in the hearts of men, they would learne both to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire
<pb facs="3"/> and reuerence his mercie in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating and preseruing the frame of the world, and stand in awe of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in correcting sinne: but so it is, that the greatest part of men go clean contrary, they dreame vpon mercie, mercy, &amp; neuer thinke vpō iustice &amp; iudgement; and that is the cause why more perish by presumption than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaire: for this cause it seemed to me most necessary to call into mens me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories the wonderfull iudgements of God, &amp; to set before their eies a view of his iustice manifested in the world vpon sinners &amp; reprobats, to the end that the drousie consciences of Gods children might be awakened, and the desperat hearts of the wicked cōfoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, when they shall see how venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance pursueth malefactours to their shame and confusiō in this life, and to
<pb facs="4"/> their destructiō in the world to come. This I haue performed (according to the measure of my skil) in this present volume, which hauing partly transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the French, and partly col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by mine owne industrie out of many Authors: I dedicate and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate vnto you as a monument of my dutifull loue which I owe &amp; am euer bound to owe vnto your selfe, your vertuous Lady, and all your genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; desiring of you a fauourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of my simple offering, and for you a protection from all such iudgements as are contained in this, and a perpetuall continuance of all happie and heauenly felicitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships in all dutie to command,</hi> Th. Beard.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>