<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE COVRTEOVS READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101880_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B13511</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10693</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101880</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE COVRTEOVS READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Kalendarium humanæ vitæ. = The kalender of mans life. Authore Roberto Farlæo. Scoto Britanio</title>
                 <author>Farley, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Cotes, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hope, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>152 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Calendars, almanacs and prognostications</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE COVRTEOVS READER.</head>
   <lg>
      <head>The Roses.</head>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Roc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e</hi> did flye, and Parti-colour'd <hi>Flora</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Now felt soft nipping colds breath from <hi>Auro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And <hi>Phoebus,</hi> usherd with the cooler day,</l>
      <l>Gave warning to prevent his scorching ray;</l>
      <l>While I the checkerd gardens walk'd along,</l>
      <l>Seeking refreshment dainty flowers among,</l>
      <l>I saw the fragrant herbes bending their tops,</l>
      <l>With pearle-like dew hanging in silver drops;</l>
      <l>And in the Coleworts cabbines I did see,</l>
      <l>The queeres of Nectar dancing joyfully,</l>
      <l>I saw the Rose beds in their <hi>Pestan</hi> weeds,</l>
      <l>Wet with the foame of <hi>Phoebus</hi> neighing steedes;</l>
      <l>The tender buds did in their night-geare stand,</l>
      <l>Of hoary plush, wrought by dame Natures hand,</l>
      <l>Ready to put it off, when they did spy</l>
      <l>Dayes charriter coursing along the sky;</l>
      <l>One might have doubt, whether the Heav'n did dye</l>
      <l>The Roses, or they purple-paint the skye:</l>
      <l>The Sunne and Rose, were in one liv'ry clad,</l>
      <l>For they one Lady <hi>Aphrodite</hi> had;</l>
      <l>Perhaps one smell they had, but that as higher</l>
      <l>Evanish'd, this breath'd sweetely from the brier▪</l>
      <l>How many minutes draweth forth an houre,</l>
      <l>So many habits chang'd this curious flower;</l>
      <l>It sometimes nimph-like, mantled was in grenee,</l>
      <l>Wearing a cap much like the Fairy Queene:</l>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <l>Sometimes it woare a comely purple crest,</l>
      <l>And had its haire in anticke fashion drest;</l>
      <l>Then by and by her brest unlac'd, to shew</l>
      <l>What heavenly fragrant Nectar did thence flow;</l>
      <l>At last sh'unvail'd herselfe, and shew'd her face,</l>
      <l>To <hi>Phoebus,</hi> with a modest blushing grace;</l>
      <l>Her dandling tresses wreath'd like threds of Gold.</l>
      <l>Scarse without envy <hi>Titan</hi> could behold;</l>
      <l>But lo dame <hi>Natures</hi> darling, which just now</l>
      <l>Did flourish naked stands, I know not how;</l>
      <l>Of so great glory then, I thought it strange,</l>
      <l>To see so suddaine and so sad a change,</l>
      <l>The Rose to bud, to blossome in her prime,</l>
      <l>To fade, to fall, to wither at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> time;</l>
      <l>Then for her mantle greene, a murry clout</l>
      <l>All torne did hang her gastly lookes about;</l>
      <l>The cap▪ the purple crest and all was gone,</l>
      <l>Baldnesse her wrinckled head did seize upon▪</l>
      <l>O what a sight it was to see her lie</l>
      <l>Vpon her mothers lap ready to die!</l>
      <l>Small comfort had the earth, to see her brood</l>
      <l>Pluckt from her milky breasts, and bath'd in blood;</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Phoebus</hi> who rising from the glassie streames</l>
      <l>Did court this Virgin with his chearefull beames,</l>
      <l>Going to bed he sees the naked thorne,</l>
      <l>And cannot love her 'cause shee is forlorne.</l>
      <l>So long as lasts a day, a Rose may live,</l>
      <l>That day doth kill the Rose, which life did give:</l>
      <l>A Virgin in the morning, and at noone</l>
      <l>Which had her prime, becomes decrepit soone.</l>
      <l>So pull the Rose, and thinke, when thou dost see</l>
      <l>It's brittle beauty, that it points to Thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>