<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>VIVAT SERENIS∣sima Regina. TO THE MOST MIGHTIE, IMPERIAL, AND
Vertuous Princesse, The Lordes Anointed, Queene Elizabeth, by the grace of
God of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, Queene, Defendresse of the faith,
&amp;c. ⁂</title>
           <author>Kett, Francis</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101081_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04811</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14945</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101081</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>VIVAT SERENIS∣sima Regina. TO THE MOST MIGHTIE, IMPERIAL, AND
Vertuous Princesse, The Lordes Anointed, Queene Elizabeth, by the grace of
God of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, Queene, Defendresse of the faith,
&amp;c. ⁂</title>
                 <author>Kett, Francis</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The glorious and beautifull garland of mans glorification : Containing the godlye misterie of heauenly Ierusalem, the helmet of our saluation. The comming of Christ in the fleshe for our glorie, and his glorious com [m] ing in the end of the world, to crowne men with crowne of eternall glorie. Beeing an heauenly adamant to drawe thee to Christ and a spirituall rod to mortifie thy life. Made and set foorth by Frauncis Kett, Doctor of Phisick</title>
                 <author>Kett, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Ward, Roger</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, coat of arms, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>VIVAT SERENIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sima Regina. TO THE MOST MIGHTIE, IMPERIAL, AND
Vertuous Princesse, The Lordes Anointed, Queene Elizabeth, by the grace of
God of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, Queene, Defendresse of the faith,
&amp;c. ⁂</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing that your Royall seate and Scepter (most mightie and
Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Princesse) is clothed with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons heauenly giftes, and doeth
holde vp the golden rodde of wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which leadeth to the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s ting
kingdome. I hope therefore (by the goodnesse of God) that it shall
please your Highnesse to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this Garlande of mans glorification to
come into your sweete gracious handes: prefixed with the bright beames of
your Maiesties princely glorious Name, vnder the high precious
<hi>Cedar,</hi> and sweete <hi>Libanus</hi> of your heauenly good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne sse
of mercie and pardon: That though I be troubled in<pb facs="2"/>heart with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eare of your supers plendent
perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, (being a mightie princes of power) to dedicate this Pamphlet to
your most excellent <hi>Maiestie:</hi> yet the singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar clearenesse of
your spirituall treasures of goodnesse, doth preuaile ouer my dutifull
minde and faithfull allegeance in such sort, as if the precious pearle of
your vertues did shine into my heart, not forbidding this litle Pamphlet to
come vnto your Highnes: trusting that the purenes of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will
increase your MAIESTIES deare soule, to an exceeding consolation touching
your bodie to bee glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. In consideration whereof, when I did beholde
the goodly order of the bright glistering starres, which the omnipotent
Creator hath placed in the firmament of the heauens: (there seeing the
resplendent starre, <hi>Corona luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi>) I was stirred vp with the
ioyfull remembrance of your Maiesties incomparable personage, being the
<hi>Lordes Anointed:</hi> knowing that your Highnesse, being vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
meeke, and mercifull, is equall with the good Kinges of Iuda, (with <hi>Asa,
Ezechias, Iehos aphat, and Iosias,</hi>) in imbracing all godly vertues to
the aduauncing of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; glorie of God: that as your Maiestie in
all points doe holde your scepter linked to the Scepter of Iuda, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an
vnfeigned friend to the holy one of Israel) so your highnes subiectes in
great consolation of heart, do pray sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely (in all humblenesse of
duety) vnto God for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation of your Maiestie lōg to reigne ouer
vs: And that at the appearance of Christ you may be a glorious Saint in the
kingdome of God. And now considering howe much Israel reioyced of
<hi>Salomon,</hi> &amp; how greatly it lamented after his departure: Am
perswaded how much all true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants do pray that the Lord may be your
shield as he was to Abraham and that your blessed personage (may by the
great mercie and s ingular goodnesse of God) gouerne this Realme as
happily and as many yeeres (and more) as good king <hi>Asa</hi> king of Iuda
did, to the glorie of God, and salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<pb facs="2"/>of soules. Wherefore
<hi>(most Mightie and Renowned Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne)</hi> when I, (an inferiour,
vnworthie to touch the groūd that your Maiestie doe walke on) had finished
this Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full garland of mans glorification, expressing the mysterie of
new Ierusalem, with her golden crownes and diademes I thought it so much to
represent the heauenly ioyes and happinesse of our euerlasting glorie:
as that it was a matter meete to be dedicated to your most excellent
Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, shewing howe your <hi>Highnesse,</hi> being an Anointed and
blessed Princesse of power vnder God, vpon the earth, shal meete (at
the great day of resurrection) the King of al kings comming in his triumphant
progresse from heauen, with the glorious companie of his holy Angels: when
your pure personage shall beholde that incomprehensible Scepter of the
euerlasting kingdome of Dauid: That as your <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie</hi> in your
progresse vpon the earth, hath highly preferred your faithfull subiectes
in Christ to honour and dignitie: so nowe that glorious King of eternitie
and euerlasting glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>will fashion your bodie to be like his owne
glorious body:</hi> for that, your blessed power hath set foorth the true
Religion, worshippe, and honour of God, to a liuely hope among your
Highnesse subiectes to obteine the eternall garlande of glorie. Thus
humbly committing this litle Pamphlet of mans glorification vnto your Princely
magnificence, and godly wisedome, doe beseech your Highnesse in your
ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der minde of mercie, to receiue it vnder your sweete gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious mans ion
of goodnesse: among your spirituall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of heauenly solace and
ioye: thereby daily remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring how your God and Sauiour Iesus Christ,
shall clothe your Maiestie with an euerlasting garment of glorie,
shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vpon you with the light of his owne coūtenance, there sitting
with Christ in his owne seate of heauenlinesse, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting the
vnspeakeable ioyes of eternall blessednesse, where you shall
glister as the shining of heauen worlde without end, beholding the beauty
of God for euer, in new Ierusalē.<pb facs="3"/>Thus hoping that your
Maiesties mercie will be as a vayle to my boldenesse, doe trust that as
your Highnesse hath truely touched the hemme of Christes garment, whereby
you haue partaken the heauenly sparkes of the vertues of Christ: that it
would please your goodnesse to admit one sparke towards the acceptation
of this glorious garlande: And so I pray God with all instance, that it may
please him of his aboundant mercie, to preserue you our Sweete beloued
Queene, and true branch of Christ, long to reigne ouer vs in tranquillitie
and peace, to the setting foorth of Gods honour, and spreading abroade of
his glorie, that your MAIESTIE may ioyfully appeare before Christ, and be
crowned with the Crownes and Diademes of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting glorification: which (O
Lord) so let it be.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble Subiect, &amp;
faithfull Orator, <hi>FRANCIS KETT.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>