<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT EXCELLENTLY VER∣tuous Lady, MARY, Coun∣tesse of Buckingham, C. N. wisheth euent of all felicitie.</title>
           <author>Newstead, Ch.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101131_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08172</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18508</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101131</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT EXCELLENTLY VER∣tuous Lady, MARY, Coun∣tesse of Buckingham, C. N. wisheth euent of all felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Newstead, Ch.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apology for vvomen: or, Womens defence. Pend by C.N. late of Albane Hall in Oxon</title>
                 <author>C. N. (Christopher Newstead)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Whitaker, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 55, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT EXCELLENTLY VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady, MARY, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesse of Buckingham, <hi>C. N. wisheth euent of all felicitie.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAM,</hi> I neede not haue a Lanterne &amp; a Candle to inuestigate a vertuous woman, as <hi>Diogenes</hi> had to finde an honest man: they appeare like so many Starres, fixed in this terrestriall Globe. Yet no sooner did the Sunne of your presence enter into the Horizon of my thoughts, but it ouershad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed all the fore-appearers Honour seated in your brest, findes it selfe adorned as in a rich Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ace, making that excellent,
<pb facs="3"/>which makes it admirable, which caused me to present vnto your Ladiships protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this my ill-looking Infant, the maden-head (as I may so tearme it) of my inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, conceiued in my brains, by the frothy word of many Hyperbolizing selfe-concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, who deeme it their greatest grace, to be able to disgrace women. If then (exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site Lady) an ouer-speedy or weaning desire of repulsing your sexes wrongs, hath caused my braines with <hi>Semele,</hi> to bring forth this obortiue Bacchus, or brood. Be you the <hi>Ioue</hi> to nourish it in the lap of your good liking, that being wrapt in the swaddling bands of your fauour, the cold of contempt may not so easily freeze it. And if <hi>Miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua</hi> grant a safe returne to my Muse traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>king in her Indies, I shall, I hope, present you with a more richer Prize.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladiships vnfainedly deuoted in all obseruant seruice, CH. NEVVSTEAD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>