<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101284_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06606</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1707</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101284</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the iudge of controuersies : Written in Latin, by the R. Father Martinus Becanus of the Society of Iesus, Professour in Diuinity. And Englished by W.W. Gent</title>
                 <author>Becanus, Martinus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 170, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE Reader, hauing perused this short Treatise, trāsla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into English, and sent vnto me by a friend; I was straight moued with earnest desire to set the same forth in Print, hoping that many wold reape great benefit by reading it, &amp; come to be resolued in the may nest of the Controuersyes that now disturbe the Christiā
<pb facs="3"/> world: yea such a Cōtrouersy, as the knowledge therof is the beginning of al Truth, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywise Errour therein the fountaine of all Contentions. For if both sides, Protestants as well as Catholikes, would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit some visible Iudge, liuing on earth, endued with full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to decide their contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersyes, about the sense of holy scripture, by sentence infallible &amp; not obnoxious vnto deceit, Contentions might be soone ended, and an vniuersall peace throughout Christendome, for in matters of Religion, establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed.</p>
   <p>Now the contrary currant
<pb facs="3"/> perswasion, That Scripturs are cleare and perspicuous in all points of Controuersy, and their true sense apparent &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious to euery simple man, that shall attentiuely peruse the Text; hath opened a wide gap for all Heresyes to enter into Christendome, rending in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ees the Peace &amp; Vnity therof, and depriuing the same of all meanes by which Cōtentions may be brought to some finall end. For men being once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded, that they see the Truth in all points of Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerted, no lesie cleerly shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Holy Scriptures, then the Sunne doth at noone
<pb facs="4"/> day; they must needs condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, as erring, &amp; wanting the light of Gods spirit, all others that shal vnderstand the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures otherwise then they do. And this so peremptorily, as they will contemne the senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of any Pastour or Pastours, that shal sit in iudgment vpon the Cōtrouersy.</p>
   <p>This presumption of light to vnderstād the Scriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue their Elders, so much proclaymed in Protestāts pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, makes our Aduersaryes disagree implacably, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope of reconcilement, not only frō vs, but also betweene themselues: Yea (as a Protestāt
<pb facs="4"/> of great name, well acquainted<note place="margin">
         <hi>Hook. Eccles. folis. pag.</hi> 119.</note> with the proceedings of their Churches, complaines) <q rend="margQuotes">this conceit hath made thousands so headstrong, euen in grosse &amp; palpable errors; that a man, whose capacity will scarse serue him to vtter fiue words in sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible manner, blusheth not, in any doubt concerning matter of Scripture, to thinke his own bare <hi>Yea,</hi> as good as the <hi>Nay</hi> of all the wise, graue, and learned iudgmēts that are in the whol world: which Insolency must be repressed, or it willbe the bane of Christian Religion.</q> Thus he.</p>
   <p>This insolent doctrine is
<pb facs="5"/> in this Treatise solidely, brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; perspicuously confuted, and the necessity of a liuing Iudge, assisted by Gods special prouidēce infailibly to decide the Controuersyes of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is so cleerly demonstrated, that I conceaue great hope, that many by the perusal ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, will cast off the foresayd proud Hereticall perswasion, which themselues are forced to confesse to be the bane of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stianity. I pray God this my wish may take effect, and thou that art a Christian, reape as much comfort by the reading thereof, as I wish vnto thee.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>