<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRI∣stian Reader, Grace and peace in Christ: &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Fairlambe, Peter</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101811_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00530</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10668</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101811</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRI∣stian Reader, Grace and peace in Christ: &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Fairlambe, Peter</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The recantation of a Brownist. Or A reformed puritan. Written by one that hath altogether, bin led in the same erronious oppinions for many yeeres together: and now since his conuersion, hath measured the pretended holy discipline, by pastors, doctors, elders and deacons, (which the disciplinarian malecontents would obtrude vpon our Church,) and hath found it far shorter, then the discipline vsed either in the primitiue Church, or in this our Church of England: if all antiquitie be not reiected</title>
                 <author>Fairlambe, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Blower (Blore), Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gosson, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader, Grace and peace in Christ: &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING beene heretofore (right cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and friendly Reader) led into the schisme of Brownists or Donatists of England, by following and beleeuing certaine of our Preaches, who drew many into a course vnder pretence of extraordinarie zeale, the grounds wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of droue vs into another far worse (God knowes) namely to that seperation from the Church of England: beeing taught by the first sort (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Puritanes) that the ministerie and discipline of our Church is Ante-christian: which whosoeuer beleeueth (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a good conscience) cannot chuse but fall into that seperation as I did, and continue therin, vntill the grounds set forth by the first sort of Teachers be shewed to be weak and vnsound: as they are most fully and learnedly by that worthy and reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther D: Bilson B: of Winchester, in his worthy and learned worke <hi>called the Perpetuall Gouernment of Christes Church:</hi> and other bookes mentioned in the discourse following. Now I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="5"/> by the great mercie of God, after many miserable dayes spent in these courses, both by land and sea, and diuers very hard imprisonments (as I deserued) to my great impouerishing brought into the bosome of this Church againe. I was well esteemed of by diuers great fauourites, of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended holy discipline as a man, fit to grace that humane deuise. For they knew that I then could, and yet can if I would (as some doe) dissemble for my bellies sake, say as much for that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise, as the most vnlearned Artificer in this Land could or can doe. But I not hauing learned their art (and the Iesuites) of Equiuocation or dissimulation, did plainely make knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, that vtterly disliked that discipline as which had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the poore Brownists their hold, as I haue prooued in the Treatise following very plainely. I had no sooner made known my Resolution but I was censured by busie Reformers, who became my vtter and cruell enemies, seeking to disgrace mee, both at home and abroad by all vnlawfull meanes and slaunders (as tis their vse, to deale with all them, that touching disciplina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie courses, change their minde, and begin to haue any liking of the present gouerment established in our Church. Trauailing into Barbary to seeke maintenance for my wife and 7. children thither they sent worde, that I had articled against two Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens, for suffring certaine Brownists to liue in the Parish, with their children vn-baptized, and that the men were vndone by me, which was with the rest a malicious vntruth: For I with a Preacher of mine acquaintance searched all the offices in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and could not finde eyther Brownists or Churchwardens of the parish of Stepney in any trouble at all. As for the Brownists I was so farre from troubling them, or causing their trouble beeing honest simple people that when they were by the Officers discouered, I went twice to that right Reuerend and worthy Father Archb. White gift in their behalfe: who did ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily condiscend that their children (beeing some yeeres of age) should be as priuately Baptized as might bee, and that in the Church and they no farther troubled, as may appeare by a letter written by Sir Edward Stanop at my Lordes appointment vnto Mr. Thomson the Minister and the Churchwardens of the said
<pb facs="5"/> Parish of Stepney. Howbeit some of them haue railed vpon me in the open streets of London with most opprobrious spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, bidding me go tell their Antechristian holinesses the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops my new masters, that they were enemies to the truth of God and all good Preachers: though these impure Railers doe submit themselues to all the orders of our Church as I do, with what conscience let the wise Iudge. It is not vnknowne to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the Parish what cruell hatred that sort hath laboured to bring me into, euen to the vndoing of my Wife and 7. poore children in the time of the last Plague, and euer since, for shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my priuate dislike of certaine seditious doctrines deliuered at that time in the Church of Stepney, by one who for diuers horrible beastly and notorious misdemeanors was suspended and silenced. They most slaunderously charged mee to bee the cause of his troubles, and so continued plotting my ouerthrow by such shamelesse meanes, accounting me worse then <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apostata, maliciously beating my children in the streetes, not shaming to say, that they hoped to see my children seeke their bread out of the durtie channels in the streetes: for driuing (as they said) that good man away: Who since that time, hath cleared mee, of their accusations publikely in the Pulpit, and washed his hands (that were so filthy before) though his flatterers giue out that he recanted for feare, onely to keepe himselfe within the safetie of the ministerie from irregularitie, yea albeit he sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed most largely, and would haue done more then that if he had beene vrged. What should I speake of their worse then Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish and more then sauage crueltie, in diswading my neighbours from my societie. What should I speake of their pride, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring with, yea preferring some of their fanaticall preachers and many of their owne selues, before the ancient fathers, yea aboue S: Peter the Apostle. Doe they not know what with Mr. <hi>Caluin</hi> that excellent light in Gods Church, did write to <hi>Iacobus Grineus</hi> before his commentary on the Romanes; concerning the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent estimation, that men ought to haue of the wisedome and authoritie of the auntient fathers. Or were they neuer acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the speech had by old Mr. <hi>Crowley</hi> our own countriman, who deemed those no better then most arrogant Heretikes,
<pb facs="6"/> which will compare any of our time, yea <hi>Caluin</hi> himselfe with S. <hi>Augustine.</hi> After they had breathed out against mee a sillie wretch, against the saints in heauen, and the holy men of our time now at rest, with the elect in heauen: their cursed threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings (in a short space after) tooke such effect that their strong venemous breath which I could not endure, droue me and mine houshold into the country: where my poore wife and children, mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>stned their bread with teares, and their drinke with we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, as chaced by these tyrants, by sea and by Land, into places vnknowne to them and me, which I pray thee O Lord lay not vnto their charge but forgiue their sinnes and relieue our distresses. Maruaile not I pray you ne be not offended at me, that I thus ease my sorrowes by relating them vnto your christian compassionate eares. My poore maintenance of a iust quarrell, in a good conscience hath occasioned these plowers to plow thus vpon my backe, and to make long furrowes. I sent a coppie of the Letters answeres confutations and replications on both sides (betwixt Mr. <hi>Barnhere</hi> and me in Barbery) vnto some of my neighbours the parishioners concerning the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies then very rife: and now raked vp againe, healing and fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out, I did not at the first aintend the publishing thereof in print or to any whome it did not concerne, which knew not of the businesse which then fell out. This is no more but a Coppie of that which I sent vnto my neighbours at Ratliffe and Lime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house, when I was in Barbary. I haue not learned to abuse any mans person, or his gifts, be they beuer so meane. But I rather say this man now deceased was a mirrour of that sort of Ministers, who for his knowledge and faith in Christ, for his painefull study and exercise in the scriptures, knowledge in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, he was to be commended, imbraced reuerenced. A man which carried himselfe with that moderation and meekenes of spirit, in the handling of these controuersies both priuately and publikely, as I wish vnfaynedly, that the measure of that grace, were bestowed vpon some of the peeuish spirits, when God hath giuen them repentance. That which I haue added to the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Coppie is the names of those bookes with &amp; against disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, which I haue read, with an answere vnto two obiections,
<pb facs="6"/> which came to mine handes since I wrote it: as also a table of such Clergie Martirs as I find in our Martyr booke, and in <hi>Euse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius Pamphil</hi>) God graunt that though these things be collected by a poore ignorant Artificer, neither professing nor hauing wherewith to doe it as it should be done: yet hee would blesse to his Glory such weake meanes in such sort, that at the least such poore men (as my selfe was once) may bee kept from rending themselues from Christes holy Church heere in England, or else where. For I doe heare that there be some increase of Brownists now in and about London, who are obstinate in their ignorance, affirming that our Church is an hold of Deuils, and a cage of vncleane birdes, whose eyes I beseech God to open, that they may come home againe with the Prodigall child. And for our selues let vs hartily pray for the peace of Ierusalem, for they shall prosper that loue the same, <hi>Psalme</hi> 122.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lorde Peter Fairlambe.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>