<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶Rychard Eden to the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101322_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07873</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18244</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101322</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶Rychard Eden to the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatyse of the newe India : with other new founde landes and islandes, aswell eastwarde as westwarde, as they are knowen and found in these oure dayes, after the description of Sebastian Munster in his boke of universall cosmographie: wherin the diligent reader may see the good successe and rewarde of noble and honeste enterpryses, by the which not only worldly ryches are obtayned, but also God is glorified, [and] the Christian faythe enlarged. Translated out of Latin into Englishe. By Rycharde Eden</title>
                 <author>Münster, Sebastian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sutton, Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>204 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>¶Rychard Eden to the reader.</head>
   <p>WHereas in this Booke (welbeloued Read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r) y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> mayest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eade ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ye straunge thinges, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d in maner incredible, except the same were proued most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn by dayly experiēce, &amp; approued auctoritie, (as shall hereafter appeare) I thought it good for thy bett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r instruction to make this Preface, wherby t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>u mightest more playnly &amp; sensibly cōprehend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he reasons &amp; causes, yf not of al, yet of some of the chiefest thinges, which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in the same<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Therfore wheras thou shalt r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ade of the great abundaūce of gold, precious stones &amp; spices, which the Spaniardes &amp; Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugales haue brought frō the South partes of the worlde, as from the newe founde landes &amp; Ilandes, the sodeyn straungenes or greatnes of the thing shal not so much amase thy wittes, and gender in thee incrudelitie, yf thou cōsider the saying of wyse Salomon, who affyrmeth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> there is no new thing vnder the Sunne,<note place="margin">nothing new vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sunne.</note> &amp; that the thing that hath been, cometh to passe again: which saying doeth greatly cōfyrme the trueth, of such thinges as are spoken of in this Boke, wheras the same perhappes to some mē might otherwyse seme in maner incredible, yf the lyke had not been sene in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yme paste, &amp; approued by auctoritie of moste holy scripture, which decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring


<pb facs="8"/>
the great wysdō, ryches, &amp; noble viages of King Salomō,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 4</note> sayth that God gaue him wisdō and vnderstāding exceding muche, and a large heart, and that he prepared a nauie of shippes,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 9</note> in the porte of <hi>Azion Gaber,</hi> by the brinke of the redde sea, which sayled to <hi>Ophir,</hi> &amp; brought frō thence .xxi. score hundreth (whiche is .xl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. M.) weyght of golde. Agay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e,<note place="margin">3. Re. 10.</note> that the weyghte of golde which was broughte to Salomon in one yere, was .vi. hūdreth, thre score &amp; .vi. talētes of gold, wheras the Hebrue talente, called <hi>Talente Haebraicū sanctuarii,</hi> was of our st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rling money 500. pounde, &amp; <hi>Talent Haebrai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>um uulgare,</hi> was halfe so much. Lykewyse y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uer was nothing worth in the dayes of Salomō, and y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he made siluer &amp; gold in Hierusalē as plētiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> as stones Agay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">2. Par. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> that he ouerlayd the house of the Lord with precious stones beauti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ully,<note place="margin">1. Par. 3.</note> and the gold wherwith he couered it, was golde of <hi>Paruaim.</hi> Also that the kinges nauie of shippes wēt once in thre yere to <hi>Tharsis,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Tharsis</hi> Golde Apes Elephā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> and brought Gold, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Apes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Peacockes, and Elephantes teeth, Which wordes surely seme so to confirme such thinges as are spoken of in the nauigacions wherof this boke entreateth, that nothinge can make more for the truth of the same:<note place="margin">Salomōs shippes.</note> and briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to speake of the places whether Salomons shippes sayled for Gold, as <hi>Tharsis</hi> and <hi>Ophir.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ophir.</hi>
      </note> This ought to be cōsydered for a general rule, that nearest vnto the south partes of the world


<pb facs="9"/>
betwene the two Tropikes vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <hi>Equinoctial</hi> or burning lyne, where the sunne is of greatest forse,<note place="margin">Where Gold is engende<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red.</note> is the chiefest place where gold is engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, although it be sometymes founde in colde regiōs as in Scotland, in Crayford more, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ngary,<note place="margin">Scotlād Hūgary</note> yet nether pure of it self, nor in great quātitie: the reason whereof is largely declared in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ookes of George Agric, &amp; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus Magnus. And wheras it is written in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oke of Kinges in the Actes of Salomon that he prepared his shippes in <hi>Azion Gaber,</hi>
      <note place="margin">3. Reg. 9 <hi>Azion Gaber.</hi>
      </note> beyng by the brinke of the readde s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a, and sayled from thence to <hi>Ophir</hi> for Golde, it is apparaunt, that (howsoeuer the names of thinges haue altered and perisshed in tyme) he sayled from thence southwarde towarde the Equinoctial lyne,<note place="margin">the <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noctial</hi> line.</note> for asmuche as there is none other passage oute of the narownesse of the readde sea, but onely into the mayne South sea, by the which the Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales euen at this daye make theyr viage to <hi>Calicut,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Calicut.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Samo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ra, Madagascar,</hi> and such other I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes in the South east partes of the worlde, where Golde, Spyces, Apes, and Elephantes are nowe founde in lyke maner.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Tharsis</hi> in <hi>cilicia.</hi>
      </note> But as for <hi>Tharsis</hi> bey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ge a cytye of <hi>Cilicia</hi> in Asia the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse &amp; the na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iue countreye of S. Paule the Apostle, and situa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e muche more toward the North, thē is Iudea, and in maner directlye ouer againste Iudea on the othersyde of the sea called Mare


<pb facs="9"/>
Mediteraneū, &amp; in the same clime, in the which standeth the Ilande of Sicilia,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Sicilia.</hi>
      </note> and the cytie of Ciuile in Spayne,<note place="margin">Ciuile in Spayne</note> it hardelye agreeth with the principles of Philosophie &amp; cōmon experience, that golde should be there engendred in lyke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundaunce as in Regions more towarde the south, much lesse Elephantes and Apes, which are no where engēdred farre frō the <hi>AEquinoctial</hi> lyne, or beyonde the two Tropikes, nor yet wil engendre yf they be broughte into those partes of the world. The lyke is to be vnderstande of Popingiayes and spyces,<note place="margin">Spyces.</note> and dyuers other beastes, fruites, and trees, which are engende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tayne climes of the worlde, and wyll not prospere in other places: the reason wherof were here to longe declare.<note place="margin">Pepper.</note> For lyke as pepper wyll not growe in Spayne, no more wyll the Orange tree bringe foorth fruite in Englande.<note place="margin">Orange tree.</note> Wherefore, it maye seme by good reason, that the Golde, Apes, and Elephantes teeth which were broughte from <hi>Tharsis</hi> (yf it were <hi>Tharsis</hi> of <hi>Cilicia</hi>) were not engēdered there, but rather brought thether by marchaūtes from the south partes of the world, out of Mauritania, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marica, Ethiopia, Libia, &amp; Arabia, or otherwise by lande, from the East India,<note place="margin">East In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dia.</note> lyke as at this daye, the greate multitude of Spyces, Golde, Precious stones, Sylke, and Iuerye, whyche is at Calicut and Cambaia, growe not al in the regiōs there about, but are brought thether frō


<pb facs="10"/>
dyuers other countreys, as doeth more largely appeare in this Boke. And that Salomōs fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours for exchau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ge of other marchaundyse, bought the same in <hi>Tharsis,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Solomō boughte golde of marchā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>g bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ght the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther frō other countreyes, as it is written in the thyrde Boke of the Kinges, that Salomon had great plentie of Gold of Marchauntes &amp; Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries. So that to conclude, I would rather thinke (sauing reformacion of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her better lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) that this <hi>Tharsis</hi> (&amp; not <hi>Tharsis</hi> of <hi>Cilicia,</hi>) from whence Salomon had so great plentie of Gold and Iuerie, were rather some other coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey in the south partes of the world, then this <hi>Tharsis</hi> of <hi>Cilicia.</hi> For<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> not onely olde and newe Histories, dayly experience, and the principles of natural Philosophie doe agree, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the places most apte to bring forth gold, spices, &amp; precious stones,<note place="margin">the south &amp; south east.</note> are the South and Southeast partes of the world,<note place="margin">Mat 12</note> but also our Sauiour Christ appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the same,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Reg. x 2. Par. 9 the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ba, the quene of the south</note> declaring that the Quene of the South (meaning the Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne of Saba) came frō the vtmoste partes of the worlde to heare the wysdom of Salomon. And lyke as by the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie of these woordes it is playne fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> what partes of the world she came, the same to a phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophical head is apparent by s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>che r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ches &amp; presentes as she broughte with her. For albeit that in the Chronacles of Salomon it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot written by expressed wordes that she came frō the Southe, yet is it wrytten that she came to


<pb facs="10"/>
Hierusalem with a very great trayne,<note place="margin">2, par. 9 3. Reg. x</note> with ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels laden with spyces, swete odours, &amp; excea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding much gold &amp; precious stones, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scripcion doeth well agree,<note place="margin">Saba in <hi>Ethiopia</hi> vnder E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gipt.</note> both with the situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the cytie of Saba in <hi>Ethiopia</hi> vnder E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt: and also with the cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>trey of Saba, being in the middel of Arabia,<note place="margin">Saba in Arabia.</note> inuironned about with great rockes wherin is a great wood of Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous trees, some of Cinomome &amp; Cassia, &amp; some bringing forth frank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ncense and myrre, as wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Plinius lib.</hi> 12. and <hi>Theophrastus li.</hi> 9. <hi>de Hist. Plant.</hi> Wherefore the Quene of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aba myghte worthely be called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he quene of the South, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as bothe Saba (or rather Sabat) in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia,</hi> whiche Iosephus thinketh to be the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of <hi>Meroe,</hi> now called <hi>Elsaba,</hi> beinge in the ryuer of <hi>Nilus,</hi> &amp; that the quene came frō thence, &amp; also Saba in Arabia, are situate farre South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde from Hierusalem, euen in maner in the middest of the lyne, called <hi>Tropicus Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ri,</hi> and the <hi>Equin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ctinal lyne,</hi>
      <note place="margin">the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ba came frō the Iland of Meroae.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>here the Pole Artike is eleuate not passing .1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. degrees or thereabout (as in Meroae) where as the same pole is eleuate at Hierusalem. 22. degrees: whereby it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the quene of Saba (whō Christe calleth the quene of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> south,) came frō the south partes about .xi. hundreth &amp; .xl. miles from Hierusalē, for the same distaunce is frō Saba in <hi>Meroe</hi> to Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>salem, as betwene Rome &amp; Englād.<note place="margin">Frō Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to Englād.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut as touching this matter, it shall suffyse to haue


<pb facs="11"/>
sayde thus muche. Nowe therefore to returne home from these farre countreys,<note place="margin">The vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of our men to <hi>cathay</hi>
      </note> and to speake somewhat of this viage which oure countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menne, haue attempted to sayle into the Easte partes, by the coastes of Norway, Lappia, and Finmarchia,<note place="margin">Norway Lappia, Finmar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chia.</note> and so by the narrowe tracte of the Sea by the coastes of Grouelande, into the frosen sea, called <hi>Maroae,</hi> Congelatū, &amp; so forth to Cathay (yf any suche passage may be found) whiche onely doubte doeth at this daye disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage many faynte hearted men, speciallye bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in the moste parte of Globes &amp; Mappes they see the continente or fyrme land,<note place="margin">Globes &amp; map<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes.</note> extended euen to the North Pole without any such pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage. Which thing ought to moue no mā great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orasmuch as the most parte of Globes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d mappes are made after Ptolomeus Tables:<note place="margin">Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus.</note> Who, albeit he was an excellent man, yet were there many thinges hyd from his knowledge, as not sufficientelye tryed or searched at those daies, as manifestly appeareth in that he knew nothing of.<note place="margin">
         <hi>America.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>America</hi> with the hole fyrme lande adherent thereunto, which is nowe found to be the fourth parte of the earth. Neyther yet knew he any thinge of the passage by the Weste into the Easte, by the strayghtes of <hi>Magellanus</hi> as you shal reade in this Boke,<note place="margin">The straygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gellanus.</hi>
      </note> Neyther of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes in the Weste Ocean Sea,<note place="margin">the Ilan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of <hi>Molucca</hi>
      </note> nor of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes of <hi>Molucca</hi> situate in the mayne Easte Indian Sea. And as touchinge this passage,


<pb facs="11"/>
albeit, it were not knowē in Ptolomeus dayes yet other auctors of later time, who perhappes haue hadde further experience of the thing (as good reason is) doe wryte not onely that there is a passage by the Northe Sea into the mayne Easte Sea,<note place="margin">Passage by the north sea into the East.</note> but doe also further declare, howe certayne shippes haue safelye sayled throughe the same,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Pius secū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dus. lib. i. Capit. ii.</hi> note wel the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> North sea.</note> as <hi>Pius secundus</hi> (otherwyse called <hi>AE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eas Siluius</hi>) an excellente aucto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e descrybeth in his Boke of Cosmographie, where he hath these wordes folowing. Of the North Ocean Sea, whether it may be sayled aboute or not, the contencion is greater, yet is it apparaunte that the greateste parte thereof aboute Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie,<note place="margin">Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</note> hath been searched by the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of Augustus themperour, euen vnto the promontorie or landes ende of the people,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Cimbria.</hi>
      </note> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Cimbri.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Caspia.</hi> the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donians</note> The seas also and coastes of <hi>Caspia</hi> were so searched during the warres of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians</hi> vnder the dominion of <hi>Seleucus</hi> &amp; <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiocus,</hi> that al most all the North on euery syde was sayled about. Plinie rehearseth the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Cornelius Nepos,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Plinius. Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Nepos Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>uia,</hi> called al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>so <hi>Succia</hi> nere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>and and norway.</note> who wryteth that the king of Sueuia (or Swethelande) gaue to <hi>Metellus celer,</hi> proconsull or leauetenaunte of Fraunce, certayne Iudians or menne of Iude, whiche saylinge out of India for mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyse, were by tempest drieuen into Germanie. We also reade in Otho, that vnder thempyre


<pb facs="12"/>
of the Germaynes, there was a shippe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians taken in the North sea of Germanie,<note place="margin">A ship of Indians driuē frō the East into the North seas.</note> and drieuen thether by contrary wynd frō the East partes: which thing coulde by no meanes haue comen to passe, yf (as many menne thinke) the North sea were not nauigable by reason of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme cold &amp; Ise. And these be the very wordes of <hi>Pius Secundus,</hi> whereunto I adde, that thys, notwithstandinge, yf it should so chaunce, that ether there can no such passage be found, or the same so daungerous, or otherwyse that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cutte thereof by which onely perhappes any shippes might passe, could not be founde, yea, or to caste the worste, yf they shoulde perishe in this viage, yet I woulde wishe all men to be of such corage and constancie in these affayres, as are valiaunt capitaynes in the warres: who, yf by misfortune they take a foyle, doe rather stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die how by some other wayes to recouer theyr honour and reputaciō diminished by the same, then with shame, losse, &amp; dishonour, euer after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde to geue place to theyr enemyes, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweare the warres. Wherefore, to conclude, yf no good can be done this way, it were worthy the aduēture to attempt, yf the same viage may bee broughte to passe, another waye, as by the strayght called <hi>Fretū trium fratrum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The via<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thay</hi> West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde &amp; by north</note> westward &amp; by North from England, whiche viage is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently knowen to suche as haue any skyll in


<pb facs="12"/>
Geographie. As for other landes and Ilandes in the west sea, where the Eagle (yet not in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place) hath so spled his winges, that other poore byrdes may not without offēce seke theyr praye within the compasse of the same,<note place="margin">the earth compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> I wyll speake nothing hereof, bycause I wold be loth to lay an egge, wherof other men might hatche a serpent. Wherfore to let this passe, &amp; to entre into another matter. Forasmuch as in these our daies hath chaūced so great a secret to be foūd, as the like hath neuer been knowē or heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, (what soeuer God meant to kepe this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery hyd so long) I thoughte it good to speake somwhat hereof: trusting y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the pleasaūt cōtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placiō of the thing it selfe, shal make the length of this preface lesse tedious, especially yf it find a reader whose soule delyteth to prayse God in his workes. The thing therfore is this, how the hole globe of the world (of the earth and wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I meane) hath been sayled aboute, by the West into the East, as doth more largely appeare in this boke in the nauigaciōs of <hi>Magellanus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gellanus.</hi>
      </note> who from Spayne sayled Westward to the Ilādes of <hi>Molucca</hi> being in the East sea,<note place="margin">The Ilā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of <hi>Molucc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi>
      </note> farre beyond y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> furthest partes of East India: &amp; the portugales came to the same Ilandes frō Spayne sayling Eastward by the coastes of Aphrica, Arabia, &amp; the vttermost India beyōd the ryuer of <hi>Ganges</hi> where, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Indian sea the sayd Ilādes of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucca</hi>
      <pb facs="13"/>
are situate. A thing surely most wōderful, and in maner incredible, but that the same is proued most certayne by experience,<note place="margin">Experiē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of al sciences</note> the teacher and mestres of all sciences, for lacke of whose ayde (experience I meane) lyke as many greate wittes haue fallen into great errours, so by her ayde, many base and cōmon wittes haue attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the knowledge &amp; practise of such wōder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full effectes,<note place="margin">Sense &amp; vnderstā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge.</note> as could hardely be comprehēded by the discourse of reasō. Which thing or other lyke, I suppose was the cause why the noble Philosopher Aristoteles sayde:<note place="margin">A senten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristotell.</note>
      <hi>Quod nihil est in intellectu {quod} non fuit prius insensu,</hi> that is, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge is in vnderstandinge, but the same was fyrst in sense, that is to saye subiect to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> senses. Yet would I not that any rashe witte shoulde hereby take holde, as thoughte eyther Aristotle or I, meant that sence were more excellent th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> reason, but rather that reasō vsing sense, taketh his principles and fyrst sedes of thinges sensy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; afterwarde by his owne discourse &amp; sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of causes, encreaseth the same frō a seede to a tree, as from an acorne to an oke.<note place="margin">Experiē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce ioined with spe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culacion</note> Nought els to say, but that experiēce to be most certayn which is ioyned with reason or speculaciō, and that reason to be most sure which is confirmed with experience, accordinge as the Phisicians determe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in theyr science, that neyther practyse i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> safe without speculaciō, nor speculaciō with


<pb facs="13"/>
out practyse. Wherfore, whereas men of great knowledge and experiēce, are to great affaires, theyr attemptes haue for the moste parte good successe,<note place="margin">A per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth no vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall.</note> as doeth moste playnly appeare in all histories: notwithstanding that some ignoraūt men wyl alledge that certayn rashe aduētures haue prospered well: which sayinge proueth no more thē yf a mā should say, that twise or thrise a mā vnarmed slew a mā armed (as dyd some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme the wyld Irishmē at bullē) Ergo,<note place="margin">what is knowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dge and learning.</note> it were better to fight vnarmed thē armed. And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I haue here spokē of knowledge ioyned w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> experiēce, I meane by knowledge y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which we cōmonly call learning, whether it be gottē out of bokes (which are the writinges of wyse and expert men) or otherwyse by conference &amp; edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caciō with such as are lerned: meaning nought els by learning, but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> gathering of many mēs wittes into one mans head, &amp; the experience of many yeres, and many mens lyues, to the lyfe of one, whō we call a learned wyse, and expert man. The which defynicion and effect of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Baltassar Castaglio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nae.</hi>
      </note> the noble &amp; learned cortier Baltassar Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staglione (the auctour of the boke called in the Italian tongue <hi>il cortegiono,</hi>) diligently consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deringe,<note place="margin">A false perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> frēshm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> doeth greatlye blame and reproue the frenshmen in that they thinke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the knowledge of letters doeth hinder the affayres of warre, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which perswasiō he proueth by many reasons


<pb facs="14"/>
and examples to be most false. But as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge the matter whereof this boke entreateth the greate Philosopher Albertus Magnus,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi>
      </note> onelye by learninge, wythoute experyence, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmed that habitable or temperate Regions myghte be vnder the Equinoctial or burninge lyne,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>perat regions vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
         <hi>Equino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctial line</hi>
      </note> as appeareth in hys Booke <hi>de Natura lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum,</hi> contrarye to the opinion of other wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters whyche were before hys tyme, and yet is nowe proued by experience to bee moste true, albeit not in all places vnder the sayde lyne, the cause whereof were here to longe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare. And lyke as Albertus Magnus by knowledge of Astronomye (wherein he excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) came to the vnderstandinge hereof, euen so that greate Clerke (but better dyuyne then Phylosopher,) Sayncte Augustyne and also Lacta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tius,<note place="margin">An error of s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine &amp; <hi>Lactanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi>
      </note> for lacke of lyke knowledge in that science, fell into a chyldishe erroure, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyinge that there is anye people, called Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>antipodes</hi>
      </note> of whom the greate Astronomer of one tyme,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>anus.</hi>
      </note> Apianus wryteth in thys maner. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes are they, whyche walke wyth theyr fete dyrectelye contrarye agaynste oures, and haue the heauen dyrectelye ouer theyr heades as we haue. Yet haue we nothinge common wyth them, but all thinges contrarye: for when the Sunne causeth Sommer wyth vs, then is it Myddewynter wyth them: and when it is day


<pb facs="14"/>
wyth vs, it is nyghte wyth them: And when the daye is longeste wyth vs, then is the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geste nyghte wyth them, and the shorteste daye. Whiche, Lactantius,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Lactāti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi>
      </note> a manne otherwyse well learned, in his thyrde Booke. Capittulo foure and twentye, childisshelye erringe, with hys lyghte and opinionate argumentes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth that there is anye suche, and mocketh the Astronomers, beecause they affyrme the earth to bee rounde,<note place="margin">the roūd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth.</note> whiche neuerthelesse they proue wyth moste certayne and apparente demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracions of Geometrye, and vn`ayleable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perymentes. Whome,<note place="margin">S. augu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>styne.</note> Sayncte Augustyne folowing, in his sixtenth Booke. <hi>de Ciuitat, Dei. Capittu. ix.</hi> wryteth after thys sorte. Suche as fable that there is Antipodes, that is to saye, menne of the contrarye parte, where the sunne ryseth when it falleth to vs, and to haue theyr feete agaynste oures, we oughte by no reason to beeleue. Those bee the woordes of Sayncte Augustyne. Notwithstandinge (sayeth Apia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus) putte thou no doubte Gentle Reader,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Apianus.</hi>
      </note> that the Apostles of Christe were Antipodes the one to the other,<note place="margin">The apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stles, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tipodes</hi> the one againste thother.</note> and stode fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>te to feete the one agaynste the other, when Iames thelder and brother to Iohn the Euangeliste, the sonne of Zebedens, was in Spayne in Galitia, and Thomas the Apostle in the hygher India, they were mooste certaynelye Antipodes,


<pb facs="15"/>
walking feete to feete one agaynste the other, almost as directly as a diametrical lyne. For the Spanyardes are Antipodes to the Indiās,<note place="margin">The spa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyardes &amp; the In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diās are <hi>Antipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</hi>
      </note> and the Indians in lyke maner to the Spany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes. Which thinge also the excellente and aunciente Auctour Strabo confyrmeth to bee true, and lykewise Plinius <hi>Nat. Hist. lib. 2. Cap. 67</hi> Volateranus also, and all other Cosmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers &amp; Astronomers. Hetherto Apianus: and to declare my opinion in fewe woordes, I thinke it no greate marueyle that Saincte Augustyne shoulde fall into an erroure in the science of Astronomie in whiche he trauayled but as a straunger, forasmuche as he erred in many thinges in diuinitie which was his chief profession:<note place="margin">S. augu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stine of the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicheus</note> and was longe of the heresye of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicheus</hi> beefore he was conuerted by Saincte Ambrose:<note place="margin">S. augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes.</note> and wrytte also at the lengthe a Booke of retractes, in whych he correcteth hys owne errours. And I beleue playnely that, that excellēt witte of hys, could not haue remayned longe in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> errour yf he had been wel exercysed in Astronomy, or had knowen any suche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>xpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryence as is spoken of here beefore, howe the Spanyardes by the Weste and the Portuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les by the Easte compassed aboute the earth, whiche coulde neuer haue come to passe yf the earth were not rounde (<hi>Quantum ad maximas sui partes</hi>) as they call it. For, as for hylles and


<pb facs="15"/>
Mountaynes,<note place="margin">
         <p>Mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, let not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> roūdnes of the earth.</p>
         <p>A galle.</p>
      </note> though they be neuer so greate, yet in respecte to the byggenes of the earth, they doe no more lette the roundnesse hereof, then doe the lyttle knobbes of the berrye, which we call a galle, lette the roundnesse of the same. Where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore I am certaynely perswaded, that yf Saynct Augustyne had continued hys stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye in Astronomye (as it hadde been pytye he shoulde) or were alyue at thys daye, he woulde also haue retracted this erroure. But yf here anye supersticious head shall thinke it a hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous matter in any poynte to contrary Sainct Augustyne, lette hym hearken howe Augustine hym selfe sayeth: that he wyll neyther hys wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges or other mennes, of howe greate name or fame soeuer they be,<note place="margin">A Sēten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of S. augusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> otherwise to be beleued then the same shall, by reason bee approued to be true: <hi>Ne{que} quorumlibet disputaciones<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> &amp;c.</hi> And lyke as the greate Philosopher Aristotel, when he wryte agaynste hys mayster Plato of the question <hi>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dais,</hi> and agaynste Socrates who by the oracle of Apollo was proued to be most wyse, and certayne of hys frendes asked hym why he durste be so boulde, he aunswered that Plato was hys frende, and so was Socrates: but trueth hys frende more then they bothe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen so I thinke it no iniurye nor contumelye to Saynct Augustyne, yf the same were sayde of hym also geuynge hym otherwyse hys dewe


<pb facs="16"/>
commendacions,<note place="margin">Cōmēda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciō of s. augustin</note> as he was surelye an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> man, of dyuyne wytte, and knowledge, and so trauayled in settynge foorth Christes true Relygion in those turmoylous dayes, in perpetual combatte, agaynste learned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tykes and Prynces of the worlde, that he is worthelye called a Doctour and Pyller of Christes Churche. And as for Lactantius,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Lactanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi>
      </note> the intente of whose wrytinges was chiefelye to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hys ende, to dyminisshe thestimacion of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophye, (as at those dayes it was necessarie to doe amonge the Gentyles) and to aduaunce Goddes woorde, (whyche they contemned for the symplicitie of the same,) albeit, he attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as farre as hys learninge woulde serue hym, to make all thynges in Philophie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne, yet are hys argumentes so slender, that vnlesse GOD by the secrete working of hys spyryte, hadde called the Gentyles to the true Faythe, I feare me leaste fewe or none of them, (specyallye of the greate wyttes) woulde haue been conuerted by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>actantius argumentes. Howe he da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeth in denyinge the yearth to bee rounde, and that it is possyble that it myghte bee longe and rounde, (lyke an Egge,) or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse longe and holowe lyke a bote, (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge I suppose that the Sea myghte bee


<pb facs="16"/>
conteyned in the holownesse of the same, wyth suche other opinyons grounded of no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, it were to longe to rehearse. Yet, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuche as he was a learned manne, and for the better satisfyinge of suche wyttes as ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> desyreous to know some appearaunce of truth by naturall reason and demonstracions,<note place="margin">Of the rounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth.</note> lette vs admytte that the earth were rounde af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter anye of those fasshions whiche he descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth: yet can it not bee denyed, but that it is conteyned wythin the holowenesse (yf I maye so call it) of the ayre,<note place="margin">the earth hangeth in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aire</note> hauynge the heauen in euerye place dyrectelye ouer euery parte of the same, as sayeth the Poete and Philosopher <hi>Virgill, Caelum undi{que} sursum</hi>: Excepte perhappes Lactantius shoulde thinke that it honge by some thynge, or were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse borne vppe wyth pyllers as the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etes Fable, that the Gyaunte <hi>Atlas</hi> beareth the worlde on hys shoulders,<note place="margin">the fable of <hi>Atlas.</hi>
      </note> whereby they meane that a manne of valiente mynde must stoutelye beare the chaunces of the worlde. Of whyche hangeinge or bearynge of the earth,<note place="margin">the word of God beareth vppe the world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> I reade a better and more true say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge in the holye Scripture, where it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Fert omnia uerbo or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s sui,</hi> that is, that God sustayneth and beareth all thinges wyth the woorde of hys mouth.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="17"/>
      <note place="margin">Iob. 26.</note>Holye Iob also sayeth, that the LORD <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth oute the Northe ouer the emptye, and hangeth the earth vpon nothynge: Meaninge by nothinge, the ayre, because to oure senses it appeareth in maner as nothynge: Or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse that it is not dependynge of anye other substaunce, but to bee sustayned onelye by the power of GOD who hath appoynted the Elementes theyr places and lymittes,<note place="margin">The ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</note> and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the heuye to stande faste: as wyt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esseth Moyses in hys songe, sayinge:<note place="margin">Exo. xv.</note> By the wynde of thy nostrels the waters gathered together, the flouddes stoode styll as an heape, and the deepe wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er congeled togeather in the heart of the Sea. Wherefore yf the heauen bee rounde (whiche no manne can reasonably denye that euer sawe the Sunne and sterres moue.) And yf the earth bee the center of the worlde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendinge as we haue sayde beefore, then m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ste it needes folowe, that they whiche inhabiting the Northweste partes of the earth, haue the Pole Artike eleuate thyrtye degree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">The ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>atiō of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>he pole.</note> muste needes bee Antipodes to them whiche inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitinge the Southeaste partes of the earth, haue the Pole Antartike eleuate in the same degree, and so the lyke to bee vnderstand of all other eleuacions and degrees. And yf here anye wyll obiect, that eyther the earth or firme


<pb facs="17"/>
land is not so large, or so farre extēded,<note place="margin">the large<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es of the eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> or other wyse not inhabited althoughe it were so large, or that the sea i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> greater then the lande, to thys I aunswere, that no mā knoweth further here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of then is tryed and founde by experience, as we haue sayde beefore. And albeit that the sea were larger then the firme land, yet foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as there are Ilande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> founde in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the mayne Sea,<note place="margin">Il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>des</note> and in maner all inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, there is no reason to the contrarye, but that the people of those Ilandes maye be Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes to such as dwel on the fyrme lande, on the contrary parte, whether the earth be round and longe, yea or square, (yf you wyll) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythstandynge. But wyth what certayne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstracion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the Astronomers and Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricians,<note place="margin">Astr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mers &amp; Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> proue the earth to bee rounde, and the Sphericall or rounde forme to bee mooste perfecte, it were to longe to declare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> I wyll therefore make an ende of thys matter wyth the sayinge of Sayncte Paule in hys Oracion,<note place="margin">Act. xv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> to the menne of Athens. That GOD made of one bloudde, all nacions of menne, to dwell vpon the hole face of the earth.</p>
   <p>¶I hadde entended here (well beeloued Reader,) to haue spoken somewhat of suche straunge thynges and Monsters, whereof mencion is made in thys Booke, to thende


<pb facs="18"/>
that suche as by the narownes of theyr vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standinge are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of capacitie to conceaue the causes and natures of thynges, myghte parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue been satisfyed wyth some sensyble rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> But beynge at thys tyme otherwyse hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, it shal suffise al good and hone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t wittes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that whatsoeuer the Lorde ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h pleased,<note place="margin">Psa. 135</note> that hath he done in heauen and in earth, and in the Sea, and in all depe places<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
   </p>
   <p>¶ Ecclesiasticus. Capit. i.</p>
   <p>¶ The eye is not satisfyed with syght, &amp; the eare is not fylled with bearinge.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>