<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Note]</title>
           <author>N., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101493_Ba1_3_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11628</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21875</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101493</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Note]</title>
                 <author>N., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The actis and constitutiounis of the realme of Scotland : maid in Parliamentis haldin be the rycht excellent, hie and mychtie princeis kingis James the first, secund, thrid, feird, fyft, and in tyme of Marie now quene of Scottis, viseit, correctid, and extractit furth of the registers by the Lordis Depute be hir Maiestieis speciall commissioun thairto. Anno Do. 1566</title>
                 <author>Scotland</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lekpreuik, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, clxiij leaves, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="note">
   <pb facs="200"/>
   <p>THE person, who has caused these cancelled leaves of the Acts of the
Scotish Parliament to be reprinted, had always doubts about the proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility
of there being a new edition of those Acts printed by Lekprevick, in
so short a space of time as from the 12th of Oct. 1566 to the 28th of Nov.
of the same year, (which are the dates that the supposed different editions
bear); but unwilling to controvert an opinion that had obtained so general
belief, among those who were most likely to judge accurately on the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
he would not hazard his own opinion, till he should have an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
of collating and comparing these supposed different editions. This
he was enabled to do by the favour of Mr. George Chalmers, who is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed
of a very fine copy of what has hitherto been supposed to be the
first edition, and which he obligingly lent for the purpose of collation.—
When this collation took place, with what is called the second edition, it
was found they were one and the same edition, and differed in nothing but
the cancelled leaves here reprinted. The Acts principally concern the
religion of the country; why they were cancelled requires no explanation,
to any one acquainted with the history of those times, when the Catholic
power was so much on the decline, and the Protestant party had become
so prevalent.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>G. N.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>