<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>B., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101226_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04641</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1476</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101226</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gales of grace; or, the spirituall vvinde : wherein the mysterie of sanctification is opened and handled. By Thomas Barnes</title>
                 <author>Barnes, Thomas, minister of St. Margaret's, New Fish Street, London</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 249, that is 250, 6 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>❧ To the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ariners vpon the Sea (good Reader) haue neede of the Winde to driue their Shippes to the hauen; and men in this world haue need of the Spirit to drawe their Soules to heauen. Which spirit the most carnall Libertines and secure worldlings that are, imagine themselues to be endued withall, though they neuer saw the want of it, knew the worth of it, nor felt the worke of it in themselues: which thing when I considerd, I made choice of that <hi>Theame,</hi> which is the ground of this Treatise, to treate of; &amp; tooke occasion from thence to frame a Discourse of the Winde of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> that according to my modell I might giue a little light to the mysticall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb facs="6"/> of Sanctification. This discourse I fitted and framed for that particular Assembly where it hath pleased God to seate me (for how long I know not) for the exercise of my Ministery. And where I preached it, there I thought to haue buried it at the first: but when I considered the necessitie of the subiect handled, and the infirmity of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor (being too swift in my deliuery) I thought the things might be let fall by the hearers, without that fruite which they desired, without that good which I intended. Whereupon I was induced in my thoughts to offer it (what-euer it bee) to publique view. This motion at the first I strongly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted, in regarde so many worthie Treatises are extant vpon the <hi>Doctrine of Regeneration.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But when I called to minde that same charitable speech of diuine <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Trinit. ca. <hi>3</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>I would that in places infected with Heresie, all men would write that haue any faculty in writing, though it were but the same things in other words; to the end that all sorts of people, amongest
<pb facs="6"/> many Bookes might, light vpon some, and the enemy in all places might finde some to encounter him:</hi> This holy wish of that worthy Father, concurring with my desire of doing good, answered those mentall obiections which I met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in my thoughts, and qualified that indisposition which I had to send it to the Presse; and, like a strong Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, bade it venture abroade into the world. Being thus called forth, I present it to thy view, I proffer it to thine vse. If thy conscience beeing drowsie may any whit be awakened by it; If thy spirit beeing heauy may bee any whit accheered by it; if thy iudgement being erronious may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whit informed by it; if thy mind, being doubtfull, may be any whit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued by it; if thy desire to walke with God may be any whit sharpened by it, and thou directed to leaue the way of the flesh, and walke after the Spirit (which are the ends as the great Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of all hearts knoweth, I chiefly aime at in making it publique) giue the glory vnto God, who gaue the
<pb facs="7"/> first motion, &amp; last resolution to set it forth: and for my recompence, let me haue thy praiers to God, that I may ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the course of my ministry with ioy. If the inserting heere and there in the margine other Authors beside the Scriptures doth distaste thee that art a weake Christian; Reader, know that I haue done it to free my selfe from a calumnie wherewithall some haue charged me, that I should bee against the vse of Fathers: and withall, for thy further satisfaction, consider that I haue done more at the Presse then in the Pulpit, as mine ordinarie hearers can testifie, whose eares it is not my wont to amaze (being plaine country hearers) with <hi>Augustine, Gregorie, Barnard, Chrisostome,</hi> &amp;c. On the other side, if that because I am no more plentifull in quotation, doth displease thee that art a curious Reader, I would entreate thee to be satisfied with this that I had rather incurre the censure of a nice iudgement vndeseruedly, then haue mine heart smite mee, and my conscience tell me, that I seeke the
<pb facs="7"/> praise of man more then of God. And what cumfort could I haue, when men should esteeme me a well read Schol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler in the Fathers (which cannot be in respect of my yeeres) and yet indeed I should be beholding to an <hi>Index</hi> (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to my hand by the industry of another,) for such allegations. Well, whatsoeuer affection thou readest it withall, profit it is that I wish to thy soule. I haue diuided the whole into Chapters, the Chapters into Sections, that thou mayest reade all as well as some, and not weary thy selfe with too much at once, if tediousnesse shall seeme to oppresse thee: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed vnlesse thou readest all, thou mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est mistake me in some things. Thine the Treatise is, thine also my selfe am, in our common Sauiour; to whose grace I commend thee,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>As a desirer of thy best good,</hi> T. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>