<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ IOHN SHVTE PAINTER AND Architecte: vnto the Louing and freindly Raders.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101701_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12159</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22464</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101701</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ IOHN SHVTE PAINTER AND Architecte: vnto the Louing and freindly Raders.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first and chief groundes of architecture vsed in all the auncient and famous monymentes : with a farther &amp; more ample defense vppon the same, than hitherto hath been set out by any other. Published by Iohn Shute, paynter and archytecte</title>
                 <author>Shute, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, xviii, that is xvii leaves, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Art and architecture</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ IOHN SHVTE PAINTER AND Architecte: vnto the Louing and freindly R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aders.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongest al other thinges (gentel &amp; louing reader) wherwith y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> deuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of almightie God hath most liberally, and plentifully endewed man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: there is nothing eyther for the dignitie and worthines of the thynge selfe, or for the wonderfull estimation and price whiche in all times it hath bene in, more excellent, pretious, and comendable then learnyng knowledge and science, the which alone causeth mortall men to be most like immortall Goddes: and as it taketh out of their mindes that rude and vncomely admiration wherwith through ignoraunce the simple in most vaine trifles are wonderfullye occupied. Jo to the wise be monumentes and woorkes skilfully practised and carfullie left both commendable &amp; merueilous: yea and suche, as neither the iniuries of any stormes and tempest can cleane wast and consume, no nor (as it semeth) the enuie of man or spoyle of enemies deface &amp; ouerthrow, neither that which is grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiste of all, time it selfe can deface or cast out of mynde. And amongest all other studies there is none in my simple iudgement of this sorte that diserueth greater prayse, then that whiche is of the grekes named Architectonica, and of the latines Architectura (I thinke not altogither vnfite nor vnaptlie by me termed in Englishe, the arte and trade to rayse vp and make excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent edifices and buildinges) the whiche like as in all other ages before hath bene in meruelous accoumpte and estimation, as ful wel appereth by diuers learned Philosophors and famous prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that imbraced y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, as Plato, Aristotel, Plini, who were excellent therin as their workes will witnesse. Allexander Magnus. Iulius. Cesar, Vespasian, Adrian with many other auncient greckes and Romaines which laboured to aduaunce their name therby who lefte many argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of their vertue, hygh intentes and doinges by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same with many other famous, of which Plini, maketh mention. Vitruuius and Frontyne, of later dayes men prayse worthy very stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and painfull therin So in vs semeth it not only to craue the wonted cōmendation, but also to be most necessarie and profitable aswell by the condition of the time as necessitie of the thing it selfe. And surely suche is the amplitude and largnes (I may well say perfection) of this facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that without sum acquaintaunce with many other artes ye shall not enter into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> depe secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: for it hath a natural societie and as it were by a sertaine kinred &amp; affinitie is knit vnto all the Mathematicalles which sciences and knowledges are frendes and a maintayner of diuers rationall artes: so that without a meane aquaintance or vnderstanding in thē neyther payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, massons, Gold smythes, enbroderers, Caruers, Ioynars, Glassyers, Grauers, in all maner of metalles and diuers others moe can obtayne anye worthy praise at all Nowe all these being braunches of that forsayd foundatiō, stocke, or science shall bring forthe the frutes of it to their great profites, and Commoditie of the Realme, which cōtinuing and through lye practised in the same) by time shall increse riches, worshippe, and same. Considering with my selfe the many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold commodities and profites that should redownde to a great many louers of the same, and contrary wise what alosse and hinderaunce it hath bene to them that lacke the langwages &amp; learning who of necessitie hath remained in ignoraunce to theyr great losse and discomodity of the Realme. Notwithstanding I know well there hath bene a multitude and at this time be very many lerned men who hath (throughe trauaile receiued) the ful perfectiō of the prudent
<pb facs="3"/> lady Scientia, of whom so depely learned I craue pardon for my rude rashnes that I hauing but tasted a certaine swetenes of her excellencie and liberalitie, wherfore naturall loue hath drawne me to aduaunce her reputation and honour, according to my poore abilitie and good wil, the thinge nothing garnished as it ought to be but most briefly and playnelye with suche demonstrations that it might edifie them which of a long time haue desired and reached at it to attaine Also for the encoraging of those which ernestly studied and fauored it. I thought it therfore good to sette out and commit to writing in our natiue language, parte of those thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche (both by great labour and trauaile, at the first for my priuat commoditie I searched out and for my owne pleasure out of diuers aswell latin and Italian, as french and dowche wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) I haue diligenly gathered. As also passed many countries and regions to see, both in Rome amongest the antiquities and in the most notable places of Italie, where are most excellent buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, and intending to write of Architecture or buildinges: I thought it best neither with the lightest or least profitable parte therof to beginne, nor altogither after the moste slender sorte to handell that which I purposed to intreate vpon. I haue therfore taken my first ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce into the writing of this arte, at the fiue antique pillers or Columnes, cōmonly-named of the places and persones partely where and of whom they were inuented, and partely of their vertues &amp; properties of those that they wer likned vnto, which pillers names are these as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. Tuscana, Dorica, Ionica, Corinthia &amp;, Cōposita, The treatise of these pillers, as it hath in it most delectation and pleasure in the beawtie and comlines of the workmanship appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto them so though at the beginning, it be mingled with a littell asperitie and as it were bitternes (for the dificultie and hardnes wherwith as both principalles and also other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of any excellencye at the first are coustomed to be, it is somewhat Comberous) yet it is both so necessary and profitable, that neither without it any man may attaine to any estimable part of the reste of this science, and with it as by a klew of thred or plaine path way a man may most eassely pearse and lightely pasouer the most darke &amp; vnknowen corners of the whole processe therof. But to speake of the worethines of this parte of Architecture: it semeth almost altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther superfluous, wherfore taking these to suffice in the part to be sayde, I will now shew what trade and order I do followe in the declaration of the measures, proportions, and garnishmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of these before mencioned pillers. For so much therfore as in teaching of all artes thre thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are chiefly to be considered that is to say diligence in geuing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> preceptes, aptnes in chosying plaine and euidente examples, and last of all practise and experience of the teacher. I haue for the first parte taken for my author chieflye to be followed the noble and excellent writer Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truuius one of the most parfaictest of all the Antiques, and for that, neither any one man in what arte so euer it be is absolute, and that other singuler men of the Antiques and he in many poinctes do disagre and differ (which Sebastianus Serlius, a meruelous conning artificer in our time) in many places of his workes learnedly doth declare. I haue added vnto him vpon what soeuer in any thing semed nedfull the opinion and meaning of the sayde experte writer Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianus, here and there also wher I thought meete I haue ioyned the minde and iudgement of one Gulielmus Philander a notable man whiche about the yere of oure lorde. <hi>15.6.</hi> wrote vnto the frenche king Anotacions vpon Vitruuius, concerning this matter or suche like. Now for examples which are necessarily required to the opening of such darke matters, I haue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where through the whole procese of this present treatise after the preceptes to the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="4"/> of them sette both demonstrtion and figure, and as for practise and experience of these thinges whiche I teache, I assure the moste gentle reader and all other that shalbe readers fo this my littel worke that I haue put no title in any part therof cōcerning y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> proportiō &amp; simetry to vse the accustomed terme of the arte of the fornamed columbes, whiche I haue not aswell seene and measured in Italie, from whence they cam first vnto vs amongest the Antique woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes as read and studied in England in the Antentique writers, that I might with so muche more perfection write of them as both the reading of the thinge and seinge it in dede is more then onely bare reding of it. This small and simple treatise of myne I can not tell whither with like felicitie brought to his parfection as with no small laboure and studie for this time ended, I thought meete as the firste frutes of my poore attemptes &amp; indeuors to leue as a duetye and dette of me to be payde, and that well receiued of all men, I shall thinke my selfe most happye, and if not of all persones, yet at the least wise of suche as be honest estemers and accepters of other mennes diligence and studies. The which if it come to passe, both I shalbe glad of my laboures in these thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed and for the loue of my naturall Countrimen be further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more incouraged hereafter to attempte greater thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Thus almightie God preserue the in godly excercices to his pleasure for euer Amen.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>