<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, WILLIAM, LORD PAGET, BA∣RON OF BEAVDESERT, GRACE AND PEACE BE MVLTIPLIED.</title>
           <author>Benefield, Sebastian</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101615_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08402</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1872</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101615</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, WILLIAM, LORD PAGET, BA∣RON OF BEAVDESERT, GRACE AND PEACE BE MVLTIPLIED.</title>
                 <author>Benefield, Sebastian</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sinne against the Holy Ghost discouered : and other Christian doctrines deliuered: in twelue sermons vpon part of the tenth chapter of the epistle to the Hebrewes. By Sebastian Benefield</title>
                 <author>Benefield, Sebastian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 181, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, WILLIAM, LORD PAGET, BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RON OF BEAVDESERT, GRACE AND PEACE BE MVLTIPLIED.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ANY yeares haue expired, since these Sermons began first to haue their life in this Famous Vniversitie. They haue hitherto lyen in obscurity. Only, a few copies of some of them haue beene tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed, for the vse of a few. Now they all see the light. They were penned with intent, to worke honest &amp; good mindes in Gods people. If they shall so farre prevaile with the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader,</hi> they haue their happynesse. Their maine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect is, the greatest of Sinnes, <hi>the SINNE against the HOLY GHOST.</hi> I describe it to be, (not every sinne of <hi>presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or of <hi>desperation,</hi> or <hi>against knowledge and Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> but) <hi>such a kinde of presumptuous offence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the profession of the Christian faith is totally renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and that, of set purpose and resolved malice against the very Majestie of Almighty God himselfe, and his Christ, our ever blessed Saviour.</hi> A sinne absolutely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable: There remaineth no sacrifice for it. The more
<pb facs="3"/> neede is there, that every man be armed against it. For this purpose at this time is this poore mite cast into the <hi>Lords trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surie.</hi> It's the best I haue in readynesse. Such as it is, I dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it to your <hi>HONOVR,</hi> vnder whose protection it may lodge in safety, as vnder the covert of <hi>Minerva's</hi> shield. I may not seeke to <hi>any other</hi> to Patronize it. It is your <hi>Honours</hi> of due. The liberall maintenance, which it pleaseth your <hi>HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVR</hi> to extend to the <hi>Reader of Divinitie for the Ladie MARGARET</hi> for his further encouragement and support, challengeth <hi>MORE</hi> from me. Meane time, accept this, <hi>my good Lord,</hi> as a gratefull agnition of your so rare bounty. <hi>GOD Almighty,</hi> the great recompenser, who <hi>rendreth to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one according to their workes,</hi> keepe <hi>you,</hi> giue <hi>you</hi> life, make <hi>you</hi> blessed in this world, and when <hi>the resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the just</hi> shall be, giue <hi>HE</hi> vnto <hi>you</hi> that never-fading Crowne of glory.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my Study in CORPVS CHRIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TI COLLEGE in OXFORD,</hi>
         <date> March 25. 1615.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your <hi>HONOVRS</hi> in all duty and service, <hi>SEBASTIAN BENEFIELD.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>