<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the friendly Reader.</title>
           <author>Culverwell, Ezekiel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101677_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09393</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1969</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101677</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the friendly Reader.</title>
                 <author>Culverwell, Ezekiel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An approued treatise of hawkes and hawking : Diuided into three bookes. The first teacheth, how to make a short-winged hawke good, with good conditions. The second, how to reclaime a hawke from any ill condition. The third, teacheth cures for all knowne griefes and diseases. By Edmund Bert, Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Bert, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Moore (More), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 109, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the friendly Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riendly Reader, I did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer purpose to publish in common these my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, but to haue giuen them priuately to whom they are dedicated, and to whom I stand deuoted: but being discouered to some of my friends, and by them made knowne to many of the rest, there importunities and earnest perswasions haue made mee put it to the presse, whereby I shal be sensured of such as haue lest Iudgement, but let it answere for it selfe; I haue not set down any thing so erronious, but being well exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it will proue iudicious: and although this subiect hath already beene dealt withall, and well handled by a Gentleman of good experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whose good and probable discourse might be a meanes to hinder my proceeding herewith, yet a great many gentlemen to whom the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of my hawkes haue beene knowne to be such as that they could not be bettered, doe
<pb facs="4"/>
strongly inforce it, that my Skill, Art &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge must be in the same degree: In truth I haue not kept any hawke aboue three yeeres, but I haue put them off for much money, besides ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thanks, and much loue. I had for a Goshawke and a Tarsell a hundeed Marks, both solde to one man within sixteen moneths. I know there are many of good experience will ouerlooke this my booke, and some that are young professors, and some that would learne to professe, but whatsoeuer he be that vndertaketh this professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I will wish him an able body, a quicke spirit, and most of all, an earnest loue and delight thereunto; to such a man a hawke will quickly teach knowledge, but of him that wanteth wit shee will make a foole, and of a dull-spirit a true pack-horse: If these good properties shall be wanting in a man, he is hardly to be made a good Austringer, and it will be hard for him to make a good hawke. I would I were able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer plainely what I vnderstand, I will set downe as familiarly as I can, the best instructions I am able, but knowledge and vnderstanding, louing practitioner must be gotten by thy diligent and carefull obseruing thy hawke, in her sundry passions and sudden toyes, such vigelance, such diligence, and such carefulnesse will worke such an apprehension in thee, as in a little time thy knowledge and vnderstanding will bring forth such effect, as that thou wilt be able to preuent
<pb facs="5"/>
all her ill intendments. I cannot set downe what thy experience will teach thee; but I rest to giue thee fullersatisfaction, by conference, then I haue herein or can possibly publish: Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my house at <hi>Collier-Row,</hi> neere <hi>Rumford</hi>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thine to his power. EDMVND BERT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>