<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right honourable and his singular good Lorde, he Lord Darcey, W. W. wisheth a prosperous continuaunce in this lyfe to the glory of God, and a dayly preser∣uation in Gods feare to his endlesse ioye.</title>
           <author>W., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101821_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14611</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24922</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101821</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right honourable and his singular good Lorde, he Lord Darcey, W. W. wisheth a prosperous continuaunce in this lyfe to the glory of God, and a dayly preser∣uation in Gods feare to his endlesse ioye.</title>
                 <author>W., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true and iust recorde, of the information, examination and confession of all the witches, taken at S. Ofes in the countie of Essex : whereof some were executed, and other some entreated according to the determination of lawe. Wherein all men may see what a pestilent people witches are, and how vnworthy to lyue in a Christian Commonwealth. Written orderly, as the cases were tryed by euidence, by W. W</title>
                 <author>W. W.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>59 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the right honourable and his singular good Lorde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he Lord <hi>Darcey,</hi> W. <hi>W.</hi> wisheth a prosperous continuaunce in this lyfe to the glory of God, and a dayly preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in Gods feare to his endlesse ioye.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F THERE HATH BIN at any time (Right Honorable) any meanes vsed, to appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e the wrath of God, to ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aine his blessing, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>errif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e secreete offenders by open transgressors punishments, to withdraw ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest natures from the corruption of euil company, to diminish the great multitude of wicked people, to increase the small number of virtuous persons, and to reforme all the detestable abuses, which the peruerse witte and will of man doth dayly deuise, this doubtlesse is no lesse necessarye then the best, that Sorcerers, Wizzardes, or rather Dizzardes, Witches, Wisewomen (for so they will be named) are rygorously punished. Rygorously sayd I? Why it is too milde and gentle a tearme for such a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilesse generation: I should rather haue sayd most cruelly executed: for that no punishment can bee thought vpō, be it in neuer so high a degree of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt, which may be deemed sufficient for such a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelish
<pb facs="3"/>
&amp; dānable practise. And why? Because al the imaginatiōs, al the cōsultatiōs, al the conferences, al the experimentes, finally all the attemptes, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges and conclusions of Sorcerers, Witches, and the rest of that hellishe liuerie, are meere blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers against the person of the most high God; and draw so neere to the nature of idolatrie (for they worshippe Sathan, vnto whome they haue sworne allegiaunce) that they are by no meanes to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the suspition of that most accursed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, nay rather they are guiltie of apparaunte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postasie, which is more heynous (considering the circumstances of their ordinarie actions, then any trespasse against the seconde table, which ouglye sinnes of blasphemie, and grosse, or rather diuelish idolatrie cōcurring in no malefactor so roūdly, as in sorcerers, witches, Inchaūters &amp;. in whō the meete with a millian of enormities more, as it were in a centre; the magistrates of forren landes, noted so precisely, that weighing the qualitie of the cryme, they kept a due analogie and proportion of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, burning them with fire, whome the common lawe of Englande (with more measure of mercie then is to be wished) strangleth with a rope. An ordinary fellon, and a murtherer offending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the morrall lawe of iustice,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Bodinus in confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione futilis opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionis Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>; Lami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, lamia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum{que} Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficia as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truentis.</hi>
      </note> is throtled: a Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer, a Witch, (whome a learned Phisitian is not ashamed to auoche innocent, and the Iudges that
<pb facs="3"/>
denounce sentence of death against them no better than hangmen) defying the Lorde God to his face, and trampling the pretious blood of that immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late lambe Iesus Christ most despitfully vnder feete, is stiffled: the one dyeth on the gallowes, and so doth the other: wherein doubtlesse there is a great inequalitie of iustice, considering the inequalitie of the trespasse, which deserueth a death so much the more horrible, by how much the honour of God is eclipsed, and the glorye due to his inuiolable name most abhominably defaced, euen to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termost villanie that they can put in practise.</p>
   <p>This I speake (Right Honorable) vpon a late viewe of tryall, taken against certaine Witches in the countie of Essex; the orderly processe in whos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> examinations, together with other accidents, I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygently obseruing and considering their trecheries to be notable: vndertooke briefly to kni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vp in a fewe leaues of paper, their manifolde abuses: and obtaining the meanes to haue them published in print, for that a number of memorable matters are here touched, to present the same vnto your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, of whose gentle acceptation though I dooe not doubt, yet will I not be ouer bolde thereupon to presume: but rather refer the same to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours iudgement and patronage, by way of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyation, that going abrode vnder couerte of your honourable name, the discourse maye seeme the
<pb facs="4"/>
more credible, your lordship knowing the grounds of this whole booke to be true and iustifiable, and therefore the further off from feare of impugning. But supposing I haue beene too tedious, and spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to trouble your Lordship with multitude of words, I buyld vpō hope, &amp; so put forth my booke, praying the Lord here to blesse your Honour, and all about you with the increase of his grace in this life, and with the presence of his diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in the lyfe to come. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund W. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>