<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the courteous Readers.</title>
           <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101486_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08875</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19157</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101486</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the courteous Readers.</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Palmerin D'Oliua : The mirrour of nobilitie, mappe of honor, anotamie of rare fortunes, heroycall president of Loue: VVonder for chiualrie, and most accomplished knight in all perfections. Presenting to noble mindes, theyr courtlie desires, to gentles, theyr choise expectations, and to the inferiour sorte, howe to imitate theyr vertues: handled vvith modestie to shun offence, yet all delightfull, for recreation. Written in the Spanish, Italian and French; and from them turned into English by A.M, one of the messengers of her Maiesties chamber</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 176 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the courteous Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I finished my seconde
parte of <hi>Palmerin</hi> of <hi>England,</hi>
I promised this worke of <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merin
D'Oliua,</hi> because it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended
so especially on the
other: to discharge that debt,
for promise is no lesse accoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted,
with the new yeere I send
him abroad, a freendly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion
for the long euenings, and a fit recreation for
other vacant times.</p>
   <p>But because some (perhaps) will make exceptions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
me, that being but one Booke in other langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
I now deuide it twaine: my aunswer is, that to
glut men with delight, may make them surfeit, and so
in expecting thanks for my paynes, I should remaine
condemned by generall misliking. Beside, a Booke
growing too bigge in quantitie, is profitable neither
to the minde nor the pursse: for that men are now so
wise, and the world so hard, as they looue not to buie
pleasure at vnreasonable price. And yet the first parte
will entice them to haue the second, when (it may bee
alleaged) the cost is as great, as though it had come al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together:
yet I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>am of the minde, that a man grutcheth
not so much at a little mony, payd at seuerall times, as
he doth at once, for this aduauntage he hath, in meane
time he may imploy halfe his mony on more needful
occasions, and raise some benefit toward buying the
<pb facs="5"/>
second parte. Againe, the other part will be new at the
comming forth, where now it wold be stale: for such
are affectiōs now a daies, that a booke a sennight olde,
is scant worth the reading. Thus no iniurie is offered
by deuiding my Booke▪ but profitte both to you and
me: yours I haue rehearsed, and mine is, that a little
pause dooth well in so long a labour, beside, this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage
would I take, that if my first parte deserued
no liking▪ you should neuer be offended by me with
the second.</p>
   <p>Yet heerein I am encouraged▪ that what hath past
with so great applause in diuers languages, can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
merite to be despised in England, being matter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
of delight, and no way offensiue: for noble
and Gentle mindes, are farre from iniuri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g the Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
that hath so highly pleased Emperours, Kinges &amp;
mightie potentates, if then the inferiour sorte mislike,
it is because they are not capable of so especiall deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinges.</p>
   <p>And yet <hi>I</hi> am perswaded, that both one and other
will freendly entertaine <hi>Palmerin D'Oliua,</hi> because his
History i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> so plentifully stored with choyse conceit,
varietie of matter and exquisit conueyaunce: as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
can be reprooued but my simple translation, yet
that I hope will be pardoned too, in that to translate,
allowes little occasion of fine pen worke.</p>
   <p>The second parte goes forward on the Printers presse,
and I hope shalbe with you sooner then you expect:
In the meane while let this haue fauourable accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce,
and that wilbe a spurre to hasten the other.</p>
   <signed>Yours to his vttermost.
<hi>A. Munday.</hi>
   </signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>