<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND VERY VERTVOVS LADY, the Lady FRANCIS, Countesse of Warwick, Dowager, the increase of all sauing Graces, and the fruition of that eternall blisse with the Saints in glory, is hear∣tily wished.</title>
           <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101697_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68568</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1962</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101697</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND VERY VERTVOVS LADY, the Lady FRANCIS, Countesse of Warwick, Dowager, the increase of all sauing Graces, and the fruition of that eternall blisse with the Saints in glory, is hear∣tily wished.</title>
                 <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ruths recompence: or a commentarie vpon the booke of Ruth : wherein is shewed her happy calling out of her owne country and people, into the fellowship and society of the Lords inheritance: her vertuous life and holy carriage amongst them: and then, her reward in Gods mercy, being by an honourable marriage made a mother in Israel: deliuered in seuerall sermons, the briefe summe whereof is now published for the benefit of the Church of God. By Richard Bernard</title>
                 <author>Bernard, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 479, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND VERY VERTVOVS LADY, the Lady FRANCIS, Countesse of <hi>Warwick, Dowager,</hi> the increase of all sauing Graces, and the fruition of that eternall blisse with the Saints in glory, is hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wished.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable Lady,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough a Woman was the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all mans miserie; yet of a Woman came saluation, to bring vs out of that estate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Grace and Glory, and for womens comfort, God of his mercy hath beene pleased to make their Sexe renowned in many examples. To some he hath giuen <hi>supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall knowledge,</hi> by enduing them with the Spirit of Prophecie, as <hi>Miriam, Deborah, Huldah</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah.</hi> Vpon other some he hath bestow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d <hi>singular wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> as vpon the woman of <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ekoah,</hi> and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w se
<pb facs="3"/> woman of <hi>Abel,</hi> in <hi>Bethmaacah.</hi> Rare was the <hi>faith</hi> of many, as the faith of <hi>Sarah,</hi> of <hi>Rahab,</hi> of the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> and of the <hi>Canaanitish</hi> woman; who haue put on better resolutions, and greater <hi>cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> for the Church in the time of perill, then some men haue done. Did not <hi>Deborah</hi> encourage <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rak</hi> to the warres, aduenturing her selfe with him, when otherwise he without her was afraid to go? Did not <hi>Iael,</hi> the wife of <hi>Heber,</hi> kill the great Captaine and Generall <hi>Sisera?</hi> And who more resolued to ico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard her life for Gods people, then beautifull <hi>Ester,</hi> with her <hi>If I perish, I perish?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Haue there not been of them famous in many other things? For <hi>attention</hi> to the Word, as the <hi>Virgin Marie</hi> and <hi>Lydia.</hi> For going farre <hi>for knowledge,</hi> as the <hi>Queene of Sheba</hi> to heare the wisedome of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi> For <hi>workes of charitie,</hi> as <hi>Dorcas.</hi> For <hi>workes of piety,</hi> helping forward the building of the<note place="margin">Exod. 35. 21, 22, 29.</note> Tabernacle, as were many women. For <hi>feruency</hi> in prayer, as <hi>Hannah.</hi> For daily <hi>deuotion</hi> in fasting and prayer, as <hi>Anna.</hi> For <hi>entertainement</hi> of Gods Messengers, as the <hi>Shunamite,</hi> as <hi>Lydia,</hi> and one <hi>Mary.</hi> For the <hi>feare</hi> of God, as the <hi>Mid wiues</hi> of<note place="margin">Rom. 16. 6.</note> Egypt. For <hi>courtesie</hi> to a meere stranger, as <hi>Rebec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</hi> For <hi>humilitie</hi> and <hi>patience,</hi> as old <hi>Naomi.</hi> Who can out-strip <hi>Ruth</hi> in loue? Are there not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded not meane ones onely, but also honourable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages for Religion and Grace? as wee may reade in the Acts 17. 4, 12. Will a <hi>Dionysius</hi> become a belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in an Vniuersitie, from among the Athenians? You shall finde a <hi>Damaris</hi> to second him.</p>
   <p>In what haue men been renowned, wherein some
<pb facs="3"/> women (according, yea, and beyond the nature of their Sex) haue not been remarkable? in Wisedome, Faith, Charitie, loue of the Word, loue to Gods Messengers, feruent affection, and desire of heauenly things? If men haue suffered imprisonment, cruell persecution, and Bands for Christ, were women behind? No verily, Acts 8. 3. &amp; 9. 2.</p>
   <p>Nay, haue they not in somewhat excelled men sometimes? Who entertained Christ so much, and so often as <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary?</hi> Who are noted to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to Christs necessities, but women? Luk. 8. 3. Who (sauing <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apostle) followed Christ to his Crosse, lamenting and weeping, but women? Who of<note place="margin">Luke 24. 24.</note> all the ordinary followers of Christ obserued where Christ was buried, but women? Who first went to his<note place="margin">Mark. 16. 1, 2.</note> Sepulcher with sweet spices to anoint Christs body, but women? We may reade of a Congregation of women,<note place="margin">Acts 16. 13.</note> to whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> preached, being gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the accustomed place of prayer, as more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as it may seeme at that time, then men.</p>
   <p>It would be tedious to repeate by name all the nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble women in the holy Scriptures, and their excellent graces; yet can I not let passe <hi>Priscilla</hi> her knowledge with her husband <hi>A quila</hi> in the ministerie of the Gospell, able to teach an eloquent <hi>A pollos;</hi> nor <hi>Loys</hi> and <hi>Eunice,</hi> Trayners vp of the famous Euangelist <hi>Timothie</hi> in the holy Scriptures; nor <hi>Persis,</hi> which<note place="margin">Phil. 4. 3.</note> laboured much in the Lord, as many other women did. Not to stand vpon more instances, one thing for their more worthy praises, is to be obserued, and not to bee forgotten; I haue read of men well esteemed of to haue been Apostates, as <hi>Demas, Alexander, Phyletus,</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/> and others; but of neuer a woman by name, once recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned among the Saints in all the new Testament; this is singular glorie.</p>
   <p>But the Lord hath not thought it enough to honor women thus, by endowing them with excellent gifts, and by their praise-worthy works, but also hee hath graced them otherwise. To whom did Christ first ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest himself after his resurrection, but vnto women? Of what act did euer Christ so speake, to make it perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually famous, as that of the woman, that powred vpon<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 7, 17.</note> him an Alabaster box of oyntment, promising that wheresoeuer the Gospell should bee preached in the whole world, there should her worke bee remembred? Hath not also the Lord directed his Penmen, and by name his beloued Apostle, to write an Epistle vnto an <hi>Elect Lady?</hi> And are there not whole books of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture dedicated to their names, as this of <hi>Ruth,</hi> and the other of <hi>Ester,</hi> for an eternall remembrance of them?</p>
   <p>I hope (Right Honourable Lady) therefore, that I may bee bold to present your Honour with this my <hi>Commentary vpon Ruth,</hi> which you may challenge of right before all others, for your bountifull and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall contribution towards my maintenance in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie of Cambridge, by the which I am now that I am; and for which, as also for your Honours euer-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing fauours to mee and mine, I remaine euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stingly a debtor.</p>
   <p>Accept therefore, I humbly beseech your Honour, this my best testimonie of all dutifull seruices, and of the acknowledgement of my most thankfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the same. And my hearty and daily prayer is, that the Lord would blesse your Honor, that as both
<pb facs="4"/> you haue intended, and also begun good works, so you may goe on with encrease therein to the end; it beeing the greatest honour before God and men, to bee great and rich in good works, for which you shall haue, for the present, many peoples prayers; for the time to come, of mindfull posterities, also great praises; and with all in heauen (which is the best of all) reward with God; who euer preserue your Honour in all happy peace and prosperitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours euer bounden to be commanded, Richard Bernard.</signed>
      <dateline>Batcombe, <date>March 22.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>