<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the louing Reader grace and health from the Lord.</title>
           <author>Thayre, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101271_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13646</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23929</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101271</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the louing Reader grace and health from the Lord.</title>
                 <author>Thayre, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the pestilence : vvherein is shewed all the causes thereof, with most assured preseruatiues against all infection: and lastly is taught the true and perfect cure of the pestilence, by most excellent and approued medicines. Composed by Thomas Thayre chirurgian, for the benefite of his countrie, but chiefly for the honorable city of London</title>
                 <author>Thayre, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, Emma</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 65, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the louing Reader grace <hi>and health from the Lord.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Alling vnto mind (curteous rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) the saying of TVLLY, <hi>Non nobis solùm nati sumus, &amp;c.</hi> we are not born vnto our selues alone, but we owe a dutie and seruice vnto our countrey, our parents, &amp; our friends, and considering with my self vnto my griefe, the sicknesse, the which it hath pleased God to visit vs withall, is greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased, dispersing it selfe into manie places of this citie to the griefe of manie: I hauing duly considered thereof, thought it my dutie to vse the small talent that the Lord hath lent me vnto his glory, and the good of my brethren: which moued mee to write this Treatise shewing the causes of the pestilence: the meanes to preserue vs from the infection of this contagious sicknesse: and the way and methode to cure such as shall be infected therewith, vsing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie in time, I meane in the beginning of the sicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, before nature be ouercome, obseruing the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this booke. And for as much as this is Gods visitation for our iniquitie, wee must therefore first fly vnto him with contrite hearts, fixing our whole trust in his mercie: And then wee must with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and thankfulnes of heart, vse the good meanes
<pb facs="4"/>
that the Lord hath ordained for our health. For to neglect the meanes, is to contemne Gods gifts; and we make our selues guiltie of our owne death, and before God we are no better then murtherers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we haue despised the meanes of our helpe that he hath ordained for vs. But I trust there are none so wilfull and obstinate in this citie. This Treatise (gentle Reader) I haue penned, and present vnto thee, plaine and simple, barren of eloquence and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led phrase to delight thee: yet herein is contained most excellent and approued remedies, and as effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall for the curing of this sicknesse, as are, or haue beene knowne. Vse them in Gods name, and doe not trust vnto light and trifling medicines, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the strength and daunger of this sicknesse: These haue power and vertue, through Gods grace, to expulse and speedily to cure this infectious sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: and for preseruing a person from infection I haue set downe manie preseruatiues. And for curing the sicknesse I haue set downe foure principall medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and three others of lesse strength, to bee vsed when the aforenamed cannot be had. All which you may haue readie or speedily made at euery good Apothecaries. Vse them I counsell thee in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this sicknesse, for delay breedeth daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: and death commonly followeth, and medicine comes too late when nature is ouercome by the sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. And for as much as I haue written this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise for the benefit of all men in generall, that thinke good to vse it, &amp; haue done it in loue &amp; good wil, so I hope the well disposed will censure it. And no god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vertuous minded Physition will be herewith offended, or enuy my endeuours, considering it is for the benefit and helpe of many in this or such like dangerous time, wherein many perish for want of counsel and helpe in their sicknesse, at the beginning
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>thereof. And where anie ouersight or defect hath passed in my booke, as I doubt not but that there are some, hauing so short time, and so little opportunity to ouerlooke it, I desire the learned Reader to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and amend the same: and in so doing I shall be vnto him beholding. And so now taking my leaue, I beseech God of his great mercy to blesse the meanes that we shall vse for our health, vnto the honour, glorie and praise of his holy name, and vnto our health &amp; comfort. Farewell luly the ninth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Non quaero quod mihi vtile est, sed multis.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in all friendly loue and good will,
Thomas Thayre.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>