<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE Dedicatorie.</title>
           <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101314_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07825</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18198</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101314</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE Dedicatorie.</title>
                 <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the nature of God</title>
                 <author>Morton, Thomas, of Berwick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Dexter, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jackson (Jacson), Ralph 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 239, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE Dedicatorie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, my dutie remembred vnto you, desiring of God your welfare as heartely &amp; more earnestly, then I either do, or euer did mine owne. I had once purposed not to make any dedication of this litle pamphlet, that so none should need to be troubled with it, saue only they (if there were any such) that wold trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues with it. But the perswasions of some friends wishing that this litle bodie going abroad, might haue some head to direct it, haue preuailed so far, that I began to thinke of some friend with whom I might make so bolde as to vse his name (at least vnderstoode the whiche may serue for once, vnlesse wee haue imitated that vnskilfull painter, who must needs set this epigramme ouer euery thing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he painted: <hi>This is such a thing)</hi> the forefront of this treatise, to giue to these fewe
<pb facs="4"/>
sheetes of paper, the name and title of a perfest booke, the which they doo so earnestly affect. Wherevpon while I did bethinke my selfe of the reasons and respects which vsually men follow in dedicating bookes, among the rest (for there are diuers besides) yet aboue the rest (for they are the chiefe) these three came to minde, the first is <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarium,</hi> the second <hi>vtile,</hi> and the third <hi>hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum.</hi> Necessitie maketh men (writing of matters not only greatly controuerted, but euen flatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted, yea perhappes spightfully oppugned) as is almost euery trueth by one or other) shrowde themselues vnder the authoritie &amp; countenance of some great personage, that so they may haue shelter against the stormes and tempests, which their malitious enemies raise against their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and the trueth which they do professe. But this seemed not needfull for this treatise, which beeing rather a Philosophical then a Theological discourse, of the nature of God in general, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, not only all Christians, but also the Iewes, yea the very Turkes and all other infidels doo agree, may safely trauel into any country without a safe-conduct, or arriue on any coast without a conuoy. The second motiue is <hi>vtile,</hi> a Planet that now adaies raigneth by his powerfull influence in the very wils of men, (the which God himselfe cannot compell) and is the Cynosura or North star, by whose aspect most men lay their plots &amp; courses.
<pb facs="4"/>
And surely men are not to bee blamed, if by this officious kinde of saluting and acknowledging the vertues of woorthie men (it beeing done without flatterie) they labor to procure vnto them deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued fame &amp; renowne, &amp; to purchase to thēselues some lawful fauor, as a recompence of their good affection. This may be done, yet it is more lawfull then commendable, for it is better to giue then to to take, and (in the opinion of some men) to want then to craue. The third respect, is the most honest and praise woorthie, for it hath an eye not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent safetie, or to future profit, but to benefites past and gone, and in a maner worne out of mind, the voluntarie acknowledging whereof, especially before so many witnesses, sheweth a good nature, and a most ingenuous minde. Here I did set down my staffe, as minding out of this companie to make my choise, yet was I not as yet come to my iourneyes end: for as wee all haue many benefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, to whom wee are much indebted, so it may bee doubted, which of them may by best right challenge this dutie to himselfe. Our best bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour is hee, from whom onely commeth euery good and perfect gift, who hath enriched vs both with temporall and with spirituall blessings, and therefore doth most woorthely deserue to bee honoured aboue all others, with the first and best of all the things we haue.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
And without question, the zeale and good affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of those men, who (euen in this our age) in thankfulnesse to God the giuer of all knowledge and wisedome, haue made him and no other, the Patrone of their bookes and labours, yea though they were not directly written of his nature, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth highly to bee praised: yet me thinkes as it is not lawfull to giue to man, the honors which are due and proper to God, so it soundeth some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what harsh (though in trueth it bee not euill, and to bee condemned as simply vnlawfull) to giue those honours to God, which are commonly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed on men: and therefore euen the godliest men haue thought it most meete to dedicate their bookes to men like to themselues, and themselues both bodie and soule to God. So then we must de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend to humane benefactours, of all which wee must acknowledge the publick Patrons &amp; fathers of our countrie, to bee as most beneficiall to vs (howsoeuer the enuie which men bear to the good one of another, maketh common benefites not to bee esteemed) so most worthie, to whom in the first place all honour, loue and dutie, should bee performed both by this, and by all other meanes whatsoeuer. Yet wee are not to stay here, for tho publicke persons be to be preferred, yet priuate duties must not bee neglected: the which thing the very heathen did see by the light of nature, and therefore assoone as they had ended their publicke
<pb facs="5"/>
seruices and sacrifices to the publicke Gods of their countries and cities, they did without faile look homewards &amp; carefully (thogh superstitious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly &amp; foolishly) honor with due rites and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies their <hi>deos penates,</hi> their houshold Gods. Neither did they herein think their publike gods to bee iniured or dishonoured: for being (though fondly) perswaded that they receiued much good euen from their priuate Gods, herevpon they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred as a most vndoubted trueth, which no man endued with common sence would deny, that whosoeuer was sufficient to bestowe benefites on men, the same was sufficient to receiue honor and thanks at the hands of men. And in very truth, he that would make a separation &amp; diuorce betwixt the bestowing of benefits, and the receiuing of thankes, hee should go about to take heate from the fire, light from the sunne, and all sence of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie out of the hearts, and from the societies of men. But howsoeuer this dutie of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse ought most religiously to bee performed, yet wee see that none is more prophanely neglected: especially towards those, to whome in respest of neare coniunction of nature, we owe double loue and dutie: but they what good soeuer they doo to vs, serue thanklesse Maisters, whereas wee knowe that Idolatrous and vniust <hi>Laban</hi> could say to <hi>Iacob,</hi> Though thou bee my near kinsman, yet it is no reason, that thou shouldst serue for
<pb facs="6"/>
nought, and be defrauded of the wages due vnto thee. And now at length to come to our purpose, I do most willingly confesse (as I would more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly haue done long ere this, if it had pleased you to accept that homage, which I thinke you could bee content still to spare) that if euer any man might of an other, then may you of me expect and require all thankefulnesse of minde, all thanksgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in word, and all actuall testification of it by this or by any other means, whatsoeuer is or may at any time lie in mee to performe. Your title is as good as is his (who hauing with great expence purchased the feesimple of a faire and fruitefull Orchard, and enioying it in quiet possession for many yeares togither, no man making any claime to it, or to any part or parcel of it, or once offering to set eyther foote or face into it: yea planting it with the best trees that could be had, and not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering them to growe wilde, and to bring foorth sower fruite, but pruning and lopping them (yet almost so as it is said of <hi>Dauid, 1.</hi> King. <hi>1. 6.)</hi> and grafting them with the best sciences that could be had eyther at home or in forrein coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys) to take and taste an apple of some tree in this his own Orchard. If you should say, the which I am perswaded you did neuer thinke, that this were a deare apple, and a sory recompence for so great cost and care: Indeed I must confesse, that you might haue bought ten thousand such bookes
<pb facs="6"/>
with lesse charges, yet we see this to be the course of the world, that when as men haue most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly both charged and toyled themselues in planting Orchards &amp; setting Gardens, yet if they do but taste of the fruite of the one, and smell of a flower of the other, they thinke that they haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for their mony, and are better apaid, then if they had had giuen thē a thousand cart-loads of any other (though farre better) eyther fruite or flowers. For all things are not to bee esteemed by profit, or to bee numbred by Arithmeticall, but rather to bee waighed by Geometricall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, which is the better: and truly I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies thought, and so it may be, that many others thinke, that you do make more account of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke good, (the which happely euen these small treatises may procure more or lesse) then of a great deale of your priuate profit: As I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten heard you say, that you thought it meete that the first borne should bee dedicated to the studie of Diuinitie and the seruice of God accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the equitie of <hi>Moses</hi> lawe made to that effect, the which ought stil to remaine in some sort, though it do not necessarely binde.</p>
   <p>And therefore instead of a better testimonie of a thanking, yet more thankfull minde, I am bolde to send vnto you, togither with a little treatise of <hi>repentance,</hi> for the which you wrote in your last letter, another of the same pitch and stature, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="7"/>
his younger brother, to accompanie him. It is needlesse I knowe, to vse many or any wordes, in commending them to you, <hi>Nepotesauis, quam filij patribus chariores esse solent:</hi> Admit them I pray you into your familie, as did olde <hi>Iacob, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> and <hi>Manasses,</hi> the sonnes of <hi>Ioseph,</hi> and let your name bee named vpon them. Yea, if you please, lay your hands vpon them, in perusing thē as your leisure will permit. Yet do not imitate him in crossing his hands, and in preferring the latter before the former, (for hee was by the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie spirit of prophecie, priuiledged to crosse his hands, and with all the lawe of God, yea which is more, because they are more the lawes of God, the lawes of nature, and of nations) for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is fitter for your purpose, and will bee more profitable for you, so much as the true practise of Christianitie, set downe in some sort in that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of <hi>repentāce,</hi> is to be preferred before naked speculation, to the which kinde I must needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse that this latter treatise doth more properly belong. I do heartely wish and earnestly desire of God, that as you haue been the means of existing to them, so they may returne vnto you in way of thankfulnesse, some spirituall good, the one for practise, which is the better part, and the other for knowledge, which is not to bee neglested. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I doubt, but that God wil in some measure heare my prayer, with whom nothing is more
<pb facs="7"/>
righteous and pleasing, then that euery one should reape the fruites of his labours, especially of their godly indeuours which do directly tend to the good of his Church: you haue sowen the seede, and therfore may wel take the crop into your barne, you haue both planted and grafted the tree, and why then should another plucke away the fruite? It would (perhappes) haue been more profitable, if according to the common course of the world, I had by this dutie worshipped the sunne, not <hi>occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem</hi> (for who regards the sun any longer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n they see the light and feele the heate of it) but <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientem,</hi> whose benefits are not in the past but in the future tense. And yet as it hath pleased God hitherto to make you the onely meanes (in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) of profit vnto me (I speake of priuate bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factours) euen from my cradle and first infancie to this present houre, yea so that you doo not yet faile or faint, (as you might well haue done since you began, without any blame) but that your last &amp; late benefits &amp; bountie do exceed the former: so if I were so minded as to vse mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>er <hi>vtile</hi> for my Pilot, and the directer of my ship and course, I know no cause why I might not hope to haue as good a Chapman of you, as of another. So then, both <hi>honestum</hi> and <hi>vtile</hi> haue giuen their voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to this choice, to the which if necessitie could be brought to giue his assent, then it were done <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimi consensu,</hi> without any gain saying: and
<pb facs="8"/>
surely in my minde he is not hard to be intreated. <hi>Pompey</hi> surnamed the great, for his great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests and triumphs, (although hee might more truly be so called for the greatnesse of his minde and vertues) being sent by the Senate into one of their Prouinces, would needs take shippe and sea in a great tempest, saying: It is needfull that I should go, because it is needfull that I should dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge my dutie, but not that I should liue: and so wee are to account it more needfull to auoyde the foule crime of ingratitude, then to haue eyther our writings, or persons safely protected. I may not though I would, trouble you any further: it remaineth onely that I desire God to returne se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen fold into your bosome, as I doubt not but that hee will doo, eyther in this or in a better life) all that good which you haue done vnto me: and so leauing you in the most sure protection of God, in whom I am perswaded that you trust, I take my leaue till further occasion bee offered, eyther of writing or of comming vnto you.</p>
   <closer>The Lord bee with you.
<dateline>
         <hi>London</hi>
         <date>this 7. of February. 99.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="8"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>