<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ A short admonition vn∣to the gentle and courteous Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Stockwood, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101800_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00472</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10607</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101800</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ A short admonition vn∣to the gentle and courteous Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Stockwood, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The duetie of a faithfull and wise magistrate, in preseruing and deliuering of the eommon [sic] wealth from infection, in the time of the plague or pestilence : two bookes. Written in Latine by Iohn Ewich, ordinary phisition of the woorthie common wealth of Breame, and newlie turned into English by Iohn Stockwood schoolemaister of Tunbridge</title>
                 <author>Ewich, Johann von</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>19, 116, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>❧ A short admonition vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the gentle and courteous Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His small treatise (right gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and courteous Reader) comming vnto my handes at suche time as God beganne afresh to visite the Citie, and many other places of the land with the fearefull and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous sicknes of the Plague: after the diligent perusing &amp; viewing of the same, thinking it as well in respect of the matter, as in regarde of the present time and occasion, a profitable discourse for suche my godly countrie men as vnderstood not the Latin tongue: according as my leasure best serued from my schole charge, I haue occupied my selfe in turning the same into our Englishe and mother language, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che being communicated with diuers of my godly, worshipfull, and learned friendes, both Diuines, Gentlemen, and Phisitions, they haue thought it a work very well worthie the publishing and setting abroade, to the benefite and profite of all such pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as it shoulde seeme good vnto God to punishe with this kinde of visitation. I haue therfore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to let it passe the presse, and come vnder thy godly viewe, and diligent examination, giuing thee before to vnderstande, that in some places &amp; names of fishes whiche thou shalte meete withall in this discourse, I haue reteined still the Latin name with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Englishing of the same at al. This thyng I haue chosen to doe purposedly, that thou mightest
<pb facs="10"/>
resort vnto some learned Phisition, heerein to vse his skilfull aduice, rather then by my gessing at all aduentures at the Englishing of the same (which I coulde neither learne out of any Authour, nor come to vnderstand by conference with others, albeit ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry godly and learned Phisitions) to bring thee into an errour, hauing more regarde vnto thy right in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction heerein, then vnto mine owne estimation, iudging it better in this behalfe to bee counted ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, then by bold aduenturing, like blind bayard, to bee worthily deemed foole hardie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy louing brother in Christe, Iohn Stockwood.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>