<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>PETER BEVERLEY IN PRAISE of the translator.</title>
           <author>B., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101952_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03432</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1356.1</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101952</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>PETER BEVERLEY IN PRAISE of the translator.</title>
                 <author>B., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine tragicall discourses : writtten [sic] oute of Frenche and Latin, by Geffraie Fenton, no lesse profitable then pleasaunt, and of like necessitye to al degrees that take pleasure in antiquityes or forreine reapportes</title>
                 <author>Bandello, Matteo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 294, 296-306, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>PETER BEVERLEY IN PRAISE of the translator.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Yfe is the rule that blames the Idell mynde</l>
      <l>The ground as great that blaseth trauels gayne</l>
      <l>Eache tonge can tell a vvorld of vyces kynd</l>
      <l>And Scacred lynes appoints offences payne</l>
      <l>But Fenton shovves in svvete and sugred stile</l>
      <l>What pleasaunt bayte doth eache state beguile,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>What carelesse youth that sees the toylyng Ant</l>
      <l>But shames to vveare his goulden tyme in vayne</l>
      <l>VVhose tender lymmes in sommer tyme do haunt</l>
      <l>The frutfull felds to rest in Borias Rayne</l>
      <l>VVhen she doth sucke the svvete of, heruest toyle,</l>
      <l>And fynds in frost relefe in dryed soyle.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The slender store that sum do novv possesse</l>
      <l>VVhose idell boones did loth in youth the lode</l>
      <l>To those that lyue suffyseth to expresse</l>
      <l>The loytring child in age knovves no abode</l>
      <l>But as the shippe tost vvith the byllovv greate</l>
      <l>So he doth yelde him selfe to fortunes threte.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>VVhat pride deserues, vvhat is blacke hatreds hiere</l>
      <l>VVhat enuye, theft, vvhat is the mysers mede</l>
      <l>In fyne vvhat fovvle offence vvhat fact so dire</l>
      <l>But scripture shovves his rights if thou list rede</l>
      <l>VVherby each may both shunne the vilest sinne</l>
      <l>And learne such lyfe as lasting Ioye doth vvinne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But Fentons frame hath vvouen an other vvebbe</l>
      <l>His paynfull penn hath died a straunger hevve</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="10"/>
He tels vvhen vvitt is in his lovvest ebbe</l>
      <l>And vvarns the Shunne the bayne that coms by vievve</l>
      <l>VVhich so doth chaunge the sence of euery vvight</l>
      <l>That from a man to beast it tournes him quitt.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>As vvhen the mynd through vvant of reasons rayne</l>
      <l>Vnbridled yelds to fond affections force</l>
      <l>And feding still the hart vvith amours vayne</l>
      <l>Conuert each part vnto a sencles cors,</l>
      <l>VVherin he lyues so odde from right and lavve</l>
      <l>As mountayn beare, that prayes deuoyd of avve.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And subiect thus vnto svvete folyes lore</l>
      <l>If vvishe he vvinne, he shovves vvhat sovver svvete</l>
      <l>The pacient suckes, vvhat bytter blisse in store,</l>
      <l>He heapes, vvhen age vvith iudgment iust shall mete</l>
      <l>VVhen profe shall saye, of all vnhappyest vvight</l>
      <l>That reapest care in lyevv of hopte delight.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But if disdayne shall quyt him vvith dispyght</l>
      <l>And yeld him loth, for long desired grace</l>
      <l>Then stabbing glayue the desperat brest must smyte</l>
      <l>Or frantycke vvyse runne out a sauage race,</l>
      <l>Thus if of gladd or sad he happ the gayne</l>
      <l>Both haue this end, in loue nought is but vayne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>VVhich reckles race to bring in vvisdoms guyde,</l>
      <l>And for to raine vvith bytt of better skill</l>
      <l>My paynfull frend did this discours prouide</l>
      <l>As brake to breake affections lavvles vvill</l>
      <l>Gyue Fenton then but freuts of his desert</l>
      <l>And gather thou that best maye please thy hart.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>P. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>