<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentle Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101062_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11377</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1582</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101062</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentle Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doome warning all men to the iudgemente : wherein are contayned for the most parte all the straunge prodigies hapned in the worlde, with diuers secrete figures of reuelations tending to mannes stayed conuersion towardes God: in maner of a generall chronicle, gathered out of sundrie approued authors by St. Batman professor in diuinite</title>
                 <author>Lykosthenes, Konrad</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 132, 135-434, 436-439, pages 438, 436-437, 1 page, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue no doubt (friendly Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) but thou shalte finde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye thinges in these my prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, vvhiche vvill seeme not so absurde as altogither repugnāt to naturall reasons: Notvvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stāding, I vvarne thee that thou vse not mās reason in searching out Gods vvorkes, for the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous vvorkes of the Lord are greate and incomprehensible (as Iob the man of God confesseth) the vvhich the kingly Prophet Dauid recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, not onely in the ninth Psalme, that euerye vvhere he vvil set out, but also in the 105. Psalme dothe exhorte al the godly to do the like, vvhere he sayeth: Mirabilium Dei mementote, quae fecit prodigia, &amp; iudicia oris eius, that is, Remember vvhat vvonders God hath vvrought vvhat straunge thynges hee hathe done, and the iudgementes of his mouth. And as all prodigies or strange tokens vvhich depend rather vpon mens opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons than vpon Gods becke, after the maner and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition of the Romaines, are not to be esteemed, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to be despised: so those true prodigies vvhiche are moste assured tokens of Gods vvrath and vengeance, &amp; vvhiche the falling out of the thing for so many hundred yeares hath declared, vvith a true and godly minde are
<pb facs="4"/> to be marked and considered. And lest in these my ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therings thou maiest finde lack of credit &amp; authoritie of the thing, I thoughte good to adde it vnto, out of al au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, frō vvhose vvatchful vvorks set forth long agone, I haue gathered mine: To vvhose painefull studie I haue putte nothing (as GOD and my safe conscience bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth me vvitnesse) sauing that vvhyche I my selfe haue seene in my time, or haue receiued of my special friends, men of good credite. It shal be thy part to take vvel, and in good vvorth my godly endeuor, vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I assure my self tēdeth very much to the furthering of Gods great glorie, and the saluation of mankinde.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>