<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>S., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101082_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05999</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1636</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101082</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>S., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentarie vpon the first and second chapters of Saint Paul to the Colossians : Wherein, the text is cleerely opened, observations thence perspicuously deducted, vses and applications succinctly and briefely inferred; sundry holy and spirituall meditations out of his more ample discourse extracted. Together with divers places of Scripture briefely explained. By Mr. Paul Bayne. B.D</title>
                 <author>Baynes, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 378, 2, 2, 315, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Mother of <hi>Nazianzene</hi> (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe relates it) was so beneficiall to the poor, that a sea of wealth was not sufficient for her. What was her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious diligence in relieving of outward ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities, was this religious Pastors in supplying the wants of such as are spiritually poore, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no time to be well imployed, which was not a testimoniall of his pious life, <hi>in word, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4, 13.</note>
      <hi>in charitie, in spirit, in faith, in purity:</hi> or of his wholesome doctrine, <hi>in reproving, corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</note>
      <hi>instructing in righteousnesse.</hi> Thus thundring in doctrine, and lightening in conversation, hee left no stone unmoved that might further the building of the new <hi>Ierusalem.</hi> For living in these last dayes, the very dregs of time, <hi>when iniquitie aboundeth, and</hi> GOD <hi>is provoked every day,</hi> so that fin cannot be more sinful, nor wickednesse more wicked; by his<note n="*" place="margin">Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cep a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empla trahunt. <hi>Sen.</hi>
      </note> exemplary deportment he fast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the naile, which was driven by judicious Instruction; in Precept and Practise A MAN OF GOD, <hi>a Beacon on an hill, a burning and a shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="5"/>Lampe.</hi> His method and matter were plaine and perspicuous; yet so as (if occasion served) hee had <hi>meate for strong men, as well as milke for babes: he became all unto all, to gaine some.</hi> Blessed Saint!—<hi>quae sparsa per omnes, In te multa fluunt:</hi>— what couldst thou more have done, than in lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing undone, to receive at thy Masters hands, an <hi>Euge bone serve, Well done good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full servant!</hi> His well-doing and well-being is an invitation unto us to doe, and to be the like: which whosoever desires, let him seriously sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey these ensuing Expositions of Scripture, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed with <hi>Laconicall</hi> brevity, yet including in them the immense treasures of divine Speculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I suppose there is none will maligne them that understand them. If there be any others; as it was once said unto <hi>Philip</hi> King of Macedon, passing unjust sentence, betweene sleeping and waking; I appeale, ô King, from thy selfe to thy selfe: So let them reade with judgement and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation; and then whatsoever fault was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the Author, will become their owne. In a word, whosoever thou art that carpest at these following Treatises, whatsoever in them thou deemest either frivolous or superfluous,—<hi>emendes illa, vel ede tua.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>