<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the righte Honourable, Sir Thomas Bromley Knight, one of the Queenes Maiesties moste honou∣rable priuie counsel, and Lord Chauncelour of Englande.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101062_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11377</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1582</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101062</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the righte Honourable, Sir Thomas Bromley Knight, one of the Queenes Maiesties moste honou∣rable priuie counsel, and Lord Chauncelour of Englande.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doome warning all men to the iudgemente : wherein are contayned for the most parte all the straunge prodigies hapned in the worlde, with diuers secrete figures of reuelations tending to mannes stayed conuersion towardes God: in maner of a generall chronicle, gathered out of sundrie approued authors by St. Batman professor in diuinite</title>
                 <author>Lykosthenes, Konrad</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 132, 135-434, 436-439, pages 438, 436-437, 1 page, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the righte Honourable, Sir Thomas Bromley Knight, one of the <hi>Queenes Maiesties moste</hi> honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable priuie counsel, and Lord Chauncelour of <hi>Englande.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas (righte Honourable) all thinges vnder Heauen, are filled with the presence of GOD by his diuine power and gratious gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that nothing can be hid from his heauenly or supercelestiall viewe: As saieth the holy Psalmist <hi>Dauid</hi> in his <hi>139.</hi> Psal. <hi>VVhether shal I go from thy spirit, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall I flie from thy presence? if I ascend into Heauen, thou art there, if I lye down in the graue or sincke into hell, thou arte there, lette me take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the vttermost parts of the Sea, yet thither shall thine hand leade mee, and thy right hand holde me, &amp;c.</hi> most manifest is it therefore (right Honorable) that whatsoeuer hath bene, is, or shalbe to proceede, either Celesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al or Terrestriall, can not be without the fore-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance and prouidēce of God, who sending these fore-warnings, as instrumentes to former ages,
<pb facs="3"/> doth by the like wonderful shewe of manifest ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance foretel no lesse dangers to happen amōg the generations of this last posteritie. And finding sundrie labours of the learned by a due considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of suche effecte, not vnprofitably followed, whereby their countries so fore-warned, haue thereby auoyded many dangers, I therfore (right Honourable) vpon sight and search of so manye prodigious birthes, Starres of vnaccustomed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, enuenomed aires, from the which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede pestilence, plague, war, hunger, frensie, ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie and heresie, haue no lesse occasion, than worthy Authours in former time, to make or set forth this <hi>Cronicle of the Doome, or warning to Gods Iudgemēt,</hi> therby to giue vnto my coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try the like occasion to beware of some more mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous plague to folow, than shapes of former view haue expressed, vnlesse some speedie amendment be found in time acceptable vnto God. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises considered, I desire that euerye one beware rashly to iudge of any thing cōtained in this Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle, vntil the discourse be aduisedly perused.</p>
   <p>And although I acknowledge my selfe a weake souldiour to accomplishe so greate a worke, yet by
<pb facs="3"/> the meanes of good armour haue beene the better able to auoide the violence of many enimies, as by this collection, translation, and interpretatiō, may be thorough reading perceiued: The enterprise, battel, and victorie hitherto hauing had good suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, requireth honorable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssistaunce, which if it please your honour fauourably to accept, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection is yours, the seruice mine, as becommeth loyall obedience to my Soueraigne, superiours, and equalles. Thus (right Honorable) I end, commē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your estate vnto the protection of the most blessed rewarder God almightie, to be youre fortification from al euil, in this world godly happinesse, and in the worlde to come end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse felicitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours at commaundment</hi> Stepban Batman, <hi>in Diuinitie professor.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>