<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the courteous Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101807_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00503</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10637</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101807</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the courteous Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Duell-ease : A worde with. valiant spiritts shewing the abuse of duells, that valour, refuseth challenges and priuate combates. sett foorth by G.F. a defendour of Christian valoure</title>
                 <author>G. F., defendour of Christian valoure</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Anne</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 79, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>To the courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, it was the authors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to have presented thee with a compleat receit for the cure of this bloudy fluxe, wherewith the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants of our age are too muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempered, but some intervenient occasions unhappily diverting the current of his endevours to another course, hee hath not beene able to comply with his earnest desires, yet having already prepared some few sheets for the presse, hee judged it not inconvenient to communicate them with thee, as an essay and pledge of what he intendeth to perfect hereafter: hoping they may prove as sometimely preparatives, to asswage and mitigate the sharpe and corrosive humours, wherewith many hearts are unnaturally tormented. And if he shall find the successe in this kinde to be in any reasonable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree correspondent to his desires and expectation. I make no question, but he will esteeme their ease not onely a sufficient recompense for his forepassed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, but also a forcible encouragement for their further cure, to accomplish that which ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth
<pb facs="10"/> unperfect. The fruits whereof thou mayest expect this next terme: till when and ever, I wish thou mayest enioy thy selfe in perfect peace and patience: which is no lesse my desire, than the Authors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>