<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A COMMONITORY TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101124_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07268</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17663</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101124</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A COMMONITORY TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of S. Elizabeth daughter of the King of Hungarie. Written in French by Peter Mathieu and translated into English by Sr T.H</title>
                 <author>Matthieu, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Antoine—Velpius, Hubert 1, widow of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Brussels</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 70 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>A COMMONITORY <hi>TO THE</hi> READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y intentions in exposinge to publique veiwe the life of this glorious saint, a knowne member of the Catholique church, is by facts to shewe the church, <hi>a posteriori,</hi> by the effects to shewe the cause; For surely god would not haue bene so so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous to reduce these wandringe sheepe to his sheepfold, as himselfe in holy writt by publique proclamation witnesseth. With an <hi>Oportet reducere &amp;c.</hi> If he could haue fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes out of it. Neither doe I thinke that any protestants, excepte either weake or mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb facs="5"/>
puritanes, will not finde matter of edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and I hope much spirituall profitt, if piously, not curiously they obserue this great Princes vertues. yet its not obscurely known to men who desire more vnitie of spiritts, especially in matter of Religion, that there are too many, who soe much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the breaches of the church, that they will haue noe Communion, euen with the wery saints begotten in her. These are they of whome <hi>Cassander</hi> sayth, that they soe hate the church, that they hate all good from her.</p>
   <p>I must confesse, I delight not much in the society of those souldiers, who would haue (though only) the vpper garment of our sauiour deuided amongst them, which <hi>Euthimius</hi> calls his cloake, but I abhorre from those, who will cutt his <hi>tunica in-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sutilis</hi> inner-coate, wich the <hi>Arabian</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretour calleth his shirte, or truet; which was in steede of a shirte beinge of wooll accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the aunciēt and mystically without seame, without schisme, and soe to be kept accordinge to the Prophett, and subiect only to a <hi>Miserunt sortem,</hi> in soe much that
<pb facs="5"/>
the outragious Iewes themselues durst not aduenture to cutt it; yet I knowe there are too many cloaked vnder the name of christians, who would rathermake more holes then stoppe one, euen in our sauiours inner coate; of whome our learned Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman <hi>master Selden</hi> in his <hi>Prolegome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na de successionibus hebraeorum; Sui dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat ingenij vi, sacras literas temere explicantes, ridiculis atque impijs pacem Christianam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uationibus perturbare solere passim videmus</hi> their factious witts are made the touch-stone of our faith: what many of them deny to the whole church, They arrogate to their owne priuate spiritts, which is, to haue power to declare all dubious, and more hidden texts of scripture, and out of them to frame newe canons of beliefe.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Vincentius Lyranensis Chap:</hi> 26. tells you of them, and how to knowe them. <hi>Audies etenim quosdam ipsorum dicere, verite, ô insipientes, &amp; miseri qui vulgo Catholici voci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamini, &amp; discite fidem veram, quam praeter nos nullus intelligit, quae multis ante saeculis la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uit, nuper verò reuelata &amp; ostensa est: sed discite furtim &amp; secretim, delectabit enim vos. Et item
<pb facs="6"/>
cum dediceritis latenter docete, ne mundus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat, nec ecclesia sciat: paucis namque concessa est tanti mysterij capere secretum.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>See there, how he prosecuteth it and when you haue perused him well, iudge if it touch not to the quicke those factious spiritts, that desire nothinge more then separation, then sedition in christ his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth: me thinkes in earnest, he hath them at euery tourninge, for their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelty; for their inuisibility, their singula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, their priuate spiritt, their clanculare conuenticles, their praeiudicate censures of all others, their refractary resistance of peace in Religion.</p>
   <p>Saint Hillarius <hi>de trin:</hi> layes open the ground of their <hi>vertigo. In deflexu motu aduersandi studium persistit vbi non voluntas rationi subijcitur, sed his quae studemus doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam coaptans.</hi> Truth and learninge must be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>squared accordinge, to their inordinate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and not their affections by truth; they wrest the scriptures and fathers to their contentious ends. <hi>Omnes tument, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes scientiam pollicentur</hi> saith Turtullian, by their ouer-weeninge conceite of themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,
<pb facs="6"/>
they swell and must breake out into botches, and infectious gangrenes to the preiudice of the wholl body of the church.</p>
   <p>Had there not bene those turbulent spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritts in our country, guilty of more will then witt, we might not in vaine haue hoped longe since, that most desired vnity in Religion.</p>
   <p>Had they reuerently proposed venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble antiquity, they would haue found all the fathers most scrupulous in giuing the least (I doe not say) cutt, but stretch to our Blessed sauiour his mystically wholl coate, which is his church according to all the fathers. Wittnes <hi>Tert: de praescriptionibus</hi> although afterwards he vnfortunately cutt it in peeces. <hi>Ireneus</hi> especially lib. 3. <hi>Epiphanius de haeresibus</hi> throughout all, saint Hierome against the <hi>Luciferans</hi> howe zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously against <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> fearing least any breach should be made by him, though indeed his flawes were not soe dangerous. as for Patronizing Origen too much, as <hi>saint Hierome</hi> notes, Apol: 2. and falsely attributing some ill opinions of <hi>Sixtus</hi> the
<pb facs="7"/>
Philosopher to saint <hi>Sixtus</hi> Pope and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir as saint <hi>Hierome notes ep. ad Ctesiphontem</hi> whereby saint <hi>Augustine</hi> was deceiued at the first, as appeares in his <hi>retractations li.</hi> 2. C. 46. and some other points. How feruent against <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> though I knowe the <hi>Magdeburgenses Cent</hi> 4. C. 8. would plead a not guilty for him, yea to haue bin too hard for saint <hi>Hierome:</hi> but the truth is, he was faulty in denying all honour to reliques as saint <hi>Hier:</hi> there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes him, and my Lord of <hi>VVinchester</hi> against <hi>Peron. Causabon</hi> against <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, super annum Domini</hi> 34. nu. 140. lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly in the name of all <hi>England,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a reuerence due to them, as saint <hi>Augustine</hi> relates of the miracles done by the earth of the holy land, which <hi>Hespe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> reuerenced worthily, as <hi>S. Augustine</hi> noteth. He was faulty also in denying the saintes in heauen to pray for vs, for this all learned protestant diuines allowe, as conformable to all antiquity. Howe care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full was saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> in this maine point, though once indeed he gaue a scratch to our Blessed sauiour his coate, yet he cutt
<pb facs="7"/>
it not, and as <hi>saint Augustine</hi> sayth, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united it againe with his owne blood. Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> in all places against all spiritts of diuision. Shall we heare a dismall sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of his li. 4. <hi>Contra donatistas</hi> Cap. 8. <hi>Constituamus aliquem castum, continentem, non auarum, non idolis seruientem, hospitalitatem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digentibus ministrantem, non cuiusquam inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, non contentiosum, patientem, quietum, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li aemulantem, nulli inuidentem, sobrium, fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, sed haereticum; nulli vtique dubium est, propter hoc solum quod haereticus est, regnum Dei non possessurum.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If he hath cutt our sauiour his wholl garment, he hath no shelter for nakednes, no defence against gods sentence of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death.</p>
   <p>And herevpon we see, with howe great care haue generall and Prouinciall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells presently bene conuocated, to cutt of all springing haeresies at their first bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. As of <hi>Arius</hi> the <hi>Nicen,</hi> in time of <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uester.</hi> Of <hi>Macedonius</hi> the first <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinopolitan,</hi> in time of <hi>Damasus.</hi> Of Nesto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius the <hi>Ephesine,</hi> in time of <hi>Celestinus.</hi> Of <hi>Eutyches</hi> the <hi>Calcedon,</hi> vnder <hi>Leo</hi> &amp;c. In
<pb facs="8"/>
like manner we might descend by al cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies. <hi>Oportet quidem haereses esse,</hi> saint Paule hath taught vs, there hath bene and will be flawes in the church, but a heauy VAE is adioyned to them that make them. My desire therefore is, where I see any brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches not to stretch them soe farre till I make them greater, least saint Paul his VAE should lay hold on me, rather, if I can sowe them vp againe, this I conceiue to be <hi>opus sanctorum.</hi> This hath bene the imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of antiquitie, you knowe <hi>Salomon</hi> adiudged the childe not to be hers, who vnnaturally would haue had it cutt in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that she might haue parte; and the holy ghost commends his wisedome. Howe much more will it argue the church, not to be his mother, who would haue her quartered? <hi>Vnum ouile</hi> saith christ. Our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour should be to keepe it one; So he left it. The woe lighteth heauily vpon those, who first broke it, and much heauier on those who delight in the breach. I find not our best Protestant diuines to deny many saintes to haue bin, euen in latter ages begotten and perfected in the church
<pb facs="8"/>
of Rome as of saint <hi>Thomas of Aquine,</hi> my lord of <hi>Chichester</hi> doubteth not to stile him saint, in his tracte of inuocation of saintes. So <hi>Selden de successionibus,</hi> saint <hi>Anselme</hi> so commonly stiled: <hi>S. Bernard, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium calculo,</hi> noe man so far callinge his owne iudgment in question, as to doubt of it. Soe doctour <hi>vvhite</hi> against <hi>vvhite</hi> dyed blacke; so my lord of <hi>Ely</hi> in his fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall sermon; my lord of <hi>VVinchester</hi> in his sermon of iustificacion frequently. <hi>Causab:</hi> in his <hi>exercitations.</hi> Whittaker de <hi>ecclesia.</hi> Saint <hi>Francis</hi> by very many, <hi>Pantalion in Cron:</hi> P. 95. saith he was a glorious saint. <hi>melancthon</hi> with many learned diuines <hi>in corpore doctrinae lypsiae. Saint Bonauenture</hi> ofen so intituled by that learned diuine, who put out <hi>Dieta salutis</hi> and <hi>Catena aurea</hi> taken out of this learned and pious saints greater volumes. Saint <hi>Brigitt</hi> by doctour <hi>Andrevves</hi> against <hi>Peron.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I could enlarge my selfe, but I haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de choyce of these more eminent diuines, and those whome our country hath reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced as Illustrious Prelats.</p>
   <p>I can not omitt one more <hi>Master Hac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clevvitt</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
in his booke of Nauigations ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth saint <hi>Xauerius</hi> borne in these times, in this Centurie, to be a very great saint, and discribes many particulers of his life.</p>
   <p>I must stoppe in a subiect soe obuious. I could wishe and so all good men, that there were more departinge christians, saints, then to vse the phrase of the Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees, we should haue <hi>more louers of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, vvho vvould pray much for the people, and</hi> for holy citty.</p>
   <p>That is the church of god; as Iudas found a <hi>Ieremy. Mac.</hi> 2.15.14. for noe doubt in heauen they assist vs, and by their holy prayers, these diuisions in Religion would be cured, and an vnity concluded.</p>
   <p>Thus far antiquity and, consent of holy fathers assure vs, as all learned Protestants agree, and in deed the <hi>creed</hi> declareth it, for there is, <hi>Communio sanctorum,</hi> a fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship betwixt the triumphant and militant church which, must needs be by spirituall graces conferred By god vpon vs, by their prayers. So saint <hi>Gregorie Nazian: oratione</hi> 18. learnedly explicateth and piously
<pb facs="9"/>
beleeueth. Nay saint <hi>Nazianzen</hi> doth not only acknowledge that the saints pray for the church in generall, but euen for his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler flocke, as there he saith of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased father. Which passage of his, I must needs say, pincheth those who would haue only a generall intercession.</p>
   <p>Neither is this all: Antiquity goeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, saint <hi>Ambros, To:</hi> 1. <hi>l. de viduis</hi> saith, <hi>Obsecrandi sunt qui nobis ad praesidium dati sunt, martyres obsecrandi quorum videmur nobis quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam corporis pignore Patrocinium vindicare, &amp;c.</hi> He saith more to the same purpose there. Neither did I euer read any learned man that doubted this booke to be his, except <hi>Master Perkins</hi> in his problemes, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reason, only because there is a booke fathered on him vpon the <hi>Romanes,</hi> wher in the first chapter he seemeth to teach the contrary. But indeed it is cleare that this booke is not his but one <hi>Hillarius</hi> a <hi>Luciferan</hi> hereticke. I haue read that saint <hi>Augustine</hi> citeth that booke by the name of one saint <hi>Hillarius</hi> how euer it seemes sure not to be his, and the other sure to be his.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>Saint Hierome</hi> in his funerall oration of <hi>saint Paula</hi> saith, <hi>vale Paula &amp; cultoris tui vltimam senectutem adiuua orationibus.</hi> what can this be called but inuocation, <hi>saint Augustine de ciuit:</hi> Li: 21. C: 10. <hi>Vos non martyribus templa sicut dijs, &amp; sacrificamus &amp; oramus sed vtrumque in ordine ad Deum,</hi> see how warily and Religiously this great saint speakes, he denieth vs to pray to saints as to gods, for so the gentills obiected against christians as is cleare in him and in saint <hi>Cyrill</hi> against <hi>Iulian</hi> li: 6. yet he gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth expresly that we pray to them in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to god, which passage or distinction of his, me thinkes hath ended all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersy betwixte vs.</p>
   <p>So that if any deny this I say as <hi>Causab:</hi> in his epistle to <hi>Bertius de Apostasia sanctorum, in hoc video nostros docere contraria antiquis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus:</hi> for surely this is against them, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore my lord of Chichester in the aforesaid tracte (a booke generally receiued in Englād) strongly sheweth, voluntary prayer to saints, not to be forbidden, and before him, Luther himselfe in his epistle to <hi>Georgius Spalatinus</hi> and <hi>master Bilne</hi> as <hi>fox</hi> noteth 462. and others.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="10"/>These and many more points of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, are now Ceased amongst the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and indeed, I thinke many more, or all would Cease, if only Learned men should examine them.</p>
   <p>But they must not be such who in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of antiquity, can publishe without blushinge a neglecte of the fathers, with <hi>Non ignoro aliter loqui Patres, as Kemnitius</hi> confidently doth. 1. P. <hi>examinus Trid.</hi> or the <hi>Non debetis credere patribus. as Pomecanus</hi> vpon <hi>Ionas.</hi> it is a gudgeon soone swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, but not easily disgested. For surely in the iudgement of the wise, it poysoneth the whole cause in hand; if we beleeue <hi>Vincentius Lyrinensis</hi> in his 40. and 41. CC. yet <hi>Caluin</hi> L. 3. C. 5. Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes them all, and C. 24. exclaimes against them for giuing pernicious doctrine of the vncertainty of election: and was not this <hi>Nestorius</hi> his arrogancy when he saw antiquity was against him, to bragge that all the doctours before him vnderstood not scripture? as appeares in the councell of <hi>Ephesus:</hi> and yet from him the french diuines haue Learned, not only to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect,
<pb facs="11"/>
but to brande their gray haires with the note of superstition; as you may see a whole tribe of them in <hi>Feuardentius</hi> in his <hi>Theomachia</hi> L. 11. <hi>de Purgatorio.</hi> These are not they <hi>per quos fiet salus in Israel.</hi> they are too hott spurred and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>prurientes auribus,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>setled in their tenents. But milde and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led spiritts may finde the truth, and by them we shall hope for a reconciliation, to which we see many of the Learned happily to incline.</p>
   <p>Againe to write the liues of saints, and so conueigh the memory of their great vertues to posterity, the holy scriptures did it in all the historicall partes, and <hi>Eccles.</hi> 24. aduiseth vs to it, <hi>Sapientiam ipsorum nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent populi, &amp; laudes eorum nuntiet ecclesia,</hi> and it was the practise of antiquity. Did not Saint <hi>Gregory Nissen</hi> write the life of <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Thaumaturgus? Athanasius</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> of Saint <hi>Anthony</hi> the great? <hi>Seuerus Sulpitius</hi> of Saint <hi>Martine?</hi> Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> of Saint <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nett?</hi> Saint <hi>Bonauenture</hi> that great and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout scholeman (as <hi>Gerson</hi> stileth him) of Saint <hi>Francis</hi> that stupēdious cōtēner of the world?</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>But peraduenture it may be obiected that we are not assured this Blessed Queene to be a Saint. To this I answere, without all question she was a wery holy woman, gaue great testimonies of vertue, of the loue of god and her neighbour. And in these two are consummated, both lawes and prophetts; all Christian perfection if we may beleeue our Blessed sauiour. Thus the histories witnes of her; and what is most of all, its the esteeme the whole church of god had of her.</p>
   <p>Which I therfore added, to preuent an obiection (which might be made) of a thiefe, who as it is recorded in Saint <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> his life, was, being dead, esteemed à Saint, wheras he was indeed a wicked man: and to that text of Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> (if it be Saint Augustines) <hi>multa corpora Sanctorum venerantur in terris, quorum animae cruciantur in inferno.</hi> Many bodies are reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced on earth, whose soules are tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in hell.</p>
   <p>But this is by my former clause aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly satisfied, for I beleene not that god will permitt the whole church, to erre in
<pb facs="12"/>
so graue a pointe as to take a diuell for a Saint; thoughe particuler churches and prouinces may be deceiued, as all diuines agree, neither did saint Augustine there intende any more, as <hi>Ambrosius Catharinus Couaruuias</hi> in his <hi>resolutions</hi> L. 1. C. 10. with Learned <hi>Corduba</hi> in his <hi>questionary,</hi> truly expound him: or els you may with <hi>Bellar:</hi> not improbably esteeme that he meaneth only those, whome the <hi>Donatists</hi> reuerenced as their Saints.</p>
   <p>And indeed what wonder if we should attribute soe much to the whole church in so graue and important a busines, since after others, Learned <hi>Cunaeus</hi> in his <hi>Rep: Iudaeorum</hi> L. 1. C. 12. obserues out of the <hi>Thalmudists</hi> that the Priestes in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> had infallible iudgment to decerne an Adulteresse from the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: and he addes the reason <hi>Sacrum quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam institutum non defuisse</hi> 70. <hi>senibus, postquam solemni actu impositae manus illis essent.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus he, grounded vpon gods promis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se in Pentateuch to the Synagogue; and can we doubt of the certainty of gods as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance to the church his spouse in decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="12"/>
false and adulterate sanctity from feigned iustice and innocency? is the spiritt of god lesse powerfull, or carefull to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect her in so maine a pointe, as to knowe his heauenly guestes, from his, and her abiured enemies? or is it lesse behouefull for her to haue that sacred instinct or tincture of the holy Ghoste, since christ his handes were imposed vpon her solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely on the Cross? especially in soe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious a case, as to knowe whether she should celebrate the memory of the dead with thankesgiuing, as antiquity did of martyrs, or with horrour as they did of Apostataes and the like? me thinkes the shadowe should not exceed the substance; hauinge larger promises of the directiue spiritt of god then they, <hi>Paraclitus docebit omnia.</hi> is it not a good Consequece, if all, then this? neither doe I thinke my L. of <hi>Couentry</hi> and <hi>Lichfeild</hi> wil find difficulty in this: especially <hi>Thesi.</hi> 2. Fol. 365. se. 3. in his grande Imposture. My Lord of <hi>VVinchester</hi> deceased, plainly held it against <hi>Peron</hi> in the end, and so doth my Lord of <hi>London</hi> against <hi>Foster.</hi> and sure I am, Saint
<pb facs="13"/>
      <hi>Augustine</hi> would haue presently subscribed to what the church soe generally should haue receiued.</p>
   <p>Thus you see my grownds (good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian reader), wherefore I haue perused and approued this history: my finall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue was that we may be incited to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, since it is an ornament for Princes Crownes.</p>
   <p>And this is indeed the cheifest honour we can giue to saints, as saint <hi>Nazian: Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione</hi> 18. speaking of Saint <hi>Cyprian.</hi> saith, the blessed Martir <hi>hoc dedit in mandatis</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by him that his honourers shall be his imitatours <hi>Chrys: ser.</hi> 1. <hi>de Martir: To.</hi> 3. hath to the same purpose. Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine ser.</hi> 47. <hi>de Sanctis, Solemnitates Martyrum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortationes Martyriorum.</hi> the memories and solemnities of saints, are the instructions of sinners; their liues, our examples. Farewell. Let vs follow Saint <hi>Paule</hi> his counsell, Pray for one another, to be inabled to followe these Princely steps, this heauenly Kings high way to eternall happines.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Friend.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>