<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WOR∣shipfull IOHN GARDNER, and Thomas Fawkener, Gentle∣MEN BAYLIVES OF THE TOWNE OF SHREWESBVRIE.</title>
           <author>Thornes, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101996_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13746</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24043</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101996</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WOR∣shipfull IOHN GARDNER, and Thomas Fawkener, Gentle∣MEN BAYLIVES OF THE TOWNE OF SHREWESBVRIE.</title>
                 <author>Thornes, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Encomium Salopiæ, or the description of the pleasant situation, commendable gouernement, and rarities, of the ancient and famous towne of Shrowesbury. By Edward Thornes of McIverley gent</title>
                 <author>Thornes, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Meighen, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull IOHN GARDNER, <hi>and Thomas Fawkener, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MEN</hi> BAYLIVES OF <hi>THE TOWNE OF</hi> SHREWESBVRIE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene an ancient custome, not onely with vs, but also with forraine Nations, that in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the new yeare, <gap reason="illegible: scratched out" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> gifts should passe &amp; bee bestowed by equals vnto their equals, Inferiors to their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, and sometimes by Superiors vnto their Inferiors, as signes and tokens of well wishing mindes, for increase of Loue and Amitie; which were commonly called new Yeares gifts, and were of diuers kindes agreeable to
<pb facs="3"/>
the abilitie and disposition of the Giuer: some, ornaments for the Bodie, as Ringes, Gloues, Jewls, and such like; some, of another kinde to recreate and refresh the mind, as Epigrams, or Pamphlets. Which cōmendable custome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing still in vse, least I should be taxed to be vngratefull to those vnto whome I owe obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or a bad obseruer of time in my selfe, I haue presumed to presēt vnto your Worships (on the behalfe of our renowned Ladie <hi>Dame Salopia</hi>) this small Pamphlet as a token of my great good wil: being most agreeable vnto my estate and disposition. Which if you wil deign to accept in good part as my poore mite, It will incourage me to giue you better satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction hereafter. Poore <hi>Bancis</hi> could not serue <hi>Iupiter</hi> in siluer plate, but in a woodden dish <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> since I cannot doe as I would, I hope you will accept of what I can. I know you haue gifts of greater value, but none bestowed with greater good will: and in gifts it is not the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but the minde that should bee respected. And yet least you should thinke that it wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth weight, I will adde this more vnto it: Which is my heartie prayer vnto the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie (that the gouernment now imposed vpon you may bee so discharged, as may tend
<pb facs="3"/>
principally to the glory of God, next to the good of the Common-wealth of this worthie Towne, and lastly to your owne credits and commendations in times present and ensuing. Many eyes looke vpon you, and you shall bee subiect to many censures: but not what is spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of you, but what shall bee done by you, will be beleeued. As you haue well begunne, God of his mercy assist you with his Holy Spirit, that you may so perseuer to the end. And so I end with my pen, but not with my loue to you; Bentstone this first of <hi>Ianuarie,</hi> 1615.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Your louing friend to, bee commanded,</salute>
      <signed>Edward Thornes.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>