<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLATOR TO the Reader.</title>
           <author>J., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101530_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15350</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20146</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101530</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLATOR TO the Reader.</title>
                 <author>J., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>De adiaphoris : Theological and scholastical positions, concerning the nature and vse of things indifferent. Where also is methodically and briefely handled, of ciuill and ecclesiasticall magistrates, of humane lawes, of Christian libertie, of scandall, and of the worship o God. A vowed worke, destinated (by the grace of God) to appease the dissentions of the Church of England. Written in Latine by M. Gabriel Powel, and translated into English by T.I</title>
                 <author>Powel, Gabriel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 191, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>HAuing been very desirous not long since, to be resolued in the truth of the Controuersies of our Church, and lighting vpon this excellent and learned Treatise of</hi> Things Indifferent; <hi>J receiued such satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereby, out of the very grounds and principles of Diuinitie, that I could not heare any difficultie obiected touching the things in controuersie, but presently I was able to resolue the same, out of those very groūds which here I had learned. VVherefore hauing receiued so great profit by this Booke: J thought it part of my dutie, to communicate the same vnto others, in a more familiar language, not doubting but many may receiue the like satisfaction thereby, as I haue done. And albeit in the very translating, it hath lost much of that elegancie, wherein it was originally penned by the Author: yet I haue endeuored to come as neere his meaning as possiblie I could. Thus much I thought good to signifie vnto thee.</hi> Adieu. From <hi>OXFORD</hi> this 28. of Nouember 1606.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in what he may, <hi>T. J.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>