<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
TO THE HONORABLE, RIGHT REVER ENDE AND HER MOST RESPECTED LADY THE LADY EVGENIA POVLTON▪ ABBESSE OF THE ENGLISH MONASTERY OF THE HOLY ORDER OF S. BENEDICT IN GANT.</title>
           <author>Gray, Alexia</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101606_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08266</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1860</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101606</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
TO THE HONORABLE, RIGHT REVER ENDE AND HER MOST RESPECTED LADY THE LADY EVGENIA POVLTON▪ ABBESSE OF THE ENGLISH MONASTERY OF THE HOLY ORDER OF S. BENEDICT IN GANT.</title>
                 <author>Gray, Alexia</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rule of the most blissed Father Saint Benedict patriarke of all munkes</title>
                 <author>Benedict, Saint, Abbot of Monte Cassino</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dooms, Jodocus (Joos)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Ghent</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 103, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
TO THE HONORABLE, RIGHT REVER ENDE AND HER MOST RESPECTED LADY THE LADY EVGENIA POVLTON▪ ABBESSE OF THE ENGLISH MONASTERY OF THE HOLY ORDER OF S. BENEDICT IN GANT.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Honorable, and Right Reuerende Madame</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>NEVER doe the newe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singe sunne spreede forth his beames, with out a newe comfort to the behoulders; neither doth the splendours yealded to so many dayes, yeares, and ages, any whitt deminish the accustomed solace ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the newe Spectatours. And can I doubt this glorious sunne,
<pb facs="3"/>
our Rule, a bright beame of diuine light, newely raised to shine in this place, by your lady shipps predicess<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ād your indeuour, bringe lesse them wonted ioy to the inioyers, ād though itt hath illustrated the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, for many dayes, yeares, ād ages, with so cleare beames of Illustrious sanctity, cannonizinge with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious triūph more thē <hi>3000</hi> sainctes▪ brought frō the obscurity of idolitry, to the light of faith, <hi>33</hi> nations adorned the Church with <hi>15000</hi> Bishopps <hi>7000</hi> Archbishops <hi>200<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> Cardinalls, and twentye foure Popes, most of which shined vnto the world, as brighte<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> starres hauinge taken ther lustre and light, as from the sunne, from this glorious Rule. Not to numbe<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
the innumerable florishinge mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steryes, the shininge and illustrious Doctours, and writters, the intyre and purest Virgines, fruites, which this holy rule, as a most comfortable sunne, hath produced, fostered, and brought vp to inlightē ād illustrait, both with word, writinges and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, of singuler sanctitye, the whole Occident all church, Can I (as Isay) yet douht, that the vigour ther of, is any whitt deminished, butt rather as an experienced and an eye wittnesse can I auere, newe comfort, ioy, ād solace, raysed in the mindes, and hares, of the newe Embracers, who vnder your lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipps gouerment, happely doe a newe inioy the splendour of that light, and most comfortably do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
<pb facs="4"/>
the fire of charity, which with herbeames, she doth inkindle in our hartes. Giue me therfore leaue, most Respected Madame, though after many ages, to lett this so holy a rule spreed her rayes a broade in our English tonge, vnder your ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippes protection, that as you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>still the loue of it in our hartes, so you would make itt obuious to our Eyes, and a monge the rest to hers, who desires to remaine as she this day is become.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladishipps. Professed and vowed child, ALEXIA GRAY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>