<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the worship∣full M. Mayor of Way∣mouth and Melcombe regis, in the County of Dorsett, and his brethren the Bayliffes and Aldermen of the same Towne, Thomas Martin wisheth en∣crease of grace, with the true feare of God.</title>
           <author>Bostocke, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101892_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06734</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17180</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101892</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the worship∣full M. Mayor of Way∣mouth and Melcombe regis, in the County of Dorsett, and his brethren the Bayliffes and Aldermen of the same Towne, Thomas Martin wisheth en∣crease of grace, with the true feare of God.</title>
                 <author>Bostocke, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A learned and a godly sermon, to be read of all men, but especially for all marryners, captaynes and passengers, which trauell the seas, preached by Iohn Madoxe, maister of arte, and fellow of All soules in Oxforde, at Waymouth and Melcombe regis, a porte in the countrie of Dorsett, the 3. day of October, in the yeere of our Lord. 1581</title>
                 <author>Madox, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>34 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full M. Mayor of Way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth and Melcombe regis, in the County of <hi>Dorsett,</hi> and his brethren the Bayliffes and Aldermen of the same Towne, <hi>Thomas Martin</hi> wisheth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of grace, with the true feare of God.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I considered with my self, (worshipful and in the Lord beloued) the manifolde and subtile practises, with the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant drifts, that the man of sinne &amp; his ministers, by the suggestiō of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan doo daily put in vre, to bring Gods word being a Lanterne vnto our steps, and a light vnto our feete, not only into contēpt &amp; disliking, but also vnto vtter ruine and decay, that he may raigne in the temple of mens harts as God alone: (I could not stay) but carefully endeuor my selfe▪ what way best I might dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently,
<pb facs="3"/>
as well to supporte and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proppe, as to promote and aduaunce the same. And for that of my selfe I am not so good a labourer in the Lordes Vineyarde, as I wish I were, yea rather a loyterer, as I wish I were not, for in truth, the good thing that I would doo I doo not, &amp; the contrary, that I would not, that doo I, yet not I, but sinne that beareth sway in me) I thought it good, to sette abroade, in the viewe of the world, to the constant comfort and ioy of the Godly, and to the griping greefe and sobbing sorrowe of the wicked, that short, sweete, and comfortable ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, which that godly, learned, and vertuous young man <hi>Iohn Madoxe,</hi> M. of Arte and fellow of all Soules in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde,</hi> in your hearing, preached heere in this Chapell of <hi>Melcombe</hi> the third of October in the yeere of our Lorde 1581. to all your great comforts. That as then in your hearts, being by the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God therevnto zealously moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, you dilligently heard him; so now
<pb facs="3"/>
the same beeing eftsoones offered vnto you to be perused, you may glorifye God in him. And that, as hee, nowe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing reaped the fruites of his faith, is made coheire with his and our Christ, in the kingdome of our good God: so his good studyes, in vertuous exercises not buryed in the pit of obliuion, may make him in fame, on earth to liue for aye. Which sermon, as by the author at my mocion, was first vvillingly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you pronounced, and at that time of you thankfully receiued, so now vnto you most gladly the same doo I dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate: and so much the rather, because you being Marchants, and therfore of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten trauailing the dangerous salt fome, may, (by taking it with you and recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the same) learne howe to passe in the acceptable feare of God, your idle times at sea, to the benefit of your own soules, and most of all to the glorye of God. So be it.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your freende in the Lord to commaunde. <hi>Thomas Martin.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>