<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Mighty, my gratious and renowned Soueraine, Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, France, and Ireland, defender of the fayth. &amp;c. Your Highnesse most humble subiect Ed. Webbe heartily prayeth for the continuance of your Maiesties health and prosperous raigne to the worldes end.</title>
           <author>Webbe, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101834_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14850</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25152</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101834</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Mighty, my gratious and renowned Soueraine, Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, France, and Ireland, defender of the fayth. &amp;c. Your Highnesse most humble subiect Ed. Webbe heartily prayeth for the continuance of your Maiesties health and prosperous raigne to the worldes end.</title>
                 <author>Webbe, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rare and most vvonderfull things vvhich Edvv. VVebbe an Englishman borne, hath seene and passed in his troublesome trauailes : in the cities of Ierusalem, Damasko, Bethlehem and Galely and in the landes of Iewrie, Egypt, Gracia, Russia, and Prester Iohn, vvherein is set forth his extreame slauery sustained many yeeres together in the gallies and warres of the great Turke, against the lands of Persia, Tartaria, Spaine, and Portugale</title>
                 <author>Webbe, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most Mighty, my gratious and renowned Soueraine, Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, France, and Ireland, defender of the fayth. &amp;c. Your Highnesse most humble subiect Ed. Webbe heartily prayeth for the continuance of your Maiesties health and prosperous raigne to the worldes end.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering (most gracious and dread Soueraigne) the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prouidence of Almightye GOD shewed towardes your Highnesse since the time of your moste happy and prosperous raigne, aswell in the preseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Maiesties person from the handes of your Highnesse enemies, as also in defending this smal Angle or Realme of England from the force of forraine foes, and the continuall blessinges of peace and plenty, with which euer since hee hath in bountifull sort maintayned it: I could not therefore but (according to my duety) render humble thankes to almightie God for the same, when to my great comfort, euen in the middest of my grieuous thraldome in Turkey, I heard it most truely reported by a Christian captiue, and your Highnesse clemency by him highly commended. The report of whose fame truely described, aswell in the administration of Iustice, and supporting
<pb facs="3"/>
of Christian religion, as also in relieuing and suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couring the poore distressed mēbers of this lande, gaue mee iust cause to pray heartely for my deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, and to long inwardly vntill I came to see your Highnesse (my dreade Soueraine) and this my natiue Countrey. And now hauing obtayned my long expected wish, I doe in all humblenesse prostrate my selfe and this plaine discourse of my trauels, to your most excellent Maiestie: wherein may bee seene that if in Turkey I would haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied my Christ, or in my trauaile would haue forsaken my Prince to haue serued for Spaine, thereby to haue become a Traytour to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty &amp; my natiue Countrey, I needed not to haue liued in want, but in great prosperity. But for as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as almightie God hath now set me fre from thraldome, and deliuered me from many daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and sent me into England, my desire is that I may be employed in such seruice and affaires, as may be pleasing to God, and found profitable to my Prince and Countrey. And thus trusting your Highnes will accept in good▪ worth this true dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course though rudelie penned I humbly take my leaue, praying for the prosperous health and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall raigne of your most excellent Maiesty.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Highnesse most humble subiect.</hi> Edward Webbe.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>