<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A Copie of a Letter, sent by the Emperor vnto the Pope</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101769_Ba1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00457</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10590</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101769</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A Copie of a Letter, sent by the Emperor vnto the Pope</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The castle of Christianitie : detecting the long erring estate, asvvell of the Romaine Church, as of the Byshop of Rome: together with the defence of the catholique faith: set forth, by Lewys Euans</title>
                 <author>Evans, Lewis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 72, 4 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="86"/>
   <head>¶ <hi>A Copie of a Letter, sent</hi> by the Emperor vnto the Pope</head>
   <opener>
      <signed>¶ Fredericke by the grace of God, the<note place="margin">Nauclerus.</note> Romaine Emperour, alwayes impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall,</signed>
      <salute>vnto Adrian bishop of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, sendeth greeting, willing him to stand vnto all those things, which Christ began to doe, and to teache.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He law of Iustice, doth restore vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mā, that vvhich is his ovvne, neyther doe vvee anye iniurie vnto our parentes, vnto vvhome vvithin this our Realme, vve doe exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite due honor, and from vvhō as our progenitors, vve haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb facs="87"/>
the dignity of our realm and crovvne. Is it founde that Siluester Byshop of Rome in the time of Constantine the Emperor, had any Kingly pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session, or authoritie? for tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovv the permission of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors godlye affection, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the church vvas graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, peace vvas restored, &amp; what Princelye thing soeuer, your popedome is knovvne to haue, the same you do hold through the liberalitie of Princes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vvhen vve vvrite vnto the Bishop of Rome, by good right and of olde, vve doe vvrite first our ovvne name, and that he so
<pb facs="87"/>
doe, as the rule of iustice is, vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto vs, vve graunt. Pervse the chronicles, and if you haue neglected the thing you reade, that vvhich vvee alledge, you shall finde it there. But of those vvhich belong vnto God by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, and doe holde anye Kingly thing of vs, vvhy maye not vve demaund homage, and othe due vnto a prince? seeing the appointer of vs, and of you, receyuing nothing of a man that is a king, but yeelding eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie good thing vnto al, payd for himselfe and for Peter, the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute due vnto Caesar, giuing therby vnto you example to do
<pb facs="88"/>
the like, and so he teacheth you saying: learne of mee, for I am meeke, and humble in heart. VVherefore let such eyther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store vnto vs our princelye pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessions, or if they adiudge these things profitable, let them pay vnto God that vvhich is Gods, and vnto Caesar that vvhich is his. Also vnto your Cardinals, the Churches be shut, the cities are not open, and that bicause vvee see them not to bee prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, but spoylers, not peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, but mony catchers, not the redressers of the vvorld, but the vnsatiable scrapers of gold. Yet vvhen vvee shall perceyue
<pb facs="88"/>
them to be such as the churche requireth, vvhen they proue to be peacemakers, vvhē they vvill giue light vnto their countrie, and vvhen they vvill assist the cause of the humble in equitie, then loe shall vvee ayde them vvith necessary stypendes, and safecōducts. But you haue not a little offended agaynst humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, vvhich ought to be the ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of your vertues &amp; meeknes, vvhen you set forth vnto secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar persons such questions as are very small furtherance vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. VVherefore, let your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhoode foresee, vvhiles you moue thinges vvhich vvee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudge
<pb facs="89"/>
vnvvorthy, least you bee an offence vnto those, vvho as vnto a latevvard shoure, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to yeelde their eares vnto your mouth. For vve can not, but aunsvvere the things vvee heare, vvhen vvee see the detes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table beast of Pryde, to haue crept, euen vnto the seate of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And in thus doing vve doe alvvaies vvel prouide for the peace of the Church. Fare you alvvays vvell.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>