<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to all Readers of this Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101441_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09539</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19819</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101441</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to all Readers of this Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A petite pallace of Pettie his pleasure : contaynyng many pretie hystories by him set foorth in comely colours, and most delightfully discoursed</title>
                 <author>Pettie, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Watkins, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 224 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Printer to all Readers of this Booke.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>HAuing sumtime in my custodie this Booke in written</hi> hande, which by meanes of a special freind of mine was cōmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto mee, I was by him eft soones ernestly sollicited to publish the same in printe. Who beeing sutch an one, whose request I would not willinglie denie, I fell to perus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nge the woorke, and perceyued at the first by the Auctours letter, that hee was not wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to haue it common, as thinkinge certaine poynts in it to bee to wanton to bee wrought by that wit which by this woorke appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to bee in hym: which, as I coniecture, mooued him to write to his freinde to keepe it priuate to his owne vse, as may appeare by his freindes Epistle, and his Letter goyng beefore. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse, to accomplish the desire of the one, and not to incurre the displeasure of the other, as also to pleasure you, the freindly Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hereof, I haue put the same in printe, vsing my discretion in omitting sutch matter as in the Aucthours iudgement might seeme offenciue, and yet I trust not leauing imperfection in the discourse, wherof if I haue not gelded to mutch, I thinke I haue deserued the lesse blame. And consideryng that in matters of pleasure, the Prynter may sooner offende in printyng to mutch, then in publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyng to litle: I haue applyed my selfe to the contrary, hopynge that how mutch the lesse I haue printed, reseruynge the discourse perfect, so mutch the lesse I shalbe blamed for the deede. As for the Gentleman that wrote this woorke, and his freinde that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured it to bee published: as they are vnknowen to mee both, so had I conference with neither, wherby the lesse I could vse their aduice in abridging any thinge, which may bee some cause of the disgracinge of that, which doubtlesse the Auctour had penned with great excellency, and eloquence. If herein, as I feare, I haue offended, I am willing, beeynge aduertysed therof, to bee refour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, crauinge pardon of him especyally, and of all other freindly Readers, for the ouersightes whatsoeuer herein committed: for whose pleasure and profite I haue left vndoone, and doone, what soeuer I haue doone in this behalfe. I haue also of my selfe added an argument to euery history, that the effect of the discourse may bee the more easily caryed away.</p>
   <closer>Fare yee hartely well.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>