<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ An Aduertisement to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101997_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13773</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24071</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101997</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ An Aduertisement to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Positions lately held by the L. Du Perron, Bishop of Eureux, against the sufficiency and perfection of the scriptures : maintaning the necessitie and authoritie of vnwritten traditions. Verie learnedly answered and confuted by D. Daniell Tillenus, Professor of Diuinitie in the Vniuersitie of Sedan. VVith a defence of the sufficiency and perfection of the holy scriptures by the same author. Faithfully translated</title>
                 <author>Tilenus, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snowdon (Snodham), Lionel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 48, 16, 132 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="36"/>
   <head>❧ An Aduertisement to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou shalt vnderstand (Christian Reader) that the Bishop wrote since a reply c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ncerning onely some of the first point<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> heerein touched, priuily passing it into the hands of some of his frien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s and fauorites, and some whom he laboured to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert: Wherein, though his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall intent was, secretly to disgrace both the sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and this defender of it, yet hath it turned wholy to his own disgrace, by occasioning this learned man largely to answere it, and so more fully to cleare the truth concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the points touched in his reply. VVhich aunswere of D. <hi>Tillenus,</hi> I haue heere also for thy benefit added: onely the Bishops reply I haue purposely omitted, partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the ground, or as much as is needfull for the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nding of the matter, is alreadie aboue at large set downe: and partly because (it being not meete to trouble thee with needlesse superfluities) each word and matter of any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or worth the answering, is in the answere euerie where <hi>verbatim</hi> (for the most part) expressed.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>