<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL SVCH AS VNFAI∣nedly hate (in the zeale of a Godly loue) all monumentes, and remnauntes of Idolatrie. The translator wisheth perseueraunce into thend, through Christ Iesus.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101361_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00284</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1040</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101361</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL SVCH AS VNFAI∣nedly hate (in the zeale of a Godly loue) all monumentes, and remnauntes of Idolatrie. The translator wisheth perseueraunce into thend, through Christ Iesus.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fortresse of fathers : ernestlie defending the puritie of religion, and ceremonies, by the trew expositio [n] of certaine places of Scripture: against such as wold bring in an abuse of idol stouff, and of thinges indifferent, and do appoinct th'aucthority of princes an prelates larger then the trueth is. Translated out of Latine into English for there sakes that vnderstand no Latine by I.B</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Erve, Egidius (Gillis) van der (Gellius Ctematius)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Emden</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>76 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO ALL SVCH AS VNFAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly hate (in the zeale of a Godly loue) all monumentes, and remnauntes of Idolatrie. The translator wisheth perseueraunce into thend, through Christ Iesus.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His hath allvvayes ben the practise and policie of the Fend, to trouble the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationes of Christe, (that haue rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ued some strēgth in Doctrine,) vvith the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions of Ceremonies, of thinges indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and Dominion: as a me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e vvherby he often doeth assuredly preuaile, vvhyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st that the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern only regardinge the direct Doctrine of faith, do lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel attend that these thinges in there vse, touch and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne often times, the first table, but aivvayes the second, and so in regard of the second, also the first. As in Corinth it did appere in Pauls time, and sithenc in diuers ages. By practisinge of vvhich deuise, he thincketh novv (onles God help vs) to ouerthrovve the vvorke of God begon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongest vs in England. Against vvhich daunger it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth all men, as in a commune al arme, to put forth him self, to serue But for as much, as it hath hether to ben re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, that this is but a particuler combate against the Mimsters of London: I haue here translated into our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish speache, the Iudgements of certaine fathers beynge on those Ministers side. To this intent, that both trueth of
<pb facs="4"/>Religion, Reuerene of these Fathers, orels shame, might preuent the enemie by causinge the lordinge. B. to ceasse, and retire there folly. And also may strenghthen such as stand, and restore those that ar fallen through there deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses: And to the fuller accomplishing her of I haue poincted ovvt, vvhere, and on vvhose side, those reuerend Fathers: Maister Bullinger, and Gualter, ar, and stand. Whose letters they haue iniustely abused, as hauing obtained them the plaine case and trueth, of the deformed estate of the Chirch of England, not opened truly to them. As er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hit belonge you shall deare Christians (I hope) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand by there vvritinges: if they ceasse not to abuse there first. Thus thristinge your health in Christ, I humbly eraue your prayers to God: that by his spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, he vvill guide me to knovve his vvill, &amp; to performe the same through Christ.</p>
   <p>The Lord Iesus kepe you, and blesse you all, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>