<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A demonstration of the trueth of that Dis∣cipline
which Christ hath prescribed in his worde for the
gouernment of his Church, in all times and places, vntill
the end of the world.</title>
           <author>Worthington, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101665_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68024</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10400</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101665</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A demonstration of the trueth of that Dis∣cipline
which Christ hath prescribed in his worde for the
gouernment of his Church, in all times and places, vntill
the end of the world.</title>
                 <author>Worthington, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A parte of a register : contayninge sundrie memorable matters, written by diuers godly and learned in our time, which stande for, and desire the reformation of our Church, in discipline and ceremonies, accordinge to the pure worde of God, and the lawe of our lande</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 546, 10, 86 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="1"/>
   <head>A demonstration of the trueth of that Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline
which Christ hath prescribed in his worde for the
gouernment of his Church, in all times and places, vntill
the end of the world.</head>
   <argument>
      <p>
         <hi>Wherein are gathered into a plain forme of reasoning, the prooft</hi>
thereof out of the Scriptures, the euidence of it by the light of reason
rightlie ruled, and the testimonies that haue been giuen thereunto, by
the course of the Church certaine hundreths of yeares after the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles
time: and the generall consent of the Churches rightly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
in these latter times: according as they are alleadged and
maintained, in those seuerall bookes that haue been written concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the same.</p>
   </argument>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>Math. 21. 38.</bibl>
      <q>The husbandmen said among themselues, this is the heire, come
let vs kill him, and let vs take his inheritance.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>Luke 19. 27.</bibl>
      <q>Those mine enemies vvhich vvould not that I should raigne ouer
them, bring hither, and flea them before me.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <head>To the supposed Gouernors of the Church
of England, the Archbishops, Lord Bishops, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons
and the rest of that order.</head>
   <p>MANY and most euident haue our declarations
been concerning the trueth of that gouernment,
which Christe hath prescribed in his worde for the
ruling of the Church, which we haue manifested vnto you,
both by our writings and speeches, as occasion hath been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered:
neuer hath any one of you taken in hande to say anie
thing against it, but it hath made his eyes to dazle, as the
clearest Sun-shining, whereby hee hath been driuen to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
hither and thither, groping for euasions, and yet coulde
not escape, but hath falne into infinite most mostrous absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities,
and blasphemous assertions, (as by their writinges yet
extant it may appeare) so forcible is the trueth, to amaze the
painesayers thereof, and so pregnant is falshood to beget and
<pb n="2" facs="2"/>
bring foorth thousands of absurdities, and euery one worse
then other. And will you still continue in your damnable,
and most diuelishe course? Haue you solde your selues vnto
Satan, to fight for him vntill you bee dammed in hell with
him? Haue you morgaged the saluation of your soules
and bodies, for the present fruition of your pompe and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
is it because you see not what you should doe? It may be
so, for many are so blinde, that they grope euen at noone day:
but me thinkes it can hardly be so, vnlesse you bee they that
haue eyes &amp; see not, for the cause hath been (by the blessing
of God) so managed, that many plough-men, artificers, and
children doe see it, and know it, and are able by the worde of
God to iustifie it, and condemne you to bee aduersaries vnto
the Gospell in resisting it. But you thinke that gouernment
not so needfull, and your fault but small (if it be any) in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing
your course begunne. The necessitie of the thing is
many wayes apparant, both in that it hath so plentifull war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
from Gods own word, (as the course of this booke doth
uidently declare,) and also in that the Gospell can take no
roote, nor haue any free passage, for want of it: and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of your fault appeareth by this, that in so doing, you are
the cause of all the ignorance, Atheisme, schismes, treasons,
poperie and vngodlinesse, that is to be founde in this lande,
which we challenge to proue to your faces, if we may indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently
be heard, &amp; wherof in the meane while we will giue
you a taste: for the first it is cleare, that you are the causers of
that damnable ignorance, wherein the people are so general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
wrapped, for that you haue from time to time stopped the
streames of knowledge, in those places where the Lorde in
mercie bestowed the same, and in steed of able and painefull
Ministers, haue pestered the Churche, eyther with presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
proude persons, that are esteemed learned and take no
paines to bringe the people vnto the knowledge of Iesus
Christe, or (which is the greatest number) suche ignoraunt
Asses, and filthie swine, as are not worthie to liue in a well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
common-wealth: and that you are the cause of all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme,
it is plaine, for one may (as in deede many doe) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse
it, and you say nothing to him for it. If the most filthie
<pb n="3" facs="2"/>
liuer will fawne vpon you, and bribe your seruants, you will
not only fauour him, but assist him against any godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster
or other: but if any that feare God, refuse to come vnder
the least of your popish ceremonies, hee shall bee molested,
till his purse be emptie, or els by your tyrannous dealing, he
haue made shipwrack of a good censcience. And are not you
the cause of all schismes, that make a hotch-pot of true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
and poperie, and so giue some occasion to fall into this
course, and others into that? And it is as cleare, that you are
so farre the cause of all treasons, as without you they had not
bin: for if euery Church had had her gouernment according
to Christes institution, our young Gentlemen, and students,
had not bin (for want of teaching &amp; careful ouersight) made
a pray vnto the seducers, and consequently to those practises
which haue brought the bodies of so manie vnto Tyborne,
and their soules into hell: and who but you be the causes of
Poperie, whilest you vse them so well, let them doe wat they
list, yea, and keepe them in office &amp; authoritie vnder you, yea
(which more is) giue them such offices as none that is not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish
can execute: I speak not of the ignorance which by your
meanes raigneth euerie where, which (as they confesse) is the
mother of their deuotion, and you are the wretched fathers
of that filthie mother, whereby you must needes be grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
(at the least) to all kind of poperie. And who can (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
blushing) denie you to bee the cause of all vngodlines,
seeing your gouernment is that which giueth leaue to a man
to be any thing, sauing a sounde Christian. For certainely it
is more free in these dayes,<note place="margin">Omnia tum liceant, non licet esse bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> to bee a Papist, Anabaptist, of the
famely of loue, yea any most wicked one wahtsoeuer, then
that which we should be, and I could liue these twenty yeres
any such in Englande (yea in a Bishops house it may bee) and
neuer bee muche molested for it, so true is that which
you are charged with, in a Dialogue lately come foorth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
you, &amp; since burned by you, that you care for nothing,
but the maintenance of your dignities, bee it to the damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of your owne soules, and infinite millions moe: Enter
therefore nowe at the last, into the serious confideration of
these thinges: remember that one day, you must bee presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
before the tribunall seate of Iesus Christe, to bee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned
for all the soules that haue gone to hell (seeing you
will needes bee the rulers of the Churche) since the Gospell
first appeared in this land, then shall you not be excused with
this, the Queene and Counsell will haue it so: not with that,
our state cannot beare it. For it shall be said vnto you, why do
you not informe thē better of my will, why taught you them
not to worship with trembling and feare, and to kisse the
sonne least he be angrie: why did you not tell them, that all
states must be ruled by my worde, and not my word by them
and their pollicies. When these thinges shall be laied to your
charge, your consciences shall answere: that if you had done
so, you should haue lost your dignities, which you loued and
sought for especially: then shall you wishe, that the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
woulde fall vppon you, and the hilles couer you from
the presence of the lambe, and from the presence of him that
sitteth vppon the throne. And I am perswaded, that you are
in league with hell, and haue made a couenant with death:
yea, you doe perswade your selues, that there is no God, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
shall there be any such day of account: or it were vnpos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible,
that you should giue your eyes any sleepe, or take any
rest in your beds, vntill you had vnto the Lord by repentance
and the Churche by confession, vuburdened your soules of
these hellish wayes, wherein you haue so long walked. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,
repent, be not ashamed to amende, though others haue
founde you out the way, iudge your selues while you haue
time, least you be made fire brands of hell beyonde all time.
Let our challendges that wee haue made in the name of the
Lord be hearkened vnto: Let vs be disputed with before in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different
Iudges, let the holy word of God be the touch-stone
to trie our disputations by, and then shall it easilie appeare,
who hath the Lorde on his side, and who not. The trueth wil
preuaile in spite of your teeth, and all other aduersaries vnto
it, (for God disdaineth to be crossed by dust and ashes.) Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
bee not obstinate so long, as vntill you will bee founde
fighters with God, but preuent his wrath, least it break forth
against you like fire that none can quenche, because of the
wickednesse of your inuentions. Venture your Bishoprickes
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>
vpon a disputation, and wee will venture our liues, take the
challendge if you dare. If the truth be on your side, you may
heereby be restored to your dignities, and bee no more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
by vs: but if the trueth be against you, what shall it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite
you to winne the whole world, and afterward loose your
owne soules. If you refuse still our offer, then must you needs
be guiltie either of this, that you knowe your cause will not
abide the triall, or of this, that you wil take no paines to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute
vs that keepe such a sturre in the Church: doe not think
that because you haue humane authoritie on your side, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
you are safe, for hee whose authoritie is on our side, is
the greatest, to whose voyce all the Diuels in hell shall stoup,
much more the sielie arme of sinfull flesh. Wet haue sought
to aduance this cause of God, by humble suite to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
by supplication to your Conuocation house, by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
in defence of it, and by challendging to dispute for it,
seeing none of these meanes vsed by vs haue preuailed: If it
come in by that meanes, which will make all your heartes to
ake, blame your selues, for it must preuaile, maugre the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
of all that stande against it, or such a iudgement must o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertake
this lande, as shall cause the eares that heare thereof
to tingle, and make vs bee a by-worde to all that passe by vs.
The Lorde open your eyes, that you may see the confusions
whereof you are the cause, and giue you true repentance, or
confound you in all your purposes, that bee against him and
the regiment of his sonne Iesus Christe. The same Lorde, for
the loue he beareth to his people, open the eyes of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie,
and the Honorable Counsellers, that they may see your
godlesse practises, and in pitie to Gods people, ridde vs from
you, and turne away his iudgements, which the reiecting
of his holie yoke hath deserued, not punishing them
that mourne for the desolation of Sion, with
those that spoyle and make hauocke
of the Lordes inheritance.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>