<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authour to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101936_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00637</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10770</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101936</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authour to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A counter-poyson : modestly written for the time, to make aunswere to the obiections and reproches, wherewith the aunswerer to the Abstract, would disgrace the holy discipline of Christ</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 80, 90-195, 6 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Authour to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>IT is sayde of Solomon (who had no small experience in the course of al things) <hi>that much reading is wearinesse vnto the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccles. 12.</note>
      <hi>flesh;</hi> but it is most true, euen in our owne experience, that to deale with the vntamed and vntaught reason of man, is a vanity &amp; vexation of spirit, vnto those who loue the truth. For what cunning shiftes and exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site variety of subtleties haue they, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the mighty strooke of the word of God? And it is no maruaile, if we poore dullardes be not only made blunt, but almost worne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye with encountring with such tough ware. The onely comfort we haue is, that when the diuell disputed, yea, continued dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting so long with the Son of God him self, hee was at the length made to retire with those milde, and yet most powrefull wordes: <hi>The Lord rebuke thee Sathan.</hi> Which<note place="margin">Iud. 9.</note> most auncient example, as it hath greatly sustayned me in this toyle of this tedious time, wherein I haue had occasion to goe bare-foote through this quicke-set hedge of thornes, which the aunswerer to the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stract</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
hath set in our way: so it doth not a little grieue me, that I am iealous ouer my selfe, that I haue not followed in such mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure as I ought, that moderation which the sonne of God; <hi>The prince of Angels</hi> kept, when he encountred with the deuil, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, I deale (as I hope) with a brother. My comfort is, that it shall be manifest, that in steede of taking occasion where it was not giuen, I haue swallowed downe that, as sweet, which is most loathsome and bitter: I haue also stayd my course within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe of the first treatise, and the daungerous appendix annexed to the same; partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I suppose he wil not abuse so much the Scripture, as to wrest the defence of plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Ciuill offices, in Ministers of God his word, of sole excommunication (which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready handled in this treatise by the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) and partly because the rest will for the most part pertaine properly to the worthye Lawyer, who hath begun this controuersie, and shall by the grace of God see a good end of the same. The Lord bring vs all to be of one minde and hart in the truth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>