<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>ALBERT GIRARD.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101439_Bo1_1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07035</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17451</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101439</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>ALBERT GIRARD.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The art of fortification, or architecture militaire as vvell offensiue as defensiue, compiled &amp; set forth, by Samuell Marolois revievved, augmented and corrected by Albert Girard mathematician: &amp; translated out of French into English. by [sic] Henry Hexam</title>
                 <author>Marolois, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jansson (Johnson), Jan 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 44, 48 pages, 1, 42 leaves of plates, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_note">
   <head>ALBERT GIRARD.</head>
   <p>THe Authour hath here aboue so disposed his calculations, that in stead of explaining
them briefly, he confounds them teadiously, as if heretofore there had bene noe certaine
rule sett dovvne in vvriting, to calculate lines and angles as is ordinarily done by the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gometrie</hi>
of plaine Triangles, although there haue bene a number of Authours, vvhich
haue treated of them, th' one after one manner, th' other after an other; and the most part of
them commixed vvith longe discourses, vvhich moved me not longe since, to putt into light
some tables of <hi>Sines</hi> in a portable volume, vvith the most succinct method that possibly could,
touching the supputation of such plaine triangles, reducing them into foure diverse cases,
vvhere I did insert in their places, some of my ovvne inventions to the purpose, knovvne as
I suppose to none others heretofore; so that it cannot be, but having 3 knovvne termes, in a
triangle, but that one maye knovve the other three, or one of them onely, vvhich one desires,
as the Reader may knovve it; the manner &amp; order thereof being much more facile, &amp; easier
to conceiue, then the reading of our Authour in his former editions, being obscure, trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some,
and hard to be attayned unto. For this reason the Learners of this science, are required
to be forevvarned before they come to the reading of this booke; &amp; are advertized hereby,
that vvhen it is sayd, a triangle hath three termes, he must understand knovvne, or given,
and that vvhen I say that a triangle right-angle hath three termes, that then I am bound
but to shevv tvvo of them; seing that this vvord (right-angle) presupposeth that the triangle
hath a right angle, to vveet of 90 degrees: moreover, that touching this present question,
these 7, 21, 5 parts, demonstrate the reason of the lines <hi>ND, DI, IF,</hi> and not the quantitie
of the same in feete, as is necessary to finde in the manner follovving.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>