<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authors preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101792_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14254</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24569</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101792</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authors preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sacke of Roome : exsequuted by the Emperour Charles armie euen at the natiuitie of this Spanish Kinge Philip. Notablie described in a Spanish dialogue, with all the horrible accidents of this sacke, and abhominable sinnes, superstitions &amp; diseases of that cittie, whic prouoked these iust iudgements of God. Translated latelie into the English tounge, neuer fitter to bee read nor deeplier considered, then euen now at this present time</title>
                 <author>Valdés, Alfonso de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jeffes, Abel</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ward, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Authors preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O great is the blindnesse wherein for the most part the world is now drowned, that I maruell not at the false iudgements by the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple conceiued of this late accident of Rome: for as they suppose Religion to consist onelie in these externall things: so seeing them so badlie hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, they thinke the faith to be vtterlie ouerthrowne, and in truthe as I cannot but commend, the holy zeale wherewith the common sorte are thereto mooued, so can I not allowe of their silence, whose dutie were to reduce them from that error. Seeing then on the one part, how preiudiciall it should be, first to the glory of God, then to the saluation of his people: and also to the honour of this most Christian king and Emperour whome God hath giuen vnto vs, if these matters should remaine thus cloaked, I haue attempted (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther led therevnto by simplicitie and hartie loue, then by foolish arrogancie to accomplish with this small seruice, these three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall things wherevnto men are bound. I was not ignorant that the matter was much more high and difficile then the measure of my forces, and yet I knowe aswell that where there is a good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Iesu Christ dooth lighten the vnderstanding, and supplie with his grace the defect of our forces and knowledge attained by humaine wit, My thought also, I did see represented before mee the false iudgements that superstitious Pharizes are like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue of this matter, wherefore let them knowe, that I write not for them nor to them, but to the true Christians &amp; faithfull louers of Christ Iesu. Aswell did I also see, the peruerse contrarieties of the common sorte, the which are so setled on things visible, as they do almost make a iest of the things inuisible. Remembring therfore that I wrote not to Gentiles but vnto Christians, whose perfection is to withdraw it selfe from things visible, &amp; to loue the inuisible:
<pb facs="4"/> I remembred also that I wrote not vnto brute people, but vnto <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whose wits, there is nothing so difficult but they are able to attaine: and seeing my desires are no others then my words expresse, I easilie perswade my selfe that I shall attaine of all that are discreete, and not counterfeit Christians, if anie default be found in this dialogue, to interpreat the same in the best sence: and impute the blame to my ignorance, and not presume to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that mallice hath any parte therein, since in all I sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my selfe to the correction and iudgement of the holy Churche, the which I acknowledge for the mother of the Disciples of the trueth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>