<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1599</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101314_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07825</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18198</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101314</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the nature of God</title>
                 <author>Morton, Thomas, of Berwick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Dexter, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1599</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jackson (Jacson), Ralph 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 239, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ereis (good Reader) a litle Treatise of a great Argument, in the which (if euer in any) that may be seene, which doth dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to passe, that the Book it self doth nothing lesse then performe that which the title doth promise and pretend: as we see and find often that the countenances of men do make a faire shew of many singuler vertues and excellent parts, which in triall are not to bee found in any part eyther of their soules or bodies. How then (may any and will some man say) do you of purpose go about to deceiue vs with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing titles, which haue vnder them no sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of matter? or were you your selues de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in taking in hand that which you were not able to accomplish? Surely whatso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uer
<pb facs="3"/>
we were, he hauing the truth plainly told him, and the fault reuealed, need not now be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued vnlesse he will himselfe, and then <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenti nō fit iniuria:</hi> but for our parts wee did enterprise this conference, not in hope of soū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the depth of this bottomelesse mysterie, but onely purposing to content our selues with that knowledge of it which is reuealed in the word of God. The which no doubt is most needfull, and also comfortable to all Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: for what eyther is or shall be our happines but the true knowledge and continuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of God? To the which purpose, if this Treatise do any whit further thee, we are glad: otherwise take our good will in good part. And so we commend the (good Reader) as we desire to be commended by thee, to the gracious assistance of Gods holy spirit, to be by him instructed and preserued in all truth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>