<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To Mr Elway Bevin upon his Canons of three parts in one▪ An EPIGRAM.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101568_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09578</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1986</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101568</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To Mr Elway Bevin upon his Canons of three parts in one▪ An EPIGRAM.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe and short instruction of the art of musicke : to teach how to make discant, of all proportions that are in vse: very necessary for all such as are desirous to attaine to knowledge in the art; and may by practice, if they can sing, soone be able to compose three, foure, and five parts: and also to compose all sorts of canons that are usuall, by these directions of two or three parts in one, upon the plain-song. By Elvvay Bevin</title>
                 <author>Bevin, Elway</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Young (Junius), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 52 pages, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>To M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Elway Bevin <hi>upon his Canons of three parts in one▪ An</hi> EPIGRAM.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>MUsicke breaths heaven, nay more, it doth disclose it,</l>
      <l>If old Iudicious <hi>Bevin</hi> doe compose it.</l>
      <l>Astronomy stares high, and doth not feare</l>
      <l>To draw heavens curtaine, and unfold a Spheare:</l>
      <l>But Musicke climbes as high as <hi>Iacobs</hi> Scale,</l>
      <l>Out-vies a <hi>Iacobs</hi> Staffe: it doth unvaile</l>
      <l>Three for her one, or rather three in one:</l>
      <l>A mystery that Art ne're thought upon.</l>
      <l>Three parts in one, are no Trichotomy</l>
      <l>Of one in three, but a sweet Trinity</l>
      <l>Combin'd in one. This may (with wonder) make</l>
      <l>An Atheist (if hee'le lay his eares to stake)</l>
      <l>Sing Trinity in Vnity, when he shall</l>
      <l>Heare that (which he thought harsh) prove musicall.</l>
      <l>Church Musicke finds applause, then why not Hee</l>
      <l>That sets forth Canons of a Trinity?</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <salute>Thomas Palmer.</salute>
      <signed>Bristoll.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>