<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Worshipfull Sir William Romney Knight, Alderman of London, and Gouernour of the worshipfull Companie of Marchants trading to the East Indies, and to the rest of the Committies.</title>
           <author>Scott, Edmund</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101657_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11767</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22061</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101657</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Worshipfull Sir William Romney Knight, Alderman of London, and Gouernour of the worshipfull Companie of Marchants trading to the East Indies, and to the rest of the Committies.</title>
                 <author>Scott, Edmund</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exact discourse of the subtilties, fashishions [sic], pollicies, religion, and ceremonies of the East Indians : as well Chyneses as Iauans, there abyding and dweling. Together with the manner of trading with those people, aswell by vs English, as by the Hollanders: as also what hath happened to the English nation at Bantan in the East Indies, since the 2. of February 1602. vntil the 6. of October 1605. Whereunto is added a briefe description of Iaua Maior. Written by Edmund Scott, resident there, and in other places neere adioyng [sic], the space of three yeere and a halfe</title>
                 <author>Scott, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Burre, Walter.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>52 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Worshipfull Sir William Romney Knight, Alderman of London, and Gouernour of the worshipfull Companie of Marchants trading to the <hi>East Indies,</hi> and to the rest of the Committies.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, because heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it hath been a vsuall custome, that those which first haue been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident in other forraine Countries, as <hi>Turkey, Persia,</hi> and <hi>Musco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie,</hi> haue registred such matters as haue hapned worthy of note in their times, beeing in those partes of the maine Continent Land; wherefore I hauing been lately Resident for your Worship in the Iland of <hi>Iaua ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior,</hi> toward the East parts of the world: Albeit I am no Scholler to performe it with an eloquent discourse; yet fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and withall beeing put in minde by some friendes, that if I neglected it, I should be condemned of slouth: haue thought good to present vnto your Worshippe, these few Lines: the which may certifie you of the great blessings of God, both in preseruing the greatest quantitie of your goods, and our liues; which are come home out of that rude and dangerous Region, into our owne natiue Countrey. Likewise your Worshippe shall vnderstand by this plaine
<pb facs="3"/>
Discourse the situation of the place, and the manners and fashions of the people; with some other strange accidents, which for breuitie sake I did not certifie you of by my Letters sent from thence: but in this small Volume you shall see, from time to time, how euery thing hath been ordered, and performed in your businesse, and other affayres. All which, I hope, will be to your good liking, considering the place, and extremitie wee were in. So de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring <hi>GOD</hi> to blesse and prosper all your proceedings, I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships, <hi>Edmund Scott.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>