<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Thomas Paulfreyman vn∣to the christen Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1560</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101415_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08850</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19137</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101415</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Thomas Paulfreyman vn∣to the christen Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A myrrour or cleare glasse : for all estates, to looke in, conteining briefly in it the true knovvledge and loue of god, and the charitie of a faithfull christian tovvardes his neyghbour</title>
                 <author>Palfreyman, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1560</date>
                 <publisher>Lobley (Loblee), Michael.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sutton, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Walley (Waley), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>124 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Thomas Paulfreyman</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the christen Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie of god hath alvvai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es appered vnto man, by his om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie mercie and loue.</note>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S wee in tyme (from tyme to tyme) haue alwayes percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and felt the great and vnspeakable mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of god, in signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng vnto vs his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (thorow his grace) his omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie and power, and his infinite loue and will prescribed vnto vs in his heauenly and diuine wourde, to the manifestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and playne settyng oute before oure eies thexcellency of his moste glorious maiestie: and for his vertue and great puissance to be an onely God aboue all goddes: who straightly also respecteth the singularitie of his owne glory, and seketh therein the onely ioye, comforte, strengthe and saluation of vs his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:<note place="margin">The loue of god to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardes his people.</note> vnto whom he commendeth his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, his truth, this promises: in whom he only delighteth, and vpon whom he gladly pretendeth to synisshe his moste beautifull wourke begun, as hereafter shall more largely appeare: whereby
<pb facs="4"/>we should be y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rather more aptely enfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced, and lyuely encouraged,<note place="margin">The loue of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth the knovvlege of god, and to be loued againe, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beied, and folovved.</note> worthyly to acknowledge hym, euen as he is, in his maiestie, most dearely to loue him, to honour hym, to attend alwais vpon hym, and reuerently in all thynges to folowe and obey hym: as vertue requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth in all good thynges, to bee with goodnes agayne requighted: So to the contrarye, of oure owne rebellious na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and apte Inclination to sinfulnes beyng but bryckle and fraile earth, and not thorowly well handled, instructed, chastised, tamed, or rightly ruled by the diligence of our almighty creatour, our Lorde, our maister, and ruler, but suffre vs withoute regarde, punishemente, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> or sharpe bandes, wyth stretched outs neckes to vse the reane at lybertye,<note place="margin">Men of his ovvne natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re vvithout goddes go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement is vvilde, vvithout
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> son, and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tractable.</note> or raunge wythoute restranytie: we are wilde, wanton, and skyttishe, very bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tishe and be astlyke without reason: we will appeare vnskylfull, and to wante perseueraūce and good vnderstādyng: we wyll forget by whome we lyue: we wyll not acknowledge our maker, nor remembre oure maister that gentelye speaketh to vs, that is carefull for vs, that feedethe vs, that comfortablye
<pb facs="5"/>nourisheth vs,<note place="margin">The fruites that prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth onely of mans na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture.</note> and taketh payne about vs: we wyll neither regarde hym nor feare hym, that is of power to strike &amp; destroy vs: we will not in any thyng, be ruled by hym, nor yelde to obeye hym, but vnreuerently striue with hym, run from hym,<note place="margin">The hartes of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>te and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ylful peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple are
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>uffe at hym, or tourne our heeles against hym: as experience with wo, hath taught throughout all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations from the beginnyng vntyl this present day: specially the headstronge and wylfulle obstinate people of this worlde, that holde their onely felicitie vpon the pleasures of this lyfe: whose hartes are hardened agaynst God their maker, maliciousely in blyndenesse to repugne his wyll, and flye from hym: no diligence wyll wynne them, no doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine reforme theim, nor no correction amend them, so damnable is their state and great stoutenes of will to wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whereby the myghty and horrible plagues of god hath fallen for their sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes vpon the earthe, to the destruction of whole nations, countreis, and kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doms, as the scriptures and other sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries mencioneth playnely to vs, to put vs in feare of his omnipotency &amp; sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of iustice, and to tourne vs backs
<pb facs="5"/>from our vayn and beastly foolishnes,<note place="margin">The excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of God, at our return to god.</note> whose fast folowynge fountaines also of mercy at oure retourne, so farre ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth the iniquitie of man, when it is at the very rypest or hyghest, that he then continually calleth, and as it were painfully trauaileth by certain means, to thende he may wynne vs, and safely delyuer vs frome she daunger of diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, if we wyl yelde to his mercy, who will ioyfully receaue vs, clearely remit vs, &amp; reward vs with euerlasting felicitie. The order wherof and thexcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of his works is signified vnto vs at large, in the booke of lyfe: Of the whiche, gentil reader, I haue at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyunyng of this my sclender laboure, made brefe relation, takyng it for a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenient and moste certayn grounde to plante on my foundation: seeyng that chiefly and aboue all thynges, the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of christianitie and holynes, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth by diuine influence, in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the maiestie of God, whyche can bee by no meanes so directe, as to note well the meruaylous order of the workes of God, whiche are greate, and meruallous woorthy to bee praised and had in honour, and to bee sought out of
<pb facs="6"/>all theym that loue them and haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in them: by the whiche also we see his omnipotente state and power, the gentlenes of his most gracious and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature, the myldnes of his mercy and the sharpenes of his iustice: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we labour with reuerence, not only for the true knowledge of his wyl how to honour hym, or in what maner we shall lyue before hym:<note place="margin">Our ovvne feeblenes driueth vs to god for strength to the vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge of rightuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</note> but also feelyng in oure selues our owne great frailtie and feeblenes, we sue for his assistence and strength, that our faith, loue, and obedience, may euer be liuely, constant and perfect before hym: and so foorthe in other vertues, that the seruice of rightousnes, may ioyntly appere right from rightuous men, in such rightuous and moste pure profession, before so rightuous and holye a God. And so I passe forthe declaryng the grounde of myne entent and meanynge: howe the diuel (the sower of sedition and worker of all mischief) hath meruailousely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualled agaynst vs: and howe he hathe made diuision amongest vs, to the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng and tearyng in peces, the straight bonde of our peace to God. I haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted also our loue &amp; duetie towardes our
<pb facs="6"/>neighbours: and howe greatly therein we haue disobeyd the wyll of God: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claryng also (certain impediments) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently raignyng emongest vs, that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth muche the true charitie of God &amp;c. And wherein soeuer in this woorke of godlynes, I haue seemed to swarue frome due order, not vsynge and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perynge the matter, in suche wyse as wysedom, experience, and greate lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng wold require, to theedifyeng and godly profytynge of the diligente and faithfull reader:<note place="margin">A requeste to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> I humbly beseeche the charitable and louyng frende, that arte zelous to vertue and godlynes to beare with my faultes, to take in good parte the vertue of my good will, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly ioyn thy wyl to the gracious good wyll of god, from whom all vertue pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cedeth, who chargeth and strayghtlye commaundeth thee, that in whatsoeuer thyng thy conscience shal herein iudge vnto thee to bee good, &amp; agreable to hys wourde, thou do in no wise contemne it, hauyng respecte to persones: but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it and preferre it, for his glorye &amp; prayse sake. It is the ende of my trauail and thouly straight marke, wherevnto tendeth the effecte of my good wyll.
<pb facs="7"/>If it shall please thee of thy goodnesse, to ioyne with me in that behalfe, seyng that nothynge is more expedient in the the life of a christian man,<note place="margin">Nothing is more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diēt in the life of a christen mā than to be mindful of god.</note> agreable to to his profession, or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> more beautifieth his honest estimation, then in al his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges to be myndfull of God, &amp; in such wyse to vse them, that God therby may bee alwayes contented, and his name woorthyly praised and magnified. So that suche simplicitie and faithful plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse, dedicated frome our hart to God, and agreablye amonge oure selues to beare one with an other, respectynge contynuallye the rewarde of the ende: there shall not then bee seene in vs any spotte of reproche, or any blemysshe of deformitie, whether of scornefulnesse, contempte,<note place="margin">Fruites frō ā vvicked hart.</note> or disdaynefulnesse one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst an other, whiche are approued euylles spryngynge from wycked har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes: frome whens proceede the defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, rashe iudgemente, sclaunder, detraction, and euyll reporte, to the great hynderyng, pluckyng backe, and discouragyng of faythfull and willyng hartes, that are at all tymes aptly bent to bee seruisable for the praise of god, &amp; to the commoditie or coumforte of his
<pb facs="7"/>people: for whose sakes and godly edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeng the fruites of righteousnes appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth frome the ryghtuous, as god shall plant in theim the plentyfulnesse of his grace: the distribution wherof, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not vppon all men alyke. If God therefore christen reader, haue poured vpon thee more abundantly the giftes of his grace, that thou seest and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>west, to his praise, that which I, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, neyther yet haue seene or knowen: whether by great wysedome, profounde learnynge, or holynes of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng with a mortified or subdued body wherby the lyght also of thy lyfe, more clerely shineth before the worlde, to the commendation of God and man: and that thou passest forth thy tyme, apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God, with inward ioy of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, as one that were conuersaunt with god in heauen: wholly neglocting the fugitiue pleasures of this lyfe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che seemeth to be of myghtie force, and annexed to ioyes incomparable: consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then I humbly beseeche thee, wyth thyne accustomed thankfulnes to god, the dewe office of these sayde vertues, nowe abiding in thee, and the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly operation of them: which at no tyme
<pb facs="8"/>or in any thynge who soeuer haue them in possession,<note place="margin">Neyther vvisedome learninge, nor holie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, slepe in priuate idlenes.</note> sleepe in priuate ydle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, or properlye serue for one onelye mannes strength and commoditye, to staye hym, or wourke force in hym, to his contentation and purpose, or to the well lykynge onelye of hym, selfe in all thinges, and scornefully reprouinge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whyche shoulde seeme to bee the fruites of a vaine and vnfrendly spirit, and greatelye dissentinge from the spy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of grace: but to beare charitablye with others Ignoraunce, basenesse of knowledge, or imperfection of holines, tenderly taking in good part, their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent appointed talente, whych god hath geuen vnto theun after the measure of his grace:<note place="margin">The chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the vvise and godlie lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned.</note> for therby truly thy lernyng thy wysedom, and thy verruous liuyng shall be the rather approued to thvse of god, and for the great comfort and good encouragemente of me and suche other like, to be diligent by the helpe of God, and to growe to further strengthe and godlye perfection to the prayse of God. And in the meane while, where this my presente doynge, shall in deede seeme vnto thee, to be but grosse, vnpleasant, dull and vnwitty, voyde of good order,
<pb facs="8"/>and barrayne of eloquencye, whyche are reprochefull impedimentes, in the skylful and learned wrighter, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly herein, by thy vertue and wise<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, beare thy pacyente and learned iudgemēt: thys cōmodytie thereby shal redounde towardes thee, that thorowe suche vnsee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>melines, disorder, and rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, of thys my sleightie and sleander doynges: the excellencie of thy lyuelye diligence, and profounde wysedome in thy learned trauayles, shall appeare muche more beautyfull and seemelye, and more clearelye to shyne to thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye and immortall fame, beynge nowe so rychelye possessed, adourned, and beautified, wyth so precious and peare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse treasures, planted in thee from the God aboue: Who gentlye at all tymes of hys mooste mylde nature, taketh in good parte, suche retourned fruites, as he beefore hathe bee gonne and sette in oure heartes, accordynge to the depth of hys grace: by whose heauenlye and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyne influence, hys faste sette roote of ryghteousnesse he mercyfullye preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, nourisheth, wat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>reth, and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, with his celestiall distillyng moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture or dewe of life: that to one or other

<pb facs="9"/>from the highest to the lawest, from the moste perfecte taster, to the moste insen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sible creature, choyse shall styll reygne to chose, that at the least some swetenes or good repast may ioyfully fal to som. This consydered, I for my parte am the rather encouraged, or by Goddes good motion enforced: I am bolde so to terme it, for as much as no goodnes procedeth from the harte of man, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his assistence and greate strengthe, thereby to spende in this behalfe, some p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rcell of my tyme, to shewe forthe the prayse of god in the works of his grace thorough the increace of vertue by the power of his holye spirite, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils moste vyolent and damnable dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, woundyng our consciences to euer lastyng death, beyng putte by and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quished, the lyfe of righteousnes maye flowe in vs, to the knowledge and loue of god: and that we may in the feare of God, seke his peace and vnitie, to loue one an other, and not to be in any wyse deuided, but to bee charitable, pitifull, and frendely one to an nother, and to prepare for the nedefull sustentation of the poore membres of Iesus Christe, who miserablye perisheth for wante of
<pb facs="9"/>succor, that the blessyng of God, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in his sonne our Lorde and sauior may plentifully descende down amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest vs, and vpon vs al,<note place="margin">The mercy of god to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards the Quene.</note> to the preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion chieflye of the Quenes most royal maiestie: whom god hath hitherto nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risshed, blessed, and mightily preserued thorowe hys mercye, and according to the lyuelye faithe and hope of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable her true frendes and obediēt sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes: and contrarye to the expectation of manye thousandes, her maliciouse &amp; most cruell enemyes: our Lorde for the greatnes of hys mercyes sake wourks in them Repentaunce, to the tournyng of their heartes, and prepare them to be now appliable and obedient subiectes, that we may altogether in vnitie, wyth faythfull and true Englishe heartes, be thankefull vnto God for her grace, to leane to her, and with a louelye feare to obeye her, to honour her, to healpe her, and reioyce in her our chief souerayne and onelye high maiestrate nexte vnder god: whome he with hys stretched oute arme and almyghtie power, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the effusion of anye christen bloud, or occasion minystred to the same, hath quietly stablished her, and brought her
<pb facs="10"/>to her imperial throne, so greately hath he vanquished the harts of her enemies, signifienge thereby vnto vs all her true englishe,<note place="margin">The pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of god tovvardes the Quene</note> and christen subiectes, that she is of purpose elected, raised vp, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued by god, to this imperial dignity, as the appointed seruaunie or high my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyster of God, for the supportacion of peace, and to take the swourd of aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in her owne hande, to the erecting or reedifying agayne of hys glorye, in peace and righteousnesse: takynge hys wourde of trueth, to be her assured good guide, aide, and strength: &amp; by the vertu and Inuincible power thereof, to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plante and treade vnder foote,<note place="margin">The ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>e of goddes vvorde.</note> all vaine deuised fantasies, crastye collusions, &amp; proude vsurpacions, to the reioyeing of Christies faithfull seruauntes, his true frendes and ministers: and to the refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation or amendement of all other his disobedient and blynde ignorant enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: if the spirite of grace wyl so work in them, for their happy conuersion, as the newe borne children of god: and by her to be supported, preserued, and safe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye defended, by the auctoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde, grounded vpon god and her gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious mooste godlye lawes. Withoute
<pb facs="10"/>whiche holye conuersion and humble submission, leauynge all wycked affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, apertlye or secreatlye repugnynge, murmurynge, conspiringe, subtle dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblynge, or wyckedlye rebellynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainste god and hys true procedynges, reueled and sette soorthe, from tyme to tyme, by hys appointed and chosen my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, for hys owne gloryes sake in righteousnesse,<note place="margin">In vvhat vvise god hath raised vppe the Queene.</note> not raysed vp wyth cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell rage by vs mooste maliciouse and wretched creatures, wyth speare and shseide, or wyth spre and swourde, but peaceablye preserue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, and therein sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, by the only vertue of goddes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine power: who wil stire vp whom he su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ceth, and wil haue his truth to raign and flouryshe maugre our heades, that hath had, or haue cursed beate hartes to the contrary, that are so wifully &amp; blind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly addicted to our fathers old fossty cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes, crepte in amongeste vs by the diuelles deuyse, and receyued or stabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by menne, wyth their consent, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men coūsails, and agrement, wythout true triall &amp; auctoritie by the wourd of god, or prefermēt by the spirite of truth, althoughe we call theym suche holye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and so many in number, gathered
<pb facs="11"/>togyther at certayn tymes and places: who sought to vpholde the swetenesse of their terrestriall kingdome, through couetousnes and theyr fayre coloured wourdes, and goodly painted shewes, makyng marchādise of vs: whose iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemente is not farre of, and their iuste dampnacion sleepeth not: for the breath of God I say, wyll confound such doin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and oure stubbourne disobedience shalbe visited with the sword I shal not here neede by expresse wordes to make mention of the greeuous and moste ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible destruction, speciallye of gods pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar people the Iewes amonge other nations, for their greate dysobedience, wilfulnes, pryde, and vnthankefulnes. Consider also that god hath now of late begonne agayne with his owne church sharpelye to visite them and diuersely, for their greate vnthankfulnes,<note place="margin">VVilful and christinate rebellions shalbe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> 1. The vvrath of god to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardes his people.</note> in the dayes of hys grace: and dydde therfore styrre vp his ministers of vnrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes diuerslye, most cruelly and impitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouselye, to vexe them, to tormente them and moste shamefully to destroye them as shepe appointed to the slaughter: and in suche wyse, their mercyles crueltye did abounde that the fauourers of their
<pb facs="11"/>religion a great numbre of them in the daies of kynge Edwarde fledde frome them, they vtterly forsoke thē: for their hartes dyd abhorre them in their doyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,<note place="margin">Occasiō of the peoples conuersion</note> and were thorowly perswaded in their consciences, that yf they or their religion had ben of god, thei wold haue been muche more pitifull, and not with such tyranny destroy the professours of Christ: so great was the wrathe of god ouer his people and flock, for thabusing of his grace, and not wel ordryng them selues in suche holy profession. Frome whome he hath now (ones more) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen his wrathe,<note place="margin">God hati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> retourned his mercy.</note> thorowe his greate mercy in Iesus Christ, and at the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble intercession (in hym) of his moste greuous afflicted saintes, to the cleare shynyng ones agayne of his glorye in truthe amongest them, for their further instruction, and more reuerente obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his lawes. If God so bytterlye vexed them, whoms he so dearely loued the louers of his gospell) for their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience sake aad dissimulation or dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blenes: how much more shall the fire of hys merciles wrath be kindled agaynst vs, that haue ben before obstinate,<note place="margin">The vvrath of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynste his obstinate and vvilful enemies.</note> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and olde repugners of ryghtuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="12"/>hynderers, blasphemers, consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours to bloud shedde, and moste cruell persecutours to the deathe, of his true ministers, faithefull prophetes, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and dearely beloued membres, although we spightfully reuiled them, mocked them, and called them seisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, and a thousande heretikes, with rathe iugement to damnation for euer, not takyng heauen nor purgatory cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably in our waie: and that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng suche thynges, are nowe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led agayne in peace, and wyl yet perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in suche wickednesse, and wilfully kicke against the pricke? Truely truly, we are well warned by the significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of god,<note place="margin">VVhat the mercyes of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> vs do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> signifie.</note> according to his mercy, to be better scooled, learned, and practised in the doctrine and rules of Christe, and to feare the swourde of goddes venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that hangeth by a feble threde, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fal vpon vs. God is the god of sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, to all them that wil harken and tourne vnto him, to leane vnto his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of mercy, to flie from tyranny, or consent to bloudshed (with such like) accordynge to his lawes and testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, whiche shall euer rise vp againste vs for our condemnation: byeause we haue in theim so greatly disobeyed the
<pb facs="12"/>will of god, obstinately flyenge frome hym, in the true faith and conuersation of his soonne Iesus, the heade corner stone, whiche the buylders refused, and moste shamefully contemned and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; whome he onely appoynted to bee the foundation of our reste and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall mansion: Against whiche (in any one parte therof) we may not spurne to breake,<note place="margin">God hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to hye vvil, among the povvers in heauen and among the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>the and ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> that may re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sist his had.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> say, what doest thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Daniel. 4</note> nor seeke by any meanes to spot and deface, but thankefully embrace and be ioyfull of goddes disposed wyll, consideryng it is his owne doyng, euen for his glories sake, although it appere neuer so meruailous in our eies: he wil haue it knowen that it is the onely po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of his right hand, &amp; that he himself hath don it.
<hi>Psal. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</hi> His works ar mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uailous: his right hād bringeth mighty thinges to passe: yea y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> right hand of the Lord hath y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> preeminēce: &amp; for the helth &amp; saluacion of his people, he myghtily preuaileth in al his entēts. <hi>Ps. 118.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to cōclude (without long depēding in admiration) seing that Goddes deter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minatiōs in rightousnes (as he himself is a God of rightousnes, must most cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taynly appere in brightnes, and of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie be accomplished a mongest vs:
<pb facs="13"/>againste whose will in his woorkes no man may without daunger rebel: let vs examine wel our selues and trie our sal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uacion in truthe, by the assistence of the spirite of truthe: and therby know our assured leanynge staye, and which way we shall rightly walke, and not stand so fast in assuraunce, to our aunciente ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med customes: and bycause the greate parte of christendome, thorow simple or wilfull ignoraunce, reeleth blindelye that waies, nor remembryng the smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and myld trade of Christes stable flocke, howe pacientely they beare the crosse of Christ, and suffer rather to bee persecuted then persecute: vnto whome god promised strength, and to be amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest theim for their coumforte, euen in the middest of the tire (although we wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedly iudge of them to dye obstinately, vayne gloriouselye, desperately, &amp; most beastly,<note place="margin">VVicked vvourkers iudge vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly.</note> like a sort of dogs, or very hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoūdes, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> such other malicious, rashe, and most cursed railynge iudgemente, contrarye to god, and the heartes of all godly men) neither regarde we the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and steppes of their conuersaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">The cōuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sation of the vvicked</note> through shamelesse pride, ambition, stoughtnes, couetousnes, outwarde ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes,
<pb facs="13"/>vnclennesse, maliciousnes, cruel murther, with suche lyke wickednesse, spronge vp in the churche of Christe, whiche are the fruites of the dyuel, and thincensementes of a wicked spirit, and therfore refused of the perfect and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous christians, because they bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to thexample of Christ, and his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye Apostles: who teacheth vs to trye spirites, and to knowe the tree by the fruite: but to yelde vs wyth all humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes bothe bodye and soule,<note place="margin">Hovve to attaine the grace of god.</note> into the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of god, and referre wyth reuerence (in suche tyme of controuersie) theffect of our whole faith and saluacion, to the wourkynge of his grace, by the power of his holy spirite, to the lyghtnyng of our vnderstanding, and to put by doubt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulnes, all controuersies, sectes, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uisions:<note place="margin">One God</note> that as we haue but one onely God, god our heauenly Father, Christ our onelye sauiour, and the holy spirite our comforter: all thre in glory equall, all one in substaunce, and in vnitie also all one and vndeuided:<note place="margin">One faith.</note> So we (the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessours of his name) may haue but one onely quicke and lyuely faith in one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (the true rule of christ) to the knit tyng of oure hartes in christen vnitie,
<pb facs="14"/>and to bee vndeuided,<note place="margin">The vertue of christen vnitie.</note> to the feclyng in our selues the true peace of God, and thexercise of goddes heauenly charitie: wherby our eyes shall ber opened to see and receyue his very perfecte and loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obedience: reuerently to submytie our selues to all his holy and most god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordinaunces: and with a thankefull and mylde christen spirite (accordyng to our most bounden duetie) to pray for the Queenes moste excellent maiestie, that God (for the greatnes sake of his mercy, wyll hencefoorth blesse hir, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue her, and prepare so for her, that her reigne maye bee longe and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous amongest vs, with muche ioy, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, wealthe, strengthe, and victorie ouer her ennemies, that she maye the more quietely in the feare of God, seke aboue all thynges the glory of God in rightuousnes, accordyng to the truthe of his wourde: and that his ministers also vnder her, may bee endued with the spirite of truthe, that his truthe in rightousnesse, maye beautyfully and cleerely shyne thoroughout her graces dominions to his euerlastynge prayse, and that we beeynge also blessed vnder her hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es hande (with ready prepared
<pb facs="14"/>hartes for the grace of God) may haue sufficient of all thynges, to the susten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of oure earthely bodyes, subdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge alwayes the enemies of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthe, that we her humble and louynge subiectes, maye reioyce (tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe hir highnesse) in the greate mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, and be thankefull; louyng more perfectly one another, and applye oure selues with more pitifull and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heartes, to see oure poore neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and christen brotherne better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued and prouyded for, that God (in Iesus Christe maye styll vnto the ende holde his mercyfull hande ouer vs, and finishe his good wourke vpon vs, new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agayne begunne: to the exaltation, prayse, and glorye of his moste blessed &amp; holy name, whiche alone is worthy all honour and glory. Amen.</p>
   <p>The peace of God the father through our lord Iesus Christ, by the workyng of his holy spirite in you, abyde in all your harts, and kendle in you the fyre of his loue. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>