<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A POSTCRIPT OF ADVERTISSEMENTS FOR THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101974_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13322</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23630</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101974</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A POSTCRIPT OF ADVERTISSEMENTS FOR THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhetstone of reproofe : A reprouing censure of the misintituled safe way: declaring it by discouerie of the authors fraudulent proceeding, &amp; captious cauilling, to be a miere by-way drawing pore trauellers out of the royall &amp; common streete, &amp; leading them deceitfull in to a path of perdition. With a postscript of advertisements, especially touching the homilie &amp; epistles attributed to Alfric: &amp; a compendious retortiue discussion of the misapplyed by-way. Author T.T. Sacristan &amp; Catholike Romanist</title>
                 <author>T. T., Sacristan &amp; Catholike Romanist</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyon, Marc, Widow of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 570, that is 540, 2, 198, that is 197, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb facs="255"/>
   <pb n="511" facs="255"/>
   <head>A POSTCRIPT OF ADVERTISSEMENTS FOR THE READER.</head>
   <p>I Request the reader of my Censure so take notice of some particulars which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred since the finishing of it.</p>
   <p>And imprimis touching the homilie and epistles alledged by Sir Humfrey in the 9. se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his safe way against the reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence and transsubstantion, I ansered in the 8. Period of my Censure what I conceiued at that present, to wit, that ther was not anie doctrine publikly or cōmonly read or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in England contrarie so the reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, or transsubstantiation, or in anie pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blik manner deliuered to the people either by Alfric or anie other Bishop or Bishops in anie synod or publik assembly in those dayes. since which tyme of the dispatch of that worke some delaye hauing ben made in the cōmitting it to the presse, &amp; hauing had greater opportunitie &amp; leasure to view the histories of our countrie which trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of the affayres of those ages in which Alfric liued, which was in some parte of the 10. and leuenth Centuries, by more exact examinatiō &amp; search in to the matter
<pb n="512" facs="256"/> I finde my selfe assured of the trueth of that which I then deliuered. And now for grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter satisfaction of the reader and more cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are conuincement of the same, I adde that touching Alfrics person, and state of life, he was first a monke by profession in the monasterie of Abington, and as Males<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie relates, <note place="margin">
         <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de gest. Pont. Aug. pag.</hi> 203.</note> Abbat of the same: then Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of wilton, and after Archbishop of Canterburie. Ther is diuersitie of opinions whether <hi>Siricius alias sigericus,</hi> or Alfric did immediately succeed S. dunstan in that seat, but that importeth little; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it he was a Roman Catholique, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Vid. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>psf. saec.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> for that an ancient Chronicle writ by a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of the same monasterie of Abington (wher of as I alledged our of Malesburie, Alfric was Abat) conuinceth testifying that he went to Rome for his Episcopall pall, as the custome was, which iourney Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fric would neiuer haue made, nor euer haue obtained his request, if he had not ben of the same faith in euerie point which at that tyme the Pope him selfe profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.</p>
   <p>That which also is most plainely demonstrated by an ample testimonie which the church of Canterburie gaue of the same Arcbishop Alfric, and at their request sent to the monkes of his order
<pb n="513" facs="256"/> and monasterie Abington for a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall memorie of his faith and manners: which for greater sattsfaction of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I will here rehearse at it as recorded by the foresaid religious man.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>To the children of the holy church of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie the clergie, and the same church after their deuoute prayers. It is knowne vnto you all how long since it is that by the successes of diuers and various euents the mother church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland hath ben depriued of her pastor and destitute of her rector, which doth pertaine not onely to our losse but alsoe to the detriment of you and all this Iland, since it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that the sollicitude and care of the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le countrie is committed to the Metroplican. For which cause we haue elected Alfric by name monke of the holy church of Abington most sufficiently knowne vnto vs, noble in brith and maners, indued with Apostolicall and Ecclesiasticall discipline, and in faith a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, by nature prudente, docible, patient, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, chaste, sober, humble, affable, mercifull, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, instructed in the lawe of God, cautelous in the senses of the scripture, exercised in Ecclesiasticall decrees or determinations. And according to the path of scripture, orthodox traditions, and Canons, and constitutions of the Prelates of the Apostolicall seat, vnderstanding, teaching,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Praesulum Sedis Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolica.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>and obseruing the Ecclesiasticall rules in a sound
<pb n="514" facs="257"/> sense, and embracing that faithfull worde which is according to doctrine: and reprehending with modestie those whoe resist it; and hauing power to resiste and redargue them: hospitable, modest, well ruling his house, not a neophit; hauing a good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or testimonie, ministering in euerie degree or order according to Ecclesiasticall tradition. Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all good workes, and to giue satisfaction to euerie one that shall demaunde it, of the hope which is in him. &amp;c.</hi> Thus proceedeth the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the electors of Alfric.</p>
   <p>And to this I ioyne that S. Dunstan his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate predecessor (excepting Ethelgar or at the most according to the opiniō of some writers. excepting Ethelgar and Siricius whoe both liued but fiue yeares or ther a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boutes) as our histories reporte at the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of his death spake much of the reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of Christ in the Eucharist in a sermon he made the same day he dyed. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Svy S. Dunstan.</hi>
      </note> And in like manner of Elphegus Alfrics successor it is reported by our English historians, he was such a mortifyed man by reason of his great abstinence, and fasting that when according to the custome of the Romā church he ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated the sacred hoaste in masse, the refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ayre appeared as it were in a glasse throu' the iunctures of his fingers. Now tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the twoe immediate predecessors of Alfric which I mentioned before to wit Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar
<pb n="515" facs="257"/> &amp; Sricius neither anie historiographer nor yet anie of our aduersaries themselues doe note them to haue diuulged or admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their tyme anie other doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Eucharist then that which was then professed in the Roman church. By which it is manifest that both immediately before and immediately after Alfrics dayes, the same doctrine of the reall presēce which at this tyme the Romā church maintaines was cōmonly tought &amp; practised in England and no other: soe that morally speaking it is not apprehensible that in the tyme of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frics being Bishop of Canterburie which according to the computation of tymes was but ten yeares or littlemore, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Godwins Catalogue.</hi>
      </note> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie doctrine and the denyall of the reall presence and transsubstantiation could haue bin publikly professed and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by diuers Bishops in their synods as Sir Humfrey Line affirmes.</p>
   <p>Besydes this Lanfranc whoe in the next age succeeded Alfric in the seat of canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <note place="margin">
         <hi>habetur in vlt. edit. Bibl. Patr. tom.</hi> 11.</note> in his booke against Berengarie of the sacrament of the Eucharist: som'at after the midest he speakes thus against his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie. <hi>Propulsatis iam quantum satis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum est calumnijs &amp;c.</hi> hauing sufficiētly repelled the calumniations which with cantumely of Bishop Humbert &amp; the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="516" facs="258"/> Church thou hast temerariously vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; it remaines that we expounde the faith of the holye church &amp; the opinion of this sect, &amp; that hauing expounded them we approue one &amp; reproue the other by a fewe authorities &amp; breefe reasons. For neither epistolar breuitie doth permit, nor anie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son requires that we insert prolix testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of either scriptures or arguments of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. For such as ar faithfull people but seduced, doe not pertinatiously insist in defence of their deprauation: but rather ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing heard &amp; vnderstanded reasons, desire humbly to returne to the way of truth, fewe things will suffice. But those whoe ar ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to contentions, &amp; determined to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siste in their infidelitie, would not be satisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed althou manie reasons should be proposed vnto them.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Diuinitus.</hi>
      </note> Wherfore we beleeue that the terrestriall substances which in the table of our lord ar diuinely sanctifyed by preistlie ministration, ar infallibly incomprehensibly, &amp; admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly by operation of supernaturall power conuerted in to the essence of our lordes bodie, the species or formes of the things thē selues remaining with some other qualities least the receiuers should abhorre crude &amp; cruent things: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cruda &amp; cruenta.</hi>
      </note> &amp; to the end that the credents or beleeuers might receiue more ample re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes
<pb n="517" facs="258"/> of their faith, the bodie of Christ it selfe existing neuerthelesse in heauen at the reight hand of his Father, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Illeso.</hi>
      </note> immortall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolated, intyre, incontaminated, vnhurt, soe that it may truely be affirmed that we receiue the bodie of Christ which he assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the Virgin, and yet not the same. The same truly in respect of the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of true nature and virtue: but not the same if you respect the species or formes of bread and wine; and the rest before com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended.</p>
   <p>This faith from ancient tymes did hould and now holdeth that Church which diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed throù the whole world is named Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique: whence it is that, as it is said before, our lord said in the Euangill. Receiue and eate, this is my bodie. And this is the chalis of my bloud &amp;c. In this cleare manner spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Lanfranc of the reall presence in this place. And page 346. of the same booke: he saith thus speaking of Ecclesiasticall histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Which Scriptures saith he) altho' they doe not obtaine that most excellent tower of authoritie which those doe which we cal Propheticall and Euangelicall scriptures: yet they ar sufficiēt to proue that this faith which now we haue, all faithfull people which haue gone before vs, haue had the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me from priuatiue tymes. <note place="margin">
         <hi>A primis temporibus</hi>
      </note> And page 347. the
<pb n="518" facs="259"/> same Lanfranc directing his speech to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarie addeth thus. more ower if that be true which thou beleeues and maintaines of the bodie of Christ, <note place="margin">
         <hi>vbique gentium.</hi>
      </note> it is false which the church beleeues of the same matter in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie natiō. For all those whoe reioyce to be called, and to bee Christians, doe glorie in that they receiue in this sacrament the true flesh and bloud of Christs bodie receiued from the virgin. Inquire of all such as haue knouledge of the latin tongue, and of our writings. Inquire of the Grecians, Armeniās, or of Christian people of anie nation what soeuer, &amp; they will with one mouth testifye that they haue this faith. Furthermore if the faith of the vniuersall church be false, either ther neuer was Catholique church, or she hath perished. nothing is more efficati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for the perishing of soules then a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious error. But no Catholique will graunt that the church either was not, or that she hath perished. In this plaine sorte testifyes Lanfranc of the faith of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall church in which it were madnes to imagine he did not include his owne I meane the church of England. And suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing he liued &amp; writ this the verie next age following the age in which Alfric dyed to wit in some parte of the leuēth centurie, it is more then monsterous impudencie in our
<pb n="519" facs="259"/> aduersaries to affirme that in the dayes of Alfric the denyall of the reall presence and transsubstantiation was commonely prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and beleeued in the Realme of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</p>
   <p>Further more. Pascasius Rathbertus writ a booke intituled of the bodie and bloud of our lord against the doctrine of Bertram, as is cōmōly supposed althoù I finde him not named by Pascasius: &amp; he hath alsoe an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle of the same subiect to one Frudegard, with an exposition of those wordes of the Euangelist. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 26.</note>
      <hi>Caenantibus autem illis &amp;c.</hi> In all which writings Pascasius most plainely defendeth both the reall presence and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiation, most frequently repeating and inculcating that the same bodie and bloud which Christ receiued of the Virgin Marie, and the same in which he was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, is really and truely present in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist and offered in sacrifice. I need not relate his wordes for euerie particular, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I knowe our aduersaries can not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye but that this Author is plainely for the Romanists and flat against them in those points of doctrine: onely I will rehearse so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me generall wordes of his in which he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res the faith of the vniuersall church in and before his tymes: for after testimonies of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers āciēt fathers alledged to this purpose in
<pb n="520" facs="260"/> the conclusion of the foresaid wordes of S. Mathewe thus he saith. <hi>Ecce habes amantissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me &amp;c.</hi> Behould most louing brother, thou haste in the end of this little booke the sentences of the Catholique Fathers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiously noted, by which thou maist learne that I haue not seene such things in rashnes of speech when I was a child, but that I haue proposed them by diuine authoritie, and by the authoritie of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Fathers to such as demaunded them. But now it being cleare that Since that ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the faith of all men is not one and the same, then cease I praye to beleeue with such as they bee, if as yet they can not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand that nothing is impossible to God, and lett them learne to assent vnto the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne wurdes in all things, &amp; to doubt nothing of those: For till this present no man is read to haue erred in them except those whoe erred aboute Christ himselfe: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obstanding manie doubted or haue ben ignorant of the Sacraments of soe great a Mysterie: And afterwardes the same au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in the same treatise saith thus. <hi>Qua ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleta voce, &amp;c.</hi> Which wordes being prono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unced (meaning the wordes of consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) we all with one consonant voyce say. Amen.</p>
   <p>And soe the whole Church in all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="521" facs="260"/> and languages doth pray and confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, that it is that thing which she prayeth for, wherby let him whoe will rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict this then beleeue it regarde what he doth against our lord him self, against the whole Church of Christ.</p>
   <p>Therfore it is a nefarious and detestable villanie to pray with all and not to beleeue that which truth it self doth testifye, and that which vniuersally all in euerie place doe teach. Whence it is that since he him selfe affirmes it is his bodie and his bloud, doubt ought not to be made in anie thing, altho' we see not with carnall yes that which we beleeue. We haue seene alsoe what Pope Gregorie houldeth of this, what S. Cyrill with all his fellow Bishops assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Ephesus, what Greece with them, what Egipt, and what S. Hierome him self whoe published the liues of the holye Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in latin. And therfore not obstanding some erre in this by ignorance neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>besse as yet ther is none that openly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictes that which the whole world doth beleeue &amp; confesse. Thus Pascasius a learned and venerable, and virtuous Abbat testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth the faith of the vniuersall Church in his dayes touching the reall presence, of Christ in the Eucharist. Whoe altho'
<pb n="522" facs="261"/> he was not English nor liued iuste in the tyme of Alfric, yet he liued within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe of the same age in which Alfric was Bishop of wilton and Archbishop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie that is the yeare 900. yea it may be Pascasius was yet aliue whē Alfric was Abbat and consequently when he is supposed by our aduersaries to haue writ those epistles which they produce in his name concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this matter. Soe that by this testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Pascasius a forcible argument is made that the contrarie doctrine of the reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence cauld not possible haue ben soe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick and common in anie parte of the Christian world in soe shorte a space of tyme as passed, (if anie passed) betwixt Pascasius and the writing of the homilie and Epistles attributed to Alfric if he did- euer write them.</p>
   <p>And how beit is may appeare by the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of Pascasius that ther were some in, or aboute his tyme whoe argued &amp; writ in an vnacustomed and new manner touching the doctrine of the presence of Christs bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and bloud in the Sacrament as particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly Ioannes, Scotus, Bertrame and Frude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, yet as much as I can perceiue by read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pascasius, Fulbertus, Stephanus Eduēsis, &amp; others whoe writ of this matter, the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>achers of this question did neuer absolutely
<pb n="523" facs="261"/> auerre and maintaine anie assertion directly repugnant to the true, and reall existence of Christs bodie and bloud in the Eucharist, but onely made a schoole question of it arguing the matter <hi>pro and contra:</hi> and that not determinately of the reall presence, but whether the same bodie, &amp; bloud of Christ which was borne of the Virgin Marie &amp; was crucifyed vpon the Crosse, was contained vnder the formes of bread and wine in the Sacrament, &amp; not rather some other kynd of Christs bodie and bloud, yet truely his and truely present in the Eucharist, thou in a figuratiue and tropicall manner.</p>
   <p>And that neither the named authors nor anie other in or aboute Pascasius tyme did plainely or of set purpose impugne the reall presence, it plainely appeares by his wordes aboue cited affirming that <hi>not obst<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anding some erred by ignorance, yet that none did openly contradict that which the whole world did beleeue and confesse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That which is yet further confirmed, for we read not that either Scotus, Frudegard, or Bertrame were euer condemned by the Church in their persons in anie Councell, or otherwise, which is an euidēt signe they were not obstinate in defence of their opinions, but onely deliuered their doubts by way of proposition, as at the least in Frudegard
<pb n="524" facs="262"/> in particular, doth manifestly appeare by the responsion of Pascasius to his Epistle, saying thus. <hi>Quaeris enim de re ex qua multi dubitant. You inquire of a thing of which manie doubt.</hi> And for conclusion of his owne Epistle Pascasius saith to Frude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard. <hi>Tu autem velim, relegas libellum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum de hoc opere. For I would haue you read my booke of this matter which you say you haue read in tymes past. And if you reprehend, or doubt of anie thing in it: let it not be tedious vnto you to reuiewe it.</hi> And finally towardes the end of his exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wordes of the institution of the Eucharist, he speaketh to Frude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard in this manner. <hi>Quapropter charis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sime. Wherfore most dearely beloued doe not doubt of this Mysterie which Christ the truth it self hath of him self bestowed vpon vs. For altho' he sits in heauen at the reight hand of his Father, yet doth he not disdaine to be Sacrifyced dayly by the preist in the Sacrament as a true hoaste.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now that the same Frudegardus doubt was onely whether the bodie of Christ contained in the Sacrament was the same bodie which he assumed of the Virgin Marie, is plaine by Pascasius anser saying thus almost in the beginning of his Epistle. <hi>Ergo cum ait. Wherfore when he saith
<pb n="525" facs="262"/> this is my bodie, or my flesh, or this is my bloud. I think he intimated no other flesh then his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne propter bodie which was borne of the Virgin Marie and hanged en the Crosse. Nor anie other bloud then that which was spilt vpon the Crosse, and which then was in his bodie. No man therfore which is soundly wise doth beleeue that Iesus had anie other flesh or bloud then that which was borne of the Virgin Marie and suffered vpon the Crosse.</hi> And for conclusion of his foresaid exposition he saith thus to the same Frudegard. <hi>Ad vltimum quaeso te. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stely I praye fallow not the fooleries of the tripar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite or triple bodie of Christ. Doe not mingle salt, nor hunnie in it, as some would, doe not adde nor substracte anie thing, but beleeue and vnderstand it all as Christ instituted, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for Scotus and Bertrame althou' their bookes haue hen reproued, yet it doth not fallow that their authors did directly and absolutely impugne the reall presence, or transsubstantiation, but they onely deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered their myndes in a doubtfull, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure, and ill sounding manner, for which cause and for auoyding of danger they were iustely prohibited, the onely the Councell of vercelles: the other by the <hi>purgatorie Index.</hi> Howbe it I find nothing in Bertram which with a pious interpretation might
<pb n="526" facs="263"/> not passe among the learned sorte of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
   <p>And thus much may suffice for proofe that in Pascasius tyme ther had ben no plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne denyall of the reall presence or transsub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation in the Christian world, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly some incident doubts made by some par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular persons, and that in a discussiue manner, not as obstinate maintainers of such Doctrine.</p>
   <p>And now by this same and the rest which I haue aboue produced out of the same Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casius &amp; Lanfrāc and others, the false Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop and Primate of Ireland is conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of an apparent falsitie, for that in the 79. page of his anser to a Iesuits chalenge, he had the face to affirme that til the dayes of Lanfranc this question of the reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence continued still in debate: and that it was as free for anie man to followe the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Bertram (he calles him Ratran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus) or Ioannes Scotus, as that of Pasca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius. This audatious affirmation of vsher I say is clearly condemned of falsitie by the same Pascasius whome he citeth, and whoe as I haue alledged, testifyes that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the reall presence in his tyme was not as yet contradicted by anie (except tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se whoe denye Christ) but beleeued and professed by the whole world, althou some, saith
<pb n="527" facs="263"/> he did erre in the same by ignorance. And this onely by way of diuertion, breefly to signifye to the reader how common a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise it is euen among the most famous of our aduersaries to maintaine their doctrine by lyes and false dealing of which I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by a breefe vewe I tooke of some parte of his worke an industrious reader may discouer no smale stoare in the great primate doctor Vsher, as well as his fellowes.</p>
   <p>But now to returne to my direct pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, I yet more efficatiously confirme that which I haue said of Alfric by the chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologie of our English historians. <note place="margin">
         <hi>In his cata. wulstan dunst.</hi>
      </note> For first according to the computation of Bishop Godwin ther passed onely some six yeares betwixt the decease of wlstā in the Archibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoprie of yorke, &amp; the promotiō of S. Dū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stan to the seat of Canterburie in which space, as likewise in the tyme of wulstan himself it is quite incredible that ther was anie doctrine cōtrarie to the reall ptesence cōmōly toucght in England, since S. Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stan at the day and houre of his death expressely professed the same as out of our owne histories I haue alreadie showed by the relation of Harpesfeld.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Vid. Osbor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in vita dunst.</hi>
      </note>
   </p>
   <p>Besides this it is certaine ther were but onely twoe wulstans Archbishops of yorke as appeareth by Godwins Catalogue: the
<pb n="528" facs="264"/> one as he reporteth deceased the yeare 955. which was at the least fortie yeares before Alfric possessed the seat of Canterburie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the account of the same catalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue. The other wulstan as the same Goduin recounteth began not his seat at yorke till the yeares 1003. which was more then 50. yeares after the death of the first wulstan. now this conographie being thus establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed euen by one of our aduersaries: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Safe way. sect.</hi> 9. <hi>§.</hi> 2.</note> I ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue in this manner against knight Humbrey affirming that the homilie and Epistles which he alledgeth were translated by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fric, and appointed to be read to the people in his dayes, my argument is this.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>If this supposed homilie, and Epistles were euer translated, written, or published by Alfric, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was when he was. Abbat, or Archbishop. But neither of these is true.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Therfore it is not true that the homilie and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles were euer translated or published by Alfric.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Minor which onely hath need of prose I conuince by the testimonie of my aduersarie, whoe affirmes the translation and publication of the freifaid writings to haue ben a boute the yare 996. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Sir Humf. page</hi> 92.</note> and directed to wulstan Archbishop or yorke and wulf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stius Bishop of sherborne by Alfric Abbat, I meane the Epistles. And yet at this tyme
<pb n="529" facs="264"/> neither was Alfric Abbat but Archbishop of Canterburie, neither was either of the two wulstans Archbishop of yorke at that tyme. the one being dead 40. yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and the other not inuested in that dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie vntill the yeare 1003. as Godwin doth witnesse. soe that by this argument it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestly appeares that the knights relation touching this matter of the publishing of the homilie and Epistles alledged by him- against the reall presence and transsub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation is contradictious &amp; voyde of truth.</p>
   <p>More ouer I finde in our English histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that aboute the yeare 950. which was some fortie and od yeares before Alfric was preferred to be Archbishop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Vid. Harps</hi>
      </note> in the tyme of Odo Archbishop of the same seat, ther were some conuented before him whoe were in an erroreous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion aboute the presence of Christs bodie in the Eucharist, but the maintainers of it (how soeuer Fox doth fable) neither were manie, nor did it long continue, but was miraculously at an instant exstinguished. For the pious &amp; zealous pastor Odo much lamenting the illusion of those miserable people, prayed God with teares in masse, that his diuine maiestie would be pleased by his infinit power manifestely to shewe
<pb n="530" facs="265"/> some thing by which both the truth of the reall presence might appeare, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie error might be confounded, when so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely at his seruants petition God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie turned the consecrated bread in to visible flesh, and the wine in to visible bloud. Which wonderous spectacle being seene, the incredulous persons presently complained of their owne perfidie and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe, and all the rest of their dayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued their faith intire and sounde: now this hauing happened aboute the same tyme at which that wulstan was Archbishop of yorke whoe hauing ben in that place some yeares: deceased the yeare 955. as Godwin relateth, it clearely appeares incredible that Alfric then Abbat should direct anie doctrine repugnant to the reall presence to wolstan Archbishop of yorke, and to vlsine, vlsius, or wulfstius Bishop of sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourne, as our aduersaries affirme, since that Odo Archbishop of Canterburie and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of England, at the verie same tyme, as of out of histories I haue rehearsed, did by the power of God operate soe strange a miracle in confirmation of the same, and confutation of the contrarie error.</p>
   <p>More then this, Vlsin or vlsius whome the knight calles wulfstius (of which name neuerthelesse I finde none in Malesburies
<pb n="531" facs="265"/> Catalogue of the Bishops of Sherbourne) could not possible haue anie Epistle dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted unto him by Alfric while he was Abbat of Malesburie or Abington, as Sir Humfrey and the rest of these tryfelers alledge, for that while Vlsine, or wulfstius was Bishop of Sherbourne which was but onely fiue yea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, as our histories doe testifye, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Hrapsfeld. saec.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> being Abbat onely of westminister in the dayes of S. Dunstan and by his procurement, whose death happened the yeare .988. as Stowe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates: Alfric was no more Abbat but Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop of wilton, and consequently he could not as Abbat write to Vlsine, Vlsius, or wulf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stius Bishop of Sherbourne, but if he had writ anie such letters as our aduersaries at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute vnto him, to that Bishop, he should haue styled him selfe not Abbat, but Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop as in deed he was all the tyme yea and some yeares before the foresaid wulfstius was by king Ethelred preferred to the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scopall seat of Sherbourne.</p>
   <p>But that which doth strik this quite dead, is that (ther hauing ben but onely twoe wolstans Archbishops of yorke) the first wolstan dyed before euer Alfric was Abbat, to wit the yeare of our Lord 955. wher as Ingulphus in Edgar relates Alfric to haue ben created Abbat onely aboute the yeare 970. at the soonest, soe that he
<pb n="532" facs="266"/> could not possible write anie Epistles to the first wolstan while he was Abbat as our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellists pretend, bebause this wolstan was departed out of this life before Alfrics tyme of being Abbat. And as for the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond wolstan it is well knowne and testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by Godwin that he was not Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of yorke before the yeare 1003. At which tyme Alfric was not Abbat but Archbishop of Canterburie as our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries them selues refuse not to graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.</p>
   <p>And soe this computation and collation of tymes vtterly destroyes the machination of our abuersaries in attrituting the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said writings to Abbat Alfric.</p>
   <p>And touching Vlsius or Vlsinus I adde to this that Alfric was consecrated Byshop of wilton in the yeare 985. or ther aboutes so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me fourteeme yeares after the coronation of Ethelred. <note place="margin">
         <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de. Pont Aug. pag.</hi> 203.</note> And he sate 11. yeares in that place as Malerburie relates. But now Vlsine as it appeares by a breef of Iohn the 15. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of this name touching the peace he composed betwixt king Ethelred and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard marques of Normandie, was Byshop of Sherbourne aboute the yeare 991. of which yeare the Popes letter carieth date, in which althou the Pope doth not call him Vlsine, but Edelsine, yet both by the tyme
<pb n="533" facs="266"/> and place of his seat, as alsoe for that ther is noe other in the Catalogue of the Bishops of Sherbourne yeare the after in which I finde related by Ingulpsus, Alfrics was Abbat of malesburie which resembleth that name; it is conuinced that this is the same man which the kinght calleth wulfstius, and to whome he affirmes one of Abbat Alfrics E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles to haue ben directed. which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shelesse is concluded to be false in regard that at that tyme of the date of the Popes Epistole to wit the yeare 991. Alfric was not Abbat but Bishop, this hauing happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned but fiue yeres before that Alfric then Bishop of wilton, was assumpted to the Arcgbishoprie of Canterburie which was the yeare 996. as all agreeably testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye.</p>
   <p>Now if our aduersaries should say that this Vlsius, Vlsine, or Edelsine is not that Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop of Sherbourne to whome they meane that Alfric writ his Epistle, but an other long before him called wulfstius.</p>
   <p>To this I replye, first that I finde not this name of wulfstius in anie author or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of the Bishops of Sherbourne, and soe I suspect it is a tricke of knight Hūfrey whoe as it seemes first inuēted the name, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Westminst. an</hi> 940.</note> sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing I finde it not in anie other either freī<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de or for the name of anie Bishop of that seat. Secondly.</p>
   <pb n="534" facs="267"/>
   <p>It is true histories make mention of one Vlsius Bishop of that seat and successor to Alfred, but neither the name agrees to knight Humfreyes feigned wulfstius, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their was he then in the world when Alfric was Abbat, but according to the catalogue annexed to Ingulphus, deceased the yeare 966. For whose successor the same catalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue putteth Alfwoldus. wheres yet it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res by the testimonie of Ingulphus that Alfric was not Abbat till either in, or after the yeare 970. by which it is cleare he could not write to this vlsius or wulfstius as Abbat, in respect he was dead some yeares before Alfric was preferred to that place by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointement of king Edgar. and soe this euasion is intercepted by the way and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares to be frustrate and false.</p>
   <p>Further more according to Bishop Vshers chronologie affirming that Alfric writ his homilie aboute 605. yeares a goe Alfric should haue writ the same the yeare 1026. or ther aboutes, deriuing the accoūte frō the tyme of Vshers publicatiō of his booke; for soe by putting fiue or six yeares which I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose hath passed since the tyme of Vshers writing, to the 605. yeares which he assig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for the tyme in which Alfric writ, &amp; ioining to all this 1026 or 7. the whole nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber amountes iust to 1632. which is the
<pb n="535" facs="267"/> yeare we now liue in. But this implyes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibilitie in regarde it is receiued by both parties that Alfric dyed the yeare 1006. that is some 20. yeares before 1026. which Vsher assignes for the yeare of Alfric's wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the homilie by which it appeares that Primate Vsher is a most prime yea and a most vnmyndefull lyer in attributing this writing to Abbat Alfric. And concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the writing of Alfrics twoe supposed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistles, if Vsher meanes they were writ and directed to wulfsine and wulstane at this sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me tyme, he is likewise manifestly conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of falsitie, for that at the tyme assigned by him, ther was no vlsius, vlsine or wulfsine (as he nameth him) Bishop of sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourne in the world to whome Alfric could haue directed anie writings, the last of that name being dead the age before as I haue shewed, as alsoe the first wulstan Arcbishop of yorke. True it is the second wulstan of yorke was then a liue to wit vnto the yeare 1023. but then Alfric being dead Archbishop of Canterburie (as I haue showed by God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wins Catalogue) almost 20. yeares before, the supposed direction of Epistles vnto him is euen in that respect concluded for repugnant and impossible with a plaine dissent of the author from him self as affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the publication of these writings to
<pb n="526" facs="268"/> haue happened in the dayes of Alfric, &amp; yet onely aboute 605. yeares agoe.</p>
   <p>More ouer these relators agrees in their Chronographie like dogges and cattes, the partes of which hange togither as theeues hang vpon the gallowes neuer a one ioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to an other. For as I haue said, Vsher affirmes Alfric Abbat's Saxon homilie to haue ben writen by him aboute 605. yeares which according to true computation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the tyme in which Vsher writ this, comes to fall about the yeare 1020. <note place="margin">
         <hi>In the</hi> 2. <hi>§. of the</hi> 9. <hi>sect of his safe way.</hi>
      </note> But Sir Humfrey speaking of the same homilie, saith it was publikely appointed to be read to the people on Easter day aboute the yeare 996. at which tyme Alfric was not Abbat but Arcbishop of Canterburie, as euen our aduersaries them selues doe relate: and soe these twoe brothers in Christ pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed not like brothers but repugne plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one to an other in their accountes: the knight affirming the foresaid homilie to haue ben published &amp; read some 24. yeares before Vsher alledgeth, it to haue ben writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Besydes this, Alfric dyed Arcbishop of Canterburie the yeare 1006. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Godwin in Alfric p.</hi> 65.</note> according to Godwins Catalogue. How then could he possible write his homilie aboute 605. yeares agoe as Vsher tells vs? that is the yeare of our lord 1020. as I haue declared: except Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fric
<pb n="527" facs="268"/> did miraculously rise againe to broache the new English faith of the Eucharist, which our aduersaries will needs defende for ancient thou' it cost them as deare as the forgeing of a false historie.</p>
   <p>More ouer the publisher of the same wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings I meane the homilie and Epistles printed at London 1623. vnder the name of Alfric, telles vs, he writ them 700. yeares agoe in king Edga'rs tyme which falles ium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe with the yeare of Christ 923. if we coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te from the tyme of the foresaid publicatiō of them. And yet as both Malesburie, Stowe, &amp; the rest of our historians testifye, Edgar was not created king vntill the yeare of our Souiour 959. soe that here is an apparent blurre in this wise Conographer's compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation inuolueing both an impossibilitie in it self, and a contradiction to the rest of his companions in this busines, whoe as I haue declared attribute them to Alfric in the tyme of Ethelred aboute some 600. yeares since, others some yeares befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</p>
   <p>Lastely Fox in his Acts and monuments althou' he doth not dissent from his follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes (excepting the fore said late publisser) in his assignation of the tyme in which the homilie imputed to Alfric, is by them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to haue ben proposed for the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="538" facs="269"/> of the people in England, viz. abou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te the yeare 996: neuerthelesse in two se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall respects he proceedes most deceite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and quite contrarie to common ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie, and reason. First for that he feigneth and prefixeth a title against the reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence and transsubstantiation to the said homilie; secondly because in his rehearsall of the tenor of the same, he leueth our the relation of two most manifest and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple miracles for the proofe of both those points of the Catholique faith in it alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the author, which craftie and vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine trickes of Fox (with which and manie others of like nature he farceth his huge volumes) as it appeares seemed soe shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that his successor the late diuulger of the same homilie was ashamed to imitate him: yea and not obstanding he was bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde vnder paine of losse of the labor of his translation and publication of that worke which otherwile he well considered would haue ben in vaine, to taxe the said miracles of fiction (as he did in a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall note) yet was he not soe impudent nor frontlesse as to raze thē quite out of the copie. <note place="margin">
         <hi>inexcusable deceipt in Fox.</hi>
      </note> And how be it I cā not denye but ther is a great difference belweene these twoe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, yet must they giue me licence to tell
<pb n="539" facs="269"/> them that neither of them both is cleare of ill proceeding, the one being guiltie of plaine imposture, the other of plaine teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. For supposing they would venture to make vse of the homilie for the aduantage of their denyall of the reall presence and transsubstantiation, for all that, they ought to haue taken it as they founde it for better or for worse, &amp; not goe a boute to pick out what they finde for their purpose, and cast a may the rest, like such vnreasonable cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers as will needes buye flesh without bones. And in deed those twoe, bones that is those twoe most patēt &amp; cleare miracles by which both the reall presēce of the bodie &amp; bloud of Christ in the Eucharist ar manifestly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrated against the new doctrine of these our tymes, were too harde for old Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Foxs teeth to chewe, or for his sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make to disgeast, therfore doubtlesse he left them out both in his saxon and English transsumpte. But these sycophants as they deale with the scriptures them selues, soe they deale with ancient authorities &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies. <note place="margin">
         <hi>lib. de bono person. c.</hi> 11.</note>
      <hi>Suo quidem priuilegione dicam sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legio vtquod volunt accipiant, quod nolunt reijci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant.</hi> as S. Augustin said of the Manichies.</p>
   <p>Againe concerning the Epistles attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Alfric ther is yet more discorde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our aduersaries. For the publisher of
<pb n="540" facs="270"/> them and the homilie aboue mentioned in his preface vnto them affirmes ther were certaines lines rare zout of a booke extant in the librarie of worceter which lines, saith he, which contained the cheefe point of cōtrouersie (that is as he supposeth against the reall presence and transsubstantiation) were taken out of twoe Epistles of Alfric written by him as well in the Saxon tongue as in the latin. But Doctor Iames and Sir Humfrey tell vs that the foresaid passage was razed in a latin Epistle ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuscript of Bennitts Colledge in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brige yet there to be seene. And wheras the author of the publication saith that the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes razed ar to be restored by twoe other Epistles of the same Alfric in latin extant in the librarie of Exceter, contrarily D. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes tolleth vs they ar to be restored not by anie latin copies, but by certaine Saxon copies of the same Epistles which he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to haue ben in the publike librarie of Oxon when he writ his booke which was the yeare 1611. Besydes this the same Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes out of Fox saith the Epistle which he affirmes to haue ben thus mangled and torne was to wulfstan Archbishop of yorke and hath for title, <hi>de consuetudine Monacho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> wheras yet the foresaid publisher of Alfrics new founde writings, intileth that
<pb n="541" facs="270"/> Epistle of Alfric <hi>de consuetudine monachorum</hi> of the order or manner of monkes, <hi>Egne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shemensibus fratribus,</hi> to the fryres or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Egnesham. Which iarres I confesse I am soe vnable to compose that I can not but vehemently suspect these mens repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to be false and counterfet. Especially considering that Iames affirmes the latin Epistle soe razed as they reporte, to haue ben directed by Alfric to that wulstan whoe was Archbishop of yorke aboute the yeare 954. wher as yet the author of the pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet in which these writings ar contained, in his prefate to the same, saith that this Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fric to whome he attributes them was equall to Alfric Archbishop of Canterburie which he alsoe affirmes to haue ben in that seat six yeares before that wulstan to whome Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fric's Epistle was writen, was Archbishop of yoke: soe that the one reportes this Epistle to haue ben wriren to the first wulstan and the other to the second not obstanding all histories and Cathologues of Bishops (among which is Godwins) doe testifye soe long a space of tyme to haue passed betweixt their standings, as it is from the yeare 955. and 1003. soe that these twoe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators drawe back warde and fore ward like twoe ill match asses.</p>
   <p>More ouer the foresaid publisher will
<pb n="542" facs="271"/> needs haue Alfric the supposed author the homilie and epistles to haue ben a distinct man from that Alfric whoe was Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Canterburie wheras neuershelesse Iohn Leland whoe professedly writ of the writers of England relating the seuerall workes of Alfric the Archbishop of Canterburie maketh noe mention of anie other writers of that name but of him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, neither doth he put anie epistle among his writings but onely one intituled, <hi>de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suetudine Monachorum,</hi> of the māner or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of monkes, which subiect how farre it disagreth frō the presence of Christs bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in the Eucharist, and transsubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I leaue to the iudgement of the reader to consider.</p>
   <p>In fine to conclude my whole discourse touching this matter I say first, that if it were true as our aduersaries pretend that in the foresaid writings ther weere anie thing contained contrarie to the reall presence and transsubstantiation, yet haue I cōuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by insoluable reasons that neither Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fric could be the author of them, neither could anie such doctrine haue ben publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maintained in the Church of England in or aboute his dayes. But what soeuer do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was then published and tought in our countrie was canformable in all points with
<pb n="543" facs="271"/> the doctrine and faith then professed in the Church of Rome with which the English Church and her Pastors had corresponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and subordination as I haue manifestly declared. Secondly Althou I am not able to iudge determinately whoe might be author of those writings because I haue noe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to come to the view of them otherwise then in that patched and mangled manner in which they are published by our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries: neuerthelesse I persuade my selfe they were writ by some Romane catholique author, soe that taken in their innocencie and prime puritie and piously interpreted they containe no vnsounde or erroneous doctrine, but rather expresse testimonie and proofes of diuers points controuersed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the nouellists of these our tymes and catholike Romanists. As appeareth in the mention they make of <hi>masse, miracles, the signe of the Crosse,</hi> and other particulars which I haue noted in my censure.</p>
   <p>Thirdly. the iudicious reader may easily persuade him self that supposing these wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings according to the relation of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries, haue remained in publike places and libraries for the space of aboue 600. yeares, if they had cōtained anie doctrine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnāt to that faith of the Eucharist which I haue historically demonstrated aboue to
<pb n="544" facs="272"/> haue ben professed in our countrie of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland euer since, and before, that tyme: its more then morally euident they would haue receiued long a fore this tyme repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension, or censure according to their desert.</p>
   <p>Finally. Supposing it were true that the foresaid writings did in deed containe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine contrarie to the reall presence, and transsubstantiation as they ar beleeued and defended by the professors of the Roman Religion wheras yet they doe not soe, but onely exclude the carnal, palpaple or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pharnaitical presence of Christ in the Eucharist, and instruct the people in the inuisible presence of his bodie, and bloude in the Sacrament in an obuius and easie māner: yet in reasō ought not anie iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Catholique to alter his faith of the same for anie argument which can be dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne or deduced from such testimonie as is voyde of other credit then is to be giuen to aduersaries in fauor of their owne cause which is iust none at all, especially they being no other then these whoe not onely in this particular, but alsoe in other matters of controuersie haue vsed much partialitie, &amp; deceipt as in an other place I haue demonstrated out of their seuerall
<pb n="545" facs="272"/> workes. And in particular the publisher of the same pamphlet in which the homilie &amp; Epistles of which I heare treate, are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, besides diuers vntruthes which he vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth as well touching the author and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of his writing, as alsoe his titles and marginall notes, and likewise in that he couningly and couseningly publisheth in the same volume a treatise of the ould, and new testament in the name of Alfric as if it included a different canon of scripture to that which is now vsed in the Roman Church, and agreeable to their now En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Bible: which is yet most apparently false for that (as I remēber) it putteth in the number and order of the Canonicall boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes Ecclesiasticus, Sapience, Tobie, Iudith and the Machabeis, which yet our aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries reiect for Apocryphal: As alsoe in that more ouer the same Pampheter addeth a testimonie to shewe that in tymes past the lords prayer, the creed and the ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements were extant and vsed in the vulgar tongue; a worke most imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently performed by him, and as it seemes onely or cheefely to enlarge the bulke and price of his pamphlet: it being certaine that the Romanists neuer neither held that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnlawfull, or at this present prohibit the
<pb n="546" facs="273"/> vse of the vulgar language for the ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements and priuate prayer of the common people but rather the contrarie as both their Catechismes and their daylie practise most plainely witnesse.</p>
   <p>By all which particulars and the rest of this my aduertissement it is euidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent that the glorious which the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellists of our countrie make by their publication of the homilie epistles and o- writings in the name of Alfric, be no other then certaine prestigious impostures to persuade the simple sorte of people by the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se false florishes, that their denyall of the reall presence of the bodie and bloud of Christ in the Eucharist, and transsubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not quite voyde of antiquitie, but hath ben preached and professed in our countrie before the dayes of luther. And now let this suffice to repulse this fictitious and deceitefull calumniation of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries touching these putatiue wrings of Alfric by the publication of which and the like counterfeit wares they pick simple peoples purses whoe take all for as true as gaspell that is put in print by anie of their owne brothers.</p>
   <p>The second aduertissement I giue to the reader is that wheras the kinght page 205. of his fafe wais cites Agobard for a denyer of
<pb n="547" facs="273"/> honor of image in his booke of that sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect: <note place="margin">
         <hi>Agobardus Episc. Lugdun. li. de pict. &amp; imag.</hi>
      </note> I haue dilgently perused the same, and finde that in deed this author speaketh mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re harshely of this matter then anie other catholique writer of these dayes how be it this was the age in which images had their greatest enimies. Neuerthelesse it is most certaine this author onely confutes the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of diuine honor and the like, vnto images, as is sacrifice, or confidence in them or prayer vnto them: reprehending the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of some particular persons whoe super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitiousely adored them, for soe he discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth a boute the end of his booke saying.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>But none of the ancient Catholiques did euer thinke them to be worshiped or adored: yet now the error by increase is become soe perspicuous that it is neare, or like to the heresie of the Antropomorphits to adore figments and to put hope in them, and that by reason of this error faith being remoued from the harte, all our confidence be placed in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible things.</hi> And a little after. <hi>Soe alsoe if we see penned or fethered Angels painted, the Apostles preaching, martyres suffering torments, we must not expect anie helpe from the pictures which we behould, because they can neither doe good nor ill: rightly therfore</hi> (these are the wordes cited by the kinght) <hi>to euacuate such superstition it was defined by orthodox Fathers that pictures should not be made in churches least that which
<pb n="548" facs="274"/> si worshiped and adored be painted in the walles</hi> which wordes being not his owne but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged out of a fragment of the Prouinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all councell of Eliberis in Spaine and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ioyned them imediately to his owne in which he onely treates of diuine honor as not due to images, it is cleare and euident he intendes to proue nothing else by their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie then that which he there proposeth. To omit that this passage of the Eliberitan coūcell was deliuered in a sense much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from this in which Agobardus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strueth it, as I haue conuinced in others pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and occasions.</p>
   <p>And that this author intendes to teache nothing else, but onely that images must not be honored with worship due to God, the seuerall testimonies which he largely produceth out of S. Augustin, S. Hierome, &amp; other ancient writers doe manifestly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate, not one of which can be taken (if they be truely vnderstanded) in anie other sense, as clearely may appeare to the diligent reader of their wordes, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressely exclude onely honor of Sacrifice, prayers directed vnto the images them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, or religion proper to God onely, in the worship of saincts, and their pictures: and alsoe Agobardus him self vppō occasiō of the places which he citeth doth auerre,
<pb n="549" facs="274"/> plainely declaring that he graunteth some sorte of honor to images wher thus he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Let vs behould the picture as a picture desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of life, sense, and reason: let the eye be fed with this vision, but let the mynde reuerence God whoe both giues to his saints a crowne of victorie, and to vs the assistance of their intercession.</hi> And the like he affirmes of honor of saincts a little aboue in this same page. Wher althou' he iustely reserueth the supreame worship of Sacrifice to God a lone, yet he expressely grauntes an other inferior honor to Saints and Angels saying. <hi>Adoretur, colatur, venere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur a fidelibus Deus, &amp;c. Let God be adored, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shiped,</hi> or serued, <hi>and reuerenced by faithfull people, let Sacrifice be offered to him a lone, either in the mysterie of his bodie and bloud, or in the Sacrifice of a contrite and humble harte, let Angels or holye men be loued, honored, with charitie, not with seruitude, let not Christs bodie be offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</hi> And according to this sense Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardus speakes throu' his whole booke, particularly in his second leafe wher he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth certaine idolaters whoe imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a certaine sanctitie to reside in images saying. <hi>In which nature these alsoe whoe call images holye, are founde not onely Sacrilegious for that they giue diuine worship to the workes of their handes, but alsoe foolish in attributing san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie
<pb n="550" facs="275"/> to images which haue no life or soule.</hi> By all which wordes it is cleare that Agobarde onely condemnes the exhibition of such honor to saincts, or images as is due to God a lone. Which doctrine is soe farre from being anie way contrarie to the honor of images practised in the Roman Church that it doth rather exactely agree with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Councell of Trent in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, which in the 25. Session defines that, <hi>due honor is to be giuen to images not because it should be beleeued that ther is anie diuinitie or vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in them for which they ar to be worshiped, or that anie thing should be craued of them, or that confidence or hope should be put in thē, as in tymes past the Gentiles did, whoe placed their hope in Idols, but because the honor which is exhibited vnto them is referred to the prototypes or persons which they represent. soe that by the images which we salute or kisse, and before which we vncouer our head, and prostrate our selues, we adore and reuerence Christ, and the saints whose representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or similetudes they beare.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>True it is, I haue noted in reading his booke that Agobard purposely refuseth to vse these wordes <hi>adorare, colere, adore,</hi> or <hi>ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue:</hi> yet I plainely gather by his whole dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, he doth not soe to signifye ther by that images ar not to be vsed with anie ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor at all, as I haue alreadie declared by his
<pb n="551" facs="275"/> owne text: but onely declineth the vse of those wordes in regarde he takes them in a strict sense, as they signifie religion or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor proper to God him self, and not due to anie creature: and perhaps alsoe becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se at that tyme as it may seeme by his nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and some others of that age, the worde adoration was offensiue euen to some whoe otherwise were both Catholique, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men: to say nothing of the common people some of whome peraduentute out of ignorance, and weakenes of iudgement, euen at this day make danger to vse it, and scruple to heare it: yet neither the one nor the other omitting to honore images ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the approbation, and practise of the Church. Wheras yet if it be taken in the sense in which the Roman Church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the definition of the 7. Synod and custome of diuines, accepteth it, that is for a kynde of inferior honor distinct from proper latrie and religion, and as (euen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the vse of scriptures) it signifyes worship common alsoe to creatures, then doth it include no manner of scandall or offense at all. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cumque introisset in conspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu Regis. &amp; adoras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set eum pro nus in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram &amp;c.</hi> 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 1. 24.</note>
   </p>
   <p>And now in that rigorous meaning Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard takes the worde adoratiō when alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geing the same wordes of the Eliberitan Councell which Sir Humfrey here resear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth,
<pb n="552" facs="276"/> he intendeth onely to proue that ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ar not to be adored or serued: in which passage he proueth nothing against the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholique honor of images, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly disputeth either against some reliquies of the Antropomorphitan heresie: or against some other superstitious, and idolatrous adorers of Saints &amp; images of those dayes, from both which kyndes of errors as Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardus him self was, soe alsoe the Roman Church with her cheefe Pastors and rulers (to which he then was a subordinate mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and prelate as other of his workes doe witnesse) were free and innocent as likewi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se now they be in this our present age not obstanding the frequent calumniations of our moderne sectaries to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
   <p>Finally I adde to this that in the verie conclusion, and last period of his booke, Agobard expressely teacheth that genufle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is to be made to the name of Iesus, which yet our Puritan aduersaries out of their singular puritie, or rather pure sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitie, reiect as idolatrous, not obstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by Gods commaundement, not onely men but deuils alsoe ar enioyned, and compelled to bowe their knees at the soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of that soueraine name. And surely he who holdes this for lawfull, as Agobardus
<pb n="553" facs="276"/> doth, must for the same reasons hold it li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewise lawfull to honor the images of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, supposing that the name of Iesus being to be honored onely for the representation it hath of him, much more lawfully may his image be soe honored in regarde it doth more permanently and ferfectly represent him then doth his name which consists in carracters, and a transitorie sounde of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Besides this, Agobardus as the verie first wordes of his booke doe declare, doth not directly and professedly treate in it of the honor and vse of images as it is practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the church, but of the sense of the first commaundement, in which he includes the prohibition of the adoration of images deliuered by God in the old Testament as a parte of the same, onely intending to proue in his whole worke that by virtue of this precept, diuine honor is not to be tendered to anie creature but to God alone, &amp; not to either idoles or images.</p>
   <p>And Therfore in his laste page the same Agobardus expressely speaketh of honor proper to God him self, applying to his purpose the wordes of Isaias <hi>honorem meum alteri non dabo.</hi> by all which it is most cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apparent that what soeuer Agobarde see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to vtter against the adoration of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, is onely spoken against such as attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="554" facs="277"/> ouer much honor vnto them worship thē in an idolatrous, or superstitious fashion contrarie to the tradition of Fathers and practise of the Catholique Church as his wordes quoted in my margen sufficiently declare.<note place="margin">
         <hi>haec est sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cera religio hic mos Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholicus haec antiqua pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum tradi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio &amp;c. Agobardus fol. vlt. post authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Patr. citatus</hi>
      </note> And soe I leaue him as no enimie to the Catholique cause, nor anie fauorer of the disalawers of the same in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular point, how be it the ambiguitie of his speech may giue occasion of error to igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or ill affected readers.</p>
   <p>To this I ioyne my responsion to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wordes cyted by our aduersarie in the same place &amp; out of the same booke of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gobardus as I suppose, for he ioynes them to the rest of those which ther he had. to wit these which followe. <hi>Ther is nos example in all the scriptures, or Fathers for adoration of images. They ought to be taken for an ornament to please the sight, not to instruct the people.</hi> To which I answer <hi>in primis,</hi> touching the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer parte of the sentence, Agobardus hath no such expresse wordes as those; he onely saying thus: <hi>the ancients alsoe had the images of saint painted, or graued: but for rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance not to worship them:</hi> which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ar soma't different from those other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearsed by sir Hum. neuerthelesse because they seeme to include a denyal of honor of images, I responde secondly. Agobard ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes
<pb n="555" facs="277"/> the wordes <hi>colere &amp; adorare</hi> which ther he vseth, in the same sēse in which he vseth them in the rest of his booke; that is for diuine honor as I haue aboue declared by seueral passages of the same. According to which acception his wordes ar verie true, nor anie way repugnant to the doctrine of the Roman Church either in those dayes, or at this present tyme, which as in all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages, soe in this in which we liue doth zealously detest, and abhorre as plainely idolatrous all diuine adoration of creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, tho' neuer so eminent either in nature, or grace. Thirdly to the latter parte of the same sentence, I say confidently, I am sure ther ar no such wordes in Agobardes boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke euen as it is published and printed at Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris by Papyrius Masson him selfe, out of whose Bibliotheke be it good, or bad, sir Humfrey produceth it: soe that I doe not vnderstand this iugling for other then plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne forgerie, or falsification.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, those laste wordes. <hi>They</hi> (images) <hi>ought to be taken for an ornament to please the sight, not to instruct the people:</hi> ar iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste contrarie to the doctrine of S. Gregorie teaching expressely that pictures ar the bookes of the illiterate, and simple people. Which doctrine of S. Gregorie, Agobarde was neither soe ignorant as not to knowe
<pb n="556" facs="278"/> it, nor yet soe impudent as to denye it.</p>
   <p>Fiftly, those same wordes manifestly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sagree to the rest of Agobardes owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as his wordes by me related suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently declare, partucularly those: <hi>Habue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt namque &amp; antequi magiues sanctorum ad recordandum &amp;c.</hi> Lastely, Sir Humfrey must knowe that Papyrius Masson is registred by the authors of our expurgatore Index, and consequently, he is no current Romanist, and much lesse is he anie of our best learned men as neither was Agobardus which ar yet those whome he professeth in the title of his booke to alledge against vs.</p>
   <p>And soe by this, Agobarde is absolutely cleared from all imputation of iconoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie or error against images, and the obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our aduersarie conuinced to be voyde of force.</p>
   <p>Furthermore touching that which the knight alledgeth out of Hincmar cōcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the decree of the coūcell of Frācfort a boute images, he deliuered it onely as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator, &amp; being young in yeares &amp; vnexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced he mistooke the definitiō of the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resaid synod for the schismaticall determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of a priuate Cōuenticle, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ben in the same place &amp; at the same ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, or presētly after the dissolution of the councell, he might easily take the one for
<pb n="557" facs="278"/> the other. In which historicall passage, as some authors opinate, by the credit he gaue to the supposed Carolin bookes, he both er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himselfe, &amp; gaue occasiō of error to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whoe relying vpō his reporte haue put the same in their generall histories publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed since his tyme: yet this being onely a priuate error of fact and that vncertaine it was without anie preiudice to the faith and practise of Catholique Church</p>
   <p>Besides it appeares euidently by an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle of 55. chapters which the same Hinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare Archbishop of Rhemes writ to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie Hincmare Bishop of laon, he was a verie pious &amp; Cotholi{que} prelate &amp; an acko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wledger of the Popes supremacie ouer the rest of the Christiā Churches Greek &amp; Latin, for soe he speakes in Hic fift chapter of that worke. <hi>qui in illius</hi> (Sedis Apostolicae) <hi>primata beatus Petrus cunctorū oucra portat, cuius princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patus authoritate mediator Dei &amp; hominum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Christus Iesus sedem Romanam super omnes sedos sublimauit, Alexandrinam decorauit, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinam confirmauit</hi> &amp;c. wherfore it is improbable that Hnicmare who speaketh soe honorably of the Romā Church, should at the same tyme haue vttered anie do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine soe contrarie to the then receiued practise of the same, as is contained in those wordes viz. Images ar to be taken for an
<pb n="558" facs="279"/> ornament to please the sight not to instruct the people.</p>
   <p>To this I adde for confirmation of my anser, it is not credible to imagine that ther hauing passed diuers letters betwixt Pope Adrian (in whose tyme due honor of images was defined against the opposers of it) and other Popes of those tymes, and this Hincmare, for composing the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie betweene him and Bishop Hincmare of Laon, as alsoe aboute other matters; it is not credible I say those Popes should not once haue reprehended and condemned him for this position, if truely he had ben a maintainer of it Besides the Ecclesiasticall histories doe testifye that aboute the same tyme, this same Hincmar at the persuasion of Pope Nicolas confuted the criminations of the Grecians against the Roman Church, of whome he would neuer haue made choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se for such a busines, if he had ben either knowne or suspected to haue defended anie doctrine repugnant to the vse and honor of images established in the 7. Synod and then commonly practised in the Christian world.</p>
   <p>And thus we see that nothing produced by our aduersarie out of this author repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gneth to the doctrine of that moderate ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of images which hath ben vniuersally
<pb n="559" facs="279"/> professed in the Roman Church both in the tyme of Agobarde and in this present age.</p>
   <p>My third aduertissement is that the knight in the 289. page of his safe way iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously accuseth Charon for a blasphemer of scriptures alledgeing him to affirme they ar imperfect, obscure, doubtfull, ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, perplexed. And yet I finde that this author in his thrid booke <hi>de tribus veritati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> (which is the same our aduersarie cites althou' not in the same language) page 97. 98. and the rest imediately following in his french edition (for I could not haue him in latin) expressely cleares him selfe and Roman church of that foule and odious calumniation feigned by Plessis in their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace. Charons wordes ar these. <hi>Venons an particularitez qu'ils nous font dire, encore qu'ils les proposent mal, &amp; autrement que nous ne le disons, pour nous rendre odieux: premierement que nous le disons l'escriture este imperfecte: an contraire nous la croyons, confessons &amp; preschons, perfecte, pleine, entiere, tres-suffisante come estant oeuure de Dieu, du quel ne sorte rien qui ne soit tel. Parquoy tout ce que Du Plessis dict, scauoir est qu'elle est perfecte, suffisante, a salut que IESV son autheur est la perfection, c'st en vain. car cela a este enseigne par nous deuan luy: &amp; ne fut iamais dict par les Catholiques chose au contraire. quant
<pb n="560" facs="280"/> a l'obscurité, doubte, ambiguite, nous n'en parlons pas de tout si cruement, mais nous disons bien franc hement deux choses, &amp; l'auons asses dict &amp; monstré cy dessus, que l'scriture est fort difficile a entendre: qu'elle est prisé &amp; employee de touts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differemment bons &amp; mauuais en caution &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fense de toutes opinions, &amp; a la ruine de plusieurs.</hi> Thes ar Charons expresse wordes which I english in this māner. <hi>Let vs come to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, wich they make vs speake althou' they propose thē wrong, and otherwise thē we vtter thē to make vs odious: first that we saye the scriptures ar im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect: on the contrarie wee beleeue, confesse, and preache them to be perfect, compleat and entire, sufficient, as being the worke of God, from who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me nothing proceeds which is not such, for which cause al that which Plessis saith viz. that the scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is peafect, sufficient to saluation, that Iesus the author of it, is perfection it selfe, is in vaine. For that hath ben taught by vs before him: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was anie thing to the contrarie euer spoken by the Catholiques. For as much as concernes, obs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, doubtfulnes, ambiguitie, we doe not spae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke altogither soe crudely or rawly, yet we say freely twoe things of which we haue sufficiently said, and demonstrated them before, that the scripture is verie hard or difficult to vnderstand: that it is taken and applyed by euerie one indifferently good and bad in caution and defence of all apinions, and to the ruine of manie.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb n="561" facs="280"/>
   <p>This is that I finde in this author to this purpose, which how repugnant it is to our aduersaries purpose the reader can not be ignorant except he be affectedly ignorant as the knight seemes to be euen in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, onely this excuse I conceiue he may haue, if it be as I persuade my selfe, to wit that trusting to that pitt of corruption Plessis, he deliuered this passage to vs by retaile as he receiued it from him which if he did I shall not besorie, for that I desire not to charge my opposites more then I must of necessitie: neither is ther anie need of amplification in that nature, where the matter is soe copious, and aboundante.</p>
   <p>Touching Christophorus de cap. fontiū alledged by Sir Humfrey in the 108. page of his safe way for a denyer of transsubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation althou' I haue said something alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in the place cited it selfe: yet hauing since had a seight of that authors worke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the sacramentaries, I haue further discouered he is falsely and with manifest iniurie to his person produced by our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie, supposing he is soe farre from vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering anie doctrine against either the reall presence or transsubstantiation, that he professedly defendeth them both in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said treatise, in which particularly touching transsubstantiation I finde these plaine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des;
<pb n="562" facs="281"/> in the 58. chapter of his fourth Action- <hi>Transsubstantiationis articulum verbi Dei autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate probaturi, illud in primis tanquam basim ac fundumentum immobile ponimus, haec Christi verba (hoc est corpus meum) in literali sensu esse verissima, proinde supernacaneum ne dicam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium esse haec ita deprauare, detorquere, mutare, vt &amp; corpus in corporis figuram, &amp; verbum est in significat, conuertatur, quasi haec sententia a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioquin vera esse, sibique nisi ad hunc modum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tata constare non possit, dicimus igitur singulae dominicae sententiae verba in sua naturali signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatione sumenda esse. Hoc ita cōstituto vt verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Christi veritas constet, primum necessariò consequens esse dico vt panis essentia conuertatur &amp; mutetur. We being</hi> (saith Christophorus) <hi>to proue the article of transsubstantiation by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the diuine worde, Jn primis we put it were for an immoueable foundation or graunde worke that thefe wordes of Christ (this is my bodie are most true in a literall sense for which cause it is I will not say im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, but at the least superfluous soe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torte, depraue, and change them, that the worde bodie be changed into a figure of his bodie, and the verbe is into signifye as if this sentence could not other wayes be true and hang togither, vnlesse it be altered in this manner. Wherfore we say that euerie worde of our lordes sentence is to be taken in their
<pb n="563" facs="281"/> naturall signification. This being thus establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, to the end that the trueth of Christs wordes may stand firme, J say first that it is necessarily consequent that the essence of bread be conuerted and changed &amp;c.</hi> Thus clearely speaketh the Archbishop, which if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it be not sufficient to conuince our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie that this author was noe denyer of transsubstantiation, let him but take a bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe view of his booke, and he will be sure to finde both that point and the reall presence most exactely and copiously proued by such a multitude of testimonies both of scriptures and ancient Fathers, as I knowe he will not be able to look vpon them without confusion.</p>
   <p>It is true I must confesse this author, in his first Action of this worke, hath broached an extrauagant opinion touching the wordes of consecration, for which cause principally as I suppose the expurgatorie Index prohibiteth his booke till it be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected. for in his 264. and 265. pages he endeuoreth to proue that preists doe not consecrate by virtue of those wordes <hi>hoc est corpus meum:</hi> but by virtue of those, <hi>hoc face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te in meam commemerationem.</hi> In confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of which his opinion althou' he discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth in an vnaccustomed manner among deuines both ancient and moderne, yet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="564" facs="282"/> diligently conferred one of is passages with an other and duely pondered the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le sense and meaning of them, I perceiue his intention was onely to dispute against and disproue those whoe hould that by the virtue and operation of these wordes <hi>(hoc est corpus meum)</hi> onely materially and lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally accepted &amp; pronounced the consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is performed, he him selfe earnestly contending that those wordes haue their virtute &amp; force from the precept Christ <hi>(hoc facite in meam commemorationem.</hi> And therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in his page 263. where he stateth his que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion he hath these wordes fellowing. <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multi sunt qui horum verborum (hoc est corpus meum) materialiter pronunciatorum operatione ac virtute consecrationem fieri putant, Vnde nonnullos equidem vidi qui cum ad consecratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem peruentum esset, miris modis halitum suum cum dictis iam verbis, super panem &amp; vinum conijcerent, non secus ac si &amp; in quantum nuda tantumiuodo verba sunt, nihil aliud in ipsis considerando, consecrationem fieri arbitrantur. Ego vero consecrationem horum verborum ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione (hoc facite in meam commemorationem) fieri existimo. Christus enim &amp;c.</hi> There be verie manie (saith this author) who think that consecration is made by virtue and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of these wordes (this my bodie) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially pronounced. Whence it is that I
<pb n="565" facs="282"/> haue seene some whoe comeing to conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate doe in a strange manner cast their breath with the foresaid wordes vpon the breade and wine as if in as much onely as they be naked wordes, not considering anie thing else in them, they did hould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secration to be performed by them. But I think that consecration is made by virtue and operation of these wordes, <hi>doe this in rembrance of mee. For Ghrist &amp;c.</hi> By which wordes it clearely appeareth that Christo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus did not absolutely denye that preists doe consecrate by these wordes, <hi>this is my bodie;</hi> but he onely affirmeth that they haue not their consecratiue virtue or force included in their owne materiall sounde, but receiue it from the precept of Christ contained in those other wordes of his <hi>Doe this in remembrance of mee.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That which I yet further conuince by o- other wordes of the same author in this sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Action wher thus he discourseth in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of his position. <hi>Nemo proinde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istimet haec verba hoc est corpus meum tech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice &amp; materialiter prolata consecrationem efficere, sed ipsius Sacerdotis orationem (in qua &amp; haec ipsa recitantur) mandati huius, hoc facite, virtute atque operatione irrogatam ac spirituali virtute roboratam.</hi> Let noe man therfore think (saith hee) that these
<pb n="566" facs="283"/> wordes <hi>(this is my bodie)</hi> artificially and materially pronounced doe make the consecration, but the prayers of the preist (in which these same wordes alsoe are reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) proceeding from the virtute and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this precept <hi>doe this,</hi> and strenthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by virtue of the same. Thus Christo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus. By which it is manifest he had noe intention to denye these wordes, <hi>this is my bodie</hi> to be them by which preists doe consecrate since he expressely affirmes that they are included and rehearsed among those prayers, benedictions and gratiarum actions by which according to his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, they dayly consecrate: But he onely in his owne priuate opinion houldes, that as well those wordes <hi>(this is my bodie)</hi> as the rest of the prayers which the preists vse, haue their virtue and efficient force of consecration not from their owne mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall sounde, but from the precept of Christ, <hi>doe this in remembrance of mee.</hi> Which altho' as it hypothetically or totally soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, it is an extrauagant and singular placet or dictamen of his, yet is it not repugnant to the Catholique Roman faith, either in the point of the reall presence, or transsub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation, as may plainely appeare to anie iudicious reader: But onely hath so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me affinitie with the tenet of the moderne
<pb n="567" facs="283"/> Grecians in this particular; whoe not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing constantly defende both the one, and the other, as I haue shewed in an other place by the doctrine of their late Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch in his responsion to the luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans.</p>
   <p>And now I hence inferre as a thing more directly for my purpose that the wordes which Sir Humfrey produceth against transsubstantiation out of a certaine trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise intuled de Correctione Theologiae Scholasticae, are not truely the wordes of this author; But that Treatise is falsely as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed vnto him and forged in his name how soeuer our aduersaries make great estimation and vse of it: That which I clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely demonstrate because it containeth doctrine repugnant to that which he him selfe teacheth in his owne vndoubded wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke against the Sacramentaries. For wheras according to the citation of the knight in his 108. page of his safe way, in his Treatise inscribed de correct. Theol. Schol. Christo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus hath these wordes: Therfore it most certaine that Christ did not consecrate by those wordes (this is my bodie) neither ar they anie parte of consecratiō. And yet in his Treatise against the Sacramentaries he directly affirmeth the contrarie saying thus <hi>Christus enim horum verborum (hoc est corpus
<pb n="568" facs="284"/> meum) vi &amp; operatione consecrationem confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit: panis natura in verum ipsius corpus sese mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tante &amp;c.</hi> Which is in English. Christ did consecrate by virtue and operation of the wordes (this is my bodie) the nature of the bread being changed or changeing it selfe in to his bodie &amp;c. Now it is plane that these wordes plainely contradict the other rehearsed by our aduersarie, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se directly and expressely affirming that Christ did consecrate by these wordes (this is my bodie) the other directely and expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sely denying the same. In soe much ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we must of necessitie grante that the Archbishop plainely contradicted him selfe, which is not to be admitted especially in a graue &amp; learned diuine as he was: or else that the Treatise in which is soe expressely contained a denyall of that same which the same author affirmeth in his owne knowne &amp; acknowledged worke, is not truely his, but falsifyed and falsely published in his name. and consequently what soeuer our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie produceth out of it proueth nothing, but is to be registred in the list of such other cōterfeit wares as he selleth to his reader for currēt in the rest of his worke. And touching his Treatise against the sacramētaries &amp; so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me other of his workes althou' they cōtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne some extrauagant positions and therfore
<pb n="569" facs="284"/> were iustely condemned to be expurged by the authors of the Index, yet because par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in his booke against the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyers of the reall presence, the author ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prssely submitteth his doctrine to the censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the Roman Church purposely place<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the frontispice of his booke, <hi>omnia sanctae Eccesiae Catholicae ac sanctae sedi Apostolicae Romanae iudicio submissa sancto,</hi> therfore his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie can not anie way preiudice the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man faith. And now let this suffice to shewe the falsitie of this citation: onely the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der must further suppose that if I had seene the Treatise it selfe I could haue cleared the matter more exactely: But our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries take an order for that keeping closse all such obscure workes and reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them for their owne pallates as great nouelties and most daintie dishes.</p>
   <p>Some fewe more authors remaine vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined by reason I could not haue them: as Cardinal Carapha. Ioānes Marius, &amp; twoe or three others. But I assure the reader the allegations drawne out of them by my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie containe no matter of importance which is not sufficiently cleared without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie further searche of the places as they stand in the bookes. Onely this inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience ther is in this matter viz. That if I had obtained a sight of the authors thē sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,
<pb n="570" facs="285"/> I should probably haue discouered so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me more of the alledgers ill proceding. In respect of which, and my other more triuial defectiuenes. I will vse the same excuse which S. Augustin hath for a certaine worke of his, concluding thus. <hi>Si quid ab eis dici solet quod forte disputando non attigi, tale esse arbitratus sum, cui mea responsio necessaria non fuisset, siue quod tam leue esset, vt a quolibet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dargui facillime posset.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="285"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>