<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST High and Mighty Monarch, Charles by the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France and Jreland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. his most Royall Consort our most gra∣tious Queen Mary, the High and Mighty Prince Charles, Prince of Wales, the most illustrious Prince Iames, Duke of Yorke, the High and mighty Princesses Mary and Elizabeth, the Royall posterity of our Soveraigne Lord King Charles: And to his Majesties most Illustrious Allyes, the most High and Mighty Prince Christerne King of Den∣marke: The high and mighty Prince Charles Prince Electour Palatine: The high and mighty Prince Henry Prince of Orange, and the most Illustrious Prince De Lorreine Duke Chereuze.</title>
           <author>Fage, Mary</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101808_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00529</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10667</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST High and Mighty Monarch, Charles by the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France and Jreland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. his most Royall Consort our most gra∣tious Queen Mary, the High and Mighty Prince Charles, Prince of Wales, the most illustrious Prince Iames, Duke of Yorke, the High and mighty Princesses Mary and Elizabeth, the Royall posterity of our Soveraigne Lord King Charles: And to his Majesties most Illustrious Allyes, the most High and Mighty Prince Christerne King of Den∣marke: The high and mighty Prince Charles Prince Electour Palatine: The high and mighty Prince Henry Prince of Orange, and the most Illustrious Prince De Lorreine Duke Chereuze.</title>
                 <author>Fage, Mary</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fames roule: or, The names of our dread soveraigne Lord King Charles, his royall Queen Mary, and his most hopefull posterity: together with, the names of the dukes, marquesses, earles, viscounts, bishops, barons, privie counsellors, knights of the garter, and judges. Of his three renowned kingdomes, England, Scotland, and Ireland: anagrammatiz'd and expressed by acrosticke lines on their names. By Mistris Mary Fage, wife of Robert Fage the younger, gentleman</title>
                 <author>Fage, Mary</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Oulton, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Crouch (Crowch), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 40, 51-103, 94-180, 177-297, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST High and Mighty Monarch, <hi>Charles</hi> by the grace of God, King of Great <hi>Britaine, France</hi> and <hi>Jreland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. his most Royall Consort our most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> the High and Mighty Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> the most illustrious Prince <hi>Iames,</hi> Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> the High and mighty Princesses <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Royall posterity of our Soveraigne Lord King <hi>Charles:</hi> And to his Majesties most Illustrious Allyes, the most High and Mighty Prince <hi>Christerne</hi> King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke:</hi> The high and mighty Prince <hi>Charles</hi> Prince Electour <hi>Palatine:</hi> The high and mighty Prince <hi>Henry</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the most Illustrious Prince <hi>De Lorreine</hi> Duke <hi>Chereuze.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ardon powerfull Princes and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Potentates, my presumption, in pressing into your presence: Impute it to nothing but zeale. It was a law amongst the <hi>Persians,</hi> that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever any man met his Monarch, he should
<pb facs="3"/> forthwith present him with somewhat as a te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>imony of that duty alwaies owing unto Maiesty. One meeting the <hi>Persian</hi> King on a time, by the suddennesse mooved, and having no better for the present, tooke up one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of water, and prostrating himselfe presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the same to the King; which the magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Monarch gratefully accepted, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally rewarded him for the same. Take this most magnificent Princes, as a bowle of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the fount of <hi>Helicon;</hi> where it comes short, let my desire of perfectnesse supply. And you most noble Princes of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> finding you participators of our <hi>English</hi> honour, I have made bold likewise with you, presuming upon like hope of pardon, mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your many weighty occasions I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Virgill, <hi>Cum canerem Regibus, Cynthius aurem vellit:</hi> Wherefore with all possible du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to your Maiesty, and the rest of you mighty Princes, casting my selfe at the foote of your Maiesty, I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Majesties Faithfull Subject and honourer of Your most Princely vertues, Mary Fage.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>