<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Right and truely hono∣rable, to the Rightly ap∣proued and deseruinglie beloued, right Worshipfull, and to the Rest of the smal number of Liberall and Charita∣ble Houskee∣pers of Chri∣stendome; old Christmas sēds louing Com∣mendations.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1017_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13436</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23745.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1017</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Right and truely hono∣rable, to the Rightly ap∣proued and deseruinglie beloued, right Worshipfull, and to the Rest of the smal number of Liberall and Charita∣ble Houskee∣pers of Chri∣stendome; old Christmas sēds louing Com∣mendations.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The complaint of Christmas· : And the teares of Twelfetyde. By Iohn Taylor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Boler (Bowler), James 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 26, 6 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the most Right and truely hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, to the Rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued and deseruinglie beloued, right Worshipfull, and to the Rest of the smal number of Liberall and Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houskee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome;</hi> old Christmas <hi>sēds louing Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>YOU that are thicke sowne and
<pb facs="3"/>
thin come vp, as if the world were barren of vertue, or past breeding of Goodnesse: you that are as rare as</hi> Phenixes, <hi>as scare as black Swans or white</hi> Negroes, <hi>and as much to be held in admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as Snow in</hi> Iuly, <hi>Strawber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in</hi> December, <hi>the Sunshine at</hi> Midnight, <hi>or a blazing Starre at Noone: I as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure you my braue worthy Benefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that I your ancient and yeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Guest</hi> (Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,) <hi>am heartily sorry to see your quondam number so much shrunke in the wetting; and although you are falne into that lamentable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption
<pb facs="3"/>
that I with my friends fauourers and followers can scarcely finde the tithe of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: yet (to shew my thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full memory to your worthy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors,) with my gratefulnesse to you (too few) that are surui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Spring, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease or multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of your successors. I send to you this my louing &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Epistle. <unclear>You</unclear> in your discetions, hold the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and golden meane way betwixt the two extreame
<pb facs="4"/>
Gulphs of Nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerality and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degality, betwixt Hunger &amp; Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, betwixt</hi> Hide all &amp; Spend all, <hi>betwixt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Slauery and wastefull Braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. I wish most vnfeignedly that the dew of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen may descend blessedly, that you may fructifie, multiply fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, encrease and ampliffe, like the tree which</hi> Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezar <hi>drempt of, whose toppe reach'd to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and whose branches exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and stretch'd to the ends of the Earth: you haue the Celesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Graces; your</hi> Hope <hi>is constant,
<pb facs="4"/>
your</hi> Faith <hi>is fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, your</hi> Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>is frequent: your</hi> Hope <hi>is in assurance of that neuer faiing pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session wherein the vnblasted tree of your</hi> Faith <hi>is firmely fixed and rooted; and your Charity is the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fruit which springs from that faithfull Tree. And he that with his Grace doth plant it, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, and cause it to increase, will crowne his own gifts on your heads, that are his beloued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments; not onely here, with blessings transi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable
<pb facs="5"/>
glory which was, is, and shall bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the best of friendship,
Christmas.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>