<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE of the Author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101997_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13773</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24071</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101997</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE of the Author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Positions lately held by the L. Du Perron, Bishop of Eureux, against the sufficiency and perfection of the scriptures : maintaning the necessitie and authoritie of vnwritten traditions. Verie learnedly answered and confuted by D. Daniell Tillenus, Professor of Diuinitie in the Vniuersitie of Sedan. VVith a defence of the sufficiency and perfection of the holy scriptures by the same author. Faithfully translated</title>
                 <author>Tilenus, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snowdon (Snodham), Lionel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 48, 16, 132 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="30"/>
   <pb facs="30"/>
   <head>
      <hi>THE PREFACE</hi> of the Author.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Iewes, who since the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, wherewith God hath iustly punished their ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and rebellion, haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies shewed themselues greedie of Traditions, and out of taste with the simplicitie of the Scripture, vsing it but for a basis or foundation whereon to plant their fables, as the Poets doe historie: recount, that God being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to giue his law to their ancestors, shewed vnto <hi>Moses</hi> a Masse of Saphir,<note place="margin">Lyr. in Exo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> c. 34.</note> made of purpose by his diuine power, whereof he commanded him to hew and square out the tables, in which he vouchsafed to write his law with his owne finger: and because the text hath <hi>(Hew thee out Tables:)</hi> They gather of it,<note place="margin">Exod. 34.1.</note> that God permitted him to retaine and appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to himselfe all the cuttings and pieces that came of this precious stone in hewing the tables, and that <hi>Moses</hi> therewith made himselfe wonderfull rich. &amp;c.
<pb facs="31"/> This fabulous Tradition, how vnworthie soeuer it be of the Maiestie of God, of the grauitie of the Scripture, of the ministerie of <hi>Moses,</hi> &amp; of the beleefe of the Church; yet is it nothing neere so detestable, as that wicked exercise of those, which ayme at, and busie themselues now a daies in nothing, but in clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and scraping out the sufficiencie and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the scripture, by the same meanes taking away their owne saluation, in the bloud of Iesus Christ; since that by it wee are redeemed <hi>from our vaine conuersation,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>at. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>8</note>
      <hi>receiued by Tradition from our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Amongst other workmen, which in these times em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themselues in this mysterie or ministery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, the Lord of <hi>Perron,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Eureux</hi> wil make known vnto vs, that before him none had sufficiētly manured &amp; tilled the ground of this Traditiō, which conuerted <hi>Moses</hi> from a Prophet, into a Lapidarie; from a Lawgiuer, into a Goldsmith: and that like as this Minister of God enriched himselfe, in hewing the Tables of the Lawe: So the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the Popes Gospell, according to the true Anagogicall meaning of this Iewish Tradition, cannot better inrich themselues, and of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans become Croesians, or Crassians, than in conuerting Diuinitie into such a Technologie, in cutting of and clipping the Gospell of Iesus Christ:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ue. 21 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>uel. 17.3. &amp;c.</note> That the more they take away from the luster of the precious stones, wherewith the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>Ierusalem</hi> is builded, the more splendour they giue to the countefeite stones of that woman
<pb facs="31"/> cloathed in purple and scarlet, which ruleth ouer the great <hi>Babylon.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For, to couer the cunning that they vse, they make no difficulty to doe some honour in shewe to the scripture, euen to guild and adore outwardly the bookes which contain it, euen thē when the mine it, clip and pare it inwardly: Like as at one time Iesus Christ was kissed, and betrayed, cloathed in purple as a king, and buffeted as a foole, crucified as a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor: Or like as yet to this day the Iewes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the scripture in shew, and by gestures, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to sit in a place of equall height, to that whereon the Bible is laid: though in effect, they set it infinitely vnder their Thalmud, of which they dare with an execrable impudencie say: <hi>That God himselfe studieth therein the three first houres of the day:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lyr. in Luke. cap 4. Lib. Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. c. 1. &amp; 3. Vide Hieron. a Sancta fide cont. Iud. l. 1. in Biblioth. S. Patrum. tom. 4.</note>
      <hi>Also that hee which shall speake any thing of it sinisterly or in euill part, shall bee damned in hell, whereas hee that transgresseth the Law of God, shall receiue none other punishment, but to bee called a transgressour of the Lawe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now, that none hath so deepely sounded the mysticall meaning of the Iewish Tradition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue recited, as the Bishop of <hi>Eureux</hi> hath done, it is manifest, because that not any of the new <hi>Besa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leels,</hi> which of later times haue laboured to plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster and to painte the Popes Tabernacle, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Hosius,</hi> nor <hi>Peresius,</hi> nor <hi>Soto,</hi> nor <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danus,</hi> nor <hi>Canus,</hi> nor <hi>Canisius,</hi> nor yet that Arch-Rabby <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> not any I say, had as yet so mightily clipped this spirituall coyne (as
<pb facs="32"/>
      <hi>Gerson</hi> calleth the Scripture) nor obserued so much drosse, nor so many defects in the pure Alley of the lawe of God, written by <hi>Moses,</hi> as the Lord of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> doth: who, hauing learned this secret of <hi>Serue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and some Anabaptists (that the honour of this inuention be not taken from the true authors of it:) clippeth &amp; cutteth of from it, not some smal things, but the immortalitie of the soule, the resurrection of the bodie, the last iudgement, Paradise, and hell &amp;c. that he might discredit in like sort thereby, and by Analogie,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ohn. 15.15.</note> the doctrine of the Gospel of our Lord Iesus Christ, who though he protesteth in expresse tearmes, to haue declared to his Apostles, <hi>All things that he had heard of his father:</hi> Yet notwithstanding this Bishop feareth not to say:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ol. 15.8</note>
      <hi>That the things alone, which he hath eyther done, or declared with his owne mouth to his disciples, are not sufficient to the institution of the Church.</hi> VVhich is not to make the little mouth, but liuely to coūterfait that mouth,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>euel. 13.5.6</note> which (as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> saith) <hi>vttereth great things.</hi> Neyther is it to be a dumbe dogge, but to barke boldly, not against the Moone, but euen against the Sunne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse. A certaine Sophister at <hi>Athens,</hi> writing of the gods,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>og. Laert. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ot g.</note> declared in the beginning of his booke, the doubtes that he had of their essence, and the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties that he found in this matter: of which the Athenians had such horrour, that they burnt the booke, and banished the Author. The like irreso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and perplexitie witnessed a Heathen Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher to Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>gust Epi. &amp; 21.</note> who had enquired of him what opinion he had of Iesus Christ: But our Bishop
<pb facs="32"/> who without difficultie, doubt, or scruple whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, peremptorily concludeth: That wee are no more to hold Christ for the perfect and sufficient doctor of the Apostles, than the Scripture for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and sufficient doctrine of all the faithful: trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth amongst Christians, yet against Christians and the Christian faith: and findeth no matter fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for his glorie, nor more richer for his purse, than such reproaches of the Scripture, such blasphemies against Christ.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Cumanus</hi> gouernour of <hi>Iudea,</hi> a heathen and a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man caused a souldier to be bee beheaded for tearing a copie of the Booke of the lawe of <hi>Moses,</hi> which he had found at the sacke of a towne: The Bishop of <hi>Eureux,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioseph. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq lib. 20. c.</note> which teareth and destroyeth not some copy only, but the very original it selfe of this law, from which he plucketh away as much as in him lieth, the leaues which containe the principles and grounds of our saluation, leauing therein nothing whole, nothing perfect, nothing wholesome nor so much as profitable, without his subsidiarie (as hee tearmeth it) or helping tradition, expecteth a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals hat, is heaped with spirituall honours and temporall goods: so that one may say of him, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puleius</hi> bearing the Idoll on the one side, and many bribes on the other, said of himselfe: <hi>that he went as a Temple, and a Barne both together.</hi> But if a <hi>Sinon</hi> with his treason, a <hi>Simon</hi> with his magicke,<note place="margin">Horreum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>die</note> doe a hundred times more mischiefe, the one within <hi>Troy,</hi> the other within the Citie of God, than ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand enemies, than all the infidels could doe
<pb facs="33"/> together without, by open force; shall we yet doubt that they, which vnder sheepes cloathing, yea with a shepheards hooke,<note place="margin">Ephes. 2.20.</note> and Bishopps Crosier staffe vndermining the foundations of the Church,<note place="margin">Aduer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tul. lib. 3.</note> builded vpon the doctrine of the Prophets and Apostles are not more pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and daungerous vnto Christendome, than euer was a <hi>Celsus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lact. lib. 5. c. 3.</note> a <hi>Lucian,</hi> a <hi>Iulian,</hi> a <hi>Porphyrius,</hi> which Saint <hi>Cyrill</hi> calleth the Father of <hi>Calumnie,</hi> and others which openly opposed <hi>Plato</hi> to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, Aristotle</hi> to S. <hi>Paul; Apollonius Tyanaeus</hi> to Christ? at least wise, if as the camell, he can drinke none but muddie water, because the cleare maketh him haue gripes in his bellie;<note place="margin">De mirabil. Scrip. libri. <hi>3</hi> apud August. tom. <hi>3.</hi> Annales Tem pli secundi.</note> if the B. of <hi>Eureux</hi> cannot relish the pure and sincere word of God, because it sendeth <hi>Ecebolian</hi> vapours into his head, I wish him to content himselfe to trouble it for himselfe onely, without spreading abroad this mudde of his Traditions, on the brinke of the fountaine, which watereth the sheep of our Lord, without driuing them from it, by this his impious cry &amp; proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Insufficiencie of the Scripture; when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwise the Ancient fathers made Collections and descriptions of the wonders of the scripture; he maketh collections and descriptions of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and imperfections of the same; making it seeme fauorable to the most monstrous Hereticks, euen to the Saduces, whose doctrine wholy ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth and abolisheth all Religion. And that they haue heard of the secret Academie, which was instituted, some few yeares, agoe in a certain place
<pb facs="33"/> of <hi>Normandie,</hi> in imitation of that, which <hi>Sadoc</hi> and <hi>Baithos</hi> erected in the mountain Garizim, where was planted the first stocke of that damnable doctrine of the Saduces, which since is so welspread and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, they that know the contents of the new <hi>Alcoran</hi> that was there expounded to their auditors, which were already there to the number of fortie: wil easily iudge by the Emblemes, scattered throughout this booke of the insufficiencie of the Scripture, what <hi>Mahomet</hi> was the author of the other, knowing the Lyon by his long nailes. Now as it was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out terrour and daunger of the new <hi>Musilmans,</hi> when <hi>Feuardent</hi> Doctor of <hi>Sorbone,</hi> preaching then in the said place, dissolued that Synagogue, being a true colony of the Synagogue of the Saduces and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines: so could I not publish the treatise of the insuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of the scripture without doing displeasure to the author, who chafeth that I found meanes to get, or as he saith, to filch a copy of it; for he nowaies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired that his mysteries should be discouered in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, and exposed to the common view of all, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention being not to shew it but in secret to his yong beginners, hauing first stipulated or conditionally required of them a religious silence, as in times past the Priests and Maisters of the <hi>Isiac Mithriac, Cleusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> and <hi>Orgian</hi> ceremonies vsed in the exhibition of their Phalles and Ithyphalles:<note place="margin">Tertul. ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> valentin. Clem. Alex in Protrep Arnob. Euseb. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> &amp; alii. Plat. in Ser</note> wherefore seeing the Proper name of his booke to bee hideous and feareful, he giueth it another name lesse monstrous, in imitation of that Pope, who hauing to name <hi>Swines-snout,</hi> was the first deuised to change that fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
<pb facs="34"/> name on the other side, he letteth loose out of his mouth all the windes of his slaunder, to see if he can ouerwhelme &amp; swallow me vp into the chaos of his iniurious speeches,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ing nips, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>u.</note> by force of exclaming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me deceiuer, Sycophant, Parasite, beast, drūk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, sēceles falsifyer, impudent, blinde, desperate &amp;c. to omitt here his mockeries, and Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>casmes, which he applyeth vnto me as leuitiues after he had so stoned and rent me.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>his treatise 10.</note> As for the fir t, vnles he race out the blasphemies out of his booke, it is to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to scrape out the title from the forefront, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp a new bush to his Tauerne; for they which read this conclusion in his discourse: <hi>the Scripture therefore containeth not sufficiently all the Princ ples of doctrine necessary to Diuinitie:</hi> if they let their eyes be still dazelled by his prestigious delusions, if they can not beleeue of him, that he accuseth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of vnsufficiency,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ril. Hieron <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>roch. 6.</note> one may well beleeue of them that they are like to Idols, which haue eyes and see not.</p>
   <p>As for the other, I verily beleeue, that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian reader will rather hast to passe ouer his inuect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iues, stopping his nose: than stay to sente such filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Now the q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>estion is not, on whether side is the subtiltie but the truth; not where the Eloquence, but the edification; not the science, but the consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: He is not enuied the quality he attributeth to himselfe, to be the greatest disputer of the world, whether herein he would imitate <hi>Manes,</hi> who taking this name of purpose for to tearme himselfe such in the <hi>Persian</hi> tongue, made himselfe a mad man in the
<pb facs="34"/> Greek: or whether he imitate that Doctour of <hi>Paris,</hi> of whome <hi>Lodouic. viues</hi> speaketh, who made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe be called the <hi>Horrible Sophister,</hi>
      <note place="margin">De caus. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> art. lib. 3.</note> esteeming this title no lesse honorable, than the surname of <hi>Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus,</hi> or <hi>Asiaticus.</hi> Neither can he hinder, whosoeuer seeth a firebrand in the Cittie, the Gaules on the Capitoll, Sacriledge in the Temple from crying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, were he a childe, yea a goose.<note place="margin">Herodo. l. 1</note> And if in times past a childe, dumb by nature, seeing a soldier come for to murder his father, found suddainly his tongue vnloosed for to crie out and vtter wordes, which stayed the murtherer from passing further: If the same happened to a wrastler,<note place="margin">Aul. Gel. l 5, c, 9</note> when one would haue deceiued him: why should we not hope, that he, that will haue the mouth of little ones to sound forth his praise, giueth sometimes to the dumb, the facultie of speach, to children strengh to crie, to the ignorāt efficacie to perswade,<note place="margin">Psalm. 8.2 Math, 21.17</note> at least one that is not altogether out of his witts: that he cease to deceaue and to murther the soules that Iesus Christ hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed: from discrediting or calling in the coyne wherewith he payed our ransome: and from clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the letters, which teach vs the value of it.</p>
   <p>And sith that cannot be done without manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accusing &amp; iniuring the heauenly Father, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing caused this money to be made, and stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with these letters, as true Soueraigne, ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it for all subiects, and giueth it to his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
   <p>If this caller in, or descrediter of it, wil be thought
<pb facs="35"/> to be of the number of these, let him reuerence the almightie, and the Christian people, at least so farre forth as did that wicked sonne, who accusing his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before <hi>Tiberius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>cit. an. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>l l. 4.</note> was so terrified at the noyse of people, which detested that fact, that he gaue ouer his accusation and fled.</p>
   <p>Now my purpose in this writing is, to treat of, and to examine all the points &amp; instances from whence he forgeth this calumnious accusation of the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, without refuting more amply his falshoodes, which hee mingleth in the recitall of our verball conference, considering how little reason he hath, to beleeue he hath well done, in disguising so the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>stic. l. 1.</note> for on the one side he hath learned of <hi>Cicero,</hi> that faith is a truth &amp; constancie, of that which one saith or doth: on the other side the Councill of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance</hi> forbiddeth him to keepe faith with heretickes. VVhence he ingeniously concludeth,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>els. 19.</note> that if he had not kept the truth of that was said and done in our conference; he had not kept the Decree of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill, but had burst and let out the winde of that holy and sacred Canon: considering withall that such frauds cannot be tearmed wicked, but godly, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the doctrine of the same Church, because they are done for a good intent. As for me, sith such Canons are not forged in our Church, nor such di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions in our schooles; I am not permitted to vse the same liberty: wherefore I will adde nothing to the bare recitall of that historie, where I haue imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted neither his disguisements, nor his inuectiues. But if there be found any word somewhat free: let him at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
<pb facs="35"/> that, eyther to the necessitie of my defence, or to the delicatenesse of the dayes; and let him call to minde, that he which saith whatsoeuer hee listeth, shall in the end heare what he liketh not, when the sharpenes of the truth beginneth to alter the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the delight. And since he taketh a verie great pleasure, when he reproacheth me that I would not continue the conference, vnlesse it were written and signed on both parts; so farre am I from repenting me of it, or denying it, that heere againe I confesse, that I insisted vpon it with all endeuour; that hee may see, that when the truth permitteth me, I oppose not my selfe any whit to his delight: For it sufficeth me for my contentation to beleeue, that the courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader will make none other iudgement of this my iust and necessarie instance,<note place="margin">Epist. 74.</note> than that which S. <hi>Augustine</hi> hoped, when <hi>Pascentius</hi> the <hi>Arrian,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing refused to write, and to signe in a disputation that hee had with him, neuerthelesse vaunted that hee had ouercome him, knowing well that his false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood could not be conuinced by any act: <hi>For in that are the lurking holes,</hi> saith S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> which they seeke, that are more desirous of contention, than of the truth. And as touching the vanities and lies of <hi>Pascentius,</hi> he answereth: <hi>It is easie to ouercome</hi> Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine; <hi>but heed is to bee taken, whether it be by the truth or by exclamations.</hi> If it hath not beene easie for the Bishop of <hi>Eureux</hi> to vanq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ish mee in the one sort, yet hath it beene most easie for him to doe it in the other, being in the middest of his <hi>Satellites,</hi> or para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sites, who by their acclamations did reenforce his
<pb facs="36"/> his cries, and did like the birds of <hi>Psaphon</hi> sing his praises. But this <hi>Psaphon,</hi> proclamed great god by the chirping of birds,<note place="margin">Cool. Rhod. antiqu. Lact. l. 3. c. 5</note> was soone after declared great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer by the iudgement of mē. For conclusion I giue him the same aduertisement that S. <hi>Augustine</hi> gaue to <hi>Pascentius,</hi> that he busie not himselfe in seeking how he may ouercome <hi>Tillenus,</hi> which is but a man, and the least of men: but that he take heed how he may ouercome the truth,<note place="margin">Vbi. sup.</note> the perfection of the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture how with his hammer of winde he can spoyle, breake, or clippe the tables of the law of God, more pure, more hard, than any Gold, than any Diamond, the least piece or shiuer of which, is more than suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to pierce and breake in pieces the forehead of this <hi>Goliah,</hi> though it be of brasse, and shamefully to ouerthrow to the earth al this great Colossus, which so proudly lifteth vp himselfe against heauen, against the voyce which breaketh Cedars,<note place="margin">Psal. 29.</note> and which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the mountaines to quake.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>