<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101772_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00458</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10591</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101772</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The hatefull hypocrisie, and rebellion of the Romishe prelacie. By Lewys Euans</title>
                 <author>Evans, Lewis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>WHAT KIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de</hi> of Phisician is he (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of a dangerouse sickenes, will then ceasse to Minister hys remedies, &amp; Phisicke? what capitayn is he, that whē his enemies do muster, wil thē either stand all amazed, or els through cowardlyefeare, will giue ouer the field? what good Christian is he, that whē Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ by ragewold raigne, will then either openlye renounce
<pb facs="3"/>
Christianitie, or els in anye wise ceasse from the constante acknowlaiginge of the same? if lewde lighte headdes shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell agaynst their soueraigne lady, who (o Lorde) can but deteste them? who can but ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre them? yea, if they rebell against god, &amp; autoritie, who (trowe ye) can holde his pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce? where shall I beginne? of what shall I fyrst speke? is not their intente more then hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouse, is it not moste hatefull, who to the intente they might bring to passe theyr trayterous
<pb facs="3"/>
purposses, will not sticke to paynte their baner with Ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, to trouble the comō pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of this Realme, to annoye (asmuche as in them lyethe) all good, louinge, and faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full subiectes? o the ende of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessite! o the fruite of hatefull Ydolatrie? we maye nowe well saye, as the Doctour &amp; fryar Uincentius once sayde. Dant <note place="margin">sermo: de Trin.</note> vnam medicinā cuilibet mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo, scz missas. &amp;c. <hi>They gyue one Medycine vnto euerye sickenesse, that is masses. &amp;c.</hi> And whye? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb facs="4"/>
bankrouteship must ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a couer, riotousnesse muste haue somme defence, treason must haue a cloake, traytours will euer haue somme collour. But God that seeth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde partes, and meanin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of men, will detecte theyr Hypocrysye, hee wyll putte into the heartes of Good people, to defende the anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, hee will endue his chosen, with the knowlaig of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, he will suppresse all tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, he will worke (accordinge vnto his secrete &amp; goodwill)
<pb facs="4"/>
all for the best▪ well to speke no more of such, it is so (Christiā reader) that beinge of late in the vniuersite of Oxforde, I herd ther, not by any mean mā but by the learnest, how myne aduersaries, na, how the true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes aduersaries had bruited, that I had reuolted from, the Gospell, &amp; that I was agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne gonne beyonde the seas, I hearde also <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ovve at my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge to the Citie of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, hovveyt vvas in the mouthes of manye, that I vvas deade. two tales, &amp; yet
<pb facs="5"/>
neuer a one true. alas, beyond the seas, what to doe? Stultus <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eda.</note> populus quaerit Romam: <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishe folkes flye to Rome.</hi> I thinke it not wisedome, in the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se dayes to flee from Eglande to a forraine realme, I thinke it no godlinesse to leaue God, &amp; to leane to Antichrist. shall we flee from light to darkenes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, from the Gospell to vayne gloses, frōtrueth to falshoode, from faithe to infidelitie, from religion to superstition? God forbidde. For mine own part, I se euery day more, &amp; more,
<pb facs="5"/>
the filthie fruites of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mishe sinagogue, and therfore in despight of satan, saye mine enemies what they will, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke men as they liste, it is the law of God that I professe, &amp; it is traiterouse Papacie that I detest. &amp; this is it which mo ued me at this time (Gentle reader) to set furthe these few leafes, wherin we maye se, the hipocrisie, from time to time, of the romayn prelacie, &amp; wher by we may learne to be wise, to knowe oure selfes, to see theyr doynges, &amp; to defie them. but
<pb facs="6"/>
as for late time, euon at the dissolucion of Abbevs, if thou wilte knowe what was the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of the irreligeouse roagues if thou wilte vewe, what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes they were then of, let vs consider certen of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasteries put down, let vs wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe the honestie of somme, for, of all, it were to muche, At Windesore kepte not eyght <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>x br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>u: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> of the Priestes, twentie and niene harlates? A Hollye whoredome. At the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasterie of Battell, were not xv. foūd to be sodomits? as for
<pb facs="6"/>
suche as kepte there harlattes theyr names be set furthe, &amp; therefore I will omit them. What were the Diuines at Cantur burie? what? eighte of <note place="margin">Cātur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burye.</note> them were sodomites, &amp; to let passe many thirtene kept four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene harlates. At Bathe twoe Priestes keepte eyghtene har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, besydes that they were proued to be sodomits. come we to moōkenfarleghe, &amp; we shal find that the Prior kept niene harlats, the prior of Maydē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bradley had fyue, the Abbate of Bristow hadde foure, the
<pb facs="7"/>
Abbate of Abindon had thre, besydes that he had twoe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by his owne naturall sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster. At Shulbred foure moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes <note place="margin">Shul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brede.</note> kepte twentie one harlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. as for the Prior of Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moundesey, <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ermoū desaye.</note> he kept no lesse by recorde then twentie. Yt is tediouse to write of all, yet it is proffitable to speake of these, that euon Children, maye see the iniquitie of the Romishe Ydolatrie. and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to make an ende, take a vew of the Cathedrall chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che <note place="margin">Ciche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</note> of Cichester, whereof Syr
<pb facs="7"/>
Ihon Champion hadde twoe Harlattes, sir William Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sse one, syr Thomas Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker twoe, sir Richarde bus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fielde one, Syr Bartholome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we Cokisleye one, Syr Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berte Hunte manye, Syr Thomas Coffe twoe, Syr Ihon Hill thirtene, Syr Roberte Moore manye, as for Syr George Barrham, &amp; sir Ihon Chāpiō, besyds that they were proued adulterers, they were also found to be sodomites. see, Christian Reader, by a fewe, vnder the profession of all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
<pb facs="8"/>
what is the fruite of a heathenishe ydolatrie. thus they lyued in King Henri the eyghte his tyme, at what tyme (not without juste cause thou seest) he ouerthrew theyr bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thell houses, theyr uncleane dē nes, &amp; their filthie caues. but that thou mayst further mark their hipocrisie, read ouer this litle boke, dedicated not vnto anye onne singuler, to aduoyde the note of vayn glorie, but vn to thee, for thy proffite, &amp; vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. And if thou wilt proffite, and doe good vnto thine owne
<pb facs="8"/>
soule, yea, if thou wilt prosper in this worlde feare God, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Gospell, obeye the Quenes Maiestie, &amp; be not a foe, but (as thou art most boū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den) a frende vnto this Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, not forgettinge, that mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre all the malice of rebelles, not onlye, the trueth is greate, and preuayle, but also as God hath donne, so will he euer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende thy soueraigne, his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted. And that he so do, as I with an vnfayned hart, so you with all fayithe full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, saye</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>