<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTI∣an and wel-disposed Rea∣der, S. Egerton wisheth grace, mercie, and peace, from God the Father, and from our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Egerton, S.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101170_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10083</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20337</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101170</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTI∣an and wel-disposed Rea∣der, S. Egerton wisheth grace, mercie, and peace, from God the Father, and from our Lord Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Egerton, S.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doctrine of superioritie, and of subiection, contained in the fift commandement of the holy law of almightie God : Which is the foundamentall ground, both of all Christian subiection: and also of like Christian gouernment, as well in church, and common-wealth, as in euery schoole and priuate familie. A pretious memorial of the substance of manie godly sermons, preached by the learned and faithfull seruant of God, Ma. Robert Pricke, minister of the vvord, at Denham in Suffolke</title>
                 <author>Pricke, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Ephraim.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Downes (Downe), Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young (Yong), William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>204 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and wel-disposed Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>S. Egerton</hi> wisheth grace, mercie, and peace, <hi>from God the Father,</hi> and from our Lord <hi>Iesus Christ.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He varietie and vanitie of idle Phamphlettes, which the loue of gaine or glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for the most part begetteth, &amp; the Presse daily bringeth forth in our English tongue: made mee the more willing to further the printing of this explanation of the fift Commandement. For
<pb facs="4"/>though the most part delight to read the vnsauorie inuentions of mens braines, and that such also as desire to reade good bookes, haue such plentie before them, that they are doubtfull, for want of good direction, which they should pitch vpon: yet I thought with my selfe, that the rare &amp; sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular piety of this Author, a holy man, and most faithfull Minister, powerful in prayer, and diligent in preaching to his flocke manie yeares together, with the perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuitie of the order, and the chois<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the matter, might the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by my testimonie, stir vp the minds of Godly Christians, to reade this Treatise, though being otherwise streighted of time, or distracted in their choise, they might perhaps neglect the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of so fruitfull a Treatise vpō
<pb facs="4"/>this Commandement, as hath not hitherto (so farre as I can learne) beene printed and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in our mother tongue.</p>
   <p>Sundry learned and godly men haue laboured verie fruitfully, in opening the sense, and laying forth the duties of euerie Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of the 4. wherin the practise both of the duties of <hi>Pietie,</hi> set downe in the first Table, &amp; of the duties of <hi>Mercie▪</hi> set downe in the second Table, is required at our handes, to be performed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a set day, and in a more so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne and serious manner: but none to my knowledge, hath published any seuerall Treatise vpon the fift Commaundement, which beeing truly vnderstood, vnfeinedly beleeued, &amp; faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practised, wil direct a christian
<pb facs="5"/>in a holy practise of all the duties of <hi>Mercie</hi> &amp; <hi>Loue,</hi> which he is to performe, either to himselfe or to any other. For whosoeuer doth walke carefully in the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of this Commandement, maintaining that honour which is due to himselfe, and euerie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, in respect of their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent &amp; seueral yeares, gifts, and qualities, callings and degrees, in the familie, Church, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: hee cannot easilie be carried to exercise any crueltie against himselfe, or any other cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the sixt Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: or to defile either his own bodie, or his neighbours, against the seuenth Commaundement: or to deale vniustly, or vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully about his owne, or other mens goods, credit, and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, contrarie to the eight and
<pb facs="5"/>ninth Cōmandements: yea, or to giue place to the least spice of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining, discontentment, or wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering motion, forbidden in the last Commandement of the law of God.</p>
   <p>There was neuer any disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and outrage, in any family, Church, or Common-wealth, from the beginning of the world to this day, neither can be: but it proceeded from the breach of the 5. Commandemēt. For how is it possible that there should be any disorder in the family, if the wife honour her husband as she ought, &amp; he her? if children giue due honour to their parents, and they also deale honourably with them? if seruants do honour their Maisters as they ought, and they their seruāts? and if children and seruants do mutually respect and
<pb facs="6"/>honour one the other as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth them?</p>
   <p>Could any trouble and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion arise in Churches &amp; congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, if the people would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member such as haue the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight of them, and do declare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them the word of God, and in giuing honour vnto them would submit themselues, because they watch for their soules, for which they must giue an accoūt before the chiefe Shepheard? And on the other side, if the Pastors and Elders would feede the flocke of God which depēdeth vpō them, caring for it not by constraint but willingly? &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Is it possible, that euer any trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, sedition or disloyaltie could breake forth in citties or king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, if people would honour their Princes, and euery soule be
<pb facs="6"/>subiect to the higher powers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedient and readie to euery good worke? and if Magistrates in their places would gouerne their Subiects as deare children?</p>
   <p>Finally, if euery one that is an inferiour anie manner of way, would carrie the affection of a dutifull child to his Superiour: and euerie Superiour, the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a wise and tender Parent to his inferiour, according to the plaine scope, and maine drift of this commaundement?</p>
   <p>But what should I need to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate the truth of this point in many particulars? Search the Scriptures, turne ouer al humane stories, call to minde what thou hast seene and obserued in thine owne time, in the family, congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, or any corporatiō where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thou art or hast beene a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber:
<pb facs="7"/>and thou shalt euidently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that the troubles and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which haue broken out in them, haue alwaies proceeded &amp; sprung from this bitter roote, I meane from the disobedience &amp; breach of the 5. Commandemēt. In which respect it is said, that this is the onely commandement of all the tenne, that hath a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar promise of a long and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable life, yea, and the onely Commandemēt of all the sixe of the second Table, that hath any promise at all annexed vnto it.</p>
   <p>O therefore, that there were in men, professing that they will heare and do the will of God, the like heart to feare him, &amp; to keep all (and among all of the second Table, specially this his cōmaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement) alwaies, that it might go well with them, and with their
<pb facs="7"/>children for euer.</p>
   <p>But to conclude, seeing God by his good prouidēce hath stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp this vigilant Pastor &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man of God, while he yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, to take such paines in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Explanation which he had often gone ouer in his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Ministerie: neglect not, I pray thee, the reading of such a sound &amp; fruitfull Treatise, which will teach thee to retaine and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease thine owne honour and dignitie, &amp; to giue to euery sexe, age, calling &amp; condition of men, the honour and dignitie which is due to them.</p>
   <p>Now, the Lord giue a gratious blessing hereunto, &amp; to all other thy holy exercises, and meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: euen for his onely begotten Sonnes sake Christ Iesus, our on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mediator and Aduocate, who
<pb facs="8"/>together with the Father and the holy Ghost, be blessed and praised for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>S. Egerton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>