<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN, AND CHARITABLE READER,</title>
           <author>S., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101748_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12094</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22397</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101748</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN, AND CHARITABLE READER,</title>
                 <author>S., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The motiues of Richard Sheldon pr. for his iust, voluntary, and free renouncing of communion with the Bishop of Rome, Paul the 5. and his Church : Published by authority</title>
                 <author>Sheldon, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 160, 55, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN, AND CHARITABLE READER,</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE God of mercies, in his most gracious prouidence, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning such, as hee hath segrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to himselfe, from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; doth often, contrarie to their intended purposes, and designes; dispose, and designe of them: then working their conuersions to him, when they least dreame thereof: yea, when they are purposely, and obstinatelie striuing against it. So hee dealt with <hi>Saul,</hi> who brought vp at the<note n="a" place="margin">Acts 22 &amp; 26.</note> feet of <hi>Gamaliell,</hi> profited so much in Iuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>isme, that by profession hee became a <hi>Pharisey,</hi> and so zealous<note n="b" place="margin">Galat. 1.</note> an Emulatour of his forefathers traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, that at the mercifull appearance of the Saviour of mankind Iesus Christ, hee was so repleat with Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant zeale, and so<note n="c" place="margin">Acts 9.</note> breathing out of threatnings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Christ, that hee obteined letters of commission; from the<note n="d" place="margin">Acts 12.</note> Chiefe Priest in <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> to goe into <hi>Samaria,</hi> and to bring vp bound, all those who should professe his name. But prosecuting this designe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause hee did it in<note n="c" place="margin">1. Ad Timoth. 11.</note> ignorance, hee obtained mercie,
<pb facs="6"/> and therefore by the most gracious voice, and shining light of him, whom hee persecuted, hee was most hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilie prostrated to the ground, in his way to <hi>Damas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus;</hi> and beeing led to <hi>Samaria</hi> (the Place, where hee intended most to oppose against Christ) hee was there not onely conuerted, by the ministerie of <hi>Ananias,</hi> but hee was further, so conforted and strengthned by the Spirit of God; that of an instrument of wrath, hee became a most Holy vessell of Election,<note n="f" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> confounding the <hi>Iewes,</hi> in their Synagogues (the <hi>Iewes</hi> I say, in their Synagogues; who were erst, the elect People of God<note n="g" place="margin">Ad Rom. 9.</note> whose were the Promises, and the Lawgiuing, who iustlie gloried in that they were the<note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom the<note n="i" place="margin">2 R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>g. 3 &amp; Ierem. 33.</note> Eternall Couenant with him and his posterity was made by God; of whose tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple God had promised to make<note n="k" place="margin">Psal, 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> his dwelling place for ener.) But, these <hi>Jewes,</hi> first so peculiarlie elected by God: yea and euen then, in some sort his true Church; (though afterwards wholly reiected, and abandoned) this most excellent witnesse of Christ, did<note n="k" place="margin">Act 9.</note> confound euery where, throughout their Synagogues; teaching that Iesus the Iust one, whom they had denied and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied, was the Messias<note n="m" place="margin">Genes. 22.</note> promised to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his seede for euer. Myselfe, who a farre of can onely admire the vertues of this admirable witnesse, doe most humblie intreat of God, that I may in the lest modell imitate his zeale, in the professing and testifying of Christs truth. Hauing beene brought vp in Papisme, and much profited therein, I became so zealous an Imitatour, and defender of all Romysh humane tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and doctrines; that I would most willinglie,
<pb facs="6"/> haue spent my bloud for the profession of the same: earnestlie labouring, by preaching, exhorting, writing, early and late, to draw all to a zealous profession of all doctrines of that Church, (for so much as meerlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned matter of Religion) as diuers both may, can, and will witnesse: which course I also prosecuted most zealouslie beeing grounded, as I then thought, vpon an inuincible Rocke, to wit, the Authority of the present Romane Church. And although (I call the heauens to witnesse) euer since I entred into the studie of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and serious perusing, and discussing of diuers controuersies; as (to wit) of the worshipping and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Images, of Indulgences, of Purgatory, of Merits, and inuocations of Saints (as necessarie to sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,) of the Popes transcendent Supremacy; of the imagined transubstantiation; of the Canon of the Masse; of the Publike seruic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in vnknown tongues; and most speciallie of the maine, principall, and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall controuersie of Iustification: I oftentimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained much vnsatisfied in my vnderstanding; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all I could read, in <hi>Bellarmine, Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Sanders, Vasques, &amp;c.</hi> against all such doubts, as ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her out of Scriptures, ancient Fathers, or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, were produced against the doctrines of these con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies as they are now most stiflie maintained, by the Romane Church: yet in respect of the misconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued dignitie, and inerrabilitie of that See, and her Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops (supposing that shee would decree nothing, nor had decreed nothing as matter of faith, but by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall consent of the whole Church.) I did so captiuate my vnderstanding, in obedience to her, and so firmelie
<pb facs="7"/> receiue all that shee taught as faith; that I would haue accounted my selfe most happie, to haue suffered death for any point of her doctrine, deliuered as a point of faith by her. Thus walking in the way from <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem,</hi> into <hi>Samaria:</hi> it pleased him, who (as I most confidently trust) hath assumed mee to his mercies; to knocke at my conscience, and to prostrate my soule, to a humiliation in her selfe, to open my eies and eares, to the hearkning of his voice; bidding mee beware of the way, in which I walked, and looke whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>herunto the corruptions of that Church, which I followed did lead mee; the which hee vouchsafed, so sweetlie to worke with his gracious illustrating, and freeing of my vnderstanding, that I could not much doubt; at first, but that it was (<note n="n" place="margin">Psal. 117.</note>
      <hi>dextra Domini</hi>) the right hand of the Lord which did touch my vnderstanding: and as hee thus wrought in my vnderstanding, so hee did also internally, and immanentlie (as me thought) moue my will, to a most sweet, sincere, and burning <note n="o" place="margin">1. Iohn 4. Prou. 8. &amp; Iohn 14.</note> loue of his Maiestie; to a most resolute detestation of all my former sinnes, greater or smaller; euen to lament them (<note n="p" place="margin">Isai. 38.</note> in <hi>amaritudine animae</hi>) in bitternesse of soule; purely for his loue onely, moouing mee also to a longing desire, to bee out of this wretched world; and to bee <note n="q" place="margin">Ad Philip. 1.</note> dissolued, and to bee with him: and withall, so long as I should breath, to beare a resolute resignation to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid all occasions of sinnes whatsoeuer, (which also since my illustration, hath so accompanied mee, that looke, as when I resolue, to follow the truth offered, so I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease in detestation of sinne; looke, as I haue temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and suggestions, moouing mee to wauer from the
<pb facs="7"/> same either in respect of credite, loue of my old ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and of the world, or of former meanes, and maintenance; so also, I had inclinations, to yeeld to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sinnes, and a weakenesse also, to withstand temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations as before.) It pleased also his infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, at these times iointly to inspire, and suggest vnto my soule, that in his mercies, and by his death and pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion only, I was redeemed, and to be saued: not as with a wretchlesse presumption, beleeuing <note n="r" place="margin">Iacob. 2..</note> this out of a dead faith, but withall, that by his holy assistance I was necessarily to liue and perseuere, in his holy loue and feare; and in the <note n="s" place="margin">Math. 7</note> obseruation of all his most holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, so farre as humane infirmity, or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance would permit mee.</p>
   <p>Thus beeing touched (pardon mee Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for this disclosing the secrets of my soule) I did often prostrate my soule, and my heart, beseeching that <note n="t" place="margin">Ad Titum. 3.</note> humanitie, and benignitie of Iesus, my onely Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate, that hee would not, for my <note n="u" place="margin">Psal. 78.</note> former sinnes, and ignorances of my youth abandon me, but that he would<note place="margin">Psal. 24.</note> vouchsafe to <note n="x" place="margin">Psal. 5▪</note> confirme mee with his principall spirit: and to remooue from my soule all shadowes and deceits of Satan, and to bring mee to his iotes: for in him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, with him onely, and for him onely, I desired to liue or die; yea so resolued therein, that whatsoeuer should betide mee, either in this life or the next; yet I estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it all happinesse that his name should be glorified in me, either by iustice or mercy. As my Soule, was thus communing with herselfe, and my Sauiour; ioint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, did present themselues to my memory, many my former thoughts, against the Romane humaine tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="8"/> and doctrines (especially the pernicious Breefes, of <hi>Paul</hi> the fift, against the Oath of allegiance) yea and euen th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n, by happie occasion, chanced into my hands, a Remes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> estament, where happily I light vpon <note n="y" place="margin">
         <hi>Annotat. in 22 Luc</hi> vpon those words, <hi>Simon, Simon,</hi> and <hi>Ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tat.</hi> vpon the first of the Acts, and vpon the 1. 10 the Corinth. 14.</note> some of their corruptions, and abuses: yea and one pernicious errour, or rather heresie, the which as I had often obserued before, but had passed it ouer, in respect of my blind obedience to their doctrines: so then I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considered more seriouslie; and withall proposed it to some in this place (who are worthily esteemed learned) but they gaue mee little satisfaction, because as the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions were wilfull, and inexcusable▪ so the errour was pernicious, and indefensible. But aboue all other; two considerations, then did offer themselues, to my serious, and pensiue vnderstanding; first, how not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the Bishop of Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e himselfe, but also all his Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists (some verie few onely excepted) all those of the societie of Ignatius, and all other the greatest firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the present Roman religion; doe obstinately maintaine, that the Popes iudgement alone, teaching the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hurch, was to bee beleeued (beleeued I say) as the infalible Oracle of God; which to my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing and faith, was so cleare an heresie, and blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy against God; contrarie to all Scriptures, all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Councels, Fathers, yea all Ancients (some few Popes only excepted, whose testimonies are either coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited, or else giuing testimony for themselues, their testimonies are not true, and worth-receiuing) that I fully resolued, not to giue, an obedient and obsequious eare to the present Romane Church therein; because shee did so perniciously erre in the verie rule of faith it
<pb facs="8"/> selfe. For if the square, and rule bee crooked, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euen, how can any thing, that is to bee leuelled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, bee right and streight? the blinde, leading the blind, both fall into the ditch <note n="z" place="margin">Luc. 6.</note> saith Christ. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie I obserued, by what preposterous meanes, contrary to all Antiquity, and Christs most expresse instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 22. Mar. 12.</note> S. <hi>Matthew;</hi> the Popes doe now challeng, and assume power to depose Princes, dispose of Kingdoms, dissolue fidelity (though with oath confirmed) not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in case of heresie, in the Prince, by him so termed (although this his mysticall power, was at first onely pretended by the learnedst Ignatians, against notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Heretikes, and manifest Apostates) but in case also, of any enormous delict, or insufficiencie, in any Princes whatsoeuer: yea and to speake plaine English; in what case soeuer, it shall please his holinesse iudicial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to proceed. For who of the Pontificians, dare <note n="b" place="margin">See pag. 43. following.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract his sentence? who euer resisted him and had peace? or was not thundred against; with excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, deposition, or depriuation? which when I seriouslie pondered; as in the sight of God, I could not but thinke, that it was soueraigntie, not religion; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of possession, not saluation of soules, which the later Popes aimed at; as also I shall, most clearely deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in my motiues following.</p>
   <p>Further, I obserued, that for the fortifying of this mysticall power of the Image of the Romane Empire, they endeauoured to make heereof a newe article of Faith: for indirect furthering whereof; most impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently without all forehead, <note n="c" place="margin">Vpon the feast of the inuention of the Crosse, P. W. in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like assembly, &amp; at a publike pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gericall oration made for the Martyrs honour at <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>aine,</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thus vnto him <hi>S. Henrice inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede pro no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>is.</hi> Holy <hi>Henry</hi> pray for vs, I doe not heare that hee made R. <hi>Hould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne</hi> a Saint, which may wel be admired.</note> diuers of the Ignatians doe labour tooth and nai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, to make the late Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traitour
<pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>Garnet,</hi> a martyr (a fit martyr indeede with his Consorts, for this their new article of faith) and by a pseudoprodigious, and mendacious straw (the imaginary face of which, was first obserued and found, by a notorious dicing and carding priest, &amp;c) to make the Authour of all goodnesse, as a witnesse of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, and integrity of that man; who with other his Complices, was not onely acquainted, but also (as the publike records of this Realme published accordingly to his triall, made in the face of the whole Kingdome doe witnesse) was a Concealer, an Abettour, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Furtherer of the same.</p>
   <p>I must needs confesse Christian Reader, that these two considerations, did produce in my soule a kind of horrour, and dread, to bee partaker of that Church; which was to bee supported by so weake and fallible a rule of faith, as the Popes variable iudgement is; and to bee ampliated, and enlarged, by such meanes, as none but the verie smoakie <note n="d" place="margin">Apocal. 9.</note> Locusts, arising from out of the bottomlesse pit, would offer to attempt. Thus my soule wauering and being tossed; I, with all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity knocked often at the gates of his mercie, who <note n="e" place="margin">Math. 7.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseth to open, to all such, as confidentlie knocke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at: I entred into a more serious search of these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; I read with great diligence; I conferred also with such as are reputed learned, and Chiesetaines in this place; so long as I saw <note n="*" place="margin">One of these, M. <hi>G. B.</hi> Archp. being very lately dead is falsely by some reported to haue changed his opinion for the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</note> them willing to giue me any sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction; but when I clearelie obserued, that their answers to the sacred Scriptures, and ancient Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities produced by mee, were meere tergiuersations; and that they resolutely rested vpon the authority of
<pb facs="9"/> the present Roman Church, and her practise, disestee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming whatsoeuer, was clearely brought against her (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whose authoritie, command, and Breefes, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding some of them doe practise) I could not but resolue, to leaue off conference with them; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that of the <note n="f" place="margin">Isai, 6. Act. 28.</note> Prophet <hi>Esay,</hi> vnto the Iewes, and vsed also by the Apostle S. <hi>Paul</hi> in like case: <hi>Incras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satum est cor populihuius, &amp;c.</hi> The heart of this people is become grosse, and with their eares, they haue heard heauily, and they haue closed their eies, lest per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance they should see with their eies, and heare with their eares, and vnderstand with their hearts, and bee conuerted, and I heale them. This their estate, as I did and do, from the very bottome of my heart lament, so it did greatly increase my doubts, mustring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to my Conscience, against the nouell traditions, and vncatholike doctrines of the Church of Rome; whereof (Christian Reader, with thy patience and good acceptance) I will communicate part, to thy courteous view: not because, I esteeme my selfe so learned, as though I were able, to produce any new learning neuer thought on before, (for in very deed, I doe ranke my selfe, amongst the meanest of Gods seruants, and Priests) nor, because, I doe seeke in matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to bee applauded by the worlds iudgement, or to please humaine censures; but alonely, that thou maist consider, vpon how waightie inducements, I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquished the intollerable, and pernicious burthen of humaine traditions; reared vp, against Gods instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that if thou bee wauering from the Firmament of Truth, of Gods word, and holy ancient Church; thou
<pb facs="10"/> maist with mee bee staied; if thou art alreadie sedu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed, (as I haue been) thou maist be reclaimed, to the sweet yoke of Iesus Christ.</p>
   <p>My heart bleeds, to thinke how many in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (and some of them my speciall acquaintance, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuously and zealously disposed) are caried away with most dangerous errors; obtruded vnto them, only vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Roman Bishops prerogatiue, of not erring: (and yet heauen and earth proclaimes that Popes may erre and be Heretikes:) God of his infinite mercy, vouchsafe to open their eies, that they may receiue the charity of Truth; that they may see that defection, and apostasie accomplished in them, and their defendants; which the <note n="g" place="margin">2 ad Thess. 2</note> vessell of election, so long agoe for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>told; and whereof the Prophet and <note n="h" place="margin">Apoc. 17.</note> Apostle in his Reuelation so clearelie discourseth; shewing that Kings and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions should be drunke, and be bewitched with the Cup of Romes Fornications: Fornications hee saith, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by most clearely demonstrating; that some Romane Church, or Congregation, (for most cleare it is, and best Pontificians deny it not, that of Rome hee prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieth) earst a Spouse, but after a Strmpet, (in respect of her spirituall aduoutries) first pure, but after most im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure; first Christian, but after Antichristian: (for her doctrines and practises, against the most pure doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, and humble conuersation of Christ) first with a cup of Christian simplicity in her hands, deuoid of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane dregs; but after, with a <note n="i" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> cup, full of abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and corruptions; with which, shee should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude all Nations, and Kingdomes of the earth: making merchandize &amp; negotiating with the souls of men: the
<pb facs="10"/> which, if it should not be already fulfilled in the Roman Church, it must bee heereafter at least, if the Prophet truly haue forespoken: The later of which, especiallie touching the merchandizing of soules in auarice, how clearlie it is already compleated, in the Roman Church; diuers earnest professors agreeing in all points of faith with the Romane Church in their times, will plainely<note place="margin">b In ementitam Constantini do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationem.</note> testifie: <note n="a" place="margin">Saepissime.</note> as <hi>Baptista, Mantuanus</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">In Henr. 3.</note>
      <hi>Valla, Rober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Lincolriensis</hi> in <seg rend="sup">c</seg>
      <hi>Matthew of Paris,</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">In Epist. 1. ad Titum.</note>
      <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Espencaeus, S.</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ab Cons. ad Eugenium.</note>
      <hi>Bernard,</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Constitut. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial pag. 39</note>
      <hi>Frederike</hi> the Emperour in his Epistle to all Prelates, <note n="g" place="margin">Baronius 992.</note>
      <hi>Arnulphus</hi> in a Synod at <hi>Rhemes</hi> in <hi>Baronius;</hi> and read <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> also in the yeere 912. where you shall find him affirming; how at the lust of whores, diuers Popes most wicked, luxurious, and auaricious, were thrust into Peters chaire; and how that custome lasted not for a short while only. <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Claudius Espen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caeus</hi> as hee is now set forth, is vvholly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, you must read his first E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</note> All these, with infinite others, do demonstrate the corruptions of the Roman Church, would God, effectually for the conuersion of seduced soules. Wherein, I can conceiue, no great hope; first, of all such popish seruants, as reape profitte, or liuing by that profession; nor of such children, as are vnder the command of some obstinate recusants: nor of any such bankrupts, and malecontents, as expect altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and long for troubled waters to fish in: nor of such scrupulous good soules, as will not dare to peruse, or read any part of holy Scripture (though of the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists Testament it selfe, falsified with their Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) lest they should proue Heretikes (as some of them haue told me) or else, remaine perplexed in their Cons<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciences: nor of some of their Priests, who are resolued
<pb facs="11"/> for the maintenance of their credit, conseruing of their meanes, and some such other respects, with their fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritesses (I meane, such like fauours as will mooue men to trauell vp to Rome, to procure dispensations for mariages; and yet in their absences and long pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, such painfull pilgrimes, notwithstanding strip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of their fauouritesses, by some of their own brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, which haue come betwixt them and home) are ready without examination of Scriptures, or Fathers, to receiue whatsoeuer the Roman Church shal obtrude vnto them. Neither may I conceiue hope of any such yonger persons who expect preferment, by <note n="h" place="margin">One of the most speciall practises of the Pontifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in <hi>England,</hi> to enlarge their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure matches in mariages: doe thou make the inferences, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader. There is a myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in it, if the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of young spirits be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly at such seasons are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther full of the heate of carnall loue, then of that fire which Christ came to send in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this world, <hi>Luk. 12.</hi>
      </note> matching into some stocke and family, the which as it abhorreth the reading of the Scriptures, so also is inueterated in Papistrie. My chiefest hope, may be of those, who as they are iudicious, so embrace that faith meerely out of conscience, and are nothing dependant of others; who either, through the peremptory, auaricious, facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and vnchast liues of their Priests; or generally, for the hatefull opposings and vncharitablenesse amongst them all; (by which they demonstrate themselues to be no disciples of Christ, whose proper badge and stemme is <note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 13.</note> dilection and loue of each other:) or else, through the vaine multiplicity of deuised fables and miracles, out of their old Legends: and withall through the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excusable ignorance of their Priests, in Gods sacred Scriptures (which I dare boldly affirme, is so great, that there are, scarse, a hundred amongst diuers hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreths of them, in this Kingdome, who can tell, either how many bookes there are of Gods Scripture, or how many Chapters there are in any of the bookes.) Or else,
<pb facs="11"/> through the inuallid successes, or euents of their vows, beeing either not heard, or not regarded by them, to whom they are made: or else, through the contiuuall disquietnesse, and torment of their consciences, in the <note n="*" place="margin">I disproue not' but highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the vse of Auricular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, when it is voluntary, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out sacrilege vsed, &amp; for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; not abused as the very means and cause by which sinners are iustified in the sight of God: much like as the Mexicans vsed Auricular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession. <hi>Botero Relationi vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sali. Part. 4. lib. 2. nel fine.</hi>
      </note> vse of their Sacrament of confession (as it is now by them most peruersly abused to the iniurie of Christ, &amp; subuersion of diuers soules) receiuing no <note n="*" place="margin">It is not imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consolable liues some (that are frequente in the vse of Confession, as necessary to saluation) doe lead, there is no stony heart, which would not pitie them, knowing their torments.</note> rest day nor night, <note n="k" place="margin">Ierem. 16</note> as seruing Gods who cannot giue it them, are growne into some distrust of the Romane Church. Of these might bee conceiued some iust hope of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersions, if they would vouchsafe either to read holie Scriptures, or else to read some learned bookes, written by some learned Priest or Preacher of the reformed and Catholike Churches, of Christendom: but I great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doubt they wil not dare, without leaue of their Priests so to doc: and I am most assured, that by them they shal neuer be permitted. A certaine Bishoppe of Italy, was not ashamed to tell <note n="l" place="margin">Claud Espene. Comeut in cap. 1 ad titum.</note>
      <hi>Claudius Espencaeus,</hi> a famous Pontifician, that the learned men in Italy it self, were afraid to study the holy Scriptures, (lest thereby they should become Heretikes) and that therefore they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed themselues in commenting vpon the Popes law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bookes, deerees, and the Decretals; (the which Booke, thoughfull of lies, contradictions, impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; yet because it is the Popes Booke it must be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected, whilest the holie Scripture lyeth as it were in the streetes neglected. But to these may not that of Christ be iustly obiected; (<hi>Serui nequam</hi>) wicked seruants, out of your owne mouthes I condemn you? Assuredly, these and like Italianized Prelates, (of<note place="margin">m Luk. 19.</note> which, for greatest number consisted the Tridentine
<pb facs="12"/> Councell) are none of those, who are reputed blessed by the Prophet <note n="n" place="margin">Psalm. 2</note>
      <hi>Dauid,</hi> for meditating in the law of God day and night. But to shorten this my letter, addressed vnto thee, Christian and Catholike Reader; I humblie request thee to accept with charitable interpretation these my Motiues, and to pray for my constancy in profession of Gods truth: I must needes confesse that I did find great difficulties in this my conuersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: First some suggestions (by Sathan suborned) how greatly this my conuersion would turne to my disesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, with all of the present Roman faith, and those my deare and old acquaintance, of whom I affirme, that they are vertuously disposed for whose saluations <hi>vtinam vt Anathema superimpenderer:</hi> Would God, to speake with the <note n="o" place="margin">Ad Rom. 9. &amp; 2. ad Corint. 12</note> Apostle, I might as an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natheme be sacrificed, yea offered and offered againe, so that they might be saued. Some other lesser difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties I found; all were humane, terrene: but when I considered that of the <note n="p" place="margin">Ad Galat. 1</note> Apostle, if I should seeke to pleasemen, I should not bee the seruant of Christ; and that of <note n="q" place="margin">Luk. 12</note> Christ; Seeke first the Kingdome of God, and the iustice thereof, and then all these things will bee added vnto you: I fully resolued for the charity, and <note n="r" place="margin">Ad Philip. 3</note> supereminent knowledge of Christ, to esteeme all that is in the world as verie dung, and rather to dwell poore <note n="s" place="margin">Psal. 83</note> in the house of God, then to dwell in the rich Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of sinners: And in this my resolution I was somewhat the more confirmed, in respect, that from my verie youth; euen then, when I was too too zealous an Emulator of all Romane superstitions: I haue euer had often suggestions, and inspirations in my mind,
<pb facs="12"/> that a time would come, when I should be calumniated, and greatly abused by the Papists, and persecuted by the Pope himselfe, whom I then admired as an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Oracle vpon earth: but most of all I was filled with such foreapprehensions, and presages (being in Rome) vpon <note n="t" place="margin">
         <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1594 the 20. of <hi>June.</hi>
      </note> the same day and houre, when that glorious and renowned Christian <hi>Marsh</hi> suffered the cutting off, of his right hand; the gagging of his mouth (by the Counsel of the Ignatian <hi>Cowlin,</hi> who boasteth himself thereof in England) after that, the pulling, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and burning of his flesh with hote glowing pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers for many howres together, thorow many streetes, of the City of Rome; and lastly death it selfe by fire; with such admirable patience and constancy, that the Romanes themselues did greatly admire him therfore. His act, for which hee was so tormented, was, because hee had throwne downe their Sacrament, as it was publikely carried thorow the streetes of Rome in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Procession, to be adored, worshipped and inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as God himselfe (an idolatrous superstition latelie crept into that Church, contrary to the custom and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of all auncient Churches whatsoeuer.) And yet notwitstanding all such suggestions, and inspirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at that time (which I constantly reiected as temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations) I did, beeing earnestly intreated and vrged thereunto by the Superiours of the English Colledge, make an Oration, and a most vehement <note n="*" place="margin">This Oration was ready pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I had little aboue a day to prouide my selfe for the prpnoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing thereof, before, so pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like an Audience.</note> inuectiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst that fact of his, in the presence of diuers Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals and Prelates; assembled together, in the English Church, to keepe a solemne Masse of the Sacrament, some moneth after the death of that glorious Christian.
<pb facs="13"/> But what may I now (vpon this euent) interpret those presages, inspirations, and forewarnings, else to haue been, then sweet motions, and inducements from him; who as I trust hath segregated mee, to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell of his beloued Sonne Iesus? the which then I passed ouer with a deafe eare, but his goodnesse vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safing now, to open my eare; I may not contradict, but blesse him eternally, for that he hath made me a child of <note n="u" place="margin">Ad Rom. 8. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t. 2</note> adoption, of acquisition, and election: beleeuing with <note n="x" place="margin">Ad Rom 10.</note> heart, and confessing with mouth, for my iustification and saluation onely, and alonely in Iesus Christ. But before I conclude, I intreat the Courteous Reader, that <note n="y" place="margin">Ad Galat. 5. Iacob. 2.</note> both by faith and conuersation; by godly <note n="z" place="margin">Act. 2</note> frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the most venerable Sacrament, of Christs body and bloud; by deuout <note n="a" place="margin">Ad Col. 3. &amp; Jacob. 1</note> attendance, and hearkning to Gods word, so daily, so clearely, so liuely preached in this Kingdome; by daily <note n="b" place="margin">Psal. 1.</note> meditating in Gods holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and aboue all by conseruing his soule <note n="c" place="margin">Jacob. 1. &amp; 2. Pet. 3. Luk. 8 Matth. 3</note> impolluted from alliniquity of sinne, and the contagion of al world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly desires, and solicitudes; by exercising <note n="d" place="margin">2. Ad Corint. 9</note> chearefully, plentifullie, all charitable offices, to all such as are in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and necessity; by keeping his bodie <note n="e" place="margin">1. Ad Thess. 4</note> a cleare vessell from all impurity, and impudicity; and his tongue from all scurrill <note n="f" place="margin">Ad Ephes. 5 Ad Rom. 13</note> and vnseemely speeches; seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously to endeauour to make <note n="g" place="margin">2. Pet. 2</note> sure his vocation; and to <note n="h" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> stop the mouthes of such, who in respect that some of the reformed Churches (especially of the Clergy) liue not conformably to their doctrine, do blaspheme the sacred Truth of Christs immaculate Gospell. I haue seene much into the liues of the Aduerse part; the which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, I find to bee more impure, auaricious, proud,
<pb facs="13"/> vncharitable, then euer I could haue imagined; yet that is not the cause, why I left them, but the impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, abominations, and superstitious impertinencies of their doctrines, worships, laws, and customes; which my soule hateth: assuring it selfe, that if I should still continue, in communion with them, I could haue no part with Christ my Sauiour: to whom, for hauing most mercifully <note n="i" place="margin">2. Ad Corint. 5.</note> reconciled mee, to his Father in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, bee onely, and alonely, with his Father and the holie Ghost, Honour and Glorie, for euer, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in Christ Iesus, R. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>