<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VER∣TVOVS, HIGH, AND MIGHTIE PRINCE KING IAMES, OVR DRED SOVERAIGNE, BY THE GRACE OF GOD, KING of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, defender of the Faith, &amp;c. long life, happie daies, and most prosperous raigne.</title>
           <author>Robinson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101591_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10857</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21128</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101591</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VER∣TVOVS, HIGH, AND MIGHTIE PRINCE KING IAMES, OVR DRED SOVERAIGNE, BY THE GRACE OF GOD, KING of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, defender of the Faith, &amp;c. long life, happie daies, and most prosperous raigne.</title>
                 <author>Robinson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The schoole of musicke : wherein is taught, the perfect method, of true fingering of the lute, pandora, orpharion, and viol de gamba; with most infallible generall rules, both easie and delightfull. Also, a method, how you may be your owne instructer for prick-song, by th help of your lute, without any other teacher: with lessons of all sorts, for your further and better instruction. Newly composed by Thomas Robinson, lutenist</title>
                 <author>Robinson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, music, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVOVS, HIGH, AND MIGHTIE PRINCE KING IAMES, OVR DRED SOVERAIGNE, BY THE GRACE OF GOD, KING of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> defender of the Faith, &amp;c. long life, happie daies, and most prosperous raigne.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S there is not any thing in this world more acceptable vnto God, (most gracious Soueraigne) then a contrite heart: so I presume that there is not any thing in this world (next to the loue of God) more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto your Majestie, then a true and loyall subject. Thus vsing this perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, for a sure argument of your Majesties gracious acceptance, I presume to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest my selfe, a most true and loyall sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject vnto your Majestie. In token where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I haue gathered the chiefe of my treasurie, the which in most humble and obedient manner, I present vnto your Highnesse: beseeching your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse not to mislike your subject, for the subject, sith it is for the good of all your Majesties louing subjects. The <hi>Art</hi> is deuine, the <hi>Jnstrument</hi> laudable, my <hi>Meaning</hi> good, my <hi>Skill</hi> drownde in the depth of <hi>Catoes</hi> wordes (who saith) <hi>Nec te collaudes, nec te culpaueris ipse.</hi> And yet I can say for my selfe, that once I was thought (in <hi>Denmarke</hi> at <hi>Elsanure)</hi> the fittest to instruct your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Queene, our most gracious Ladie and Mistres.</p>
   <p>Thus prostrating my selfe at your Majesties feet, incessantlie crauing pardon for my bold attempt, I rest. Restles in praier, for your Graces wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, both now and euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Majesties most loyall and obedient subject, Thomas Robinson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>