<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101856_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15051</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25355</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101856</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Peri ydroposias: or, a discourse of waters : their qualities, and effects diæteticall, pathologicall, and pharmacaiticall. By Tobias Whitaker, doctor in physicke of Norwich</title>
                 <author>Whitaker, Tobias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Grismand (Grismond), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 159, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the first view this sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject may seem light, simple, and scarce worth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; but whenas you have consulted with your second
<pb facs="3"/>thoughts, you cannot but confesse, that our whole beeing in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the same, doth depend upon the right use and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of water, as being so necessary in meates and drinkes, as also in medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental compositions, which cannot but be a matter of very great consequence, since no natural good
<pb facs="3"/>can bee equall to life and health, which is lost or injoyed by the ill disposition of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ayre. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to offer a sacrifice more grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and acceptable to my Countrey, and dearest friends, I have indeavoured to wade throgh springs, pools, moats, moores, as also the sea (which is the wombe of them
<pb facs="4"/>all) And that I may guide both my selfe and others safely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver these Washes, no lesse dangerous then the rocks and quick-sands of the Ocean, therfore I have bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed a light from those ancient guides which have steered the course so many hundreds of yeares without shipwracke. This stile and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod are answerable
<pb facs="4"/>to my intentiō, which is onely to informe strangers in our art, without prejudice to the same, considering that I have inabled no man any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, then to defend himselfe, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve his health by the choice of a whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some situation in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of water, which is so usefull in the whole course of his life, and so dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,
<pb facs="5"/>if proceeding from an unwholsome earth, whether used in medicament or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et: For this cause I have clad my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course in such robes as are most fashiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the place and persons, to whom it is chiefely intended: and although <hi>Suum cuique pulchrum,</hi> bee the common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe, and that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans owne childe
<pb facs="5"/>seemes to himselfe the fairest, howsoere ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled; yet in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (whatsoever o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise my affection is) I cā admire beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in others more lovely then my owne; and will bee bold to taxe censorious spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, chiefely in such as never yet were fruitful themselves: not knowing but that their owne birthes may prove as mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous
<pb facs="6"/>and deformed as any; and also o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who out of a cōtentious spirit shall oppose any positive truth, or indeavour to raise their owne names by the defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming others more worthy then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves: for example, who is ignorant of that subtle <hi>Argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius,</hi> as also with what malignity and contentious spirit he
<pb facs="6"/>doth oppose the solid &amp; learned doctrine of <hi>Galen;</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing there is a liberty of exception granted to all wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and hath beene practised by all both ancient and modern, as is extant in many volumes, where wee plainly see the scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler at foyles with the Master, and one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with another; which were a new la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb facs="7"/>and would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire another tract to make particular demonstration: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to avoyde all strife, I have chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laboured to shews plainely the ancient opinions, practice, &amp; use of this subject, as it may conduce to the preser vatiō of health generation of sicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and recover of the same; and from hence to teacl
<pb facs="7"/>how dangerous it may be to forsake the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten roade or path, in which the ancient Worthies have safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walked so many ages, losing our selus &amp; dangerously mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leading others into unknowne wayes, which cannot but be doubtfull, how ever wee escape. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in thus doing I have given offence to any, tis beside my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
<pb facs="8"/>or desire; if otherwise I have not, then I have the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of my time and labour, which might have been more neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently spent: yet had I desired to shew my selfe, rather then make good the just requests of my spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall friends, then J would have chosen another part, which I suppose might have beene better acted;
<pb facs="8"/>but lest the Gates should exceede the Citie, I take my leave.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Tobias Whitaker,</hi> Doctor in Physicke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>