<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Courteus Readers.</title>
           <author>R., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101923_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10809</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21082</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101923</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Courteus Readers.</title>
                 <author>R., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Honours conquest : Wherein is conteined the famous hystorie of Edward of Lancaster recounting his honourable trauailes to Ierusalem, his heroic adventures and honours, in sundrie countries gained: his resolutions, and attempts in armes. With the famous victories performed b the knight, of the vnconquered castel, a gallant English knight, his admirable forces, and sundrie conquests obtained, with his passions and sucesse in loue: full of pleasant discourses, and much varietie. VVriten by H.R</title>
                 <author>H. R. (Henry Roberts)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Danter, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>140 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>To the Courteus Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ike as the Load-stone pointeth at the immoueable poles of Heauen, and will not lye still otherwise: so true generous and noble mindes euer ayme at vertue, and esteeme their noble houses by them halfe stayned, vnlesse in valorous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wesse, wise policies, and kinde courtesies, they equal themselues to, (if not surpasse) the most famous of their Progenitors, yea of all whereof memoriall is extant: by which their worthie endeuors they liue in most great honourable reputation in this world, and after do liue by fame euerlastingly. Among which famous worthies, this <hi>Edward</hi> of <hi>Lancaster</hi> here mētioned, deserueth not the least praise or prise. And if any will alleage, that in this Poeticall praising of him, there be many fictions (as, <hi>Poetis et pictoribus permagna conceditur licentia)</hi> let such learne to reade these manner of bookes, as <hi>Socrates</hi> wished women to vse their looking glasses; namely, fairewomen, to look on their glasses, to beware that their good maners may shine as well as their beautie; and
<pb facs="2"/>
      <pb facs="2"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>ill-fauoured women, to indeuour that their inward vertues might make gratious theyr outward defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. So let Gentlemen by reading these bookes obserue therein onelye those things, the practise whereof may innoble them more and more, and the baser and cowardly sort, here learne onely what may promote them: And thus wishing the ende of all thy reading to bee to attaine true vertue, I wish thee an eternall reward of glorie. Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>