<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Congratulation to the Muses, for the im∣mortalizing of his deare Father, by the sacred Vertue of Poetry.</title>
           <author>Beaumont, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101234_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06468</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1694</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101234</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Congratulation to the Muses, for the im∣mortalizing of his deare Father, by the sacred Vertue of Poetry.</title>
                 <author>Beaumont, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Bosvvorth-field : with a taste of the variety of other poems, left by Sir Iohn Beaumont, Baronet, deceased: set forth by his sonne, Sir Iohn Beaumont, Baronet; and dedicated to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Beaumont, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 180, 183-208 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>A Congratulation to the Muses, for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalizing of his deare Father, by the sacred Vertue of Poetry.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>YE heau'nly Sisters, by whose sacred skill,</l>
      <l>Sweet sounds are rays'd vpon the forked hill</l>
      <l>Of high <hi>Parnassus:</hi> You, whose tuned strings</l>
      <l>Can cause the Birds to stay their nimble wings,</l>
      <l>And silently admire: before whose feet,</l>
      <l>The Lambs, as fearelesse, with the Lions meet.</l>
      <l>You, who the Harpe of <hi>Orpheus</hi> so inspir'd,</l>
      <l>That from the Stygian Lake he safe retir'd;</l>
      <l>You could <hi>Amphions</hi> Harpe with vertue fill,</l>
      <l>That euen the stones were pliant to his will.</l>
      <l>To you, you therefore I my Verse direct,</l>
      <l>From whom such beames celestiall can reflect</l>
      <l>On that deare Author of my life inspir'd</l>
      <l>VVith heauenly heate, and sacred Fury fir'd;</l>
      <l>VVhose Vigour, quencht by death, you now reuiue,</l>
      <l>And in this Booke conserue him still aliue.</l>
      <l>Here liues his better part, here shines that Flame,</l>
      <l>VVhich lights the entrance to eternall Fame.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="7"/>These are his Triumphs ouer death, this Spring</l>
      <l>From <hi>Aganippe's</hi> Fountaines he could bring</l>
      <l>Cleare from all drosse, through pure intentions drain'd,</l>
      <l>His draughts no sensuall waters euer stain'd.</l>
      <l>Behold, he doth on euery paper strow</l>
      <l>The loyall thoughts he did his Sou'raigne owe.</l>
      <l>Here rest affections to each neerest friend,</l>
      <l>And pious sighs, which noble thoughts attend;</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Parnassus</hi> him containes, plast in the Quire</l>
      <l>With Poets: what then can we more desire</l>
      <l>To haue of him? Perhaps an empty voyce,</l>
      <l>While him we wrong with our content lesse choyce,</l>
      <l>To you I this attribute, Sisters nine;</l>
      <l>For onely you can cause this VVorke diuine;</l>
      <l>By none but you could these bright fires be found;</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Prometheus</hi> is not from the Rocke vnbound,</l>
      <l>No <hi>Aesculapius</hi> still remaines on earth,</l>
      <l>To giue <hi>Hippolitus</hi> a second birth.</l>
      <l>Since then such Godlike pow'rs in you remaine,</l>
      <l>To worke these wonders, let some soule containe</l>
      <l>His spirit of sweet musicke, and infuse</l>
      <l>Into some other brest his sparkling Muse.</l>
      <l>But you perhaps, that all your pow'r may speake:</l>
      <l>VVill chuse to worke on subiects dull and weake:</l>
      <l>Chuse me, inspire my frozen brest with heat,</l>
      <l>No Deed you euer wrought, can seeme more great.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Iohn Beaumont.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>