<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Letter of G. P. to R. B. concerning this woorke.</title>
           <author>P., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101441_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09539</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19819</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101441</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Letter of G. P. to R. B. concerning this woorke.</title>
                 <author>P., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A petite pallace of Pettie his pleasure : contaynyng many pretie hystories by him set foorth in comely colours, and most delightfully discoursed</title>
                 <author>Pettie, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Watkins, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 224 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Letter of G. P. to R. B. concerning this woorke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orced by your ernest importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and furthered by mine owne idle opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, I haue set downe in writinge, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to your request, sent vnto you cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of those Tragicall trifles, whiche you haue heard mee in sundrie companies at sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye times report, and so neare as I could I haue written them word for word as I then told them: but if any of them seeme bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto you now then they did then, you must attribute it to my lisping lips, which perchaunce did somewhat disgrace the grace of them: and yf any seeme worse now then than, you must impute it to this, that perchaunce there was then some <hi>Pallas</hi> in place which furthered my inuention. For I am in that point of <hi>Ouid</hi> his opinion, that, <hi>Si cupiat sponte disertus erit.</hi> But whether they seeme vnto you good or ill, I trust you will take them as a token of good will, and that is the onely commoditie I looke to reape by them. I pray you only to vse them to your owne priuate pleasure, and not to impart them to other, perchaunce to my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice, for that diuers discourses touch neerely diuers of my nere freindes: but the best is, they are so darkely figured forth, that only they whom they touch, can vnderstand whom they touch: yet to auoide all captious constructions, I pray you in any wise let them bee an obiect only for your owne eyes. If this mislike you in my discourses, that I make <hi>Camma,</hi> vse the example of the countesse of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> the Dutches of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> and sutch who were of far later yeeres, then the auncient <hi>CAMMA</hi> is, with the like in diuers other of the stories: you must consider that my <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> is of fresher memory then any of them, and I thinke in your iudgment, of fresher hew then the fayrest of them. Likewise, if you like not of some wordes and phrases, vsed contrary to their common custome, you must thinke, that seeing wee allowe of new fashions in cutting of beardes, in long wasted doublets, in litle short hose, in great cappes, in low hattes, and almost in al things, it is as mutch reason wee should allow of new fashions in phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
<pb facs="4"/>
and wordes. But these faultes, or whatsoeuer els, I care not to excuse vnto you, who are the only cause I cōmitted them, by your ernest desire to haue mee set downe these trifles in writing. And as my wordes hytherto haue tended to this end, that you should take these trifles well, so now I am to exhort you that you will vse them well: that with the spider you sucke not out poyson out of them: that by some light example you bee not the sooner inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to lightnesse. For beleeue mee (I speake it freindly, therefore take it freindly) I thinke it more needfull to send you a bridell then a spur that way. And if my example may bee a bridle to restraine you from vanity, doe but imitate mee hereafter, or if my counsayle may containe you in continency, doe but follow this aduise: if you bee free, that you come not into bondes: if you bee bound, <hi>vt te redimas captum quam queas minimo:</hi> for trust me, the broad blasphemy of <hi>Pigmalion,</hi> and the sodain <hi>Aposta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> or rather right conuersion of <hi>Alexius,</hi> haue setled me in this fayth, that I thinke him <hi>Ter{que} quater{que} beatum, qui a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sortio mulierum se cohibere potest.</hi> You meruayle, I am sure to heare these wordes of mee, and that I should so soone turne my tippet and recant, who but yesterday, as it were, entred into heresy. But beleeue mee (my B.) <hi>nunquàm nimis citò est ad bonos mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res via. Qui non est hodié, cras minus aptus erit.</hi>
   </p>
   <lg>
      <l>Principiis obsta, serò medicina paratur,</l>
      <l>Cum mala per longas conualuere moras.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Errare humanum est, in errore perseuerare, belluinum.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>Sinnes oft assaied, are thought to be no sinne:</l>
      <l>So sinne doth soyle the Soule it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eth in.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Thus haue I sent you in that booke some fruites of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer folly, and in this letter the profession of my present fayth, desiring you to vse the one to your honest pleasure, and to follow the other to your godly profite. I meane▪ god willing, the next spring to goe on pilgrimage with <hi>Alexius,</hi> and if you were so deuoutly disposed, I should thinke my selfe most happy to haue sutch a companyon. Frō my lodging in Houlburn this. 12. of Iuly.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Tuus semper, aut suus nunquàm: Omnia in mundo, immunda. G. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>