<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVL, THE MASTER, WARDENS, AND Assistants of the Companie of Carpenters of the Citie of London: And to all other the curteous Readers.</title>
           <author>More, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101895_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07688</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18075</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101895</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WORSHIPFVL, THE MASTER, WARDENS, AND Assistants of the Companie of Carpenters of the Citie of London: And to all other the curteous Readers.</title>
                 <author>More, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The carpenters rule, or, a booke shewing many plain waies, truly to measure ordinarie timber, and other extraordinarie sollids, or timber : with a detection of sundrie great errors, generally committed by carpenters and others in measuring of timber; tending much to the buyers great losse. Published especially for the good of the Companie of Carpenters in London, and others also; ... By Richard More carpenter</title>
                 <author>More, Richard, carpenter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 56 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVL, THE MASTER, WARDENS, AND Assistants of the Companie of Carpenters of the Citie of London: And to all other the curteous Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had long considered, and that not without some griefe, the great losse that commeth to those of my Companie and others, by errors or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily committed in measuring of timber; I did often thinke with my selfe what might be the readiest course to redresse them. One while I thought to haue declared to you the Master and Wardens, what errors I had obserued in our ordinarie measure, and so to haue desired you in all dutie to haue prouided a remedie. But when I perceiued, that custome had caused error to be receiued as a truth, and that therefore men would not forsake them, vnlesse they were plainly conuinced to haue erred: And when I did also see, that most men are very ignorant in true measure, though they seeme and professe to know much therein; and did also remember that not only Carpenters in this Citie doe in this sort erre, but also Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters elsewhere, as also Shipwrights &amp; others, and that throughout the whole land, for the most part: then this course seemed to me to be too priuate, and such as was like to doe but little good. The best course that I could thinke vpon, was, to publish some booke, wherein not onely true measure should be set downe, but also the common errors plainly laid open to the capacitie of the simplest; that so all men might take knowledge thereof.</p>
   <p>My selfe I knew to be very vnfit for this worke, both because of mine inabilitie, as also by reason of some exceptions that diuers
<pb facs="4"/>might take against me, to their owne hindrance and my discourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But when I saw none addressed hereunto then (remembring the saying of a Heathen, <hi>that men are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> for themselues, but for their Countrey</hi>) I did set aside all lets, and both boldly and rudely haue put out this my simple booke, in manner as you see.</p>
   <p>The booke I haue diuided into three parts. In the first part I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the errors most commonly committed, and taken for truth, in measuring of timber. In the second part I shew how ordinarie timber may be measured, both by sundrie plaine waies, as also by waies more artificiall. And in the third part I shew, how extraordinarie timber and sollid formes may be measured.</p>
   <p>The errors ordinarily committed in measuring timber, are many. But of them all, especially two, bringeth losse to the buyer. The first is by buying of waynie timber and measuring it as square. The other is by taking halfe the breadth and thicknes of a peece being added together, for the square thereof.</p>
   <p>These errors are such, as bring apparant dammage: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are not to be respected lightly. I would they might not bee said to be a great cause, if not of the ouerthrow, yet of the impairing of some mens estates.</p>
   <p>For as for wainie timber, who knowes not, that as it is often mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured and hewed, a loade and a halfe will not goe so farre in vse, as a loade of good timber being well hewed and iustly measured.</p>
   <p>And as for haluing the summe of the two sides for the square, the dammage hereby is exceeding much; not onely to those that buy much Timber at the first hand, but also, and that especially (which is the more pitie) to the poorer sort that buy at the second hand. For my selfe haue abated of that which workmen themselues haue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured a peece vnto by the foresaid false way, after <hi>3, 4, 5,</hi> yea <hi>6</hi> foote of timber in <hi>20:</hi> and yet I haue giuen them no more then their measure.</p>
   <p>I cannot stand to amplifie these errors in this place: they are more fully set downe in the booke it selfe. By which (if they be well weighed and considered vpon) it will plainly appeare to be true as I haue said, namely, that there commeth great losse by the ordinarie measuring of timber.</p>
   <p>Now seeing the case so stands, my desire and request is, euen to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb facs="4"/>man, but especially to you the Master, Wardens, and Assistants of our Companie; that you would put your helping hand to reforme these errors. Many reasons might be alleaged to induce you hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but for some reasons best knowne to my selfe, I omit them all, not doubting of your care and regard hereunto.</p>
   <p>I haue heard some men wish, that wee had an act of Parliament procured for redresse of false measure. But truly that seemeth to be the law of our land alreadie, though not the statute law: for the law intendeth that the buyer should haue that which he buyeth. And when we buy a loade of timber, doe we not intend that we haue bought <hi>50.</hi> foote of sollid timber, euery foote being full <hi>12.</hi> inches euery way, that is, in length, breadth &amp; thicknes? Why then may we not require so much for a loade, and why is not the seller bound to deliuer it? And if a man that buyeth twentie bushels of wheate, will not take ninteene; or if he buy a yard of cloath, he will not take three quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: Then why should we (buying a loade of timber) take <hi>40.</hi> foote for it, yea and lesse too (as oft times it fals out) whereas wee should haue <hi>50.</hi> foote.</p>
   <p>I know that many men will obiect many things; and it is not for me at this time to refute them. Onely whereas some may say, that what is wanting in the measure, is allowed in the price. I answere: <hi>1.</hi> That is not alwaies. <hi>2.</hi> But where allowance is made, it is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the value of the losse comming by the false measure. <hi>3.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it is a preposterous course, to raise or let fall a price by altering of a set measure to an vncertaintie, whereas we vse in all trades to raise or let fall the price according to the goodnes or badnes of the wares, keeping stil the same measure for them both. And surely here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are but deceiued: For oft times we haue twelue pence bated in the price of a loade, and lose foure or fiue shillings in the measure thereof.</p>
   <p>Therefore let vs either haue iust measure, if we buy by measure; or els let vs buy it by gesse. For it is a shame to pretend to measure truly, and yet doe nothing lesse.</p>
   <p>As touching my selfe, I desire that my endeuour may be fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably accepted: for I write with no other mind then as tendring my Companies good. If any thing that I haue said, be impugned as false, I will be readie whensoeuer you will call me, to proue my affirmations.
<pb facs="5"/>If any man of knowledge shall except against me, for my rude writing and grosse demonstrations: I pray them to vnderstand, that I writ not for them, but for the simple; and therfore I demonstrate grossely, not being well able to doe better: Also, that I am not a scholler but a Carpenter, and therefore could not but write rudely. Vnto such also I doe further say, that my desire is, that they would take knowledge, that this hath been one cause of my writing, euen to prouoke them (seeing our present error and losse, with which peraduenture they were not so well acquainted as my selfe) to take some paines to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the same, in better sort then either I haue or can doe.</p>
   <p>While this booke was in printing I came to the sight of a Ruler, sometimes inuented by one Master <hi>Bedwel;</hi> which as it is easie, so it is most speedie, and not lesse certaine (being truly made) for the measuring of timber and boord; which I expect and hope will be shortly published for the common good. But I will not trouble you with more words. Onely let me put you in minde of this one thing: That in as much as nothing is more fit for Carpenters to make them readie, not only in measure but also in other things, then Geometrie: that therefore such as are of reasonable capacitie, would spend some part of their spare times to studie the same, in some measure at the least. For your furtherance herein, there are especiall good helps, both by the Lecture at <hi>Gresham</hi> Colledge euery Thursday in the Terme times (if you were but a little entered) as also by <hi>Euclides</hi> Elements of Geometrie, which the right Worshipfull Sir <hi>Henry Billingsley</hi> Knight, to the great good of the Common-wealth, though to his own great trauell and charge, hath translated and published in our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish tongue. But I am ouer tedious: I pray you accept of this my poore endeuour, as a fruit of my heartie good will to my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and others whom it may concerne. If it take none effect, I shall be sorrie: but if it doe any good, I haue enough for my labour.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>RICHARD MORE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>