<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentle Reader.</title>
           <author>Saunders, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101651_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11529</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21778</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101651</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentle Reader.</title>
                 <author>Saunders, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true discription and breefe discourse, of a most lamentable voiage, made latelie to Tripolie in Barbarie, in a ship named the Iesus : vvherin is not onely shevved the great miserie, that then happened the aucthor hereof and his whole companie, aswell the marchants as th marriners in that voiage, according to the curssed custome of those barbarous and cruell tyrants, in their terrible vsage of Christian captiues: but also, the great vnfaithfulnesse of those heathnish infidels, in not regarding their promise. Together, with the most wonderfull iudgement of God, vpo the king of Tripolie and his sonne, and a great number of his people, being all the tormentors of those English captiues. Set foorth by Thomas Saunders, one of those captiues there at the same time</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>GEntle Reader, I haue here presented to thy vew, (although of my selfe altogether vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, yet wonne with the earnestnesse of such (my friendes) as I might not withstand) the true reporte of my troubles and of diuers others my Companions and fellowes in <hi>Tripolie,</hi> vnder the <hi>Turkes</hi> dominion, which I had thought at the first setting downe in paper, should neuer haue bin put in print, but notwithstanding now, I commit it to thy fauourable consideration, and (I hope) to thy benefit and good liking. Beseeching thee to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me for such faultes as I haue groselie ouerslip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, considering alwaies that trueth needeth no fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led termes: If there be anie thing that deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thee I haue my desire, if otherwise, friendlie controule, and then wil I rest content, and so farewel.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to vse, Thomas Saunders.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>