<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>PROEMIAL ANNOTATIONS vpon the Booke of Psalmes.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101944_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11777</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2207</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101944</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>PROEMIAL ANNOTATIONS vpon the Booke of Psalmes.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The holie Bible faithfully translated into English, out of the authentical Latin. Diligently conferred with the Hebrew, Greeke, and other editions in diuers languages. With arguments of the bookes, and chapters: annotations. tables: and other helpes ... By the English College of Doway</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2 volumes (20, 1115, 1, 1004, 1, 1002-1124, 4 pages), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="3" facs="571"/>
   <head>PROEMIAL ANNOTATIONS vpon the Booke of Psalmes.</head>
   <p>THE authoritie of this Booke was euer authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,<note place="margin">This booke vndoubtedly is canonical Scripture.</note> and certaine, as the assured word of God, and Canonical Scripture. But concerning the author, there be diuers opinions. For although it be manifest by the testimonie of Philo, and Iosephus, that in their time,<note place="margin">Late Hebrew Doctors and some Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques hold di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers authors of sundry Psalmes.</note> and alwaies before, only King Dauid was by al Hebrew Doctors holden for Author of al the Psalmes: yet after that lerned Origen, and other Christian Doctors, expounded manie Psalmes of Christ, the Iewes being pressed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, begane to denie that al were Dauids: alleaging for their new opinion, the titles of diuers Psalmes, and some other difficulties, ministring occasion of much needles dispute, stil acknowledging the whole booke to be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical. Wherupon S. Ierom, and S. Augustin, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times<note place="margin">Prefat. in Psal. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. 134. 139.</note> admitted those as authores of certaine Psalmes, whose names are in the titles thereof. S. Cyprian, S. Cyril, S. Athanasius, and others agree in general, that Dauid writte not al: but differ much in particular, touching other supposed authores. In so much that <hi>Melchisedech; Moyses, Asaph, Eman, Idithun, The sonnes of Core, Salomon, Ieremie, Ezechiel, Esdras, Aggaeus, and Zacharias, are al</hi> (<hi>with</hi> more or lesse probabilitie) <hi>reputed authores of seueral Psalmes.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles<note place="margin">It is much more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that Dauid was author of al.</note> it semeth that S. Ierom rather related other mens iudgement, then shewed his owne; as we shal note by and by. And S. Augustin (<hi>li.</hi> 17. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>de ciuit</hi>) maturely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussing this doubt, saith plainly, that <hi>their Iudgement semed</hi>
      <note place="margin">Proued by S. Augustin, S. Chrysostom, and greatest part of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors.</note>
      <hi>to him more credible, vvho attribute al the hundred fiftie Psalmes to Dauid alone.</hi> Further explicating that wheras some Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes haue Dauids owne name in their titles, some haue other mens names, some none at al, <hi>this diuersitie importeth</hi>
      <pb n="4" facs="572"/>
      <hi>not diuers authores, but signifieth other thinges, either perteyning to the same persons, or by interpretation of their names, belonging to the present matter, as our Lord inspired him.</hi> Likewise S. Chrysostome resolutely iudgeth, that only King Dauid was author of this whole Booke. Moued especially by this argument, for that Christ and the Apostles alleaging the<note place="margin">Mat. 22. v. 16. Act. 4. v. 24. Ro. 4. v. 6. Ro 11. v. 9. Heb. 4. v. 7.</note> Psalmes, do oftentimes name Dauid as author, and neuer anie other. Also Origen, S. Basil, S. Ambrose, S. Hilarie,<note place="margin">The common voice of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians &amp; some general coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, cal it Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids Psalter.</note> Theodoretus, Cassiodorus, Beda, Eutimius, and most part of ancient and late writers, with the most common voice of Christians, cal this booke the Psalmes of Dauid: and the General Councels of Carthage, Florence, and Trent, in the Cathologue of Canonical Scriptures recite this booke, by the name of Dauids Psalter.</p>
   <p>Moreouer it is clere, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. that the second Psalme, though it want his name, is Dauids. And other Scriptures<note place="margin">Proued by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> 2. <hi>Paral. 7. v.</hi> 6. and 1. <hi>Esd. 3. v.</hi> 10. say plainly, that Dauid made the Psalmes, 104. 105. 106. 117. 135. beginning: <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse to our Lord, because he is good, because his mercie is for euer.</hi> VVhich he appointed the Leuites to sing, or play on instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: 1 <hi>Paral.</hi> 15. &amp;. 16. and yet they haue not his name in their titles. Againe, 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 23. <hi>Dauid</hi> is only intitled <hi>the egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,</hi> or excellent <hi>Psalmist of Israel.</hi> Neither were Asaph, Eman, and Idithun anie where called Prophetes (as are al the writers of holie Scriptures) but only masters of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sike, 1. <hi>Paral.</hi> 25. And the sonnes of Core were only porters. 1. <hi>Paral.</hi> 26. Finally S. Ierom (whose iudgement the whole Church singularly estemeth, in al questions belonging to holie Scriptures) semeth as much inclined, that only the Royal Prophet Dauid was author of this whole booke, as to the contrarie. For in his Epistle to Paulinus, prefixed before the Latin Bible, comprehending the principal ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments<note place="margin">S Ierom attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buteth the summe of this booke to Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid only.</note> of seueral bookes, when he cometh to the Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, without mention of other authors, saith: <hi>Dauid our Simonides, Pindarus, and Alceus; Flaccus also, Catullus, and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renus,</hi>
      <pb n="5" facs="572"/>
      <hi>soundeth out Christ, vvith harpe &amp; tenne stringed Psalter, rising vp from hel:</hi> so attributing the summe of this whole booke to the Royal Prophet Dauid, as if he supposed no other author.</p>
   <p>Touching therfore the argument, or contentes of this<note place="margin">The Psalmes are a Summe of al other Scriptures.</note> diuine Psalter, al Catholique Doctors vniformly agree that it is the abridgement, summe, and substance of al holie Scriptures, both old and new Testament. As may first be probably collected, by that Christ himselfe often compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending al the old Testament by the termes of the Law and Prophetes, in one place (<hi>Luc. 24. v.</hi> 44.) semeth not<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 7. 11. 22. Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 16.</note> onlie to reduce al to <hi>the Lavv and Prophetes iointly,</hi> but also to <hi>the Psalmes alone,</hi> or seuerally. But whether this be our Sauiours diuine meaning or no in that place, out of this and manie other places, al the ancient Fathers teach expresly, that the Psalmes are an Epitome of al other holie Scriptures. For example, S. Denys, <hi>li de Eccles. Hierar. contemplat.</hi> 2. after brief recital of the contents of other holie Scriptures, saith: <hi>This sacred booke of diuine Canticles, doth exhibite both a general song, and exposition of diuine thinges.</hi> S. Basil calleth the <hi>Psalmodie of Dauid the common and most plentiful storehouse of al sacred doctrine: the treasure of perfect Theologie. S. Ambrose accounteth it the register of the vvhole Scripture.</hi> Origen, S. Cyprian S. Ierom, S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostom,<note place="margin">S. Greg. in Psal. penitent.</note> S. Gregorie, S. Beda S. Bernard, Cassiodorus, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timius, and others vse the same, or very like termes. S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin particularly distinguishing al the Scriptures into foure sortes of bookes, sheweth that the Psalmes conteyne<note place="margin">They cōteine the summe of Legal, Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical, Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiential, and Prophetical doctrine.</note> al: <hi>The Lavv</hi> (saith he) <hi>teacheth somethinges, the Historie some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinges, the Prouerbes also and Prophetes teach somethinges: but the Booke of Psalmes teacheth al. It proposeth the lavv, recounteth thinges of old, prescribeth the due ordering of mens actions, and prophecieth thinges to come. Briefly it is a common treasure of good doctrine, aptly administring that is necessarie to euerie one.</hi> And a litle after, exemplifying in particular points: <hi>Is not here</hi> (saith
<pb n="6" facs="573"/>
he) <hi>al greatnes of vertue, and is not here the right square of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice? is not the comlines of chastitie; the consummation of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence? is not vvhatsoeuer may be called good, lerned in the Psalmes? Here is the knovvlege of God; the clere prenounciation of Christ to come in flesh; the hope of general Resurrection; feare of torments; promise of glorie; reuelation of mysteries. Euen al good thinges are here, as in a common great treasure, laide vp and heaped together.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>See then and obserue here (Christian reader) the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable<note place="margin">Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in sweetly draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent &amp; coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wil, which is necessarie to saluation.</note> wisdom, and goodnes of God. The meanes of mans saluation being so disposed, that his owne free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, and cooperation is therto necessarily required, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that most approued doctrin of the same S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin: <hi>Qui creauit te sine te; non iustificat te sine te. He that created</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ser. 15. de verb. Apost.</note>
      <hi>thee, vvithout thee, doth not iustifie thee vvithout thee:</hi> to helpe our weaknes, and sweetly to draw our mindes, otherwise auerse from trauel and paine, the Holie Ghost<note place="margin">S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>asil. in pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>log.</note> hath ordained that in smal rowme, and in pleasant maner, we may attaine necessarie knowlege of God, &amp; our selues, easely kepe the same in memorie, and dayly put in practise our chiefest dutie, in seruing and praising God, by singing, reading, or hearing these diuine Psalmes. which one booke (as euerie one shal be able to lerne it, more or lesse per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly) openeth and sheweth the way, to vnderstand al other Scriptures, and so to finde, &amp; enioy the hidden trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of Gods word: in like maner as a key openeth a lock. For the whole sacred <hi>Bible is a sealed Booke,</hi> and not rightly<note place="margin">Apoc. 5.</note>
      <note place="margin">Holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures a sealed booke.</note> vnderstood, til the seale, or lock be opened, by the key of Gods spirite, geuing knowlege; which the Holie Ghost, amongst other wayes, inspireth very often, by sacred Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sike or Psalmodie. As S. Gregorie noteth in holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note place="margin">li. 4 dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logi, c. 42.</note>
      <note place="margin">The Psalter is the key of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> (4. Reg. 3. v. 15.) where Eliseus not yet knowing Gods wil in a particular case, called for a Psalmist (or player on instruments) and <hi>vvhen the Psalmist sang, the hand of our Lord came vpon Eliseus,</hi> and presently he prescribing what should be donne, procured plentie of water without rayne, where
<pb n="7" facs="573"/>
was none before, and prophecied victorie against the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Reason also and experience teach, that as <hi>men of cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hart are apt to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>g:</hi> so the exercise of reading, singing, or<note place="margin">Iac. 5.</note> playing Psalmes, is a conuenient and a special meanes, to attaine quietnes or cheerfulnes of mind.</p>
   <p>But as this holie Psalter is the key of other Scriptures, so it selfe is most especially a sealed, and locked Booke, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring<note place="margin">But it self is also sealed.</note> manie keyes. <hi>Euerie Psalme</hi> (saith S. Hilarie) <hi>hath a peculiar key, and oftentimes there be so manie lockes and keyes of one Psalme, as there be diuers persons that speake, to diuers endes and purposes.</hi> For albeit diuers mysteries are sometimes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected,<note place="margin">But one prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal key of ech Psalme.</note> and so require sundrie keyes, yet there is but one principal, &amp; proper key of ech Psalme: otherwise it should be diuided into manie Psalmes. Our first endeuour ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore must be, to find the proper key of euery Psalme, that is,<note place="margin">Tenne keyes of the Psalter.</note> to know what is principally therein conteyned. To this purpose the lerned Expositers of this booke, haue obserued tenne general pointes, or seueral matters, to which al the contents may be reduced, as it were, so manie keyes, and meanes of entrance into the sense, and true vnderstanding of al the Psalmes. And the same may likewise be called<note place="margin">Also tenne stringes.</note> the tenne stringes of this diuine instrument. Vpon one of which, euery Psalme principally playeth, touching the rest more or lesse, as cause requireth, for more melodious har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, and perfect musike.</p>
   <p>The first key, or string, is God himself: One in Substance:<note place="margin">1. Key. One God the B. Trinitie.</note> Three in Persons. Almightie, Alperfect, Powre, VVis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Goodnes, Maiestie, Iustice, Mercie, &amp; other Diuine<note place="margin">2. Gods workes.</note> Attributes. The second, is Gods workes of Creation, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation,<note place="margin">3. Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> and Gouerning of the whole world. The third, Gods Prouidence, especially towards man, in protecting<note place="margin">4. The Hebrew people.</note> and rewarding the iust: in permitting, and punishing the wicked. The fourth, is the peculiar calling of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew people, their beginning in Abraham, Isaac, and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob: their maruelous increase in Aegypt: diuers estates,
<pb n="8" facs="574"/>
manie admirable and miraculous thinges donne amongst them; with their ingratitude, reiection, and reprobation. The fifth principal key, and string is Christ, the promised<note place="margin">5. Christ our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demer.</note> Redemer of mankind: prophecying his Incarnation, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitic, Trauels, Sufferings, Death, Resurrection, Ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and Glorie. The sixt is the propagation of Christs<note place="margin">6. Conuersion of Gentiles, the Catholique Church.</note> name and Religion, with Sacrifice and Sacramntes, in the multitude of Gentiles beleeuing in him, euen to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termost coastes of the earth, the Catholique Church euer visible. The seuenth is the true maner of seruing God,<note place="margin">7. Faith &amp; good workes.</note> with sincere faith, and good workes. The eight, holie Dauid interposeth manie thinges concerning himselfe. As<note place="margin">8. Dauids owne actes.</note> Gods singular benefites towards him, for which he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth thankes, and diuine praises, recounteth his enimies, dangers, and afflictions of mind &amp; bodie, namely by Saul, Absalon and others, humbly beseeking, and obtaining Gods protection. He also expresseth in himselfe a perfect image, and patterne of a sincere and hartie penitent: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayling, confessing, and punishing his owne sinnes. The<note place="margin">9. General Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection, &amp; Iudgement.</note> ninth is the end and renouation of this world, with the general Resurrection, and Iudgement. The tenth is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal<note place="margin">10. Eternal glory and paine.</note> felicitie, and punishment, according as euerie one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth in this life. These are the tenne keyes of this holie Booke; and tenne stringes of this Diuine Psalter.</p>
   <p>Moreouer to finde which of these is the proper key, and principal string of euerie Psalme, lerned Diuines vse foure<note place="margin">Foure wayes to find the proper key of euerie psalme.</note> especial wayes. First by the title, added by Esdras, or the Seuentie two Interpreters, for an introduction to the sense of the same Psalme. So it appeareth that the third Psalme<note place="margin">1. By the title.</note> treateth literally of Dauids danger, and deliuerie from his sonne Absalon: which is the eight key. though mystically it signifieth Christs Persecution, Passion, &amp; Resurrection, which is the fifth key. Secondly, if there be no title, or if it<note place="margin">2. Allegation in the new Testament.</note> declare not sufficiently the key, or principal matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned, it may some times be found by allegation and
<pb n="9" facs="574"/>
application of some special part thereof in the new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So it is euident <hi>Act. 4. v. 25. c. 13. v. 33. Heb. 1. v. 5. &amp;. Heb. 5. v.</hi> 5. that the second Psalme perteyneth to Christ, impugned and persecuted by diuers aduersaries. VVhich is the fiftkey. Thirdly, when greater thinges are<note place="margin">3. Greatnes of thinges affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> affirmed of anie person, or people, as of Dauid, Salomon, Iewish nation, or the like, then can be verified of them, it must necessarily be vnderstood of Christ, or his Church, in the new Testament, or in Heauen. So the <hi>conclusion</hi> of the 14. <hi>Psalme: He that doth these thinges, shal not be moued for euer,</hi> can not be verified of the tabernacle, nor temple of the Iewes; but of eternal Beatitude in heauen. VVhich is the tenth key. Though the greater part of the Psalme sheweth, that iust and true dealing towards our neighboures, is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie for attayning of eternal Glorie. Fourtly when,<note place="margin">4. Conference of places.</note> both the title and Psalme, or part thereof seme hard and obscure, some part being more cleare, the true sense of al may be gethered, by that which is more euident. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note place="margin">li. 3 c. 4. de pecca. merit.</note> to S. Augustins rule, <hi>li. 2. c. 9. &amp; li. 3. c. 26. Doct. Christ.</hi> So the title, and former part of the fifth Psalme, being more obscure, are explaned by the last verses, shewing plainly that God wil iustly iudge al men, both iust and wicked, in the end of this world. VVhich is the ninth key. By these and like meanes the principal key being found, it wil more easily appeare, what other keyes belong to the same, and what other stringes are also touched. At least the studious may by these helpes make some entrance, and for more exact knowlege search the iudgement of ancient Fathers, and other learned Doctours.</p>
   <p>But besides this singular great commoditie, of compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious handling much Diuine matter in smal rowme, this<note place="margin">The stile of this booke is Poetrie.</note> booke hath an other special excellencie, in the kind of stile, and maner of vttering, which is Meeter, and Verse, in the original Hebrew tongue. And though in Greke, Latin, and other languages, the same could not in like forme be
<pb n="10" facs="575"/>
exactly translated, yet the number, and distinction of verses is so obserued, that it is apt for musike, as wel voices as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments, and to al other vses of Gods seruants. Neither<note place="margin">Abuse deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not from good thinges.</note> is musical maner of vttering Gods word and praises, lesse to be esteemed, because profane Poetes haue in this kind of stile vttered light, vaine, and false thinges. For the abuse of good thinges, doth not derogate from the goodnes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but rather commendeth the same, which others desire to imitate. And clere it is, that this holie Psalmodie was<note place="margin">Dauids Psalter more ancient then any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane poetrie now extant.</note> before anie profane poetrie now extant. For Homer the most ancient of that sorte, writte his poeme, at least two hundred and fourtie yeares after the destruction of Troy: as Apolidorus witnesseth; others, namely Solinus, Herodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, and Cornelius Nepos say longer. VVheras kind Dauid our Diuine Psalmist, reigned within one hundred years, after the Troianes warres. There were in dede Amphion, Orpheus, and Muscus before Dauid, but their verses either were not written, or shortly perished, only a confuse me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie remaining of them, recited, altered, and corrupted by word of mouth: but before them were the sacred Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Iob, almost al in verse; and the two Canticles of<note place="margin">Musike very ancient.</note> Moyses, <hi>Exodi</hi> 15. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. It is moreouer recorded that<note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>bal (long before Noes floud) was the father of them, that sang on harpe, and organ. Musike therfore is maruelous<note place="margin">Sacred poetrie most excellēt.</note> ancient. But sacred Poetrie is in manie other respectes most excellent, and most profitable. <hi>This holie Psalmodie</hi> (saith<note place="margin">Prefat.</note> S. Augustin) <hi>is a medecine to old spiritual sores, it bringeth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent remedie to nev vvvoundes: it maketh the good to perseuere in vvel doing, it cureth at once al predominating passions, vvhich vexe mens soules.</hi> A little after: <hi>Psalmodie driueth avvay euil spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, iuuiteth good Angels to helpe vs, it is a shield in night terrors, a refreshing of day trauels, a guard to children, an ornament to yongmen, a comforte to oldmen, a most seemlie grace to vvemen. Vnto beginners it is an introduction, an augmentation to them that goe forvvard in vertue, a stable firmament to the perfect: It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyneth</hi>
      <pb n="11" facs="575"/>
      <hi>the vvhole Church militant in one voice, and is the spiritual eternal svvete perfume of the celestial Armies, al Sainctes and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in heauen.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To al this we may adde other causes, which moued the<note place="margin">VVhy King Dauid w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>te diuine poetrie</note> Royal Prophete to write this diuine poetrie. First he had from his youth (by Gods special prouidence) a natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to Musike; wherin he shortly so excelled, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">The first cause his natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to musike.</note> al the Musitians in Israel, he was selected to recreate king Saul, whom an euil spirite vexed. And his skil, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his deuotion, had such effect, that <hi>vvhen he playde</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 23.</note>
      <hi>on the harpe, Saul vvas refreshed, and vvaxed better. For the euil spirite departed from him:</hi> saith the holie text. VVherfore he made these Psalmes, that him selfe and others might by singing them, imploy this gift of God to his more honour.<note place="margin">2. Verse more easie &amp; more plesant.</note> Secondly, verse being more easie to lerne, more firmly kept in mind, and more pleasant in practise (for <hi>as wine, so musike doth recreate the hart of man</hi>) the Holie Ghost con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descending<note place="margin">Eccli. 40.</note> to mans natural disposition, inspired Dauid to write these Psalmes in meeter, <hi>mixing the povvre of diuine doctrin, vvith delectable melodie of song, that vvhiles the eare is</hi>
      <note place="margin">S. <hi>Aug.</hi> S. <hi>Basil. in Prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>at</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>allured vvith svvete harmonie of musike, the hart is indued vvith heauenlie knovvlege, pleasant to the mind, and profitable to the soule.</hi> Thirdly, Dauid singularly illuminated with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege<note place="margin">3. Most special great, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges writte in verse.</note> of great, and most diuine Mysteries, indued also with most gracious disposition of mind, <hi>the man chosen according to Gods ovvne hart</hi> (1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 13.) would vtter the same Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, with godlie instructions, and praises of God, in the most exquisite kind of stile; that is in verse. For otherwise he was also very eloquent in prose, as wel appeareth by sundrie his excellent, and effectual discourses, in the books of Kinges, and Paralipomenon. For which cause Moyses also described the passage of Israel forth of Aegypt through the read sea in a Canticle, after that he had related the same<note place="margin">Exo. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> whole historie, more at large in prose; that al might sing, and so render thankes with melodious voice, and musical
<pb n="12" facs="576"/>
instruments praising God. Likewise in an other Canticle<note place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> he comprised the whole law, a litle before his death. So also Barac and Debora: and after them Iudith, song praises to God for their victories in verse. Salomon writte the end of<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iudic</hi> 5. <hi>Iudith.</hi> 16. <hi>Prou</hi> 31. 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2. <hi>Isa.</hi> 38. <hi>Isa.</hi> 12. 26. <hi>Eze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>h</hi> 38 <hi>Ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi> 2. <hi>Abac.</hi> 3. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. 2.</note> his Prouerbes, and a whole booke (intituled Canticles) &amp; the Prophet Ieremie his Lamentations in verse. Anna ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing obtained her prayer for a sonne, gaue thankes to God with a Canticle. The like did king Ezechias for recouerie of health. The Prophets Isaias, Ezechiel, Ionas, A bacuc,<note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ticles in the new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and the three children in the fornace: againe in the new Testament, the B. virgin mother, iust Zacharie, &amp; deuout Simeon gaue thankes, &amp; sang praises to God in Canticles.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, albeit the holie King was not permitted, to build the gorgious Temple for Gods feruice, as he greatly<note place="margin">4. Both diuine musike and dirtie in Gods temple.</note> desired to haue done, yet he prouided both store of mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians (foure thousand in number, of which 288. were<note place="margin">1. Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 23, 25.</note> maisters to teach) &amp; made these Psalmes as godlie dirties, for this holie purpose, in al solemnities of feastes, and day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie sacrifice, when the Temple should afterward be built.</p>
   <p>Fiftly, he made these Psalmes not only for his owne, &amp;<note place="margin">5. The great vse of these Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church.</note> others priuate deuotion, nor yet so especially for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Diuine seruice in the Temple, and other Synago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues of the Iewes, but most principally for the Christian Catholique Church, which he knew should be spred in the whole earth. Forseing the maruelous great, and frequent vse therof in the Christian Clergie, and Religious people of both sexes. As he prophecieth in diuers Psalmes. <hi>Al the earth sing to thee: sing Psalmes to thy name.</hi> Againe, <hi>I vvil</hi>
      <note place="margin">56. 117. 65.</note>
      <hi>sing Psalmes to thee</hi> (ô God) <hi>in the Gentiles, in al peoples, and Nations.</hi> VVhich him selfe neuer did, but his Psalmes are euer since Christ, song by Christians, conuerted from gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitie, as we see in the Churches Seruice. For the whole<note place="margin">The whole Psalter in the ordinarie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="5 letters">
            <desc>•••••</desc>
         </gap> weke.</note> Psalter is distributed to be song, in the ordinarie office of our Breuiarie euerie weke. And though extraordinarily, for the varietie of times, and feastes, there is often altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="13" facs="576"/>
yet stil the greater part is in Psalmes. Certayne also<note place="margin">Certaine Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> euerie day.</note> of the same Psalmes, are without change, or intermission<note place="margin">4. (30. adv. 7) 53 62. 66. 90. 94. 118. 133. 148. 149 150.</note> repeted euerie day. And such as haue obligation to the Canonical Houres, must at least read the whole Office pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatly,<note place="margin">Many Psalmes in other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices.</note> if they be not present where it is song. The Office also of Masse, ordinarily beginneth with a Psalme. In Lita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and almost al publique Prayers, and in administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of other Sacraments, and Sacramentals, either whole Psalmes, or frequent verses are inserted. Likewise the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test part of the Offices, of our B. Ladie, and for the dead are Psalmes. Besides the seuen Poenitential, and fiftene Gradual Psalmes, at certaine times. So that Clergie mens daly office consisteth much in singing, or reading Psalmes. And therfore al Byshops especially, are strictly bond by a particular Conon (<hi>Dist.</hi> 38. <hi>cap. Omnes psallentes</hi>) to be skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful<note place="margin">Bishops bond to be skilful in Dauids Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> in the Psalmes of Dauid: and to see that other Clergiè men be wel instructed therin. According to the Holie Ghosts admonition, by the pen of the same Royal Prophet<note place="margin">Other Priestes to haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege therin.</note> (<hi>Psal</hi> 46.) <hi>Psallite sapienter;</hi> Or: <hi>intelligenter,</hi> that is. <hi>Sing Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes vvith knovvlege, and vnderstanding them.</hi> Not that euerie one is bond to know, and be able to discusse al difficulties, but competently, according to their charge vndertaken in Gods Church. Otherwise euerie one that is, or inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to be a Priest, may remember what God denounceth to him, by the Prophet Osee (<hi>c.</hi> 4.) <hi>Because thou hast repelled knovvlege, I vvil repel thee, that thou do not the function of Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood vnto me.</hi> Thus much touching the Author, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes▪ the poetical stile, &amp; final cause of this holie Psalter.</p>
   <p>As for the name, S. Ierom, S. Augustin, and other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>each, that wheras amongst innumerable musical<note place="margin">VVhy this booke is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the psalter.</note> instruments, six were more specially vsed in Dauids time, mentioned by him in the last Psalme. <hi>Trumpet, Psalter, Harpe Timbrel, Organ, and Cimbal.</hi> This booke hath his name of the instrument called Psalter, which hath tenne strings, signifying the tenne commandements, and is made in
<pb n="14" facs="577"/>
forme (as S. Ierom, and S. Bede suppose) of the Greke, letter Λ <hi>delta,</hi> because as that instrument rendreth sound from aboue, so we should attend to heauenlie vertues,<note place="margin">Other instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes make consorte with the Psalter.</note> which come from aboue: Likewise vsing the harpe, which signifyeth mortification of the flesh, &amp; other instruments, which signifie and teach other vertues, we must finally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre al to Gods glorie, reioyce spiritually in hart, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<note place="margin">Al vertues are referred to Gods honour.</note> al praise to God.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>