<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A preface of this booke, to the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101046_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04491</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1462</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101046</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A preface of this booke, to the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dialoge describing the originall ground of these Lutheran faccions, and many of their abuses, compyled by syr William Barlowe chanon, late byshop of Bathe</title>
                 <author>Barlow, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cawood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>176 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ A preface of this booke, to the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this presente Treatyce folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng (gentle re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der) is not onlye vttered and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed the beast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye begynnynge of Luthers fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious faction, in Saxony, with the sedicious Scismes of the sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramentaries, Swynglius, Oecolampadius, and other of Swycerlande: but also verye playnlye here is shewed theyr monstruous maners and muta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bilitie, theyr cankered contenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and horrible ipocrisy, their deuely she deuyses, and bytter blasphemye, with infinite lyke reliques of that raylynge rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, wherby the christian rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="3"/>
shall ryghte well perceaue, what fylthy frute buddeth out of this frantike fraternitie, and synfull Synagoge of Sathan, infernallye inuented, to seduce symple soules. Neyther canne there be a more open marke, to publyshe the pestiferous practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of these peruerse preachers, and wycked generation, than here is most lyuely and truelye set fourth to the worlde, by the auctor hereof, who had euident experience of theyr maners, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion, and order of all states of them, beynge longe time by his owne confession, in theyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye, and conuersaunte with them, euen with those whiche were of the hyghest reputation both for sobrenes of lyfe, &amp; fame of literature, whose doynges &amp; doctryne to muche myslyked
<pb facs="3"/>
him, that for no hatred to them, nor yet fauour to other, but euē for the discharge of his owne cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>science, instruction, and informa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of suche as be catholike, he thoughte it necessary playnelye to shewe the veritie thereof, to the ende that suche as nowe be addict to their horrible and hay nous heresies, when they shall perceaue and se in theyr life and learnynge, theyr crafty and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable iugglynge, lewde ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, and deuelyshe disagre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of a muster of monstruous maried monkes, and false flesh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye freers, shal by goddes grace both forsake theyr fashions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teste theyr doctryne, and leaue theyr learnynge, whiche boke &amp; dyalogue, beyng for this intent and godlye purpose longe agoo set forth and printed, it hath ben
<pb facs="4"/>
thought good for diuerse consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracions (the prynte beynge nowe worne out) yet eftesones at this present to be reuiued, &amp; communicate to the catholyke readers, wherfore good reader callynge to remembraunce the olde wyttie sayinge: <hi>Felix quem faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt aliena pericula cautum,</hi> Happy is he whom other mens perylles or daungers do make circumspect or ware: Folow thou the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of S. John: who in the. iiii chapter of his canonicall epistle sayth as foloweth: <hi>Nolite credere om<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni spiritui, sed probate spiritus siex deo sint.</hi> That is to saye, Geue not cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyt to euery spirite, but do you proue yf they be of God.</p>
   <closer>Farewell in God.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>