<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO
THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101746_Bo1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00430</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10561</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101746</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO
THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Catholique traditions. Or A treatise of the beliefe of the Christians of Asia, Europa, and Africa, in the principall controuersies of our time : In fauour of the louers of the catholicke trueth, and the peace of the Church. Written in French by Th. A.I.C. and translated int English, by L.O</title>
                 <author>Eudes, Morton</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Morrant, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 96, 99-235, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="126"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO
THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hose that do build Religion on Ceremonies, will thinke
that this Booke is lame or maimed, because that it doth
not declare those, which are obserued by euery Nation.
But we thought it a labour as much vnprofitable, as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious
to the most iudicious Readers. <hi>Calecas</hi> a Romane Catholicke
hath written a volume against the Grecians, wherein hee speaketh
almost of nothing else. That we may not omit any thing of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
we doe aduertise, that there are two euill Ceremonies found
among the Grecians. The first is, that they vse Leauened bread in
their Sacrament: The other that they abstaine from things strangled
and from blood: In both they thinke themselues grounded vpon the
holy Scripture, The <hi>Grecians</hi> hauing opposed themselues against
the <hi>Latines,</hi>
      <note place="margin">In answer to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of Ausburg.</note> doe reprehend them because they vse litle Wafers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leauened,
and not ordinarie Bread, as our Sauiour did. They doe
not thinke that this word Bread, agrees to those Hosts or Wafers,
and that most commonly that name is not giuen them. Moreouer to
make their fashion seeme better, they haue thought good to say, that
Iesus Christ did not institute this Sacrament in the dayes of sweete
bread. As for vnleauened Bread, the Romane Catholickes doe not
insist much vpon it. And it is not so important a matter of faith,
to know vpon what day the Sacrament was ordained, prouided that
one pretend not to preiudice thereby the Historie of the Gospel, the
passages or sentences whereof may bee better reconciled through the
one,<note place="margin">Acts 15. 15.</note> then through the other. As for abstinence from things strangled
and from blood: It is founded vpon the decrees of the Apostles assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
in Ierusalem, the which Decree they doe not thinke to be abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated,
because that their Church which they hold to be true and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke,
hath still obserued it: Yea, this maner of abstinence hath
beene confirmed by the sixt Synode. There is likelyhood that they
haue remitted this to a generall Councell, for they haue not much
pressed this point against the Latines. The <hi>Aethiopians</hi> are both
in the one and in the other, on the Romanes and Protestants side. In
<pb facs="126"/>
      <hi>France</hi> the Protestants doe vse leauened Bread, after the fashion of
the Grecians.</p>
   <p>Against the Churches of the Abyssines in the South is obiected
that they are rebaptized euery yeare: But the Ambassadour of
<hi>Prester-Iohn</hi> saith, that the cause why they bath themselues in Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
and Ponds, is not because that they thinke it necessary to salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
but they doe it vpon the day of the Epiphanie in remembrance
of the Baptisme of our Sauiour. It is to be noted, that this cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie
is new amongst the Abyssins: for their King <hi>Dauid</hi> which
raigned but about some hundred yeares agoe, said that the same was
by the institution of his Grandfather. The Romane Catholikes haue
no occasion to impute this vnto the Abyssins for an errour: seeing
that in the Church of Rome they baptize Bells, and contrary to the
practise of the Apostolicke Churches, they sprincle water euery day
entring into their Churches, for remission of veniall sinnes, a custome
taken eyther from the Iewes, as the Grecians doe reproach them, or
else from Pagan Idolaters.</p>
   <p>The other accusation against the Iacobites is, because that they
tollerate Circumcision: vpon which <hi>Berthius</hi> saith thus: <hi>They cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcise
their children, both Male and Female, but they bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
not that from the Iewes:</hi> (insomuch that the same is not for
any Religion sake, as <hi>Aluares</hi> also saith) but it is an auncient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome,
for <hi>Herodotus</hi> witnesseth, that the Ethiopians in times past
likewised vsed it. It hath beene likewise thought by some, that the
Iacobites baptize with fire: But the Historiographers and those of
the Countrey doe certifie vs, that the same is not so: but they make
incisions in their temples, either for comlines, or els for their healths
sake. If the Ethiopians haue no other errours, then those which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
vnto vs, we might (peraduenture) appropriate vnto them by
better right that place of Scripture,<note place="margin">Cant. ca. 1.</note>
      <hi>vbi cubas in meridie,</hi>
then the auncient Donatists could attribute it
vnto themselues.
{inverted ⁂}</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>