<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE POLISHING OF THE
Twelve stones in the High-Priests
Pectorall.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101346_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04154</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14297</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101346</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE POLISHING OF THE
Twelve stones in the High-Priests
Pectorall.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ecclesiastes : The worthy church-man, or the faithfull minister of Iesus Christ. Described by polishing the twelve stones in the high-priests pectorall, as they were first glossed and scholyed on in a Synod-sermon; and after enlarged by way of discourse, to his two brethren. By Iohn Iackson parson of Marske in Richmond-shire</title>
                 <author>Jackson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Moore (More), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE POLISHING OF THE
Twelve stones in the High-Priests
Pectorall.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is usuall (my good
brothers) to earne the
favour of great Ones
by writing bookes for
their use, and entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
them to their
names for their honor.
I will essay against no
man, but suffer every
one to enjoy his owne
wisdome. I chose rather to give my thoughts issue
upon a few sheetes of paper to you: both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
I deeme it more honest to <hi>pay debts,</hi> then to
<hi>offer Presents,</hi> and to serve <hi>vertue</hi> before <hi>fame:</hi> and
also because I remēber what I lately read in<note n="*" place="margin">Florentin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Hist. lib. 7.</note>
      <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavel,</hi>
that wise childe in his generation, <hi>that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
things doe procure more envy, then those which
without oftentation are honestly covered.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The theam that I choose being a Church-man, &amp;
writing unto Church-men, is to make a draught of
<hi>A WORTHIE ECCLESIASTES,</hi> and
a deserving Church-man indeed.</p>
   <p>I will not at all preface in generall termes, which
like lightning breaketh in the ayre, but seazeth on
no particular subject; it is better to cull out some
text of holy Scripture to be the burthen of my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course,
and I know none fitter then to polish those
twelve precious stones in the High Priests Pecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
as they are twise set downe by <hi>Moses</hi> in these
words,</p>
   <q>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <bibl>The Text. Exod. Ch. 28. v. 17, 18, 19, 20. and also
Chap. 39. ver. 10, 11, 12, 13.</bibl>
      <p>And they filled the breast-plate with foure rowes of
stones. The order was thus: A Sardius, a Topaze,
and a Carbuncle, in the first row. And in the second
row, an Emeraud, a Saphire, and a Diamond. And in
the third row, a Ligure, an Achate, and an Amethyst.
And in the fourth row, a Tarshish, an Onyx, and a
Iasper. And they shall be set in ouches of Gold.</p>
   </q>
   <p>Which place is notoriously concentrique,
with that <hi>Apocalyp. Chap. 21. vers. 19, 20. The
foundations of the wall of the City were garnished
with all manner of pretious stones, the first foundation
was Iasper, the second of Saphire, &amp;c.</hi> Yet I perceive
some termes of difference; those are fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,
these superstructives; those to adorne a City,
the new <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> these the watchmen of that city;
those signified the 12. Apostles, these the twelve
Tribes; those have neither all of them the same or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
nor the same names with these: for the <hi>Iasper</hi>
which is the first there, is last here; and foure of
those names, the <hi>Calcedony</hi> which is the third, the
<hi>Chrysolite</hi> the seventh, the <hi>Chrysoprase</hi> the tenth,
the <hi>Hyacinth,</hi> the eleventh; though (as S. <hi>Hierome,</hi>
and our English Rabbin) they be the same stones,
yet are they otherwise called.</p>
   <p>In both of which places we must not be so<note n="d" place="margin">Religentem o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet esse religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osum nefas. Agel. lib. 4. cap. 9.</note> su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitiously
religious of the barke and shell of the
letter, as to neglect the kernel of the spiritual sense;
We may not thinke these or those stones were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="4"/>
for ornament and shew, nothing for use and sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy.
It is as easie to imagine a shadow with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
a body, a ceremony without a substance, a type
without an antitype, a prophecy without an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishment,
a promise without a performance,
as that nothing is hid under these stones. Vnder
the leaves of metaphors are often the sweetest
truths. Vnloose <hi>Benjamins</hi> sacke, and the piece
of plate will be found; unvaile <hi>Moses</hi> his face
and it will shine. Yet know I not any text of holy
Scripture more burthened with descant of
mans wit, which useth to churne the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere
milke of the word till it bring forth butter,
and wring the nose (prophanely called a nose of
wax) till blood come<note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Prov. 30. vlt.</hi> Naseus cereus, Albertus Pighi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, hierar. l. 3. c. 3</note>. What vexed questions are
here about the names, colours, properties of these
stones? What paralleling of every stone with a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
Patriarch? what citing of the authorities of
<hi>Pliny, Dioscorides, Albertus, Aristotle,</hi> as if God
and nature had taken these into their cabinet-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells
in producing their works? but be these things
left to those who can trifle with a great deale of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry<note n="f" place="margin">Magno conatu nugari, Ter. in Heauton.</note>;
they are rightly censured already to bee
<hi>Magorum vanitas</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Plin. lib. 37.</note>, <hi>learned trifles</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">Doctae nugae.</note>, and we
cannot better either confute their tenets, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish
the authors, then by a forgetfull neglect, and
writing that in sand which they thought to have
cut in marble. I will not offer you that losse, as to
obtrude on you any thing which my selfe hath
beene more curious to know, then credulous
to believe.</p>
   <p>Thus much is emergent hence by good conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
<pb facs="5"/>
that <hi>the legall Priesthood then, and the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall
Ministery now, should bee as jewels and precious
stones.</hi> If <hi>Aaron</hi> and his sonnes were so under the
Law, surely Christ and his Apostles, and those who
succeed them, are no lesse under the Gospell; it is
well therefore that they are mentioned by St. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
as well as <hi>Moses;</hi> in the <hi>New</hi> Testament, as well as
the <hi>Old;</hi> in the New <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> as well as the old
<hi>Tabernacle.</hi> We should all be Gems and Iewels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
as that worthy <hi>Antistas</hi> of <hi>Salisbury</hi> B. <hi>Iewell,</hi>
was both in name and nature, according to the
Greeke Lyricks of <hi>Io. Brosserius</hi> a French man in his
Epitaph<note n="l" place="margin">Vita &amp; mers luelli per D. Humphredum.</note>.</p>
   <q>
      <l>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>,
<l>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>.</q>
   <p>Iewels and stones of price wee are or should be:
first in the esteeme of God, of whose mysteries wee
are disposers; let men thinke of us as meanely as
they will, we are a chosen generation, and a royall
Priesthood to him, <hi>amat gentē nostrā,</hi> he loves the
Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> as they in the Centurions behalfe,
<hi>Luke</hi> 7. Secondly, at the rate of good men, if the
<hi>Galathians</hi> will give their eies for <hi>Paul,</hi> the <hi>Milanois</hi>
will give <hi>animam pro Ambrosio,</hi> their lives for their
<hi>Ambrose.</hi> Thirdly, in regard of those rich endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and vertuous habits of grace, which by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>working
with God we should labour by frequent
and iterated acts, to introduce both into our owne
and others soules. <hi>Brightman</hi> a man of a right heart
and bright braine (his particular conceits reserved)
I warrant him, expresseth himselfe in these words,
<pb facs="5"/>
which may serve for a good glosse on my Text,
<note n="m" place="margin">in Apoc. c. 21.</note>
      <hi>It is certaine</hi> (saith he) <hi>that the excellency of gifts
wherewith teachers excell above other men, are noted
unto us in this place by those things which are most
precious of all other upon the earth: and withall wee
are hereby taught, both what precious accompt God
makes of such teachers, as also how greatly they ought
to be esteemed amongst men; and it is no lesse certaine
that every one of these excellēt vertues did shine forth
most cleerly long agoe in the old Apostles.</hi> So he.</p>
   <p>I need not trespasse against mine owne ease to
labour for either words or method; not for
words, for rare beauties are most lovely plaine dres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
and stones rich in themselves shew best set in a
foyle: not for method, it is already <hi>ordo quincunx,</hi>
one breast-plate into foure rowes, and those foure
rowes into twelve stones, three in each row; as the
yeere into foure quarters, and those foure quarters
into twelve moneths, three in each quarter: or <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodo
analytica,</hi> twelve stones contracted into foure
rankes, and those foure into one pectorall.</p>
   <p>So then according to the number of the stones,
there are to be 12. severall rhapsodies or divisions
in this discourse, as there are twelve chapters in the
booke of the Preacher; or as <hi>Ahijah</hi> taking hold on
<note n="*" place="margin">1 King. 11. 30.</note>
      <hi>Ieroboams</hi> garment rent it into 12. peices; in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
one of which shall bee touched first the hidden
<hi>vertue</hi> of the stone, for I verily thinke <hi>there is no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
stone without some egregious vertue,</hi> as <hi>Cardan</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">Nullum lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem pretiosum alicujus egregiae virtutis expectē. Car. Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>til. lib. 7</note> who made <hi>Millaine</hi> as famous for a Philosopher,
and a Physitian, as St. <hi>Ambrose</hi> did it for a Bishop▪
Secondly, the apparent <hi>colour</hi> or visible quality,
which is limited and bounded in the surface and
<pb facs="6"/>
extremity thereof, which is so notable as many Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morists
blazon by the colours of precious stones.
You cannot expect from me any digression at all,
or long commoration upon any thing in prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting
these things. I may truly say as she prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
with our Saviour <hi>Iohn 4. The well is deepe, and
I have little to draw with.</hi> I will therefore doe no
more but lap of these waters <hi>tanquam canis Nilum,</hi>
or as <hi>Gideons</hi> souldiers <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7. &amp; not so much nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
till I have darted forth one ejaculation.</p>
   <div type="prayer">
      <head>The Prayer.</head>
      <p>BLessed Saviour, who in thine incarnation was a <hi>stone</hi>
         <note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 2. 34.</note>
         <hi>cut
out of the quarry without hands,</hi> in thy Passion<note n="b" place="margin">Zach. 3. 9.</note>
         <hi>a stone
cut full of eyes,</hi> in thy Resurrection and Ascension<note n="c" place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 6.</note>
         <hi>a chiefe
corner stone.</hi> Thou art the Sonne of God command these
stones to be made bread, even such heavenly Manna &amp; spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
food as may feed our soules to life eternall, to this end give
me thy booke and thy roule to eate, that I may speake truly, and
judge wisely, and so worship thee the <hi>first truth</hi> &amp; <hi>chiefest wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
Take away the stoninesse of our harts, that the seed of the
word fall not into stony ground, and prove fruitlesse. Lord, there
is nothing will hinder but our sinnes, which are ever interposing
betwixt thy goodnesse and our needs: make us therefore as truly
sorry that ever they were committed by us, as desirous that they
may be remitted by thee, and as endeavouring that wee may not
<hi>sin,</hi> as we are hopefull thou wilt not <hi>impute</hi> sin. O Iesu Christ,
whom wilt thou heare if not <hi>us</hi> who have no portion but in thee,
having forsaken all to bee thine Altar servants? or who will
heare us, if not <hi>thou,</hi> who art a Priest aswell as a Prophet or
King? or where wilt thou heare us, if not in this place which is
the <hi>house of Prayer?</hi> or when wilt thou heare us if not <hi>in the
houre of Prayer,</hi> when so many of us are gathered together in
thy name? and in what words wilt thou heare us, if thou wilt not
acknowledge the phrase and stile which thy selfe hath taught us,
saying, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>