<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Preface]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101662_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00802</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24163</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101662</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Preface]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most godly enstruction and very necessarie lesson to be learned of all christen men and wome [n], before they come to ye communion of the bodie &amp; bloud of our sauiour Christe Iesus. Compiled by Richard Tracie. Anno .M.D.xlviii</title>
                 <author>Tracy, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint Peter sayeth that oure aduersary the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl, <note place="margin">i. Peter .v.</note> lyke a roringe lion goeth aboute sekynge whom he may deuowre. So that his erneste studie and purpose is euer fixed, other wyth fierce cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty or with pleasaunte suggestiō or wyth importune hote tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, to allure and entise man, to disobeye goddes lawe, whereby he myght bringe man, into lyke misery and eternall peyne where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he nowe iustly suffereth. But if he can not atteyne his purpose by these meanes before declared: then he transfigureth and chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth hymselfe, into an Angell of lighte, and pretendeth to setforth and maynteyne religion, takyng some text and parte of holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to bee hys whole authoritie principle &amp; groūd. So that bring<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge and allegynge for him, the
<pb facs="4"/> holye scripture: no man shall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struste any disceyte or euyl in hys procedinges, and then moste cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ftelye he intendeth to disceyue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as he entended to disceyue Christe, coluring hys malyciouse entent, with authorities of holye scripture. <note place="margin">Mat .iiii.</note> Euen so he wyth lyke disceyte and policy and wyth no lesse malice towardes man (hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge thys promise of Christe, He that eateth my fleshe &amp; drinketh my bloude dwelleth in me and I in him) hath inuented the doctrin of transubstanciation, of breade into Christes naturall body, and of wyne into Christes naturall blude, by force of certaine wordes spoken by the priest.</p>
   <p>And so by the clerenes of the wordes spoken by a priste: wyll perswade the Ignorant people, wyth lyke fonde opinion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Caparnites wer led, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue
<pb facs="4"/> that they mygthe eate Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes fleshe wyth theyr teeth, and dryncke and swallowe Christes bloude wyth their throtte, frome the whiche grosse opinion Christ perswaded the saide Caparnites to leaue, sayinge. Dooe these my saynges offend you? What and you shal se the son of man ascend wher he was before? It is the spi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite that quickeneth, the fleshe profiteth not any thing. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell not wythstanding thys doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Christ, wherby he taught the spirituall eatynge of his flesh and drinkinge of his bloud, hath sowed this false doctrine of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssubstanciation, in the hertes of greate clerkes byshopes and of other spiritual pastours, and wit tye babes of the worlde, that by suche teachers, and highe powrs the people myght be led, &amp; taught to truste, that they had sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="5"/> eaten Christes fleshe, whē they haue eaten the sacramente, wyth their teth &amp; trusting to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gros eat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing with their teth: thei shuld not enquire, nor serch, for anye godly and spirituall eatynge of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes fleshe, by fayeth, whereby it myght be profitable to their sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, for the which entent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose all sacramentes, were insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted &amp; ordeyned, that is to feede the mynde, and not the mouth, to comforte the soule? and not the body, and all thys false doctryne of transsubstanciation the deuyl hath enduced thorow the clernes of these wordes spokē by the prist saiyng, this is mi bodi, although that thorowe all the holye scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, where they entreate of sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramentes, they euer call sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes by the same name of the thinges wherof they be sacramē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, as it appereth the .xvii. of Ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesis, where circumsicion is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="5"/> goddes couenaunte, whiche was but the sacramente thereof, and in the .xii. of Exodi where the Easter lambe, was called the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssouer of the Lord, which was but a sacrament therof. And the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice is called the newe testamente which is but the sacrament ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, yea Christ is called syn, which was onely the sacrifice for synne, And therfore Christen reader be not disceyued by the clearnes of the wordes, but conferre and trie the scriptures, by other places of holy scriptur diligently readyng this litel treatise folowing, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> shalt find, I trust a spiritual eating of christs flesh &amp; drinking of his bloude, taughte by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue churche and the auncient holy fathers, whiche dyd write of the same, before the deuyll hadde corrupted the holy scripture with false gloses and wicked interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions.
<pb facs="6"/> And thys I commytte the gentle reader to almyghtye GOD who geue the hys spirite whereby thou mayste haue the true vnderstandynge and swete taste of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worde and spirituall eatinge of hys fleshe to thy spiritual co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall healthe of thy soule. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>