<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣rable, Sir Christopher Hattō, Knight, Captaine of hir Maiesties Garde, Vizchamberlaine to hir highnesse, and of hir Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsaile.</title>
           <author>North, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101744_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00423</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10552</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101744</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONO∣rable, Sir Christopher Hattō, Knight, Captaine of hir Maiesties Garde, Vizchamberlaine to hir highnesse, and of hir Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsaile.</title>
                 <author>North, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The stage of popish toyes : conteining both tragicall and comicall partes: played by the Romishe roysters of former age: notably describing them by degrees in their colours. Collected out of H. Stephanus in his Apologie vpon Herodot. With a friendlie forewarning to our Catelin Catholikes: and a brief admonition, of the sundrie benefites we receiue by hir Ma: blessed gouernement ouer vs. Compyled by G.N</title>
                 <author>Estienne, Henri</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 65, that is 95, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, Sir Christopher Hattō, Knight,</hi> Captaine of hir Maiesties Garde, <hi>Vizchamberlaine to hir highnesse, and of hir Maiesties most honorable priuie Counsaile.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Age <hi>Sibilla</hi> (right honorable) said to <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> that no way could be closed againste <hi>Vertue:</hi> affirming that al actions happily succeeded whatsoeuer the attēpt be, <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute duce.</hi> And <hi>Theodorus Biblian der</hi> defineth <hi>Vertue</hi> to be inuested with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers titles, according to the diuersity of hir proper motions, as in discerning the deceit of mans traditions, in choosing the veritie, and in flying false Hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie, she is called <hi>Prudence:</hi> in maintayning Gods glorie, in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Popes tirannie, and in defending the true felowship of <note place="margin">Prudence.</note> Christian societie, she is named <hi>Fortitude:</hi> in suppressing Idolatrie, in embracing mercie, and in aduauncing the ministers of his heauē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <note place="margin">Fortitude.</note> maiestie, she is saide to be <hi>Iustice,</hi> in moderating Romish furies, and weake affections, in qualifying Popish quarrels, and peruerse cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, <note place="margin">Iustice.</note> &amp; in vsing either to bring both to the true vse of Gods word, she is tearmed <hi>Temperance.</hi> A Prince with these pillers doth euer preuaile: a tree with these brāches, doth euer blossom, &amp; a body with <note place="margin">Temperāce.</note> these members ouercommeth the labours of <hi>Hercules.</hi> Besids these general graces of <hi>Vertue,</hi> there are two special precedents chiefelie to be loked into, the cause, and the execution, both which, your honor (whose forward fauour to al Christs professors (vnder hir Maiesty) among the rest of right honorable) long since considered of, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, confirming, &amp; executing the effect, in such famous sort as the whole Worlde is amazed and mated at hir Maiesties moste hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie and blessed gouernement, whereby you haue hitherto proued in your noble person, <hi>Sibillas</hi> sayings to be true, that nothing can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile against this diuine Vertue: which some define to be God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe.
<pb facs="3"/>
And now, seing his auntient and opposite enimie the Pope, hath foysted in among vs Petifoggers, who (like sheete stealers, tinckers, or Connyskin buyers) creepe in corners to vtter their trash, my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune being (by a French man) to meet with a packe of their paultry, I presume in humble sort to present the first shew therof to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, wherin if I play the bad Pedler (so your honor pardō me) I force not, for truelie I am not their feed Broker. I haue entituled it <hi>The Stage of Popish toyes,</hi> as a most meet tearm for the matter. the sum &amp; substance wherof I confesse to haue collected out of <hi>H: Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus</hi> in his <hi>Apologie</hi> vpon <hi>Herodot,</hi> who coateth thē in theyr Couchanele colours: and therfore if any part haue his wrong dye, I must yeelde to the fault, and excuse my Author. But my selfe (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vaunt) a martial professor, and continuallie armed to the proofe with a seruisable &amp; dutiful hart to your honor: I hope my errors shal passe for the easier payment, and be the better born with, for that hereby I affirme this auntient Emblem, <hi>In v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trumque paratus,</hi> and vow my daylie prayer, for the proceeding and encreasing of that which God at the first placed in you, and is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the saying of <hi>Plato, No man to be noble without a heauenly inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors most bound seruaunt in all humble duetie.
GEORGE NORTH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>