<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the truly Ho∣nourable, and Reli∣gious Sir Roger Townsend, &amp; Sir Robert Crane, Knights and Baronets, and their Noble and vertuous Ladies, increase of joy and peace in beleeving.</title>
           <author>Yates, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101332_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15826</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26087</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101332</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the truly Ho∣nourable, and Reli∣gious Sir Roger Townsend, &amp; Sir Robert Crane, Knights and Baronets, and their Noble and vertuous Ladies, increase of joy and peace in beleeving.</title>
                 <author>Yates, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The saints sufferings, and sinners sorrowes. Or, The evident tokens of the salvation of the one, and the perdition of the other : Phil. I.28, 2 Thes. I.6,7</title>
                 <author>Yates, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>70, 282 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the truly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Sir <hi>Roger Townsend,</hi> &amp; Sir <hi>Robert Crane,</hi> Knights and Baronets, and their Noble and vertuous Ladies, increase of joy and peace in beleeving.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Honorable, and worthy Witnesses.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Crave your testimonies, as well for
<pb facs="3"/>the preaching, as the printing of these Sermons. You were at sundry times, and in severall places, the best and chiefest of my hearers, and it concernes your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to be as inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in the hearing as it was my duty to be innocent in the speaking. You cannot be ignorant of the Accusation,
<pb facs="3"/>and if that were suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make a man guilty,
<note place="margin">Si accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sasse suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiat, qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> erit Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens?</note> who should be innocent? as once <hi>Julian</hi> said of the Christians, the worst man of the best living.</p>
   <p>It is the saying of <hi>Syracides.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccles.</hi> 11.7.</note> Blame not before thou hast ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined the truth: understand first, and then rebuke. It was the sharpe censure
<pb facs="4"/>of King <hi>James</hi> in his <hi>Daemonology,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 3. Cap. 1.</note> that <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine report, is the authour of all lies:</hi> yet they are worse who <hi>lye in wait to finde fault and to turne good into evill,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ecclus 11 31.</note> of whom the wise man hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained long since, and we may see how every age of the world renders it, day by day more malicious.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>Alas, when there is wanting that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which in all men we call <hi>Honesty:</hi> and that speciall gift of God which in Christians wee call <hi>Charity,</hi> how are men condemned without hearing, and wounded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence given? We see in experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that dogges al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes barke at
<pb facs="5"/>those they know not, and that it is their nature to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in those cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors: so is it with the inconsiderate multitude, being once set on, they trust to their tongs, their teeth are gone, and barke and bleat when they cannot bite.</p>
   <p>It is a pennance
<pb facs="5"/>to a Preacher to bee troubled with tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flers, who have neither eyes to see, nor heads to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what is said; yet dare they thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and threaten, as if they meant to beare downe all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them: Every understanding hath a peculiar judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by which it answereth other mē,
<pb facs="6"/>and valueth it selfe; and therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not seeme strange to me to be abused by reports. Let vaine men pricke on in their pride, hoyse up the top-sayle of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, and flant it out against us, yet God forbid, that these should al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes have wind at will, and finde as free passage to supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours
<pb facs="6"/>as they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine. But seeing it is so easie to faine, and face out re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, I must be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to leave such professors, to their easie wayes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension, than the which, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of more frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
   <p>When <hi>Moses</hi> saw the <hi>Jsraelite,</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> fight, hee
<pb facs="7"/>did not say, <hi>Why strive you?</hi> but drew his sword, and slew the <hi>Aegyptian:</hi> but when hee saw two <hi>Israelites</hi> quarrell, he said, <hi>Yee are brethren, why strive you?</hi> If any thing delivered bee an <hi>Aegyptian,</hi> let it be slaine by the sword of the Spirit, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reconciled: but if an <hi>Jsraelite,</hi> and yet questioned, why
<pb facs="7"/>strive you? What wrong I have done, let all judge that reade this Sermon: what wrong is done to mee by the accusation, Heave to him, that either mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stooke me, or meant me a mischiefe. Hee hath put an <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> in the place of an <hi>Jsraelite,</hi> and an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in the place of a truth. I said, <hi>God is
<pb facs="8"/>often a mothe in our counsels,</hi> meaning in the successe, and event of mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultations, which to be an <hi>Israelite,</hi> these Scriptures doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.28. <hi>Hos.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.4. How these words may be strained to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels of State (as they are by my accuser) I confesse it passeth
<pb facs="8"/>my understanding.</p>
   <p>It may be the failes and follies of some in preaching, to seeke vulgar ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause; A vanity much avoyded by wise men. <hi>Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> affirmed,
<note place="margin">Laudari a bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> timeo, &amp; amari a ma io de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testor.</note> that <hi>he feared the praise of good men, and detested that of evill.</hi> And to them that will reade and remember, our ancients have given
<pb facs="9"/>better rules. Saint <hi>Ierom</hi> desired in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,
<note place="margin">Hier ad Nep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t. Lachryma auditorum sunt lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des tua. Non pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum, sed planctum.</note> rather to have the <hi>praise of the teares than of the tongues o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> his hearers.</hi> Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> being applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, answeres: <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia haec sunt, nos fructu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> quaerimus. These a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> but leaves, we looke fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> fruit. Chrysostome</hi> tol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> his hearers, <hi>he ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> them thanks, when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <pb facs="9"/>payed him teares. Si haec audientes, doletis, maximas me debere vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis gratias confiteor, quis est enim qui melae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificat, nisi qui contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>statur ex me?</hi> These rules shall I desire to follow both in preaching; and in printing, and for this end I have desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to make my thoughts more legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and my selfe
<pb facs="10"/>and my Sermons, the subject of every opinion, wise, or weake.</p>
   <p>I have presumed vpon the Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and having thought upon some Witnesses and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, have addres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed my selfe to such friends, as love the truth, and deserve to be loved of it. I wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> not trouble you o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="10"/>any other with fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reasons of my writing, or with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuses. He that doth ill, no plea can war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant him: and hee that doth well, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not easily be discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged with any cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures. I crave no mans pardon in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving good counsell, but his acceptation; And presents of love may be well ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="11"/>both of friends and strangers. The things I dare say, are both <hi>commoda, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodata,</hi> seasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and profitable for our times, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in God smiteth, and his houshold smar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth; and such begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings will have feareful endings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their enemies.</p>
   <p>An heathen wis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> man could say, Ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>versities
<pb facs="11"/>are <hi>Tributa vivendi,</hi> tributes of living. And wise Christians above all ought to know them, and to pay them most willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Their Lord and master hath gone before them, and it is their duty to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, not as those whining soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, <hi>qui gementes se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur Imperatorem;</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/>but as those worthy Martyrs, which like a cloud of witnesses, have gone before them. And here I remēber some pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages that may bee patterns for others, which I have heard from some of you, well agreeing with the subject of my Text,
<note place="margin">Dicta do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta &amp; pia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> verè diligentis deum, &amp; Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</note> as namely: <hi>He will never dye for Christ, that will not
<pb facs="12"/>first learne to live for him.</hi> Another of the like nature was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning comfort in death. <hi>videl. Death takes away the pleasure of all worldly things, and Religion the paine of death.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This may well make us prize the rule of the Apostle, that <hi>Godlinesse is great gaine,</hi> and sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a godly life is to
<pb facs="13"/>be preferred before all good things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us. VVhat can it advantage a man to be well for the world, and ill, and vile for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe? He gaines no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that wins the world, with the losse of himselfe. Very Ethnicks in their Ethickes have laid it downe for a rule, that nothing is
<pb facs="13"/>so good for a man as to live well. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, riches, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, have their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luations in the world, and they are the greatest markes men shoot at, and straine their consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences to the highest. But howsoever men give these their good word, yet they will be wanting in the day of death,
<pb facs="14"/>when nothing but the gaine of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse will profit us.</p>
   <p>To purchase ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, we make ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches our servants; and yet even this consisteth for the most part in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which it may be will follow us in faire weather; but will be sure to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake us in the first
<pb facs="14"/>tempest of misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and steere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way before the Sea, and wind, leaving us to the rualice of our destinies. Who would trust such an heard of Animals, that please them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with the noise they make, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the cause, or the distinction of vertue and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune?
<pb facs="15"/>Let the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious prosper, and they shall be applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and let the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous be unhappy, and they shall bee despised. Fortune raiseth up men to the horse, and rideth them: who when they are descended, and on foot like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, and they and their fortune parted, we shall see
<pb facs="15"/>a bitter contempt spurne at the one with as great liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as a base Groome dare presume to beat the other. Who seeth not then the profit of Godlinesse to be preferred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all worldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages?</p>
   <p>That skill must needes be the best, which can teach a man to know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
<pb facs="16"/>and that gaine the greatest, which is accōpanied with the favour of God, grace of Christ, and comfort of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and which can made us blessed in this life, and the life to come. The Saints sufferings, and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners sorrowes, have cōtrary beginnings, and contrary en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. Their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings
<pb facs="16"/>are known by their shortnesse, their endings can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be knowne for their Eternity. A good man knowes the worst at the first, and his very sorrow is turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to joy, and his joy is unspeakeable and glorious: but a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man knowes his best at the first, and his joy is turned
<pb facs="17"/>into sorrow, and his sorrow is not to bee defined. All that our Text can say of it, is, <hi>What shall his end bee?</hi> Nay, there is yet more both in their joy and sorrow. It is not an alteration, but a conversion. A good mans sorrow is not onely chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and removed; but converted into
<pb facs="17"/>joy, as the matter of it: but the joy of the wicked is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken away, but made the matter of his future sorrow, and oftentimes as an unknowne sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row springs from an unknowne sin, as we shall discover in a second Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
   <p>The joy and woe of this world, how
<pb facs="18"/>great soever, will saile out of sight; and then death which pursues us, and keepes us in chase, will lay hold, and fasten on our bodies, as prises for wormes, and leave our soules to a worse reckoning. O what an extreame madnesse were it, in the shipwracke of all worldly things,
<pb facs="18"/>where all sinkes but the sorrow, to save that for another world? What then remaines to him that all his life hath injoyed fortune for a servant, and time for a friend, but the heavy, secret, sad, and severe thoughts of another life, where neither Time nor Fortune shall favour him? Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb facs="19"/>are all those that have grace to value worldly vanities, at no more than their owne price, and by retaining the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable memory of a well-acted life, can behold death with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dread, and the grave without feare, and imbrace both as necessary guides to endlesse glory.</p>
   <p>The sorrowes of
<pb facs="19"/>this life, are but of two sorts; The one hath respect to God, when we complain to him against our selves, and for our offences, count him just in all that wee suffer; and to such sorrow Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath promised bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednesse. The other hath respect to the world, when wee mutter to our selves
<pb facs="20"/>against God, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> complaine of him as if hee had don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> us wrong, either it not giving, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away what we desire to have an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to hold: forgettin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that humble and ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> acknowledgment o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> holy <hi>Job, The Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> hath given, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Lord hath taken, bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed be the Name of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Lord.</hi> And such sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="20"/>the Apostle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ath threatned with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eath.</p>
   <p>Questionlesse hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s either a foole, or a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ebell that wil quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ell with God in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>avours, or frownes. A foole, if he be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant whence bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings and crosses come: a rebell, if he know it, and bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mpatient. How meane soever our
<pb facs="21"/>estate be, yet is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> same farre greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> than that w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> oweth us; and ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> sharpe soever o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> afflictions be, yet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> same are farre les<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> than those whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> are due unto us. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> know impatience full of excuses, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> wee say wee rath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> murmure at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hand, than the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er that beats us: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="21"/>take heed, lest like some foolish Curres whilst we bite the stone, wee barke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the hand that threw it. See God in all his chastise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and beare with patience, for whatsoever the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning is, the end shall be happy.</p>
   <p>To conclude, My desire is to all, and you in speciall, for
<pb facs="22"/>the acceptation, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usall, and Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of these Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. It is but a small testimony o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> my unfained obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of you, and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that love the truth▪ And thus I take my leave, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend both you, and yours to the God o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> mercy, and truth, who guide, comfort, deliver, sanctifie,
<pb facs="22"/>and preserve you all, and fill you with the comforts of the blessed hope of the appearing of Iesus Christ.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the service of Iesus Christ, to be ever commanded, <hi>JOHN YATES.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>