<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right noble, learned, and
worthie minded Lord, Edward de Vee, Earle of Ox∣enford,
Viscount Bulbeck, Lord Sanford, and of Ba∣delsmere,
and Lord high Chamberlaine of England: A. M.
wisheth continuall happines in this life, and
in the world to come.</title>
           <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101486_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08875</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19157</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101486</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right noble, learned, and
worthie minded Lord, Edward de Vee, Earle of Ox∣enford,
Viscount Bulbeck, Lord Sanford, and of Ba∣delsmere,
and Lord high Chamberlaine of England: A. M.
wisheth continuall happines in this life, and
in the world to come.</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Palmerin D'Oliua : The mirrour of nobilitie, mappe of honor, anotamie of rare fortunes, heroycall president of Loue: VVonder for chiualrie, and most accomplished knight in all perfections. Presenting to noble mindes, theyr courtlie desires, to gentles, theyr choise expectations, and to the inferiour sorte, howe to imitate theyr vertues: handled vvith modestie to shun offence, yet all delightfull, for recreation. Written in the Spanish, Italian and French; and from them turned into English by A.M, one of the messengers of her Maiesties chamber</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 176 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the right noble, learned, and
worthie minded Lord, Edward de Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, Earle of Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enford,
Viscount Bulbeck, Lord Sanford, and of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delsmere,
and Lord high Chamberlaine of England: A. M.
wisheth continuall happines in this life, and
in the world to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the <hi>Spartanes</hi>
right noble Lord, and sometime
my honorable Maister, nothing
was accounted more odious,
then the forgetfulnes of the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt
towardes his Maister:
which made <hi>Mucronius,</hi> who
had beene seruaunt to <hi>Hagar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi>
a poore Arte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>an, and for his vertues afterward cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
to the office of a <hi>Senatou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> in all assemblies to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
his poore Maister, so that he would often say: <hi>It was
honour to</hi> Mucronius, <hi>that he had beene seruaunt to</hi>
Hagarbus.</p>
   <p>Though this example (my good Lord) be vnfit for me,
in what respect, beseemes me not to speake: Yet that excel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lent
opinion of the <hi>Spartanes,</hi> I count it religion for me
to immitate. For if this vice was so despised among such
famous persons, what reproch wold it be to so poore an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
as my selfe, beeing once so happy as to serue a Maister
so noble: to forget his precious vertues, which makes him
generally belooued▪ but cheerf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly mine owne dutie, which
nothing but death can discharge, In remembraunce ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
of my officious zeale, I present your Honour the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
endeuours of your late seruaunt: howe simple soeuer
they be, right perfect shall you make them by your fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="4"/>
acceptaunce, this being added, that were I equall in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility
with the best, all should be offered to my noble Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</p>
   <p>If <hi>Palmerin</hi> hath sustained any wrong by my bad trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
being so worthely set downe in other languages:
Your Honour hauing such speciall knowledge in them, I
hope will let slip any fault escaped, in respect I haue doone
my good will, the largest talent I haue to bestowe.</p>
   <p>And seeing the time affordes me such oportunitie, that
with ending this first parte, the olde yeere is expired: I
present it my noble Lord as your seruauntes New yeeres
gift, and therewithall deliuer my most affectionate dutie,
euermore ready at your Honours commaundement.</p>
   <p>Needelesse were it, by tediousnes to growe trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some,
when a woord suffiseth to so sound iudgement: I sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
my selfe and my Booke to your gracious conceit, and
the second part, now on the presse, and well neere finished
I will shortly present my worthie Patrone.</p>
   <p>In meane while, I wish your Honor so many New yeers
of happines, as may stand with the heauenly appointment,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd my modestie to desire.</p>
   <signed>Sometime your Honours seruant,
<hi>yet continuing in all humble duty.</hi>
Anthonie Monday.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>