<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Prayer to be sayde before the Sermon.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101291_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06932</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1736</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101291</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Prayer to be sayde before the Sermon.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A new postil : conteinyng most godly and learned sermons vpon all the Sonday Gospelles, that be redde in the church thorowout the yeare</title>
                 <author>Becon, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 254, 257-260, 259-312, 195 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prayers</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prayer">
   <head>A Prayer to be sayde before the Sermon.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>FOR AS MVCHE AS</hi> we mooste lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge Lorde and sweete Sauioure <hi>CHRIST IESV</hi>) are here assembled,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 12. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.</note> and gathered together in thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, blessed, and glorious name, to heare the health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulle woordes of Euerlastynge Lyfe, conteyned in thy
<pb facs="18"/>
pure and lyuely Gospell, whych is the power of God vnto sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, to euery one that beleueth, whiche also is able thorow the workyng of the holy Spirite to saue our soules:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Iac.</hi> 1.</note> we with one heart and with one mynde approche at this present vnto the gracious throne of thy diuine maiestie, moste humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sechyng thee,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 51. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.5 <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. <hi>Luc.</hi> 24. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 16. <hi>Math.</hi> 9.</note> that forasmuche as we of our selues and of our owne nature are altogether corrupte, ignoraunt, blynde, and vtterly estranged from the felyng and perceauynge of thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine mysteries (suche is our ignorance and blyndnesse thorow olde Adam) it may please thee of thy mercyfull goodnesse by thy holy and blessed spirite, to open our senses, to leade vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all truthe, to purifie our heartes, and to make oure myndes mete vessels to receaue the swete wyne of thy most swete and glorious Gospell.</p>
   <p>O open thou our eyes, that we may see the wondrous thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of thy lawe.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.</note> Hyde not thy commaundementes frome vs, but teache vs thy statutes, and make vs to vnderstand the way of thy commaundementes, that we may talke of thy meruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous workes. Teache vs O Lord, the way of thy statutes, and make vs to go in the pathe of thy commandementes. Encline our heartes vnto thy testimonies: quicken vs in thy wayes, and take not the worde of truthe oute of our mouthe. O geue vs vnderstandyng acordyng to thy word, that we may learne thy commandementes, and be occupied in thy lawes. Let oure heartes be sounde in thy statutes, that we be neuer ashamed. O shewe the lyght of thy countenance vpon vs thy seruantes: teache vs thy testimonies: and so order oure steppes in thy worde, that no wickednes may haue dominion ouer vs. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie vs thorowe thy truthe:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> for thy woorde is the truthe.</p>
   <p>Geue to me thy Minister and stewarde of the mysteries of God, a well learned tongue, that I may confort them whiche are troubled,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>Esa.</hi> 50. <hi>Esa.</hi> 61.</note> yea and that in due season, that I may shew good tydynges vnto the poore, that I maye bynde vp the wounded heartes, that I may preache deliueraunce to the captiues, and open the prison to them that are bound, that I may make ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full all them that are in heauynesse, and thorowe thy worde geue to them that mourne, beaultie in stede of ashes, ioyefull
<pb facs="18"/>
oyntment for syghyng,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ezech.</hi> 34.</note> and pleasant rayement for an heauye mynde: that I may hold vp the weake, that I maye heale the sycke, that I may bynd together the broken,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esa.</hi> 61.</note> that I may bryng agayne the outcastes, and seke vp them that are loste, so that thys people may be called trees of righteousnesse, and a plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of the Lorde for hym to reioyce in. O geue me that mouthe, that spirite, that wisedome,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luc.</hi> 21. <hi>Act.</hi> 6. <hi>Ps<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>l.</hi> 68.</note> agaynst the whyche all the aduersaries of thy truthe shall not be able to speake, nor resyst. Geue to me that preache, thy worde with great power, that I may be able to exhort by wholsome doctrine, and to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue them, that speake agaynst it.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Geue me grace also, O Lorde, that I may not only be the salt of the earth, but also the lyghte of the worlde,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 5.</note> namely that I may not onely truly and faithfully, sincerely and pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>3.</note> reuerently and godly bryng foorthe oute of the treasure house of thy holy worde thynges newe and olde, that is to say, the doctrine bothe of the olde and newe testamente, euen the lawe and the Gospell, but also that in my lyfe and maners I may be an ensample to the faithfull in worde, in conuersation, in loue, in spirite, in fayth, in puritie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 2.</note> and in all pointes shew my selfe laudable vnto God, a workeman that nedeth not to be ashamed, distributynge the woorde of truthe iustly, so that I may be to the flocke an ensample of good workes in honestie and grauitie, that he whyche withstandeth, maye be ashamed,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Tit.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> hauyng no euyll thyng to speake of me, lest by any meanes it come to passe, that when I haue preached to other,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.</note> I my selfe should be a cast away, and so become a slaunder to the good do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that I professe and teache.</p>
   <p>Geue also to the people, that are here gathered together to heare the worde of their saluation, a good spirite, that (al clou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of ignorancie brought in by olde Adam vtterly dispelled &amp; driuen away) they may learne to knowe thee to be theyr alone Sauiour: which knowledge is perfect righteousnesse,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Sap.</hi> 15. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.</note> and the roote of immortalitie, yea it is euerlastyng lyfe: and without the whyche knowledge, we all are but as moyles and horses, voyde of all goodnes and grace, walkyng in the vanities of our owne imaginations, vtterly estranged from God and all
<pb facs="19"/>
godlynesse. O moste louynge Lorde, open theyr heartes, that they may vnderstand thorough the preachyng of the word, thy holy and blessed wyll, and always doo that, not whiche carnall reason, fleshly imagination, blynd zeale, good intent, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne wysedome iudgeth to be good and holy, but that only, whiche thou in thy blessed lawe commaundest to be doone, all strange woorshippynges vtterly excluded and banyshed. O swete sauiour,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 13.</note> make them that good earth, which receuing the healthfull sede of thy moste wholsom worde, may bryng forth fruite plentuously: some an hundred folde, some sixty folde, some thirty folde.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. <hi>Iac.</hi> 1.</note> Geue theym grace so to lyue; and so to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue them selues in all poyntes, as it becommeth them, that embrace thy Gospell. Lette theym not bee of the number of those, whyche wyth theyr mouth professe God, and with their deedes denye hym, but make them not onely diligente hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of thy woorde, but also feruent and earnest doers of the same.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Math.</hi> 25.</note> Let them not be lyke the fyue foolishe virgins, whiche hadde lampes and no oyle, but rather so woorke in theym by thy holy spirite, that they maye worthyly be resembled to the fyue wyse virgins, whyche had not onely lampes, but also oyle in their lampes, that is to saye, they dyd not onely beare the name of Chrystians, but theyr conuersation also was garnyshed wyth woorkes meete and seemely for Christians. Make them suche as no man can iustely complayne on, euen the vnfayned sonnes of God without rebuke,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> shynynge as greate lyghtes in the worlde, euen in the myddes of a croked and peruerse nation; holdyng faste the woorde of lyfe, that they, whyche backebyte them as euyll doers, seynge theyr good workes;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> may cease to speake euyll, and glorifie thee our Lord God in the day of visitation.</p>
   <p>Fynally, graunt bothe to me the Preacher, and to these the hearers, and to so manye as vnfaynedly professe thy bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed name, grace and strength from aboue, that we maye soo handle and heare thy woorde,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iac.</hi> 1.</note> that we beynge no forgetfull hearers, but diligent doers of the same, may thorowe Faithe in thee, obteyne that blessyng, whyche thou haste promysed to all theym that heare the worde of God,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luc.</hi> 11.</note> and kepe it. Grant
<pb facs="19"/>
thys O moste louyng lorde and swete Sauiour for thy greate mercy and goodnes sake. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>