<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Terry, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101270_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13630</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23913</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101270</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Terry, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triall of trvth : containing a plaine and short discovery of the chiefest pointes of the doctrine of the great Antichrist, and of his adherentes the false teachers and heretikes of these last times</title>
                 <author>Terry, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Broome (Brome), Joan</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 160 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is a necessary duty (good Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader) for every mēber in mans body, even for the meanest and basest as wel as for the most principal to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their common service for the cōmon benefit &amp; preservation of the whole: even so it is as needful for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry member of the Church &amp; cōmon weale, be he higher or lower, greater or lesse, to walke pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in his seueral calling, &amp; in obediēce to God, who hath thus or thus placed him &amp; carefully to discharge that dutie which the Lord requireth at his hands. For there are none of Gods blessings, be they in cōparison of the greater of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so low a rate &amp; estimatiō, but that they are worthy that we should employ our cares &amp; cogitations about the lavv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obtaining, encreasing, &amp; preserving of the same: &amp; there is no talent so smal cōmitted to any, that is carelesly or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuously to be flunge aside, <hi>tied vp in a napkin,</hi> or <hi>buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 25.</note>
      <hi>in the groūd.</hi> Should a little light be cleane put out, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it may fit some little cādlesticke, &amp; serue to lightē some little house? Or should a man of meane stature, when he is assaulted by his enemy, stand nothing at al vpon his owne defence, but cast away al manner of weapon, because he is not able to vse <hi>Hercules</hi> clubbe? Our Saviour Christ (which <note place="margin">Isa 42 3. Mat. 21. 16.</note>
      <hi>breaketh not the bruised reede, nor quencheth the smoaking flax)</hi> reiected not the testimony of very <hi>childrē crying in the tēple &amp; saying, Hosanna, the son of Dauid,</hi> but gaue strēgth vnto it with <hi>Haue ye never reade; out of the mouthes of babes</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 8. 2.</note>
      <hi>and sucklings thou hast made perfite thy praise.</hi> Little <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> vnable to beare the weapon of a man of warre, beeing <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.</note>
      <pb facs="6"/> strengthned by the Lords aide, prevailed against great Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah. And experience doth teach that in martiall services, a meane souldiours bullet may strike some cheife man of the adverse part, and so further the winning of the fielde, and helpe to the getting of the full victorie. The Lords hād is not shortned, nor his spirit tied: the planting and watring of such as haue the greatest giftes is nothing, <hi>vnlesse God</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 7.</note>
      <hi>giue the encrease:</hi> and the laboures of the meanest Minister of Christ may be profitable to his Church, when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the Lord to giue a blessing therevnto. Yea the meaner the instrument, the greater is the glorie of him that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by the same, when <hi>all men that see it shall say, this hath</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Cor. 47.</note>
      <hi>the Lord done: and shall perceaue that it is his worke.</hi> Vpon these groundes haue I beene emboldened (good Christian Reader) albeit but a meane souldiour to come into the fielde with the residue of the Lordes army, to the succou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, if it be but of one soule, or to the rescuing of one cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue out of the enimies handes.</p>
   <p>Many things do plainly cōvince the B. of <hi>Rome</hi> &amp; his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herēts as the most capitall enimies of Christes Church in these last times &amp; endes of the world. For howsoever they pretend thēselues to be the onely preservers, yet in truth they are most greavous destroiers of the Catholike faith: &amp; albeit they make a shew as if they were the cheifest pillars, yet they are the greatest pullers downe of the Church of Christ: and although they glory of their perfect consent and agreement with the doctrine of Christ, yet in truth they maintaine many flat &amp; direct cōtradictiōs against the very groūds &amp; foūdations of the doctrine of Christ. The shortest sūme &amp; abridgment of the doctrine of Christ is, <hi>Repēt, &amp; beleeue the gospel.</hi> Repētāce &amp; Faith. Whereof the <note place="margin">Marc. 1. 15.</note> one is occasioned <hi>by the due consideration of our owne most
<pb facs="6"/> manifold and greavous corruptions,</hi> the other <hi>by the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension of the Lordes most singular and endles goodnes.</hi> And therefore the scope of the whole Scripture tēding to teach repētāce &amp; faith, tēdeth likewise to these two ends, on the one side to display &amp; lay open the incomparable excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies &amp; perfectiōs that be in God, that by the beauty therof we may be most earnestly stirred vp to desire reconciliatiō &amp; fellowship with him, to place our whole hope &amp; confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dēce in him &amp; to ascribe vnto him al honour &amp; glory: &amp; on the other side to discover the infirmities &amp; corruptions of man, that therby he may be induced, al selfe loue set aside, to distrust, deny, &amp; renoūce himselfe, to hāg down the head being cōfoūded in himselfe &amp; cast downe to the bottomles pitte of hell. So the Prophet <hi>I say</hi> setting downe the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty working of the gospell at the coming of the Messias te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifieth that thereby <hi>the high lookes shall be humbled, and the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isa. 2. 17. &amp; 24. 23.</note>
      <hi>loftines of man shall be abated, and the Lord onely shall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted in that day: yea that the Moone shal be abashed, and the Sunne ashamed, whē the Lord shal appeare:</hi> that is, that such things, as in our selues seeme beautiful as the Sūne, shalbe covered with darknes, &amp; dashed over as with a coa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the brightnes of Gods most admirable goodnes shining in the face of the glorious Messias. And wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> else also meaneth the Prophet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>zechiell in saying, that <hi>when</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ezech. 16.</note>
      <hi>the Lord hath confirmed his everlasting Covenant with vs, &amp; is pacified towards vs, thē we shal remēber our waies &amp; be ashamed, &amp; neuer open our mouthes any more in respect of our shame?</hi> Wherefore if we will bee partakers of the fruite of the gospell, we must be moued thereby to looke throughly into our own corruptiōs, &amp; to cast down our eies as it were vpō our own fowle feete, that so we may haue our part in that shāe which is the path way to worship &amp; honor. We <note place="margin">Eccl. 4. 21.</note>
      <pb facs="7"/> must not be gazing vpon our peacockes tailes, nor <hi>behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sūne when he shineth, nor the Moone walking in her</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob. 31. 26.</note>
      <hi>brightnes:</hi> that is, we must not admire ourselues no not in respect of our tēporal or spiritual gifts, lest our owne harts do flatter vs in secret, &amp; so induce vs to kisse our own hāds. Surely this is an iniquity to be cōdēned, seing it is a denial <note place="margin">Hab. 2. 4.</note> of the Lord aboue. For <hi>he that lifteth vp himselfe, his hart is not vpright: for the iust shal liue by faith:</hi> which teacheth vs not to admire ourselues, or to trust in our selues, but to go out of our selues and to trust in God, and to place our whole hope in the riches of his grace, &amp; in the fulnes of his goodnes. And in truth we can hardly detract to much from man <hi>(in whose flesh dwelleth no good thing, &amp; al the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiōs</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 7 18. Gen. 6. 5.</note>
      <hi>of whose hart are only evil cōtinually)</hi> that so he may be brought to cast away al selfe loue, pride, &amp; cōfidence in himselfe, &amp; take to himselfe his due deserved cōfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ion and shame, &amp; be vnfainedly hūbled as he ought to be: As on the cōtrary side we cā as hardly ascribe to much to Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or be overlavish in extolling the hight lēgth, bredth, &amp; depth of the loue of Christ that passeth knowledge, that so the pledges of his endles favour may raise vs vp to a true &amp; liuely faith, &amp; to giue him that glory that is due to him. And why should mire that lieth in the streete be so gready to be seasōed with sugar &amp; spice, &amp; a vile peece of a rotten post to be gilded over with fine gold? why should wretched &amp; sinful man be desirous to enlarg his own estimatiō &amp; by advaūcing &amp; lifting vp himselfe prepare a way to a most dā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous downfall? So God be glorified, we ought not greatly regard what becometh of vs, seing all is due to him, &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to vs. And verely the most blessed servants &amp; saints of God being purged and clensed from all corruptions, &amp; being admitted to the vision of God, and to bebold not his
<pb facs="7"/> hinder partes, but even to see him face to face, and so to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his vnspeakable glory, as farre forth as the creature is capable of the same, albeit they are so highly advaūced, yet they take their crownes from their owne heades, and cast them downe before the throne, saying: <note place="margin">Apoc. 4 10. &amp; 11.</note>
      <hi>Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receaue honour, &amp; glorie, &amp; power: for thou hast crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all thinges, &amp; for thy willes sake they were &amp; are created;</hi> never ceasing day nor night to sing <hi>holy, holy, holy, Lord God</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apoc. 15. 4.</note>
      <hi>almighty: who shal not feare thee &amp; glorify thy name, for thou only art holy?</hi> Yea our most glorious Lord &amp; Saviour Christ Iesus himselfe, who was annointed with the oile of gladnes aboue his fellowes, and endued vvith the spirite vvith out measure, vvho is advaunced to the right hand of GOD, and hath all power in heaven and earth giuen vnto him, &amp; is appointed iudge of quicke &amp; deade, when he shall haue finished the worke of his Mediator-shippe, and shall haue placed al the elect of God in the peaceable possessiō of that most glorious kingdome which he hath purchased for thē with his owne blood, thē, as he is man, he shal deliver vp his kingdome to God, &amp; be subiect to him, &amp; that to this end, <hi>that God may be all in all,</hi> all glorie &amp; honour, power &amp; <note place="margin">1. Co. 15. 28</note> praise being worthely ascribed only to him. Whereby it is evident that God can never be sufficiently magnified in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of his incomprehensible goodnes &amp; glory; as on the contrary side man can never be sufficiently hūbled &amp; aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, especially in comparison had vnto God.</p>
   <p>And yet the members of the Church of Rome, fearing belike that Gods great grace should be to highly magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp; that to much should be yeelded therevnto, &amp; being loath (as it seemeth) that man should take to himselfe that due deserued shāe that belōgeth vnto him, wil haue <hi>neither</hi>
      <note place="margin">Conc. Trid. sess 6. cap. 1. Can. 7.</note>
      <hi>al our workes before our cōversatiō being dōe without faith
<pb facs="8"/> to be condemned for sinne, nor all our good workes after our</hi>
      <note place="margin">Cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>. con. 25. Cap. 2. can. 4.</note>
      <hi>conversion to be stained so much as with any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ental sinne, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all our very sinnes to be damnable and mortall nor yet our conversion it selfe to be wrought only by the spirit of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but also by the power of our owne free wil: neither our salvation to be ascribed to the only death of our all sufficient Saviour, but also to our owne merites and desertes.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <note place="margin">Cap. 11. can. 32. Psal. 115. 1.</note>
      <hi>David</hi> was of another spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e: <hi>Not vnto vs, O Lorde</hi> (saith he) <hi>not vnto vs, but vnto thy n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e giue the praise, for thy loving mercy &amp; for thy truthes sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e, Oh,</hi> (saith <hi>Aust.) God doth prevent thee in all thinges, prevent thou also his wrath: How? Confesse that all good thou receivest of him, and all evil</hi>
      <note place="margin">Serm. 10. de ver. Apost.</note>
      <hi>from thy selfe.</hi> But the Church of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ome regardeth not this holesome counsel of this learned Father, shee will not haue her children to disgrace themselues so much, as to confesse themselues voide of al goodnes and replenished with all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill: neither will shee haue the free mercy of God in Christ so farre fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fied and extolled, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> all the due deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved glory of al celestial graces were to be ascribed thervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: and therefore God in his iust wrath hath given her over to her owne blindnes, that making her boast that her faith <note place="margin">No maner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth more then hee that thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver erreth.</note> cannot faile, yet shee teacheth divers and manifold errours contrary to all the grounds of the Catholike faith. For ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grievous and damnable are the heresies, wherewithall the Bishop and Church of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ome are most truely and iustly charged by vs, which professe the Gospell of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esus Christ: for the removing wherof the words indeed of the scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ure are alleadged by them; but the question being of the right sence thereof, albeit the children of that Church pretende for the iustifying of their interpretations <hi>the consent of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi>
      <note place="margin">Stap. doct. princ. li. 7. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> 8 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> l. 10. cap. 11.</note>
      <hi>the common testimony of the faithfull, &amp; the decrees of councels,</hi> yet at the last only, or at the least principally, they
<pb facs="8"/> rest vpon <hi>the definitiue sentence and censure of the Pope.</hi> So that the question being whether the Pope bee Antichrist, the ful and finall decision thereof must in the ende as they teach) be devolved to the Pope himse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fe, and hee must be the Iudge in his owne cause Now what is this, but aske my fellow, nay aske my selfe, whether I am a thiefe? Whereby they make manifest vnto the whole world the great weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and wretchedne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of their owne cause, which cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise be iustified &amp; approved, vnlesse the guilty parties thēselues be suffered to pronounce the definitiue sentence. Whereas our Saviour Christ testifieth of himselfe, saying: <hi>If I shoulde beare witnesse of my selfe, my witnesse were not</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioh 5. 31. Ioh. 8. 54.</note>
      <hi>true.</hi> And againe: <hi>If I should honour my selfe, my honour is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth.</hi> If then our Saviour himselfe would not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved vpon his owne bare word, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t had his doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by his Fathers voice from heaven, by the testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Prophets, and by his owne miracles: what pride possesseth the Popes heart, that he will not submit himselfe as Christ did, and be tried as he was tried? Now herein the Antichristian presumption of the Bishop of Rome in exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himselfe aboue our Saviour Christ beeing manifestly detected, with the great nakednes and wretchednes of his cause, his friendes to shadow &amp; darken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he same, haue rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <note place="margin">Camp. rat. 2 Poss. Bibl. select no. 7. cap. 18.</note> vp a mist of a most notorious slander against vs, as if we were those parties, that would be tried by none but by our selues, and would allow in no manner of controversie the iudgement of any Interprete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, but <hi>Luthers, Melancthons, Caluins, Bezaes</hi> or the like. The which thing if it were true, we see no reason why we may not iustifie the same far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then they can their depending vpon the Popes chaire. For these mē were painefully exercised in praier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, reading, and meditation, and were furnished with the knowledge of
<pb facs="9"/> Artes and tongues which are great helpes to the attaining vnto the right interpretation of holy scriptures. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is averred by men of their ovvne profession as a thing notorious, that many of their <hi>Popes haue not vnderstood the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Alphonsus li. 1. c. 4.</note>
      <hi>groundes and principles of the very Grammer it selfe: and of those that haue beene learned, the greater sort haue beene ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in pointes of policie, rather then in sound and profound Divinity.</hi> Now right interpretation of holy scriptures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obtained from God <hi>not extraordinarily by revelation</hi> in these daies, but <hi>ordinarily by meanes,</hi> let all indifferent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons iudge vvhether the vnlearned or politike Popes, or the other so wel studied &amp; learned men were like to be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Interpreters of holy scriptures. But indeede we stand not vpon this exception, but constantly avouch that this their accusation is a most impudent and shameles slaunder raised vp in al likelyhoode even against their ovvne consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, as it may appeare by the appeale of that reverend Father John Juell in diverse controversies betweene thē and vs made vnto all approved antiquity cited &amp; censured euen by themselues. For vve like of the testimonies of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <note place="margin">Camp. Rat 5.</note> Church and Councels, and haue iust cause in many pointes to allovv of their decisions: but we tie not the truth necessarily vnto them, but vnto the spirit of truth, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Autor, is also the best interpreter of holy Scripture, having therefore plainely set downe in them all necessarie points of faith, that the plaine &amp; easie places therof, might be as lightes to the darke and obscure, for the better ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and explaning of the same.</p>
   <p>Yea as in al Artes &amp; Sciences there are some principles and grounds vndeniable and vnavoideable, having open &amp; manifest truth in themselues evident to the light of nature shining in vs, and winning credit to thēselues by their own
<pb facs="9"/> perspicuous verity, by the which the certainety of al other precepts of lesse perspicuity &amp; authority is to be tried: evē so in Theology also there are certaine principles &amp; groūds, having open, confessed, &amp; vndeniable truth in themselues, such as are the Articles of the Apostles creede, vnto which the interpretations of darker places are to be referred, &amp; by which the doubts &amp; cōtroversies in matters of faith are to be decided. For these are even as great torch-lightes, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning both themselues &amp; others also. And as any having but meane skil in that craft, if he set but the level to the worke, shal soone see whether it be right: or if he rub the mettal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the touch-stone, he shal quickly perceiue what it is: even so to any that is but meanly experienced in the doctrine of Christ, if he compare his faith to these grounds of faith, he may soone perceiue whether he hold a soūd faith. For as in Law, &amp; Physicke, &amp; in al other libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>al Arts &amp; Sciences the painfull studēt may attaine to a sufficient knowledge of the same by the helpe especially of their maine groundes and principles, albeit there bee no vnerring Interpreter able to decide al doubts and controversies therein: even so in The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ology, albeit there be none vnerring Interpreter amōg mē, yet the studious &amp; devout Christian may attaine to a suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient knowledge of al such points of faith as are necessary to salvatiō by the helpe of the maine grounds &amp; principles of faith. Or may we suppose that the God of all, but especially of such as beleue, hath bin more careful for the <hi>naturalmā</hi> by leaving those principles which stande vpon their owne ground, that so he may attaine to the knowledge of all such Arts &amp; sciences which are profitable for the maintenāce of this tēporal life: that he hath not left the like principles and groūds for the <hi>regenerate mā,</hi> wherby he may attaine to the knowledge of al such things as do cōcerne eternal life? And if Aristotle bee iudge in Philosophy, Galene in Physicke,
<pb facs="10"/> Iustinian in the law, albeit many of their rules &amp; precepts he diversly expounded by their Interpreters: even so albeit there be diverse expositions of holy scripture, yet God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide but the holy scripture of God the most cleare &amp; pure fountaine of truth should be the iudge of faith, &amp; that espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by the maine grounds of faith therein cōtained. The which are therefore named by the aunciēt Fathers <hi>the key</hi>
      <note place="margin">A b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> serm 38. Aug. de doct. Christ. l. 3. cap 2. &amp; 3. De Temp. Serm 119. So r. hist. Eccles. lib. 5. Cap. 10.</note>
      <hi>and rule of faith,</hi> for that the perspicuity &amp; plainnes of thē doth open as it were a doore into all the mysteries of faith. And hereof it was, that not only Theodosius the Emperor vsed thē as a meanes to end all cōtroversies in his time: but S. Austin also, being to expoūd the first booke of Moses, called Gen. setteth thē down in the forefrōt of his worke, as a rule whereby he meaneth to frame al his interpretatiōs: that if they misse in the meaning of any particular place, yet they may not erre in the substāce of faith because he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voucheth nothing but that which is agreable to the groūds of faith. So likwise Tertulliā &amp; Iraene that liued near the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles <note place="margin">See Kemnis. Exa Trid. Conc. de tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionibus.</note> time, whē certaine heretikes charged the scriptures (as the mēbers of the Church of Rome doe now) that they were <hi>in sufficiēt, dark, &amp; ambiguous, &amp; that the truth could not be foūd out by them without traditions,</hi> they ioined issue with thē, &amp; referred themselues to the iudgmēt of that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which the Apostles delivered by tradition to the Churches: the sūme whereof they relate, altogeather as it were, evē as it is set down in the Apostles Creed, being the very pith &amp; substāce of that faith, which was delivered first by mouth by the Apostles thēselues, &amp; afterward set downe in their writings, that it might be the pillar &amp; foūdatiō of faith: &amp; al interpretatiōs of scripture they require to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable to this entire &amp; perfect body of truth, as they had learned of the Apostle S. Paul, that al prophecie should bee <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 6.</note>
      <pb facs="10"/> sutable &amp; proportionable to the faith. Vnto the which Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies of these learned Fathers, I adde the iudgment of Beza &amp; Kēnitius quoted before, that al indifferēt persōs may perceiue, that we walke in the sāe waies, that these learned Fathers haue trod out vnto vs, &amp; vsed the same meanes to attaine to the right interpretatiō of holy scripture, and to a sound &amp; catholike iudgment in matters of faith. <hi>No hūble</hi>
      <note place="margin">Serm. in c 3. Cant.</note>
      <hi>christiā</hi> (saith Beza) <hi>if he desire to be taught, cā be deceiued in the interpretatiō of holy scripture, if he diligētly cōfer place with place according vnto the exāple of our S. Christ, &amp; the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 4. 7.</note>
      <hi>practise of the aunciēt Coūcels: &amp; if with all he referre the whole vnto the correspōdēcy of the articles of our faith, which we call our Creede, being the sūmary abridgmēt of every fū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damētall point of our Christian religiō.</hi> Most notable also to <note place="margin">Serm 4 de Incarnat. Dumini.</note> this purpose is that of Leo: <hi>If any</hi> (saith he) <hi>shal preach vnto you any other thing besides that which ye haue learned, let him be accursed preferre not wicked fables before evidēt truth: &amp; whatsoever it shall happē that ye read or heare cōtrary to the rule of the Catholike &amp; Apostolike Creede, accoūt it alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather dānable &amp; divelish.</hi> By which testimony of this lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Father we may gather, that the doctrine of faith sette down in the Creede is that evidēt truth which was delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Apostles, &amp; whatsoever is contrary to the same is a wicked fable &amp; to be accursed, as being no better then flat dānable &amp; divelish. Wherefore (good Christiā reader) if thou wouldst not willingly hold that faith which is fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, accursed, dānable, &amp; diuelish, examine thy faith ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to those groūds, which are both easie, short, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, least thou shouldst plead ignorāce in thy selfe, or lēgth &amp; tediousnes in the worke it selfe. Be not ouer credulous in this matter of so greate moment, nor so simple as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue any pointes of faith, which are not agreeable to this rule of faith, No although that they be ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ght by that
<pb facs="11"/> Church which maketh her boast that she cānot erre, and that the faith of her cheife governor cā never faile Nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if thou wilt be a sound scholer in the schoole of Christ, learne to <hi>yeelde that reverence &amp; honour only to the bookes of</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug ep 91. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>litron.</note>
      <hi>the diuine scripture, that thou firmely beleue that none of the Autors of thē erred any whit in the penning of the same:</hi> giue this prerogatiue only to the worde of God, that it hath his sufficiēt warrāt &amp; credite in itselfe, because it is inspired of God &amp; proceedeth frō him which cānot erre, deceiue, or be deceiued: &amp; as for the writtings of all other, albeit they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel in wisdom &amp; holines, receiue thē not because they haue thus iudged, but for that they are cōfirmed by the autority of the Canonicall scripture, or by some reasō agreable vnto <note place="margin">Hom. 13. in 2. ep ad Cor</note> trueth. And verily <hi>it is an absurd thing</hi> (as Chrysost saith) <hi>in a mony matter not to trust an other, but to tell that evē af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a mans own father, &amp; in matters of farre greater momēt, which cōcerne Gods glory, &amp; the salvatiō of our owne soules, in a simple &amp; sottish credulity to follow the iudgmēts of other men, whereas also we haue a most exact ballāce &amp; rule, even the cēsure &amp; determinatiō of the divine lawes. Yea whereas we are precisely cōmāded to proue all, &amp; to approue the best: &amp;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Th. 5. 21. 1. Ioh 4. 1. 1. Cor. 14. &amp; 32.</note>
      <hi>not to beleeue every spirit, but to try the spirits, whether they bee of God or no: for that the spirits of the Prophets are sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Prophets &amp; therefor by trial to be foūd true before they be beleeued.</hi> Neither is it any disgrace to the iudgmēt of man, to be subiect to the cēsure of Gods spirite, already set downe in the canonical scriptures: for evē the spirit of God speaking in S. Paul was cōtēt to be tried by the sacred scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that is in truth by himselfe; &amp; the Bereās at cōmēded <note place="margin">Act 17. 11. Apoc. 2. 2.</note> for doing the same: as the Ange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l of the church of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>phesus is also cōmended for <hi>examining</hi> thē which said they were A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles &amp; <hi>finding thē liars.</hi> So likewise our Saviour Christ
<pb facs="11"/> the wisdome of God, in whome were hid al the treasures of knowledge, willeth his auditors to <hi>search the scriptures,</hi> &amp; <note place="margin">Ioh. 5. 39.</note> so to try by thē, whether he taught any other doctrine thē was cōtained in these sacred bookes: <hi>for in them</hi> (saith he) <hi>ye thinke to haue life,</hi> &amp; they are my deponēts &amp; witnesses: Neither doth he desire any better lurers to giue evidēce cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the truth of his doctrine. And S. Hierome foretel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth of the faithfull of these last daies, that <hi>they shall not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi>
      <note place="margin">In Nah. c. 3.</note>
      <hi>thēselues any longer to be kept in ignorance by their blind guides, but shal ascend vp to the moūtaines of the Apostles &amp; Prophets, that by the cleere light of their infallible doctrine they may be directed in the right way to their eternall salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Wherefore as many of vs as <hi>desire to be saued by cōming</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 4.</note>
      <hi>to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> let vs follow the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt of Christ and his Apostles, &amp; the example of the noble Bereās, &amp; of the faithful of these last time; let vs ascēd vp to the mountaine of the Apostles &amp; Prophets, &amp; take them to be our guids in all our ghostly &amp; spirituall affaires, &amp; let vs by their Canonicall writings, especially by the foūdatiōs of faith in thē cōtained, as by a most certaine &amp; sure rule, try the doctrine of al mē &amp; angels, &amp; of al particular Churches whatsoever, be they Frēch, Duch, Spanish, or Italian. I hat law that will not be tried, is worthely suspected, &amp; that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which flieth the light, is the doctrine of darknes. For truth seeketh not corners, it would not be covered vnder a bushel, but set on a cādlestick, she would not haue her face masked, lest she should passe vnknown, she would appeare with opē coūtenāce, that so she might be iustified of all her childrē. For thy furtherāce herein (good Christiā <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eader) in this short treatise (the which if it giue but occasiō to some other to hādle the same matter in māner more suffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ient, I neede not accoūt my labour to be lost) I haue laide purple
<pb facs="12"/> to purple, that it might the better be discerned, as also the cloth of the cōtrary colour: that is, I haue ioined to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our Christian Creede, the points of our Christian faith agreeable therevnto, as also such erronious and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical positions, which are repugnāt &amp; contrary to the same. The which thing being so behouefull and necessary, it had bin convenient that some one of great giftes had been em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied therin, neither could his learning &amp; eloquence haue beene more advanced, then in being handmaides in so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable a service. But now it pleaseth the Lorde to send this present vnto thee by the hands of a simple servitour, and in a rude and vnpolished speech as in an earthen platter or wodden dish, that so the meate may rellish for the meates sake it selfe, &amp; not for the fairenes or goodlines of the dish. But first thou must purge and free thy taste frō the corrupt humors of partiality, and of al obstinate &amp; wilful resolutiōs: neither must thou presume to appointe of thy selfe what shal be sweet, &amp; what sowre, but suffer the Lord himselfe only to be thy taster therein: and so thou maiest also in thy course both taste and see how gracious the Lord is, and at the length attaine to the blessednes of al such, as place their whole hope and confidence in him. The Lord for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies sake disperse more &amp; more the grosse misles of al spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall blindnes and darknes, and open thine heart, as hee did the heart of <hi>Lidia,</hi> &amp; giue thee vnderstanding in all things, <note place="margin">Act. 16. 14.</note> graunting vnto thee the spirit of truth to leade thee into al truth, for his owne glory, and thine vnspeakeable comfort and ioy.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, JOHN TERRY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>