<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101648_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11333</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21593</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101648</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Narbonus : The laberynth of libertie. Very pleasant for young gentlemen to peruse, and passing profitable for them to prosecute. Wherein is contained the discommodities that insue, by following the lust of a mans will, in youth: and the goodnesse he after gayneth, being beaten with his owne rod, and pricked with the peeushnesse of his owne conscience, in age. VVriten by Austin Saker, of New Inne</title>
                 <author>Saker, Austin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 146, 2, 123, that is 125, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶ To the Gentlemen Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Stood maruailing Gentlemen, after the</hi> vvriting of this troublesome trashe, and the fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of this tedious trauaile, and fared like <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexanders</hi> man, who shiuered in the Sunne and svvet in the shadovv: or like the <hi>Thessalian</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die that wept, when she beheld her protrated Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and vvas sorrovvfull vvhen she vvrote any letter, fering it should be disliked: I doubted, vvhether best present this to the Printer to be put in the Presse, or giue it the Painter to pinne on a Poste, but remembring that the Painter, if a mā be bald, he paints him bare: then thought I, this beeing nothing nice, he vvill dravv it starke naked: yet let the Printer haue any booke, and it shall be bought though but a bable, and let the Painter haue any Picture, and it shall be stared on, though but a Beast. Seeing therfore <hi>Vulcan</hi> to be draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en with his foule foote, so well as <hi>Venus</hi> to be painted vvith her faire face, I thought my booke might as well lie in a shop, as other ballads which stand at sale: yet he that puts any thing in Print to the end to haue it praised, is like him that coms into a Church to haue his bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery noted: But <hi>Tullie</hi> (I remember) the most eloquent, pleased not al vvith his svveete sayings: and <hi>Crassus</hi> so broade mouthed as any, was liked of some, with his sowre sothings. The solacing strings of <hi>Orpheus</hi> could not saue his life vvith his sweete Musick, yet the Pipe of <hi>Pan,</hi> was liked vvith his rusticall melodie: he vvas regarded in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and I happely shal be read in the Court: he vvas a stale to many, and I looke to be a laughing stock to moe: If the best vvriters haue not beene liked of some wantons, should my selfe thinke mutch to be loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed of many that are vvilfull. I looke not that <hi>Fortune</hi> vvhich was neuer fauourable in woords of small vvaight, should novv be freendly in workes of great wisedome: And as my ill happe hath hetherto beene so hard as anies, so looke I not to haue it amended by this heereafter. The old saying is: he that liues in hel, thinkes there is no other heaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>▪ and he that daunceth with the Diuell, careth not, so he bee loued of his Damme. <hi>Augustus</hi> sayd, he had rather be a Pigge in <hi>Herodes</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, then a child in his Court: for all the male children he put to the sword, but Svvines flesh amongst the Ievves, was loathesome and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sauerie,
<pb facs="5"/>
and he that shall write to please the faculties of all fancies, must either reache beyond the Moone, or misse of his marke: And if any thinge be vvorthy blame, reprooue <hi>Narbonus</hi> vvho knovves you not, and if <hi>Saker,</hi> any way haue merited shame, let him be repayed vvith such sauce, though he hate you not: Yet had not I liked to loue you, this should neuer haue come foorth of my Libertie: and had I not beene willing to saluted you courteously, I should expected to beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvarded as carelesly: and the moste that I aske, is but <hi>Bona verba,</hi> for my willing minde, and good vvill for my honest meaning: if you repay me with lesse, I must liue by the losse, but if you graunt me so much, it is the vttermost I looke for: And Gentlemē, if you pardon me, for this same beeing the first, I vvill excuse my selfe vvhen I present you the second? vvhich if you denie me, I vovv it shall be the last: And if you gaine saie me this reasonable request, I vvill neuer offend your eares vvith so vnseasonable a sute: As for the verdite of fooles, I plead not for their pardons, and for the sottish sort, I meane not to prooue them vvith protestations: I knovv some will grinne, but not take hould of my flesh: and other vvill snap, but not touche my finger: Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men I knovv vvill be ruled with reason: as for others, I feare not their rigour: for vvho so likes of my doings, I shall be bound to commend their demeanours, but who pretends me faithlesse fauour, I must of force requite vvith flattring freendshippe.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>