<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Protestants
Relation of the Conference,
IVNE 27. 1623.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101879_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00602</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10738</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101879</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Protestants
Relation of the Conference,
IVNE 27. 1623.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Romish Fisher caught and held in his owne net. Or, A true relation of the Protestant conference and popish difference : A iustification of the one, and refutation of the other. In matter of fact. faith. By Daniel Featly, Doctor in Diuinity</title>
                 <author>Featley, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 46, 106, 176, 12, 50, 49-191, that is 190 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Protestants
Relation of the Conference,
<date>IVNE 27. 1623.</date>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing commanded by my Lord his Grace of
<hi>Canterbury,</hi> from his Maiesty, to certifie
the truth of that which passed in a late con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,
in point of Religion, at Sir <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey
Linde</hi>'s house in <hi>Sheer-Lane,</hi> in <hi>London:</hi> we,
who were present at the Conference, partly, out of the
fresh memory of such passages as we then obserued; but
especially, by help of such Notes as were taken in the
Conference it self, subscribed by both the Disputants,
drew vp, within a week after, as perfect a Relation of
the substance thereof, as we could: wherein as we added
nothing to the aduantage or preiudice of either party; so
wee omitted nothing of moment, in the Current of the
Arguments and Answers. As for some interlocutory
speeches of the right honourable the Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi>
who diuers times seasonably interposed, and, when the
Disputants or standers-by grew into any heat or distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
discreetly tempered both sides,
<q>Ille regit dictis animos, &amp; pectora mulcet.</q>
—those passages we inser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
not into our narration, because, the Earle beeing not
then in <hi>London,</hi> we held it incongruous, without his
<pb facs="7"/>
Honours knowledge, to vse his name to the King. For
other omissions, the Iesuites are beholding vnto vs: for,
they were in fauour of them; wee beeing loth to bee <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues
in vlcere,</hi> to bee thought to rub too hard vpon a
gawle, but rather desirous to carry the whole Relation as
fairly and passably as might be.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12. 13.</note> We had thought, the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites
would haue pardoned vs this wrong.</p>
   <p>After this originall Draught was by vs tendered
to his Grace of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and by his Grace deliuered
to the Kings Maiesty, some Copie (as we vnderstand)
was taken, for the satisfaction of a Person of quality:
which, passing from one to another, in the end fell into
the hands of some Stationers; who, without licence or
knowledge of those whom it most concerned, committed
it to the Presse, <hi>de questu magis, quàm quaestione
soliciti.</hi> And the better to vent this new wine, they
set a faire Garland before the dore, intituling it, <hi>The
FISHER caught in his owne Net.</hi> Which Title
was not deuised nor prefixed by any of vs: we willingly
leaue the vanity of such affected inscriptions to our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries,
who make themselues ridiculous in this kinde.
One intituleth his Answer to D. <hi>White, WHITE
dyed black.</hi> Another cals his woodden Pamphlet,
<hi>The Gag of the new Religion, or of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
Gospell.</hi> Another, his Reply to M. <hi>BELL,
Cecidit BELL, The dolefull knell of THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAS
BELL.</hi> This is not the sound of <hi>AARON'S
golden Bell;</hi> but rather of the <hi>tinkling Cymball</hi>
mentioned by Saint <hi>PAVL, 1. Cor. 13.</hi> Fancies and
Iigs make no good Church-musick.
<q>
         <l>Nobis non licet esse tam disertis,</l>
         <l>Qui Musas colimus sacratiores.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
For the Title therefore, wee approoue it not: but
for the Conference it selfe, it containeth nothing but the
truth, whatsoeuer the <hi>Aduersaries</hi> giue out to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
who (as it seemeth) hold it a work of supererogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
to forge and coyne signall and transcendent Leasings
for the Catholick Cause; for, although the Iesuites, at
this Conference, were often vncertaine, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
very slow and tardy in their Answers, and (in
fine) answered nothing, but that they would not answer
Doctor <hi>FEATLY</hi> his instance in <hi>CHRIST</hi> and his
<hi>Apostles;</hi> yet haue they or their Schollers proclaimed
in <hi>Gath,</hi> and published in <hi>Ascalon,</hi> such a victory as
neuer was heard; much like <hi>the wonderfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction
of the superior Planets, which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er
seene.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>About a weeke after the Conference, the noble Earle
of <hi>Warwick,</hi> who had bin present at it, hauing occasion
to passe ouer the Seas, and comming to Saint <hi>Omers,</hi>
had the Company of Doctor <hi>Weston</hi> at his Inne; to
whom this Doctor (taking the Earle for a Romane Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick)
told for fresh and most happy newes out of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
that at a Conference betweene Father <hi>FISHER</hi>
and <hi>SVVEET,</hi> Iesuites, and two Protestant Ministers,
in <hi>London,</hi> the Iesuites had quitted themselues so well,
and the Catholique faith preuailed so farre, that two
Earles, and an hundred other of the Auditory
were gayned to the Church of Rome by this
Incounter: of these two Earles, the party to
whom hee spake, was one, who could not but smile
at this Relation.
<q>
         <pb facs="8"/>
         <l>Risit Atlantiades; et me mihi, perfide, prodis,</l>
         <l>Me mihi prodis, ait?</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>A pretty Comick Scene, where the Spectator is made
an Actor, and a false person put vpon him to his face:
a renowned and constant Protestant, borne downe to be
a Romish Proselyte. As for the reuolt of the other Earle,
and pretended Centurie of Protestant Romane Conuerts,
we beleeue it as firmely, as that<note n="a" place="margin">Vitae Sanct. Brigittae. Vitae S. Aldelmi.</note> S. <hi>BRIGET</hi> laid her
Wimple, and Saint <hi>ALDELME</hi> his Chesible vpon a
beame of the Sunne, which supported them. That Saint
<hi>NICOLAS,</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Festivale de Sancto Nicolao.</note> while hee lay in his cradle, fasted
Wednesday and Fryday; these daies hee would not suck,
but once in the day. That<note n="c" place="margin">Legend. de Sancto Patricio.</note> Saint <hi>PATRICK</hi> caused
a stolne sheep to bleate in the belly of him that had eaten it.
That the corps of<note n="d" place="margin">Legend. de Sancto Stephan.</note> S. <hi>LAVRENCE,</hi> at the coming
of Saint <hi>STEPHENS</hi> body, smiled for ioy, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
it selfe to the other side of the Sepulcher, to make
roome for him;<note n="e" place="margin">Ep. Clem. ad Iac. in Ep. Pontif.</note> that <hi>CLEMENS</hi> wrote a Letter
to Saint <hi>IAMES</hi> the brother of our Lord, seuen yeeres
after hee was dead; that<note n="f" place="margin">Vide Breu. &amp; picturas Dionys. vel interrog. Paris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>enses.</note> Saint <hi>DENNIS</hi> carried
his head in his hand three miles, and rested at each place
of the posts, that are set betweene <hi>Paris</hi> and Saint <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis;</hi>
that<note n="g" place="margin">Legend. de Dunst. &amp; picturae pass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Saint <hi>DVNSTONE</hi> held the diuell fast by
the nose with a paire of tongues; that the<note n="h" place="margin">Hist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ire de N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>stre Dame de L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>retto.</note> chamber of our
Lady was carried by Angels through the Ayre, from
<hi>Palestine</hi> to <hi>Loretto,</hi> in <hi>Italy;</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">Annot. in Clemanges ex Caesario.</note> that our Lady
helped Saint <hi>THOMAS BECKET</hi> to mend or
stitch his hayre-cloth;<note n="k" place="margin">Legend. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Cant.</note> that a Parrat crying out, Saint
<hi>THOMAS help me,</hi> was deliuered from an Hawk;
<note n="l" place="margin">Legend. de L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>that Saint <hi>LVPVS</hi> shut vp the diuell in a tankard all
night; that<note n="m" place="margin">Legend. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. vid. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Theol.</note> Saint <hi>DOMINICK</hi> made the Diuell
<pb facs="8"/>
hold the candle to him till hee burnt his fingers; that
<note n="n" place="margin">Vitae Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisci.</note>Saint <hi>FRANCIS</hi> swallowed a Spider in a Chalice
which Spider came whole out of his thigh; that the
<note n="o" place="margin">Cheney Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr Carthus.</note>Image of the Crucifix turnd tayle to <hi>GREGORY</hi>
the Monke, when hee went from the <hi>Vespers,</hi> to walk
in the <hi>Chapter-</hi> house; that<note n="p" place="margin">Sedul. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisc.</note>
      <hi>Fryer ANDREVV,</hi>
to correct his appetite of eating birds at the Table, by the
signe of the <hi>Crosse,</hi> commanded them to fly away after
they were rosted;<note n="q" place="margin">Author of the Relation of the Western Religion.</note> that the <hi>Thunder</hi> of the <hi>Popes</hi>
excommunications so blasted the <hi>Hugonotes,</hi> that their
faces were growne as black and vgly as the diuell;<note n="r" place="margin">Vitae Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>j.</note> that
<hi>FRANCIS IVNIVS</hi> had a round clouen foot like
an Oxe;<note n="s" place="margin">Beza redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuus.</note> that <hi>BEZA</hi> recanted his religion before his
death;<note n="t" place="margin">My Lord of <hi>Londons</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacie.</note> that the reuerend Doctor <hi>KING,</hi> late Bishop
of <hi>London,</hi> died a Papist; or,<note n="u" place="margin">Interroga vicin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> de re iam recenti.</note> that the Protestants at
<hi>Black-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ryers,</hi> by knocking certaine pins out of the tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
caused that late &amp; lamentable fall of the floar: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
about 200 Papists were assembled, and neere a 100
slaine. They who teach pious frauds, and write of holy
hypocrisy, and doctrinally deliuer the lawfulnesse of
equiuocation, may securely report, whatsoeuer maketh
for the <hi>Catholique</hi> Cause. The more incredible and
palpable the Lie is, the more merit in him that maketh
it, and in them that beleeue it. <hi>Popery</hi> is a doctrine
composed of Lies: and <hi>Philosophy</hi> teacheth, that all
things are fed and maintained by such things of which
they are bred and made. The <hi>aliments</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> must
bee correspondent to the <hi>elements</hi> of which it consisteth:
and verily as hee said in the Poet, <hi>Si ius violandum
est, Regni causa violandum,</hi> if a man must transgresse
the Law of honesty and Iustice, he must doeit for a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:
<pb facs="9"/>
so it is like they are resolued, if a man must lye,
certainely hee must lye for the good of the Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;
and if lie in so good a cause, lye to some pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose.</p>
   <p>The first report concerning the issue of this Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
was of a silly woman, said to be present, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted
thereby to the Romish faith, who forsooth stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
vpon her <hi>English Bible,</hi> and solemnly renounced
the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion vpon it; protesting, she would
neuer trust hereticall Translation any more. But, alas!
this was but a silly lye, made by some p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>isne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ouice of
the petty forme, to see how a lye in this kinde would
take. The higher Schollers in the Iesuites Schoole,
thought it behooued them to make a <hi>Catholick</hi> or vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall
lye for the <hi>Catholick</hi> cause, by giuing out, that
the whole company of Protestants present at that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,
was gayned to the Romish faith, yea, and many
more Protestants then were there also for 100, some say,
400▪ is the summe of the supposed Conuerts; whereas
there were not neere a hundred persons in both parties
in all at the Conference; and (as wee conceiue) neere
20. were professed Papists, and knowne Recusants: and
for the rest, which were Noble-men, Gentle-men, and
Gentle-women of quality, with some few Diuines, there
was not one of them any way staggered in Religion by
this meeting; but on the contrary, they haue openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest,
that they were much established and confirmed in
the truth of the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion by it: and Master
<hi>BVGGES</hi> himselfe, (whose satisfaction by this
Conference was principally intended) who before had
doubted of our Church, after this Disputation, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth
<pb facs="9"/>
himselfe fully resolued through the mercy of
God: to whose grace we commend all that loue the Truth
in sincerity.</p>
   <p>As for those, who contrary to the euidence of truth,
and so many testimonies beyond all exception, are yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued
to beleeue what the Iesuites report for their owne
aduantage in their owne cause; the Iesuites, wee say,
who maintaine, that a man may vtter an vntruth in
words without the guilt of <hi>Veniall</hi> sinne, so hee be sure
to make it vp by a mentall reseruation: vpon such as
stand thus affected, wee bestow the blessing of<note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>August. Thuan.</hi> ad An. 1556. Carama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis <hi>Caraffa</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetiam Regni Metropol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greditur, solitâ pompâ, tanquam Pontificis Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus; vbi cùm signum Crucis, vt fit, ederet, verborum, quae proferri mos est, loco, ferunt eum vt erat securus de numme animo, &amp; summus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionum derisor occursante pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sim populo, in genua procūben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, saepiùs secretâ murmuratione haec verba inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minâsse: Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doquidem, &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall
CARAFFA:</hi> who, when the people flocked
to him in great multitudes to be blest by him, (beeing ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
at <hi>Paris,</hi> comming as Legate from the Pope), lifting
vp his eyes deuoutly to heauen, and making▪ ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the manner, crosses in stead of the accustomed
forme of <hi>Episcopall benediction,</hi> blessed the honest
vulgar French-men in these words: <hi>Quandoquidem
iste populus vult decipi, decipiatur:</hi> If so be this
people will bee gulled or deceiued <hi>(with such shewes
and fopperies),</hi> let them be gulled or deceiued.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>