<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101572_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05679</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1579</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101572</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The portraiture of hypocrisie, liuely and pithilie pictured in her colours : wherein you may view the vgliest and most prodigious monster that England hath bredde</title>
                 <author>Bate, John, m.a</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dalderne, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 192, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>
      <pb facs="6"/>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE lamentable securitie (good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader) of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie many men who by their life &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersation doe shew that either they acknowledge no God at al, or think that God (as it is in <hi>Homer</hi>) doth so dallie out the time amongest I know not what <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> that he hath no leasure at all to looke on the state of mankinde: hath mooued me to set abroch this litle portrature of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisies, wherein the corruptions of such double faced protestants are in
<pb facs="7"/>
some part discouered, whose actions are not answerable to their christian profession. For although these men, maruellous wise in their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, perswade themselues that they are sufficiently learned vnto saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: yet are their cogitations darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and they are strangers from the life of God, through the ignoraunce that is in them. And therefore the life of these men may not vnfitly bee compared vnto the life of a madde man, or one that is infected with the falling sickenes. For euen as madde men, or they which are spent with the falling sickenes, do wound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues &amp; know it not, do strike them selues and feele it not, &amp; euen them when they thinke them selues to stande fastest, do slippe most soden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie into dreadfull daunger: euen so these men, which perswade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
<pb facs="7"/>
that they bee sharpe sighted, when they are as blinde as they that are blind on both eyes, are so far past all sense of sinne and feeling of Gods iudgements, that though they bee strikē, they know it not, &amp; although they bee beaten, they feele not the blowes. No, they thinke that they walke in the light, when they grope vp and downe in grosse and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble darkenesse: they thinke they liue when they abide but in death, and promise to thēselues libertie, being (in verie deede) those bondslaues of the diuell, which plucke vppon their owne pates a speedie damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The patterne of which care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse men thou mayest behold in the person of this carnal <hi>Autophilus,</hi> who in his discourse with the good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian <hi>Philoxenus</hi> to smoother his sins &amp; hide his hypocrisie, hath alwaies
<pb facs="8"/>
an excuse as good as an Aperne made of figtree leaues: here in my onely desire is, that this my poore labour may bee accepted of the Lord, and profitable to his people.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>