<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Ho∣norable Sir William Cecill Knight, Baron of Burghley, Knight of the Honorable order of the Garter, one of the Lordes of hir Maiesties priuie Councell and Lord high Treasurer of England, Ieffray FENTON wisheth long life.</title>
           <author>Fenton, Geffray</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101953_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00658</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10793a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101953</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Ho∣norable Sir William Cecill Knight, Baron of Burghley, Knight of the Honorable order of the Garter, one of the Lordes of hir Maiesties priuie Councell and Lord high Treasurer of England, Ieffray FENTON wisheth long life.</title>
                 <author>Fenton, Geffray</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A forme of Christian pollicie drawne out of French by Geffray Fenton. A worke very necessary to al sorts of people generally, as wherein is contayned doctrine, both vniuersall, and special touching the institution of al Christian profession: and also conuenient perticularly for all magistrates and gouernours of common weales, for their more happy regiment according to God</title>
                 <author>Talpin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 352, that is 408 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Sir <hi>William Cecill</hi> Knight, <hi>Baron of</hi> Burghley, <hi>Knight of the</hi> Honorable order of the Garter, one of the Lordes of hir Maiesties priuie Councell and Lord high Treasurer of England, Ieffray FENTON wisheth long life.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE IS</hi> nothing in this world more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie then to hold soueraintie ouer people and nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor any thing more happie then where a whole common weale is dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in conuersation of iustice and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: which, yet if they bee not ioyned with true Religion, can holde no long continuance, for that chaunging accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the perplexities of tymes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning daily in Realmes and Countreis,
<pb facs="3"/> they suffer alteration by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and in the end slyde into vices and imperfections, which breede the reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucions and ruines of all estates. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion can not be entertained, if it bee not backt with ciuill Iustice, which, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocallie hath need of a deuout pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: for that as Religiō is iust, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of it selfe, is holy and religious: so thei are the two estates which the scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture names the true foundacions and pillors of cōmon weales. They embrace and kisse one another, and (as <hi>Hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates twyns</hi>) they ar sick togither, &amp; well togither, they laugh togither and weep togither, and suffer in cōmon euē like &amp; self affections: Ther is nothing necessary to the one, which is not profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the other, nor any thing meete for the one which is not made worthie
<pb facs="3"/> of both, yea they concurre in the same sociable vnion which we see obserued in the partes and members of an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier body, who, albeit they suffer distin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction in their seuerall office and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, yet they aspire and trauell to one common end, which is to entertaine se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie in the whole. Many auncient Magistrates therefore, foreseeing the necessitie of Monarchies to bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected vpon these two pillors, consulted to raise ordonances for the perpetuall continuance of the Church and cōmon weal in one indissoluble vnitie: of those some followed <hi>Moyses,</hi> who as he was inspired of God, and perswaded the people of <hi>Israell</hi> to be obedient to him: so that eternall Lorde sent them ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commaundementes to establish the actions of their mindes: and rates of
<pb facs="4"/> policie to rule the residue appertaining to the necessitie of life: wherein as by a diuine feare and reuerēce those peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple durst not attempt any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to those holy lawes, so the statuts pollitike, and substitutes of iustice, so supplied the residue, that their cōmon weales, so long as Religion was main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined and iustice obserued, and either one subsisting equally in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of affaires: seldome suffered other chaunge then from good to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and neuer frō ill to worsse. Much is required in the Magistrat to support these twoo pillors which holde vp the whole: which then he dooth best per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, when, both in the councell, and action of things, hee bringes the one to consult with the other, as vppon whose vnitie dependes the safetie of all, and
<pb facs="4"/> without whose conformitie and full a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, much lesse that there can be any suretie of policie, seeing of the contrary, things can not but diuolue to reuolt, euen as in a temple or other buil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, whose foundaciō being deuided, the whole worke can not but shake, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no stay to keepe him in integritie. For this cause (right honorable) haue I ben bold to put out this discourse of <hi>Christiā policy,</hi> qualified according to the rule of the infallible trueth, which is the Scripture, which onely showeth to man the true and right way for his assured gouernement in the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation he ought to follow, whether it be particular or publik, and wherin he cā no more erre, then the skilfull Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, following the line, rule, and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>passe of his arte. Many and great are
<pb facs="5"/> the commaundements in the Bible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended straitly to Gouernours, as well Ecclesiastike as ciuill, to holde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in their hande that holy booke, learning not onely that belonges to the office of their owne estates, but also what they ought to prescribe for the policie of others, for whom they are to render accompt in the iudgement of God: wherin as to trauailing Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, subiect to the seruice of sundrie great causes, is reserued slender opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to studie the Bible at large, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to find out the dutie of their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate charges or to limite statutes to the multitude: and much lesse that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular sorte (for want of instruction) hath meanes to vnderstand how farre their office stretcheth by the doctrine of that booke: euē so I iudged it apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning
<pb facs="5"/> to my dutie, aswell for the ease of the one, as aduertisement of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and common benefite of both, but specially for the dutifull affectiō I haue alwaies borne to your Honor, to offer to the same particularly these Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an memorials, representing the very course and purtraite of the present go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement vnder hir most Gracious Maiestie, by the carefull direction of a most graue and wise counsell, amongst whom it seemes God hath dispersed the very vertues and spirite of <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> leading this Realme in such reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to God, and obedience to hir Highnes, that al nations confesse that here the mightie holy one of <hi>Israell</hi> hath chosen his Sanctuarie, and here hath he raised hir right excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iestie to that estate of power and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
<pb facs="6"/> that onely she hath in hir handes the attonement of most part of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in this circuit of the earth which we call Christendome: Amongest some of whose Princes and chiefest Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, as I haue heard much attributed to the grauetie and prouidence of this worthy Senate for the quiet regiment of hir Maiesties Realmes in these cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiring seasons: so, God graunt that as they haue happely begonne, they may also long continew (vnder hir High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) carefull watchmen in the watch tower of this Church and cōmon weale of <hi>England,</hi> laboring stil to maintaine peace, first with God, which he will thē perpetually assure and ratifie, when he findes him selfe sought to and serued with one only true Religion: and then to bring so many infinit soules and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="6"/> (the naturall subiectes of these do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions) to beare to hir Maiestie but one vnfained hart and obedience: which cannot but happen, if there bee suffered no diuorce, nor controuersie in faith, and that in the church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, remaine but one constant consent and wil touching the regiment and disposing of all affaires.</p>
   <p>J humblie beseech your Honor, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this poore testimonie of my good will, not with any iudgement of the merit or worthines of the worke, but as a simple interpretor of the dutie I owe to your rare and reuerent vertues: in which, I am bolde to repose much for the protection of this my small labour, and therwithall (according to my long profession) I humbly dedicate my selfe and seruice to your Honour, on whom
<pb facs="7"/> J doubt not, but God will suffer still to attend that good Aungell which hee appointed to bee the guide of <hi>Tobias,</hi> and to accomplishe all his vertuouse and iust desires. At my chamber in the <hi>Blacke Friers,</hi> this xvj. of May. <hi>1574.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours in assured and faythfull seruice,</hi> Geffray Fenton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>