<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translator to the Chri∣stian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101653_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11530</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21779</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101653</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translator to the Chri∣stian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The practise of the banckrupts of these times : in whom are considered, 1. Their fraudulent and deceitfull actions. 2. The evills accompanying their courses. 3. Laws and punishments ordain'd to curbe them. 4. The charitable cure of so great an evill. A worke now very necessaary. Written in Latine by Mr Dainel Sauterius, and made to speake English for the generall good of all commerce</title>
                 <author>Sauter, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Garrett, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 109, that is 111, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Translator to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wish from my heart (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that this Booke usefull (as it seemeth) in other Countreyes, had been needlesse in ours. So might I have spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my labour in translating it, and you bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter have imployed your time than in reading it. But such is the frequency and obliquity of Banckrupt courses at this day with us, that it was thought necessary to fetch these An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidotes and Medicines for the same from our neighbors Countrey. And J knew not where better to finde them, than in this learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Author; who in this his discourse hath spoken of this subject briefly, and yet useful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, judiciously, religiously. Read it thorough, and seriously consider each passage. No in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous and well-minded peruser hereof can choose but be bettered by it in his judgment,
<pb facs="8"/>as, for the producing in his heart an hatred of this vice: so, for discerning the crafty wiles &amp; tricks of them, who will lay Harpyes claws on what they can catch, and part from nothing which possibly they can hold. Jt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwise be, but that some persons at sight hereof will fret in their hearts, bend their brows, and sowre their speeches. I wish them a better temper, and more calme affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, &amp; such a demeanor towards them, who minde their good, as may cleerely testify good ground of hope for their amendment. <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel Sauterius</hi> the religious and learned Author hereof, being a worthy and faithfull Watch-man of God, hath given warning of the evill in the world, which he saw to grow too rife and encrease exceeding much;<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.17.18.</note>
      <hi>Hee hath admonished the wicked of his wicked way, and done what God his Master enjoyned him:</hi> It remaineth also that men doe their parts,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.21. &amp;c.</note>
      <hi>And turne out of their evill wayes, that they may live.</hi> Jf there be any who notwithstanding will run headlong on in their owne courses and frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent practises, to them J say; Goe too now
<pb facs="8"/>yee false and deceitfull dealers: rejoyce in your advantages subtlily got, whilst they which loose by you, weep: Cloth your selves bravely, feed daintily, looke high, whilst your Creditors goe with dejected Countenances, bee barely clad or naked, and want necessary food: Abound you in all jollity und earthly pleasure, whilst others groane under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of sad miseries, into which you have cast them: But remember that for all these things God will bring you to Judgment. But I hope better things of you, and such as tend to the future reformation of your courses. I wish the intelligent and godly Reader to hope the same with me, and admonish all who have been subtle and fraudulent delinquents in the practises here spoken of, not to deceive us in our hopes, least they deceive themselves of their future comfort. More I shall not need to say, because the religious Author hath very well opened his minde concerning this Treatise, and I have briefly comprised it in the Epistle precedent.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>