<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ CERTAINE CONCLVSIONS partly holden and defended by good Docters senten∣ces contained in this booke, and partly to be de∣fended by the Translator, if the same be not sufficiently defended by the Doctours mentioned in this Booke, against all that vvyll vvrite against them.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101361_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00284</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1040</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101361</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ CERTAINE CONCLVSIONS partly holden and defended by good Docters senten∣ces contained in this booke, and partly to be de∣fended by the Translator, if the same be not sufficiently defended by the Doctours mentioned in this Booke, against all that vvyll vvrite against them.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fortresse of fathers : ernestlie defending the puritie of religion, and ceremonies, by the trew expositio [n] of certaine places of Scripture: against such as wold bring in an abuse of idol stouff, and of thinges indifferent, and do appoinct th'aucthority of princes an prelates larger then the trueth is. Translated out of Latine into English for there sakes that vnderstand no Latine by I.B</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Erve, Egidius (Gillis) van der (Gellius Ctematius)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Emden</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>76 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>¶ CERTAINE CONCLVSIONS</hi> partly holden and defended by good Docters senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces contained in this booke, and partly to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by the Translator, if the same be not sufficiently defended by the Doctours mentioned in this Booke, against all that vvyll vvrite against them.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Kynge Prince or other supreme Magistrate hath power and aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to exercise his sword and to punish with it all the Bushoppes Elders and Clerckes of his Realme or Countrey yf they be offendors &amp; Breakers of Gods, lawe either with imprisonment, or depriuation, or with Death: or any such lyke punishmēt, according to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the offence that is committed.</p>
   <p>If the Bishops or Elders either do not theyre dewties in preaching, or preache false Doctrine and commit faultes worthey depriuatiō, he may commaund the Clergie that is neither infected with false doctrine, nor Idolatrie neither defiled with any notable crime of euell lyfe, to examin the fautie Bushops and their Doctrine, and if they deserue hit, suspend them, depriue them, or to make them recante.</p>
   <p>The Lordshippe of Bushops now exercised o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer both the rest of the Clergie, and ouer the lay people, hath no grounde in the word of God.</p>
   <p>Christ is onely the head of his mistical bodie
<pb facs="5"/>which is the Chirch, as the Prince or cheif Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate is the head of the Politique bodie of his Realme and countrey.</p>
   <p>The supreme Magistrate is bound to obey the worde of God, preached by Christes Messen gers, and he is also subiect to the discipline of the Chirch.</p>
   <p>Neither the Prince nor anie Prelate hath any aucthoritie by the word of God, to make any ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall lawe or rite, to bind mens conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in paine of dedly sinne to kepe them.</p>
   <p>Princes haue aucthoretie so to reforme the Chirch, that they reforme it not after any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or traditions of their owne makinge or any other mans makynge: But onely accordinge to the written word of God, and then shall they bringe none of theire policies into the Church be they neuer so gorgeous and goodly to looke to.</p>
   <p>As the lewes were greatly to be commēded which offered theyr bare neckes to be cut of with the Souldiars swordes, rather then they wold contrarie to their lawe, and libertie suffer the Emperours Image to be brought into their Temple: So the Pall ors of Christes flocke are greatly to be cōmended that had leuer lese their goodes and lyues, then suffer any mens Polyti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Rites &amp; traditions to be brought into Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes Chirch, wherby eyther the whole Church and especially the Ministers shold be brought into any bondage or the word of God should be hyndred therby &amp; man shold be made as it were a God, or take vnto him the honor of God.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>