<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101668_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B13477</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10511.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101668</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A wonderfull and most lamentable declaration of the great hurt done, and mighty losse sustained by fire that hapned : and mighty stormes of winde, thunder, lightning, haile, and raine, with inundations of water, that fell in the towne of Erfford and Weinmar; and in countr of Wurtenburgh, as namely in the townes of Nagolt, Hernburg, Rotenburch, Tubingen, Issingen, Elwang, and Dunken-spiel, as also in many other places of Germany, to the great destruction of thousands of men, women, and children; houses, cattle, corne, money, houshold-stuffe, and many other things; i the month of May, but much more in the month of Iune last past, anno, 1613. With a briefe relation of a great fire, which vpon the fourteenth of Iune hapned in the citty of Constantinople, and burnt fiue thousand houses. ... Printed at Collen in High Ducth [sic], and translated into English</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Archer, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the great and fearefull day of the Lords terrible and last Iudgement to be giuen vpon this wicked world, is at hand, and ready to come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs (good Reader) now more then sufficiently is seene and manifestly percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; for that daily experience, together with the fore-shewing and Prophesyings of our Lord and Sauiour Iesus Christ himselfe, and his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets doe assure vs thereof which plainely tels vs, that signes and tokens shall be seene in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, and that men heere on earth should thereby and there-with be stricken into great feare, griefe, sorrow and anguish of heart, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the same; that the wicked and vngodly would become so obdurate and obstinate that they should vtterly reiect all warning, counsell, admonition, or instruction whatsoeuer, giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them for amendment of life, and humbling and bending of their stubborne hearts by prayer vnto the Lord, that pride, and hatred, malice, and contention, with other wickednesse and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations should so much therein abound,
<pb facs="3"/>that the Lord cannot chuse but speedily come to iudge and punish the great vn-righteousnesse of man, for proofe whereof it is needlesse to say much, when it is so manifes<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly &amp; euidently seene daily, hourly, and continually from time to time. For was there euer more or greater wickednesse knowne and practised in the world, then is now at this day committed by all sorts of men, who daily and nightly consume their time, and the great and good gifts of God, in superflous and gluttenous eating, drinking, lust, pleasures, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, thefts, and many other abhominable and wicked sins and offences committed against the maiesty of God, without all remorce of consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or any feare of his iudgments daily shewed vpon vs. So that we cannot, but must needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, that God in his righteous and iust iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is truly moued and incited to with-draw his mercifull and most bountifull hand from vs, and in respect of our great vnthankfulnesse towards him, and the extreame cruelties, and vnmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse by vs vsed and continually shewed vnto our Christian brethren, to strike vs with the arrowes of his fierce wrath and indignation, by his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of plague, pestilence, famine, warre, fire, stormes of wind, thunder, lightening, haile, raine, and inundations of water, with many other such like punishments, by vs well and meritoriously deserued at his hands. As for example. Did not God this yeare most bountifully shew forth his great goodnesse; grace &amp; mercy throughout the whole spacious Country of <hi>Germany,</hi> by sending
<pb facs="3"/>them so goodly and prosperous a spring, and so seasonable a Summer, that the fruits of the earth were seene to bee so forward, faire, and in so great aboundance, as that in many hundred yeares heretofore the like was neuer seene, nor knowne? But o most mercifull God, how soone by thy mighty power hast thou ouer-whelmed the same? how soone haue they lost all their great hope? how quickly haue they beene bereaued of those goodly fruits thy great blessings? and how soone (as it were in a moment) haue they beene cast downe from the mount of felicity into the deepe valley of sorrow, woe, and extreame heauinesse? by the great stormes of wind, thunder, lightning, haile and raine, with inundations of water, and extreame fires, which many places there in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> haue of late felt, and found, to their most great, vn-speakeable, and intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble losse and lamentable destruction, the particulars whereof here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ensue.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>