<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>W., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101830_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14828</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25124.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101830</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>W., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dialogue betvvixt a secular priest, and a lay gentleman : Concerning some points objected by the Iesuiticall faction against such secular priests, as haue shewed their dislike of M. Blackwell and the Iesuits proceedings</title>
                 <author>Mush, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 134, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst many Letters and Treatises that haue come vnto my hands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the matters in question be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Secular Priests and the Iesuits: one of most moment, pyth, and substance (in mine opinion) is this ensuing Dialogates discourse. Which by so much the more meriteth my poore commendation in gracing it with a generall Preface: by how much as it is in a sort an Abstract, Compendium, or a Breefe of all, and the most important matters that are in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie betwixt vs and the said Span. or Iesuiticall faction. For (omitting other perticulars) you haue here exquisitely hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, The great contentiō about superioritie arrogated to the Iesuits ouer the Secular Priests: you haue here discussed, The question about Schisme; and the vnlearned, but very malicious libels of Fa. <hi>Lyster</hi> the Iesuit, couertly confuted. You haue here deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, The case of obedience and disobedience; and, what ignorant obloquie the common sort of Catholicks haue the Secular Priests in, for they know not what themselues, but a forgery filed with Iesuiticall lying lips, which hath giuen it a glasse of a stainlesse die, in a sencelesse conceit of infallable truth, to rest in the bare words of a wretch vnworthy the naming, for the honour of Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood mightily preiudiced by him. You haue here set downe, The causes of the Iesuits double dilligence in defending the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priest; together with their many vnhonest, vncharitable, irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,
<pb facs="3"/>
vnpriestly practises for a supremacie. You haue here insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated vnto you, The Iesuiticall vnspeakable pride, ambition, enuie, mallice, extortion, crueltie, and aboue all, their more intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable backebiting tongues for inuectiues against whome they hate, than euer had <hi>Ouid, Horace,</hi> or any other malignant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractor, scold, or Cinicall slaunderer. In few, you haue here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planed, The grounds of all the Iesuiticall calumnies, defamations, and iniuries, wherewith their apparators, sumners, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers haue and doe still vex, torment, and crucifie Christ his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants with their tongues, in as mercilesse a pursuit as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people of the Iewes (at the Scribes and Pharisies instigation, suggestion, and egging forward) pursued our Lord and master Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ himselfe, on earth amongst them. These with many the like points of importance are here very learnedly treated of: whereby to giue all Catholickes (as well priests that are not of the deepest reach: as also and most especially the laitie, both men and women, marvellously seduced, blinded, and led into error by the Iesuiticall faction) to vnderstand, what may doe them good, if they list to accept of it in these daungerous times of our common calamities: how and wherein they are to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure or suspend their iudgement, vntill they heare the case deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: and who they are, <hi>scil.</hi> the secular priests or the Iesuits, that haue most offended the state, preiudiced both Pope and Prince, giuen greatest scandale, and incurred the highest displeasure, with desert of sharpest punishment to bee inflicted vpon them at the hands of God and man. And for to giue the deuout Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke reader a little tast for an antepast of this ensuing discourse, I desire nothing more than that which the noble Senatour desired of king <hi>Auener</hi> his soueraigne, to wit, that all passion, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and partiall doome set aside, choller, hastinesse, and the furie of that part and third portion of and in man, called <hi>pars iras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibilis,</hi> shut vp in prison, committed to close keeping, in silence for the time; and reason set on the throne of iustice, in the court of a good conscience, to iudge of all things as they are in their own proper kind, vprightly weighed in the ballance of equitie and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,
<pb facs="3"/>
without collusion in the matter, sophistication in the worth or falshood in the weights, vnequally proportioned: to consider with me these few points following, euen for Gods loue, for the reuerend regard all true Catholickes haue or ought to haue to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry annointed priest, and for their owne vertuous intents sake, as desirous not wittingly and willingly to be led away with error, nor to conceiue amisse of well meant endeuours.</p>
   <p>The first calumniation here handled, is Disobedience, laid to the secular priests charge, by the seditious Iesuits: wherein these points are to be considered: first, how that these two disiunctiue consorts, Obedience, and Disobedience, doe the one of them follow the other by as necessary a sequele as the shaddow dooth the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, when either the obiects they both respect, or els the subiests wherein they are inherent, stand in opposition by contrary quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, properties, or motions: <hi>verbi gratia:</hi> A man seruing two masters at once, the one as Emperour of the sea in the field of warre; the other as high Constable, Seneshall, or Lord Chaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of the Realme, &amp;c. in the land of peace: If these two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund <hi>simul &amp; semel,</hi> an act to be acted by their said ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, agreeing to their place, office, and calling; the obedience to the one must needs inferre a disobedience to the other, in that same action. But if withall these two great commaunders bee aduersaries: then is the case most cleare. And this was the cause why our Sauiour said that <hi>Nemo potest duobus dominis servire, &amp;c.</hi> And by consequent then it may be inferd by an argument made by way of comparison, That it is impossible to be obedient to the See Apostolick, but that by necessary sequele, the same obseruant must disobey Master <hi>Blackwell</hi> the Archpriest: And the reason is: for that our disobedience in the case proposed as in controuersie betwixt vs and him together, with his great masters the Iesuits, consists in this, <hi>scil.</hi> That we would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of no innouation, or new institution, or authoritie, which is not conformable to holy Apostolicall, Ecclesiasticall, Canonicall custome decree and order in elections, without his Holinesse speciall Bull and Breue, for allowing, ratifying, and confirming
<pb facs="4"/>
of the same. But Master <hi>Blackwels</hi> authoritie was in that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of opposition, in many points contrarie to the churches Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and Apostolicall order: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the obedience to the See Apostolicke in resistance of him as an Archp. at the first: must needs be an act of disobedience to him, in not acceptance of him as our lawfull superior. Againe, in another sence, our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the foresaid case in controuersie, consists in this, <hi>scil.</hi> That we would not admit of any such authoritie as might im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach vs of any disloyaltie by act, word, or thought, in things wherein our dutifull obeysance was requisite, or whereby wee might be iustly said to haue stained our religion with treason, or entangled our priestly function with princes affaires: but this authoritie of Master <hi>Blackwels,</hi> hath drawne him and the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits together, with all the confederates, conspirators, abettors, and aiders of him and them in it, within the compasse of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, by reason of the platforme which is for inuasion; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compasse of a premunire, by reason of his presumed autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, to make laws and exercise <hi>jura regalia siue in spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liabus siue in temporalibus: Ergo,</hi> our obedience to her Maiestie, in resistance of the Iesuiticall Arch-priest, with detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all such vnnaturall plots, drifts, and intendments, as were approued to lie close couched in his authoritie, being so much the greater, by how much as the said traiterous pretences were masked with a seeming religious zeale; must needs be an act of disobedience to the said Archpriest and his fellowes (subiects of Father <hi>Parsons,</hi> as <hi>Garnet</hi> and others) in the highest degree of contempt, that ambition frustrated of aspiring hopes, can imagine to haue possibly beene offered vnto them. Secondly, there occurreth then also to be well weighed, the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a subordinate and a supreame authoritie to commaund, and therewith also the like difference to obey. For although obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience be due in all inferiours to their superiours: yet, with this prouiso by custome, practise, course, and order of all lawes, <hi>scil.</hi> That if the inferiour subiect be wronged by any subordinat of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall, or magistrat, hee may alwayes appeale for iustice from
<pb facs="4"/>
that subordinate court and authoritie to a higher office and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer aboue the president incumbent: and so in order from one to another, vntill he come to the highest supreame or soueraigne in cheefe. And so we say that <hi>in spiritualibus</hi> obedience is due in euery parishioner to his Pastor, but yet in order, vnder his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop: of euery Diocesean to the Bishop of that Diocaeces, &amp;c. but yet in order, vnder the Pope or vniuersall Bishop. And againe, <hi>in temporalibus</hi> obedience is due in euery inferiour subiect to the meanest officer placed in authoritie vnder his soueraigne, but yet in order, first, to all such as are subordinate one vnder another to the ordinarie Iustices of the peace, but yet in order, to these vnder the high Commissioners, and to these in order: to the Lords of the Honourable priuie Councell: and to them all in order vnder the soueraigne or supreame Maiestie: and then by consequent the Iesuits and their Archpresbiteran or Spanish faction inueighing against the Secular Priests, for appealing to the See Apostolick for iustice <hi>in spiritualibus</hi> and to the regall throne of sacred Maiestie in defence Apologiticall of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie <hi>in temporalibus,</hi> doe peruert all lawes, customes, and orders, and arrogate to themselues a dignitie, preheminencie, and authoritie aboue both Pope and Prince: and are thereby guiltie of high treason, with many blasphemies breathed out by the ignorant multitude vpon this occasion against them both. Thirdly, there doth here occurre to be considered, the nature, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and condition of those acts which are to be enacted, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and performed vnder obedience to that legifer, promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gator, or other commaunder ouer his subiects. For that, such may the act be in it selfe, as no power on earth may lawfully commaund it: and if there doe, yet ought it not, neither may it (without incurring mortall sinne) be obeyed. For example, If eyther Pope or Prince doe commaund their subiects or sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to commit incest with their owne mother, or to murther their parents, or to commit any other act, which in it selfe is euill, and as we say, <hi>intrinsice malum:</hi> no dispensation, pardon, nor placard, can euer make that act to be iustifiable
<pb facs="5"/>
and good, although it may be forgiuen before God and man, <hi>quia miserecordia ejus super omnia opera ejus.</hi> And seeing God can forgiue more than man can offends then <hi>a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiori,</hi> mans offence to man, may and is more easily forgiuen. Conformablie then hereunto, for as much as the Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe may bee lawfully resisted and disobeyed in causes tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall: especially, when the matter concernes the vtter subuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of a whole Common-wealth: nay, of many mightie king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes (as this platforme laid by the Iesuits, doth aime at no lesse, in suggestion to his Holinesse for the Spaniards inuasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:) therefore doth it necessarily follow, that this act of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to our Soueraigne, as wee are English subjects, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of her royall person and our natiue land, doth take away all the least sinne or offence that can be imagined by our diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the same See Apostolicke for so doing and actuall resistance, made against his Holinesse, or any forraigne power that should come with hostile hand to pierce this Realme. Nay, seeing it was oracled from those diuine lips that were blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to thinke they could either erre, dissemble, or possibly lie, <hi>scil.</hi> that <hi>Reddenda sunt Caesari quae sunt Caesaris, &amp;c.</hi> And seeing that Maxime holds irrefragably sure, that <hi>non est faciendum malum vt inde eveniat bonum (posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ponendis inter bonum &amp; malum:)</hi> I say then that it were a sinne, and a most great and greeuous breach of the law of God, of Nature, and of Nations; and he or she to bee holden for traitors, that vnder any pretence should occasionate the conquest of their natiue land, or (standing as the State of England doth this day) should not defend it, <hi>dentibus &amp; ensibus &amp; vsque ad sanguinem,</hi> euen while one drop of bloud were left in his bodie. This Hipocriticall shew and vaine vaunt of religion, together with the Iesuits masked pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of restoring the Catholicke Romane faith, are as farre wide from the matter or any likelyhood of the Churches flourish by that bloudie meanes, as the conuersion of a soule is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, after it is once out of this mortall life. Thus then you see
<pb facs="5"/>
what a vile, malicious, and most sottish, cousening, and sence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse slaunder it is, that the Iesuits and their seditious brokers haue raised of the Secular Priests and other Catholicks, that will not rub on their loftie banke of ambition and vnnaturall as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring conspiracie: euery one, lad, and lasse, tag and rag; and as well the ignorant as those of more wit, but no lesse mallice, vpbraiding priests, with disobedience to their Superiour, when they neither know what obedience nor disobedience is, nor when, to whome, or wherein it is, or is not due. Yea, so sencelesse they are herein, That if eyther the Pope and the Church, or her Maiestie and the State, would take them at the worst: they might all bee iustly condemned for erronious and trayterous persons, by their owne censure applied in the premisses to these two contraries.</p>
   <p>The second Slander or calumniation here handled, is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famies, obloquies, and reprochfull words in passages giuen out by the Iesuiticall fastion against the secular priests. And for that I verily thinke neither <hi>Zoilus, Aristarch, Timon,</hi> or other Misanthropos, euer equal'd, or els was to be compared with a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit in the damnable art of detraction or enuie: therefore doe these points occurre herein to be duly considered of euery deuout Catholicke. First, what great contempt these wicked men haue brought Priesthood into, by this most vngodly meanes: which I thinke there is no auncient Catholicke in England this day, of any compassionat religious mind, whose heart dooth not bleed to behold and to thinke on the difference betwixt the reuerend regard had in times past, and at this present, as well by one priest of and towards another, as by the Catholicke Laitie in generall to all priests, without this newfangle Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risaicall most daungerous exception of persons, &amp;c. For what Catholick, before these Iesuits got footing in England, would not haue trembled at the heart to haue called an annointed Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Priest (howsoeuer he had earst liued) a Knaue, a Villaine, a Spie, a Southsayer, an Idolater, a Schismaticke, a Libertine, an Apostata, an Atheist, with other the most odious tearmes
<pb facs="6"/>
that the diuell or mallice is able to inuent? And yet than this, nothing is more common now euery where amongst this leaud brood of the Iesuiticall faction: our common aduersaries euen of their owne humanitie, and for ciuilities sake shewing a more reuerend esteeme and respect to be had of priests (at least for their learning, scholarisme, morall vertues, and other good abilities noted in most of those, had by that faction in disgrace) than any of these new pestiferous Puritanean Iesuiticall Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries will eyther acknowledge, or giue any signe to bee had of them. All the wonted benedictions of priests now are reiected, their prayers, their sacrifices, their hallowes, and their holies, contemned; and whatsoeuer else they doe, pertaining to priestly function and authoritie (though in neuer so bad persons, yet to be reuerenced, remaining in the Catholicke Church) despised, as of no valliditie, worth or efficacie, more than if the said Priests were but lay persons. Loe what a readie way these mischieuous men haue made for Antichrist, vnder pretence of their Pharisaicall zeale. Secondly, it is to be considered, That the end these vngodly polliticke set the ignorant multitude on gog for against Priesthood and the Secular Cleargie, is onely and wholly to withdraw all Catholicke hearts from them, to themselues and their societie; with more like diuellish than humane mallice in them. And to make it seeme more plausible and easilier seased on in weake idle braines: they possesse their inconstant, flexible, wandering thoughts with follies, scruples, and feares; as, That the Secular Priests are become prophane Publicanes and grosse sinners, vnlearned, ignorant, infirme and weake men, of no reach, iudgement, nor conscience in things; that they runne on without making any account or reckoning of sinne: that they haue no authoritie, but all is lost they had, by their bad demcanure: that they remaine Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes onely in show for the time, but are indeed very A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theists (for so the speech will neuer out of my mind which one vsed of Doctor <hi>Bagshaw</hi> in the Gate-house, after his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Wisbich, tending wholly to this infamous kind of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant
<pb facs="6"/>
backbiting) that they are daungerous men to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into any mans house, &amp;c. All these, with many the like most impious speeches and slaunders are here touched, as rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by that faction against innocent men, blessed Martyrs, and reuerend Priests, euen from the beginning (of enuie in a Iesuits heart, to see any doe well that followed not them) to this present houre. And now they heaue at all in generall, whereas before they maligned but some certaine priests in spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall: whereof my poore selfe haue tasted so great and heauie an ouer-weight, as euen enuie, mallice, and themselues might seeme with shame to keepe silent hereafter, and horror of their account appaule them for the wrong they haue done me. But yet I liue, and so I must a while, maugre the deuils mallice and all the Iesuits that hate me. Thirdly, it is furthermore to be well weighed, That their enuious proceedings herein, is most pernitious to all those Catholicks, euen whom they beare most in hand of all good meant on their partie vnto them. For who doth not see it, that the onely cause of this their infeoft emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation at the Seculars good hap, riseth vpon this, That God sweetly so disposing, as their innocencie beeing knowne to her Maiestie and Honourable Councell, together with the Iesuits trayterous hearts, they finding more fauour than the Iesuits do, and thereby lesse daunger incurred by those that doe receiue them: the Iesuits very pollitickely (but most impiously, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciously, and vnpriestly) imagining that in the end, this course taken, would occasionate all the Catholicks in England to side with the Secular Priests, and vtterly renounce the sayd Iesuits: for their most safetie, they haue no other shift nor meanes in the world to auoid this eminent daunger of perpetuall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile out of England (as their like practises caused their odious banishment out of Fraunce) than to beare the people in hand, That her Maiestie and the State meaneth no fauour nor good to be extended to the innocent more than to the guiltie; that the Secular Priests are but vsed as spies; that the State intendeth to get out of them what they can, and then to cut both them
<pb facs="7"/>
and those they conuerse with all off together. And for those and like reasons are the Secular Priests (say they) very daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous persons, and ought not of any Catholicke to bee trusted. Which most vile, vncharitable, and wicked speech of theirs, is so much the more sencelesse, by how much as it implicats a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction; as in this ensuing discourse will appeare at large. Meane while it is to be considered, Whether <hi>Daniell,</hi> or <hi>Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras,</hi> or <hi>Zorobabell,</hi> or <hi>Tobias,</hi> or <hi>Esther</hi> in the time of the Iewes captiuitie, or the sweet Paranimph or <hi>Ioseph</hi> of Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathia, or the mournefull <hi>Magdalen,</hi> or the choice vessell of election in the sorrowfull prime-birth of the Church her infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: or yet Saint <hi>Sebastian,</hi> Saint <hi>Martyn,</hi> S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> S. <hi>Ambrose,</hi> S. <hi>Clare,</hi> or any other, in time of the like heauie calamities in the Catholicke Church to these of ours, finding extraordinarie fauour with God, and grace with men more than others, yea perhaps farre before them, or at least their equals in vertue and true Catholicke religious zeale, could find, that were in the same predicament with them of disgrace; were they (I say) to bee condemned by other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Christians in these dayes, for that they found more friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship at the ciuile Magistrates hands, than others could? Was <hi>Daniel</hi> thought to be a rebell, or <hi>Esdras</hi> a spie, or <hi>Zoroba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi> an Atheist? Or good <hi>Tobias</hi> an Ideot, or Queene <hi>Esther</hi> a make-bate: for that the first was made Generall of those Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours forces, vnder whom (as captiue) he liued: the second in speciall esteeme, trust, and affiance with the same princes: the third sent home with great treasure, to build vp the ruinated Temple and Citie: the fourth often spared, being taken in the exercise of his countries rites, ceremonies, religious acts, and other workes of charitie, which most of his fellowes if they had been taken tripping in, had been sure to haue died for: and the fift and last of these, obtaining mercie, grace, and pardon, not onely for herselfe, but also for her whole countrey, people, and Nation, proscribed all to death irreuocable, by false suggestion of <hi>Haman</hi> the traitour? Againe, Was blessed S. <hi>Iohn</hi> euer
<pb facs="7"/>
the worse, for being not onely admitted into the iudgement hall by permission of the highest Priest: when all the rest of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours Apostles were forced to flie away (or else had beene sure by all morall coniecture to haue in the Iewish furie, tasted of their Lord and maister his cup of torments at least, if not of death:) but also being then free, and neuer once examined what he thought of his maister Iesus, he was able of his bare word to bring in his fellow S. <hi>Peter:</hi> who, if an vnhappie girle had not been, might haue stayed there still, without any sinne or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence committed by that action. And yet in and by a Iesuiticall censure, they had been certainely condemned as spies, if they had escaped scotfree as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> did, and S. <hi>Peter</hi> might, if no worse matter had happened vnto him than that his personall presence there. Was good old <hi>Ioseph</hi> thought to bee a Statist, or should our blessed <hi>Ladie,</hi> or <hi>Nicodemus</hi> (as timorous as most of our English schismatickes are) haue had a scruple or doubt of beeing betrayed in going to take downe and entombe the bodie of God, her onely Iesus, because the said Aramathian found more than ordinarie fauour at the high priests hands, in obtaining of him, to burie it where he thought good? Was the blessed <hi>Magdalen</hi> suspected to bee a worse woman, for that, that she was permitted of the souldiours to passe and repasse to and from the sepulchre vntouched of them? Was Saint <hi>Paule</hi> condemned of any one, for hauing leaue (being prisoner) to goe where he lift, for any to come to him that would, and for that <hi>Festus,</hi> that <hi>Felix,</hi> that king <hi>Agrippa,</hi> and others, vsed him kindly, often sent for him, and would not permit his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen the Iewes to haue their bloudie will satiated when and as they desired. In few, were any of these that found more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour than their fellowes in any time of persecoution, ouer heard of to be iudged, censured, and condemned as spies, as daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous persons, as reprobates, or fallen from their faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this day? No certainely. The Iesuits amongst many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations in the Church of God, haue brought this in first of any other for one, <hi>scillicet,</hi> That all men fortunes, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb facs="8"/>
fauours, and actions whatsoeuer, should bee euill thought of, which were eyther beneficiall to any, without a commoditie to their soeietie; or not squared, agreeing to their trecherous proceedings, or but onely done without their consent, ratibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, allowance, and liking. Well, as their pride, their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, and their mallice hath been vnspeakeable herein: so their teares, their bloud, and all their liues (if they were giuen and bestowed in recompence and way of satisfaction) will neuer bee able to rince out that staine of their good names, which they haue charactered in their torne consciencelesse heart, and credite, which they haue lost thereby in the hearts of all other vertuous, wise, and sound Catholickes, naturall Englishmen and women of all degrees.</p>
   <p>As for their other generall slaunders: That the matter in contention was once alreadie decided at Rome, and therefore would they make the world beleeue, That the Secular Priests were seditious, turbulent, and factious persons: and also, That they (the said Priests) are the onely Statesmen and meddlers, statizing more daungerously than they (the said Iesuits) doe Hispanize or Spanifie, &amp;c. the one and the other, are both most false, meere calumniations, forgeries, and slaunders, without any truth in the report or broachers of them abroad: and very sensibly, prudently, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly are they here confuted, and their shamefull dealing, trecheries, and impietie, couertly discouered thereby; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the foysting in of that poore simple man, Maister <hi>Blackwell,</hi> into an office and authoritie, hee little knew (God wot) what it meant, or what treasonable practises were intended to bee wrought by him. Finally, there doe here occurre to be well considered (as a point in my mind of as great a drift, moment, and consequence, as any wee yet touched) the panigeries of the Iesuits praises, the causes moouing them to send foorth their spirits to course both sea and land with bugle blasts of bloudie <hi>Bellonaes</hi> menaces, to all that dare presume to contradict a Iesuit: and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame
<pb facs="8"/>
follie, madnesse, lunacie, or what to tearme it (I know not) in sundrie of the Catholicke Laitie, yea, and of the more vnlearned and lesse experienced sort of Priests, that will beleeue euery word to be an Oracle that falleth from a Iesuits lips, (in so much as once one sayd: That if such a Priest, a follower and factor of the Iesuits faction, should bid him hang himselfe, he would doe it) that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be otherwise persuaded, but that all the whole Church and Common-wealth of Christendome depends vpon these impotent aspirers: that stand stiffely in it as a thing impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, how euer the Secular Priests should preuaile against such rare peerelesse Sance-peres: that thinke it no way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing to Catholicke Christian doctrine, how euer such pure illuminats (who haue, as they say of themselues, a more neare familiaritie with God, than any other priests) should euer faile in points of faith, good life, gouernement, and order in all things: that their liues, words, and acts haue beene touched to the quicke, and euer hetherto haue been found faultlesse, spotlesse, and (as a man might say) immaculate without crime, for to the same end dooth one Father <hi>Holtbies</hi> speech in a rayling letter tend, (as writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to a Catholicke ladie, of no lesse noblenesse for her ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, than for her bloud) against all the Apellants in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, but against a reuerend Priest (maister <hi>Mush</hi> by name, whose bookes <hi>Holthie</hi> is vnworthie to carrie) in speciall: that they are the most learned, the most prudent, the most vertuous, the most religious, the most what not perfection on earth is in a Iesuit; with the contraries in all others to be found. These straunge paradoxes, as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage a high marke, which the Iesuits aime at, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall a heauie ruine, so doe they demonstrate a sencelesse, witlesse, and idle braine in those that doe beleeue them, that cannot see into them, that will not be informed of their daungers by following their vnnaturall faction, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall
<pb facs="9"/>
prognosticate a sorer, absurder, and a more mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheeuous heresie (if not Antichrist himselfe) to bee brought in by them, than euer yet was heard of in the Christian world, to this houre. For how is it possible (vnlesse the dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous date of mans miseries be well nigh spent, and wee the miserable wretches, reserued to liue in these heauie dayes of the Churches last calamities) that euer any issuing out of <hi>Adams</hi> loines, should be so ignorant of Natures frailetie in man, as these Iesuit fautors seeme to be by this sencelesse at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing vnto them a state of innocencie in a sort aboue that wherein our Plasmist created our protaplast in terrestriall Paradise?</p>
   <p>Mans wit, though it haue suffered a great diminution by our protoparents fall, as all the rest of the parts and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers in humane nature haue, (yea, euen synderisis is not exempted, but seemeth in many to be extinguished, rather than to haue any being at all) yet these sparkes of Natures light are left in our soules, <hi>scil.</hi> First, to be of so high ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie, insatiable longing, and touring reach in search after diuine knowledge, as nothing can content the vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or intellectuall part of man, saue onely <hi>summum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ens entium,</hi> eternall felicitie, beatitude, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and no more: which euen Heathen Philosophers, <hi>Plato, Aristotle, Socrates,</hi> and others, haue acknowledged, sought for, and died insatiable, because they wanted faith to find it by. Secondly, the Diuell by naturall knowledge, perceiuing well in the law of kind, that couert barren could not make a band, thought it in vaine for him to tempt our protomother <hi>Eue,</hi> with eating of the forbidden tree, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse Father <hi>Adam</hi> could haue been drawne (as he was) to haue tasted of the same: and thereupon hoped the fiend (as it came to passe) to cut the entaile of his heauenly inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, caused our parents to make a conueighance by fine and recouerie to the deuill, a forfeiture of his tenure, a
<pb facs="9"/>
breach of the conditions with his maker, a defeature of the heires male of his bodie for euer, and put the heires gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to a desperate forme-downe. Thirdly, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this, That the originall writ of priuiledge was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked, and humane nature left to it selfe naked and vnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med amongst so many enemies and allurements to impietie, as that thereby it came to that impotent degree wherein now it is: yet a light sparke of Synderesis, breaking out in the pure naturals of proper kind, moued euen Philosophers, and such as were onely conuersant in naturall affaires, (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing by lamentable experience the still continuance and vncured scars of that combat; which were, and so they are, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, Error, Concupiscence, Sinne, Sorrow, Hunger, Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, Sickenesse, Death it selfe, and other afflictions found in themselues, and vnacquainted with what they had lost in their first auncestor) to deplore the state of man so much, that they were not afraid to affirme, That Nature onely in the preduction of man behaued her selfe as a step-mother, and not as a naturall parent.</p>
   <p>If Heathen Naturians could diue so deepe in finding euen by Natures instinct, the miseries, infortunities, fraile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, imperfections, and impurities of man: if <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Naturals, <hi>Plato</hi> in his Common-wealth, <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Orator, <hi>Aristotle</hi> in his Happie Man, <hi>Plinie</hi> in his Proaeme, <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his Epistles, <hi>Homer</hi> in his Odes, <hi>Empedocles, Democritus, Heraclitus,</hi> and other Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in their writings doe complaine of Natures vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in this point of imperfection left in man: if Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> against <hi>Iulian, Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> in his Stromateus, and diuerse other Doctours, Legifers, and Hystoriors doe note this acknowledgement of humane imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie to be in these Heathen Wisards, ignorant of the cheefe point which we Christians doe know and firmely beleeue to haue occasionated these our downefals, imperfections, and
<pb facs="10"/>
ignorance in all things: then what conceit should Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans haue of mans state, constancie, and sickerness, in any, or all his actions: compared by holy writ in one place to a reed shaken with euery wind: in another, to a daungerous conflict in set battell: (for so said <hi>Iob, militia est homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis vita super terram</hi>) and in another, to a withered flower, to day fresh, to morrow in the furnace; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes like a weathercocke, chaungeable, wandering, and vncertaine.</p>
   <p>True it is, and cannot be denied, That the Heathens complaint was vniust, and proceeded of loosenesse, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and mallice; especially the blockish and beastly Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures, to whom, Natures infirmitie was such a stumbling blocke, as they thereupon denied the prouidence diuine of God towards man, and all religion and reuerence of man to him againe. Yet the scope of my speech tending onely to this, To bewray the Catholickes extreame follie, in conceiting the Iesuits to be such men of such rarenesse, such excellencie, such worthinesse and perfestion, as (excepting our Sauiour Christ, as man, our blessed Ladie, perhaps S. <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> if the Iesuits will giue me leaue) their like neither was, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, neither euer will be found in <hi>rerum natura,</hi> from <hi>Adams</hi> fall to the worlds end. There cannot be a sounder argument taken, to confirme, That the Iesuits are but mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wretches, and as impotent, weake, fraile, imperfect, and sinfull men, as we poore Publicanes (so esteemed of by them) are. Then this deducted out of the principles of Natures owne lawes, customes, and traditions in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels: for Cat will to her kind: Bunten to his bay: Frie to his hole, and Man to his miserie. And all this, by reason that the wound which was inflicted in the state of innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, hath so festered in the whole posteritie of <hi>Adam,</hi> as no hope of cure, during the time of mans mortalitie. And the transgression of the first law-breaker, was so venomous
<pb facs="10"/>
a seed to bring foorth wickednesse in the race of man: that neuer any Legifer, spirituall or temporall, either by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in themselues (as a president to subiects,) or by any decree, ordinance, reward, or preferment for vertue, or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie and punishment for vice, or any other engine or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument, cold root it out. Read the booke of <hi>Kings,</hi> of <hi>Iob,</hi> of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> of Saint <hi>Paule</hi> to the Romanes, of <hi>Dauid</hi> in his fiftieth Psalme: of <hi>Philip Bergan</hi> in his Hystorie, of <hi>Iosephus</hi> in his Antiquities, of <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> in his inuentions, of <hi>Virgil</hi> in his Aeneides, of <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> in his workes, of <hi>Stow, Grafton, Fabian, Fox,</hi> and other Hystorians in our English Chronicles: and you shall find all this I speake to bee true. No <hi>Bohemus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Bohemians, no <hi>Tuball</hi> amongst the Spaniards, no <hi>Belus</hi> amongst the Assyrians, no <hi>Ceres</hi> or <hi>Rhada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manthus,</hi> no <hi>Draco, Solon,</hi> or other Legifer amongst the Athenians, no <hi>Mercurius</hi> amongst the Aegyptians, no <hi>Minos, Lycurgus, Charandos, Phorondus, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus, Pythagoras,</hi> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> amongst the Cretensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Lacedemonians, Tyrians, Grecians, Romanes, Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, Archadians; no <hi>Druides</hi> amongst the Gaules, no <hi>Martia, Mulmutius, Gildas, Alfrede, Edward,</hi> or any other vertuous king, polliticke prince, prudent regent, or exquisite Legifer amongst the Britons or Englishmen: at a word, no Law-maker of, to, or for any nation, could euer vtterly take it away. Neither any <hi>Abraham, Lot, Iob, Moyses, Samuel, Salomon,</hi> or <hi>Adam</hi> himselfe (that had tasted the difference of both estates, of innocencie and sinne, of originall iustice and originall offences, of synde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall prudence and sottish ignorance; and had preached of all these to the primitiue world) could by any exemplar, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together root it vp. Neither yet Christ Iesus, the wisedome of God his father, and coequall God with him, the most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Law-maker, President, and Examplar, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception,
<pb facs="11"/>
our Priest, Sacrifice, and Redeemer, that tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, offered, and payed so rigorous a raunsome for mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, deliuerie, and demerites, that the least part, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and portion of his tres-sacred, immaculate, and infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly valuable oblation; was both able, effectuall, and worthy not onely to haue cleansed all mallice, rancour, and venome of sinne, but the whole infection of all other infirmities and defects in any creature: would not for all that wholly take them from the world, but left them as a perpetuall penitenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all memoriall of a former euill desert, to tontinue in this state of pilgrimage: and as they were contracted by <hi>Adam</hi> in our first fall from innocencie in Paradice, so perfectly to be renewed by Christ in our last resurrection to endlesse hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse. The law deliuered to Angels, was transgressed in Heauen, before euer <hi>Adam</hi> came within a ken of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, (if we follow the common opinion, That the Angels were created in that imperiall pallace) the law giuen to man in the state of innocencie, was broken in Paradice ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restriall; the vnwritten law vnder the Patriarkes, the written law of <hi>Moyses,</hi> the Euangelicall and most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect law of Christ, all haue beene broken, and too often violated on earth. Of this, all ages, all times, all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, all persons of note and common sense haue complained: God and Angels from Heauen complayned: Prophets and prudent Princes, wise and polliticke Regents, carefull and vetuous Gouernours on earth complayne: the Patriarckes and auncient first Fathers, before the Law; Priests; Princes, and Prophets vnder the Law; Christ his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, Disciples, and all holy men in the Law of grace haue complained: the first man complayned: the last man will complaine: our Elders before (sayth <hi>Seneca</hi>) hereof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained: we our selues complaine: and those that shall liue after vs, will complaine of mans miseries, infirmities, fraile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, imperfections, and weaknesse in all things. And
<pb facs="11"/>
shall any Catholicke then bee so blinded with an erronious conceit of an extraordinarie perfection of pieties, of religion, of deuotion, of familiaritie with God, of freedome from sinne, of peculiar indowments with grace, for soule points, gouernment and instruction in all things, to rest in a Iesuit, aboue all other men on liue? Phy, Catholickes phy: let neuer so vncatholicke a thought take a momentarie repose vpon the buttresse of your breasts; or once sincke into the centre of your hearts, least you sinke downe into hell without redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in so blasphemous a thought as this were; and as too many of you haue beene infected, though not as yet I hope so peruerted as that you are remedilesse impossible to be cured. If the Iesuits will be Puritanes, and esteeme better of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues than all their neighbours doe besides; yet purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize not you with them: least they take incouragement by your ignorant applauses, to prosecute their impious courses, and so draw you on to attempt their owne and your destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; yea, and I pray God, not perdition also of bodie and soule, by running into some desperate heresie, with, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them.</p>
   <p>What should I say more? I am still too tedious: for such are the Meandrian passages in discourse of the Iesuiticall platformes, drifts, and deuices, as dayes, months, and years, would faile to set downe all the errors, calumnies, and prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes vsed by them and their correspondent consorts, on their owne behalfe, against the Secular priests, and all that ayme not at the period of their fatall course: From which I beseech God to blesse, preserue, and keepe all inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, sincere, harmlesse, well meaning hearts; and to recall, reuoke, and deliuer all those out of their snares, that are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie infected with their flatterie, falshood, and follie. And so crauing pardon, if I haue exceeded too farre the limits of an Epistle, or any way otherwise offended any person that
<pb facs="12"/>
is not Iesuited in affection or faction, I now in a generall congie to all gentle censurers of my well meant (how meane soeuer) endeuours, as heartily, as hastily being called away, doe take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours all (gentle Readers) in all good wishes of health, honor, and happinesse vnto you. <hi>W. W.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <p>Rectorem te posuerunt, noli extolli, esto in illis quasi vnus ex ipsis,
<bibl>Eccle. 32.</bibl>
         </p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <p>Non efficiamini inanis gloriae cupidi: inuicem prouocantes inuicem inuidentes.
<bibl>Gal. 5, 6.</bibl>
         </p>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>