<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The booke vnto the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101151_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06083</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1653</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101151</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The booke vnto the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Solon his follie, or A politiqve discovrse, tovching the reformation of common-weales conquered, declined or corrupted. By Richard Beacon gent. Stvdent of Grayes Inne, and sometimes her Maiesties Attorney of the province of Mounster in Irelande</title>
                 <author>Becon, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Barnes, Joseph</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 114, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="the_book_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The booke vnto the Reader.</head>
   <p>SITH <hi>Circe</hi> at the instance of <hi>Vlysses</hi> hath once againe graunted vnto dumbe creatures liberty of speech, I may not but complaine, for that she hath brought vs from our former rest &amp; silence, now to speake before that wise <hi>Vlysses,</hi> who havinge not tasted of the sweetenes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of this our solitary life, since which time <hi>Circe</hi> first chaunged vs <hi>Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> into the habite of mute and dumbe creatures, may fortune to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his wisedome, and to holde our former silence and rest as contemptible. And againe of the other side, we beeing long deprived of the vse and arte of subtill speaking, shall much discontent wise <hi>Vlysses,</hi> with our homely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses. But <hi>O Circe,</hi> hath the love of <hi>Vlysses,</hi> and the cuntry of <hi>Greece,</hi> drawn thee vnto this indignation against vs, as with <hi>Epaminondas,</hi> naked and vnarmed, I must oppose my selfe against the scornes and reproches of al ages, as against a <hi>Graecian</hi> army? And with the fonde lover in <hi>Petrarke</hi> must thou of force make me a sorrowfull minister thereof? And with the silly birdes fast tied and bounde, must I represent the face of thy loving thoughts? Then what comfort remaineth, If I may not say with them, though here we remaine fast tyed and bounde, subiect to all scornes and reproches, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved of our former liberty and delightes, yet this one Ioy resteth, that the Author of these our Calamities, is falne more deepely then our selves ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, in such sort as with vs he must tast the bitternesse of disdaine and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, with the which cōfort, I heere present my selfe vnto your most friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viewe, hoping that this my naked and innocent simplicity shall have your leave if not your likinge.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>