<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Learned, and my worthily respected friends, D. BONHAM, and Maister NICHOLAS CARTER Physitions.</title>
           <author>Bretnor, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101645_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11334</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21594</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101645</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Learned, and my worthily respected friends, D. BONHAM, and Maister NICHOLAS CARTER Physitions.</title>
                 <author>Bretnor, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Opiologia: or, A treatise concerning the nature, properties, true preparation and safe vse and administration of opium : For the comfort and ease of all such persons as are inwardly afflicted with any extreame griefe, or languishing paine, especially such as depriue the bod of all naturall rest, and can be cured by no other meanes or medicine whatsoeuer. Dedicated to the illustrious, high and mighty lords, the estates generall of the vnited prouinces in the Netherlands. By Angelus Sala Vincentinus Venitus. And done into English, and something inlarged by Tho. Bretnor M. M</title>
                 <author>Sala, Angelo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30, 81, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Learned, and my worthily respected friends, D. BONHAM, and Maister NICHOLAS CARTER Physitions.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EE not offended, worthie <hi>Doctor,</hi> if I presume to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel you with a Physition, which netther is nor wilbe dubbed <hi>Doct.</hi> for any mans pleasure, nor cares a whit for any clothing in Bysse, how worthy soe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er. For the which I blame him the lesse, sithence nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Aesculapius, Hippocrates, Galen, Auicen,</hi> nor any other of the old stampe euer assumed any such title, though better giuen them. But <hi>tempora mutantur,</hi> and therefore now adaies for distinction and decorum sake it is very conuenient
<pb facs="3"/>
and necessarie to giue such attributes, especially to men indowed with so excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a qualitie as the true knowledge of Physicke, and guift of healing is. But how vilely this worthie Science and profession is traduced and abused! Witnesse the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Mounte-bankes, Quack-saluers, Horse-leaches, Cunning-women, Imposters and Vpstarts, who hauing learned (my chance) the Calcining of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> the preparation of <hi>Antimony,</hi> or the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition of some home-spun medicine, and hauing scraped together some triuiall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments out of some old Manuscripts, or from some brazen-fac't <hi>Bragadotio,</hi> will presently forsooth set the Physition at open defiance, boasting and protesting that they haue saued the life of twentie, whom such and such a Physition had quite forsaken and giuen ouer for dead. Nay I haue heard a good fellow (I will not say a <hi>Pharmaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paean,</hi> and that no simple one neither) bouldly affirme that if hee should not now and then adde or diminish something from the Physitions Bill, the fat were in the
<pb facs="3"/>
fire, and twere as much as the Patients life were worth, aggrauating the matter in such manner that my very eares haue glowed to heare it, seeing that by this their scandalous detraction, they arrogate to themselues and impose vpon the simple people, bringing them into fooles para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise! But the Physitions are well enough serued, for if they would expulse one packe of these, snaffle another, and take a little paines with <hi>Fernelius,</hi> to prepare or see prepared their principall Medicines, and not to be so idle as to giue too much credit to the Druggist, nor let each giddie-headed fellow be partaker of their secrets, it were doubtlesse better for the Common wealth, more profitable vnto themselues, and more pleasing vnto God: but of this inough. There resteth nothing now (my worthy friends) but that you would vouchsafe to stand betwixt me and such malicious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractors; for if they dare baspheme the tall Cedars, what will they not doe vnto the lower shrubs. The subiect of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise is so well knowne vnto you, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
<pb facs="4"/>
some nice and scrupulous persons may make question of the veritie of the passages, or of the safetie and excellencie of the medicine, you are so well instructed in the composition and vertue thereof, that no wise man will oppose you, some may imagine that I might haue made better choice of some famous and remarkable Collegians for my patrons, but vnto you onely, and vnto that worthie Doctor <hi>Gwin</hi> am I obliged, whose multiplicity of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, iudgement and discretion, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with affabilitie, humanitie and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie is more then apparantly knowne to all your acquaintance; Let me therefore craue this boone at your hands, that you would accept this simple translation as a testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of my louing remēbrance towards you, and that you would defend it from the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trectations of scandalous tongues, and you shall euer make mee</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, THO. BRETNOR.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>