<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>DIFFERENCES BE∣TWENE THE PRIMITIVE FAITHE OF ENGLAND CONTINEVVED ALMOST THE∣se thousand yres, and the late pretensed faith of pro∣testants: gathered out of the History of the chur∣che of England compiled by Venerable Be∣de an English man, aboue DCCC.
yeares paste.</title>
           <author>Facuwez, Bourgeois.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101386_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07396</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1778</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101386</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>DIFFERENCES BE∣TWENE THE PRIMITIVE FAITHE OF ENGLAND CONTINEVVED ALMOST THE∣se thousand yres, and the late pretensed faith of pro∣testants: gathered out of the History of the chur∣che of England compiled by Venerable Be∣de an English man, aboue DCCC.
yeares paste.</title>
                 <author>Facuwez, Bourgeois.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The history of the Church of Englande. Compiled by Venerable Bede, Englishman. Translated out of Latin in to English by Thomas Stapleton student in diuinite</title>
                 <author>Bede, the Venerable, Saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Laet (Latius), Hans (Jan) de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 192, 4 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>DIFFERENCES BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TWENE THE PRIMITIVE FAITHE OF ENGLAND CONTINEVVED ALMOST THE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se thousand y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>res, and the late pretensed faith of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants: gathered out of the History of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of England compiled by Venerable Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de an English man, aboue DCCC.
yeares paste.</head>
   <p>BEcause if the saith first plāted amōg vs englishmen, was no
right Christen faith at all, then protestants (if their faithe
be right) are n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w the Apostles of England, let vs cōsidre
what Apostolicall markes we finde in our first preachers, wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing in
protestants.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> S. Augustin our Apostle, shewed <hi>Signum Apostolatus sui in
omni pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ientia in signis &amp; prodigijs:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Cor. 12.</note> the token of his Apostleship
in all patience, in signes and miracles, as S, Paule writeth of him selfe
to the Corinihians, whose Apostle also he was. And of such mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
wrought by our Apostle S. Augustin, and howe Eth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lbert the
first Christen king of englishm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n, was thereby induced to the faith, the
first booke, the <hi>xxxvj.</hi> and the <hi>xxxi.</hi> chapters, Item the second booke,
the second chapter do evidenly testifie. Miracles in confirmation of
their doctrine protestants haue yet wrought none.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the primitiue church of the Apostles, we read, <hi>Creden in̄ erat
cor vnum &amp; anima vna.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> The multitude of them that beleued, were
of one harte and of one minde. How much our Apostles tendred this
vnite, it may appeare in the second booke, the <hi>ii.</hi> Chapter, where they
labour to reduce the olde Brittons to the vnite of Christes church. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
is more notorious in protestants, then their infamous dissension.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Our Apostles and first preachers wer sent by an ordinary vocatiō
as Christ was sent of his Father,<note place="margin">10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 20.</note> and of him the Apostles. The histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
reporteth their vocation in the first book, the xxiij. Chap. Protestāts
haue first preched their doctrine without vocatiō or sending at al, such
<pb facs="10"/>
as the church of Christ requireth, as it is other where at large proued.</p>
   <p>If this enterprise be of men saied Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aliel of the Apostles preaching,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
it shall perish. But if it be of God it shall not perish.<note place="margin">Act. 5.</note> Our faith of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland
hath continued 900. yeres and vpward. The protestants faith is
already chaunged from Lutheran to sacramentary in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
of lesse then 20. yeres, and their primitiue faith is loste, Luther
being now accompted a very papist.</p>
   <p>S. Paule s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ieth. <hi>Fides est sperandarum substantia rerum.</hi> Faith <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
is the grounde or substaunce of thinges to be hoped for.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> And againe,
that the Iust mā liueth by his faith.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> Such faith putteth thinges by the
belefe and practise wher off we may be saued. Such a faith our Apostles
taught vs. Our Crede, our sacraments, our lawes and Canons ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical
receaued of them do witnesse. The faith off protestants is (as I
may so saie) <hi>ablatarum substantia rerum.</hi> A substaunce or masse off
things taken away and denied. It is a negatiue religion. It hath no af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiue
doctrine but that which catholikes had befor. Al that is their
own, is but the denial of oures. This other wher is proued, and may also
presently appere by the differences which folow in doctrin betwene them
and vs.</p>
   <div type="section">
      <head>Differences in doctrine.</head>
      <p>Our Apostles saied masse. In the first book, the xxv. Chap. it is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
Item of their successours in the fourth book the xiiij. and xxij.
chap. Nothing is more horrible in the sight of protestants then Masse.</p>
      <p>In the Masse is an externall sacrifice offred to God the Father the
blessed body and bloud off Christ him selfe. In the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>fe booke the xxij.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
chap. this doctrine is expressely reported. This semeth an extreme blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy
to protestants.</p>
      <p>This sacrifice is taught to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e propitiatory in the iiii. booke, the xxii.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
chap. Protestants abhorre vtterly such doctrine.</p>
      <p>Off confession off sinnes made to the priest the fourth booke doth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
witnesse in the xxv. chap. and xxvii. chap. This sacrament in the faith
off protestants off our countre is abolished.</p>
      <p>Satisfaction and penaunce for sinne enioyned, appereth in the fourth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
book the xxv. chap. also: which in like maner the court off protestants
<pb facs="11"/>
admitteth not.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Merit off good works in the history is eftesoones iustified. In the. 4.
book the 14. and 15. chap. This doctrine semeth to protestants preiudic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>all
they saie to Gods glory, but in dede to their licentious liberte.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Intercession off Saints protestants abhorre. The practise theroff ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth
in this history in the first booke the xx. chapter before we had
the faith, and in the iiii. booke the xiiii. chap. after the faith receaued.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> The clergy off our primitiue church after holy orders taken, do not
mary. In the first booke the xxvii. chap. Now after holy orders and
vowe both to the contrary, priestes do mary.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> In our primitiue church the vow of chastite both off men and wemen
was thought godly and practised. See the history the 3. book the 8. and
27. chap. the 4. b. the 23. chap. and in many other places. Such vowes now
are broken, are estemed damnable, are not so much as allowed in suche
as woulde embrace that perfection commended in the ghospell and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersally
practised in the primitiue church off the first v. C. yeares.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> Such monkes and virgins liued in cloister, in obediēce, in pouerty. It
appeareth through out all the three last bookes off the history. Namely
in the 3. booke the 8. chap. and the 4. booke the 6. chap. All such cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
and orders the religion off protestants hath ouer throwen as a sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
damnable and wicked.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Praier for the dead, dirige ouer night and Requiē Masse on the
mornīg was an accustomed matter in our primitiue church. Witnesseth
this history the iij. booke and ij. chap. I tē the iiij. boo. the xxj. chap. This
deuotiō the sober faith of protestāts estemeth as abhominatiō before god.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> Reseruation of the blessed Sacramēt thought no superstitiō in our
primitiue church, or prophanation of the sacrament. <hi>lib. 4. cap. 24.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> Howseling before death vsed as necessary for al true christiās. As the
practise specified in this history witnesseth <hi>lib. 4. ca. 3. &amp; 24.</hi> Protestāts
vnder pretence of a cōmuniō do wickedly bereue christē folcke thereof.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> Consecrating of Mōkes and Nunnes by the hāds of bishops a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised
solēnite in our primitiue church. It appeareth in the 4. booke the
19. and 23. chap. Protestāts by the liberty of their gospel laugh and scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
thereat.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="11"/>Commemoration of Saintes at Masse time. In the fourth booke the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/>
14. and 18. chapters. In the communion of protestants such commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
are excluded as superstitious and vnlaufull.</p>
      <p>Pilgrimage to holy places especially to Rome a much wount matter <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/>
of all estates of our countre in our primitiue church, the history wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth
in the <hi>iiij.</hi> booke the 3. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d <hi>xxiij.</hi> chapter. Item in the <hi>v.</hi> booke,
the <hi>vii.</hi> chap. Nothing soundeth more prophane or barbarous in the
religious eares of protestants then such deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tion.</p>
      <p>Of relikes of holy men, of the reuerence vsed tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rdes them and off <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/>
miracles wrought by them the history is full. Namely the first booke
the 29. chap. the 3. booke the 29. the <hi>iiij.</hi> booke, the 6. chap. Nothinge
is more vile in the sight of protestants, then suche reuerence of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</p>
      <p>Blessing with the signe of the Crosse, accompted no superstition but <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/>
practised for godly and good, in our primitiue church, witnesseth the
history in the <hi>iiij.</hi> booke the <hi>xxiiij.</hi> chapter: and in the <hi>v.</hi> booke the <hi>ij.</hi>
chapter. In the deuotion of protestants it is estemed for magicke.</p>
      <p>Solemnites of Christen buriall protestants despise and sett light by,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/>
terming it a vaine of gentilite or heathen superstition. The deuotion of
our primitiue church was to be buried in monasteries, churches and
chappels, as it appeareth in the history, in the second booke the <hi>iij.</hi> chap.
the third booke the <hi>viii.</hi> chap. and otherwhere.</p>
      <p>Benediction of the bishop, whereby the superiorite of the spirituall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/>
pastour ouer the laie, according to the reasoning of S. Paule, euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
appeareth, is to be read in this history of our primitiue Churche,<note place="margin">Hebr. 7.</note> in
the <hi>iiii.</hi> booke, the <hi>xi.</hi> chap. Protestants confounding all good order, do
scorne at this also.</p>
      <p>The seruice of the church was at the first planting of our faith in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/>
latin and lerned tounge, as it may appeare in the first booke, the <hi>xxix.</hi>
chapter and the iiii. booke the <hi>xviii.</hi> chap. This protestants haue alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
bothe against due or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er, and condemning wickedly other partes of
Christendom for the contrary.</p>
      <p>Aultars protestants haue plucked downe contrary to the order of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/>
         <pb facs="12"/>
our primitiue faith, as this history witnesseth in the first booke, the
<hi>xxix.</hi> chap. And in the second booke, the <hi>xiiij.</hi> chap.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> Aultar clothes and holy vestements the prophane saith of protestāts
admitteth not. Our primitiue church vsed them, witnesseth the Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
in the first booke the <hi>xxix.</hi> chap.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> Holy vessels in like maner for the due administration of Christes
holy Sacraments, protestans bothe diminishing the number of them
and prophaning the right vse of such as they kepe, knowe none. Our
first faith had and vsed thē. The history reporteth it in the first booke
the <hi>xxix.</hi> chap. and in the second booke the last chapter.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> Holy water protestants abhorre. Our first faith vsed it. In the
history <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> appeareth. In the first booke the <hi>xxix.</hi> chap.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> Nothinge is more reuiled of protestants, then the ecclesiasticall ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
of the clergy. How, after what maner, and wherefore the church
of Christ vseth it, the history disputeth and sheweth at large, in the fifte
booke the <hi>xxii.</hi> chapter, toward the ende.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> Our primitiue church was gouuerned by Synods of the clergy only,
in determining controuersies ecclesiasticall. The History declareth this
practise in the first booke, the <hi>ii.</hi> chap. the fourth booke the <hi>v.</hi> chap. the
<hi>xvii.</hi> chap. and <hi>xxviii.</hi> chap. Protestants haue called the determination
of ecclesiasticall matters from thence to the laie Courte only.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> The spirituall rulers of our primitiue church were bishops and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours
duly consecrated. It appereth in the History, the first booke the
27. chap. and the second booke the 3. chap. Protestants haue no such due
consecration, no true bishops at all.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/> Protestants haue brought the supreme gouuernement of the church
to the laie authorite. In the primitiue faith of our countre the laie was
subiect to the bishop in spirituall causes, Peruse the <hi>xiii.</hi> and <hi>xxii.</hi> chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of the third booke.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> Last of all, the finall determination of spirituall causes in our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue
Church rested in the See Apostolike of Rome. This practise ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth
in the second booke the <hi>iiii.</hi> the <hi>xvii.</hi> and the <hi>xx.</hi> chapters. Item
in the fifte booke the <hi>xx.</hi> chap. How farre that See is nowe detested by
<pb facs="12"/>
the sober religion of protestants, all men do see.</p>
      <p>To note how differently the Catholike faith of al Christendom was
first planted in our countre, and the parted faith of protestants hathe
corrupted the same, the first difference is clere herin that our first Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik
faith we receaued of the See of Rome. This heresy hath begon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/>
by first departing from that See. The Apostles of our faith came
from Rome, the messangers of these schismes beganne first by scattering
frō the See Apostolik of Rome. How we receiued our faith of Rome,
the later chapters of the first booke, and the first of the secōd do testifie.</p>
      <p>Againe our faith was first preached with Crosse and procession.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/>
Lib. 1. cap. 25. These heresies first raged by throwing downe the Crosse,
and altering the procession therewith.</p>
      <p>Our first Apostles were monkes. See the first booke, the <hi>xxiii.</hi> chap.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/>
and the third booke the <hi>iii.</hi> chap. The first preachers of protestants haue
ben Apostatas. Luther, Oecolampadius, Bucer, Peter Martyr, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
Barlow and other.</p>
      <p>The first impes off our faith, the first scholers off oure Apostles <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/>
were holy and vertuous mē. Reade the xxvj. chap. of the third booke.<note place="margin">In postilla magna in Dom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. Ad.</note>
The broode of protestants in the very first issue hath ben so enormous,
that Luther the holy Father thereof confesseth his scholers to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
him farre more wicked, then they were before vnder the Pope.</p>
      <p>The first preaechers of our faith liued Apostolically in voluntary <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/>
pouerty, as the history reporteth in the first booke the xxvj. chap. This
Apostolicall perfection, protestāts bearing thē selues for the Apostles of
England, neither practise them selues, neither can abide it in other.</p>
      <p>As touching the effect and consequences of both religions, our faith <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="41"/>
builded vp monasteries and chirches as the history reporteth in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ste
booke the 32. chap. in the third booke, the iij. and xxxiij. chap. Itē in
the fourth booke the iij. chap. Protestants haue throwen down many, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
none.</p>
      <p>By the first Christians off our faith, God was both serued day and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/>
night, as in the fourth booke the vij. chap. it is expressely mencioned.
Protestants haue abolished al seruice off God by night, and done to the
<pb facs="13"/>
deuill a most acceptable sacrifice.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="43"/> By the deuotion of the people first embracing our catholike faithe
much voluntary oblations were made to the church, as in the first boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
the xxvij. chap. it appeareth. By the rechelesse religion off protestants
due oblations are denied to the church.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="44"/> Princes endued the church with possessions and reuenues, moued
with deuotion and feare of God.<note place="margin">Li. 2. ca. 3. lib. 4. ca. 3. &amp; 16.</note> The loose lewdenes off protestants ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
stirred Princes to take from the church possessions so geuen.</p>
      <p>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="45"/> Last of all our first faith reduced the Scottishmen liuing then in
schisme to the vnite of the Catholike church.<note place="margin">Li. 2. ca. 4. li. 3. ca. 25.</note> This late alteration hath
remoued them from vnite to schisme.</p>
      <p>All these differences touching doctrine and ecclesiasticall gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
are proued to concurre with the belefe and practise of the first
vj. C. yeares, in the second part of the Fortresse of our first faith set for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the
presently with the History.</p>
      <p>ET Priuati &amp; Brabātici Regiae Maiestatis Consilij di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plomate
cautum est ne quis infra quadriennium proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum
Historiam ecclesiasticam gentis Anglorum, Authore
Venerabili Beda Presb. a Thoma Stapletono in Anglicum
sermonem versam, per omnes Burgundicae ditionis regiones
imprimat aut alibi impressam distrahat aliter quám eidem
Thomae videbitur, sub poena in Diplomate constituta.</p>
      <closer>
         <dateline>Datum Bruxellae. <date>20. &amp; 23. Iunij. 1565.</date>
         </dateline>
         <signed>Subsig. Bourgeois. Facuwez.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>