<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Praeface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101153_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06098</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1657</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101153</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Praeface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Antichrist the pope of Rome: or, the pope of Rome is Antichrist : Proued in two treatises. In the first treatise, 1. By a full and cleere definition of Antichrist ... In the second treatise, by a description 1. Of his person. 2. Of his kingdome. 3. Of his delusions. ... By Tho: Beard</title>
                 <author>Beard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, Isaac</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 425, 1 page, table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Praeface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ext vnto the knowledge of our Lord and Sauior Iesus Christ, there is nothing so necessarie, as the true and solide know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Antichrist, the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellest enemy to Christ and his members. For, as except wee know Christ, we cannot either put our affiance in him, or obey his word, and so obtaine saluation by his meanes; so, except we know Antichrist we can neuer beware of him, nor resist him, nor fight against him. Besides, as it is a notorious iniurie and outrage, to call any one by the name of Antichrist, or to flye from him, he being not so; so it is a palpable flattery vnworthy a Christian, to honour, reuerence, and adore as a God on earth, him whom we ought to detest and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre, as the most pernitious Organe of the diuell.</p>
   <p>Now, that Antichrist ought to come into the World, there is no controuersie among Christians: but vvho, and what kinde of man this Antichrist should bee, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="5"/> into great variety and diuersity of opinions. For the most Ancient Doctors which wrote before the time of his reuealing, exprest themselues with so many doubts, repugnances, and light coniectures (as it ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily falleth out in the vnfolding of Prophesies) that a man may easily perceiue thereby, that they meant not that their opinion should be receiued as certain and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted trueths. As also, the luster, authoritie, and brightnesse of the Church of Rome, especially at that time when the cheefe glory of their Bishops was this; to shedde their blouds for the confession of Christ, so dimmed and dazeled their eyes, that they could not perswade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, that such a Monster should one day establish his Tyranny, in so flourishing a part of Christes King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
   <p>As touching those that came after, and could more cleerely discerne the markes by the which he is painted out by the Spirit of God in holy Scripture: some of them haue confessed and divulged him to the world. Others carried with the current of the inueterate opinion of the authority of the Church of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ome, haue not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed the truth, but also banded themselues against it, with all their force. Albeit that God notwithstanding these clouds of darkenesse, and the furie of Antichrist, which ruined all that durst open their mouth against him, raised vp alwayes certaine holy men, who neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne liues, gaue glory to God, and discouered the impostures of this Sonne of Perdition: insomuch, that since diuerse centuries of yeares, it hath pleased the Lord to manifest more fully his abhominations, by the preaching of the Gospell.</p>
   <p>But as this excellent benefite amongst all those that
<pb facs="5"/> wa receiue from God in this decrepite Age of the world, ought to be prized and acknowledged in all respects; so there are verie few which regard it as they ought Some by their negligence, suffering the Empire of Antichrist to be repaired where it was abolished: Others, by their miserable dissentions, opening away for this Woolfe, to enter into the Sheepe-fold of Christ: And others, by ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together all their dexteritie and quickenesse of fraudes, sophismes, and lies, labouring to vpholde his seate from falling. For to this purpose serue the new wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of those that endeauour to make the world beleeue that Antichrist is not yet come, to the end, to lull men asleepe vnder his tyranny. And therefore as these men employ all their diligence to maintaine the life of this Beast, against whom all ought to arme themselues: So ought the true Seruants of God, stiffely to bend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues both with voyce and pen against him, for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their master Iesus Christ.</p>
   <p>It is true, that there a sort of men too politicke and timorous: who otherwise being sound of Religion, yet thinke, that truth may be sufficiently taught, and error confuted, without making any mention of Antichrist: a kinde of people which require of vs another manner of discretion in the execution of our charges, then was v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed by the Prophets and Apostles, and which consider not how great imbecility is in man, and how easie hee is to be transported into error, especially then when it cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth in vnder the maske and appearance of Holinesse &amp; Meekenesse: and therefore how needfull it is to be pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to the quicke, that hee may bee retained constant in the profession of the truth: and in a word, that regard not what dutie of obedience they owe to the Commande<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="6"/> of God, made to vs all, <hi>Apoc. 18, 6.</hi> For vvhat a tyrannous part would it bee, to hinder those that know and see the Wolfe, from making an outcry against him? What a lazinesse to spare him, that spareth and careth not for the ruine of so many soules, which hee holdeth Captiue? Nay, so farre it is, that faithfull Teachers ought to hold their peace, that they ought rather vvith full throat to cry out, and vnite their Veines with that which resounded from heauen; <hi>Come out of her my people, that ye bee not partakers of her sinnes: for her sinnes are ascended vp vnto heauen, and the Lord doth remember her iniquities.</hi> And albeit no man should answer to our cry, yet at least wee should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer our owne soules from death, and carry this witnes in our consciences, that we haue not held the trueth in vniust silence, to the danger of soules, which Christ hath bought with the price of his blood.</p>
   <p>This is that which causeth this Treatise to come forth into publique, that they which yet know not Antichr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st, may at length know and detest him: and they vvhich both know and detest him, may bee confirmed in their knowledge, and encreased in their detestation; and so hereby may make more account of the benefits of Christ, and be more rauished with his loue. For the more wee know and detest Antichrist, the more are we enamored with Christ, and long for his comming, and desire the full reuelation of his glory. So that such as do not w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th all their heart abhominate this Man of sinne, let them vaunt of themselues what they will, yet are they farre estranged from true piety, and that holy zeale, vvhich made <hi>Dauid</hi> to say, Psal. <hi>139.21.22. Lord, should not I hate them that hate thee? and shall I not bee
<pb facs="6"/> offended at them that rise vp against thee? Yes, I hate them with a perfect hatred, as if they were my enemies.</hi> Now if this plaine confession doeth further enrage Antichrist against vs, &amp; it come so to passe that we must seale it with our blood, we shall be thrice happy: for then, shall we be receiued into heauen, there to sing alowd this blessed song; <hi>Aleluiah, saluation, glory, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and power be to our Lord God:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Apoc. 19, 1, 2.</note>
      <hi>for his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are true and iust, because hee hath taken ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of the great Whore, which corrupted the earth with her Fornication, and reuenged the blood of his Seruants from her hand.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The method which shall be obserued in this Treatise for more facility, is this. The first part shall containe the definition of Antichrist, drawne out of holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: The second, shall bee an application of this defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Pope, by certaine proofes. And the third, shall refell the opinion of the Romish Doctours touching Antichrist.</p>
   <p>For the rest, I protest that my intention is not to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend mens persons: I onely desire to destroy errour, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the gift of Grace giuen me of God, and to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour the reuealing of the kingdome of Antichrist, in what person soeuer I meete withall. And in that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale my name, it is not in apprehension of any feared censure, which shall be alwaies most acceptable to me, if it proceede from the Spirit of Charity, which ought to guide the hearts and hands of Christians. But I haue alwayes bene of opinion in this subiect, that trueth hath more force, being all bare and naked, then shadowed with the names of men. And if after the labour of so
<pb facs="7"/> many learned men, that here illustrated this matter, and whose footsteps I haue purposely followed, there bee found some clearing by this Treatise, as I hope will bee to them that shall take the paines to reade it through, and especially the third Part; I desire, that the glorie thereof may bee rendred to GOD alone, who will right soone make knowne to the world by the comming of his Sonne, the vtter abolition of him, whom he hath already so cleerely discouered by the Torch of his Gospell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>