<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honorable and vertu∣ous Lady, Anne Countesse of Oxenford. Geffray Fenton desireth long and Honorable life.</title>
           <author>Fenton, Geffray</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101911_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00659</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10794</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101911</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honorable and vertu∣ous Lady, Anne Countesse of Oxenford. Geffray Fenton desireth long and Honorable life.</title>
                 <author>Fenton, Geffray</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Golden epistles : contayning varietie of discourse both morall, philosophicall, and diuine: gathered as well out of the remaynder of Gueuaraes workes, as other authors, Latine, French, and Italian. By Geffray Fenton</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 200 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Honorable and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lady, Anne Countesse of Oxenford. <hi>Geffray Fenton desireth long and Honorable life.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the first crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one perticularly hath found so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny calamities and trauels of life, that it hath bene a perpetuall industrie in all to search wherein rested this true and assured contentment, which we cal felicitie. Some referred it to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritie of riches, &amp; with others it was established altogether in vertue. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of as the one, being but the possessions of fortune and therefore both vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and miserable, brings with it his proper confusion: So, the other aspiring to immortalitie, hath no subiection to
<pb facs="3"/>
frailtie or infirmitie, and therefore iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifying it selfe by his owne nature, is worthely adiudged that felicitie which the world so much desireth. What man is possessed with a spirite of vertue, in the same man is truly expressed the si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude and action of be atitude, the one holding such communitie with the other, that as vertue is the forge wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this soueraigne good is wrought, so, felicitie is the effect and stipend of the same, and they both no other thing then the very heauen and residence of God, wherein the soule is fourmed and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. No man feeleth a perfect tast of felicitie, if with al he embrace not ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, no more then the sauor of meate is pleasant to the sicke whose sences suffer imperfection, infirmitie, or error: nor any standeth destitute of beatitude,
<pb facs="3"/>
whose mind communicates with desires and mociōs of vertue, as to those whose faith is vnfained and incorrupt, is as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured the estate of eternitie and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Patrimony. This vertue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides that it is originally administred by diuine influence and grace, hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so his naturall meanes subsisting to his perfection &amp; stabilitie, which the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient followers of Philosophie &amp; wise<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, haue referred to the studie and science of good thinges, as coollers best apt and conuenient to blase the true coat and figure of vertue. Sciences say they, prepare mens mindes to vertue, and all our thoughtes and mocions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made foule by our first corruption, are yet repurged by the qualety of Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and knowledge, as the drosse and scumme of mettall is mortified by the
<pb facs="4"/>
industrie of workers to whom the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession appertayneth: Infinit are the commodities of knowledge &amp; science, which shining in their perticularities as well in the workes of many wise mē, as in their life and examples, it agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not now to recompt thē: Only, there are few who in studie and knowledge find out notable rules to gouerne the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>die, and excellent doctrines to qualifie the mind, with autentike counsels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, to exercise the residue of the man in the necessary consideration of his mortalitie and frailenes. Science traue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to the fauour of posteritie, and is the assured protector of mens actes and monuments against forgetfulnes and enuie. It is the pillor of prosperitie, and infallible retrait and refuge in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie: It fashioneth the rudenes and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance
<pb facs="4"/>
of youth, and restraineth the crabbednes of age to modestie &amp; ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. Jt inuents councels to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishmēt of our affaires, &amp; ministreth to our mindes stabilitie and resolution of courage. Yea Science and knowledge are the very seminary or seedes out of which do bud all our florishing blossoms of vertue, and wherein our sprites are made hable to iudge of highe and hard thinges, and so raised to those ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly desires of well dooing, wherein all good men reapose their soueraigne contentment.</p>
   <p>These happie fruites of Science and learninge raise Noble personages in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to merit and dignitie, and sets a worke excellent wittes to record the reputatiō of their greatnes &amp; vertues, deuiding the doings of their life some into war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings
<pb facs="5"/>
to auoyde harmes and miseries, and some into precepts the better to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablish examples and drawe to imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And as aboue all others of our time, your honour hath bene alwayes right worthely noted a diligent follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of those Artes and studies which best serue to the declaracion and glory of true vertue and pietie: So at the contemplation of the same, I am bold to bring forth (vnder the protecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of your Ladiship (this treatise con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning morall discourse sorted with Philosophie, &amp; some texts of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Not that I hold it worthy your view and iudgement, but (according to good meanning,) to vse it as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of the deuocion and seruice wherein I am vowed to your Ladiship and your honorable house and parents.
<pb facs="5"/>
And where, in the intentions of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in these dayes this is a lamentable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, that they consider not those customes &amp; good doctrines agreeing with holy vertues and commaundements of the law of God, but thinke it is a great testimonie of their singularitie and excellencie to publish vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fourmes of speech, matter either merely vaine in it selfe, or at least vnfruitefull to the vse and instructiō of life. I thought good by the experience of their writings, not to be so curious to set out this worke with elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of phrase and Retoricke, as to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit precepts to liue well, ioyning to that smal eloquence of wordes I haue vsed, a diligence withall to dresse and institute conuersation and manners; the same being the direct line that leades to vertue, which (without this) is but the figure and image of that it ought to be. Wherein hauing respect to modestie, I
<pb facs="6"/>
am farre here from meaning to chalenge the labours of others, and much lesse seeke to obtrude vpon mine owne any dignitie or merite, but referre me and my trauels to the opinion of your Ladiship, whom I humbly be seech, as touching the order and partes of Art in the Booke, to iudge them with that propertie of fauour which is wont to conster nothing to blame: and for the textes and precepts whether morall, ciuill, or of diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, your Ladiship, in al the workes you shal read, can not find better doctrine, then in the life of your honorable Father, in whose maner and actions is fulfilled a more ful ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ample of vertue, then in all the rules and si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes which my pen can deliuer. And as stones of rare and precious price expresse their lustre better in gold then in any other mettall, so, good and well qualefied discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses are holden so much the more noble and
<pb facs="6"/>
deare, by how much are worthie and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lēt the persons to whom they are presented, the dignitie of the one supporting and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifying the nobilitie of the other. And as trees transplanted or remoued out of their naturall stocke into a better, become both more faire and goodly to behold, and yeeld a fruite more pleasing the tast: In like sort, a worke of learning drawne out of his proper Author and recommended to some noble &amp; vertuous personages, becomes so much the better receiued, and with a fruit more liked, by how much it is incorporate in the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and name of an excellent patron. In which respect, knowing that there shines in your Ladiship a vertue of learning and iudgement, as doth the pearle in the gold, &amp; that your mind is diuinely enclined to the cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>templation of vertuous studies, I beseech you let this be admitted amongest the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="7"/>
monumēts of your vertue, though farre vnworthy of your noble desire, yet, beeing couered with the winges of your authoritie and name, it may bee holden so much the more perfect and plawsible, by how much it is an imp grafted in the soyle of your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and enritched with the golde of your name and vertues, Referring the faultes rather to the infirmitie of my skil and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, then to my desire and will which is wholly dedicated to the seruice of your right honorable Father and his house.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>At my chamber in the Blacke Friers in London <date>the fourth of February. <hi>1575.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your honours humbly to dispose and commaund. <hi>Geffray Fenton.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>