<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101119_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06108</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1659</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101119</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The theatre of Gods iudgements: or, A collection of histories out of sacred, ecclesiasticall, and prophane authours : concerning the admirable iudgements of God vpon the transgressours of his commandements. Translated out of French, and augmented by more than three hundred examples, by Th. Beard</title>
                 <author>Beard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 79, 90-472, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F to auoid and eschew vice, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the saying of the Poet) be a chiefe vertue, and as it were, the first degree of wisdome; then it is a necessarie point to know what vice and vertue is, and to discerne the euill and good which either of them bring forth, to the end to beware least wee dash our selues vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares against vice in stead of vertue, and be caught with the deceitfull baites thereof. For this cause the great and famous Philosopher about to lay open the nature of morall vertues (according to that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and light which nature afforded him) conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not himselfe with a simple narration of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, essence, and obiect of them, but opposed to euery vertue on each side the contrarie and repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant vice; to the end that at the sight of them, being so out of square, so hurtfull and pernicious, vertue it selfe might be more amiable and in greater esteeme. And for this cause also God himselfe our soueraigne and perfect lawgiuer, that hee might fashion and fit vs to the mould of true and solide vertue, vseth ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner negatiue prohibitions than affirmatiue comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements in his law: to the end aboue all things to distract and turne vs from euill, whereunto we are of
<pb facs="5"/> our selues too too much inclined. And as by this meane sinne is discouered and made known vnto vs, so is the punishment also of sinne set before our eyes by those threatnings and curses which are there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced: to the end, that whome the promises of life and saluation could not allure and persuade to do well, them the feare of punishment (which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth sinne as a shadow doth the body) might bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and restraine from giuing them ouer to impietie. Now then if the very threatnings ought to serue for such good vse, shall not the execution and perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of them serue much more? to wit, when the tempest of Gods wrath is not only denounced, but also throwne downe effectually vpon the heads of the mightie ones of the world when they are disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and rebellious against God. And hereupon the Prophet saith, <hi>That when Gods iudgements are vpon earth, then the inhabitants learne iustice.</hi> And doubtlesse it is most true, that euery one ought to reape profit to himselfe by such examples, as well them which are presented daily to their view by experience, as them which haue beene done in times past, and are by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of history preserued from obliuion. And in this regard historie is accounted a very necessary and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable thing, for that in recalling to mind the truth of things past, which otherwise would be buried in si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, it setteth before vs such effects (as warnings &amp; admonitions touching good and euill) and laieth vertue and vice so naked before our eyes, with the punishments or rewards inflicted or bestowed vpon the followers of each of them, that it may rightly be called, an easie and profitable apprentiship or schoole
<pb facs="5"/> for euery man to learne to get wisedome at another mans cost. Hence it is, that Historie is tearmed of the ancient Philosophers, <hi>The record and register of Time, the light of Truth, and the mistresse and looking glasse of mans life.</hi> Insomuch as vnder the person of another man it teacheth and instructeth all those that apply their minds vnto it, to gouerne and carry themselues vertuously and honestly in this life. Wherefore they deserue great praise and commendation that haue taken paines to enroll and put in writing the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable actes and occurrents of their times to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate the same to their posteritie: for there the high and wonderfull workes of God do most clearely, and as it were to the view, present themselues; as his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and prouidence: whereby albeit he guideth and directeth especially his owne, to wit, those that in a speciall and singular maner worship and trust in him, (as by the sacred histories touching the state and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the auncient and primitiue Church it may appeare) yet he ceaseth not for all that to stretch the arme of his power ouer all, and to handle and rule the prophane and vnbeleeuing ones at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure: for he hath a soueraigne empire and predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ouer all the world. And vnto him belongeth the direction and principall conduct of humane mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in such sort, that nothing in the world commeth to passe by chance or aduenture, but onely &amp; alwaies by the prescription of his wil; according to the which he ordereth &amp; disposeth by a straight and direct mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as well the generall as the particular, and that after a strange and admirable order. And this a man may perceiue if he would but marke and consider the
<pb facs="6"/> whole body, but especially the end &amp; issue of things: wherein the great and marueilous vertues of God, as his bountie, iustice, and power, doe most clearely shine; when hee exalteth and fauoureth some, and debaseth and frowneth vpon others, blesseth and prospereth whome hee please, and on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, curseth and destroieth whome he please, and that deserue it. It is hee also which erecteth principalities, and which maintaineth commonwealths, kingdoms, and empires, vntill by the summe and weight of their iniquities, they sinke themselues into ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. And herein is hee glorified by the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his most iust and righteous iudgements, when the wicked after the long abuse of his lenitie, benignitie, and patience, doe receiue the wages and reward of their iniquities. In this (I say once againe) shineth out the wonderfull and incomprehensible wisedome of God, when by the due ordering of things so different and so many, hee commeth still to one and the same marke which hee once prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, to wit, the punishment of the world according to their demerits. And this same is most manifest and apparant euen in the histories of prophane writers, albeit in their purpose it was neuer intended nor thought vpon, nor yet regarded almost of any that read the same; men contenting themselues for the most part with the simple recitall of the storie, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to take pleasure and passe away time, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specting any further matter: Notwithstanding the true and principall vse of their writings ought to be, diligently to marke the effects of Gods prouidence and of his iustice: thereby to learne to containe our
<pb facs="6"/> selues within the bonds of modestie and the feare of God, seeing that they which haue carried them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues any thing vprightly in equitie, temperance, and other naturall vertues, haue beene in some sort spared: and the rest (bearing the punishment of their iniquities) haue fallen into ruine and destruction.</p>
   <p>This consideration ought to persuade euerie man to turne from euill and to follow that which is good; seeing that the Lord sheweth himselfe so incensed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all them which lead a wicked, damnable, and peruerse life. And this is the cause why I hauing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the great and horrible punishments wherewith the Lord in his most righteous iudgement hath scourged the world for sin, according to that which is contained as well in sacred as prophane histories: hauing gathered them togither and sorted them one after another in their seuerall roomes, according to the diuersitie of the offences, and order and course of time, which as neare as I could I endeauoured to follow: To the end, to lay downe as it were in one table and vnder one aspect, the great and fearefull iudgements of God vpon them that haue rebelled or repugned his holy will. And this I doe not with purpose to comprehend them all, (for that were not onely difficult but impossible:) but to lay open the most notable and markeable ones that came to my knowledge: to the end, that the most wicked, disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and disordered sinners, that with loose raines runne fiercely after their lust, if the manifest tokens of Gods seueritie presented before their eyes, doe not touch them, yet the cloud and multitude of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, through the sight of the ineuitable anger &amp;
<pb facs="7"/> vengeance of God vpon euill liuers, might terrifie and somewhat curbe them. Periurers, idolatours, blasphemers, and other such wicked and prophane wretches; with murderers, whoremongers, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, rauishers, and tyrants, shall here see by the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe that hath fallen vpon their likes, that which hangeth before their eies, and is ready to lay hold of them also. For albeit for a time they sleepe in their sinnes and blindnesse, delighting in their pleasures, and taking sport in cruelties and euill deeds, yet they draw after them the line, wherewith (being more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>snared than they are aware) they are taken and drawn to their finall destruction.</p>
   <p>And this may teach and aduertise both those that are not yet obstinate in their sinnes, to bring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to some amendment; and those that feare God already, to strengthen and incourage them in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure and continuance in their good course. For if God shew himselfe so seuere a reuenger of their sins that take pleasure in displeasing him: there is no doubt, but on the contrary, hee will shew himselfe bountifull, gracious and liberall in rewarding al them according to his promise which striue to please him, and conforme their liues vnto his will. Great and small, yong and old, men and women, and all other of what degree and condition soeuer, may here learn at other mens charges, how to gouerne themselues in duty towards God and betwixt themselues, by a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vnblameable life in mutuall peace and vnity: and by shunning and eschewing sinne, against the which, God (a most iust iudge) poureth forth his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, euen vpon the heads of them that are guiltie
<pb facs="7"/> thereof. Beside here is ample matter and argument to stoppe the monthes of all Epicures and Atheists of our age, and to leaue them confounded in their errours, seeing that such and so many occurrents and punishments are manifest proofes, that there is a God aboue that guideth the sterne of the world, and that taketh care of humane matters, and that is iust in punishing the vniust and malicious. Againe, whereas so much euill and so many sinnes haue raigned and swaied so long time, and doe yet raigne and sway vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, we may behold the huge corruption &amp; peruersitie of mankind, and the rotten fruits of that wormeaten roote <hi>originall sinne;</hi> when wee are not directed nor guided by the holy spirit of God, but left vnto our owne nature. And hereby true faithfull Christians may take occasion so much the more to acknowledge the great mercy and singular fauour of God towards them, in that they being receiued to mercie, are renewed to a better conuersation of life than others. In briefe, a man may heare learne, (if he be not altogither void of iudgement and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing) to haue sinne in hatred and detestation, considering the wages and reward thereof: and how the iustice of God pursueth it continually, euen to the extreamest execution, which is both sharpe and rigorous.</p>
   <p>Touching the word <hi>Iudgement,</hi> I haue imitated the language of holy Scripture, wherein as the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and commaundements of God are called Iudgements, because in them is contained nothing but that which is iust, right, and equall: so likewise the punishments inflicted by God vpon the despisers
<pb facs="8"/> of his commandements are called by the same name, as in <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.6. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.12. &amp; 22.8. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 5.8. &amp; 11.9. and elsewhere, because they also are as iust as the former, proceeding from none other fountaine saue the most righteous iudgement of God, whereof none can complaine but vniustly.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>