<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY DEARE AND LOVINGE countreywomen and sisters in Christ as∣sembled together to serue God, vnder the holie order of S. Briget in the towne of Rone in Fraunce.</title>
           <author>C., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101688_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00412</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10541</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101688</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY DEARE AND LOVINGE countreywomen and sisters in Christ as∣sembled together to serue God, vnder the holie order of S. Briget in the towne of Rone in Fraunce.</title>
                 <author>C., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The contempte of the vvorld, and the vanitie thereof, written by the reuerent F. Diego de Stella, of the order of S. Fr. deuided into three bookes, and of late translated out of Italian into Englishe, vvith conuenient tables in the end of the booke</title>
                 <author>Estella, Diego de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fr. Parsons’ Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 269, 3 leaves, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedicatory_epistle">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY DEARE AND LOVINGE countreywomen and sisters in Christ as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled together to serue God, vnder the holie order of S. Briget in the towne of Rone in Fraunce.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His discourse treating of the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and contempte of the vvorlde, after I had perused, and in myne ovvne opinion conceyued, a speciall liking thereof: I fell into some desire vvith my selfe, to haue it made common, to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of my freindes and vvelvvillers, such as I vvist vvell vvold like of the argument, and vvold be delighted to see it vvell &amp; cōningly handeled: And because I cold not haue the effect of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, nor they, the fruite of that good, I vvished them, except it vvere made cōmunicable by some mans trauayle and industrie, in reducing it out of the spannishe or Italian language, (vvherein it vvas first vvritten) into our vulgare &amp; mother tongue. I thought good, since I vvanted not good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvill, and therto had store of good leysure, beinge at that tyme secluded from all companye (rather then to leaue so good a vvorke vndoone, that might tend to the benefite of many) to aduenture vvhat I cold doe my selfe therein, and by myne
<pb facs="3"/>
ovvne experience to make triall, vvhat a meane diligēce vvas able to doe, euē in the most vnusuall exercises vvhereinto vvhen I vvas entred, being daylie dravven vvith desire to see so good a vvorke at an end, &amp; continually entised forvvard vvith the svveetenes of the vvorke &amp; soundnes of the matter, and the good handelinge thereof, I founde no greate difficultie in the attempt, but passed throughe the same, in a moch shorter time, then I supposed it possible for mee (at the first) to haue done.</p>
   <p>Thus loue maketh labor light, and harde thinges are made easie by delighte: yea euen the vearie thing it selfe, that this booke intreateth of, vvhich to vs vvordly men, is of all others the most hard, as that vvhich our corrupted nature most misliketh &amp; abhorreth, is made by loue, not onely easie, but most pleasant and delectable. VVee see daylie hovv the vvicked and vngodlie, leaue no mischeefe vndone, vvhat daunger so euer they incurre, in the doing thereof, to haue their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and satisfie their desire, vvhich is caused onely, by the peruerse loue and levvde affection, ouer firmelie fixed vpon the thinges that they fansie and desire. It seemeth that loue alone, is the directer &amp; guyde of all our actions, eyther good, or euill, so as the vvell, or euill orderinge thereof doth make vs eyther good or euill.</p>
   <p>Nothing then can be more conuenient for vs,
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hen to haue a good order and methode proposed, vvhat is meete to be beloued and folovved, and vvhat is meete to be detested &amp; eschevved. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ath bene the teachinge of almightie God hym <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>elfe, from the begynnynge of the vvorlde. It vvas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he first lesson that hee taughte our father Adam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Paradise, vvhen hee gaue hym &amp; order vvhat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e sholde take, and vvhat hee sholde refuse. Both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he lavve &amp; the prophets tended to no other end, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut to instruct the people vvhat they shold loue &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lovve, and vvhat they shold hate and auoyde.</p>
   <p>Our Sauiour Christ hym selfe comminge in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>she to redeeme mankinde, preached no other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>octrine to the vvorld but this. His holy Apostles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d teachers sithence, haue trauayled aboute no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>er thinge. The scope of all, that hath bene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ther vvell taughte or vvritten in the vvorlde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>till this day, hath bene to no other effect, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ly to instructe vs aright, vvhat vvee haue to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>vve, and vvhat to flie, and to prescribe vs or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>lie meanes, vvhich vvay vve shold doe it best.</p>
   <p>Amongest those that haue labored in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d busines, and haue bestovved their trauaills <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>framyng and cōpilinge some necessarie vvorke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>hich mighte aptlie teach the vvaye to lyue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ell, and to rectefie the mynde of man, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>fect and true loue of God, and contempt of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>orld, vvhich be as it vvere, tvvo inseperable cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ions, and haue their connection alvvayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb facs="4"/>
so as vvee can not loue God, but if vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> contemne the vvorld, nor contemne the vvorld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vvee ought, if vvee loue not God. Amongest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> (I say) that haue taken paynes in gods Church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> teach the readie vvay to a good lyfe, none hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> (in my small iudgemēt) more happelie atchieued that vvhich hee hath gone aboute, then the auth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> of this booke, vvho leadinge a most religious an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> contemplatiue lyfe hym selfe, hath by due obser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uation, and diligent labor, chosen out so man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> good rules &amp; preceptes for that purpose, &amp; hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> as aptlie applied them, and in so good order di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gested them, so bevvtefyinge them vvith apt sim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>litudes and sentences of holie scripture, to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> them asvvell h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dthfull as gratefull, that heard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vvere (I thinke) any vvhere to finde a vvorke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> better fruite, and more likelie to profit the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>der.</p>
   <p>And as it is novve made familier to oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> christian nations abrode, and vvell receyued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> thē, so can I not thinke, but that it shall be asvv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vvellcome to you, vvhen you are once made a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>quaynted therevvith, but if the habite that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> cometh clothed in, doth seeme ouer rude &amp; ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> for so good a guest, remember I pray you, fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> from vvhome it cometh and at vvhose handes▪ hath receyued this simple aray, next to vvho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> it goeth that is, to them that haue vvholie, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> acte, and vvill, vtterlie cast of, the desire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>vorldlie conuersation, so as to you the difference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> not greate, betvvixt a kendall coate, and a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e Roabe, the substance not the shevve, is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>vhich you desire.</p>
   <p>Lastlie the booke it selfe is such as asketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> outvvarde settinge out, nor glorious shevv of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>vordes, the vvhole argument thereof, entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ge of nothing els, but onely of the contēpt of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>vorld, and the vanitie thereof, so as it vvere nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>er agreeable vvith the matter, nor conuenient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the persons, to come either richelie arrayed, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y better then meanelie appareled. If the letter selfe be trulie expressed, and the authors minde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>thfullie delyuered, I haue that I sought for, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s it that vvhich I trauayled to doe, both for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> ovvne honestie, and the readers satisfaction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>vv vvell I haue fulfilled it, let the learned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>der be Iudge, vnto vvhose examination and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>sure I referre it. My trauayle herein I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore others dedicated vnto you, for that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ughte it a meete vvorke for you, and the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ment thereof so vvell agreeing vvith your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ion. VVherein if you fynde any furtherance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> meanes of any helpe that doth arise to you by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> small paynes taken herein, I praye you of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>aritie, that for my paynes, you vvill afforde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> parte of your prayers, and by your interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> intreate for mee at goods handes, that vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> I seeke to carrie a candle to gyue others light
<pb facs="5"/>
I vvalke not in darkenes my selfe, and lose <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> comforte of that, vvhich I procure to get for oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> folke, but that if I chaunce to trippe or stomble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> my vvay (as God knovveth I doe full ofte) yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> may the sooner by your good healpe recouer m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> selfe agayne, and escape the euerlastinge ruyne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> my soule, so as at the last after these hard storme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> be past, I may by gods mercie be receyued to som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> peece of his glory. Fare ye vvell, &amp; God send yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the assistance of his holie spirite to conduct you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the ende of your vvell begonne iourney. Amen▪ From the prison Aprilis <hi>7.</hi> Anno domini. <hi>1584</hi>▪ nost. capt. <hi>7.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your faythfull vvellvviller, and true frende in Christ Iesu. G. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>