<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right noble and most vertuous Ladyes (being the Nursing-Mothers, and Comforters of many poore-afflicted people) The Lady SYDNEY of Walsingham, and the Lady STRAVNGE, wife to the Honourable Knight, Sir HAMON STRAVNGE of Hunston; RICHARD SEABROOKE wisheth the encrease of Gods good blessings in this life, and all graces leading to life eternall.</title>
           <author>Seabrooke, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101949_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11834</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22133</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101949</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right noble and most vertuous Ladyes (being the Nursing-Mothers, and Comforters of many poore-afflicted people) The Lady SYDNEY of Walsingham, and the Lady STRAVNGE, wife to the Honourable Knight, Sir HAMON STRAVNGE of Hunston; RICHARD SEABROOKE wisheth the encrease of Gods good blessings in this life, and all graces leading to life eternall.</title>
                 <author>Seabrooke, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Seabrookes caveat: or His warning piece to all his louing country-men, to beware how they meddle with the eyes : In which is contayned the exact and most certaine remedies for all manner of infirmities, which shall happen vnto the eyes. Written for the generall good of this whole monarchie of great Brittaine. By Richard Seabrooke, practicioner in the art of the occulist</title>
                 <author>Seabrooke, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>62 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right noble and most vertuous Ladyes (being the Nursing-Mothers, and Comforters of many poore-afflicted people) The <hi>Lady</hi> SYDNEY <hi>of</hi> Walsingham, <hi>and the Lady</hi> STRAVNGE, <hi>wife to the Honourable Knight, Sir</hi> HAMON STRAVNGE <hi>of</hi> Hunston; RICHARD SEABROOKE <hi>wisheth the encrease of Gods good blessings in this life, and all graces leading to life eternall.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most noble and vertuous Ladies,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I called to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the most iust con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of that euill ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant in the Gospell, who buried his one Talent: It did quicken my conscience and stirre vp my minde on the contrary, ere death should preuent mee (according to that measure of knowledge in my professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherewith God hath endued mee) to communicate with my dearest Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="3"/>
my skill (such as it is) by publishing in this small Treatise the principall obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations of my whole practise. True it is, I haue now attained to the age of seauenty and two yeares, being from my youth by profession an <hi>Occulist.</hi> In which course of life, as (to my great reioycing in the Lord, through his blessings vpon mine endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours) I haue helped very many (who haue beene long darkned) to their perfect sight, so haue I seene by lamentable experience, not a few poore Christians, of both sexes, and all ages, by sinister meanes and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations made helplesse, and vtterly depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the most deare and delightfull light of their eyes. The originall of these mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes are sometimes to be imputed to the negligence of Mothers and Nurses: But for the most part, the Practicioners in this kinde are to be taxed, and of them also the negligent, the vnskilfull, and the wilfull, most of them more, studious to lighten the purses, rather then the paines of their grieued patients. All these sorts (after my plaine manner) I haue briefely touched in certaine caueats: then I shew the causes of Blindnesse, the seuerall hurtfull humours incident to the eyes, their qualities, and how to iudge which be curable and which incurable: and lastly, I haue annexed the most approoued medicines and remedies which I haue found by long experience to be most profitable.</p>
   <p>I fore-see (most vertuous Madames) that
<pb facs="3"/>
these aduertisements comming from my selfe a plaine olde man; shall not escape the detractions and scoffes of proud and malicious censurers; but hauing for the warrant of my doings the testimonie of a good conscience (that I haue sincerely, charitably, and vpon knowne grounds pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded herein) I cast behinde mee all the vniust aspertions they possibly can throw vpon my name, I am a poore man my selfe, and my poore mite I freely cast into the poore mans treasury, wishing all them that are so humbly minded, not to despise what they not vnderstand: But first to make tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, then to trust, and so to take in good part that which is tendred vnto their good. And very sure I am that I cannot want good attestation of my cures performed by these meanes; and thankfull acknowledgement also from such as (vnder God) haue found helpe by mine applications.</p>
   <p>Now the reasons enducing me (most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Ladies) to present this my simple labour to your excellent selues, are the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous reports of your noble vertues, whose charity, and piety, like two goodly col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbs, support and hold vp a world of poore distressed people, which otherwise would perish and fall to dust in the ruines of their afflictions and affirmities, as also that I know the excellencie of your clement na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, will vouchsafe to accept a small pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, being offered of great good will and affection: In which since I can finde no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strust,
<pb facs="4"/>
because your goodnesse is my war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. I humbly craue pardon for my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and vowe euer till this little sand of my life be consumed, to remaine, The euer obliged seruant and true admirer of your vertues;</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>RICH. SEABROOKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>