<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The argument of this present boke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1561</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101311_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14366</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24684</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101311</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The argument of this present boke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A moste necessary treatise of free wil : not onlye against the Bapistes, but also against the Anabaptistes, which in these our daies, go about to renue the detestable heresies of Pelagius, and of the Luciferians, whiche say and affirm, that we be able by our own natural strength to fulfil the law and commaundementes of God. Made dialoge wyse by Iohn Veron, in a manner word by woorde, as he did set it forth in his lectures at Paules</title>
                 <author>Véron, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Tisdale (Tysdale), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1561</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>176 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>¶The argument of this present boke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this disputatyon or dyscourse of free wyll, we doe fyrste speake of it, as it was in man at hys fyrst creation, and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore his fall, where it is shewed, that the place that is aleadged out of the .xv. chapiter of Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, for the defence of free will, ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte to be vnderstanded of manne being in the estate of innocencye. For, then as S. Augustine dothe declare, hadde he free wyll, but by transgressing the lawe of God, he dyd lose it. Whereby he did bothe bryng hym self, and all hys poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity into a miserable bondage, and thraldome. In the whiche we doe still remaine vntyll the sonne of God, by his holye spiritte hathe made vs free. For tyll then we are so pressed downe with the seruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of sinne, and with the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon
<pb facs="8"/> of oure owne fleshe, that we cannot as much as thincke a good thoughte, ye we runne headlonge into all kindes of sinnes, beynge mooste prompte and readye to doe what so euer the fleshe and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil do moue, and tempte vs vnto. But after that we be once by the drawinge of the father, come vnto oure sauioure Iesu Christe, and haue fellowshyp wyth hym, then do we by and throughe him, reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that, which we lost in Adam, but yet not so, that we be alwayes able to do the good, that we wold. As saint Paule him selfe dothe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme, sayinge:<note place="margin">Rom. vii.</note> I do not the good thing, which I wold, but the euel that I woulde not, that do I. To be shorte, after longe disputation, and many obiections made by the aduersaries, and substantially an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered by Gods word, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of the auncient fathers, it is in fine concluded that all the good that we do, commeth nether of our
<pb facs="9"/> fre wyl nor of our owne strength, but of the mercy and grace of god, who worcketh the same in vs by his holy spirite, and that all the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill that is in vs cometh of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil and of our selues. Laste of all, mention is made of the lawe, and of the fulfilling of the same. Wher it is plainlye proued, that no man is able to fulfil the law with such a perfection as God dothe requyre of vs, and yet that no vnrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse can be laid to god, although, he commaundeth thinges, that be impossible for vs to do. By y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> way the righte vse of the lawe, and the vtility and profit of it, is diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly setforthe, and by what meanes we are delyuered from the curse of the same. And so an end.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>