<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Aduertisement.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1564</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101757_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09907</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2017</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101757</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Aduertisement.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse wrytten by M. Theodore de Beza, conteyning in briefe the historie of the life and death of Maister Iohn Caluin : with the testament and laste will of the saide Caluin, and the catalogue of his bookes that he hath made. Turned out of Frenche into Englishe, by I.S. In the yeare of our Lorde. M.D.LXIIII. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed in the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Bèze, Théodore de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Harrison, Luke (Lucas)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1564</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="notice">
   <pb facs="36"/>
   <head>¶ Aduertisement.</head>
   <p>FOR bycause that there is none of the Faythfull, who woulde not gladlye vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the truthe of the number of Bookes that haue bene written by the late M. Iohn Caluin, to the end that hereafter men be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, as is wel knowen that the like hath hapned to the writinges of great and excellent personages that men haue falsely set foorth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vnder their name: It hath seemed therefore good to ioyne to thys a Catalogue, as well of hys bookes and writings in Latine &amp; French already Imprinted, as of those that yet are not, at the least of as many as may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to minde.</p>
   <p>Those which are not yet in French are marked wyth thys marke.*.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>