<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle of the Female Frailty, to the Mal-Gender, in Generall.</title>
           <author>Hit-him-home, Mary Tattle-well &amp; Joane</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101732_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13395</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23706</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101732</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle of the Female Frailty, to the Mal-Gender, in Generall.</title>
                 <author>Hit-him-home, Mary Tattle-well &amp; Joane</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The womens sharpe revenge: or an answer to Sir Seldome Sober that writ those railing pamphelets called the Iuniper and Crabtree lectures, &amp;c : Being a sound reply and a full confutation of those bookes: with an apology in this case for the defence of us women. Performed b Mary Tattle-well, and Ioane Hit-him-home, spinsters</title>
                 <author>Tattle-well, Mary</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Becket, James.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20+ 214+ pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_male_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Epistle of the Female Frailty, to the Mal-Gender, in Generall.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou beest of the Masculine Sexe, we meane thee, and thee onely: and therefore greete thee with these attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes
<pb facs="3"/>
following: <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable, Loving, Kinde,</hi> and <hi>Courteous: Affable</hi> we call thee, because so apt (I will not say to prate but) to prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle with us: <hi>Loving,</hi> in regard that the least grace being from us granted, you not onely vow to love us, but are loath to leave us: <hi>Kinde,</hi> that you will not meete with us, without Congies, not part from us
<pb facs="3"/>
without Kisses: and <hi>Courteous,</hi> because so willing to bring your selves upon your Knees before us: more prone to bow unto <hi>Beauty,</hi> than to <hi>Baal</hi>; and to Idolatrize to us, rather than unto any other Idoll: and therefore our hope is, that what you use to protest in private, you will not now blush to professe in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke: Otherwise in
<pb facs="4"/>
clearing our Cause, and vindicating our owne vertues wee shall not doubt to divulge you, for the onely dissemblers.</p>
   <p>And in this case we appeale unto your owne Consciences, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the most crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and censorious, the most sowre and supercilious, which of you all hath not solicited our Sexe? petitioned to our
<pb facs="4"/>
persons? praised our perfections? &amp;c. w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> of you hath not met us comming, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us flying, guarded us going, staid for us standing, waited on us walking and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busht us lying? use VVomen to Court men? or have wee at any time complained of their Coynesse? Have we bribed them with our Bounties? Troubled them with
<pb facs="5"/>
our Tokens, Poetiz'd in their praises, prayd and protested, su'd and solicited, voted, and vowed to them? or rather they to us: would you <hi>apprehend</hi> a new <hi>Antipodes,</hi> to make al things to be carried by a contrary course, and run retrograde.</p>
   <p>Then let the Rad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish Roote plucke the Gardner up by the Heeles, and the shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Mutton put
<pb facs="5"/>
the Cooke upon the Spit: for you as well may prove the one, as produce the other.</p>
   <p>Yet suffer you us to be reviled, and railed at, taunted &amp; terrified, undervalu'd, and even vilified, when among you all wee cannot find one Champion to oppose so obstinate a Challenger, but that wee are compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to call a Ghost from her Grave, to
<pb facs="6"/>
stand up in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of so proud a defiance. Since then you will not be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batants for us in so iust a cause, wee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to become competent Iudges, to censure indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betwixt the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser, and the Accused; to punish his petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy, and not to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour us, if wee bee found the sole faulty.</p>
   <p>So, if you shall give
<pb facs="6"/>
our defamer his due, and that we gaine the Honour of the Day: If you be young men, we wish you modest Maides in marriage; if Batchellours, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Mistresses; If Husbands, handsome wives, and good hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifes: If widdowers, wife, and wealthy widowes: if young, those that may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light you; if old, such as may comfort you:
<pb facs="7"/>
and so we women be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath unto you all our best wishes.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From our Mannor of</hi> Make-peace:
<date>
            <hi>Dated the third day of Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-month, in the year of</hi> Iubile, <hi>not of</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Mary Tattle-well. Joane Hit▪ him-home.</hi> Spinsters.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>