<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right worshipfull Sr Willi∣am Crauon, Knight, and one of the Alder∣men of the Honourable City of London, Eternall Happinesse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101575_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06004</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1638</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101575</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right worshipfull Sr Willi∣am Crauon, Knight, and one of the Alder∣men of the Honourable City of London, Eternall Happinesse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A counterbane against earthly carefulnes : In a sermon preached at Cranebrooke in Kent. 1617. By Mr. Paul Baine</title>
                 <author>Baynes, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 25, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right worshipfull S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Crauon,</hi> Knight, and one of the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>of the Honourable City of London,</hi> Eternall Happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worshipfull and worthy Sir, hauing receiued an assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red testimony of your fauour and loue, and not beeing able to render, nor your Worsh. ad-mitting the most vsual gratifications; I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, because I would auoid Ingratitude (a vice most odious vnto God and man) to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest vnto you my thankefull mind in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, altogether out of my element; but that it hath pleased God to dispose of it so fitly, that in the very <hi>Interim</hi> of your fauor this Sermon was broght vnto my hands, without a Patron, to bee published in the world. And seeing I
<pb facs="3"/> conceiued it not conuenient so to send it forth incident to so much enmity in regard of its op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to the worlds affections, I presumed to make bold with your worship, who had bin my patron to entreat your fauor also towards this orphane, that vnder your protection it may passe more safely &amp; freely into the hands and hearts of worldly men. And indeed it will be very necessary for them to carry this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote alwaies about them neare their harts: for so shall they escape that death which by earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carefulnes is ready to seize vpon them. For the more the world is drowned in worldly lusts and cares, (as hardly was it euer so deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as now) the more requisite is it that there should be all meanes vsed to pull men vp out of this whirle-pit wherein they are diuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their euerlasting perdition: now what means can be more effectuall heereunto, than the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication and fit application of that which our blessed Sauiour himselfe hath prescribed to this purpose? euen to turne our mindes from seeking earthly things which perish with the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing (&amp; for the getting and vsing whereof God will require a strait account at our hands) vnto those things which are spiritual and will endure
<pb facs="3"/> with vs to our comfort for euer. And heerein did the reuerend and learned authour of this Sermon expresse himselfe to be a wise steward, <hi>viz.</hi> by giuing a fit portion to worldly men in fit season. For if it could once be fixed in mens mindes to loue Gods kingdome and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes, so as to seeke it first of all, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that all necessary earthly things should be added vnto them; then the deadly cares of the world would vanish away &amp; trouble them no more, at least nothing so dangerously. But this is rather to bee wisht than hop't for, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the world hath so deceiu'd men, that now nothing on earth is esteemed good but that which is gaineful: nay goodnesse it selfe findes little regard but for the gaining of earthly com-modity; so that most men set themselues to catch at the shadow of good, in the meane time losing the substance of it. Yet this essaie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer men into their right mindes againe, and to reduce them into the true way of happiness as it was most commendable in the holy prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher hereof: So I hope the publishing of it shall not bee vnacceptable vnto any. Howsoeuer, I humbly desire your worships fauourable as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect vnto it: &amp; if it shall please you (when you
<pb facs="4"/> are free from greater affairs) to cast an eie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, I doubt not but you shall find somthing worthy your view and consideration. But my slender commendations will but dim the splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of this burning light: and therefore firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hoping and humbly desiring your worships pardon for my ouermuch presumption, I com-mend you to the almighty pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ection of God the wise gouernor of euery thing in heauen &amp; earth; who makes all things worke-together for the best vnto those that loue him.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships most humbly at command, <hi>N.N.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>