<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A SVPPLIMENT OF ADDITIONS TO THE APPPENDIX.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101974_Ba2_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13322</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23630</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101974</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A SVPPLIMENT OF ADDITIONS TO THE APPPENDIX.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhetstone of reproofe : A reprouing censure of the misintituled safe way: declaring it by discouerie of the authors fraudulent proceeding, &amp; captious cauilling, to be a miere by-way drawing pore trauellers out of the royall &amp; common streete, &amp; leading them deceitfull in to a path of perdition. With a postscript of advertisements, especially touching the homilie &amp; epistles attributed to Alfric: &amp; a compendious retortiue discussion of the misapplyed by-way. Author T.T. Sacristan &amp; Catholike Romanist</title>
                 <author>T. T., Sacristan &amp; Catholike Romanist</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyon, Marc, Widow of</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 570, that is 540, 2, 198, that is 197, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="supplement">
   <pb facs="336"/>
   <pb n="101" facs="336"/>
   <head>A SVPPLIMENT OF ADDITIONS TO THE APPPENDIX.</head>
   <p>I Haue alreadie noted diuers most foule corruptions and falsifications in Sir Humfrey linds pretented safe way in soe much that I am almost quite surfeted with the multitude of them, yet in my opinion ther is scarce anie amōg all those which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes neare to the false dealing and cousi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage which the same Sir Humfrey vseth in the 205. page of his <hi>Deuia,</hi> which if it were for noe other reason, yet for this a lone it might most iustely deserue the name, not as it is falsely applyed to the Romanists, but as it is his owne proper worke, which if the reader will but please to haue a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle patience, I will plainely set before his eyes.</p>
   <p>Wherefore Sir Humfrey in the place now cyted vndertaking to proue that trās<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiation wants antiquitie, vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salitie, and succession, hauing first cited some testimonies both out of Greeke and Latin authors (which neuerthelesse are either of noe force for his purpose, or els
<pb n="102" facs="337"/> haue ben ansered partely by Bellarmin and other Catholique diuines, and partely by my selfe in my Censure he stumbles last vpon the late Patriarch of Cnnstantinople whome he alsoe produceth to the same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in the 10. and 13. chapters of his first anser to the Germanes, affirming that this author teacheth what is meant by that change or transmutation made in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, saying, he tells vs: the bodie and bloud of Christ are truely misteries not that these, <hi>Metaballomena,</hi> are changed in to humane flesh but wee vnto thē: thus Sir Humfrey soe confidently as if he had ben Greeke Professor in Oxford he coud haue done no more. And in deed I must needs confesse that this passage of his is able to make a greate showe especially bringing a Greeke worde in the midest of it.</p>
   <p>But now when I came to examen the matter in the booke it selfe and conferred the Greeke and the Latin togither as I founde it printed at witerberg a place voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of all suscipition on our syde, I found first that the author speakes soe plainely of the reall presence and transsubstantiation, that altho' he vseth not the verie same wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, yet doth he vse other wordes equiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, as, <hi>conuersion, transmutation,</hi> or the lyke, at the least ten or a dozen tymes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely
<pb n="103" facs="337"/> in those verie chapters. Nay and more then this, I fynde that where he speakes of the conuersion or transmutation he vseth that verie worde <hi>Metauallo,</hi> which the knight denyeth him to vse, where he dini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the change of the bodie and bloud in to humane flesh, which is a forceble argumēt a contrario that the Patriarch speakes of a reall change whersoeuer else in this matter he vseth that worde.</p>
   <p>Secondly. I fynde that those wordes which Sir Humfrey cytes are not spoken by the Grecian Patriarke of the proper transmutation in the Sacrament, but of an other transmutation which belong onely to the vse of the Sacrament to wit, he sayth and that verre truely, that when a faithfull person receiues the Sacrament, the bodie and bloud which he receiues are not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in to humane flesh, but the receiuers in to them. <hi>Non quod haec</hi> (saith the Patriarch) <hi>in corpus humanum transmutentur sed nos in illa melioribus his praeualentibus:</hi> and here it is that he vseth the worde <hi>Metaballomeua</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth it to be verifyed in this kynde of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, speaking according to that which an ancient Father of the Church sayth to the same purpose: <hi>Non tu mutaberis in me, sed ego mutabor in te.</hi> That is to saye. <hi>O lord thou shalt not be changed in to mee, but I in to
<pb n="104" facs="338"/> thee.</hi> Which spirituall change or vnion the same Patriarch doth learnedly prosecute and declare with examples, not intending by that to exclude the reall presence of Christs bodie &amp; bloude in the Sacramēt by transsubstantiation (as Sir Humfrey would willingly persuade his simple reader but supposing and includeing the same as in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of his passages in these twoe chapters is most apparent, and particularly where he sayth not farre before, <hi>ac quamdiu panis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>situs iacet, nihil nisi panis est repositus tantum Deo: postea verus panis fit &amp; reuera transmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur, cuius rei ratio &amp; modus nullo ingenio, nullo ore humano explicari potest.</hi> And page. 97. <hi>Honorabilia haec dora in ipsum Dominicum transmutantur corpus quod haec omnia recepit, scilicet quod crucifixum sit, quod resurrexit, quod in Caelos ascendit. Tbe honorable giftes</hi> (he meanes the bread and wine) <hi>ar changed into the lordes bodie it selfe &amp;c.</hi> and in the precedent page, <hi>qui operationis sanctorum my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steriorum proprium hoc opus statuunt vt dona (intellige panem &amp; vinum) in diuinum Christi corpus &amp; sanguinem, transmutentur, in finem hunc vt fideles sanctificentur, peccatorumque re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missionem, regni haeriditatem, &amp; id genus alia accipere credant, non tales beatos praedicamus?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus the Patriarch soe perspicuously that he who either vnderstādes Greeke or Latin
<pb n="105" facs="338"/> yea or English either, may euidently see that the Patriarch is cited by our aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie euidently against himselfe, and quite contrarie to his true meaning.</p>
   <p>Yet was not Sir Humfray content with that, but as a mā runing forwarde in mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to his owne confusion he cites the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me author in his former tenth chapter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to proue out of him that it is not the reall and substantiall flesh of Christ which is offered but the Sacrament of his flesh, he tells vs sayth the knight, that the flesh of Christ which he caried aboute him was not giuen to his Apostles to be eaten, nor his bloud to be drunke, neither doth the bodie of our lord descend frome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for this were blasphemie, which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des I confesse the Patriarke hath (excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting these: <hi>in the Sacrament:</hi> Which are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the text by Sir Humfrey) but as he hath them soe hath he others omitted by our aduersarie the knight both before and after these, which clearely declare his myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de touthing the reall presence. The prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent wordes are these: <hi>Dominus enim illa no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte accepit panem gratias egit, fregit, &amp; dixit, accipite &amp; comedite. non dixit hoc est azinum, aut typus corporis, sed hoc est corpus meum, hic est sanguis meus:</hi> that is our lord that night tooke bread, gaue thankes, brake it, and
<pb n="106" facs="339"/> said, take and eate. He said not this is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leauined bread, or this is the figure of my bodie, but this is my bodie, this is my bloud. And then immediately ensue the wordes cited by Sir Humfrey, after which alsoe immediately followes: <hi>Sed &amp; tunc, &amp; nunc inuocatione &amp; gratia omnipotentis illius sacrorum rituum Antistitis Spiritus sancti, sacrarum precationum &amp; diuinorum oraculorū interuentum panis quidem in ipsum Domini cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, vinum vero in ipsum Domini sanguinem conuertitur &amp; transmutatur.</hi> But both then and now by inuocation and grace of that omnipotent Prelate of sacred rities the holie Gost, by interuention of sacred pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and diuine oracles, the bread truely is counuerted and changed into Christs bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die it selfe, but the wine into to his bloud.</p>
   <p>In which wordes the learned and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent reader can not but see both the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all presence and the conuersion or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of the elements of bread and wine (which is nothing els but transsubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation) into the bodie and bloud of Iesus Christ most plainely specifyed. Which may abundantly serue to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate the truth of the Patriarkes meaning, and that no man liuing excepting such a lad of mettall as the coragious knight would haue had the face to make vse or rather
<pb n="107" facs="339"/> abuse of such a testimonie as this, soe quyte opposite to his purpose, <note place="margin">
         <hi>multa enim de illâ (Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na) audiū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur apud vas quae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis displi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. Ierem. Patriarch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi>
      </note> especially the second place being taken out of that chapter in which the author him selfe in the begining of the same doth expressely affirme, that ther are manie things maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the lutherans in the supper of our lord which displease the Grecians, one of which doubtlesse and not the least, is the point of transsubstantiation which the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans reiected in their remonstrance to the Greeke Church, and Ierimie the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arcke maintaines in his anser to the same. To all which may be added yet more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse wordes of the same Patriarke say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus. <hi>Statuit igitur Catholica Ecclesia mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari conseeratione facta panem quidem in ipsum corpus Christi, vinum vero in ipsum sanguinem eius per spiritum sanctum &amp;c.</hi> The Catholique Church therfore (saith he) defins that the consecration being made the bread is changed into the bodie of Christ but the wine into his bloud by the holie Gost &amp;c. And it is to be noted that he vseth the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de <hi>Metauallomena</hi> in these places in which he speakes of the conuersion or transmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the bread and wine into the bodie and bloud of Christ, which doth manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stly de monstrate the Grecian Patriarch to maintaine that same change of the bread
<pb n="108" facs="340"/> and wine in the consecration of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist which the Romanists in Latin call trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substātiation which is sufficient to cōuince the preposterousnes of the iniudicious knight in makeing vse of this great Prelate for his owne contrarie position.</p>
   <p>Touching inuocation of saincts and their worship Sir Humfrey in the 232. page of his deuious way alledges against the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists the confessiō of the Greeke Church quoting in the margen the same Patriarch of Constantinople and relating his wordes in his anser to the German Doctors cap. 1. Wher according to his relation, the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch sayth in the name of him selfe and fellowes, that they doe not properly inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate saints but God, fot neither Peter nor Paule heare anie of those that inuocate them, but the gift and grace that they haue according to the promisse: I am with you till the consummation of the world. Thus the knight rehearses that authors wordes but yet corruptedly, for first the Patriarch hath not those negatiue wordes: <hi>We doe not properly inuocate saints,</hi> but this affirmatiue: <hi>inuocation doth proporly agree to God onely,</hi> and it doth agree to him primarily and most immediately (which wordes Sir Humfrey leaueth out) but inuocation made to saints is not properly inuocation but acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally,
<pb n="109" facs="340"/> and as if we should say by grace or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor: which latter words alsoe the knight partely mangled and partely omitted.</p>
   <p>Secondly the Patriarch dot not saye Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Paule doe not heare their inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors but he sayth: they doe not <hi>exaudire,</hi> that is they doe not heare and graunt by their owne power the petitions of those that inuocate them. And ther is soe much betwixt <hi>audire &amp; exaudire,</hi> that his hearing and graunting that which is heard, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thou' the one vndoubledly agree to the saints both in the doctrine of the Grecian Church and the Roman: yet of the exau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or hearing with a graunt, doubt may be made euen according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Roman Church whether it is proper to saints or noe, in regarde it may be cōceiued that altho' the saints be truely intercessors betweene vs and God, yet haue they not power to graunt out requests but onely to mediate for vs by way of impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And therfore the same author saith that Peter and Paule doe not <hi>exaudire</hi> that is, not soe heare vs as they them selues graunt our petition which they heare but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> that is according or by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor they haue by virtue of the promisse of our Sauior: <hi>I will be with you till the end of the world,</hi> as the Grecian Patriarch doth
<pb n="110" facs="341"/> sufficiently declare. And that the Grecians doe in generall termes graunt inuocation of saints (which is that which both agrees with the Roman doctrine and differs from the doctrine of the pretented reformers) it is manifest not onely out of this place but alsoe out of other places of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes anser, as particularly in the 13. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pag 102. wher it is said by him: that in the sacrifice or masse, <hi>mentionem beatissimae Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis facimus, laudes eius praedicantes, interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sione sanctorum omnium petentes, misericordiam Dei implorantes pro viuis mortuisque supplican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp;c.</hi> And yet more plainely in the verie 21. chapter cited by our aduersarie, where the Patriarke hath these wordes. <hi>Haec medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio nunc in Ecclesia fit &amp; depraedicatur, &amp; ad sanctos exclamamus, &amp; ad dominam nostram &amp; ad sanctos Angelos: &amp; ad dominam quidem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stram, tersancta domina Deipara pro nobis inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede peccatoribus: ad sanctos autem Angelos, omnes caelestes potestates sanctorum Angelorum, &amp; Archangelorum orate pro nobis &amp;c. This me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation is now made &amp; preached in the Church: we both crye aloud to the saints and to our ladie, and to the Angels: and to our ladie truly, thrise holie ladie mother of God intercede for vs sinners. But to the holie Angeles all you, Celestial. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of holie Angels, and Algels pray for vs &amp;c.</hi> Loe heare the verie same forme of
<pb n="111" facs="341"/> prayer to saints which the Romanist vse: soe that the reader may easily iudge how pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posteroussy Sir Humfrey hath proceeded in the citation of this auther. And howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it is that the Grecians will not call this proper inuocation of saints, yet that is but <hi>questio de nomine,</hi> a question onely aboute the name or worde inuocation, which little importes supposing that in reallitie and substance they disegree not from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists, but rather are most conformable vnto them euen in the manner of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpellation.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>And besydes this if wee</hi> note the Lutherans wordes to the Patriarke, it will euen thēce manifestly appeare what the Grecians de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fēd touching his point. For say the Doctors: <hi>Non dubium est quin sit de sanctis reuerenter sentiendum, &amp; loquendum &amp;c. non tamen sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus eos esse inuocandos vt sint nostri mediatores atque iutercedant apud Deum pro nobis qui iam mortui sunt.</hi> Which wordes of the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans being those which they directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose against the doctrine of the Grecians in this particular, it is clearer then the leight of the sunne that the Grecians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with vs, and be contrarie to the tenets of Sir Humfrey and other sectaries of our tymes. And thus we see that altho' Sir Hū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey both in this and diuers other places of
<pb n="112" facs="342"/> his bookes doth much labore to persuade the reader that the Grecian Church agrees with the pretented reformers and differ from vs in doctrine of controuersie, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse his worke wil not fadge, it being manifest to them whoe haue viewed the doctrine of their Patriarke in his foresaid anser to the lutherans, that excepting the point of the Popes supremacie (in which neuerthelesse the Grecians doe not in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie respect agree with them) they doe not fully ioyne with the nouellists of our age in anie one of the questions in controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie betwixt vs and them. And soe I may conclude that Sir Humfrey not obstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the fraudes and diuises he hath v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in laboring to make the Grecians see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to stand for his faction, he doth but onely rase duste to molest and dasle his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders eyes.</p>
   <p>More ouer the same Patriarke page 243. of his anser to the lutherans doth absolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely prnounce that saints are to be invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for thus he saith. <hi>Ad haec nos ope diuina respondemus inuocandos esse sauctos quod ipsi eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am auxiliari pessint.</hi> And he addeth after war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. <hi>Nec id faciunt solum viui sed etiam mortui.</hi> And a little lower he subioyneth. <hi>Inuocatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne sanctorum daemones abiguntur, morbi fugan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, tentationes tolluntur &amp;c.</hi> Also page 244.
<pb n="113" facs="342"/>
      <hi>honorandi igitur sunt sancti tanquam amici Dei.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In like maner touching the images of Saints he further addeth. <hi>A nobis etiam ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginibus ipsorum reuerentium exhiberi, aut adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri nemo reprehendit. &amp;c.</hi> That is, <hi>none of vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth that reuerence, or adoration be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to their images.</hi> Meaning of the Saincts. And in the page following he saith in this manner. <hi>At (inquit aliquis) Deus dixit. Deum tuum adorabis &amp; illi so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li seruies: &amp; non facies vllam similitudinem.</hi> He ansereth thus. <hi>Est vero ita; sunt hoec lege diuina sancita, verumtamen qui hoc praecipit Deus, idem docet nos in deuteronomio. Non ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabis ipsa, non seruies.</hi> And page 254. Soe he speakes. <hi>Vt igitur qui non honorat filium (vt ait dominus) non honorat patrem: sic qui non honorat imaginem nec illum quem imago refert honorat.</hi> And in the same page. <hi>Qui non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorat Crucem, eum nequidem Dominum crucifix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um adorare iustum est. Non quidem certe natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram ligni &amp;c. Sed memoriam &amp; picturam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pessorum &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Finally of merit he saith thus. <hi>Haec &amp; similia sunt ob quae homo regno coelesti dignus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur.</hi> That is <hi>these &amp; the like ar these thing for which a man is held worthie of the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestiall kingdome,</hi> thus much touching the
<pb n="114" facs="343"/> abuse of the Grecian Patriarke by Sir Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey.</p>
   <p>But one of the grossest errours that I finde committed by our aduersarie in the Doctrine of the latinists or Romanists, is in his page 234. where he hath these wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Others (as namely Antisiodorensis &amp; Biel) teache that neither the Saints pray for vs, neither are we to praye to them. Thus Sir Humfrey, further adding that he may safely conclude these and the like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons considered that inuocation of Sains wants antiquitie, vniuersalitie, &amp; succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
   <p>And yet I hauing examined the matter &amp; taken a viewe of the 30. Lection of Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel Biel which is the place the knight ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes for his hallucination, I finde that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor expressely teacheth the affirmatiues of both those negatiues which he falsely affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes him and Antisiodore to maintaine.</p>
   <p>Wherfore touching the first proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Biel in the place cited hath these wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des for his conclusion. <hi>Credendum est igitur &amp; nullatenus dubitandum sanctos in patria in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedere nobisque suffragari merito, ac prece, siue voto.</hi> And for proofe of the same he addeth thus. <hi>Quae veritas authoritate ostenditur &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, authoritate vtriusque testamenti veteris &amp; noui simul, &amp; sanctorum Patrum.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="115" facs="343"/> his conclusion he saith: <hi>fuit haeresis quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumdam, nimia temeritate omnem sanctorū cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum penitus tollere volentium qui nullum sanctis honorem impendi debere mussitabant, neque vllas ad eos preces dirigi, nec eorum reliquias venerari. Huius author &amp; haeresiarcha primus fuit Jouinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus &amp;c,</hi> Which wordes altho they doe suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently declare what this author holdes of the second parte of this point, yet doth he more expressely vtter the same towardes the end of this lection saying: <hi>ex quibus patet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces nostras spemque consequendae beatitudinis per mediatores sanctos in Coelo inanes non esse sed ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne à Deo iustituto nos ad eorum auxilia confugere debere &amp; debita veneratione eos semper implorare.</hi> By all which wordes Biels doctrine is foe plaine for the Romanists, &amp; soe plaine against Sir Humfrey that I am verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suaded he either neuer read this author touching this particular, or if he read him, he did not vnderstand him.</p>
   <p>And the like I say of Antisiodore whoe being in the same place cited, I fynd that he himselfe teacheth quite contrarie to that which the knight chargeth him with. For wheras he is alledgeth by Sir Hūfrey in the 4. parte of his summe lib. 3. q. 6. to resolue that neither the saints doe praye for vs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are wee to praye to them: it is true An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisiodore relates the opinion of manie whoe
<pb n="116" facs="344"/> say that neither are wee to praye to the saints nor they praye for vs but onely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly, to wit because we pray God that the merits of his saincts may helpe vs, whē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce it is consequent that their merits may helpe vs: Neuerthelesse for his owne reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the question he puts the contrarie proposition saying. <hi>Concedimus quod oramus Sanctos proprie, &amp; ipsi orant pro nobis proprie, vt cum dicimus sancte Petre ora pro nobis, &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Wee graunt</hi> saith Antisiodore <hi>that wee praye to the saincts properly, &amp; that they pray for vs properly as when we say: Sainct Peter pray for vs.</hi> And now loe here how faithlessely the knight hath proceeded in his allegation of the testimonies of these twoe authors, whoe both soe plainely conspire against him: &amp; let the reader alsoe consider how little reason our aduersarie had to conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that inuocation of saincts hath neither antiquitie, vniuersalitie nor succession, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing that he can conclude no other safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie out of these and the like premisses then such as proceeds frome his owne forgerie &amp; deceite.</p>
   <p>And altho' Gabriel cites an opinion of manie others that graunt the Saints doe praye onely improperly for vs by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of their merits, yet doe they not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all prayer to saincts, as Sir Humfrey
<pb n="117" facs="344"/> &amp; the rest of his pretensiue reformed bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe, whoe if they would but graunt the same, the Roman Church would not soe much complaine of them; neither is the difference of those Romanists frome others in the substance of this question in controuersie, which is whether the saincts intercede &amp; praye for faithfull Christians liuing in this world, &amp; whether we may praye vnto them &amp; inuocate them, in both which partes of doctrine all Romanists agree, but these diuines mentioned by Biel doe dissent from the rest onely aboute the maner of intercession which saints doe vse making a question whether they performe that charitable acte by formall prayer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vnto God for vs or by interposition of their merits by that meanes to moue his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine maiestie to graunt our requests, which manner of mediation as it is not the cheefe question betwixt our aduersarie of these ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes &amp; vs, soe neither is it an argument of defect of antiquitie, vniuersalitie, or suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession in the Roman doctrine, nor anie proofe of the same notes to concurre in the tenets of the moderne sectaries as Sir Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey doth falsely suppose &amp; proueth not, but onely equiuocateth in the state of the question, or rather by affected ignorance
<pb n="118" facs="345"/> transuersteth the meaning of the foresaid diuines touching this point taking the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for the substance of the matter, &amp; soe either throu' affected ignorance or plaine malice diludes his reader. To let passe that altho' the foresaid authors doe not graunte that the saints vse anie formall or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per forme of prayer to God for vs, yet doe they not deuie our in vocation vnto them. Nay supposing these diuines of whose doctrine the kinght would faine take hould as if it were contrarie to the vniuersalitie of the Roman faith: supposing I say as Sir Humfrey him selfe relates out of Gabriel they defend the mediation of saints by their merits at the least, if he had had is sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses in readinesse, he might easily haue either inferred that those same authors in like māner hould that we may inuocate &amp; pray vnto them euen peoperly &amp; formally: or at the least it is plaine he neither ought nor could deduce the non inuocation of saints frome the foresaid mediation, as erroneou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly he doth, &amp; consequently he greatly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the maintainers of that opinion in that he produceth them against the vniuersali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, antiquitie, and continuall succession of the Roman doctrine in this particular; see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they differ not a iot frome other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique diuines in it touching the substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce
<pb n="119" facs="345"/> of faith: yea they are soe farre from this, that they expressely consent with them both in the doctrine of mediation &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, both which points neuerthelesse the Nouellists doe obstinately impugne, soe that it appeareth as a manifest trueth that Sir Humfrey can not possible with all his arte &amp; deuises scrape anie thing out of them for the antiquitie, vniuersalitie, &amp; succession of his pretensiue reformed congregation, but rather that which doth quite destroye it if he had his dyes aboute him to percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it.</p>
   <p>To the wordes cited by Sir Humfrey pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge 263. concerning images; Biel subioyneth these. <hi>Nec tamen propter haec imagines proij<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciendae sunt aut de oratorijs eliminandae occasione idololatriae deuitandae, aut peregrinationes ad certas imagines vel certa loca praesertim consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta vel etiam consecranda penitus reprehendenda, non enim vsque quaque negandū est quin in certis locis singulariter reluceant beneficia &amp; maiora crebrius quam in alijs vel propter imagines sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, reliquias ibi conditas, uel occulta ministeria (alias mysteria) futuris temporibus ibi celebran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da aut celebrata vel alias causas nobis occultas propter quas Deus vnum locum elegit suo cultui, non alium,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus much Biel in can. missae sec. 49. Which wordes neuerthelesse are slylie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="120" facs="346"/> by Fir Humfrey, &amp; his freind Cas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sander, which other wise are soe plaine for the Catholique practice in this matter euen at this day, that they confounde them both. And this is their false plot which they vsed to make this most Catholique author seeme to fauore their ill cause, wheras in reallitie he is plainely against them.</p>
   <p>Page 152. of the by-way, Canus is cited by Sir Humfrey lib. 3. cap. 3. And falsely alledged as if he gaue a reason wherfore <hi>traditions are aboue scriptures.</hi> For he onely affitmes that they are of greater force to conuince haeretikes then scriptures, that which in substance was taught long since by ancient Tertullian &amp; is no blemish vnto the written worde of God, which in other respects both the same Canus &amp; all other Romanists at the least equalize yea prefer before the vnwritten doctrine of the Church in generall.</p>
   <p>In his citation of Canus page 399. of his by way, Sir Humfrey puts the obiection as if it were the doctrine of the author whoe propoundeth &amp; ansereth the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in his last chapter of the first boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, sharpely reprehending Pighius out of whose opinion the obiection is fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Canus &amp; reproued. Altho' he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuates with all that the error of Pighius.
<pb n="121" facs="346"/> Is not in matter of faith &amp; doctrine ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessatie to saluation, which is that onely which Canus professeth to maintaine in the defense of the authoritie of Councels, <hi>Nos enim in dogmate fidei &amp; deeretis ad salutem fidelium necessarijs Conciliorum authoritatem as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serimus: in rerum gestarum iudicio &amp; ordine non asserimus. Canus de locis lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap. vlt. ad sep. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentum.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>When Costerus pag. 44. of his Enchir. prefers traditions before the word of God: he takes tradition as it is writen in carnall tables of the harte by the finger of the holy spirit: &amp; on the contrarie he takes the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten worde of God precisely as it consists in letters &amp; caracters which may perish or be corrupted by the false construction of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, or otherwise. And therfore Coste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus calles the first internall, the secōd exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall scriptures in the margen of the same page 44.</p>
   <p>And when the same costerus citcd by Sir Humfrey page. 149. of his <hi>Deuia,</hi> in the first chapter of his Euchyr. saith these wordes. <hi>praestantia huius scripturae &amp;c.</hi> the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of this scripture doth surpasse the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <hi>multis partibus,</hi> in manie respects or by manie degrees those scriptures which the Apostles left vs in partchement, he doth not speake of the vnwritten tradition of
<pb n="122" facs="347"/> the Church, but of that scripture which (as afterwardes he declareth) <hi>Spiritus sanctus in cordibus imprimere dignatus est,</hi> that is which the holie spirit doth digne or vout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to imprinte in our hartes. Which as he speakes before in the same chapter, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but the spirit of consent of the Catholike Church in faith, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording doctrine of all faithfull Christians, not of those onely which now liue in the whole world, but those alsoe whoe by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall succession haue propagated the faith of Christ from the tyme of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles which is that Scripture which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle saith 2. cor. 3. is read by all men, and the vnction. <hi>quaest.</hi> 2. <hi>Io.</hi> 2. <hi>docet nos de omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp;c. which teaches vs all things,</hi> which as he further addeth afterwardes hath all truth in it selfe and containeth all faith and mysteries of Christian religion, and resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues all doubtes which may aryse in matter of faith, and soe costerus compareth not the vnwritten worde with the written pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisely but the internall with the externall, which internall scripture is iustely prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by him before the bare written worde or caracter, because as he takes it here it includes the true sense of both the one and the other: by which it appeares that the exceptions which Sir Humfrey takes at
<pb n="123" facs="347"/> this authors wordes ar captious and voyde of reason.</p>
   <p>Vrspergensis is produced by Sir Humfrey page 400. of his deuia as a witnesse that the second councel of Nyce or seuēth generall synod assembled in the yeare 788. was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected in the councell of Francford as vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly voyde and not to be named the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth. And yet hauing examined this pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage in that author, I fynde he speakes not a worde of the Nycene councell but of a cettaine councell of Constantinople which he affirmes to haue ben called the seuenth synod general by the Emperatrice Irene and her sonne Constantine: his wordes are these. <hi>Sinodus etiam qua ante paucos annos in Constantinopoli congregata sub Irene &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantino filio eius septima &amp; vniuersalis ab ipsis appellata est, vt nec septima nec aliquid diceretur quasi superuacua ab omnibus (nimirum patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Concilij Francfordiensis) abdicata est.</hi> Vrs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perg. pag. 176. in which wordes of what soeuer Councell vrpergensis intended to speake, yet none of them mention the Councell of Nyce as all those whoe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand latin may easily perceiue. And if Sir Hunfrey will replye and say that tho' that author doth not mention the Nycene Councell in wordes, yet doth he sufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly declare his meaning to be of no other
<pb n="124" facs="348"/> Councell then the seeond Nycene Synod in regarde he affirmes it to haue ben vnder Irenne and her sonne, and the same which was condemned in the Councell of Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, I anser that by reason this author doth vtter twoe things which seeme to implye contradictiō to wit that this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell was assembled at Constantinople and yet that it is the same which was reiected by the Councell of Francford, it euidently fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that no certaine argument can be drawne frō his wordes whatsoeuer his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was, and this is sufficient to shewe that he is cited in vaine by the knight.</p>
   <p>Secondly I say not obstanding vspergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis hallucination, and suppose he did truely meane that the Councell of Nyce concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the adoration of images was repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the Synod of Francford, as some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther authors admit in their disputatiōs with the sectaries of our tymes, yet doth this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing auaile our aduersaries cause both in respect the Synod of Francford is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by the Romanists for an authenticall Councell in this particular, as alsoe for that (as some opinate) it proceeded vpon false information, and persuasion that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Synod of Nyce had decreed that ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were to be adored with diuine honor, and by this meanes the Fathers and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors
<pb n="125" facs="348"/> ther assembled were deceiued and committed an error of fact. Which error neuerthelesse neither can nor ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice that doctrine which was before esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished by an authenticall generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell as was the secōd Synod consisting of a happie cōiunction of both the latin &amp; Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Church as of sune and moone. And the reader may see that Sir Humfrey hath both dealt some thing insincere in the allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō of Vspergensis, and alsoe hath proceeded preposterously in that he indeuored to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe the authoritie of the greater Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell by the vncertaine proceeding of the lesse.</p>
   <p>Page 261. of the same <hi>deuia</hi> he detortes the S. Irenaeus wordes contrarie to his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning against Apostolicall traditions. And yet S. Irenaeus euen in the wordes which are cited by him, speakes onely against those who denyed absolutely that the trueth is deliuered by the Scriptures but onely by tradition, and soe made them selues or their onwe traditions the rule of faith. Of which number of hererikes saith he were Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Marcion, Cerinthus, Basilides, of who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me he vttered the wordes cited by Sir Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey, as affirming that the truth could not be founde by Scriptures by those whoe were ignorant of traditions for say they: the
<pb n="126" facs="349"/> truth was not deliuered by writing but by worde of mouth, yet notobstanding this the same Irenaeus afterwardes speakes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst others whoe doe not denye scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, or rather against such as follow scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures onely and reiect traditions receiued from the Apostles by succession of preists and conserued or obserued in the Church saying that they haue founde the pure truth. (as the pretended reformers nowe commonly babble) of whome he saith that <hi>They neither consent to scriptures nor tradition, and against whome</hi> (saith the saint) <hi>we ought euerie way to resist.</hi> Soe that it is cleare that he disputes here onely against such heretikes as neither yealde to scriptures nor traditions, and therfore he putteth for the litle of his chapter in this place <hi>quod ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que scripturis neque traditionibus obsequantur haretici: that heretiques neither obey scriptures nor traditions:</hi> both which S. Irenaeus doth expressely imbrace.</p>
   <p>And by this lett the reader iudge how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempestiuely the knigh doth produce this testimonie against those (I meane the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists) who neither reiect the scriptures nor approued traditions but like twoe indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided companions receiue them both: and let him alsoe consider whether the doctrine of holye Irenaeus in this place be not farre
<pb n="127" facs="349"/> more contrarie to the tenet of the pretēded reformers then to the doctrine of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church: whoe make onely scriptures expounded according to their owne sense the sole rule of faith. Especially considering that the same ancient Father in the next ensuing chapter doth expressely receiue A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicall traditions saying in the verie first wordes: <hi>traditionem itaque Apostolicam in toto mundo manifestam in Ecclesia adest perspice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re omnibus qui vera volunt audire, &amp; habemus annumerare eos qui ab Apostolis instituti sunt Episcopi in Ecclesijs &amp; successores eorum vsque ad nos qui nihil tale docuerunt neque cognouerunt quale ab his deliratur.</hi> By which wordes it is manifest that S. Irenaeus doth confute his aduersaries the heretikes not by scripture onely, but alsoe &amp; cheefely by traditiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie authoritie of the Bishops succeeding fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the Apostles: which is directly opposite to the tenets especially of the purer sorte of nouellists whoe neither admitte tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions nor Episcopall authoritie but the onely written worde for absolute and sole Iudge of all Controuersies &amp; confutation of heresies.</p>
   <p>Caietan in his Commentarie vpon the historian bookes of the old Testament (as I am persuaded) doth not plainely affirme (neither doth Canus charge him with that error)
<pb n="128" facs="350"/> that the bookes of Machabies are not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely Canonicall, as Sir Humfrey alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth but he onely reprehendeth him for vsing a vaine distinction of Canonicall scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures as if there were some Canonicall one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for instruction of manners and not for matters of faith: against the infirmitie or vnsoundnesse of which distinction Canus vseth this reprehensiue conclusion saying. <hi>Cum sub eodem contextu omnes illi libri nullo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto discrimine definiantur esse Canonici</hi> (scilicet Ecclesiasticus. Sapientia, Tobias, Iudith, Machabaeorū libri duo, &amp; Baruch) <hi>ridiculum est vt partim in vna significatione partim in alia libros Cenonicos habeamus. Ac si hāc semel distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem admittimus authoritate Conciliorum at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Pontificum nullus liber Sacer constare po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And presently after <hi>Id quoniam absurdum omnino est, retineamus potius eam rationem opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet quam Caietanus voluit evertere vir (vt saepe iam dixi) cum primis eruditus &amp; pius, sed qui in libris Canonicis constituendis Erasmi nouitates ingeniumque secutus, dum alienis vestigijs voluit insistere propriam gloriam maculauit.</hi> And soe you see Canus doth not confesse that dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly Caietan maintained the Machabies not to be Canonicall but onely with that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction: neither did in deed Caietan more denye the authoritie of those bookes then
<pb n="129" facs="350"/> he did the Epistle to the Haebrewes, &amp; that of S. Iames which neuerthelesse he held ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely for Canonicall tho' not perhaps in the same rigorous sense in which he iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all the rest of the bookes of scripture to be in the Canon, by reason those, as alsoe some other partes of scripture, haue ben by some ancient authors doubted of, in which doubt onely he seemeth to founde his distinction.</p>
   <p>Touching the Canonicall bookes of the olde Testament Sir Humfrey doth most falsely alledge the authoritie of S. Isidore persuading his reader that he reiecteth tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se same bookes which he and his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in the newe religion condemne for Apochripha. Weras in deed that ancient author numbereth them all in the Christiā Canon. And to the end the knights impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie may more plainely appeare I will rehearse S. Isidores expresse wordes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the same whoe in his 6. booke of ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes or etymologies saith thus. <hi>Quartus est apud nos ordo veteris Testamenti eorum librorum qui in Canone Haebreo non sunt: quorum primus sapientiae liber est. Secundus Ecclesiasticus. Tertius Tobias. Quartus Judith. Quintus &amp; Sextus Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaboeorum.</hi> Quos licet <hi>Haebraei inter Apochry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha separent, Ecclesia tamen Christi inter diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos libros &amp; honorat &amp; praedicat.</hi> By which
<pb n="130" facs="351"/> wordes it is soe euident that this holie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther standes for the Romanists and against the pretensiue reformers in this point; that I much maruell how Sir Humfrey could haue the face to produce him in fauor of his cause. Nay more then this out of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction which he maketh betweene the the Hebrewes &amp; vs Christians in receiuing the foresaid bookes for Canonicall, I frame a firme coniecture that either all or most of these ancient authors whoe seeme to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exclude them out of the Canon, doe onely intend to declare that they were not inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in it by the Iewes as S. Hilarie. S. Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, &amp; S. Epiphanius &amp; other authors: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which point the reader may please to reade the same S. Isidore <hi>in lib. Prooemio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum de libris veteris, &amp; noui Testamenti.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the 431. page of his by-way the kinght abuseth Canus whome he there ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes lib. 12. cap. 13. For he foysteth in by a parenthesis of his owne the worde <hi>reall</hi> which neither Canus hath, nor yet put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the force of his reprehension <hi>of the bishop of Bitont</hi> in that he affirmed in the Councell of Trent that Christ did not offer his reall bodie in his last supper, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he affirmed that Christ did not offer his owne bodie absolutely, abstracting frō reall or not reall, the question not being in
<pb n="131" facs="351"/> that passage of the reall presence, but of the Sacrifice of Christs bodie &amp; bloud in the Eucharist, which as it seemes by Canus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation the foresaid Bishop in the discussion of this point by way of proposition was of that priuate dictamen, how beit after war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des he willingly conformed him selfe to the rest of the Fathers &amp; to the decree of the Councell. By which it is plaine that this Bishop was not of anie firme &amp; setled opinion which might fauor Sir Humfreys doctrine in that particular. <hi>Illud primum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimaduerto iure Cornelium Episcopum Bitonti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in Conelio apud Tridentinum à Patribus &amp; Theologis vniuersis explosum qui dixerit Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum in Coena non suum corpus &amp; sanguinem ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulisse.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Canus loco citato.</hi>
      </note> And soe you see this is one of Sir Humfreyes prittie pettie trickes which omong other greater will serue to reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish his pages.</p>
   <p>The kinght alsoe in his 157. page of his <hi>deuia</hi> corrupteth the same author cited in his third booke &amp; third chapter. Where for these wordes, <hi>in sacrificio Eucharistiae simul cum corpore sanguinem sacerdotibus esse confici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum, &amp; sumendum &amp;c. Sacrae litterae nus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam forte tradiderunt:</hi> he translates, <hi>the consecrating &amp; receiuing of ehe bodie, &amp; bloud of Christ by the preist &amp;c. Are nowhere happily to be found in scripture.</hi> In which pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage
<pb n="132" facs="352"/> the attentiue reader may easily see that the knight plaieth the iugler most nimble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For wheras Canus putteth the force of his sentence in the wordes <hi>simul</hi> together, or at once, &amp; in the other worde <hi>sumendum,</hi> making an hipotheticall proposition of all his wordes ioyned togither: our craftie Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culator soe hādleth the matter that his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may imagin that Canus affirmed that the consecration of the Eucharist according to the custome of the Roman Church is not found in the bible. That which that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor neuer dreamed, but onely intended to produce as an instance of Apostolicall tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions that copulatiue of the practice of the preists consecrating &amp; actuall recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing both the bodie &amp; bloud at one &amp; the same tyme in the vse of the Eucharist, which Canus supposeth rather to be a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition then expressely contained in the text of scripture.</p>
   <p>More ouer Sir Humfrey cites Gretzerus but onely twise: first in his defense of the tenth chapter of the third booke of Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin <hi>de verbo Dei pag.</hi> 15. And of his owne by way page 503. And secondly in the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Gretzers defense of the first chapter of the first booke of Bellarmine <hi>verbo Dei.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the first place he abuseth that author in that he produceth him to proue that the
<pb n="133" facs="352"/> Church is finally resolued in to the Pope as head &amp; bodie of the same. And yet in the verie same chapter page 1456. &amp; next lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe Gretzer plainely teacheth that our faith is lastely resolued in to diuine reuelatiō, or in to God reueiling or that which is the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in to the prime veritie in which our faith is founded. His wordes are these in latin. <hi>Nam sides nostra vltima resoluitur in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelationem diuinam seu in Deum reuelantem seu quod idem est in primam veritatem qua &amp; niti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur fides nostra tanquam fundamento paimario tametsi non inficior fidem quoque resolui in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siam seu Ecclesiae propositionem, altho I doe nor denye that faith is resolued in to the Church, or the proposition of the Church: &amp;c.</hi> Immedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely after this he saith. <hi>Sed haec resolutio non est omniuo vltima &amp; in principium plane sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiale &amp; essentiale: sed tantum vt in funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum secundarium seu vt in conditionem sine qua fides neque recipitur neque retinetur.</hi> And euen in these wordes by the knight, the Pope alone is not put by Gretzerus for the whole Church, but he doth onely say, he denyeth not that the Romanists vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand by the Pope the Church in one acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, not absolutely. Which is manifest out of his wordes in the precedent page where he saith: <hi>Intelligimus etiam nomine Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiae Pontificem pro tempore viuentem quod ipse
<pb n="134" facs="353"/> congregare &amp; conuocare potest Concilium, &amp; hunc summi Pastoris &amp; aliorum Praesulum cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum dicimus esse immediatum &amp; ordinarium &amp; visibilem omnium Controuersiarum quae de reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione existunt Iudicem.</hi> By which wordes it is apparent that Gretzerus doth not take the Popes person alone for the head &amp; bodie of the Church, but for the head of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of the Church. How be it I doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye but that the Pope as head &amp; cheefe parte of the whole Church may by a senec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doche be taken for the whole Church as he is accepted both by Gretzer and other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, but yet this acception will nothing profit Sir Humfrey whose wise designe in this place is to persuade his simple reader that the Romanists take the Pope alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne without a generall Councell truely and properly for the whole Roman &amp; Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church which is his owne phamtasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call dreame, not our doctrine.</p>
   <p>In the other place Sir Humfrey plainely falsifyeth this author, for wheras Gretze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus onely redargueth his aduersaries whoe falsely affirmes that what soeuer the deuill suggesteth to this or that Pope in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar euen against manifest scripture, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists receiue it for Gods worde, saying, that these things be <hi>crepitacula nugantium Praedicantium,</hi> the clappers of prating prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,
<pb n="135" facs="353"/> &amp; that in truth wee Romanists one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiue &amp; reuerence for the worde of God that which the cheefe Bishop doth by Cathedrall definition propose vnto vs as the supreme master &amp; Iudge of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies: Sir Humfrey by fraudulent displaceing of the worde <hi>onely</hi> &amp; putting it before <hi>the worde of God,</hi> quyte peruertes the sense ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his reader beleaue that Gretzer affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, that onely to be the worde of God which the Pope proposeth, and as if they held not the scripture it selfe to be Gods worde; the contrarie of which neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse the Iesuit deliuers immediately before in expresse termes saying that, it (meaning the scripture) is had &amp; reuerenced by the Pontificians for the worde of God which is soe well knowne that the impudencie of the Predicants can not denye it. And thus much touching the corruption &amp; abuse of Gretzere by the calumnious knight.</p>
   <p>Moreouer wheras Sir Humfrey cites Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stro in his 12. booke as affirming the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall of Purgatorie to be a most notorious &amp; knowne error of the Greciās &amp; Armeniās, that author is abused by him, for he meanes onely of the moderne Grecians not of the ancient Grecian Fathers, as the knight gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues his reader to vnderstand, falsely apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Canus wordes page 181. to the Greek
<pb n="136" facs="354"/> Church of the first ages, soe that here is plaine forgerie.</p>
   <p>In like fashion in his 536. page of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia,</hi> he falsifyes the same author lib. 1. cap. 9. For where Castro saith: <hi>quamuis enim tenea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur ex fide credere verum Petri successorem esse supremum totius Ecclesiae pastorem,</hi> for those wordes <hi>quamuis teneamur</hi> that is, <hi>altho' we are bound,</hi> Sir Humfrey translates, admit we are bounde to beleeue that point, as if Castro had doubted of it, of which neuerthelesse he makes not anie question, but onely saith, men are not obledged to beleeue by faith that this or that particular person is true Pope. Neither yet doth he denye that euerie Pope hath infallibilitie in a reight line of succession frō S. Peter as the knight doth falsely taxe him: but he affirmes onely that it is not a matter of faith soe to belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of euerie Pope in particular. And therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re he addeth that altho' he were not to be accounted an heretike that should denye obediēce vnto this or that particular Pope, to wit Clemēt or Leo, yet should he not for doubt of his election sustract him selfe from his obedience. And soe we see that here his no other argument then of want of honest dealing in our aduersarie.</p>
   <p>And yet in his 21. section of the <hi>deuia</hi> page 551. he traduceth the same Alfonsus
<pb n="137" facs="354"/> as if he had scoffed at the Dominicans in generall for that thay were wonte to brag before the people that he that hath once receiued their habit can not erre or fayle in fairh. Wher it is true that Castro repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends sharpely, &amp; not without reason, so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me particular religious men that vsed such speeches, but he is soe farre from saying they are Dominicans, that he expressely addes that least he should seeme to taxe the whole order he purposely conceiled the name. <hi>Ne hoc toti ordini ac societati impressisse videar nomen ordinis ex industria subticui.</hi> &amp; this he did of Charitie. But Sir Humfrey contrarily is soe farre from the exercise of that great virtue that he will needs make Castro to impose that vpon a whole order which he meant onely of some particular person of persons. Which is a trick of a iuggler thou' a verie pore one. Neither can I conceiue, except it were by reuelation, howe Sir Humfrey came to know that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stro spake of the Dominicans more then of anie other religious order, but let that passe for one of his great miracles.</p>
   <p>Touching the mariage of priests cassander is corrupted by Sir Hūfrey in the 23. art. of his consult. p. 990. where for <hi>antiquae consue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinis immutandae,</hi> he puteth in English, <hi>the change of the lawe,</hi> and soe leauing out the
<pb n="138" facs="355"/> worde <hi>ancient</hi> as alsoe the wordes <hi>prisci moris,</hi> which signifyes the custome of celibate to haue ben no newe lawe as he would falsely persuade hir reader, but established in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient tymes. And more then this he foy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth in to his translation the worde <hi>necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> in steed of <hi>flagitare videntur,</hi> And thus like a bungling boteher he patcheth togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther those vncertainties of Cassander to make himselfe and others a deceitfull safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of greater confort and benefit for the soule which he erroneously supposeth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be in his misreformed faith them in the Romish. And now how vnfaithfull, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, &amp; pore proceeding of Sir Humfrey this appeares to be, let the indicious reader con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider.</p>
   <p>The knigh moreouer traduceth Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min in the preface to his booke de Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Pont. translating in euerie place for <hi>Graeci, the Greeke Fathers,</hi> as if the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall did confesse that the ancient and most famous Greeke Fathers to wit S. Chryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, S. Basil Epiphanius and others did impugne and resiste the supremacie of the Bishop of Romane. Wheras it is plaine Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin meaneth onely such Grecians as sate in the Councell of Calcedon whoe frandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently defined in absence of the Popes lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, that the Patriarch of Constantinople is
<pb n="139" facs="355"/> soe the second after the Roman Bishop as that yet he hath equall priuiledges, whence Sir Humfrey will needs inferre that the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie of the Pope wantes succession: as if the Popes resistance to this attempte of vsurpation in those Grecians were suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to exstinguish a true and estblished suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of all former tymes.</p>
   <p>In his page 104. of the deuia touching Salmeron the knight falsely affirmes out of chamier that he speakes in the person of the Grecians when he vttereth those wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. <hi>For as much as the benedictton of the lord is not fuperfluous &amp;c.</hi> For Salmeron neither mentions Grecians nor Latinists but onely argues for the second opinion which he putteth of those which seeme to hould that Christ did not consecrate his bodie and bloud with those wordes. <hi>This is my bodie.</hi> But whose soeuer those wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des bee the matter is not great, yet certaine it is that Sir Humfrey dealeth falsely and deceitfully in that he produceth them and Salmeron to proue that the grand point of transsubstantiation (as he pleaseth to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me it) hath neither foundation in the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, nor certaintie in the Fathers, nor v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie among the Romanists whenas neither those wordes of Salmeron are spoken to proue that the grand point of transsubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation
<pb n="140" facs="356"/> (as he pleaseth to terme it) hath neither foundation in the scriptures, nor certaintie in the Fathers, nor vnitie among the Romanists. When as neither those wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Salmeron are spoken to anie other end but onely to confirme the opinion of such as hould that out Sauior did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrate with those wordes: <hi>This is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</hi> Howbeit, both he and they agree most vniformely in that how soeuer Christ him selfe did whose power being infinite was not tyed to anie wordes at all for the effecting that which he intended no more then he was in the operation of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles &amp; particularly in the miraculous transsubstantiation of water in to wine in the mariage feast of Cana: yet Preists whoe are but his substitutes or instruments in that sacred action doe vndoubtedly conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate with those determinate wordes: <hi>This is my bodie,</hi> in which all Romanists yea &amp; Grecians (excepting some moderne Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians whoe adde some other deprecatorie wordes) doe consent &amp; vnanimously ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde. Wher vpon Salmeron before he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to rehearse opinions touching that point whether Christ him selfe did conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate with these formall wordes, saith plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely. <hi>Illud igitur tanquam certum &amp; constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum est apud omnes hanc fuisse nobis formam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrationis
<pb n="141" facs="356"/> praescriptam, &amp; iure diuino institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ac nobis traditam.</hi> Which wordes suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declare that there is no incertaintie among the Romanists aboute the foresaid wordes of consecration: Nay &amp; if ther were that incertaintie among diuines aboute the forme of the Eucharist which Sir Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey pretendeth, yet doth it not follow that the Doctrine of transsubstantiation is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine supposing that both Salmerō &amp; all the same diuines agree that the bread and wine are truely transsubstantiated or turned in to the bodie &amp; bloud of Christ, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently this author is impertinently al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged as hauing nothing for the knights purpose. Besydes that parte of the wordes which he cites out of Salmeron whether they be the Grecians or not, they include clearely the doctrine of transsubstantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to wit those in particular, <hi>when he gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it transmutation was alreadie made:</hi> &amp; soe the vnwarie knight hath alledge this passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge against him selfe. For if the change of the bread &amp; wine was made before Christ gaue the Sacrament to his disciples, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists haue their desire &amp; intent, that Christ did truely transsubstantiate the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, it importing little to this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion by what meanes he performed his action.</p>
   <pb n="142" facs="357"/>
   <p>Page 547. of his <hi>deuia</hi> the kinght cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts Salmeron by a mangled relation &amp; false construction of his wordes which he produceth to proue that some Romanists &amp; particularly Salmeron hould the Popes iudgement infallible. But how soeuer it be that some Roman diuines hould the Popes authoritie euen without a generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell infallible in determining controuersies in matters of faith, &amp; others the contrarie which as Bellarmin noteth is no matter of faith. Yet certaine it is that Salmeron is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re abused by Sir Humfrey for that in this place cited (what soeuer he doth in others) he rather attributes all infallibilitie in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soluing &amp; declaring matters of controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, cheefely to the assistance &amp; power of the holy spirit, then either to the Pope or Church. His wordes are these. <hi>Neque haec sunt satis nisi accedat vnctio &amp; eruditio Spiritus Sancti quem Dominus mansurum nobiscum in aeternum, qui &amp; in generalibus synodis, &amp; in Christi Vicario &amp; Petri successore residens omnes incidentes quaestiones &amp; ortas de fide controner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sias sua authoritate terminet atque absoluat. Thus Salmeron prologom.</hi> 9. <hi>can.</hi> 1. Wher the reader may perceiue that the kinght hath either ignorantly or malitiously applyed the relatiue <hi>qui</hi> to the Pope, which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse is referred by Salmeron to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="143" facs="357"/> Gost. As anie Grammer boy that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stands latin, may eassely perceiue. And yet blinde Sir Humfrey whoe not being yet a perfect Gramarian, will needs playe the Doctor of diuinite, englisheth &amp; rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth Salmerons wordes thus. <hi>The lorde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised his Spirit to Christs Vicar &amp; the successor of Peter &amp; by his authoritie the determins all matters of faith.</hi> Let the reader compare the english with the latin &amp; he will presently discouer the fraud.</p>
   <p>S. Isidor Pelusiota writ the Epistle cited by Sir Humfrey page 630. to a monke na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Zenon, complaining vnto him of want of virtue &amp; corruption of maners in the Church in comparison of the primatiue tymes, all which that holy man affirmes to proceed from dissention &amp; wickednesse or malice of these whoe gouerne especially of preists thou' not of all: but he hath not a worde of the Pope, or of anie defect, or of the latencie or inuisibilitie of the Church which our aduersarie professeth to prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute in that his section.</p>
   <p>And this which I say is made plaine by the last clause or conclusion of the epistle which is this. <hi>At tu ò conspicue Ecclesiae alum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ne ad eos qui naufragio pereunt animum at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendas nec cum segnibus &amp; ignauis teipsum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares: verum scientiae lumen splendidius, subinde
<pb n="144" facs="358"/> redde per vitae probitatem ac virtutem ipsum ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigans. Atque sponsum expecta ingressum quidem cum ijs qui animis &amp; corporihus virgines sunt. De ijs autem qui virginitatis &amp; sucerdotis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitati per flagitia sua contumeliam intulerunt, supplicium sumpturum.</hi> By which wordes it is plaine here is nothing of anie reformatiō in Faith made or yet desired in those dayes which is that Sir Humfrey aymeth at. Nor is ther anie worde which fauors lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers pretēded reformation of the Church. Neuerthelesse if Sir Humfrey and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sociates could but pick vs out one halfe dozen of such chaste and religious monkes as these, out of all the seuerall Congregatiōs of their illuminate brothers since the dayes of Luther, then would we most willingly giue licence vnto them to reforme the Church at their pleasures.</p>
   <p>Sir Humfrey in the 24. chapter of his <hi>deuia</hi> cites a great number of Romanists with intention to proue the inuisibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Church: &amp; the <hi>medium</hi> he vseth for his proofe be the testimonies of those authors whoe acknowledge abuses to haue ben in the Church in their seuerall ages euen till the dayes of luther: &amp; whoe signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye in their writings that they haue desired reformation of such abuses. Out of which
<pb n="145" facs="358"/> holting premisses Sir Humfrey inferreth this crooked conclusion to wit that Luther was the man that made the soe long wished re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. Which illation as the reader may easily perceiue is as lame as her parēts, neithet is that consequens anie more neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie then that Mahomet was the reformer of the Church because at the same tyme and before he founded his sect ther were perhaps some things which wanted amēd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And yet much lesse can anie man imagin how out of those twoe propositions viz that diuers learned and pious people complained of abuses and corruption of maners and desired redresse, therfore the Church was latent and obscure or inuisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or yet further that that latent and obs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Church was the Church of the pretēded reformers, or that those zelous and godly persons who soe complained in seuerall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, were members of the same, and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther virtuous and religious Romanists as in deed they were, all which inferences because Sir Humfrey neither doth nor can possible proue to be sounde and legitimate, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hath spent much tyme in vaine in that he maketh a large rehearsall of the speeches of such authors as haue noted the common and publike vices of their dayes, which and the like sinnes and abuses no
<pb n="146" facs="359"/> Romanist euer denyed but they may be euen in the members of tre true visible Church.</p>
   <p>Now to come to particulars to the end the follie of our aduersarie may more plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely appeare I will examen some passages which he citeth out of Gerson which being those which seeme most plausible for his cause when the reader shall see them decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and rectifyed, he will without anie more exacte discussion be able to iudge of others of lesse apparence and color.</p>
   <p>I confesse that Gerson was free in his spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aches as being a zelous and plaine man, and a sharpe represender of vices, neuerthelesse I finde not in his writings but that he was an humble acknowledger of the Popes autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie yea and an earnest defender of those points of doctrine which luther and the rest of the pretended newe reformants hould for errneous and false opinions, for superstions and idolatrie. As the vse of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, prayer to saints, Purgatorie, the seuen Sacraments, the reall presence and the rest of the matters in controuersie betweene vs and thē: <note place="margin">
         <hi>de numero Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torū scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quod septē sunt Gers.</hi> 2. <hi>part. Act.</hi> 26.</note> as his workes printed at Strasburg in foure partes or tomes declare, neither did he euer desire anie reformation in the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of these particulars, howe be it I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye not but that as he might finde some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buses
<pb n="147" facs="359"/> in the practise of the same, soe might he alsoe wish for amendment of them, but this is not contrarie to the doctrine and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ze of the Romanists but most conformable to the same, whoe as they confesse that so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me things deseruing correction may creepe in to the particular members of the Church yea and into the head and cheefe pastor him selfe, soe doe they not onely desire but alsoe procure reformation of the same by all direct and lawfull meanes. And soe whatsoeuer Gerson saith in this nature if it be not detorted to a sense contrarie to the true meaning of the author (as here it is by Sir Humfrey) the Romanists most willingly imbrace it as profitable to the soules of manie and for the good of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersall Church.</p>
   <p>It is true Gerson speakes something har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shely and by excesse when he saith: euen as wee see in like manner in some countryes touching censures and lawes inuented a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute particular obseruances or rules not necessarie to saluation which are often ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes preferred before the lawes of God and of the Gospell, And this same wee see mâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestely in the decrees and decretalls. whē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce it is that some tymes a monke is more seuerely punished for going without his hood then for cōmitting adultring or sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge,
<pb n="148" facs="360"/> and he that offendes against one of the Popes commandements then he that sinnes against one of the commaundemēts of God, and the Euangell, according to that reprehension of our Sauior: you haue frustrated the commaundements of God for the traditions of men.</p>
   <p>In an other place the same Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son complaines of the abuses and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of fryers, Nunns, and preists of the great varietie of images which he bids the reader consider whether they be not occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of idolatrie in the simple people: of the canonization of newe saints and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious orders, of which he saith ther are to manie alreadie, and that the feasts of the newe saints are more religiously obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued then the feasts of the Apostles, of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrypsall Scriptures and prayers, super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious opinions of obtaining remission of sinnes by saying soe manie Pater nosters in such a Church before such an image. And in his treatise de Concil. Gen. <hi>vnius obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae</hi> he saith thus: if the Church may not be reformed according to the state in which it was in the tyme of Christ and his Apostles, yet at least it should be brough to the state it was in the tyme of Pope syluester.</p>
   <p>In an other place Gerson as it were by way of complainte saith <hi>in hac tempestate</hi>
      <pb n="149" facs="360"/> (meaning in that season in which he liued) he did see, matters standing as they did, that scarce anie due determination or spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and free execution of iustice was found in doctrine appertaining to faith, religion, to good and hoalsome manners, vnlesse it were by strong fauor of the secular po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</p>
   <p>This is that in substance which Sir Hūfrey alledgeth out of Gerson yea an something more then he him self produceth: And yet neuerthelesse as the reader may easily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand there is nothing agreeable to the reformation of Luther and Caluin. For Gerson onely reprehends, and that iuste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, some particular persons in some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular countryes and in some particular ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruations, which soe exactely and rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously obserue theit rules &amp; lawes &amp; soe ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>orbitantly estreeme of them that they often tymes by indiscreet zeale are more diligent in performing them then they are in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the lawes of God, and that they some tymes punish more seuerely a religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son offending against one of those mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall rules or statutes, or against one of the Popes preceps, or lawes of the decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls, or others, then they punish him whoe committeth adulterie or sacrilege. Wher as those twoe false reformers Martin and
<pb n="150" facs="361"/> Iohn were not content with this, and to procure a reformation in some particular persons, rules, and statues, but they too<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke away all monasticall obseruations ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vowe, rule, or constitution, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingnissed all Ecclesiasticall lawes both of the Pope and Church as much as lay in their power violating, euerting, and razing the verie buildings of religious houses and consuming by fyre the bookes of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals and whole Canon lawes, quyte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying that and much more by rage and furie which Gerson out of a pious &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian zeale onely wished to haue amended.</p>
   <p>Gerson complained of the euill life of fryres and nunnes with desire to haue them reformed and reduced to the obseruation of their ancient rules and constitutions, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely excepting against the multiplicie and varietie of religious orders: <note place="margin">
         <hi>suntque per haec caelestia tonitruasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blata pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibita &amp; damnata omnia isti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us generis vota peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissimè. Lut. tom.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 272.</note> But those companions in impietie Luther and Caluin would haue all religious and monasticall discipline wholely extingnished as Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious damnable, and contrarie to the lawe of God vsing opprobrious speaches against all Religious persons &amp; their profession.</p>
   <p>Gerson tooke to consideration whether the multitude and varietie of images might not be occasion of idolatrie in the simple people yet did not he reproue the due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
<pb n="151" facs="361"/> of them: But our newe reformers or rather deformers either will haue no ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at all in Churches as Caluinists, or at the least they will not haue them honored with religious reuerence as Lutheranes, repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all kinde of veneration or worship of them as superstitious and idolatrous.</p>
   <p>Gerson onely reprehended the excesse (as he apprehended) in the canonization of soe manie newe saints &amp; the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious obseruation of thers feastes then of the feastes of the Apostles by some particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar persons or Churches: but these twoe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane fellowes allowe not of anie religious celebration of the feasts of either ancient or moderne saints neither of Apostles nor Euangelists, neither of confessers nor mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres, making account onely of the sabaoth day (as they cōmonly call the sunday) in that nature: alsoe houlding the canoniza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of noe saints for either necessarie, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, or authenticall desiring rather their memories should be extingiushed rhen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced. Gerson likewise comdemneth instely superstitions comitted by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar persons in the worship of saints, &amp; vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne obseruations, &amp; ouer great credulitie gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by them to euerie passage recounted in some inauthentichall legendes, yet admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; defending due &amp; moderate honor
<pb n="152" facs="362"/> of saints &amp; the authentical &amp; true histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of their liues: But our pretended refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers reiect all religious honor of Saintcts &amp; hould the relatiōs of their liues &amp; mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles for Apocriphall &amp; fabelous at the least of moderne saints.</p>
   <p>Gerson defended the Roman doctrine of indulgences most Catholiquely as his treatice of that matter doth testifye, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarum cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessio non est parui pendenda seu contem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nenda sed amplectēda deuote, &amp; in fide spe &amp; chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Domi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni nostri Iesu Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sti qui po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>testatem lium claui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>um Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticarum dedit homi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nibus Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son p.</hi> 2. <hi>act.</hi> 23.</note> and onely taxed some particular pardons of sinnes as he relates, for saying soe manie pater nosters in such a Church, before such an image, calling them superstitious opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niōs and friuolous additions as hauing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ben approued by the Roman Church: But our newe doctors &amp; masters Luther &amp; Caluin vtterly condemne all sortes of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence graunted by the Pope yea and the power of the Church to graunte them.</p>
   <p>Gersō speaking onely of some vitious Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical persons reprehendes preists for that vnder the pretense of maydes they keepe cōcubines yet plainely supposing the lawe of Celibate or single life of cleargie to haue ben in vse in and before his tymes as a thing lawdable and fitting for their voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <note place="margin">
         <hi>&amp; quoniā assidue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stri sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes sacris occupantur mysterijs quid diuini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us quam vt continua polleant ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitate. Gers.</hi> 2. <hi>part. dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. de ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib. Act.</hi> 4</note> But those twoe luxurious imps the one a professed fryer, the other a vowed priest, according to their newe reformation
<pb n="153" facs="362"/> teach it lawfull and laudable for preists not obstanding their vowes of chastitie, to chā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the state of chastitie in to the state of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage they being the first that gaue example of that sacrilegious action and leading the daunce them selues.</p>
   <p>Gerson complaines that Cathedrall Churches are made dennes of theeues, and consecrated monasteries markets &amp; Innes: But by the followers of Luther and Caluin, those holie cloysters are not onely made markets and Innes, but euen stables and hogstyes, &amp; Cathedrall Churches as it were common burses or exchanges for relation of newes and negotiations, in which mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fould iniustices and illicit contracts are plotted and accorded to the great profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the house of God ordained for onely prayer, seruice, and Sacrifyce, soe that if Gerson were now aliue doubtlesse he would rather taxe the pretended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers in this nature then those Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique profaners of his owne tymes.</p>
   <p>Gerson bids inquirie to be made if ther be not Apocryphall Scriptures, and prayers introduced in the Church to the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice of Christian faith, not meaning of anie Scriptures or prayers approued for Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, and pious by the authoritie of the Roman Church as are the bookes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chibies,
<pb n="154" facs="363"/> Sapience, Ecclesiasticus, Tobie, and Iudith and prayers to saints all which Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son him selfe did receiue for such but he onely reprehendes such false Scriptures or prayers as some newfangled priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons had published and inuented with out warrant or authoritie of the prelates and gouernors of the Church: But Luther Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin and their schollers peremptoriely reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and excluded out of the text and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of seripture the forosayde bookes and some others, as allsoe all manner of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to sainrs, euen those prayers and kookes of scripture which had ben most anciently approued and read in the seruice of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall Church at the least since the tyme of Innocēt the first Pope of that name, and soe vsed in the dayes of S. Augustin and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer since till the late dayes of Luther.</p>
   <p>And now by this breefe collation or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parision which I haue made the reader may plainely viewe the great difference ther is betweene the desired reformation of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and that of the pretended Innouators of our tymes, the one being almost quite opposite to the other: the one intending onely to redresse the Church in some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular accessorie defects, the other indeuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring violētly to destroye the whole frame and foundatiō of the visible Church and to
<pb n="155" facs="363"/> build a newe one: and finaly the one being a reformation either wholely or cheefly in the life and maners of some corrupted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons the other cheefly in faith &amp; doctrine and not regarding reformation of life but rather giuing more scope and libertie to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiousnesse then euer was heard of in the Christian world.</p>
   <p>And altho' Gerson doth insinuate the necessitie of reformation euen in matters of faith and religion, yet doth he not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane of the faith and teligion maintained approued and practized by the Roman Church, but he speaketh onely of the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of heretikes &amp; some abuses of other particular persons cropen into the exercise of the true religiō in which he desired refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to the end the state of the Church may remaine and cōtinue firme in her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer puritie without staine of erroneous doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine or corrupted manners. In all which he wished the slownesse of the prelates might be hastened by the power of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular authoritie of kings and Princes, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then lye vnamended, with danger of the Roman faith and preiudice to the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of soules. Which pious zeale of that renowned chanceler was highly to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended as farre different from the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the authors of our newe pretended
<pb n="156" facs="364"/> reformation who to acquire them selues a name of famous men vnder the colour of reforming the Church made a preye of the same with infinit losse of Christian soules and generall domage to virtue and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life.</p>
   <p>More ouer I am to aduertice the reader that in the citation of this author Sir Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey hath cōmirted twoe notable fraudes. The first is in that he reherses a great parte of his wordes as if he had founde them allogether &amp; in one continuated order or text, wheras the author hath them in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places &amp; to diuers purposes. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample Sir Humfrey ioyneth that which Gerson saith of remission of sinnes by so mainie <hi>Pater nosters,</hi> which he hath in his treatie of Indulgences, with that other pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage of preferring the particular obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of some countries before the lawe of God, which he hath not in the same place, but in an other treatise intituled <hi>de directio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne cordis.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Secondly I finde those wordes of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son which all or most of them being spoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by him onely of correction of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the kinght applyeth thē to matters of faith to persuade his reader that ther were corruptions in the Church euen in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith, and that the chancelor procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="157" facs="364"/> reformation of them. An exemple of this fraude you haue in the 650. page of the <hi>deuia,</hi> where the knight sayth Gersō wished at the least a restoring of the ancient faith of the Fathers tyme citing for this his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice intituled, <hi>de Coucilio Generali vnius obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiae,</hi> and quoting these wordes in the margin. <hi>Ecclesia sinon ad statum Christi &amp; Apostolorum Saltem ad statum Syluestri restitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda.</hi> Which wordes neuerthelesse Gerson speaketh not of matters of faith, but onely of the prouision and collation of benefices as both his whole discourse and especially his precedent wordes doe most clearely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate. Which are these. <hi>Sed longe aliter imprimatiua dolatione</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>donatione.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>distribuebantur bona ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia quam postmodum tempore praelatorum qui cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perunt paulatim refrigescere a sanctitate priorum tandem abusi sunt collationibus bene ficiorum &amp; ciusmodi administratione quod Papae ad se paula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim multa reuocauerunt vsque adeo quod fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliter datis occasionibus &amp; acceptis quas non est hic opus recitare quasi tota iurisdictio &amp; col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio talis paenes Papam &amp; eius curiam remane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</hi> And after theses wordes Gerson vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered those other at which Sir Humfrey cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched yet according to his inueterated cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome related not syncerily, which if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise he had truely reheharsed they would haue presently discouered the truth and
<pb n="158" facs="365"/> of what matter they were deliuered, for Gerson saith: <hi>vel redeundum esset ad statum Ecclesiae tempore syluestri &amp; Gregorij quando quilibet Praelatus dimittebatur in sua iurisdictione &amp; sollidudinis parte.</hi> nowe let the reader con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all these wordes of Gerson with the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Sir humfrey in the page aboue noted &amp; he will presently perceiue howe he hath corrupted thē both in tenor and sense, and how he hath foysted in the worde <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia</hi> wher it is not to be founde in the text of the author.</p>
   <p>As alsoe in the place taken out of Gersons in his consolatorie tract of rectifyind the hart, he transposeth and mangleth his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des leauing out the worde <hi>particular:</hi> and for the wordes <hi>in aliquibus religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus,</hi> translating, <hi>in manie conuents</hi> puting <hi>manie</hi> in steede of <hi>some.</hi> And where the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Gerson in an other place complaining of the imperfections and vices of the regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and secular Cleargie doth explicate him selfe not to meane of all but of some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular persons, Sir Humfrey guilefully omits his wordes which are these. <hi>Sed nunquid ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die omnes Domini &amp; Paelati in intedictis &amp; post dicendis culpabiles sunt malis? absit, reliquit enim Dominus sibi in Israell septem millia virorum quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum genua non sunt curuata ante Baal.</hi> and where the author speaking of disorders of
<pb n="159" facs="365"/> the monasteries of nunnes and fryres vseth the worde <hi>quasi</hi> to giue the reader aduertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that he speaketh not absolutely but onely by way of comparison: <note place="margin">
         <hi>In cōsolat.</hi>
      </note> the maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous knight leaues it out, as if it were not to the purpose, as he omits alsoe the worde <hi>nō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunqnam</hi> when the author speakes of the dāger which some tymes happeneth among the simple sorte by reason of the multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of such things as he ther mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</p>
   <p>In like manner in an other tract in wheras the Chancelor at the first making some doubt of the obtaining of a certaine Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence by saying soe manie <hi>Pater nosters</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an image of the Crucifix, yet afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des doth moderate his owne speeches soe that it plainely apppeares he doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the same, the fraudulent knight soe relateth the passage as if Gerson had not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely taxed that forme of indulgēce in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular but alsoe had absolutely renoūced the Romā doctrine touching the lawfullnes of Indulgēces in generall: his wordes are these <hi>Circa haec itaque &amp; similia multum caute pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedendum est &amp; prouidendum, ne opponatur fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma vel pertinax credulitas propter erroris pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum neque etiam oportet eiusmodi omnino &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinaciter dissentire, nec etiam penitus contemnere &amp; improbare, est igitur ambulandum in his via
<pb n="160" facs="366"/> media &amp;c.</hi> by which and other the like sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missiue &amp; temperate wordes which he hath afterwardes in the same place, the reader may see Gerson was as farre from being one of the newe reformers as is the spirit of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie frome the spirit of pride and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte, which is the onely guide of all those whoe reiect and impugne the Roman doctrine in all points of controuersie.</p>
   <p>Finally in those wordes cited by Sir Hū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey out of Gersons Apolotgeticall dialog, wheras the author speakes in the case of scisme when the true Pope was not certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely knowne, and cheefely of one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar point to wit of the condemnation of that proposition, <hi>a tyranne may be lawfully killed by priuate authoritie or by anie priuate man.</hi> the deceitfull knight soe applyes the wordes as if Gerson had generally dispared of the reformation of the Church, and the more easily to persuade his reader he omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes the wordes, <hi>hac tempestate</hi> and those <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus vt sunt manentibus.</hi> Gersons wordes truly rehearsed are these. <hi>video quod in doctrinis quae religionem, quae bonas &amp; salubres respiciunt mores, vix inuenietur in hac tempestate (rebus vt sunt manimentibus nec habito forti fauore po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae saecularis) terminatio debita vel expedita iustitia</hi> Which wordes if the reader compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res them with the wordes cited in English
<pb n="161" facs="366"/> by the knight he will easily spye more faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes then I haue noted. And then from hēce, and the rest which I haue produced tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the whole allegation of Gerson he will be able to iudge both of the false dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our aduersarie &amp; how smale reason he had to indeuore to make that famous and renowned Romanist one of the blind brothers of his inuisible Congregation. But now for conclusiō &amp; plainer intellectiō or vnderstanding of that which I haue said touching this author, the reader must take noticie that Gerson liued in a tyme of a great scisme rased by the erroneous electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of diuers Popes by diuers partes of the faction, by reason of which strife finding in his iudgement no other meanes to bring matters to a peaceable issue and attonemēt then by giuinge greater authoritie to a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell then to the Pope, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the power of a Councel before the authoritie of the Pope: which scisme alsoe was the true cause why he likewise seemed to dispare of the reformatiō of the Church, and therfore he labored to haue a generall Councell vnder one Pope by occasion of which desire he writ his treatie intituled <hi>De Cōcilio vnius obediētiae</hi> to deliberate the cōpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the Ecclesiasticall debate a and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal dissentiō all which is by himselfe clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely
<pb n="162" facs="367"/> deliuered in seuerall places of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and particularly in his Apolageticall dialog fol. 75. saying. <hi>hoc vnum scio quod ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus hahendae vnionis in scismate tam desperato tantique temporis, fecit multa tolerari quae fuis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent aliunde nec tolerabilia nec toleranda &amp;c.</hi> And now by this it is sufficiently cleare that Gerson is not for the new reformation of moderne sectaries in anie one pointe of doctrine or manners.</p>
   <p>In his citation of Cusanus lib. 3. concod. Cath. cap 16. the kinght hath in his owne page 378. 8. 9. of the by way notably cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted him, for he reheareses his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des without anie order, &amp; alsoe quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to his sense &amp; meaning as that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors owne wordes most euidently conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in his 17. chapter following, where he hath this plaine clause <hi>Ecce quod de pertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus ad religionem Imperator inter Episcopos iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicare non debet.</hi> Et in his 18. chapter he saith thus. <hi>Firmitas autem iudicij &amp; omnium quae ita aguntur in concilio per quoscunque ex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sensu tantum, synodica dependent authoritate. Quare etsi aliquando sententiasse iudices tales le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur, ex cousensu &amp; synodica commissione vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor sententiae dependebat, &amp; non ex imperiali cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missione, cuius authoritas synodum virilem non praecellit.</hi> Thus much Cusanus touching iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatiue authoritie in generall councels,
<pb n="163" facs="367"/> which as is plaine by these wordes doth not depend vpon the Emperor. It is true Cusanus grauntes (I knowne not how tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ely) that he fyndes the Emperor did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>praesidere</hi> that is preced or take the first place in the councels, but he doth not say (as Sir Humfrey feysteth in) <hi>primatum habuit, he had the primacie.</hi> But o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely graunteth the Emperor &amp; his Iudges with the senate, locall preheminence befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the Pope or at the most depending on the Pope, &amp; councell, as his whole discourse in diuers chapters of the booke cited by the kingth. manifestely declare.</p>
   <p>And cōcerning the cōgregation or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation of generall Councels, it is almost euident out of the precedent chapters of the same booke that this author graūtes no Primacie to the Emperor, but cheefely to the Pope. For altou' in the begining of the 13. chapter he hath these expresse wordes <hi>ex superioribus habetur Imperatores sanctos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationes synodales vniuersalis concilij totius Ecclesiae sēper fecisse.</hi> Yet presētly after expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caing him selfe better he saith. <hi>Breuiter dico quod ita se habet Imperator ad vniuersalē Ecclesiae Catholicae synodum, sicut Rex ad vniuersale Regni sui concilium, non quad coactiue sed cohor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue colligere debet.</hi> And yet more plainely presently after. <hi>Vigilare dehet Imperator &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei
<pb n="164" facs="368"/> &amp; pacis custos, &amp; Romani Pontificis primo synodi necessitatem insinuare, &amp; eius consensum congregandi concilij in definito loco requirere.</hi> By all which it doth manifestly appeare how shamelessely the kinght abuseth Cusanus, &amp; how smale reason he had to produce his testimonie for the Popes vsurpation (as he termeth it) both in calling &amp; assuming pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence of place &amp; dignitie, in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, supposing that author (as being Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of the Popes creation) soe professe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly maintaines his authoritie both in the resolutorie assembling &amp; cōfirming of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall synods.</p>
   <p>And if the reader desire greater satisfactiō concerning the doctrine of this author aboute the Popes authoritie in Councels, let him please to read his epistle to Rode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric, &amp; he will easily perceiue howe plainely he purgeth himself from all sinister impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in that nature: and that if perhaps in his immature age when he writ his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique concordance by reason of the great fame which he conceiued of the Councel of Basill, he inconsiderately vttered anie thing which might seeme to diminish the power of rhe Bishop of Rome in respect of a generall Councell: yet afterwardes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing that those whoe preferred the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Councels before the authoritie
<pb n="165" facs="368"/> of the cheefe Bishop &amp; pastor the Church proceeded soe farre as to attempt the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Antipope Foelix, against the true Pope Eugenius, then presently he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented him self that he had soe much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled their schismatticall syond, imitating in this both Cardinall Iulian &amp; Aeneas syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius, whoe both of them in the begining defended the Councell of Basill against Eugenius the true Pope, yet in the end re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting their action maintained most ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly his authoritie against t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e same sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. That which is sufficient to manifest the inconsideration, ignorance &amp; insyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie of Sir Humfrey in his production of this author whoe suppose he had deliuered his mynde lesse clearcly in one place &amp; occasion, yet did he amēd the same in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more exact worke of his owne hand &amp; industrie, &amp; of his owne accorde, how be it althou' our aduersarie takes him at the greatest aduantage he can, yet reightly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lierstanded &amp; alledged he doth not a iot aduantage his cause.</p>
   <p>In his citation of the Rhemes Testament in the annotation vpon the 6. of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle the Hebrewes v. 16. the knight rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth wordes in which the author of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes affirmes that God should be iniust if he rēdered not heauen for meritorious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,
<pb n="166" facs="369"/> But to make the matter more odious he craftely omittes the wordes of S. Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me there cited for proofe of the same lib. 2. contra Iouinianum cap. 2. saying that in deed great were Gods iniustice if he would onely punish sinnes and would not receiue good workes. And if that cōditionall of the Rhemists be not iustifyable, then may our aduersarie more iustely taxe, S. Augustin who lib. de nat, and Grat cap. 2. And lib. 4. contra Iulianum cap. 3. gaue then examples of that forme of speech. Saying in the first place▪ <hi>non est iniustus Deus qui instos fraudet mercede iustitiae,</hi> and in the second, <hi>per quod vera iustitia per hoc &amp; regnum Dei: Deus nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ipse, quod absit, erit iniustus, si ad eius reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num non admittitur iustus.</hi> Wherfore except Sir Humfrey will ioyne in his accusation those two renound ancient Fathers, he can not in reason accuse those learned doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</p>
   <p>Althou I conceiue it may seeme vnseaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to my present purpose distinctly to treate of anie matter of doctrine in this pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and occasion yet in regarde I haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely reflected that Sir Humfrey professes him selfe an enimie to implicit or vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed faith, therfore I esteemed conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the accomplishing of my worke, to
<pb n="167" facs="369"/> insert a compendious discourse touching that point.</p>
   <p>And to come to the purpose, I can not conceiue or inuente anie other motiue in our aduersaries for their soe obstinate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall of vnexpressed faith, except it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause euerie one of them confidently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumes to knowe the expresse contents of Scriptures as well as him who made them, yet on the contrarie I am assuredly persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that in reallitie a verie great parte (if not all their congregatiō) inioyes not this great extrauagant priuilege what soeuer they imagin, or conceiue of them selues. For altho' it is true that the illuminate bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers generally vse to brag they are <hi>docibiles Dei,</hi> and admit noe other schoolemaster in this matter then God almightie him selfe: yet is it certainely knowne that some of them be soe ignorant that they knowe not as much as their Abcedarie, or Christ crosse rowe. And now of these whoe can not read the Bible, I question our aduersaries thus, either these ignorants beleeue althings cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the whole scripture, or no? If they doe not, then they ar heretikes for refusing to beleeue the whole worde of God. If they doe beleeue all, and euerie particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scripture, then necessarily they must haue an implicit faith, in regarde
<pb n="168" facs="370"/> manie particular truethes be there inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded which they can not possibly knowe by reason they can neither haue them selues, nor receiue a perfect knowlege from anie other of euerie seuerall trueth therin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: and consequently, if anie faith they haue of those particular verities con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scripture which they knowe not, it is onely an implicit, vnexpressed, or implied faith supposing this consists in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing esse but a generall faith euen of those particulars of which the beleeuers haue no expresse knowledge, except onely in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine cōfuse or generall manner, or as they ar contained in other generall propositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or matters, which expressely and seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lally they know to be reueiled in the worde of God, and of which they haue an explicit, expresse, or disinuolued faith. For as he who eypressely graunteth, or assents to anie general Principle or proposition, for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that all Angels ar incorporall, or wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout bodies, or that all men ar reasonable creatures, doth by necessarie consequens assent implicitly to all the particulars there included, viz, that S. Michael S. Gabriel, and euerie other particular Angel is incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and that S. Peter, and Paule, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie other particular man is a reasonable creature altho' he neuer had anie particular
<pb n="169" facs="370"/> knowledge of them: Soe in the verie same manner those whoe with an expresse act of faith beleeue al the Church proposeth vnto them in that kynde, or all the scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teines: doe likewise necessarily beleeue with an implicit or tacit faith euerie seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall matter included in those general tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</p>
   <p>And this kynde of implicit faith, our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries must either graunt, or else neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarily confesse that euerie Mecanike hath as much knowlege in the Scripture as the most learned Minister, and euerie sheep as much as his pastor: which neuerthelesse euerie rude rustick is able to iudge for most absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and voyde of trueth. Soe thus we see that of the denyal of an implicit faith eyther the ignorant, and vnlearned sorte of people in the pretensiue reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches knowe as much in the Scripture as their greatest doctors: or that they ar plaine heretikes because they beleeue no more in the Bible but that onely which they expressely knowe.</p>
   <p>And the same I say with proportion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the learned sorte them selues, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade they seldome, or neuer ar soe conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant in Scriptures that they explessely kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we euerie seueral proposition, or particular truth conteined in the text, and consequē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly
<pb n="170" facs="371"/> euen they who ar the greatest Rabbies in their reformed flock, haue no explicit, or expresse faith consisting in an assent to all they expressely knowe in the text of scripture, but they must as well as theire brothers, be content with an implicit faith of those particulars they expressely knowe not, or else they ar to be accounted hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes for not beleeuing them, as I said before of the ruder sorte In respect of both which sortes of people I meane both the learned and vnlearned beleeuers in the pretensiue reformed Churches, this same argumēt may yet farther be vrged euen according to their owne receiued doctrine by which they cōfesse they haue not all their faith expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sely in the scriptures, but parte of it drawne by their owne consequences, or deductions from the text of scripture: of all which il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations or inferences of theirs it is manifest they could not possible haue anie other faith of them then implicit or vnexpressed, before they made them, in regare that those supposed verities or truethes which they soe deduce were not otherwise contained in the text or deliuered to the Church then in that inclusiue or hidden manner as it most apparent in regarde that if otherwise they had ben contained in the scripture that is clearely or expressely, then no illation or
<pb n="172" facs="371"/> deduction had ben necessarie for belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers for the bnowledge and establishing of their faith in those particulars, as both na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural reason, and euen common sense con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince: and consequently either the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue reformers had an implicit faith of all those obiects which they nowe confesse them selues to beleeue according to that deductiue manner, or else they had noe faith at all of them before they were dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: whence it farther followes that euer since they made their foresaid illations or consequences their faith is newe and quyte distinct from their owne faith in former tymes: the absurditie of which most neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie sequele I remit to the censure of the reasonable, and iudicious learned reader to determine.</p>
   <p>By occasion of this I desire the reader to take yet more cleare notice of the great per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uersitie of the proposterous Nouellists, who as they reueile their violēce in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the foresaid receiued doctrine of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit or inexpressed faith, soe likewise they ar no lesse peremptorie in defending their owne newe distinction of fundamental and not fundamental points in Religion, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to which their position they obstina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely maintaine the Church can erre in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith, that is in such points of faith
<pb n="173" facs="372"/> as in their conceite ar not foundamentall.</p>
   <p>But against the falsitie of this distinction I argue first vpon their owne supposed principle to wit that nothing is to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in matters of faith which is not founde in scripture either explicitly and clearely, or by cleare and certaine consequence wherfore this doctrinal distinctiō of theirs being a matter of faith and yet not founde in scripture in either of those two manners related, plaine it is that according to the pretended reformers doctrine, it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deserues faith nor credit. More ouer this distinction is soe newely coyned by our aduersaries and soe farre from hauing anie foundation either in scripture or anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent doctors that I neuer read anie mention of it in the first and cheefe establishers of the pretended reformatiō. Onely Chamier who is in deed a violent defender of Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme in his booke <hi>de natura Ecclesiae,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cap.</hi> 13. <hi>num.</hi> 11.</note> seemes plainely to suppose the same distinction in substance affirming that the Catholique Church can erre, <hi>licet non in fundamento salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis: tho' not in the foundation of saluation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Yet Chamier haueing writ his Panstratia but of late yeares either our English No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellists receiued it from him, or inuented it them selues not long before soe that the noueltie of it a lone were sufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince
<pb n="174" facs="372"/> it of vntrueth and vanitie. And altho' I might iustely take exceptions at the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it selfe for the newnesse of it according to the Apostles counsel to Timomothie to auoyde profane nouelties of wordes, in regarde the worde <hi>not fundamentals</hi> as it is applyed to matters of faith and thee errors of the Church ther in by our aduersaries, it is a kynde of profanation both of diuine faith it selfe which is truely fundamental in al respects, and also of the authoritie of the Church which likewise is infallible as much in one matter as an other: Neuerthelesse my cheefe intention is not to insiste in the reproofe of wordes (which I graunt may v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon occasion and for better declaration of a trueth, be inuented and vsed by the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches authoritie) but I onely stande vpon the sense or obiect of them, directely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinceing the matter signifyed by those wordes <hi>not fundamental in faith</hi> to be repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant both to scripture and, Fathers. That which I proue by a seconde argument of the same nature to wit because the scripture expressely teaches that <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>Ecclesia est</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>the Church is a pallar or firmament of truth.</hi> And our Sauior pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misseth his Father <hi>will giue to his Apostles</hi> (and their successors) <hi>an other Paraclete</hi> the spirit of trueth to remaine with them for euer, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 14. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 16.</note> which same diuine Spirit (as he
<pb n="173" facs="373"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="174" facs="373"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#oxf" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="175" facs="374"/> him selfe declares afterwardes in the 16. chapter will teache them all trueth, which vniuersal terme <hi>all,</hi> includes and signifyes both fundamental and not fundamental truethes, and consequently it expressely excludeth this vaine distinction of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellists. To which purpose S. Cyrill vpon the 10. chapter of the same Euangelist spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>akes most fittly and appositly saying, that althou' in this life we knowe onely in parte as S. Paule affirmes, <hi>non manca tamen sed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegra veritas in hac parua cognitione nobis reful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit: yet not a meamed or imperfect, but an intyre true faith shined vnto vs in this smale know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> And the place now cited out of the first to Tim. 3. is by all interpreters of scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture both ancient and moderne expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the firmenes and stabilitie which the Church hath by the assistance of the holie Goste in her deliuerie of true doctrine to her particular members, conformable to which sense Tertullian (to omit the rest for breuitie) in the 28. of his prescriptions hath a most fine sentence as it were in deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of those who teach the vniuersal or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Churche can erre in matters of faith. <hi>Could not</hi> (saith hee) <hi>the holie Goste haue respected her soe much as to haue induced her into all truth, he hauing ben sent by Christ to this ende hauing ben requyred by his Father to
<pb n="176" facs="374"/> be the Doctor of trueth, should villicus Christi vicarius the stewarde, the vicar of Christ haue ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected the office of God suffering the Churches in the meane tyme to vnderstande and beleeue other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise then he him selfe preached by the Apostles,</hi> Thus plainely, generally &amp; absolutely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Tertullian of the infallibilitie of the Catholique Churche in points of doctrine and faith.</p>
   <p>And nowe farther supposing that al these passages both of the scripture &amp; their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positors ar absolute, general, &amp; sans limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, it is most apparent they can admit no such distinction in their true sense &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, but that at the leaste the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Churche can not teache or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue anie error at all in such things as ar contained within the total obiect of faith in which ther can not possible be anie par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te or partial which is not fundamental by reason that all kinde of diuine faith is the verie foundation of Religion &amp; christian iustice according to the saying of S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin. <hi>Domus Dei fide fundatur, the house of God is founded in faith:</hi> &amp; if the foundation of the house of God were faultie, it would doubtlesse fall to ruine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to his owne promisse or affiirmation viz. That the gates of hell shal not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile against it.</p>
   <pb n="177" facs="375"/>
   <p>Neither is it auaileable for our aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to saye that the Church can not erre in the cheefe articles of her faith, as ar the Trinitie, the Incarnation of Christ, which ar fundamentals: but in such points as ar not fundamental, as ar the reall presence, iustification, the true quantitie, &amp; sense of Canonical scriptures, &amp; other such like matters in controuersie with vs &amp; them, the Church may teache erroneous &amp; false doctrine.</p>
   <p>For thir euasion I replie it is grounded not in inuincible, but in vincible &amp; grosse ignorance of the nature of true faith which being in it selfe one simple, or single entitie or essence as according to the doctrine of the Apostle, God &amp; Baptisme ar. <hi>Ʋna fides, vnum Baptisma, vnus Deus;</hi> how different soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer its obiect be, it is euer essentially one &amp; the same in it selfe cleare from distinction, &amp; cleare from error, the cōtrarie to which neuerthelesse should necessarily be true if ei-faith were diuided in to fundamental &amp; not fundamental faith, &amp; the Church could erre in her propositiō of the one &amp; not of the other. And to this I adde that one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of the true Church is holines: but now what sanctitie, integritie, or holines can possible be in the Church if it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with errors in faith of what nature soe
<pb n="178" facs="375"/> euer they bee. For as the scripture affiir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, <hi>sine fide</hi> (that is true, pure, &amp; intyre faith) <hi>impossibile est placere Deo.</hi> True faith is the forme, fashiō, &amp; beautie of the Church which is the immaculate sponse of Christ' not hauing spot or wrincle. In soe much that if she be defaced thus with errors she can not possible be the sponse of Christ as in the cided place, &amp; like wise in the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles she is described, all faire, or comely, but rather she would be like a leaper, or most deformed creature.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, I confesse for my parte I could neuer perfectly vnderstand what the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellists truely meane by fundamental &amp; not fundamental points, by reason I finde the matter in none of their workes suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently explicated, &amp; I veriely cōceiue they purposely anoyde the declaration of it, to the ende the absurditie may lesse appeare. Neuerthelesse it seemes in probabilitie that by fundamentals they meane all those points which according to their owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position ar contained in scriptures, &amp; the three creedes. And by not fundamentals the points of controuersie betwixt vs &amp; thē: as is the number of Canonical bookes, the infallible rule of interpretation of scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, the real presence, transsubstantiation, iustification' &amp;c.</p>
   <pb n="179" facs="376"/>
   <p>This beīg supposed I argue thus. Either those points which our aduersaries call not fundamentals, ar matters of faith' &amp; to be beleeued by all sortes of Christians accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the diuersitie of their tenets, vnder paine of damnation, or not to be beleeued. If they ar thus necessarily to be beleeued by faith, then doubtelesse they ar included in those truthes touching which, (as I haue declared &amp; cōfirmed before by both scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures &amp; Fathers) Christ promised to his Church the assistance of the diuine Sprit to remaine with it eternally that is till the consummation of the worlde, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Church can not committe anie error in proposing them to the people as being no lesse fundamental in that respect then anie of the rest of the articles of faith.</p>
   <p>But if our aduersaries on the contrarie denye them to be necessarily beleeued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of losse of Saluatiō, &amp; hould thē onely as matters of indifferencie, &amp; such as may either be beleeued or not be beleeued without preiudice of faith: or māners vpon this supposition I graunte the Church may erre in proposing thē to her flock, but yet in this case that parte of our aduersaries di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctiō affirming that the Church can erre in not fūdamētal matters of faith is still fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se and impertinēt in regarde those particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars
<pb n="180" facs="376"/> aboue telated in which they teache the Church can erre, ar soe farre from being either fundamentals or not fundamentals in matter of faith, that according to the former supposition they ar not either one way or other with in the circuit of faith: and consequently that parte or member of our aduersaries dinstinction viz that the Church can erre in not fundamentals is both false, nugatorie, and impertinent in which sense soeuer they intend to maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne it.</p>
   <p>Fourtly I proue directly that the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiues euen of those particulars contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted betwixt vs and the professors of the English Religion, ar fundamental points of faith, and by consequence that if the Church can erre in them that parte of their new distinction is false according to which they auerre the Church can not erre in fundamental points of Religion: which I conuince in this forme of argument.</p>
   <p>That distinction is false and absurde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which it necessarily followes that the Church can erre in matters the true faith of which is necessarie to salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
   <p>But according to the distinction of fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental, and not fundamental matters
<pb n="181" facs="377"/> of faith it necessarily followes the Church can erre in matters necessarie to saluation.</p>
   <p>Ergo The distinction of fundamental, and not fundamental matters of faith, is a false and absurde distinction.</p>
   <p>The minor in which the total difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie consists, I proue because according to this distinction, the Church may erre in these propositions. The Church hath the true complete Canon of scripture, The Church hath the true interpretation and sense of scripture. Christs bodie and bloud ar truely, really, substantially, and not by onely faith contained in the sacred Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist &amp;c. And yet the faith of these either af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiuely or negatiuely, is necessarie to saluatiō, as the aduersaries thē selues if they will not be occounted obstinate in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter soe cleare and manifest, can not denye. Therfore it is hence concluded by forcible sequele that their distinction of fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, and not fundamentals in matters of faith is false and absurde.</p>
   <p>Fiftely, I reason in this manner against the same distinction. If the infallibilitie of the Churches authoritie consistes in fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental points of Religion onely, and not in all that the true Church shal at anie tyme declare vnto her members concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their faith and Religion, then were
<pb n="182" facs="377"/> not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e prouidence of Christ perfect to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his sponse, but more defectiue then God was towardes the synagog of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, neither were this anie other then to imagine that Christ in deede did laye a sounde foundation for his Church, but lefte walles and roofe exposed to be deiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or caste to grounde with euerie puffe of winde which how repugnant to reason &amp; his owne inuiolable promisse this is, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may easily consider, and censure.</p>
   <p>Sixtly, I argue yet more positiuely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the distinction related because, our aduersaries frame it either in respect of the greater, or lesser dignitie of the obiects of fundamental and not fundamētal points of faith in them selues, or in respect of the greater or lesse necessitie of them to sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation by reason of the necessitie of faith which the members of the true Church haue of them all and euerie one in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, Now if we respect onely the material obiects in them selues, and the necessitie of them to saluation precisely, soe I confesse ther ar some particular matters of faith which much surpasse orhers, and in that respect alsoe the one may not vnaptely be termed fundamental in comparision of the rest which haue not that preheminencie. For example that ther is a God, and that
<pb n="183" facs="378"/> God is a rewarder of workes quod <hi>Deus est, &amp; remunerator sit.</hi> That he is one in three persons, that the second person in Trinitie became incarnate or tooke humaine nature vpon him, was borne of the Virgin Marie, suffered death for our dedemption &amp;c. are matters both more noble and dignifiable in them selues, then those: Christ fasted fortie dayes, and fortie nights, an Angel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to him in his agonie, Peter denyed Christ, and other such like truthes, Yet this how true soeuer it bee, it is nothing to the purpose which here we treate, nor afordeth anie grounde or foundation for the preno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated distinction of our aduersaries, in regarde that althou' ther be neuer soe great difference among those and other points of Religion in the dignitie of the material ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, by reason of which in some sorte the one may be named fundamental, the other not fundamental: neuerthelesse because the faith of the one is no lesse necessarie to saluatiō then the faith of the other, thēce it is that absolutely the one is as much funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental as the other and consequently ther ar no not fundamentals in matters of faith as the distinction of out aduersaries doth falsely suppose.</p>
   <p>And hence in like manner it farther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sueth, that if the Church should erre but
<pb n="184" facs="378"/> onely in the definitiō, or proposition euen of those matters of lesse qualitie, the error would be directly against diuine faith, and consequently the Church in this case should truely be said to haue erred eued in funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental points of faith, and in matters ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie to saluation, fundamental points, as I haue declared and often repeated, being no other then all those reuailed truethes the faith of which is necessarie in the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church for the obtaining of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life, not obstanding anie difference which otherwise may apppeare in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the seueral obiects or matters, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing no one parte but the whole intyre faith of Christ and euerie parte and partiall of those verities which he hath reuailed to his Church, is the foundation of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, and Catholique Religion, it being as necessarie to saluation for euerie true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian to beleeue truely and syncerely if it be proposed vnto him by the Church that the cocke crowed at the tyme of S Peters denyal of Christ, or that a soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier lanced our sauiors side with a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are, as that he dyed vpon the Crosse for our redemption, and risse againe for our iustification.</p>
   <p>But Finally, If peraduēture our aduersaries should say that within the compasse of true
<pb n="185" facs="379"/> faith some things be necessarie to saluation and others not necessarie, and that conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently some things be fundamental, but others not.</p>
   <p>To this instance I replye, it is founded in a manifest equiuocation. For althou' it is true that their be some, things within the compasse of saith which ar not necessarie for euerie member of the Church to kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we them expressely, yet is it necessarie to saluation for euerie faithfull Christian thou' neuer soe simple or ignorant, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue euerie parte and partiall of those ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects or matters which God hath reuailed, if for such by the Church they be proposed vnto him, otherwise he should incurre the censure of that strict and fearefull sentence of the most iuste and equal iudge Christ our Sauior, <hi>qui vero non crediderit condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur:</hi> and soe the faith euen of all those things which euerie one by reason of his state or condition of life, or for want of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding is not obledged to knowe, is necessarie to saluation, and consequently all kinde of faith of what matter soeuer it be that God hath reuailed, is as much fūda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mētall as is faith of the greatest matter or mysterie of the whole Christiā beleefe: whē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce it is that as S. Gregorie Nazianzen trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the vnitie and integritie of faith in
<pb n="186" facs="379"/> his 39. oratiō aboute the ende declareth by example or similitude that faith is like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a goulden chaine connected and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of diuers linkes, from which if you take anie one away, you loose your saluation as S. Ambrose in the ende of hir sixt kooke vpon the Euangell of S. Luke declares. By which it is manifeste that faith of euerie point or matter within the compasse of faith, is necessarie to saluation and therfore fundamental absolutely, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the obiect be great or little, and no faith not fundamētal, as the new distinction of the Nouellists most falsely affirmes: which ther distinction doubtnesse was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by them to the ende they might ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a more plausible coulor to accuse the Roman Church of errors comitted in faith, (as alsoe for excuse of ther owne) their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and irreligion being so great that like vnconscionable taylers they chose rather to cutte out a Church for Christ of such cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted stuffe as this, then to liue or dye vnreuenged of the Catholique Roman Church.</p>
   <p>And for conclusion I adde that since I haue made manifest by these my reasons that the faith euen of those points of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which our aduersaries terme not fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental, is absolutely required to the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation
<pb n="187" facs="380"/> of euerie Christian soule, if euen in rhese particulars onely the Church could erre, none could assuredly be persuaded that by makeing them selues members of it, they ar in the certaine &amp; infallible way to the obteining of eternal blessednes, but still should remaine in the like dangerous &amp; desperate state they did before they were in the Church of Christ, &amp; cōsequently by reason of this vncertaintie &amp; perill a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall neglect of procuring to enter in to the true Church of Christ would be caused in the mindes of men, which inconuenience in regarde it proceedes by inauoiable cōse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence from this distinction broached &amp; vsed by our aduersaries, it plainely appee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res the doctrine of it is in diuers respect most pernicious &amp; damnable as not ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in anie sorte to the reformatiō of the Church, as is by them pretended, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectely to the ruine &amp; destruction of it.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deuia. sec.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 45.</note>
   </p>
   <p>S. Augustin in the 23. chap. of the 13. boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of his cōfessions affirming that spiritual men must not iudge of the scripture, is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by Sir Hūfrey, for he meaneth not that spiritual men must not in anie case iudge of the true sense of scripture for that were both false, yea &amp; repugnant to the doctrine &amp; practise euen of the pretensiue reformers them selues who as they can
<pb n="188" facs="380"/> not denye, whether they be spiritual or not spirituall vse to read &amp; interpret scriptures much more comonly then the Romanists doe: yea &amp; giue libertie therin euen to those of the feminine sexe or gender. But the true &amp; obuious sense of that diuine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor in the cited place onely is, that spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual men must not iudge anie thing contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the scripture (as presently he subioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) <hi>non rite veraciterque dictum esse,</hi> that is, <hi>not to be ritely &amp; truelly spoken,</hi> but submit their vnderstanding, <hi>etiamsi quid ibi non lucet</hi> altou' some thing be not cleare, or perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous in it. This is the pure &amp; syncere sense of S. Augustin as his verie wordes declare, And nowe let the impartial reader decide whether it doth not rather militate or warre against the manner of dealing with scriptures which the Nouelists practise, then againsts the Romanists: how be it I synce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely confesse it directly makes neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the one nor the other, but precisely against such as iudge those passages of scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture to be false, or not ritely deliuered, which they ar not able to vnderstand. <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituales ergo siue qui presunt, siue qui obtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, spiritualiter iudicant: non de spiritualibus cogitationibus quae latent in firmamento. Non enim oportet de sublimi authoritate iudicare, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que etiam de ipso libro tuo: etiam si quid ibi non
<pb n="189" facs="381"/> lucet quoniam submittimus ei nostrum intellectū: certumque habemus etiam quod clausum est as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectibus nostris recte veraciterque dictum esse. Sic enim homo licet iam spiritualis' &amp; renouatus in agnitionem Dei secundum imaginem eius qui cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auit eum, factor tamen legis debet esse, non index.</hi> These ar the wordes of S. Augustin synce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely rehearsed in which as anie vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of latin may easily perceiue, ther is nothing founde in fauor of Sir Humfreys tenet in the place aboue cited, viz that scripiure is the sole iudge of controuersies &amp; interpreter of it selfe: but rather is ther some thing expressely repugnant to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther position of his congregation defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that scriptures ar easie to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standed or interpreted onely by conferring one place with an other, the contrarie of which neuertelesse, is plainely insinuated by those wordes of S. Augustin, <hi>certumque habemus etiam quod clausum est aspectibus nostris &amp;c. And we ar eertaine euen that which is shutte from our eyes, is ritely &amp; truely spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi> And yet our corrupt aduersarie hath corruptedly interrupted them conioyning the first parte to the last &amp; omitting the verie harte of the sentence, &amp; for the latin wordes <hi>spiritualibus cogitationibus,</hi> putting in English, spiritual knowledge, for <hi>spiritual cogitateons:</hi> like wise inserting by a parente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis
<pb n="190" facs="381"/> this his owne glosse vpon the worde <hi>firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> expounding it of the scriptures them selues I knowe not by what other rule or authorite then by the dictamen of his owne priuate or familiar spirit: all which particulars I remit to the censure of the iudicious reader.</p>
   <p>And by occasion of this passage I aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise the reader that wheras the author for the greater credit of his worke, &amp; as it were to limme it with the authoritie of that aureous Doctor S. Augustin hath cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him in his by-way alone, at the leaste 60. seueral tymes: yet hauing diligently viewed and discussed the places as they stā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in the tomes, I indoubtedly assure him that of those 60 sentences there ar not 6. to the purpose for which they ar alledged, and yet those 6. either such as partely by diuers Romanists in their seueral worke, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely by my selfe in this my censure, haue sundrie tyme receiued their anser: the rest of the total number being some of quyte impertinent others neither for our aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie nor against the Romanists, others plainely against him, and for the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists: especially those which proue the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent and conspicuous visitabilitie of the Catholique Church; others finally ar not syncerily rehearsed, but mangled, cropt, or
<pb n="191" facs="382"/> curtald with abuse of the author and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
   <p>S. Chrisostome like wise, and S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose haue their meaning detorted by the knight in the same section the one in his 13. homilie vpon Genesis, in his 7. homilie v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the first epistle to the Thesalonians: the other in his 8. sermon vpon the 118. psal. for. S. Chrisostome onely treates in those places of twoe particular cases, to wit in the Genesis he argueth against some whoe denyed the terrestriall Paradise, and vpon the foresaid Epistle of saint Paule, he reprehendes some others who were of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niō that the soule is a particle of the diuine nature. And touching these two particular points S. Chrysostome affirmes that the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred scripture expondes it selfe, and suffers not the reader to erre, but he said not that the scripture in all other places and in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters doth soe interpret it selfe as Sir Humfrey falsely alledgeth.</p>
   <p>Now S. Ambrose saying that the dore shall be opened vnto him who diligētly examēs the difficult and obscure passages of scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by no other but by the worde of God, he doth not there meane by the worde of God the scriptures them selues, but the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine word that is Christ our sauior the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond person in Trinitie, and therfore he
<pb n="192" facs="382"/> addes to the wordes cited by Sir Humfrey. <hi>de quo legisti in Apocalipsi quod Agnus librum signatam aperuit,</hi> of which thou haest read in the Apocalips. that the lambe opened the sealed booke, which laste wordes of S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose because the knight perceiued that by their plaine explication of the former, they discouered the whole sentence to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for his purpose, he deceitfull smun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and left them vnrehearsed by which his palpable and grosse abuse of these two graue and ancient authors doth euidently appeare.</p>
   <p>An much according to this fashion he proceeds with Pope Clement whome he ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in the same place, and for the same pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. Whoe neuerthelesse is soe repugnant to the tenet of the nouellists in making the sole scripture interpreter of it selfe in all cases, that he expressely teaches that we must not according to our owne sense but, <hi>secundum traditionem patris,</hi> according to the tradition of the Father, that is either accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the tradition of the Pope him selfe as deliuerer of the sense of scriptures vnto vs, or <hi>secundum traditionem Patris,</hi> that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tradition of the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: and therfore he addes afterwardes. <hi>&amp; ideo oportet ab eo intelligentiam discere scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam qui eum a maioribus secundum veritatem<pb n="193" facs="383"/> sibi traditam reseruauit vt ipse possit ea quae recte suscepit cempetenter asserere.</hi> That is, And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought to learne the intelligence or vnderstanding of scriptures of him whoe reserued it to him selfe according to the trueth deliuered vnto him by his ancetors to the end he might cōpetently assert tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se things which he ritely receiued.</p>
   <p>But Sir Humfrey conceiled these wordes, as alsoe the greater parte of the period out of which he cited those wordes he alledges, yet ioined vnto them the rest of those which he rehearseth, not obstanding they ar parte of an other clause, alsoe adding the worde <hi>seeing</hi> which neither is in the authors text, nor agrees with his sense and meaning, which is not that the scripture alone is an intyre and firme rule of faith, but the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture expounded according to the sense re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from the ancients, as immediately before he affirmed. But vaine Sir Humfrey was soe desirous to seeme to his reader to haue a Pope for an a better of his position, that he chused rather to prostitute his owne honestie in the euill vse he made of his authoritie, then seeme to wāt the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minie of soe renowned a personage. And yet is the knight soe farre from obtaining his purpose, that if the wordes were not soe manie that they can not with conueniencie
<pb n="194" facs="383"/> be intyrely related, they them selues would make it apparent how much the author of them is abused by the false relater. The supplye of which I remit to the more diligent reader as tyme &amp; leasure shall giue him occasion.</p>
   <p>But I confesse now I am quite tired with the examen of my aduersaries misal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged testimonies of the authors he produces in fauor of his misremormed doctrine and must needs draw my selfe to a conclusion of my labors, hoping I need not doubte but by these fewe passages the reader will easily persuade him selfe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the rest they ar all of the same nature and soe be satisfyed with that implicit or general knowledge he will haue of them by this meanes, and his owne discourse, althou perhaps by his owne industrie and inquisitiō he is not able in particular to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the fraudes and come to the true sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se and menning of thē in anie more expresse and declared manner. Yet if my aduersarie him selfe will not be satisfyed with this compendious course I haue vsed, but will farther require an cxacte anser to euerie particular allegation, vpon condition he will first iustifye his proceeding in these I haue shewed defectiue, I promisse with Gods
<pb n="195" facs="384"/> assistance I will be readie both to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine soe much as I haue alreadie done and said, and alsoe to proceed farther in my view and censure of those places which as yet I haue not touched if God be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to giue me health and opportunitie of bookes, these being rhe greatest difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties I haue had im the performance of the worke.</p>
   <p>To omit the printe which is well knowne what a trouble in is vnto tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se of our Religion and nation, and how great an aduātange our aduersaries ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of vs in these particulars, some of vs being forced to passe the seaes for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie smale matter we haue to publish, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sydes the perill of importing the bookes into the countrie, which is subiect to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munerable casualities and daungers of molestation for the same as experience doth testifye, God almightie amend it and restrore vs to our ancient Catholique liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Religion.</p>
   <p>And to returne to thee proceeding of my aduersarie I say for a man some tymes inculpably to erre, or mystake ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in wordes or sense especially in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate matters, I doe not admire it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dare I iustifye my selfe in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="196" facs="384"/> (I let passe the faultes of the printer to which euerie one is subiect) but that one should erre soe frequently and gros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sely as Sir Humfrey hath erred in his ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of all sortes of authors both an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and moderne in the whole discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se of his two bookes, and yet neuer in fauor of his aduersaries, but euer in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of his owne cause, this I say is no way excusable, and in my opinion it is such a fortune as chanceth to no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture excepting him selfe, or some of his illuminate brothers.</p>
   <p>That which I soe much the more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and deplore in regarde he hath not onely suffered his owne proper iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be insotted with such inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate delusions but likewise, as I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by reporte of others, hath by the same prestigious sleightes deliuered his owne nearest and dearest freind his inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous ladie, whose otherwise well dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed and once Catholike iudgement, if yet he had conuinced by syncere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and honest vse of scriptures. Fathers, and other writers, it had ben lesse intolerable, but to winne her with such false wares as these, is an action no way iustifiable either before God or men.</p>
   <pb n="197" facs="385"/>
   <p>And if I might be admitted to your Counsell Sir Humfrey, I would aduise you to cease writing bookes in this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is neither your profession neither as I conceiue, and am informed, ar you able to performe anie such wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke without the assistance of tutors which must of necessitie be chargeable vnto you. A dozen or sixteene of the Puritan Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strie will quickely make a greate hole in an ordinarie knights estate, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if they be assembled in such a place as the wine office, which as the verie soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the worde denotes, necessarily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes much good fellowship and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently great expense. Beware of that black garde, they will haunte your house li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke so maine ill spirits, not so much by night as by day: they ar meridian spirits, they assaulte most in the midest of the leight, therby to dasle mens eyes more easily, aboute dinner tyme you shal be sure to haue them most busie aboute you.</p>
   <p>For as a conceited Protestant reportes. <hi>Where the meat is best ther a Puritan confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes most, for</hi> (saith hee) <hi>his arguing is but the efficacie of his eating, and the Pope he best concludes against in plum broth.</hi> This consell proceedes from a freind, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="198" facs="385"/> if you please to make vse of it, the profit will be your owne, the thankes due to mee. This is now the third anser your first booke hath receiued by men of three seueral professions, by a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, a preist, an a clerke, <hi>triplex fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis difficile rumpitur</hi> which cordes I hope will tye your iudgement with in the boundes of reason. Fare you well Sir Humfrey in Christ our Sauior, and receiue this as from him who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires nothing more then your moste happie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, &amp; sempi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>