<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the most excellent and moste vertuous ladye our moste gracious Soueraigne, Marie by the grace of God Quene of Eng∣lande, Fraunce, Naples, Hierusalem and Irelande, Defedour of the faith, princesse of Spaygne &amp; Sicilie, Arche∣duchesse of Austria, Duchesse of Mil∣laine, Burgundie and Braband, Coū∣tesse of Haspurge, Flaunders &amp; y∣ole, your Maesties moste faythfull, louynge, and obedient subiecte Iohn Proctor, wissheth all grace, loge peace, quiet raygne, from God the father, the sonne, and the holy Ghost.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1554</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101196_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10150</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20407</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101196</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the most excellent and moste vertuous ladye our moste gracious Soueraigne, Marie by the grace of God Quene of Eng∣lande, Fraunce, Naples, Hierusalem and Irelande, Defedour of the faith, princesse of Spaygne &amp; Sicilie, Arche∣duchesse of Austria, Duchesse of Mil∣laine, Burgundie and Braband, Coū∣tesse of Haspurge, Flaunders &amp; y∣ole, your Maesties moste faythfull, louynge, and obedient subiecte Iohn Proctor, wissheth all grace, loge peace, quiet raygne, from God the father, the sonne, and the holy Ghost.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of wyates rebellion : with the order and maner of resisting the same, wherunto in the ende is added an earnest conference with the degenerate and sedicious rebelles for the serche of the cause of their daily disorder. Made and compyled by John Proctor</title>
                 <author>Proctor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Caly, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1554</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 17 leaves, pages 18-25, leaves 26-96, 6 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the most excellent and moste vertuous ladye our moste gracious Soueraigne, Marie by the grace of God Quene of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, Fraunce, Naples, Hierusalem and Irelande, Defe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dour of the faith, princesse of Spaygne &amp; Sicilie, Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duchesse of Austria, Duchesse of Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, Burgundie and Braband, Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesse of Haspurge, Flaunders &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ole, your Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esties moste faythfull, louynge, and obedient subiecte Iohn Proctor, wissheth all grace, lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ge peace, quiet raygne, from God the father, the sonne, and the holy Ghost.</head>
   <p>IT HATH been alowed, most gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious soueraigne, for a necessary po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie in all ages, as stories do wytnes, that the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicious enterprises of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed,
<pb facs="3"/>
whiche haue at any tyme attēpted with trayterous force to subuert or alter the publike state of their countries, as also the wise and vertuous policies of the good, practised to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue the common weale, and to repell the enemies of the same, shuld by writing be committed to eternal memorye: partly that they of that age in whose tyme such thinges happened, mought by the oft reading conceiue a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine gladnes in consideryng with them selues, &amp; beholding as it were in a glasse, frō what calamitie and extreme ruine, by what policie &amp; wisedome their natiue coūtries were deliuered, besides the great misery &amp; peril they them selues haue escaped: partly for a doctrine and a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition
<pb facs="3"/>
seruing bothe for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent &amp; future tyme: but cheifly and principally that the tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours themselues, who through hatred to their prince or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey shall either of their owne malicious disposition be stirred, or els by other peruerse counsel therunto induced, may alwaies haue before their eyes the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ende that happeneth as iust reward to al suche caytiues as either of ambition not satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with their owne state wyll seke prepostorously to aspire to honoure, or of malice to their prince wyll entre into that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible crime of preuie conspiracie or opē rebelliō. The industrie of writers doth sufficiētly declare in a numbre of stories that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracie &amp; treason hath alwayes
<pb facs="4"/>
turned to the authours a wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched &amp; miserable ende, &amp; if their persones happen at any tyme to escape temporal punishm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt, as rarely they haue done, yet their names, spicially of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> notorious &amp; principal offenders, haue ben al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies had in suche vile &amp; odible detestation in all ages &amp; among all nations, as for the same thei haue been euer after abhorred of all good men. These general considerations mouing other to indict and penne stories, moued me also to gather together and to regester for memorie the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueilous practise of Wyat his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable rebelliō, litle inferior to the most daūgerous reported in any historie, either for desperate courage in the authour, or for the mōstruous end purposed by his rebellion. Yet I thought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng
<pb facs="4"/>
lesse at the begining, then to publishe the same at this time or at this age, minding onely to gather notes therof where the truth mought be best knowen, (for the which I made earnest and diligent inuestigation) and to leaue them to be published by others hereafter to the behof of our posteritie. But hearing the sundry tales thereof farre disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naūt in the vtteraunce, &amp; many of them as far wide frō truth, facioned from the speakers to aduaunce or depraue as they fantased the parties: and vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stādyng besydes what notable infamie spronge of this rebelliō to the whole countre of Kent, &amp; to euery mēbre of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, where sundrie &amp; many of them to mine owne knowledge shewed them
<pb facs="5"/>
selues most faythfull &amp; worthy subiectes, as by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> storie self shal euidently appeare, which either of hast or of purpose were omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a printed booke late sette furth at Cāterbury: I thought these to be speciall cōsideratiōs, wherby I ought of duetie to my countrey to compyle and digest suche notes as I had gathered cōcerning that rebellion, in some forme and fashion of historie, &amp; to publishe the same in this age and at this present, contrary to my first intent, as well that the very truth of that rebellious en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terprise mought be throughly knowen, as that also the sheire where that vile rebellion was practised, might by opening the full truth in some parte be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered frō the infamy whiche as
<pb facs="5"/>
by report I heare is made so ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral in other shyres, as though very fewe of Kent were free frō Wyates conspiracie: most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie beseching your highnes to take this my traueil in so good and gracious parte, as of your graces benigne &amp; gentle nature it hath pleased you to accept my former bookes dedicated vnto your highnes. Wherby I mynde nothinglesse then to excuse or ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuse any affectionately, but to set furth eche mannes doynges truely according to their deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, that by the cōtemplation hereof both the good may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in the execution of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite obedience &amp; vnspotted loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the wicked restrained from the hatefull practice of suche detestable purposes.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>