<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfull Doctors and profes∣sors of Phisicke of the Colledge in London, authorized by ancient Charter: and the rest of the Doctors, professors and Students of the same learned facultie, either resident in the Vniuersities of Cambridge and Oxford: Or else∣where dispersiuely placed, and authorized in any cities or townes through this Realme of England: Encrease of knowledge, and prosperous successe in your seuerall affaires and cures, to the glory of God, good of his people, and aduancement of your profession.</title>
           <author>Russel, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101643_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11188</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21455</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101643</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfull Doctors and profes∣sors of Phisicke of the Colledge in London, authorized by ancient Charter: and the rest of the Doctors, professors and Students of the same learned facultie, either resident in the Vniuersities of Cambridge and Oxford: Or else∣where dispersiuely placed, and authorized in any cities or townes through this Realme of England: Encrease of knowledge, and prosperous successe in your seuerall affaires and cures, to the glory of God, good of his people, and aduancement of your profession.</title>
                 <author>Russel, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Diacatholicon aureum: or a generall power of gold : purging all offensiue humours in mans bodie: good in generall for all diseases, where there needeth any purgation: as also for any sicknesse yearely incident, or which is feared to approach by the increase of any euill humor, distemperature of diet, or otherwise how so euer growing towards any disease, to preuent the same, and keepe the bodie in health. It may lately be taken of all maner of people, of what age so euer, sucking children, old men and women, in the quantitie of two, three, or foure graines, according to the age, strength, and disease of the partie. Whosoeuer stand in neede of this powder, may haue it at the signe of the Hand and Pistall, neere vnto Iuic Bridge, for two shillings sixe pence the graine</title>
                 <author>Russel, Thomas, an empiric</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 <publisher>Flasket, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right worshipfull Doctors and profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors of Phisicke of the Colledge in London, authorized by <hi>ancient Charter: and the rest of the Doctors, professors and</hi> Students of the same learned facultie, either resident in the Vniuersities of <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford:</hi> Or else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where dispersiuely placed, and authorized in <hi>any cities or townes through this Realme of</hi> England: <hi>Encrease of knowledge, and prosperous successe in your seuerall affaires and cures, to the glory of God, good of his people, and aduancement of your profession.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very Art and facultie (Right worshipfull Doctors, professors and Students in the necessary and honourable facultie of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke) whose foundation is not layd on demonstration, but onely on probable and phisicall coniectures, is in it selfe so hidden and intricate, that euen about the principles, elements and grounds thereof, there are diuers and almost contrary opinions: from whence in euery such facultie spring vp diuers heads of sects, which in time infinitely multiplie, and as this proposition we see by experience true in all generalities, so in this facultie of Phisicke it is dayly verified. Hence in Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens time (as he witnesseth in his booke <hi>Desectis</hi>) there were three sorts of Phisicians: the first which were called <hi>Emperici</hi> and <hi>Memores:</hi> the second, <hi>Dogmatici</hi> and <hi>Rationales:</hi> the third, <hi>Methodici</hi> and <hi>Abbreuiatores:</hi> to these three, this age hath added a fourth, called <hi>Paracelsians,</hi> but they themselues would be called the ancient Phisicians, the true Philosophers, the Chimists, and the Spagerists, to set downe the groundes of either of their professions, the opinions on either sides: their arguments to maintaine those opinions, would be to enter into a large fielde of discourse, which at this time is not mine intent to doe, left I might say with the Poet, <hi>Ante diem clauso componet vesper Olympo:</hi> this only hath here moued me to mention them, thus to shew
<pb facs="3"/>
mine opinion of them in briefe, that whereas some doe attribute so much to distillations and preparations of Minerals, Animales, and Vegetables, that they firmely hold both the parts of Phisicke as well <hi>Hygeinen</hi> as <hi>Thera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peyticen</hi> to bee completely perfourmed onely by them, and others so much wilfully bent or ignorantly seduced against the true intended perfection of Phisicke, doe contrarily hold, that it is onely desperate and dangerous Phisicke which is attempted by minerals, prepared by the Spagiricall arte, and that it had bene farre better, that it had slept in silence and neuer bene knowen to the world. Betwixt these two extremes I thinke it best to hold a meane, so that I neither allow the extremitie of the one, nor imbrace the defects of the other: but mine opinion is, that both the sorts of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinable preparation of simples, as well that which is done by the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries craft, as also by the Spagiricall art, I say, both of them haue their proper place and necessary vses in Phisick, <hi>(amicus Plato, amicus Aristoteles, sed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis amica veritas)</hi> so that I iudge this latter age of the world much bound to the careful searchers out of those hiddē secrets of nature, which are so bound vp in minerals and vegetables, and outwardly do not appeare but by extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and magisterie, and great folly it were vtterly to reiect them as many wilfully doe. Let them but attentiuely reade <hi>Hippocrates</hi> booke <hi>De arte,</hi> and see how he there deciphereth out a wise man, and a mad malicious foole, the wisedome of the one consisting in the finding out in arts, those things which are not yet found out, and in the bringing imperfect things to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect end, but the malicious foolishnesse of the other being seene in rayling on those things which are already found out, controlling, but not corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting any thing amisse. The wordes of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> are these, <hi>Eorum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid quae nondum inuenta sunt inuenire, quod{que} inuenisse quam non inuenisse prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiterit, similiter{que} imperfecta ad finem deducere id mihi videtur illius esse munus, qui intelligens exiflimari expetit: qui vero ea quae ab aliis sunt inuenta inhonesto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum verborum artificio contaminare contendit, neque quicquam corrigit, sed a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruis inuenta apud imperitos traducit, is sane prudentiae existimationem tueri velle non videtur, sed potius naturam suam at ignorantiam malitiose prodere.</hi> By which wordes it is manifest, that <hi>Hippocrates</hi> did not so ambitiously presume vpon his owne knowledge and absolute perfection in this facultie of Phisicke: but that he did confesse, &amp; as it were intimate, that the time would be, when as it would be bettered by far, and brought to more perfection, which <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> himselfe did prophesie of in his booke <hi>De prisca medicina,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging there, that only an entrance was found out to Phisicke, but more excellenter things by farre in processe of time should bee: the words are these: <hi>In medicina principium &amp; via inuenta est, per quam praeclara multa longo temporis spatio sunt inuenta, &amp; reliqua deinceps inuenientur si quis probe compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus fuerit, vt ex inuentorum cognitione ad ipsorum inuestigationem feratur.</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
Which <hi>Galen</hi> also affirmeth in the conclusion of his booke intitled, <hi>Quod op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus medicus idem sit &amp; philosophus,</hi> affirming there, that if we diligently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our selues to the studie of Philosophie, and seeke to bee true emulators of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> so doing we may become not onely like to him, but farre excelling, truely vnderstanding those things which are deliuered by him, &amp; finding out by our owne industrie, those things which remain in the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Phisicke, vnknowen by the wordes: therefore both of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> there were many things in Phisicke which were vnknowen to them, and in their time not found out, <hi>Galen</hi> himselfe witnessing in the ninth booke <hi>De simplicium medicamentorum facultate,</hi> that he had neuer tried whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Quicksiluer, being applied outwardly or taken inwardly, would kill or no. So by both their iudgements those were worthy of praise and not discredit, which by the true grounds of natural philosophie, and by the help of those things truely deliuered and set downe by those two pillars of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, did by all labour indeuour to finde out more excellent things for the curing of diseases. Yea, which is more, we are enforced (lest open scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall and reproch should redound to the art) to seeke out newe remedies for some diseases which were vnknowen both to <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> as the French Pox, the Measils, and the English sweate, and others of the like kind, otherwise Phisicke would hardly be deemed an arte.</p>
   <p>These two graue and reuerend fathers of Phisicke I haue therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged (though necessity and common good had bene a sufficient shielde for this mine enterprise) that vnder the couerture of their wings, <hi>tanquam sub Palladis aegide,</hi> I might be shadowed from reproch &amp; blame, and hauing two such strong Atlasses, I might the better beare the burden of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince which I haue vndertaken, namely, to publish to the world, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to your Worships good considerations, triall and equall censures, an vniuersall purging powder made of golde, siluer, and minerall water by arte and sire to that perfection decocted, whose operation and vertues I haue briefly set downe in the small Treatise following, referring the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular vse of it to the iudgemēt of euery Phisician, to specificate it at his own discretion with any other purging simple, that it may worke the effect spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and bee more properly directed to any humor afflicting, or peculiar member afflicted: and although in the publishing of a true secret, I neither vse dialecticall arguments to enforce, rhetoricall perswasions to allure, Lawyers il-loquence to vrge, Poets fictions to delight, Painters colours to deceiue, all which may make that seeme to bee which is not, and that which is, seeme not to be: yet this I humbly intreate, that as I nakedly delyuer an approoued trueth, so it may curteously be censured, as it shal be found by perfect triall: for Trueths auncient Hierogliphicke, is a virgine bare and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and hauing no deformitie, being from toppe to toe pure, vnspotted and
<pb facs="4"/>
beautifull, needeth no borrowed or counterfeit colours. This powder I present vnto your Worships, and make knowen vnto the world, for the loue and increase of the desired perfection of Phisicke, and the generall good of the diseased, and withall for mine owne commoditie, being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto animated by the graunted authoritie of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other of our neotericke classicke Phisicians, lest such a secret in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke should bee buried in his owne ashes, the publishing whereof, I hope, shal not giue any offence to the learned, but wil rather bee allowed and gladly accepted: which done, I rest humbly at your Worships pleasures and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, deuoting vnto you the fruits of all my hopes and studies.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Russel.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>