<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The antiquitie of Englande first called Brutaine.</title>
           <author>Webbe, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101062_Fr1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11377</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1582</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101062</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The antiquitie of Englande first called Brutaine.</title>
                 <author>Webbe, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doome warning all men to the iudgemente : wherein are contayned for the most parte all the straunge prodigies hapned in the worlde, with diuers secrete figures of reuelations tending to mannes stayed conuersion towardes God: in maner of a generall chronicle, gathered out of sundrie approued authors by St. Batman professor in diuinite</title>
                 <author>Lykosthenes, Konrad</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 132, 135-434, 436-439, pages 438, 436-437, 1 page, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="history">
   <head>The antiquitie of <hi>Englande</hi> first called Brutaine.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rute</hi> entred this Ilande, being the sonne of <hi>Siluius</hi> the son of <hi>Ascanius</hi> the sonne of <hi>Aeneas,</hi> after the deth of his father, a Gentile by lignage, and arriued at a place nowe called <hi>Totnes</hi> in <hi>Deuonshire</hi> the yeare of the Worlde. <hi>2855.</hi> of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuaunce <hi>2689.</hi> the yeare before Christs natiuitie. <hi>1108.</hi> there he first beganne to settle himselfe and his armie, vntil he had subdued diuerse mightie people, tal and strong, tearmed Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antes, then as King he named this Ile <hi>Brytaine,</hi> or as some hath written <hi>Brutaine,</hi> whose race continued in kingly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, vntill the time of <hi>Ferrex</hi> and <hi>Porrex</hi> two brethren, through whose discorde and bloudie conspiracie the linage of <hi>Brute</hi> was extinguished, when this Realme, by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> space of <hi>616.</hi> yeres had bin gouerned: then from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> time of <hi>Mulmucius Dunwallo</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> son of <hi>Cloten</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornewale,</hi> who was the first King that in this Ile ware a Crown of golde, vntill <hi>Cassibelan</hi> that was subdued by the force of <hi>Iulius Caesar,</hi> fiftie yeare
<pb facs="8"/> before the byrth of Christ, after which victorie the <hi>Brytaines</hi> became tributaries vnto the Romaines, and they as conquerors, helde the gouernement, vntill the time of <hi>Vortiger</hi> King ouer the <hi>Brytaines,</hi> whiche was the yeare after Christes incarnation <hi>447.</hi> shortly after which season, the <hi>Brytaines,</hi> beside their seruitude vnder the <hi>Romaines,</hi> were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellously vexed with the <hi>Scots, Pictes</hi> and <hi>Danes,</hi> nations that both robbed them of their goods, and slewe their people, notwithstanding al these grieuous plagues, by the means of a time of quietnesse, that happened in the time of <hi>Arthur</hi> king ouer the <hi>Brytaines</hi> and other whose valiant gouernement many yeares since hath bin slenderly estéemed, the sayde <hi>Brytaines</hi> became exercisers of lewde luste, ryotting and Idlenesse, which was the cause of their confusion, for God sent suche a plague and morrain, as wel among beasts, as men, that the liuing were not sufficient to burie the deade. And through the helpe of <hi>Scottes</hi> and <hi>Pictes,</hi> the <hi>Saxons</hi> subdued the <hi>Brytaines,</hi> in which greate dissention, the <hi>Danes</hi> became a plague vnto the <hi>Saxones:</hi> then was discorde in euery shire, and no manne sure what to possesse vntil the time of <hi>Edwyne</hi> the first Christiā king of <hi>Northumberland:</hi> in whose time there was no generall peace, but that the former rage waxed somewhat calmer, and so a lesser violence continued vntill <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy</hi> subdued the whole lande, by a general conquest, whiche was aboute the yeare of our Lorde God. <hi>1066.</hi> the fourth day of October being Saterday, in the which sayde yeare was séene a blasing Starre, the sequele being considered, these Verses folowing make relation.</p>
   <q>
      <l>A thousande sixe and sixtie yeare</l>
      <l>it was, as we do reade,</l>
      <l>When that a Comet did appeare</l>
      <l>and English men lay deade.</l>
      <l>Of <hi>Normandie</hi> Duke William then</l>
      <l>to <hi>England</hi> warde did sayle.</l>
      <l>And conquerde Herolde with his men,</l>
      <l>and brought this lande to bale.</l>
   </q>
   <p>The <hi>Saxons</hi> by the helpe of <hi>Vortiger</hi> entred this lande, about the yere of our Lord <hi>450.</hi> and there continued against the <hi>Brytaines</hi> and <hi>Danes,</hi> the space of <hi>600.</hi> yeares. Thys last gouernement hath continued without conquest of any other nation from <hi>Anno. <hi>1066.</hi>
      </hi> vntil this present yeare of our Lorde God <hi>.1581.</hi> the space of <hi>515.</hi> yeares, God graunte vs happy continuaunce, with such care to auoyde those of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, for the which God gaue ouer former gouernements, that we in eschewing their leude liuings, maye be euermore defended, not onlye from the seruile sworde by conquest, but also and most specially from euerlasting Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>