<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER, TOVCHING THE present controuersies betweene vs and the Romish Church.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101725_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15093</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25394</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101725</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER, TOVCHING THE present controuersies betweene vs and the Romish Church.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The way to the trve chvrch : wherein the principall motiues perswading to Romanisme and questions touching the nature and authoritie of the church and scriptures, are familiarly disputed, and driuen to their issues, where, this day they sticke betweene the Papists and vs: contriued into an answer to a popish discourse concerning the rule of faith and the marks of the church. And published to admonish such as decline to papistrie of the weake and vncertaine grounds, whereupon they haue ventured their soules. Directed to all that seeke for resolution: and especially to his louing countrimen of Lancashire. By Iohn White minister of Gods word at Eccles. For the finding out of the matter and questions handled, there are three tables: two in the beginning, and one in the end of the booke</title>
                 <author>White, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bill, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Barrett, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 454, 10 pages, tables, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER, TOVCHING THE present controuersies betweene vs and <hi>the Romish Church.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not as some thinke touching the questions between the Church of Rome and vs, that there is no reall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. Would to God it were so. But they that examine the points shall find it farre otherwise. 1. Concerning the Scriptures the Church of Rome teacheth, that<note n="a" place="margin">Can. loc. pag. 251.</note>
      <hi>Manie things appertaine to faith and Christian doctrine, which, neither openly nor obscurely, are contained in holy writ.</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Totalis enim &amp; adaequata regula, est Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tura, &amp; Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio simul. Dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Traditio pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem habet cum Scriptura. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can. circul. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin. p. 278.</note> For <hi>the totall and full rule of our faith is Scripture and Tradition both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Tradition being of equall authoritie with the Scripture.</hi> This assertion is directly against the doctrine of our Church, and leadeth men into pernicious errors pretended to be deliuered by Tradition, and withdraweth them from the obedience of onely Scripture, to the following of vncertaine authoritie. 2. Concerning the iustification of a sinner,<note n="c" place="margin">Viguer. Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tut. theol. p. 286</note>
      <hi>whereby of a wicked, vniust, and vncleane person, he is made cleane, holy, and simply iust:</hi> it teacheth that this is done, by the habite of our owne inherent righteousnesse, and not by Christs. Bellarmine, expounding the Councell of Trent, saith,<note n="d" place="margin">De Iustif. l. 2. p. 1032. c.</note>
      <hi>Our owne inherent iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice is the formall cause of absolute iustification, not the iustice of Christ imputed to vs:</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Pag. 1071. d.</note>
      <hi>besides the merits of Christ imputed to vs for our satisfaction, there is in vs an inherent iustice, which is the true and absolute righteousnesse whereunto, by the iust iudgement of God, not punishment, but glorie is due.</hi> This opinion containeth so reall a difference from the truth, that S. Paule<note n="f" place="margin">Gal. 5.4.</note> saith of it: <hi>Ye are abolished from Christ, ye are fallen from grace, whosoeuer are iustified by the Law.</hi> 3. Concerning the merite of our workes it holdeth,<note n="g" place="margin">Mich. Bai. de merit. oper. p. 12</note> that <hi>when men ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing conuersed godlily and righteously in this mortall life to the end, obtaine eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life: this is not to be deputed to the purpose of Gods grace, but to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of nature, appointed presently in the beginning, when man was created. Neither, in this retribution of good things, is it looked to the merite of Christ, but onely to the first institution of mankind, wherein by a naturall law it was set downe, that, by the iust iudgement of God the keeping of the commandements should be rewarded with life, as the breaking of them is punished with eternall death.</hi> Whereby we see that there is a plaine difference betweene the Church of Rome, and vs, in the principall article of our faith, touching the saluation
<pb facs="9"/> of our soules; we beleeuing stedfastly that it is to be ascribed to the merits of Christ, they expecting it for the merite also of their owne works. 4. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Images,<note n="h" place="margin">Concil. Trid. sess. 25</note> it practiseth the hauing and worshipping of them: yea<note n="i" place="margin">Azor. Instit. tom. 1. p. 737.</note>
      <hi>the Diuines</hi> of that Church <hi>hold that euery Image is to be honoured with the same honour, wherewith they worship the samplar.</hi> No man can be so simple but he may see a substantiall difference in these points: and the like may be shewed in aboue two hundred questions controuerted betweene vs, though I will not denie that in many things the heate of the contenders hath deuised diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences where there are none, and to discredit one another they haue wrested that which might be well vnderstood.</p>
   <p n="2">2 Besides the Church of Rome not onely requireth vs to professe her faith, but also to do it<note n="k" place="margin">Bell. de laic. c 19. p. 19; 9 c.</note> with <hi>subiection to the Pope:</hi> and teacheth,<note n="l" place="margin">Turrecr. quaest ex S. Tho. q. 13.</note> that <hi>this is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely necessarie to saluation.</hi> A point so fully opposite to the gouernment of our Church that it can no way be reconciled, forsomuch as we know the same to be a meere pretence to hide their tyrannie.</p>
   <p n="3">3 And as the difference is reall, and of long continuance, so is there no hope to reconcile it. The Papacie, that standeth in opposition against vs, was brought in by Satan at the first, and is still continued, onely to seduce the world: and<note n="m" place="margin">2. Cor. 6.14.</note>
      <hi>what fellowship hath righteousnesse with vnrighteousnesse? what communion hath light with darknesse? or what concord hath Christ with Belial? or the temple of God with idols?</hi> It is in vaine therefore to hope for reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things so farre vnlike, vnlesse our aduersaries would wholly renounce their parts, and embrace the truth, which<note n="n" place="margin">2. Thess. 2.11.</note> they will neuer do, Many meanes haue bene vsed, but neuer anie could preuaile. The Emperours, Ferdinand, and Maximilian, trauelled painfully herein, and by their appointment Cas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sander, a great learned Papist, drew<note n="o" place="margin">Consult. de Artic. controu. ad I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>app.</note> a proiect, to shew his iudgement. And in the time of Charles the fift, it was much laboured in Germanie to accord the sides, both by Papists and Protestants. And it is<note n="p" place="margin">Act colloqu. Ratisbon. an. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>41. Lindan. L de querela pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis. Praefat.</note> reported, that, at a mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at Regenspurge, there was an agreement made of many weighty points, touching <hi>Free will, Originall sinne, Iustification, Faith, Merits, Traditions, the Masse, &amp;c.</hi> but this held not; neither indeed can the wit of man auoide that<note n="q" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.19 2. Thess. 2.8. &amp; inde.</note> which God will haue, for the triall of his Church, and manifesting of his truth. There is in our aduersaries that refractarie frowardnesse, that they seeke nothing but to be contrarie vnto vs, and euen hate the name of peace. <hi>This opinion,</hi>
      <note n="r" place="margin">De Grat. &amp; lib. Arb l 5. c. 1.</note> saith Bellarmine, <hi>we imbrace and defend so much the more willingly, by how much it displeaseth our aduersaries, and especially Caluin.</hi>
      <note n="s" place="margin">Maldon. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Ioh. 6.</note> Another, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding a place of Scripture, saith: <hi>Though I haue no author for my exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet I allow it rather then that of Austin and others, though it be most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable;</hi> because this of mine more crosseth the sence of the Caluinists.</p>
   <p n="4">4 Hauing therefore to do with aduersaries so contentious, with doctrine so pernicious, with a Church so diseased; it is a better way to examine the questions and betake our selues to the true part, then to hope for that which will not be. And this was the course that the Christians tooke when the Church in ancient times was vexed with Arianisme and Pelagianisme. They were not indifferent which side preuailed, but they claue fast to the truth: they
<pb facs="9"/> did not neutralize betweene both; they did not idly sit, and deride those that contended for the truth; they made not the questions of religion the matter of their quarrels, and rude discourse in Tauernes and streetes, and euery base companie; but with godly affection they lamented the Churches trouble, and with zealous consciences, and earnest prayer, and religious endeuour they sought the faith. This is the way that all men should take, now when the rumor of the contention groweth so great: 1. with HVMILITIE to craue at Gods hand the direction of his Spirit: 2. then with DILIGENCE to reade and learne the Scripture, whereby to iudge: 3. and so with LOVE to the persons of the men, and with a mind prepared to yeeld to the truth, to trauell through the questions. The want of which no doubt is the true cause why contentions grow, and questions multiply, and all things are vncertain. For the preachings and writings of learned men are licentiously censured afore they be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood: the most people making the same onely a matter to cauill at; neuer considering with what religious hands they ought to touch the questions of faith, wherin whosoeuer erreth, loseth no lesse then his soule thereby. The questions of faith, and all matters of religion, require in such as will profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly exercise themselues therein, three things: <hi>Humilitie</hi> of mind, because they concern the holy things of God: <hi>Diligence</hi> in attending, because they are spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually discerned: and <hi>strength of iudgement,</hi> because enemies and seducers are exceeding cunning to beguile a slothfull examiner, and deceiue him that considereth not attentiuely.</p>
   <p n="5">5 Our aduersaries that manage the Papacie, if euer any, haue expressed this cunning and skill in perswading and setting forth their heresie, so farre that it cannot be denied, they haue omitted no art that might set it forth, nor no diligence that might adorne it. We reade strange things of certaine pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, how admirably they cast and shadowed their workes; but the skilfullest painters that euer were are our Iesuits and Schoolmen, and others, the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for the Church of Rome. Not the famous Zeuxis (<note n="t" place="margin">Plin. l. 35 c. 9.</note> who wrote vnder his table, when he had drawne it, that <hi>men should sooner enuy then imitate him</hi>) was to be compared to these painters: not the ancient Polignotus, nor Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhasius, not Mycon, Timanthes, Bularchus, Phidias, did euer bestow such pains on their images, as these haue done on their idol the Papacie: specially the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suite, who, as Plinie<note n="u" place="margin">Lib. 35. c. 10.</note> noteth of Parthasius, is <hi>soecundus artifex, sed quo nemo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solentius &amp; arrogantius sit vsus gloria artis: a workman full of deuice, but no man vseth the reputation of his skil more proudly and arrogantly then he.</hi> Zeuxis being to make the image of Iuno, to hang vp in her temple, chose out certain virgins, to put the seuerall beautie of them all into his picture: so haue these painters made choise of the exquisitest deuices that all the heresy in the world could yeeld, to put the same into their religion; no policie in Machiauell, nor Sophistry in Aristotle, nor eloquence in Rhetorick, but they haue contriued it into their Image, that, saue <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>sinceritie,</hi> there is nothing wanting. Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian saith, <hi>As the Gentiles with their hands, so heretickes with their words, are the makers of idols: for euery lie that they speake of God, is a kind of idolatry.</hi> The
<pb facs="10"/> Prophet Esay<note n="x" place="margin">C. 44. v. 12.</note> setteth downe a liuely description of this matter. <hi>The Smith ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an instrument, and worketh in the coles, and fasteneth it with hammers, and worketh it with the strength of his armes: the Carpenter stretcheth out a line, he fashioneeh it with a thred, and plaineth it, and pourtrayeth it with the compasse, and maketh it after the figure of a man, and according to the beauty of a man, that it may remaine in a house. He heweth him downe Cedars, and Pine trees, and Okes, and he taketh thereof and burneth it, and warmeth himselfe, and baketh his bread: yet he maketh a god and worshippeth it, an idol and boweth downe before it: he burneth the halfe of it in the fire, and vpon the half of it he eateth his meate; he rosteth it, and is satisfied: also he warmeth himselfe, and saith Aha, I am warm, I haue bin at the fire; and the residue therof he maketh a god, euen his idol; wherto he boweth, yea he worshippeth and prayeth vnto it saying, Deliuer me, for thou art my god.</hi> In which words the God of heauen deriding the Gentile, doth very fitly shew vs the idolatry of Rome, and the maner how the idol religion therof was framed and set on foote. At the first it was but a rude block, and ragged trunk, rough hewne by bungling workmen that were not their crafts masters, till the Smith, the Carpenter, and the painter came, euery one in his place, and shewed his skill. First the Canonists like blacksmiths blew with the bellowes of their Decrees, and hammered, and heat it in the coles of the Popes Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions: these smithes were Gratian, Pope Iohn, Gregory, and Boniface, with their prentises that serued them, Hostiensis, Innocent, Panormitane, and the rest of that profession. Next, the Carpenters that tooke it in hand were the Friers and Schoolmen, which stretched their line ouer it, and brought it into better shape. Thomas, and Scot, and Alexander fashioned it with line and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, they stretched out the line of Method ouer it, and with the thred of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction they plained it where it was rough, and with the compasses of their Logick and Philosophy made it in the fashion of a man. After that the great Lateran Councell, about the yeare 1215. had polished it, and giuen it strong ioynts to stand vpon: not long after the Councels of Constance, Basil, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Lateran hewed it ouer again, and altered the fashion in certain points touching the Popes authoritie. There some Cardinals, Senensis and Cusanus, thought the head stood too high aboue the shoulders, and would haue had it bowed downe a little lower. At last they brought it to Trent, into the hands of their best workmen, as<note n="y" place="margin">Absolutissima Trident. Synod. Posseuin bibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth. select. pag. 18. A.</note> they say, who mended it from top to toe, and set it vp againe when the wormes had welnigh consumed it: since which time the third sort of workmen the Painters haue taken it in hand; the Iesuits and their fellowes, who neuer cease to paint it day and night. There is no colour but they haue tried it to make it beautifull. Some with varnish and plaister stop vp the crackes, which the Sunne shining vpon it, hath made, that they might not be seene Bellarmine and his associates in that kind, stirre all colours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and varnish ouer the smokie and dustie places so skilfully, that a man can scarce tell what the colour is. Surius and Baronius with other colours, ground by Legendaries, cast a shadow ouer it for seeming too youthfull, but they haue painted a gray beard to a greene head: the rest stand by, such as are
<pb facs="10"/> Sixtus Senensis, Lindan, Staphylus, Posseuine, like Censors, commending the workmanship, and flattering the workmen, and extolling the idoll against them they call Lutherans and Caluinists. Thus at the last haue they polished their Dagon, and set it vp before the Lords Arke: saue that it may not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten that with some of it they warme themselues, and rost their meate; as Pardons, the Masse, and Purgatorie; and laugh in their sleeues at such as turne the spit: <hi>Ah I am warme, I haue bin at the fire.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="6">6 This is the labor and workmanship that our aduersaries haue bestowed on their religion, to set it forth: whereby they haue made their Church so seeming Catholicke. And indeed we haue alwayes obserued that there be two principall things which draw mens conceits to Papistrie. The first is the Name and report that goeth of the Church of Rome, while men perswade themselues that a Church so ancient, and renowmed in all ages, cannot but be the true Church of God. The second is the rumour and opinion of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries learning, as if it were vnpossible so learned men should be deceiued, and their writings could be answered. Neuerthelesse it is easie enough to see the truth through all this, if men will consider of things attentiuely. For tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the name and shew of the ROMANE CHVRCH, it is but an empty sound of words and titles: this present Romane being wholly departed, in the questions controuerted, from the ancient, and retaining nothing but the title. This should deceiue no man. For the true, ancient, and Apostolicke Church of Rome, so much commended by the Fathers, and sought to by the world, professed another kind of faith then this doth, and the same that now we defend against them; whereas this is fallen from it; and yet skilfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining still the same Seate and Title, imposeth maruellously vpon the world hereby. Isidorus Pelusiota<note n="b" place="margin">L. 3. Epist. 408.</note> hath a saying that sheweth the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of this: <hi>In the daies of the Apostles, and afterward, when the Church florished, and laboured as yet of no disease, the diuine graces of God went, as it were in a ring, round about it; the holy Ghost administring all things, and all the Bishops thereof inciting and turning it towards heauen: afterwards it grew diseased, and was troubled with faction, and then all those things flew away. Thus the Church is like a woman fallen from her ancient happinesse, and retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning onely some signes thereof. She hath the sheathes and caskets where her orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments lay, but the goods themselues she is spoiled of. Not through his carelesnesse and negligence that first enriched her, but through their naughtinesse that gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not things as they should haue done.</hi> This Doctor well perceiued that a Church may lose the faith, and yet retaine her name still: and he saw that, in his time, things fell to decay, and the faith of Christ began to be altered. To what purpose then should any man respect the name of the Romane Church, when the true faith is changed? or what do the prerogatiues and royalties of the ancient Church concerne this that is turned to another reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? or who regardeth a house of stately building, and honorable title, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke memory since Iohn of Gaunt, when the plague hath infected it, and theeues possesse it? Besides, when it was at the best, in the Apostles time and after, yet other Churches were commended as well, and counted as good, as
<pb facs="11"/> it.<note n="c" place="margin">Meditat. &amp; Respons. in iute Graecoroman. tom. 1. p. 449.</note> These are the words of Balsamon: <hi>The fiue Patriarkes</hi> (of Rome, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, Constantinople, Ierusalem, and Antioch) <hi>had identitie of honour:</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>and obtained the roome of one head ouer the body, that is, the holy Churches of God.</hi> And Nicephorus the Patriarke of Constantinople,<note n="e" place="margin">Concil. Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sin pag. 307.</note> in an Epistle to Leo, the Bishop of Rome, saith, <hi>And we also, who haue obtained the name of new Rome, being built vpon one and the same foundation of faith, the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, where Christ our Sauiour and God is the corner stone:</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>in the matter of faith are nothing behinde the elder Romanes. For in the Church of God there is nothing to be reckoned before the rest. Wherefore let Saint Paul glory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in vs also, and ioyning new things with old, and comparing vs in doctrines and preaching, let him glory in vs both alike. For we, as well as they, following his doctrines, and institutions, wherein we are rooted, are confirmed in the confession of our faith, wherein we stand and reioice, &amp;c.</hi> So that the Greeke Churches in the East thought themselues equall with Rome, and the commendations of the Apostle to belong to them as well as to the Church of Rome; whereby we may iudge how vndiscreet a part it is to be caried away with the name of a Church afore we haue enquired whether it keepe the ancient faith: or so to be conceited of one Church that we will looke toward no other but it.</p>
   <p n="7">7 The second point that deceiueth manie, is the rumour and opinion that goeth of our aduersaries learning: which is as weake a motiue to build on, as the former; when the greatest heretickes that euer were haue wanted no learning, and we may be sure, this of our aduersaries is not commended with the least. Themselues are vnmeasurable, and more then odious in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling their owne facultie, and their people as ridiculous and irkesome in reporting it It is nothing beseeming Christians to leaue the cause, and to fall a boasting. Let our bookes be viewed, and the disputations betweene vs weighed, and it will appeare they haue no such vantage, no not in Art and learning: and, but that vnsetled braines are giuen vainly to admire nouelties, our Church at home here in England (to say nothing of those abroad, who haue made our proudest enemies feele the edge of their learning) hath brought forth, and at this day yeeldeth, as learned as our aduersaries euer had anie. And that the Reader may haue some triall of this, I will giue an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or two wherein he shall see, and by that iudge of the rest, how learnedly they carrie themselues now and then against vs, and how great their skill is to helpe them when they are a little vrged.</p>
   <p n="8">8 They haue a solemne tradition among them concerning the Assump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Virgine Marie, the story whereof you may reade in the<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 1.14.</note> Rhemish Testament, to this effect: <hi>Now at the time of her death all the Apostles, then dispersed into diuerse nations, to preach the Gospell, were miraculously brought together (sauing S. Thomas, who came the third day after) to Ierusalem, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour her diuine departure and funerall: where before her death, and after for three dayes, not onely the Apostles and other holy men present, but the Angels also and powers of heauen did sing most melodiously. They buried her bodie in Gethseman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>: but for S. Thomas sake, who desired to see and reuerence it, they opened the sepulcher the third day, and finding it void of the holy bodie, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly
<pb facs="11"/> fragrant, they returned, assuredly deeming that her bodie was assump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into heauen, as the Church holdeth, and therefore celebrateth most solemnely the day of her Assumption.</hi> And<note n="h" place="margin">Anton. chron. part. 1. p. 147. Suar. tom. 2. p. 200.</note> some adde, that <hi>companies of Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and Christ himselfe (for how else should he haue fulfilled the cōmandement, Honor thy father and thy mother) met her, and with great glory and ioy placed her in her throne.</hi> This is the Legend; and that no man should mistrust they could not defend it,<note n="i" place="margin">Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ard. in Hest. pag. 616. Rhem. act. 1.14 Bristo. mot 32.</note> most bitterly they raile vpon all that denie it, perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding men<note n="k" place="margin">Baron. an 48. nu. 17. &amp; 24.</note> that it is <hi>the iudgement of the vniuersall Church:</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">Cathar. opusc. dè concept.</note> yea <hi>a point of faith.</hi> The ground whereupon they stand, is the Testimonie of many authors: a certaine writing of Iohn the Euangelist. Dionysius Areopagita, Melito, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanasius, Ierome, Austine, Damascene, Bernard, Andreas Cretensis, Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus, Metaphrastes, Glycas, &amp;c. Who would not thinke but here were a learned defence of that they say? But marke the issue: First we haue shewed them, and it is the truth, that whatsoeuer the later writers Damascene, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, Andreas, Metaphrastes, Nicephorus, Glycas and others of those times, haue written touching this matter, is borrowed from the former authours, Dionysius, Melito, the writing of S. Iohn, Athanasius, Ierome, and Austin: and can haue no more credite then the said authours haue from whom it is bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed. Now these authors we proue to be all forged, and our aduersaries, in the pursuite of the matter, confesse it.<note n="m" place="margin">D. 15. sancta Romana. Sixt. Senens. p. 104.</note> The booke going vnder the name of S. Iohn is bored through the eare by the Pope himselfe in a Councell, and so is Melito, as<note n="n" place="margin">An. 48. n. 12.</note> Baronius acknowledgeth, who calleth him <hi>an idle companion, full of dotages and fooleries vnworthie of Christian audience.</hi> The same censure he giueth<note n="o" place="margin">Nu. 13. &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.</note> of Sophronius, and Ierome, to Paul &amp; Eustoch. and<note n="p" place="margin">Nu. 20. &amp; inde</note> of Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasius, confessing them to be <hi>forged in their names,</hi> and <hi>full of lies and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postures.</hi> And<note n="q" place="margin">Nu. 17.</note> of that which goeth vnder the name of Austine, as the Diuines of Louan haue done before him. Dionysius is he that, when all is done, must beare the burden. But he also is acknowledged by<note n="r" place="margin">Erasm. declar. ad Censur. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risiens. theol. p. 180. Caietan. &amp; Valla annot. in Act. 17.</note> right skilfull Papists, to be a counterfet. And if the Rhemists<note n="s" place="margin">In Act. 1.14.</note> say true, that the blessed Virgine liued but 63. yeares, then, by<note n="t" place="margin">She bare Christ at <hi>15.</hi> yeares. Christ died at <hi>33</hi> then she was <hi>48.</hi> whereto if you adde <hi>15.</hi> more, it maketh them <hi>63</hi> and that yeare falleth into the yeare of Christ <hi>48.</hi>
      </note> computation of times, she died in the eight and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth yeare after Christs birth, what time Dionysius could not (as the booke going vnder his name pretendeth) be present. For the same Rhemists<note n="u" place="margin">Table of Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Paul. <hi>p. 375.</hi>
      </note> say, he was not conuerted till an. 51, and Baronius<note n="x" place="margin">An. 52. nu. 1.</note> not till an. 52, which was three or foure yeares after her death. Besides Baronius<note n="y" place="margin">Nu. 19.</note> is driuen to confesse <hi>her sepulcher was not found, or knowne in Ieromes time: but when at the length, not much before the dayes of Iuuenalis the Bishop of Ierusalem, it was found, and that without the body, by occasion hereof the argument of writing concerning the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming of her body into heauen, was exhibited for before that time none had writ so.</hi> Let this be noted. If her sepulcher was <hi>not knowne,</hi> nor her <hi>body missed</hi> out of it, nor <hi>no man writ of her assumption</hi> till Iuuenalis time; how can Dionysius that liued so long afore, mention it? Againe, let the booke be Dionysius his owne, and legitimate: yet the words thereof conuince not this Assumption. He saith no more but thus:<note n="z" place="margin">De Diuin. no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. p. 281. graec</note>
      <hi>When we also, as you know, and your selfe, and many of our holy brethren came together to behold the body which the Prince of life was in, and which receiued God; where Iames the brother of our Lord also
<pb facs="12"/> was present, and Peter the highest and ancientest top of the Diuines: then, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we had beheld, it pleased all the Bishops, as euerie one was able, to praise the almightie goodnesse of his infirmitie that was the beginning of life vnto vs Where Ierotheus, as you know, excelled all the other holy Bishops, except the Apostles, being wholly rapt out of himselfe.</hi> In which words he mentioneth no more but<note n="a" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> THE BEHOLDING OF THE BODY WHICH THE AVTHOR OF LIFE WAS IN, AND WHICH RECEIEVED GOD: and the PRAISING OF CHRISTS GOOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES: which speech is so obscure and vncertaine, that Baronius<note n="b" place="margin">An. 48. n. 6. &amp; 3.</note> obserueth, some haue expounded it of the <hi>Sepulcher</hi> which receiued the body of Christ, and some of Iohn the Euangelists <hi>house</hi> which entertained the holy Virgin, and some of the <hi>flesh</hi> of Christ wherin the Diuinitie dwelt. But supposing the body of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> virgine Mary be meant, which they came to see, yet how followeth it that this was at her death, and funerall, and assumption, &amp; all the rest that the Rhemists tell? where is the learning that should proue this? Moreouer we shew them how vaine and vncertaine all things touching this matter are. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors are vnsufficient. No man can tell either when she died, or where the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher should be, or when she was assumed. Touching her age when she died, whereupon dependeth the credit of Dionysius,<note n="c" place="margin">Suar. tom. 2. p. 197. Baro. an. 48. n. 24.</note> they say it is <hi>vncertaine and vnknowne.</hi> The time of her assumption is noted by<note n="d" place="margin">Suar. p. 200.</note> some to haue bin the same day she died by<note n="e" place="margin">Rhem. act. 1.14.</note> others, 3 daies, by<note n="f" place="margin">Beleth. explic. diuin. offic. pag. 559. Durand. rational. p. 447.</note> others 40. daies after. Baron.<note n="g" place="margin">Nu. 4.</note> saith there is <hi>monstrous diuersity among writers touching these things.</hi> And concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the sepulcher, you see the Rhemists say confidently it was in Gethsemani: but the counterfet<note n="h" place="margin">Ep. ad Paul. &amp; Eustoch.</note> Ierom saith, <hi>in the vally of Iehosaphat.</hi> Baronius thinks it is <hi>vnknowne.</hi> But how is the matter then defended, after they haue so grauely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated it, and so reuiled the Protestants for not beleeuing it? as in many more questions, so in this, when they haue florished awhile, and spent a few vaine brags, their blood cooleth, and the swelling swageth.<note n="i" place="margin">Durand. vbi supra.</note> One saith: <hi>The truth is, she was taken vp in soule, but whether her body remained on the earth it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine. And better it is piously to doubt, then rashly to define any thing tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the matter. Yet it is piously to be thought, she was totally assumed.</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">Suar. vbi supra.</note> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther saith: the opinion is now so generally receiued that it cannot, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rashnesse, be denied: yet <hi>there is neither Scripture nor sufficient tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to make the faith hereof infallible.</hi> Baronius saith,<note n="l" place="margin">Nu. 9.</note>
      <hi>the things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to this historie are strengthened neither by the Scriptures nor the testimonies of the auncient fathers.</hi> If their learning could haue iustified their fable, they would not first raile at the Protestants for refusing it, and then in the end themselues h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lfe mistrust it, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it vpon bare tradition, and intreating the world to receiue it as a godly opinion, though there be no testimonie in antiquitie to proue it.</p>
   <p n="9">9 Another example to shew what little cause we haue to feare or regard their learning, shall be this that followeth. When the second Nicene Councel had brought in the worship of images, the Emperour Charles assembled ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Councell at Frankford, and condemned it againe, and reiected the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene: whereby it appeareth that images were brought in at that time,
<pb facs="12"/> and that the Church of Rome, in confirming the said Nicene Councel, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ancient faith. Our aduersaries haue had time enough to thinke vpon this, and to frame their answer. But they know not what to say, the best lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned among them confuting one another in the point. First<note n="m" place="margin">Suar tom. 1. p. 800. c. Vazq. adorat. p. 303. Bin. tom. 3. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. p. 427.</note> they endeuour to proue, that this of Frankford was but a prouinciall Councell; and faine they would haue it so, that they might say it erred, and must giue place to the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene which was generall. But we shew this to be false: for<note n="n" place="margin">Visperg. pag. 187. Rhegin p. 30.</note> the stories report it to haue bene a generall Councell of three hundred Bishops, assembled out of all the prouinces of the Empire, the Popes owne Legates also being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent: and therefore<note n="o" place="margin">Ouand bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiloq. in 4 sent. pag 52 Baron. an 794. nu. 1.</note> other Papists let go this answer, graunting it was a full Councell, and cannot be reiected as a prouinciall: and that it did condemne the Nicene Councell, but this, they say, was erroneously; being deceiued by those that penned the booke of Charles against Images, and thinking it had decreed they should be worshipped with Latria, diuine honor, which was the reason why they reiected the Nicene Councell.<note n="p" place="margin">Bozi de Sign. eccl tom. 2. pag 270. Genebrard chron. an. 794. Bellar. de imag. c. 14 Baron. an. 794. n. 31. &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.</note> Many of the learnedest flie to this answer: but we reply, that besides that it is against<note n="q" place="margin">Concil. Basil. epist Synod. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>spons. de au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorit. Concil.</note> a principle of their owne, that a generall Councell cannot erre, it is manifestly against the truth. For the mind of the Nicene Councell was well enough knowne, and the same Popes Legats that were at the one, were at the other: and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary cannot be shewed out of Charles his booke, whereupon other Papists perceiuing this answer cannot be defended, giue it ouer, and confute it, and betake themselues to a worse.<note n="r" place="margin">Alan. Cope. p. 570. Sand. visib. monarc. p. 480. Sur. comment. p. 445. &amp; concil tom. 3. p. 428. Alp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>on. contra haer. p. 139. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharin. de sanct. glor. p. 67. Suar. tom. 1. p. 802. Vazq. adorat. p. 302. Binn. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. tom. 3. pag. 429.</note> They say, that in the Synod of Frankford, the Nicene Councel was not condemned, not any thing attempted against it, but the Councell of Constantinople vnder Constantinus Copronymus which had condemned Images: yea it ratified and confirmed the Nicene Councell, and decreed the worship of Images, as it had done. A strange assertion; yet Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius<note n="s" place="margin">An. 794 n. 26.</note> saith <hi>It is the answer of very many good Catholickes;</hi> as it is indeed: but note what<note n="t" place="margin">De imag. c 14.</note> Bellarmine saith of it, <hi>I wish this were true, but I doubt it is false.</hi> For marke into what desperate straits they haue brought themselues that hold it. First, they of the former opinion confute them. Next, we produce the vniuersall consent of the Church stories against them. The booke of Charles the great<note n="u" place="margin">Praefat. circa med.</note> saith, <hi>There was brought forth the question touching the late Synod of the Grecians, which they made at Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>tinople concerning the adoring of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, wherein it was written, that they should be cursed which did not giue the same seruice and adoration to the images of Saints, which is giuen to the diuine Trinitie. This our most holy Fathers</hi> (of Frankford) <hi>despised, and with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent condemned.</hi> To this agree diuers other authors: Hincmarus, Ado, Vrsper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gensis, Rhegino, Aimon, Auentin, &amp;c. But they answer: Hincmarus (though he were Archbishop of Rhemes, and liued at the same time) his authoritie is nothing.<note n="x" place="margin">Cope. p. 582. Vazq. p. 309.</note> The words are forged, or he was deceiued: the rest that followed him, are all either corrupted, or mistaken.<note n="y" place="margin">An. 794. n. 33.</note> Baronius saith, the bookes of Charles deceiued them. Suarez,<note n="z" place="margin">Tom 1. p. 804</note> that either they erred, or their bookes are corrupted, or they speake not of the second Nicene Councel. Vasquez,<note n="a" place="margin">De adorat. p. 309.</note> that they were all manifestly deceiued by Hincmarus, as Hincmarus was by the bookes of Charles. And thus all the blame is layd on that booke, the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb facs="13"/> whereof notwithstanding they cannot infringe, though<note n="b" place="margin">Ala. Cope. p. 566. Bellar. de Concil. l. 2. c 8. Suar. tom. 1. p. 803. Vazqu 277 Baron. an. 794. n. 30.</note> they do their vttermost, to proue that Charles wrote it not. For first it beareth his title, as all other books do theirs.<note n="c" place="margin">Bell. de imag. c. 14. Baron. n. 31</note> Secondly it containeth the acts of the Synod of Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, and the Councell therein confuted is the second Nicene. Thirdly<note n="d" place="margin">Cope. p. 568. Vazqu. p. 277. Baron. n. 31.</note> it was written in the time of Charles. Fourthly<note n="e" place="margin">Baron. ibid.</note> it was sent by Charles to Pope A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian. Fiftly, one chapter thereof<note n="f" place="margin">Baron. n. 32. &amp; 46.</note> is confessed to be the work of Charles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. Sixtly, and at the worst,<note n="g" place="margin">Hadrian. Ep. ad Carol. tom. 3 concil. p. 263.</note> it was written by such as were neare about Charles. This is a briefe summe of all that long discourse betweene vs tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Councell of Frankford; which I haue obserued, that the Reader may perceiue what is to be thought of our aduersaries learning, so much bragged of: for were it able to do that which is boasted, they would neuer suffer themselues thus to be distracted, and driuen to these beggerly shifts, and foxed out of one hole into another, that they know not where to set their foote. Let them speake directly, and go forward with the point in any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie, and we feare not their learning.<note n="h" place="margin">1 Reg. 20.11.</note>
      <hi>Let not him that girdeth on his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, boast himselfe as he that putteth it off.</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">Pro. 21.30.</note>
      <hi>There is no wisedom, nor vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, nor counsell against the Lord.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="10">10 This opinion that they haue of their owne learning is it that puffeth them vp, and maketh them more then idle, euen base and ridiculous in their owne commendations; and (which ill beseemeth the Ministers of Christ) filleth their mouths with contumelious and stagelike speeches against vs; such as these are:<note n="k" place="margin">Rhem. 1. Tim 1.7.</note>
      <hi>In the sight of the learned they are most ignorant of the word of God, not knowing the verie principles of Diuinitie, euen to the admiration truly of the learned that reade their bookes, or heare them preach.</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">Caluinotur. cism. p. 360.</note>
      <hi>Their vnlearned and beggerly Ministers:</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">Brist. mot. 31.</note>
      <hi>Looke to their Vniuersities, and see whether there be any appointed publicke Readers or Teachers of such matters</hi> (the mysteries of Diuinitie) <hi>any that priuately make them their studie: whether they do not all in maner studie nothing but the art of speaking, or else but certaine new bookes of common places for a few points of their new doctrine, and them so lightly, that the common sort of Catholickes are able to answer all their arguments, and to say also more for them then they can say for themselues.</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">Brist. reply. p. 364.</note>
      <hi>More declamatiōs in Greek in one common schoole of the Iesuites, then in both your Vniuersities</hi> (<note n="o" place="margin">This sheweth they dare say any thing.</note> I dare say) <hi>being ioyned together: and better maisters of Arts of two or three yeares teaching through all logicke and philosophie, then with you in seuen yeares. No, no, regnum Grāmaticorum is past date, all are not children as they were when this geare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan: your tongues will not now serue, no nor your study of Diuinitie it selfe in Caluins Schoole. Come once to the Catholike Schooles, and you will be ashamed of your selfe, as many a one already is, that thought himselfe, and was thought of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, at home a iolly fellow.</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">Hard. confut. Apol. pag. 279. <hi>And Stapleton saith worse in his</hi> Counter bl. p. 481.</note>
      <hi>Your Ministers be Tinkers and Tapsters, Fidlers &amp; Pipers,</hi> it is incredible to heare their veine in this kind, and how they vaunt of themselues withall, as if they were playing vpon a stage the first Act and Scaene of Plautus his<note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Miles glorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.</hi> A liuely pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent brags.</note> Braggadochio. But it is a base course and cannot be pursued without lying and ostentation; and therefore the Gentiles themselues deriding it,<note n="r" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Phurnut. de nat. Deorum p. 42.</note>
      <hi>Sacrificed an Asse to Mars the God of warres,</hi> because the noyse and braying of the one agreed fitly with the tumult and confusion of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="13"/> the other. And yet it were the easiest matter of a thousand to requite them with testimonies of their owne writers. For Theodoricke of Niem<note n="s" place="margin">L. 2. c. 12. de Schism.</note> saith, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are created Bishops to day, which yesterday like iesters and stageplayers, and prodigals, did nothing but run vp and downe the streetes and tauernes, and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected places.</hi> And Clemangis<note n="t" place="margin">De corrupt. statu. eccl. p. 15.</note> writeth, how <hi>innumerable Parish Priests came to their benefices, not from the Schooles, and their studie, but from the plow, and seruile occupations, which could neither reade nor vnderstand Latin, nor know b from a battledoore.</hi> Yea the Bishops themselues,<note n="u" place="margin">Pag. 30.</note> saith he, <hi>haue neither read, nor heard, nor learned the sacred letters, nor so much as touched the Bible, vnlesse peraduenture it were the hilling thereof. Ignorant and vnlettered persons hold the roomes of Bishops.</hi> I could easily produce many of their owne authors (if our selues had knowne or seene nothing in their old Priests and young Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries:) to discouer as much in their owne Clergie as they reuile vs with, whether it be our<note n="x" place="margin">Maxima hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticorum pars nimis maturè, ex scholis ad pulpita aliosue gradus, euoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Alan. Apol. p. 106.</note> youth, or conditions, or vnlearnednesse, if I would imitate their vanitie. Their<note n="y" place="margin">Sixt. Sen. p. 245.</note>
      <hi>Mus</hi> that preached at twelue yeares old: their<note n="z" place="margin">Baron. ann. 1033. n. 6.</note>
      <hi>Bennet</hi> that was Pope being vnder ten yeares old, and<note n="a" place="margin">Baron. ann. 955. nu. 1. 2.</note>
      <hi>Iohn</hi> not aboue sixteene: their<note n="b" place="margin">Baron. ann. 925. n. 9.</note>
      <hi>Archbishop</hi> of Rhemes at fiue yeares old: their<note n="c" place="margin">See D. Reyn. apol. thes. p. 292.</note>
      <hi>Cardinals</hi> vnder 12. yeares old: their<note n="d" place="margin">Baron. an. 925. n 11.</note>
      <hi>youths</hi> and <hi>nephewes</hi> thrust into Bishoprick; their<note n="e" place="margin">Sa. apho. pag. 208.</note>
      <hi>idiots</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to minister. These &amp; such like practises of their Church will shew what small cause there is why they should disdaine vs, supposing we had lesse lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning then we haue. Irenaeus<note n="f" place="margin">L. 2. c. 45.</note> hath a saying which I commend vnto them when they thinke they haue so much vantage of learning against vs: <hi>It is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more profitable to be simple and of small knowledge, and by loue to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach neare God, then to thinke themselues to know much, and to be of high expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and in the meane while to be found blasphemers against God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="11">11 We know no cause therefore why we should not constantly and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully go forward with our profession, and confirme our selues daily more and more therin, against all the premises and oppositions of the Romane Church whatsoeuer. First, we haue the Scripture in manifest places free from all am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguitie, on our side; secondly, we haue the principles of religion, contained in the Lords praiers, the Creed, and the ten Commandements, that directly leadeth to euery point of our faith. Which is the true reason why the Church of Rome forbiddeth the reading and exercise of these things to the people, lest they should see so much. Thirdly, we haue the ancient fathers in expresse termes, in all things that they held constantly &amp; certainly, with one consent I do not deny but our aduersaries in some smaller points, as Purgatory, &amp; praier for the dead, may make shew of some particular opinions in the fathers: but vpon triall it will fall out they held thē waueringly &amp; doubtfully, that no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty can be set downe touching their resolute iudgement. Whereas in the principall points touching the Scriptures, iustification, merit of workes, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and all the rest, they write most clearely with vs. Fourthly, and which may perswade any man not drunken with his owne preiudice, we haue the mercies of God to pleade for vs, whereby our Church hath bene miraculously vpholden: when they <hi>threatned,</hi> God defended vs; when they <hi>practised</hi> and <hi>expected</hi> our vtter ruine, God disappointed them; when they wrought all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="14"/> of <hi>treasons,</hi> yet God deliuered vs. Fiftly, and this is our further assurance, that we haue done nothing against the Church of Rome, but innumerable people in all ages wished it long ago. What ceremony? what doctrine? what custome? what one parcell of their superstition haue we refused, but the world long since complained of it? yea the learnedst men that were groned vnder the very burthens that we haue haue shaken off.<note n="g" place="margin">Evetusto quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>am libro refert Illyric. catolog. test. tom. 2. p. 805.</note> It is written of Gerson the Chauncellor of Paris, who liued about one hundred yeares before Luther, that the Sorbonists expulsed him the Vniuersitie, and in his old age depriued him of all his d gnities<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>: because, as it is like, he misliked diuers errors in the Church of Rome. What time he betooke himselfe to teaching of schoole, wherein his manner was daily to cause all his schollers, the little children, to ioyne with him in this short praier; <hi>My God, my maker, haue mercy vpon thy miserable seruant Gerson.</hi> It should seeme by this, that he tooke small com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in those times, when forsaking all confidence in the glory of his Church, he would call for mercy at the hands of God, rather in the company of a few poore childrē, then in the societie of such as were reputed the Doctors of the world. And it may easily be thought, Gerson saw more then he either loued or liked, because the moderne Papists reiect his iudgement, &amp;<note n="h" place="margin">Resp. Card. Bellar. ad reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut Io. Gerson.</note> confute his writings: and<note n="i" place="margin">Fra. Victoria. relect. 4. p. 138.</note> say, <hi>This Doctor in all things was an enemie to the Popes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and, with his heresie infected many others. His opinion touching this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter little different from schisme.</hi> Yea at this day they see more errors then they will reforme. <hi>O God,</hi> saith<note n="k" place="margin">Naucler pag. 499.</note> one of their Historiographers, <hi>what will become of our age when our vices are grown to that, that they haue scarce left vs any place with God for mercy. What couetousnesse is therein Priests? what lust, what ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what idlenes, what pompe, what ignorance both of thēselues and of Christian doctrine? how little religion, and fained rather then true? God haue mercy on vs.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="12">12 And h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>, omitting the way that is by triall of arguments, I offer cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine externall markes, and sensible tokens whereby the falshood of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church may be discouered, &amp; the most resolute Papist that liueth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to misdoubt his owne religion: for it is vnpossible that these things fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing should be found in the true Church, or practised by men of the right faith. The first is, their enmitie with the sacred Scriptures, the word of God: whereof I haue spoken in the 22. Digression of this booke. For the words<note n="l" place="margin">Esa. 8.20.</note> of the Prophet are cleare: <hi>To the Law, to the Testimony: if they speake not according to that word, it is because there is no light in them.</hi> And one of their practises a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it whereby they haue depriued it frō being the totall rule; hath left thē vtterly voide of all meanes to secure their faith by, and to find the truth. For the Church, the fathers the Councels, the Pope, which is all they can pretend, are yeelded by themselues to be subiect to error. And how can that giue them assurance of their faith, which it selfe is not assured from error? The second is the very face and outward state, and gouernment of their Church, cleane contrary to the first antiquitie. How vnlike is their Pope to Peter? their Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals to the Apostles? their Prelates to the ancient Bishops; in state, in ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in intermedling? This is noted at large by many among themselues. Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barella, Cusanus, Marsilius, Occham, Duarenus. How vnlike is their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
<pb facs="14"/> Masse, halfe Communion, Latin Seruice, Image worship, to the ancient Seruice of the Church of God? If it were the true Church, no continuance of time could thus haue altered it: age changeth the colour of a mans haire, and the sound of his voice, but not his complexion or the shape of his bodie. The third is, that THERE IS NO POINT OF OVR FAITH BVT MANY LEAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NED IN THEIR OWNE CHVRCH HOLD IT WITH VS, AND NO POINT OF PAPISTRIE THAT WE HAVE REIECTED, BVT SOME OF THEMSELVES HAVE MISLIKED IT AS WELL AS WE. And this may be demonstrated in all the questions that are betweene vs, and they know it, and for that cause haue purged and razed the principall bookes of the elder Papists, and some of them they haue vtterly forbidden. <hi>In the bookes of latter Catholickes also,</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">Index libro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum prohib. p. 25. §. 3.</note> saith the Index, <hi>which were written since the yeare</hi> 1515. <hi>if that which needeth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting can be amended by taking away or adding of a few things, let the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors see it be done: but otherwise let it be wholly razed out.</hi> The fourth is, that the most points of Papistrie are directly and at the first sight absurd and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst common sence, and the law of nature. For who can conceiue that it should be the <hi>Popes</hi> right to Lord it thus ouer the Scriptures, Fathers, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, Church, and all the world? What possibility is there that the kingdomes of the world should be subiect to him? What likelyhood is there that <hi>Images</hi> should be worshipped? our <hi>workes</hi> should merit heauen? the <hi>cup</hi> should not be allowed to the people? the <hi>Seruice</hi> should be in a language vnknowne? the <hi>Body of Christ</hi> should be in ten thousand places at once? the Priest should haue iudiciall power to <hi>forgiue sinnes?</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> in heauen should be made mediators for vs to God. He that will indifferently compare these and many points more shall finde them manifestly against the principles of religion, and the light of nature. What man can thinke it to be the true Church that teacheth to <hi>equiuocate,</hi> to <hi>murther the King,</hi> to <hi>pay no debts,</hi> to BLOW VP THE PARLIAMENT, to dispense with <hi>murther</hi> and <hi>whoredome?</hi> The fift is, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate and vnchristian proceeding against vs. For if they were of the truth, they would not defend themselues, and confute vs with grosse lying, vncharitable railing, and irreconcileable malice, which are the weapons of darkenesse; but with grauitie and sinceritie as becometh Christs Gospell. Who will beleeue that any can be so impious, that holdeth there is a God, as to make him <hi>the author of sinne?</hi> and yet<note n="n" place="margin">Posseuin. bibl. select. p. 533.</note> they shame not to say we do it. Who can thinke that any man is so absurd as to deny <hi>the necessitie of good workes,</hi> and a godly life? and yet they say our Church doth it. There is very little of our doctrine but maliciously they traduce and misreport it. That we haue neede to put them in minde of Philoxenus the Poet,<note n="o" place="margin">Hesych. Illust. vit. philosoph. in Arcesilao.</note> who hearing certaine Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters singing his verses vndecently, brake their pots: <hi>For,</hi> saith he, <hi>I breake your pots, and you marre my verses.</hi> What truth or sinceritie is it to publish abrode to the world, that in England, Catholickes (so they call themselues vntruly) are so cruelly persecuted?<note n="p" place="margin">Nonnullae de castissimis vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginib vestris in Lupanaria alia{que} loca inhone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sta (praeclarissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma in hoc Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netis, Luciae{que} virginum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empla secutae) protrusae sunt. Alan. consolat. pag. 159.</note> That <hi>young women,</hi> which are found to be of that religion, are <hi>put into the stewes:</hi> and such like vntruthes mentioned thicke and threefold in their<note n="q" place="margin">Concert. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl Cathol.</note> writings.<note n="r" place="margin">Aquiponta. de Antichristo. p. 110. post San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. visib. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch l. 7. p. 664</note> That ten thousand Churches and aboue are ouerthrowne: more then two hundred Martyrs slaine, an infinite multitude
<pb facs="15"/> of all sorts, and sexes, imprisoned, banished, and bereaued of their goods. One Cardinall, three Archbishops, eighteene Bishops, one Abbot, foure Priours, foure whose Couents, thirteene Deanes, foureteene Archdeacons, six hundred Priests, seuentie seuen Doctors, one Queene, eight Earles, ten Barons, sixe and twentie Knights, foure hundred Gentlemen. What could they haue said more if Queene Elizabeth had bene as cruell as Queene Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie was against vs in her time? Yea their hatred against vs is such, that they hold vs to be<note n="s" place="margin">See Lindan. de suga idol.</note>
      <hi>possesse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> (not simply seduced but <hi>euen possessed</hi> by the diuell) and thereupon, when any of vs reuolteth to the Papacie, and is reconciled to them, they haue an order to exorcize the party,<note n="t" place="margin">Pontifical. Rom. pag. 206.</note>
      <hi>who kneeling vpon his knees the Bishop saith: I coniure thee, vncleane spirit, by the name of God, that thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this seruant of God, whō he hath vouchsafed to deliuer frō thy errors, and to bring backe to his holy Church: he cōmandeth thee thou cursed and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned spirit, who suffered for the saluation of man, &amp;c.</hi> Besides, their malicious<note n="u" place="margin">Staplet. prom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptuar. moral. ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiu. pag. 493. Answer to the libel of Engl. Iust. pag. 170. &amp; inde.</note> threatning of the peace of our Land, euen then when it had the happiest time, and vnnaturall treasons against vs, shew the true sanctification of Gods spirit not to be among them, which teacheth meekenesse and forbearance, not rankor, and impatience, and rebellion. Saue that hauing said,<note n="x" place="margin">Id.</note>
      <hi>They were but thriftlesse yonkers, vulgar readers, common persons, that would not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded our countrey and state to be in the greatest, and most daungerous termes</hi> (in the Queenes time) <hi>that euer it was, since or before the conquest, and in far worse then any countrey in Christendome:</hi> it pleased God by the coming of his Maiestie to deride these their Prophecies; and in scorne thereof, at this day we enjoy the very same peace and libertie that we then had.</p>
   <p n="13">13 The sixt is the prodigious ignorance whereinto they fall that liue in Papistry. For as their Church commendeth it, so their people follow it most desperatly, euen in the chiefest things touching their saluation. I will not speake how vnable they are to render account of the faith, to vnderstand the points of the Catechisme, to iudge of things lawfull and vnlawfull, and such like: I will only mention what I saw and learned, dwelling among them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the saying of their prayers: for what man is he whose heart trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth not to see simple people so farre seduced, that they know not how to pronounce or say their daily prayers? or so to pray, as all that heare them shall be filled with laughter? And while superstitiously they refuse to pray in their owne language with vnderstanding, they speake that which their lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders may blush to heare. These examples I haue obserued from the common people.<note n="*" place="margin">The maner how the vulgar sort of people, addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to Papistry, say their praiers: the which I haue obserued by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing with them: and set downe for no other purpose but to note the pitiful ignorance and confusion whereinto the Church of Rome plungeth her chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren. <hi>Non ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda reteg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>, sed inuerecūda resuto: vtinam nobis relique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint moderni Noc, vnde à nobis possent aliquaten ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riti. Bern. ep. 42.</hi>
      </note> The Creed: <hi>Creezum zuum patrum onitentem creatorum eius anicum Dominum nostrum qui cum sops, virigini Mariae: crixus fixus, Ponchi Pilati au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitiers, morti by sonday, father a fernes, sclerest vn iudicarum, finis a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus. Creezum spirituum santum, ecli Cathóli, remissurum, peccaturum, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum obliutorum, hitam &amp; turnam again.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The little Creed.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Little Creed, can I need,</l>
      <l>Kneele before our Ladies knee:</l>
      <l>Candle light, candles burne,</l>
      <pb facs="15"/>
      <l>Our Ladie prayed to her deare Sonne,</l>
      <l>That we might all to heauen come.</l>
      <l>Little Creed, Amen.</l>
   </q>
   <p>This that followeth, they call the White Pater noster.</p>
   <q>
      <l>White Pater noster, Saint Peters brother,</l>
      <l>What hast i'th t'one hand? white booke leaues.</l>
      <l>What hast i'th t'other hand? heauen yate keyes.</l>
      <l>Open heauen yates, and<note n="*" place="margin">Shut.</note> steike hell yates:</l>
      <l>And let euery crysom child creepe to it owne mother:</l>
      <l>White Pater noster, Amen.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Another Prayer.</p>
   <q>
      <l>I blesse me with God and the rood,</l>
      <l>With his sweet flesh and precious blood:</l>
      <l>With his Crosse and his Creed,</l>
      <l>With his length and his breed,</l>
      <l>From my toe to my crowne,</l>
      <l>And all my body vp and downe,</l>
      <l>From my backe to my brest,</l>
      <l>My fiue wits be my rest:</l>
      <l>God let neuer ill come at ill,</l>
      <l>But through Iesus owne will,</l>
      <l>Sweet Iesus Lord, Amen.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Many also vse to weare Veruein against blasts: and when they gather it for this purpose, first they crosse the herbe with their hand, and then they blesse it, thus:
<q>
         <l>Hallowed be thou Veruein, as thou growest on the ground,</l>
         <l>For in the mount of Caluary there thou was first found:</l>
         <l>Thou healedst our Sauiour Iesus Christ, and stanchedst his bleeding wound:</l>
         <l>In the name of the Father, the Son, and the holy Ghost, I take thee frō the around.</l>
      </q> And so they pluck it vp, and weare it. Their prayers and traditions of this sort are infinite, and the ceremonies they vse in all their actions are nothing infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the Gentiles in number and strangenesse. Which any man may easily obserue that conuerseth with them: the Which I haue noted in this place, not to disgrace the persons of any, but to shew the pitiful barbarousnesse wherein they liue that refuse to heare the Gospell, and whom our Seminaries haue trained vp, boasting that there is no religion, or knowledge, or deuotion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, but in these people. And let any man iudge how it can possibly be the Church of Christ, that nourisheth this barbarous, and more then brutish ignorance &amp; superstition among the people. And it cannot be answered, that these are the customes of a few simple people: for this that I say, is generall throughout the country, the whole bodie of the common people practising nothing else, vntill it please God by the ministery of his Gospell to conuert them. Yea the most men and women addicted to Papistry, though wel borne and brought vp for ciuill qualities, and of good place in the countrey, yet lie plunged in this ignorance, being perswaded that what they haue learned by
<pb facs="16"/> long custome and continuance in their old religion (so they style it) they should not giue ouer. Yea this sore is so foule and grieuous, that it may not endure to be looked into.</p>
   <p n="14">14 This brutish condition of their people may the better be credited, and is the lesse to be wondred at, because the open practise of their Church giueth them example, and encourageth them by their idolatry and supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion toward the Saints departed. For how can that people discerne their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, whose Pastors euen before their eies, in their open Seruice and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bookes, serue the Saints and worship them with the same seruice that they giue to Christ? This I offer for the seuenth motiue, to induce any Papist to suspect his owne religion: for it cannot be the faith of Christ, that taketh his honor and giueth it to another. In their Seruice and prayers the virgine Marie is made an intercessor for sinne,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.5.</note> as if Christ were not the sole Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, vnlesse the merits and mediation of another did come betweene. Let these formes be an example.</p>
   <q>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Offic. Mar. pag. 13.</note>By the prayers <hi>AND MERITS</hi> of the euer blessed virgin Mary, and of all Saints, our Lord bring vs to the kingdome of heauen. Amen.</q>
   <p>Againe:
<q>
         <note n="c" place="margin">Ibid. pag. 27.</note>All haile ô Queene, mother of mercie: <hi>OVR LIFE,</hi> sweetnesse and <hi>HOPE,</hi> all haile. We exiled, the sonnes of Eue, do crie to thee. To thee we sigh, groning and weeping in this vale of teares. Therefore ô thou our <hi>ADVOCATE,</hi> turne those thy mercifull eyes vnto vs: and shew vs after this exile blessed Iesus the fruite of thy wombe. O clement, ô pitifull, ô sweet virgin Marie: pray for vs ô holy mother of God.</q> Againe:
<q>
         <l>
            <note n="d" place="margin">Ib. pag. 33.</note>Marie that mother art of <hi>GRACE,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Of <hi>MERCIE</hi> mother also art,</l>
         <l>
            <hi>SAVE</hi> and defend vs from our so,</l>
         <l>Receiue vs when we hence depart.</l>
         <l>
            <note n="e" place="margin">Ib. pag. 47.</note>The guiltlesse bands <hi>VNBIND,</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Blind men their sight <hi>ASSVRE:</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Ill things from vs expell,</l>
         <l>All good for vs procure.</l>
         <l>A mother shew thy selfe,</l>
         <l>He takes our plaints by thee,</l>
         <l>That being for vs borne,</l>
         <l>Vouchsafed thy sonne to be.</l>
         <l>Grant that our life be pure,</l>
         <l>Make safe for vs the way,</l>
         <l>That while we Iesus see,</l>
         <l>Our ioy may last for ay.</l>
      </q> Againe:
<q>
         <note n="f" place="margin">Missal. Sarisb. 8. Septēb. Alle celeste.</note>O Virgin, the only chast mother, loosing our sinnes, giue the kingdom where the blessed companies do raigne: for thou as Queene of the world, art able to do all things, and <hi>WITH THY SONNE DISPOSEST ALL RIGHTS.</hi>
      </q>
      <pb facs="16"/> Againe:
<q>
         <note n="g" place="margin">Antidotar. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimae. p. 101.</note>O Marie, the starre of the sea, the hauen of health to such as suffer ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, the godly guide, the sweetest patron of the miserable, the learnedst <hi>ADVOCATE</hi> of the guiltie, the onely <hi>HOPE</hi> of the desperate, the <hi>SAVIOVR</hi> of sinners: I beseech thee at my last day enlighten me with the beames of thy most cleare face. Then there is no other hope but thou. <hi>SAVE ME Ô SAVIORESSE: REDEEME ME Ô REDEEMER:</hi> my sinnes loade me, the flesh defileth me, the diuell lieth in waite, &amp;c.<note n="h" place="margin">Hist. chor. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust. cōmemor. virgin. Mariae.</note> Thou calledst thy selfe the Handmaid of Iesu Christ, but as Gods law teacheth, thou art <hi>HIS LADY</hi> mistris: for right and reason willeth that the <hi>MOTHER BE ABOVE THE SONNE.</hi> Therefore pray him humbly, and <hi>COMMAVND HIM FROM ABOVE</hi> that he leade vs to his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome at the worlds end.</q> It is vnpossible to excuse this kind of praying from formall idolatry, wherein the same titles are giuen to the Saints, and the same things by the same merits asked of them, that appertaine to Christ alone. And yet<note n="i" place="margin">Suar. tom. 2. disp. 23. per to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. Bellar. de Sāct. beatit. c. 17</note> the Iesuites at this day excuse it, and will not suffer it to be reformed. Yea we find in the writings of the most learned Papists that are, things touching the virgin Mary as bad, and worse then all this. Dodechinus<note n="k" place="margin">Append. ad Maria. Scot. pa. 470.</note> writeth, that <hi>an infant lying in the cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, saw the virgine Mary standing before the tribunall seate of Christ, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king most earnest intercession for the world.</hi> Biel<note n="l" place="margin">In Cano. lect. 8. p. 233.</note> saith, <hi>We flie principally to the blessed Virgine, the Queene of heauen, which is signified in Hester the Queene, who coming to appease king Assuerus, he said vnto her, It shal be giuen thee, though thou aske the halfe of my kingdome. So the Father of heauen hauing his iustice and his mercie as the chiefest goods of his kingdome, keeping his iustice to himselfe, sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred his mercy to the Virgine mother.</hi> And<note n="m" place="margin">Specul. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empl. d. 7. n. 41.</note> they tell a vision, how <hi>Christ preparing to iudge the world, there were two ladders set that reached to heauen: the one red, at the top whereof Christ sate: the other white, at the top whereof the virgine Marie sate: and when the Friers could not get vp by the red ladder of Christ, but euermore fell downe, Saint Francis called them to the white ladder of our Ladie, and there they were receiued.</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">Bern. Senens. ser. 51. c. 3.</note> Another saith, that <hi>Christ was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate more for the redemption of the blessed virgine then for all mankind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides.</hi> Bozius<note n="o" place="margin">De sign. eccl. tom. 1. pag. 679. &amp; 681.</note> saith, <hi>The victory obtained ouer the diuell, is to be ascribed altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Christ himselfe: but by Christ it must also principally be ascribed to the virgine Mary. Seeing the blessed Virgine is the most noble part of the Church, it is chiefly referred to her to be Heuab, which signifieth the mother of the liuing: namely because by the vertue of Christ, Marie principally giueth eternall life to mankind, and through her we increase in the faith, and are multiplied in charitie, and replenish heauen. By the two Cherubins vpon the Arke, were signified Christ and Marie, through whom God is mercifull, and heareth our prayers. There must needs be something in the Church to answer those old ceremonies. Wherefore in the Church there must needs be some woman, who being blessed with Christs gift and merits, may beare all men to God, and by whom God may be mercifull to vs.</hi> But this that Galatinus writeth, deserueth the noting: he saith,<note n="p" place="margin">De Arcan. Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thol. verit. pag. 489.</note> that FOR THE LOVE OF IESVS AND MARY, GOD CREATED THE WORLD. <hi>For the loue of the vndefiled Virgine, who is the wisedome of the world, God made heauen
<pb facs="17"/> and earth: and it was not onely made for her loue, but also preserued: for it could no way stand, our deeds are so euill,</hi> BVT THAT SHE BY PRAYING FOR VS MERCIFVLLY VPHOLDETH IT.<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 515.</note>
      <hi>Adam following sinne incurred death, but the glorious Virgine and her Sonne being no partakers of Adams sinne, and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether free from originall sinne, of right were to be impassible and immortall. But forsomuch as the death of Christ was needfull for the redemption of mankind, therefore it was necessary that the body of Christ should be passible and mortall: and so likewise the immaculate Virgine being to beare a Sonne passible and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, which was to be one flesh with her, and that could not naturally be if she were impassible and immortall, therefore she was also necessarily mortall; and so both the mother and the sonne died.</hi> THE DEATH AND PASSION OF CHRIST AND THE HOLY VIRGIN, WAS FOR THE REDEMPTION OF MANKIND. <hi>It was impossible she should haue died afore the passion of her Sonne. The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reason is, that</hi> SHE ALSO MIGHT COME BETWEENE (God and vs) FOR THE REMISSION OF SINNE, <hi>seeing all things must come betweene for the remission, that came betweene when Adam did it.</hi> Thus they ioyne the virgine Marie with Christ, in the very worke of our redemption, and ascribe to her, no lesse then to him the execution of all Gods mercies toward vs. Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git in her reuelations<note n="q" place="margin">Pag. 21.</note> saith. the virgin Mary told her, that AS ADAM AND EVE SOLD THE WORLD FOR ONE APPLE,<note n="*" place="margin">Filius meus &amp; ego redemimus mundum quasi cúm vno corde.</note> SO HER SONNE AND SHE REDEEMED THE WORLD WITH ONE HEART. Thus they haue ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a creature with Christ, and giuen his honour to another; yea that honour of redeeming and sustaining the Church, which no creature is capable of. And this idolatry they haue committed not with the blessed Virgine alone, (who is <hi>blessed and honorable, though not to be worshipped, but her selfe worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him that was borne of her flesh,</hi>
      <note n="r" place="margin">Lib. 3.</note> saith Epiphanius) but euen with the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest of their Saints, that we may know in what vile account they hold Christ the Sauiour.<note n="s" place="margin">Lib. Conform. Francis. pa. 304.</note> They say, he imprinted his fiue wounds vpon Francis of Assise the Frier; as if he also were to suffer for the world, and redeeme mankind: and market<note n="t" place="margin">Posseuin. bibl. select. p. 295.</note> the verses of Tursellinus the Iesuite, concerning the same:
<q>
         <l>Exue Franciscum tunica lacero{que} cucullo,</l>
         <l>Qui Franciscus erat iam tibi Christus erit:</l>
         <l>Francisci exuuiis, (si quâ licet) indue Christum</l>
         <l>Iam Franciscus erit qui modò Christus erat.</l>
         <l>Strip Francis from his coate and cowle, all nak'd, and you shall see,</l>
         <l>He that euen Saint Francis was, to Christ will turned be:</l>
         <l>Againe, put Francis coate and cowle on Christ <hi>(and marke the lier)</hi>
         </l>
         <l>He that euen now was Iesus Christ, will Francis be <hi>(the Frier.)</hi>
         </l>
      </q> The same conceit, or a worse,<note n="u" place="margin">Boz. de sign. eccles. tom. 2. pag. 200.</note> is thus expressed by another Iesuit, Fr. Bencius.
<q>
         <l>Sancte patrum, spirans Christi exspirantis imago</l>
         <l>Tempore quam nullo deleat vlla dies:</l>
         <l>Quas etenim fers ipse manus, fers ipse pedes{que},</l>
         <l>Has tulit ille manus, has tulit ille pedes.</l>
         <l>Nec minus &amp; teli transfixum cuspide pectus,</l>
         <l>Quale tibi patulo pectore vulnus biat:</l>
         <pb facs="17"/>
         <l>Cuncta estis similes: illum qui fortè verentur</l>
         <l>Reddere, te saltem cur imitentur habent.</l>
         <l>O holy Francis that of Christ, dying vpon the tree,</l>
         <l>The very breathing image art, for euer so to be:</l>
         <l>What hands thou bear'st, what feet thou hast, such hands such feet had he,</l>
         <l>And such a wound wide in his brest, as in thy brest we see.</l>
         <l>In all things you are both alike, that he which is ashamed,</l>
         <l>Him, t'imitate, may follow him at least, and not be blamed.</l>
      </q> Out of all this, the Reader must obserue what the Church of Rome ascribeth to Saints, and how farre they intrude them into the office of Christ: and then take a scantling thereby of the religion, and iudge whether it be the Church of God that offereth this iniury to his Sonne.</p>
   <p n="15">15 Let people therefore open their eyes and view the Papacie a title bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, how it hath incroched vpon heauen and earth; that not the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, or the states of the world, or the consciences of men haue escaped the malice thereof, but it is busily doing with them all; the which, me thinketh, should moue them if no other thing could be obiected. For what tyrannie and vsurpation is it thus to loade the world with their traditions? and fill the Church with more then Iewish idolatry and superstition? Moreouer, what had the Councell of Trent to do, now after 1500. yeares, to make a new Creede and profession of faith, which, euen the people of their owne Church were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bound to before? This is a point worth the looking at, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Rome should take vpon him to adde twelue more articles to the Creed, and to bind men by oath and confession to receiue them. This shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him to be the same<note n="x" place="margin">2. Thess. 2.4.</note>
      <hi>that sitteth in the Temple of God, exalting himselfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all that is God,</hi> and his people to be in a miserable state, that must haue the matter of their faith increased, diminished, and changed at his deuotion. I will let downe this new Creed word for word, that such as haue not seene it may consider thereof, and see the new faith which the Pope hath taught his children. Thus it lieth in the Popes<note n="y" place="margin">Bulla Pij 4. super forma iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramenti pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessionis fidei.</note> Bull, which calleth it THE PVBLICKE PROFESSION OF THE ORTHODOXAL FAITH, TO BE VNI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORMLY OBSERVED AND PROFESSED.<note n="z" place="margin">THE NEW CREED OF THE CHVRCH OF ROME.</note>
      <hi>I. N. do with firme faith beleeue and professe all and singular things contained in the Creed which the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church vseth: namely, I beleeue in one God the Father almightie, maker of heauen and earth, and of all things visible and inuisible. And in one Lord Iesus Christ the onely begotten Sonne of God, borne of his Father before all worlds, God of God, light of light, very God of very God, begotten not made, being consubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall with the Father, by whom all things were made: who for vs men and for our saluation came downe from heauen, and was incarnate by the holy Ghost of the Virgin Mary, and was made man: crucified also for vs vnder Pontius Pilate, suffered, and was buried, and rose againe the third day according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ascended into heauen, and sitteth at the right hand of his Father, and shall come againe with glory to iudge the quicke and the dead, whose kingdome shall haue no end: and in the holy Ghost the Lord and giuer of life, who procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from the Father and the Sonne, who with the Father and the Sonne is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped
<pb facs="18"/> and glorified, who spake by the Prophets. And I beleeue one Holy, Catholick, and Apostolicke Church. J beleeue one Baptisme for the remission of sinnes, and I looke for the resurrection of the dead, and the life of the world to come. Amen. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Apostolick and Ecclesiasticall</hi> TRADITIONS, <hi>and other obseruances and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions of that Church do I firmly admit and embrace. Also the sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> according to</hi> THAT SENCE WHICH OVR MOTHER THE CHVRCH HATH HOLDEN AND DOTH HOLD <hi>(whose right it is to iudge of the true sence and interpretation of holy Scriptures) do I admit. Neither will I euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and expound it but according to the vniforme consent of the Fathers. I do <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> also confesse that there be truly and properly</hi> SEVEN SACRAMENTS <hi>of the new law, instituted by our Lord Iesus Christ, and necessary to the saluation of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, though all be not for euery man: that is to say, Baptisme, Confirmation, the Eucharist, Penance, extreme Vnction, Order, and Mariage: and that they confer grace, and that among these Baptisme, Confirmation and Order cannot be reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated without sacriledge. Also the receiued and approued rites of the Catholicke Church vsed in the solemne administration of all the aforesaid Sacraments, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and admit. All and euery the things which concerning</hi> ORIGINALL SIN <hi>and</hi> IVSTIFICATION, <hi>were defined and declared in the holy Councell of Trent, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> I embrace and receiue. Also I confesse that in the</hi> MASSE <hi>is offered to God a true, proper, and propitiatory sacrifice for the quicke and the dead: and that in the holy</hi>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> EVCHARIST <hi>is truly, really, and substantially the body and blood, with the soule and Diuinitie of our Lord Iesu Christ; and that there is made a conuersion of the whole substance of the bread into his body, and of the whole substance of the wine into his bloud; which conuersion the Catholick Church calleth</hi> TRANSVBSTANTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ATION. <hi>I confesse also that vnder</hi> ONE KIND ONLY, <hi>all &amp; whole Christ, and the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> true Sacrament is receiued. I do constantly hold there is a</hi> PVRGATORY, <hi>and the soules detained there are holpe by the suffrages of the faithful. And likewise that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> the</hi> SAINTS <hi>raigning with Christ, are to be worshipped and prayed vnto. And that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> they offer their prayers to God for vs: and that their</hi> RELICKS <hi>are to be worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. And most firmly I auouch that the</hi> IMAGES <hi>of Christ, and the Mother of God alwayes a Virgin, and other Saints, are to be had and retained, and that to them <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> due honor and veneration is to be giuen. Also that the power of</hi> INDVLGENCES <hi>was left by Christ in the Church; and I affirme the vse thereof to be most wholsome <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> to Christs people. That the Holy, Catholicke and Apostolicke</hi> ROMANE CHVRCH <hi>is the mother and mistris of all Churches, I acknowledge: and I vow and sweare true obedience to the Bishop of Rome, the successor of S. Peter the Prince of the Apostles <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> and the Vicar of Iesus Christ. And</hi> AL OTHER <hi>things likewise do I vndoubtingly receiue and confesse which are deliuered, defined and declared by the sacred ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and generall Councels, and especially the holy Councel of Trident: and withal I condemne, reiect, and accurse all things that are contrary hereunto, and all here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies whatsoeuer, condemned, reiected and accursed by the Church: and that I will be carefull this true Catholicke faith (out of the which no man can be saued, which at this time I willingly professe and truly hold) be constantly (with Gods helpe) retained and confessed, whole and inuiolate to the last gaspe, and by those that are vnder me, or such as I shall haue charge ouer in my calling, holden, taught
<pb facs="18"/> and preached, to the vttermost of my power: I the said N. promise, vow, &amp; sweare, so God me help, and his holy Gospels.</hi> The Schoolmen &amp; Lawyers were long ago in hand with this question, whether the Pope had authoritie to make a new Creed? And because they were long tempering with it, and the affirmatiue seemed a strange position, we maruelled what they would make of it. But now we see they meant in good earnest indeed, and this belike was the Creed whereof the Pope was with child, and all his Church must receiue it. This is a strange presumption, that taking vpon them to bring new matter of faith into the Church, and to make that necessary to be beleeued for saluatiō, which before was not so: yet their people should be so blind as not obserue it. Suarez the Iesuit,<note n="a" place="margin">Tom. 2. p. 30.</note>
      <hi>The matter may come to that passe, that without any new &amp; explicate reuelation, the Church may haue sufficient motiues for the defining of this</hi> (or that) <hi>veritie, by the infolded and still reuelation of God: for this manner of defining</hi> (whereby that which was not before, is now made an article of faith) <hi>it is sufficient, that any supernaturall veritie be infoldedly contained in tradition or Scripture; that the common consent of the Church, (by which the holy Ghost often explicates traditions and declares Scripture) increasing, the Church at the length may bring in her determination; which hath the force of a certaine diuine reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in respect of vs. This consent of the Church may so increase, that at the length she may simply and absolutely define it.</hi> This sheweth plainly that they thinke the Pope hath power to make a new Creed; and hereby the world may see that vnder pretence of <hi>things lying hidden in the Church, and the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the Church increasing,</hi> the Pope may multiply the matters of faith, and so fit in the conscience as he pleaseth.</p>
   <p n="16">16 It is no small griefe to all that are well minded, to see this more then Egyptian bondage, whererein so many people liue; but yet if any man looke attentiuely vpon it, the matter will not seeme so strange. First, their custome and long continuance in blindnesse bindeth them in, there being nothing harder then to breake an ignorant man of his custome.<note n="b" place="margin">De Doctrin. Christ. l. 4. c. 24.</note> Saint Austin coming to Caesarea, <hi>where the people had an ancient custome once a yeare, for certaine daies together, to diuide themselues into parts, and throw stones one at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, whereby many were slaine:</hi> found it an exceeding hard matter to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade them from it. Then the societie and alliance, whereby they are linked one to another, restraineth them; being ashamed to depart with their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintaince, and the things which long continuance of friends hath inured them to. This is noted by S. Basil in the vulgar of his time, seduced by Arius: <hi>There is,</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Ep. 70.</note> saith he, <hi>small hope of reducing them to the truth, who are linked to heretickes, with the band of long amitie.</hi> And Saint Austin yeeldeth the same reason why the Donatists could so hardly be reclaimed. <hi>How many,</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Ep. 48. ad Vincent.</note> saith he, <hi>being moued with the truth, would euen presently haue bene good Catholickes, and yet deferred it daily, fearing the offence of their friends? How many did, not the truth, but the heauy band of obdurate custome, hold together; who thought th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Church to be with Donatus, because their security made them slouthfull and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie in searching the truth? How many were hindred by the rumours and slanders that went of vs? How many stucke to Donatus, because there they were borne, and
<pb facs="19"/> no man constrained them to depart thence, and go to the Catholicke Church?</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, they are in the hands of skilfull workemen and wary leaders, that know how to entertaine and hold them, and with faire words to deceiue the simple: whose first worke, when they seaze vpon a Proselite, alway is to teach him foure conclusions, before he go any further: and I wonder their drift therein is not espied. First that the Protestants are heretickes, and their Church come vp but lately, and therfore he must neuer heare any Protestant or regard what he saith in the matter of religion. Next, that the Romane Church is the true Church, wherein onely saluation is to be found: and this Church can erre and teach false, in nothing. Thirdly, that the Scriptures are obscure, imperfect, troublesome, and therefore it is not for simple men to meddle with them, or once to hope that they cā therby come to any certain resolutiō. And then last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that in all things he must referre himselfe to his mother the Church, and his ghostly father, to whose cure God hath committed him, whose directions if he will follow resolutely, he may be carelesse in all the rest. When silly creatures haue drunke in these principles, (which a wise man will examine before he beleeue) what maruell is it if they be hardly conuerted? and when their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers haue thus hedged them in, and taken away their eyes, their eares, their vnderstanding, it is no wonder if they be easily trained into any thing.</p>
   <p n="17">17 Who are againe and againe to be admonished that they looke into these things, because no lesse then the saluation of their soules lieth vpon it: and it is the foolishest thing in world in matters of such consequence to rely on the persons of men, or our owne affection. For which cause, and for whose sakes, I have penned this booke, to shew the full triall of such motiues as they seeme to stand vpon. And whosoeuer will reade it attentiuely, shall finde therein a iust and complete answer to the principallest things that are obiected against our Church. Yea he shal reape this benefit by reading it, that he shall see the very point where diuers questions sticke, that are much talked of, but little vnderstood by many. I haue done it moderately, and with all the respect of my aduersary that I could. I haue meddled with the persons of no man, but onely debated the cause, and followed the argument as it led me. And I will freely confesse that my aduersaries kinde of writing, which I much liked, allured me to answer him, because as it is schollerlike performed, so it bringeth aboord the best questions &amp; reasons that are ordinarily discoursed. His writing is borrowed wholly frō Gregory of Valentia his Analysis fidei, &amp; tract. de obiecto fidei: who is as acute an aduersarie as any this day dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth against vs. In my answer I hold this course throughout, to lay the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or question plainly downe, and then to answer it directly and perspicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, that the reader may vnderstand what is said. And because the iudgement of the ancient Church is much obiected against vs, I haue indeuoured to cleare that point also, by shewing in euery question, as the cause requireth, the practise of the Primitiue Church, and the opinions of the fathers, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the points. And although in their time they knew not of our questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (the Papacy being risen since their dayes) whereby they might speake directly as witnesses betweene vs; yet teaching the truth of the Gospell, which
<pb facs="19"/> the Papists haue corrupted, they shew who be the innouators; and to this day strike the Church of Rome as if they liued and saw it: wherein we are so well assured, that we embrace that kind of triall, which is by antiquity, most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly, and daily finde our aduersaries to be galled thereby.<note n="e" place="margin">Sim. Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrast. vit. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan.</note> The Legend telleth, that <hi>Epiphanius being dead, as he lay on the ground, and one looking cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously at him, gaue him such a blow with his foote, that he strooke the winde out of his belly.</hi> Thus the Fathers dead in their graues, yet strike our aduersaries to the ground with their feete, that if the Pope were not made interpreter to helpe at a dead lift, they could not stand an houre. Which is such a iest that no doubt themselues smile at it. For if the Fathers rule the questions of faith, and the Pope rule the Fathers, and the Church of Rome the Pope; this wil be like<note n="f" place="margin">Plutarck.</note> the merry conceite of a little boy in Athens, the sonne of Themistocles: that pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ying among his companions would tel them he could rule all Athens: For, saith he, <hi>my father can rule Athens, and my mother can rule my father, and I can rule my mother.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="18">18. Againe, in all the questions handled I haue confirmed our owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and expositions, and confuted our aduersaries, by the authoritie and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies of the Papists themselues: which course I dare vndertake may be maintained in all the questions betweene vs: and I haue obserued it princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, to make it appeare, that the Romish faith came in by the faction of some particular persons, and was alway resisted as it grew, and contradicted by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men; and that our aduersaries mouths may be stopped when they shall see some learned man or other in their owne Church to hold the same things that we do.<note n="g" place="margin">Refert sed ipsa nosse quae messemnecant Zizaniorum se mina Prud. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheos.</note> The Church of God hath alway thought this a fit course. Diony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius Alexandrinus<note n="h" place="margin">Niceph. l. 6. c. 8.</note> said of himselfe, that <hi>he vsed somtime to be occupied in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the writings and treatises of heretickes, though it something polluted his mind with touching their vncleane opinions; because he reaped this profit therby, that he might the easilier refell them, and the more execrate &amp; detest them.</hi> If any will take vpon him to confute me, the lawes of Christian conference, specially in the points of faith, bind him, 1. to do it temperately, abstaining from rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and reproaching. 2. perspicuously, that I may certainly know his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning 3. honestly, that what I say be faithfully set downe, and what I proue my sayings by, be not dissembled. For I affirm nothing that concerneth the cause, but I proue it, either in the text by reason, or in the margent by authoritie, which I would not haue dissembled, or (according to an vsuall trade taken vp of late among them) traduced with taunts and outcries, as if it were false alledged, vntill it appeare to be so indeed. Which if he performe, I shall thinke my lot the better to haue met with so profitable an aduersarie. And so wishing the good Reader that with loue to all men, and reuerence to Gods truth, and care to leade a sanctified life, he would pursue the cause of religion: I take my leaue, beseeching our Lord Christ by the power of his spirit, to make way for the truth in all our hearts. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>