<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101971_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13201</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23498</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101971</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A newe reuenge for an olde grudge. Lately sette forth by I.S. VVho buildeth not vpon sure grounde, hath often beene, and now is founde a losse of time, a vaine expence, thus saith Goddes worde. An ouerthrowe of his presence. Thankes to the Lorde</title>
                 <author>Sutton, J.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Coldock (Coldoke), Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or asmuche as we are taught in the firste of <hi>Iosua,</hi> that in the booke of <hi>God</hi> we should recorde day and night: and also be circumspecte to doo accordyng to the same, that our wayes might prosper: so assuredly, they that in that sort trauell, and make ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a willinge exercise, shall finde therin such Felicitie, such fruitefulnes, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte,
<pb facs="3"/> as I (oh Christian Reader) am not with my penne able to expresse: for in the Scriptures is wealth to be founde for those that be in miserie: helth for such as be sicke: lighte to expell darkenesse: comfort to those that be afflicted: in extreme perill, present preseruation: and for the defence and sauegarde of suche as are of the householde of Faithe, there is also to be fownde
<pb facs="3"/> both armour and weapō, to wage battel with that aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciēt enemie Satan: of whom as the sacred <hi>Scriptures</hi> make mention, to haue bene euen from the beginninge an vtter enemie to <hi>Christ,</hi> his Gospell, and professours of the same: and sekinge in sundrie wise through his sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teltie to subuert the, whome although the glorious <hi>God</hi> at no time leaueth vndefen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to the greater cōfusion
<pb facs="4"/> and shame of that subtile Serpent, yet for al that sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth he not still to stirre vp his Hellish armie, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to make new attemptes to trouble and assayle the flocke and famelie of the Faithfull: and that onely as muche as in them is, to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse, and darken the light of the glorious Gospel of our <hi>Sauiour Iesus Christe,</hi> which comfortablie shineth amongst vs, which through
<pb facs="4"/> Christe wee haue receiued, whiche we now enioye, and are partakers of (to God be thākes therfore) who graūt the same a free passage tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the whole worlde, to the more magnifiynge of his mightie name, the cōtinuall comforte of his Church, and vtter destruction of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and aduersaries of the same, For euer. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>