<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE LORD, AND REVEREND FATHER in God, IOHN, by diuine prouidence Bishop of LINCOLNE, Lord Keeper of the Great Seale of ENGLAND.</title>
           <author>Ailesbury, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101513_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00003</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1000</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101513</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE LORD, AND REVEREND FATHER in God, IOHN, by diuine prouidence Bishop of LINCOLNE, Lord Keeper of the Great Seale of ENGLAND.</title>
                 <author>Ailesbury, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached at Paules-Crosse the second day of Iune, being the last Sunday in Easter terme. 1622. By Thomas Ailesbury student in diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Ailesbury, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Becket, Leonard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Eld (Elide), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wilson, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 52 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE LORD, AND REVEREND FATHER in God, <hi>IOHN,</hi> by diuine prouidence <hi>Bishop of</hi> LINCOLNE, <hi>Lord Keeper</hi> of the Great Seale of ENGLAND.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all created things <hi>(Right Honorable)</hi> which doe in their kinde set forth the Creators greatnesse, <hi>Coeli enarrant, &amp;c:</hi> And in the firmament the Heauens glory; the Sunne, <hi>In Sole posuit tabernaculum suum:</hi> And in the Sunne these three, <hi>The glorious light, piercing beames,</hi> and <hi>refreshing
<pb facs="3"/> heat</hi> thereof draw with them most admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
   <p>Man an earthly Sunne, amazeth man to consider what is in man: But when these three, <hi>Learning, Vertue,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> meet in one man, as in one <hi>Center,</hi> who can but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, who can but to such a man owe, and tender all <hi>obseruancie?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>From hence is that <hi>Scitum</hi> of a knowing man; <hi>Honorem esse escam, Doctrinam hamum, Virtutem rete amorís.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But <hi>quorsum ista?</hi> Say that all these (as all must say who will speake the truth) not onely are, but doe after a goodly propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion shine in your Lordship; shall it not be said presumption in me (who am as yet but a twig of the <hi>Leviticall</hi> Tree,) to offer my fruits (which may seem perhaps but <hi>leaues,</hi>) and that first of all to your Selfe, who are so firme, so fruitfull, and so profitable a root, both in our Church, &amp; Common-wealth?</p>
   <p>Yet because both Church, and Common-wealth doe truly say that of You, which <hi>St. Bernard</hi> hoped he might say of his <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius,
<pb facs="3"/> In te facta est mutatio, non de te; nec priori statui tuo successit promotio, sed accessit:</hi> I repaire to your Lordship, though I bring no more to you then <hi>Noahs Doue</hi> did to him; <hi>A little branch in my mouth;</hi> being very sensible, that seeing it sprang from a tree in Gods garden, that the onely putting forth of your hand may not onely take me that bring it into the <hi>Arke;</hi> but giue to it growth with a plenteous blessing; which being all my suit to your Lordship;</p>
   <p>I humbly beseech the God of heauen, to assist you with his grace, <hi>foeliciter currere, ac foeliciùs in Christi pietate consummare,</hi> to the great good of Church, and Common-wealth here, and to the vnspeakable good of your owne soule, and body hereafter.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours vnfainedly devoted in all obseruance, and dutie, <hi>THOMAS AILESBVRY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>