<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ Hadrianus Iunius of Harlem, D. in Physicke, to the gentle Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101779_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00437</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10566</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101779</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ Hadrianus Iunius of Harlem, D. in Physicke, to the gentle Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lyves, of philosophers and oratours: vvritten in Greeke, by Eunapius, of the cittie of Sardeis in Lydia. Brought into light, translated into Latine, and dedicated to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, our moste gracious princesse and soueraigne, Queene Elizabeth. By the great learned man, Hadrianus Iunius Hornanus. 1568. And now set foorth in English, at his request: and dedicated to the right Honourable, the Lord Chauncellour of England. 1579</title>
                 <author>Eunapius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 43, 5 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>❧ <hi>Hadrianus Iunius of Harlem, D. in Physicke, to the gentle Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Yrus</hi> in <hi>Xenophon,</hi> beeing at the poynt of death, did admonish his Children, that the moste holsome and best doctrine was to be gathered of examples passed. They can be found in no place so purely, as in Histories (which some haue called the Mistresse of Lyfe, and the soule of trueth:) wherin, both the matter and acts of priuate men, and also vniuersal affaires, be propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be red, as in a Glas before the eyes. I being wholy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to this labour, whiles I make an History of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to instruct the present age, and our posteritie, I was the firste that tooke in hand, to enterpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e Eunapius, a Greeke wrighter by leysure, pulled out of darkenes: yet maymed and spotted in manye places, and as obscure as might be, for the short Phrase of speaking, peculiar to the nature of that age: Notwithstanding it hath pleasantnesse, instilling an higher puritie of doctrine in the minde, and deliuereth knowledge, of things omitted and vnknown of other wrighters. Also more destrous, to expresse the sentence, then the stile and conduct of the wordes, and rather to cleane to the eares, then ouer vare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to leaue them.</p>
   <p>And though be inueieth somewhat sharply against Monkes, in whose contemplations, the foundation of Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, was layd &amp; taught in the time of <hi>Constantine</hi> the great: who woulde not suffer that an Infidell, and an enemye, of the faith and trueth? Seeing we suffer, reade, cary about, and weare with handes, both night and day, <hi>Porphirius,</hi> the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary of Christianitye, <hi>Luciane,</hi> the obstinate scorner of our Sauiour, and <hi>Iuliane,</hi> the reuolter, persecutor of the <hi>Galilees:</hi> (for so doth he call thē that profes Christ) whom, if he had had longer life, he would vtterly haue bestroyed. Therfore good men shall take an iniurye spoken of a common enemye of Christes name, as not spoken: and cast it forth and contemne it: Yea, shall rather turne the scorne into their glory.</p>
   <closer>Farewell and enioy.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>