<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the READER.</title>
           <author>Whitfeld, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101726_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15114</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25410</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101726</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the READER.</title>
                 <author>Whitfeld, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Some helpes to stirre up to Christian dvties : Wherein is explained the nature of the dnty [sic] of stirring vp ourselves. Instances are given in the most necessary Christian duties. Some questions about this subiect are profitably resolved. By Henry Whitfeld B D. preacher of Gods word, at Ockley in Surrey</title>
                 <author>Whitfield, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bartlet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 228, that is 230 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the <hi>READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr spirituall life being the most choyce and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous treasure that we carry about us in these our earthen vessels, in the lively sense and operations of which consists the very life of our lives, and the the height of our comfort and solace here below: How needfull is it that we consider of all meanes, and wayes, by which this life may be preserved, and inlarged, that we may have it in more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. And this we should the rather doe, both in regard of
<pb facs="7"/> those inward annoyances, which flowing from our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, doe cause many faintings, and decayings even in the best, as also in regard of those evils, which comming from without, and breaking in upon this life, do wondrously waste, weaken, and hinder the operations of it. Now as it fares with our naturall life, that stirring and exercise proves specially helpefull for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of it; so that which makes our spirituall life more lively, and fils it with stronger spirits, and activenesse, is the exercising of the severall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and faculties of it, the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gifts and graces of it, in all those acts and wayes in which it is to put forth it selfe. The serious thought of which hath caused me (Christian Reader) to make this Eslay, and to come to thy helpe in what I might in this short discourse following:
<pb facs="7"/> The matter I know is necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and of generall use for all Gods people, though the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of handling of it will not be found so notionall, accurate, or judicious; yet finding none, as I could call to minde, that had travelled in this Subject, I thought my weaknesses in this kinde might bee sheltered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my desire of a more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall good.</p>
   <p>I considered also I had many of my Christian friends, and neerest kindred farre removed from mee, who being part of my care, I was willing to put somewhat into their hands, which might, not onely bee as a pledge of my love to them, and some direction for them, but might also (by Gods bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing) have somewhat in it to quicken them up in their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian course. I saw my glasse running out apace, and I knew it would bee a griefe of heart
<pb facs="8"/> unto me, if either they or I had beene called for hence, before I had left with them some proofe of my care and love, which I conceived might best be effected this way.</p>
   <p>I viewed also the way, and course of many professours of Religion, even of such as are counted of the forwarder sort; where I found much sloth, luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmenesse, and backsliding. I thought if I could throw but a sparke into the heart of any such, who did know what a fire it might kindle: In many also (though well minded) there is plainly to be seene a lownesse, and flatnesse of spirit, together with a contentednesse to goe an easie and ordinary pace in their Duties and performances: Now if I could but a little heighten the affections, desires and endevours of such, and cause them somewhat to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance and put forward, it
<pb facs="8"/> would bee abundant recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for what-ever paines I could bestow in this kind.</p>
   <p>I found also I had a dull and sluggish heart of my owne, which by this meanes might haply be quickned up, and that thus setting rules, and lawes to my selfe, what I had written might be of further use for me for the time to come.</p>
   <p>Some fruit also, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance I found amongst such, where I preached over these Notes, in a shorter manner. All which layed together have now prevailed with me to doe that which I never intended to do, <hi>viz.</hi> to give way to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing of them, and bringing them into a more open light. What-ever I have done, I offer it unto thy view, and submit it to thy loving censure; hoping, that if thou gaine ought by what is written, thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him at the Throne of
<pb facs="9"/> grace, whose ayme and end was meerly thy profiting. And thus, beseeching the Lord in mercy to guide us with the Spirit of wisdome and meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in writing and reading, that we may be able to give up a comfortable account of both in the great day of our recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord Iesus Christ,</hi> H. WHITFELD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>