<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>EDMOND REEVE
His Reasons
For bovving to Lords-Tables, and placing them
Altar-vvise, related and refuted.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101532_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10197</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20474</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101532</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>EDMOND REEVE
His Reasons
For bovving to Lords-Tables, and placing them
Altar-vvise, related and refuted.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A quench-coale. Or A briefe disquisition and inquirie, in vvhat place of the church or chancell the Lords-table ought to be situated, especially vvhen the Sacrament is administered? : VVherein is evidently proved, that the Lords-table ought to be placed in the midst of the church, chancell, or quire north and south, not altar-wise, with one side against the wall: that it neither is nor ought to be stiled an altar; that Christians have no other altar but Christ alone, who hath abolished all other altars, which are either heathenish, Jewish, or popish, and not tollerable among Christians. All the pretences, authorities, arguments of Mr. Richard Shelford, Edmond Reeve, Dr. John Pocklington, and a late Coale from the altar, to the contrary in defence of altars, calling the Lords-table an altar, or placing it altarwise, are here likewise fully answered and proved to be vaine or forged. By a well-wisher to the truth of God, and the Church of England</title>
                 <author>Prynne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>‘Richt Right’ Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78, 2, 358, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb n="53" facs="27"/>
   <head>EDMOND REEVE
His Reasons
For bovving to Lords-Tables, and placing them
Altar-vvise, related and refuted.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>CHISTIAN READER,</hi> before I entertaine thee
with a serious Epistle, give me leave to detaine thee a little
with some late Paradoxes in <hi>Edmond Reeve,</hi> printed by Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense,
to prove the necessity &amp; Lawfulnes of bowīg to and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the Altar and Communion. Table at our entring in
and going out of the Church, to refresh thy spirits withall.
His first reason is this.</p>
   <p>
      <q>
         <note n="a" place="margin">The Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Booke Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, p. 132.</note> As the people of God being entred into Gods house
(to wit, the Temple of Ierusalem) did worship towards
the Sanctuary or mercy Seate from which he was heard
speaking (not their Altars or Shew-bread-Tables) so now
also ought EVERY ONE being come into Gods house,
to prostrate himselfe, that is, make low obeysance towards
Gods mercy Seare, being the uppermost part of our
Temples, unto Almighty God there.</q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb n="54" facs="28"/>
This reason is properly reduced into these two Logicall
Arguments, point-blanke against his Conclusion.</p>
   <p>
      <q>1. The Jewes worshipped towards the Sanctuary and
mercy Seate, from which God was heard speaking (a
Type of our Pulpits and Reading Pewes, if of any thing;)
not towards their Altars or Tables:</q>
   </p>
   <p>Ergo, EVERY ONE <hi>now also ought to bow to Gods mercy
Seate,</hi> (the Pulpit and Reading Pew, from which he is heard
speaking in his Word; not unto Altars and Tables.</p>
   <p>
      <q>2. Every one ought to prostrate himselfe towards the
uppermost part of our Temples, unto Almightie God there:</q>
But the Roofes of our Temples, at least the East wall of them,
in the Authors sence, not the Table or Akar (or our Pulpits
standing higher then they) <hi>are the uppermost part of our
Temples.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <q>Ergo, we must prostrate ourselves towards them to God
there; Not towards the Table or Altar.</q>
   </p>
   <p>But how then a prostration of the body towards the
ground the lower part of the Temple, can be a prostration
towards the Roofe or upper part of the Church, when as it
removes the body further from it (unlesse Mr. <hi>Reeve</hi> can tell
me how a man may prostrate himselfe upward) I cannot yet
discerne.</p>
   <p>
      <q>2. His second Argument is this:<note place="margin">Ibidem p: 134.</note> The Divine wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
of the Church calling the Communion-Table Gods
Board, doth give us to understand, that that is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
the peculiar Seat of God within the Temple.
(For after a Church or Chappell is consecrated by a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop,
Gods gracious presence is ever at his mercy Seate,
saith the Margent) and therefore towards it unto God
there, we are to make low obeysance, whensoever we come
<pb n="55" facs="28"/>
into Gods house, to pray. Also as the Chaire of State is
alwayes to be honoured, though the person of the Royall
Majesty be not seene there: So is <hi>GODS BOARD EVER
TO HAVE DUE REVERENCE</hi> (therefore this
bowing is done &amp; due to the Board itselfe not God,) and
God who is there perpetually, is alwayes to be prostrated
unto, yea whē as the body &amp; blood of Christ in the blessed
Sacrament is not upon the same, (So the Passage in <hi>Bishop
Mortons</hi> too,) nor Divine Service in saying therein, or in
any other place of the Holy Temple. For which cause it
is prescribed, that ever the holy Communion-Table should
be kept Sacred.</q>
   </p>
   <p>This I have else-where fully answered out of <hi>Shelford</hi> &amp;
<hi>Widdowes,</hi> who produce neither Scripture nor Reason for all
this they say, nor any authority, but their owne.</p>
   <p>1. First therefore let them prove: That God hath and
ought to have a Seate in every Church.</p>
   <p>2. Secondly, that this Seate is the Communion-Table
only, not the Pulpit, Reading Pew, Bible, or any other part
of the Church.</p>
   <p>3. Thirdly, that God alwayes sits there by his grace, when
there is no body in the Church, to beare him Company, no
Service, no Sacrament of Christs body and blood.</p>
   <p>4. Fourthly, that when there is Divine Service read in
the Church, a Sermon preached in the Pulpit, or a Child
Christned at the Font, and no Service or Sacrament at the
the Table, that he yet sits still on the Table, and is there only
specially present by his grace, and not at these other places in
any of his Ordinances.</p>
   <p>5. Fiftly, that God is alike present at the Table by his
grace when there is no Communion as when there is
one.</p>
   <p>6. Sixtly, that men ought in point of duty to bow to every
place where God is present: And to one part only off, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument
<pb n="56" facs="29"/>
in the Church, and not to the whole Fabricke:</p>
   <p>Seventhly, that a Bishops consecration confines God
close prisoner to his mercy Seate, the Table, so as never to
suffer him to stirre one inch from thence, no not when there
is no Sacramēt, no Divine Service, no person there to doe him
homage, nor use of his speciall presence.</p>
   <p>Till these bedlam Paradoxes be proved, which wilbe <hi>ad
G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aecas Calendas,</hi> we may well demurre to this second reason.
Of which more fully anon. Only to retort the reason, let
me argue thus.</p>
   <p>The place where God is most specially present by his grace
ought to be bowed unto.</p>
   <p>But God is most specially present by his grace in Heaven,
in the Church-Bible, and midst of his people, not at the East
end of the Church where none must sit neare him, as I
bare else-where proved; And in every good Christians
heart.</p>
   <p>Ergo, these, not the Table, are to be bowed unto. As for
his Chaire of State; That it ought alwayes to be bowed
unto. (I thinke when it is in the ward-robe, Cart, Imbroy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers
or upholsters shop, &amp;c. should have been excepted,) he
must shew us some Law or Statute for it, ere we can beleeve
it.</p>
   <p>And though some men bow unto it now and then, because
the King sits some times personally in it: This Gentleman
must prove, that God sits personally some-times on the Table,
which he can hardly doe. But he and others tell us, that
<hi>God sits alwayes there;</hi> Very good; Then I thus retort the
similitude.</p>
   <p>No Man is so sottish to bow to the Kings Chaire of State
when the King himselfe is sitting in it, but only when he is
absent; For when the King his in it, they never doe it, but
bow only and immediately to the King, without any respect
to the Coaire.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="57" facs="29"/>
Therefore since God is alwayes sitting on the Table, they
ought not to bow or doe any reverence to it at all.</p>
   <p>And so this Simitude cuts the throate of their cause if
rightly paralleld and applied.</p>
   <p>This will likewise overthrow his<note n="c" place="margin">Ibid. p. 136. 137.</note> Argument for the
the placing of the Table Altar-wise, else-where at large
refelled.</p>
   <p>
      <q>Here also (writes he) it is to be considered unto the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring
of Gods holy name (of his Table rather) in what
place of the Chauncell Gods Board or Seat should stand.</q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <q>Doth not nature itselfe teach us, that in every common
house the Seate of the chiefest should be above every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour?</q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <q>And should not Christianitie teach us, that no Seate of
any person, much lesse of any of the Laity, (it seemes then
the Cleargie may sit above God himselfe if they please)
should be above Gods mercy Seate, the Sacred Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion-Table
in the Chauncell? &amp;c.</q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <q>And when as the Lords-Table is set in the uppermost
place within the Chauncell, is it not decent that the ends</q>
thereof (thus this Expositour and Patron of the Common-Prayer-Booke
dares controll it) be towards North and
South?</p>
   <p>
      <q>The Holy Ghost commaundeth all things to be done
decently and according unto order, (Ergo Lords Tables
ends must be turned North and South, against the expresse
order of the Common-Prayer-Booke:) And if it ought
so to be in all things, much more ought it to be in every
thing about Gods house &amp; especially in the standing of his
Sacred Seate; As if this Seate stood very undece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tly and
quite out of order, unlesse the Ends of it stood North and
South contrary to order.</q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb n="58" facs="30"/>
But of this me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ry profound Divinity hereafter: This
only by the way for a Breakfast: The Authour, having in
all this forgotten his good Instruction in his <hi>Epistle to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishioners.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>That we are all bound in conscience for to learne, believe and
obey whatsoever is commaunded in the Commuuion-Booke, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies
Booke and Constitutions or Canons Booke.</p>
   <p>All which condemne his bowing to, and placing of the
Table North and South: And so by his owne censure, not
<hi>speaking according to the Communion Booke Doctrine.</hi> J may
<hi>with a safe conscience before God affirme that there is no light of
Gods holy spirit within him.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>They are his owne words and censure, of all those who
speake not according to the Communion Booke Doctrine,
which himselfe professedly speakes against, in all these, and
other passages.</p>
   <p>But enough of this ridiculous <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> who hath
wronged the Pope exceedingly, in giving the Titles of <hi>HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LINESSE</hi>
and <hi>HOLY FATHER</hi> to our Bishops,
whom he makes absolute Popes in many Passages of his
crack-brainde Treatise.</p>
   <div type="note">
      <pb n="59" facs="30"/>
      <head>NOTE THIS.</head>
      <p>It appeares by Num. 1. 50. &amp;c. &amp;c. 2. v. 2. 17. That the
Tabernacle of the Lord stood in the <hi>midst of the Campe of
Israel, and the Levites were there commaunded to encampe
ROVND ABOVT IT:</hi> To which that text of <hi>Rev.</hi>
5. 11. &amp;c. 7. 11. hath relation, as Learned Mr. <hi>Meade</hi>
there proves at large.</p>
      <p>It is also evident by Numb. 3. 26. c. 4. 26. <hi>(And the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
for the dore of the gate of the Court which is by the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle
ROVND ABOVT, &amp;c.)</hi> That the Passage in
the Counsell of Constantinople where the same phrase is
used, is to be taken properly as Bishop Jewel and others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret
it, not as the <hi>Collier</hi> hath most absurdly perverted
it, the words being the same both in Latine, Greeke and
English in all places.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>