<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The postscript to all the readers of this Sur∣uey in generall.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101491_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07919</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1829</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101491</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The postscript to all the readers of this Sur∣uey in generall.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The suruey of popery : vvherein the reader may cleerely behold, not onely the originall and daily incrementes of papistrie, with an euident confutation of the same; but also a succinct and profitable enarration of the state of Gods Church from Adam vntill Christs ascension contained in the first and second part thereof: and throughout the third part poperie is turned vp-side downe</title>
                 <author>Bell, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 208, 207-346, 337-519, 524-536, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The postscript to all the readers of this Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey in generall.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that I had accomplished this present volume, a friend of mine gaue me to vnderstand, that some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons were offended, because I say in the epistle dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory of my Motiues, that S. Paul erred gentilizing. For whose satisfaction, if they wil be satified with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; I say first, that the nature and condition of some persons is such, that though they be slow to doe well themselues; yet are they very propense to reprehend that, which is well done by others. I say secondly, that if such persons would deeply consider the prudent law of the sage &amp; wise Persians, other things well said shuld haue mooued them to conceale that fault, though it were as ill as they imagine. I say thirdly, that such persons seeke <hi>Nodum in scirpo,</hi> and that it is no fault at all. I prooue it euidently, because to gentilize is nothing els, but to play the part of a gentile, and consequently, since S. Paul, then named Saul, did as cruelly persecute the Christians, as euer did the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall gentiles, <hi>Nero, Domitian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, Traiane, Seuerus, Maximinus, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cius,</hi> or <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesianus:</hi> It followeth of necessitie, that he did gentilize indeed. For as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writ recordeth, Hee breathed out threatninges and slaughter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the disciples of the Lord.<note place="margin">Act. 9.1. &amp; 2.</note> He desired letters to <hi>Damascus,</hi> that hee might bring bound to Ierusalem, all aswell women as men, that professed the name of Christ Iesus, insomuch, that a voice cried from heauen vnto him,<note place="margin">Act 9.4. 1▪ Cor. 15.9.</note> and saide, Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me? He likewise saith of himselfe, that hee is not worthy to be called an apostle, because he persecuted the church of God: and all this doubtlesse he did in error, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause as himselfe saith of the Iewes his brethren if they had knowen,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.8.</note> they would neuer haue crucified the Lord of glorie. Yea hee himselfe saith of himselfe,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.13.</note> that hee was receiued to mercie, because hee erred ignorantly through vnbeliefe. S. Paul therefore erred gentilizing, though hee were a Iew, in that he persecuted Christ and his church, euen as did the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, &amp; in the error of Gentilitie. Which thing being spoken <hi>obiter</hi> in the way of mine honest purgation, and not to establish anie point of doctrin, was not a sufficient motiue to offend anie wel affected reader. Well, I say with the apostle,<note place="margin">Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.10.</note>
      <hi>Si hominibus placerem, Christi seruus non essem.</hi> As before, so now againe, I willingly employ my whole industry to glorifie my God and to profite his church, if by any meanes I can. And as I greatly wish to pleasure thankful persons, who euer accept in good part godly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors so do I make no great account to discontent malitious Zoili, who seldom or neuer broke that wel, which is well done by others.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>