<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the louyng reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1554</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101196_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10150</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20407</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101196</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the louyng reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of wyates rebellion : with the order and maner of resisting the same, wherunto in the ende is added an earnest conference with the degenerate and sedicious rebelles for the serche of the cause of their daily disorder. Made and compyled by John Proctor</title>
                 <author>Proctor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Caly, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1554</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 17 leaves, pages 18-25, leaves 26-96, 6 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the louyng reader.</head>
   <p>THe safe &amp; sure recordation of paynes and pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryls past, hath present delec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ion (sayeth Tullye.) For thinges, were they neuer so bit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and vnpleasaunt in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, being after in peace and securitie, renewed by report or chronicle, are bothe plausible and profitable, whether they touched our selues or other.</p>
   <p>Beynge thus in this poynte persuaded (louynge reader) I tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ghte it a trauayle neyther vnpleasaunt for thee, nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankeful for me, to cōtriue the late rebelliō practised by Wyat,
<pb facs="7"/>
in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me of a chronicle as thou seest. Whereby as I meane not to please the euyl, nor displease the good, so I muche desire to amende the one by settinge before his eye the lamentable Image of hateful rebellion, for the increase of obedience: and to helpe the other by setting furth the vnspotted loyaltie of suche as aduenturouslye and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye serued in this daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous time, for the increase of knowledge and policie the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to represse the like dangers, if anye hereafter happen.</p>
   <p>And further although hereby I couete not to renewe a feare of a daunger past, yet would I gladly encrease a care and stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in euery good mannes hart to auoyde a like daunger that
<pb facs="7"/>
may happē, and most tymes ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>peneth, when a daunger with much difficultie auoided is not sufficient warninge to beware of the next. I haue forborne to touche any man by name, Wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at onelye excepte, and a fewe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which the story would not permit to be leaft out. Yet take me not that I meane to excuse anye mans faulte thereby. For what shoulde I shewe my selfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o vngrate or vnnaturall vnto my naturall countreimen, as namelye to blase them to the worlde, whome eyther their owne good happe, or the quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes surpastinge mercie woulde to be couered at this time.</p>
   <p>And although I touch some by name, terming them in certain places traitours and rebelles,
<pb facs="8"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ust ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>les of their desertes, yet (God is my witnes) I do it not of malice or enuye to anye of their persons. I neuer hated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of them, no not Wyat him selfe: whome, although he was vtterly vnknowen vnto me, yet for the sundrie and singular gif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, wherwith he was largelye endued, I had him in great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration. And now I rather pitie his vnhappie case, then malice his personne. And doe muche lament that so manye good &amp; commendable qualitie &amp; were abused in the seruice of cursed heresie, whose rewarde was neuer other then shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full confusion, by one waye or other to all that folowed her wayes. Finallye, if thou sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose I haue not fully set furth
<pb facs="8"/>
the whol case al as it was I shal not again sai it. neither thought I it necessarie so to doe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther so muche as for this time might be both plausible &amp; profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, &amp; shuld satisfie such poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes as in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dedicatorie epistle to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> quenes maiestie are expressed. Herafter it may be y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> further be sayd touching this matter. In meane tyme y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> hast no iust cause I trust to be offēded w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this my present enterprise, either for the maner of handlinge, or for the matter herin handled, the one hauynge sufficient perspicuitie, and plaines, thother ful trueth: for which I haue made such di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent inuestigation, as I haue found it, &amp; haue herin expressed the same, especially so much as concerneth Kent.</p>
   <p>VALE.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>