<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Terry, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101270_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13630</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23913</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101270</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Terry, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triall of trvth : containing a plaine and short discovery of the chiefest pointes of the doctrine of the great Antichrist, and of his adherentes the false teachers and heretikes of these last times</title>
                 <author>Terry, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Broome (Brome), Joan</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 160 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="100"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F many stūbling blocks (good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader) that are cast in the way by the servants of Antichrist to keep the people that they do not so much as turne their eies to behold, much lesse, settle their affectiōs to embrace the glorious lighte of the gospell of Christ: this is not the least that they are not ashamed to charge, not only some principal and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent persons, but generally all the professours thereof with an huge sea of outragious sins, and a great drought of godlines and vertue: yea many points of the most holy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine it selfe they avouch to tende directly to the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of good maners in all states. But to omit their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> slāders raised vp against particular persons, which haue bin fully answered by others, our severe cēsors of Rhemes, <note place="margin">Rhem. in e. 7. Math. The profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers of the gospel most vniustly charged by the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to bee sacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestuous &amp; men of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>tiable si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> beside many grievous crimes which they avouch to be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with vs and al other heretickes, charge vs particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with sacriledge against God and the prophanation of all holy things, and incestuous marriages: and these with the other abominatiōs they would haue the world beleeue to be in so high a degree among vs, as they are likely to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all such, as are men of insatiable sin. Now if the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe of Idols, and the destroying of Idolatry, &amp; the removing of the superstitious worship of creatures, &amp; the restoring of the pure worship of one almighty and alsuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient God in spirit and truth, according vnto the prescrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his owne most holy word, be sacriledge, &amp; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of all holy things: and if the abolishing of the common stewes, and the disanulling of the vow of single life, which was indeed the cause of abominable pollutions
<pb facs="101"/> and of vnnatural and monstrous murders, and the restitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 3.</note> of holy matrimony according vnto the direct cōman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God by the penne of the Apostle be incestuous pollutions; and if these and the like make vs men of insatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sin, then we must be content to vndergoe this slander; seeing herein we are made but conformable to our Master <note place="margin">Ioh. 6. 48.</note> Christ, who was charged to haue beene in league with the Devil, whereas his comming was to destroy the workes of <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 19.</note> the devil: and to haue beene a friend to Publicanes &amp; sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, being in truth the greatest enemy to sin that ever was borne of flesh &amp; blood. But what manner of men are these themselues, which lay to our charge so grievous crimes? yea what are their most holy and most godly Fathers the <note place="margin">Sāctissimi, pijssimi. Lyr. in Mat. c. 16 Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na in Rom. c. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>drian. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa. In nomine domini in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit omne malum. Bern. in Cant. serm. 33. The most corrupt &amp; abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble liues of the chiefest enemies of the Gospel of Christ.</note> Popes, vnto whose very becke they owe all obedience? Is it not recorded by principal men among them, that many of them haue beene apostataes from the faith and very mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and mishapen creatures: such as succeeded not Peter in feeding, but Romulus in manquelling: that they preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the name of God and the service of Christ, but vnder that name wrought all maner of mischiefe, and did service vnto Antichrist. Neither did this spirituall contagion stay in their greatest personages, but spread it selfe abroad in al states and callings. And no mervaile seeing the whole world doeth frame it selfe to the likenes and liking of such as be in greatest power &amp; authority: especially where the vow of obedience without gaine-saying, yea without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring whether it be lawfull or no, is esteemed as one of the highest steppes to the greatest perfection. Whereby it came to passe that Rome it selfe the chiefe city of this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire became the mother of all abominations, and grew to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uch ripenes and perfection in sin, that shee deserved the name of the westerne Babilon, where the whore of whores
<pb facs="101"/> evē the great Antichrist of these last times should sit, who was to make drunke all the kings of the earth with the cup of his spiritual fornications &amp; adulteries. Vnto the which place whosoeuer should haue his recourse, first he should see, and then he should be acquainted with, and the thirde time hee himselfe should become a wicked person. For there is liberty of all other thinges, saue only of true pietie <note place="margin">Romae om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia cum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceant non licet esse pium. Māt.</note> and godlines. So outragious and abominable haue beene the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ormities of prince &amp; people in this church of Rome that they haue poisoned after a sorte the very aire where they liued, and haue caused those, who in some respectes, were their favorites &amp; friends, thus to haue cast their own dunge in their owne faces, and to haue dashed over their mishapen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eatures with the blacke coale of euerlasting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>herefore small cause hath the viperous brood of this venimous generation thus to hisse against vs, and to spet out their poison against our persons: for albeit we bee not angels without spot, yet we be not Englishmen J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>alia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, that is, Devils incarnate: much lesse against our most <note place="margin">The holy doctrine of the gospell vniustly charged to be the seed of all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes and sinne. Luk 10. 20. The cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of faith &amp; the assuraunce of election no hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer but a fu therer of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ety &amp; godlines.</note> holy and pure doctrine, as if that were the seede of all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes and sinne.</p>
   <p>The certainty of our election to eternall life, and the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance that we are the childrē of God, &amp; haue our na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nes written in heaven, which is the most forcible inducement of all other to cause vs to reioice in the Lord, and to walke as the children of God, and to haue our cō<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ersation in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, they accuse to be the mother of pride &amp; pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tumptiō, and of carnal socurity and dissolutenes of life. What is it credible that when J continually cal to my remembrance and set before mine eies, that God to assure me, that hee is my gracious God and louing father hath created mee, and sustained me from my mothers wombe, &amp; hath preserved
<pb facs="102"/> me from these and these dangers, and hath bestowed vpon me these &amp; these blessings, &amp; hath made these &amp; these his creatures to serue to my vse that I might the better serue him, yea and hath caused these &amp; mine affections to haue beene good and profitable vnto me, is it credible I say that the assurance of this so great kindnes &amp; loue should breed in mine hart vnkindnes to God, and the neglect of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, &amp; of mine owne good? Either is it credible that when I continually call to my remembrance &amp; set before mine eies, that God, to assure me of my reconciliation vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and of my receiuing into his fauor, hath reuealed vnto mee his sonne Iesus Christ the pledge of his loue and the meanes of my reconciliation, &amp; hath opened vnto me his perfect obedience to the whole lawe not for himselfe but for my righteousnes, and his invincible patience euen thē when he dranke so deeply of that so bitter cup of his pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full passion, that it caused him to sweat water &amp; blood not for his owne but for my sins, when I say this is revealed by <note place="margin">Culpamea: culpa mea: culpa mea maxima.</note> God to be done for me by so worthy a person, who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his manhood receiued the spirit without measure, and according vnto his godhead was infinite holines, puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fection it selfe, that so I might bee assured of so absolute a righteousnes, and so full a satisfaction for all my sins, as might stand before the most exact iustice of God, is it credible I say that the assurance of so great kindnes &amp; loue should breed vnkindnes in mine hart, and a carelesnes of embracing and holding fast so great mercy, and of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in such loue? Either is it credible that when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually cal to my remembrance and set before mineeies, that God to assure me of mine adoption into the place &amp; number of his children hath sealed me with the spirit of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, and hath by him sanctified mine vnderstanding
<pb facs="102"/> with the knowledge of his most exact iustice in punishing my sins with such severity vpon my surety, that I might be assured of mine acquitting from the same, and of his end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse and vnspeakeable mercy in sparing not his own sonne to spare me, and of his wisedome in making his iustice, and mercy so to conspire togither for my fuller assurāce of my salvation wrought thereby; when heereby also my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and affections are so rectified and sanctified, that I esteeme to know nothing but Jesus Christ and him cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: and account all other things as losses and dong that I might win Christ, and be found in him, and be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the fruit of his death, and of the benefire of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ection: is it credible, I say, that so great kindnes should breed vnkindnes in mine hart, and cause mee to prophane and to treade vnder foote this holy blood, and to bee grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vousome to this so comfortable spirit? Lastly is it credible that when I cal to my remembraunce and set before mine eies that God to certifie mee of his fauour and loue hath opened vnto mee in his worde that greate charter and graunt of remission of sinnes and of eternall life in Christ Iesus, and for my further assuraunce thereof, hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his gracious promises as vndoubted evidences there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in mine hart, that I might no more doubt of my most as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured obtaining of these so great giftes, then I neede of the admitting and allowing of these evidences, that hee hath given me to shew for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ame, when I come to appeare before the throne of grace: is it, I say, credible that this so great security for mine everlasting blessednes should with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>raw mine hart from the loue of my blessednes and cause me to wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ke in cursed and damnable waies which tende to eternal miserie and woe? Sure I am that the goodlier our temporal possessions are, &amp; the better evidences we haue
<pb facs="103"/> to shew for the same, and the kinder our parents were that bestowed them vpon vs with charge not to passe them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in any case, the more careful we shal be to keepe the same, both for the loue of our most kinde parents, and also for our owne welfare and good: and shal the assurance of the most glorious inheritance of the kingdome of heaven given vnto me by mine heavenly father, whose kindenes so much surpasseth the kindnes of any earthly parentes, as God himselfe surpasseth man, make me carelesse to keepe so goodly and glorious an inheritance, &amp; to performe the wil and commandement of mine heavenly father? <hi>VVhere</hi>
      <note place="margin">Matth 6. 22.</note>
      <hi>your treasure is</hi> (saith our Saviour Christ) <hi>there will your hart be also.</hi> And therfore if this wil not moue me through<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to set mine hart and affections on heavenly things, that I haue so good evidence for them, that they are assuredly mine, and that I shal vndoubtedly reape by them such an huge harvest of vnspeakable blisse, what wil then moue &amp; perswade me therto? yea if hereby I am allured &amp; drawen vnto sinne, what is able to induce me to piety and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? But this argument hath beene touched in the former &amp; is more fully handled in the latter part of this treatise: &amp; therfore omitting now to wade further therin, let vs come to examin whether that other maine point of the Gospel, I meane, Iustification by faith without works, be any cause or provocation to sin, as it is vniustly charged by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of grace, and by the favourites and patrons of their owne merites.</p>
   <p>In this question of Iustification there are these three pointes to be considered: First, before our effectual calling vnto the state of grace, the great sufficiency of our natural corruptions to procure wrath, and the great insufficiencie of our best workes to prepare vs and to make vs meete to
<pb facs="103"/> be partakers of the Lordes loue. Secondly after our effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual calling the great inhability of our faith, repentance, loue, and of the residue of our works of grace to merite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of sinnes and eternal glorie. Lastly the onely suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of the obedience of Christ for the perfect accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishing of this great and weighty worke of mans redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. When the scripture teacheth that man by originall sinne is wholy corrupt, and <hi>that in vs, that is, in our flesh</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Rom. 7. 18.</note>
      <hi>dwelleth no good thing,</hi> the purpose therof is not to detract from man al manner of good: (for the substance and the naturall powers &amp; workes both of body &amp; soule are good, in that they are the Lordes creatures and the workeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of his owne handes: and the light of reason whereby we are taught that there is a God, and that iustice &amp; equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is to be observed in the ordering of our publike &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate affaires is also good, and was preserved by God in the soule of man when he fell from God, that therby he might be directed and guided for the better managing of al such thinges as belong to the preservation of this present life:) and therefore there are yet remaining in man since his fal some things that are naturally and civilly good. But there <note place="margin">There is nothing in man by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that is religiously good.</note> is nothing remaining in him by nature that is religiouslie good: that can prepare &amp; fitte vs to the readier receaving of faith &amp; repentance, &amp; further vs to the performing of any such thing as belongeth to the true worship &amp; service of God. <hi>For the very wisedome of the flesh is enmitie to God,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 7.</note> (and therefore is no friend or furtherer of his service) yea it is <hi>not subiect to the lawe of God, neither indeede can bee.</hi> So that vntill we condemne our owne wisedome of follie, we cannot yeeld over our selues to be guided and ruled by the wisedome of God: and vntill wee wholy renounce our selues, we cannot be admitted into the Lordes family and
<pb facs="104"/> houshould. Neither is it to be feared least the regenerate man being lightned by the word of God to behould &amp; to condemne his owne vniversall corruption, and embrace salvation only by faith, should therby be induced (as Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian <note place="margin">Cāp. rat. 8. The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stification is no provo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation or spur, but a strong bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to all iniquity &amp; sinne.</note> avoucheth) to wallow still in the stinking and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some sincke of all iniquitie and sinne, to accuse nature, to despaire of vertue, &amp; to withdraw himselfe frō the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of God. Nay the more great &amp; grievous his sins haue beene before his conversion, &amp; the more clearely he seeth and behouldeth the same, the more they will stinke in his own nostrels, &amp; the sooner he wil loath &amp; leave them also. And howsoever he be tempted to returne with the dogge to his vomite, &amp; with the hogge to the wallowing againe in the mire, either by the remnāts of his owne corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or by the instigations and ensamples of others, yet he doth not yeelde himselfe captiue to these temptations: but casting his eies backe vpon his former corruptions both o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall &amp; actual, he doth with David most severely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them and himselfe also for the same, &amp; doth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by sharpen and increase his vnfayned &amp; harty repentāce, and his setled purpose of amendement of life, as it is to be seene in the one and fiftieth psalme. He taketh not liberty hereby to offend againe, and to adde vnto the multitude of his former corruptions, but rather protesteth with St. Peter to the contrarie: <hi>Oh it is sufficient that we haue spent</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 3.</note>
      <hi>the time past of our life according vnto the lustes of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles:</hi> Now seing that the Lord hath made vs to behould &amp; to abhorre our former rebelliōs, we must resigne the time of our life to come wholy to God: Yea the greater hath bin the number of our former sinnes, and the more the Lords mercy in pardoning the same, the greater must be our care that we offend not any more so gracious a God and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful
<pb facs="104"/> a father, by adding vnto the huge heap of our former iniquities. Indeed there haue bin some carnall libertines in al ages, who hearing that the greater our sins are, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the mercy of God in pardoning the same, haue tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the grace of God into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>antonnes, and haue said; let vs continue in sinne that grace may abound. But as to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane al thinges are vncleane, yea the most holy and pure grace of God is an occasion to encrease their vncleane &amp; impure lusts: so to the pure al things are pure, yea the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude &amp; greatnes of their vncleane sins causeth them to loath and abhorre them the more, &amp; to loue him the more also, that hath most franckly and freely pardoned them all. <hi>There was</hi> (saith our Saviour to Simon the Pharisee) <hi>a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine lender that had two debtours, &amp; the one owed him</hi> 500. <note place="margin">Luk. 7. 41.</note>
      <hi>pence, and the other</hi> 50. <hi>VVhen they had nothing to pay hee forgaue them both: which of them therefore tell me</hi> (saith he) <hi>will loue him most? Simon answered and said, I suppose, that he to whom he forgaue most. And he said vnto him, thou hast truely iudged.</hi> Wherby it is evidēt that the faithful, the more they perceiue the greatnes of their sinnes, and how much they are endebted and endangered vnto God for the same, togither with the great mercy of God in pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them all, will not take occasion thereby to contemne God, &amp; to cast themselues againe into the like dangerous sinnes, but will loue God the more, and take the greater care to testifie the same by their duetifull obedience to his commaundements.</p>
   <p>Now concerning the second and third pointes that are to be considered in this question, it is most true that the Psalmist testifieth, <hi>that no man may deliver his brother,</hi> no <note place="margin">Psal. 49. 7.</note> not so much as from temporal death, <hi>nor make atonement vnto God for him:</hi> for it cost more to redeeme soules: in so
<pb facs="105"/> much that the Son of God himselfe was to become man, <hi>that he might giue himselfe a ransome for many.</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">The all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficiency of any thing that is in man, and the all suffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iency of the death of Christ to per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>orme the worke of mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mption.</note> the scripture displaying the insufficiency of any thing whatsoever that can be giuen by man him selfe for the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of his sinnes and for the redemption of his soule, giveth present testimony vnto the most ample sufficiency of the most pretious bloud of Christ for the full accōplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that worke. For what if man could giue his house full of treasure? yet <hi>wee are not redeemed vvith corruptible thinges as with silver and gould, but with the most pretious bloud of Christ, as of a lambe vndefiled and without spotte.</hi> Or what if he would offer vp in sacrifice a 1000. rammes, or a 1000. bullockes and goates? <hi>It is impossible that the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Heb. 10</note>
      <hi>bloud of bullockes and goates should take away sinnes.</hi> And therfore when the Apostle had avouched by the warrant of the Prophet, that the Lord would not haue burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and sacrifice, nor the bodies of slaine beastes, then he giueth testimony to the offering of the body of Christ as to the onely true expiatory sacrifice. Lastly what if one would offer vp to God the spirituall sacrifices of faith and repentance, and of all such workes as are commanded in the morallawe? Surely of these also the Apost<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e hath testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>that it vvas impossible to the lavv in as much as it was</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 3.</note>
      <hi>weake by reason of our flesh,</hi> to worke out the worke of mās redemption, and therfore that God sent <hi>his owne sonne in the simtlitude of sinsul flesh, and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> sin condemned sinne in the slesh, that the righteousnes of the law might bee fulfilled in vs,</hi> and so we made righteous before God. For our faith, repentance, iustice, temperance &amp; the rest, are but as bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and clipped money, they are to light to weigh in the ballance with our most heavie and burdensome sins: and they are also but as one to a thousād toward the discharge
<pb facs="105"/> of our most huge debt. Moreover in the perfourming evē of our best workes, the flesh rebelleth against the spirite, &amp; so staineth their purity and blemisheth their glory: and our spiritual and inward man is but renued in part, so that wee can do no good worke with al our hart, soule, and strength in that degree and measure as the law requireth: now that which wanteth of that which the law requireth, is a trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression of the law, and therefore sin: and sinne defiling the worke, wherein it is, causeth our very righteousnes to bee as a stained cloath, and therefore in that respect odious to God, procuring his wrath, and making vs subiect to the curse of the lawe, and therefore not meriting everlasting glory. Thus are euen our best sacrifices but as the offering vp of the lame and maimed, and therefore of themselues cannot be, much lesse make vs, acceptable vnto God. And thus are these garmentes of our owne righteousnes both stained, &amp; too short also to couer our nakednes: they may be likened to the curtalled garmentes of Davids servantes <note place="margin">2. Sam. 10. 5</note> which made them ashamed to come into the kings court, and to present themselues in his presence. And verily if but one of our acquaintance beeing of some good place happen to see vs, when wee haue on a sluttish aperne, or a fowle ruffe, or some base and regardlesse attire, how squea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish are we, and how do we imagine, that wee haue done our selues some great discredite? Howe much more then may we worthely blush and be ashamed to come into the presence of the most pure and glorious God, who so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely loatheth and abhorreth all impuritie &amp; vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, beeing covered with the slubbered and curtalled gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our owne righteousnes? And how ought we to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by all meanes possible to put of and to lay aside these rotten ragges in the case of our iustification, &amp; to embrace
<pb facs="106"/> and lay hold on Christ <hi>that we may be found in him, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi>
      <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 9.</note>
      <hi>our owne righteousnes which is by the lawe,</hi> but that which is by faith in him? For they are the precious &amp; costly garmēts of his righteousnes, that arelarge enough to couer our nakednes, be it never so great: they are also so cleare, pure, &amp; holy, that they are able to endure the presence of the holy of holies, &amp; to present vs pure &amp; holy in his sight.</p>
   <p>So then the workes of our faith, repentance, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes cannot present vs pure and holy before God, nor make satisfaction to his iustice for our sins, nor me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ite the crowne of eternall glory: but these so great blessings are procured for vs by the bloud of Christ, and are given vs most frankely and freely by his mediation. Now if a master shal giue vnto his faithful servant an estate in a liuing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by copy or lease freely without any fine or income, wil this kindnesse make him malepert and saucy, to set at naught his masters commandement, &amp; careles to pay his rent and to performe that suite and service that is required at his handes? Neither is it credible that the faithfull ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantes of God hauing an estate in the glorious inheritance of the kingdome of heaven most frankely and freely gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto thē in Christ without, nay, cōtrary to their owne deservings, should thereby take occasion to sinne against God, and become careles to performe their obedience to his law, being the rent, suite, and service that is double due vnto him. So neither is it likely that they well vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the guiltines of sinne to bee so great, that it could not be done away but by the bloud of Christ, and the wrath of God against sin to be so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>etled, &amp; his iustice so implacable, that rather thē the sins of his own elect should e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cape vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punished, he punished thē with so great severity evē vpon his own deare son, should hereby be encouraged to cōmit
<pb facs="106"/> sin, &amp; to receiue into their boso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s such a venimous serpēt whose sting is so dāgerous, yea almost incurable. Wheras on the cōtrary side if sin we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> so smal a matter that it might be done away by holy water, holy bread, pardons, masses, pligrimages, almes, praiers, fastings, &amp; by other workes of <note place="margin">Popish do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations to sinne.</note> popish penāce: &amp; if there were so rich &amp; pretious a gift of charity infused into the heart of every faithful Christiā, as that therby he were able to make God endebted not only to himslfe but to others also: then indeede we needed not altogither to make so great a matter of cōmitting sin and offending God, seeing we could so many waies make satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the same, and make God amendes, and further also make him endetted vnto vs; as herevpō many men are bold to trespasse their neighbour, for that either already they are as much or more in their debt and danger, or for that they can else in time to come easily make thē amēdes for their former trespasse. But God can no way be pleasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by vs, neither is worshipped with mens hāds, as if ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any thing were added vnto him, and he made endetted <note place="margin">Act. 17. 25.</note> vnto vs for the same. For as for the workes of our faith, repentāce and loue, we are therby more &amp; more endebted vnto him: for that he worketh them in vs by his spirit: and he is no otherwise endebted vnto vs for the same, but only for that of his owne most free and vndeserved goodnes in Christ he hath bound himselfe by promise to giue them a reward. And as for the least sin that is, bee it but a desire to <note place="margin">The most heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den even of the lightest sinne, and the great deformity of the least iniquity.</note> steale a sticke out of thy neighbours hedge, or to eate an apple of the forbidden tree, seeing in doing the same either we set God so at naught, that we vtterly forget him &amp; his holy commandements <hi>(Thou shalt not covet thy neighbours house &amp;c.</hi> &amp; <hi>Cursed is he that continueth not in every point of the law to doe it)</hi> wheras we ought most religiouslie to
<pb facs="107"/> keepe a constant and continual remembrance thereof: Or if we remembring the cōmandemēt of God, &amp; the heavy curse annexed to the transgression of the same, yet blesse our selues, and promise our selues peace, when God mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth warre, and so giue more credit to the suggestions of Satan, then to the sacred testimonies and oracles of God, harkening to the devil rather then to God, and preferring the devil before God, seeing herein as much as in vs lieth, we robbe God of his truth and iustice, &amp; of his soveraigne auctority over vs, by refusing him to raigne over vs, and making choice of the devil to be ruled by him, taking after a sort the scepter out of the Lordes hand and the crowne from his head, &amp; giuing them vnto the Devill: if the Lord for this so intollerable an indignity should depriue vs vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly of his favour and loue, and of all his gracious giftes &amp; blessinges, and deliver vs cleane over vnto the devill to bee partakers with him of al māner of curses &amp; plagues, what should he doe heerein, but that in al iustice &amp; right is most due vnto vs? And how should he herein serve vs also, but even according vnto our owne choice? For the lesser the commodity or pleasure is, for the which wee are so soone perswaded to cast away God, and to set his cōmandemēts at naught, the more manifestly is our vile corruption con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, in that we are so quickly hyred to so wicked a work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vpon so base and meane wages. And heereof it is that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel is bold to cal the trāsgression of Saul (in sparing the <note place="margin">Gigantum more bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re cum deo</note> best of the sheepe &amp; oxen, at the earnest motion, as it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, of the people, &amp; that to this end, to offer sacrifice vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to God) <hi>rebellion;</hi> for that therin he did rebel against God, &amp; ioyne himselfe to that notorious rebell Satan: &amp; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly so, but he further likeneth it to the most odious and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable sin of Idolatrie and witchcraft. And verely as the
<pb facs="107"/> witch renounceth God, &amp; giveth her selfe vnto the devil: and the Idolater forsaketh the worship and service of God, and betaketh himselfe to the service of the Deuill: euen so every sinner euen in the smallest and least sinne, as much as in himselfe lieth, casteth away God, and maketh choice of the deuil: and therefore if the Lord shoulde vtterly cast him of for the same, &amp; deliuer him ouer to that cursed ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent to haue his part with him in his torments &amp; plagues, he should do no other thing therin, thē that which is most iustly deserued. And verelie had not our alsufficient Savior made full satisfaction by his most precious bloode for the least as wel as for the greatest of the sinnes of the elect thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, &amp; had not he procured a pardon for the same, they woulde haue beene so heauy and burdensome vnto them, that they would haue pressed them downe to the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse pit of hel: Neither would their holy life either past or to come haue beene able to haue di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>charged them of the burden thereof. For if one, otherwise a very good subiect, and of most ciuil and vpright conversation, falling into the company of loose and lewd persons, by their counsell and perswasion do but ioine with them in one robbery, and so commit a trespasse, if it bee but against one of the Princes subiects, and but against one of the lawes of the common weale; it is not his honest life past, and the keeping of al the rest of the lawes, and the doing good to many of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <note place="margin">It is a thing worthy to be condē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned iustly to be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to mē: what an offence thē is it to be grievous vnto God?</note> subiects, and his duety neuer so well performed before to prince and country, nor yet his harty repentance, &amp; his sincere promise of amendment, that can discharge him frō the same, but that law must proceede against him, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution must be done accordingly, vnlesse a pardō be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from the prince: how much more if one sin against the incomprehensible maiesty of the most glorious deitie
<pb facs="108"/> by treading vnder foote the least of his commandements shal the se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tence of eternal condēnation proceede against him, vnlesse hee obtaine the forgiuenesse thereof by the blood of Christ? <hi>For if one man sinne against another, the</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2. 25 Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 23. Eze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 10. 20</note>
      <hi>iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e may iudge it: but if one sin against God, who shall plead for him? The wages of sin</hi> (saith the Apostle) <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> death. That soule</hi> (saith the prophet) <hi>that sinneth, that soule shall die.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bas. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Hier. ep. 14</note> What sin is it (saith Basill) that any da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> cal light? I knowe not (saith Hierome) whether we may cal any sinne light or small, the which is done with the contempt of God. This then is our doctrine of iustification, that our best workes are stained and stand in need of mercy: and therefore can neither merite eternal glory, nor make satisfaction to God for the least of our sins: and that the lightest of our trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions would haue beene too heauy for vs to beare, yea they would haue pressed vs downe to the bottomlesse pit of hel, had not our most mercifull Sauiour succoured vs herein, by removing them also graciously from vs, and by laying them vpon his owne shoulders. And if this doctrine provoke to sin, I know not what can revoke from the same.</p>
   <p>But now let vs proceede to that other part of the slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der wherewith all the enemies of the gospel do charge the profession thereof, euen with the great penury and want of al good workes. For not only the Rhemists do take from vs for the most part the sheepes cloathing; that is, the very outwarde shew of good workes: but also the composer of the <hi>VVard word,</hi> vpon occasion of some civil behaviour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be in some of our Recusants, taketh vpon him with the prowd Pharisie not only to advance himselfe and his, farre aboue vs base and vile Publicanes, but also he woulde haue the worlde beleeue, that if question were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them and vs of good works, our chiefest captaines
<pb facs="108"/> would straight waies relinquish the field, &amp; not bee so bold as to strike one stroke. But this is but one of their Thraso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical brags. For I doubt not but a meane souldier fighting vnder the ensigne of the gospell of Christ may encounter herein euen their stoutest champions. For if either we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect the sounde doctrine, or the sincere practise of good workes (for good words bring forth good manners not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at their birth but also in their growth) it shalbe declared in the treatise following that the holsome doctrin of good workes is most soundly delivered by vs and not by them: and as for the practise let vs nowe briefly take a true view thereof euen in the fowre cardinal vertues, wisedome, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, temperance, and iustice, and let vs in a word see whether we haue iust cause to giue ground vnto them and to yeeld backe one foote.</p>
   <p>Concerning wisedome (which is the Lady and M<seg rend="sup">is</seg>. <note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors of the gospell are no whit behind the papists, but a great way before them in the holy exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of all vertues.</note> to all the residue of the vertues) not onl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> our doctrine but our practise also is, that both priest and people haue their dayly resort to the word of God the full fountaine &amp; wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring of true wisedome, and meditate thereon day and night, that their harts being continually moistened with the sweete droppes thereof, they may be made partakers of her fruits. And is it not a point of true wisdome, for one that cannot of himselfe wisely iudge of al thinges, to make choise of a wise instructer &amp; teacher? But the doctrine &amp; the practise of the church of Rome is to cause the people for the most parte to reiect the daylie reading of the word of God, and therfore what wisedome can there be in thē? <note place="margin">Ier. 8. 9.</note> yea it hath not bin required, much lesse practised by their priestes and great Bishops to be much busied in the Lords booke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> it hath beene thought to haue bin inough for them to haue bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> skilfull in their portuise and in their pontificall.
<pb facs="109"/> It may shame (indeede) the priestes of Italy, who truelie, <note place="margin">Aenaeas Silvius cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. de dict. &amp; fact. Alphon. regis 1. 2. 17 Eras. 1. 9. ep ad Natal. Bedd.</note> as it is wel knowen, haue no not so much as once read over the new testament: whereas among the Thaborites (that is the Gospellers) yee can hardly finde any woman which cannot aunswere both out of the olde testament and the new. And a prove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>be went currant in Scotland not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares since testifieng the blindnes and brutishnes of some of their great Bishops: <hi>ye are like the Bishops of Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelden who knew neither new nor olde lawe.</hi> Now concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning true Christian courage and manhood, it hath beene so great in many thousands of the professors of the Gospel of Christ, &amp; that even among such as were of the meanest trades and occupations, that they haue willingly lost both their liberties and liues to giue testimony vnto the truth of their most holy faith: and the paucity of the seedsmen of rebellion that haue bin executed for treason against their prince and country, and for the defence of the vsurped iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction of the Romish Antichrist, may no way bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and matched with them. And as for the exercise of temperance and chastity it is well knowne to the whole world, how we reverence the divine institutiō of holy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony and keepe our selues within the bounds of this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Lord: Wheras among our Romish votaries simple fornication hath beene accounted no sinne; and it hath beene thought to goe well with them, if they liued <note place="margin">Si nō castè <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ameé cautè</note> charily, though not chastly. And howe chastly some of their religious persons liued among themselues, some of their fishpondes haue testified sufficiently: and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their secular priestes, the tōgues of such as liued with them haue witnessed, that very few wives in their parishes were left at the least vnattempted by these their ghostlie Fathers: that I may omitte the vowed trotting on pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb facs="109"/> by many, that the barren wombe might so be made fruitfull. Lastly concerning iustice, equity, conscience, and an vnspotted and vnblameable life, as it hath beene repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Reinerius an inquisitor, and that no doubt vpon suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient inquiry, of our brethren the poore men of Lions, that they had a great shew of godlines, &amp; lived iustly with men, and beleeved al things well concerning God, and all the articles of the creede, saue only (saith he) that they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; blasphemed the church of Rome: so I doubt not but that the like testimony may be given of al the sincere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors of the Gospel, and that by the mouth of the very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, if that he wil lay aside blind malice, as Reinerius did, and simplie and plainely declare the truth. At least sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, his conscience wil not make vs worse then, those of his religious orders; of whō it hath bin testified long since, that they haue fallen from <hi>conscience to science, and from</hi>
      <note place="margin">Petr. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulph. Tos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sian▪ histor. Seraph▪ religion. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>science to be bareences.</hi> And what conscience I pray you, and what regard to Gods commandements was in those that apprehended Thomas Sanpaulinus at Paris vpō sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of heresie, for that he reproved one for swearing in vaine, and never left him vntil they had brought him from the tortures of the racke to end his life in fiery torments?</p>
   <p>And yet these things are not spoken to this end, as if we meant to detract al ciuil carriage from all the members of the church of Rome: nay, that the Deuill himselfe may haue his right, we ingenuously confesse and acknowledge the outward exercise of many civill &amp; politicke vertues in many of them, especiallie the most profitable works of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty liberality and mercy in founding Colledges, Hospitals and the like. But yet so, that if they would take from their Faulcons eies the hood of selfe loue and partiality, &amp; look into one little corner of the glasse of that paineful labourer
<pb facs="110"/> in the Lords vineyard <hi>Master Doctor VVillet,</hi> they might <note place="margin">Andrew-Willet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trov. gener. 19. error. 104.</note> see that the professours of the gospel are nothing behinde them in those so goodly and glorious workes. How beit al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we were not altogither matchable with thē in the outwarde worke of these vertues, for that wee are no way matchable with them in those great dignities, priviledges, offices, and honors, and in those large and ample possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which they enioied to the ful: yet they may know that the poore widdowes mite is as much and more also with Christ, then al the large summes which were cast into the treasury by the Scribes &amp; Pharisies: especially if they were giuen as parte of that pray which vnder pretence of long praier they got from poore widdowes. And from whence I pray you, did most of those greate Donatiues proceede, that were cast into the treasurie by our popish Pharisies? Is it not likelie that they were either part of that bootie that they gained by thesale of their Masses and pardons: or at the least some portion of the fleeces which they tooke frō the sheepe for their little and course, yea no feeding at all of the flocke of Christ? And what then was this, but to rob Peter and to pay Paule? or it may be, it was the bringing in of <hi>the price of an whore,</hi> yea perhaps of many whores into <note place="margin">Hagg. 2. 15. Deut. 23. 18</note> the temple of God, and the offering vp of the vncleane in sacrifice vnto him. And here by the way I would demande also of them, whether it be not as good and as profitable a worke both to church and common-weale to bring vp our owne natural children begotten in holy matrimony at our owne cost and charges in some honest calling, according to our habilitie, and carefullie to provide for them conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient portions: as to leaue large summes to our base chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, kinsfolke, servants, or any other whosoeuer, of whose good education as wee haue not the like care, so of their
<pb facs="110"/> good conversation we cannot conceiue the like hope? But yet here, least we be mistaken, protestation is to bee made, that as we thinke not that we are borne only for our selues and for our children, so wee teach not any to employ their goods to the benefit of themselues and their children on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but also to the seruice of God, Prince, &amp; country, and of al other also, who are our neighbours, if they may bee suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured and relieved by our meanes. Yea we constantly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch that the more in wisedome &amp; discretion we imploy that way, the greater treasure wee lay vp in the safest place not onlie to our owne best gaine, but also to the greatest commoditie of our children. And as for those which haue no children at al, there is no doubt but that the more is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at their hāds to be emploied to the benefit of other, if they wil shew their fidelitie to him, whose bailiffes they are in al that they possesse, and bee esteemed of him as his faithful servants. And yet here it is to be remembred, that liberality is but one duty amōg many, that are required in the commandements of God. it is but one branch among manie other also, that are to spring out of vs, if we wil bee good and fruitfull trees: it is but parte of that seruice that we must performe vnto God, if we wilbe acknowledged of him for his faithful seruants. Neither must we esteeme him to be a good christian, albeit the world like neuer so well of him, who is a swearer, drunkard, or whoremaster, if so bee he be a good almes man, and careth not who eateth of his <note place="margin">Liberality no fitte cloake to cover sinne</note> meate: as if this were a cloake to couer al faultes, and a suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient amends for al sinnes: for this is but a counterfeit &amp; a shaddow of liberality, it is not true liberality indeede. For shee is not an whore, but a chast matrone: shee vseth not to sorte her selfe with such base companions: shee sorteth her selfe only with her princely peeres, and keepeth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie
<pb facs="111"/> with all the residue of divine and heauenly vertues. Neither doth her beauty so much consist in the great glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the outward work that is wrought, as in the readines and willingnes of the minde of the giuer: seeing not many rich, noble, &amp; mighty are effectually called, but the poore base &amp; weake of this world which are more glorious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in with spiritual graces, then beautified with the shew and pompe of outward works. And yet whereas God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied mercy to no state or condition, those which are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led being rich and noble must know, that the more that is given vnto them, the more shal be required at their hands: and that they that sowe sparingly shal reape sparingly: and seeing that God is so liberal and bountiful in all respectes towardes them, they ought to be liberal and bountiful for his sake, especially towards his sincere &amp; faithful servants. that so their Lord &amp; Master may say vnto them, <hi>goe too yee good and faithfull servants, ye haue bin faithfull in a little, I wil make you Lordes over much, enter yee into the ioy of the Lord.</hi> And againe <hi>Come yee blessed of my father inherit the kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world: for I was hungry and yee fedde me.</hi> Wherfore to conclude, it is evident in part by those things which haue bin hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to delivered, that our doctrine of the Gospel is no provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to sin, and that our life is not vtterly void of the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of all good workes: for then wee should haue greatly provoked the Lord to haue pulled downe the hedge of this our vineyard, and to haue remoued his candlesticke out of the midst of vs. But blessed be the Lord, the wal of this our vineyard stādeth as yet, the bright candle of the sound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of faith and good works burneth in the candlesticke of this our Church of England, the which is lōg since put out in the Church of Rome: and therfore howsoever they
<pb facs="111"/> greatly boast of the workes of light, there can indee de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound among them nothing but the vnfruitfull workes of the kingdome of darknes. The which I beseech those due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to consider of, who among them belong to the number of Gods elect, that so vnto them in all holy humility and godly sincerity taking a due view of the doctrine of light, god may shew so much mercy, as to lightē the eies of their spiritual vnderstanding, and so translate them out of the kingdome of darkenes into the kingdome of light. The which thing (I beseech thee Christian Reader) to helpe forward with thy devout and daylie praiers vnto God; es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially that the cādlesticke of this our Church may stand stedfast and vnremoved vnto the worldes end, that Gods glorie may more and more be manifested in all the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and corners of this little Iland, and many children in all succeeding ages may heere be continually begotten &amp; borne vnto God. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord IOHN TERRIE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>