<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Newes out of Cheshire, concerning
the new found Well, as it is contained in a
Letter lately sent from a Cheshire man, to
a Gentleman a deere friend of his in North∣hampton-shire.</title>
           <author>W., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101818_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14591</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24904</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101818</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Newes out of Cheshire, concerning
the new found Well, as it is contained in a
Letter lately sent from a Cheshire man, to
a Gentleman a deere friend of his in North∣hampton-shire.</title>
                 <author>W., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Newes out of Cheshire of the new found well</title>
                 <author>G. W.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>15 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prefatory_letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Newes out of Cheshire, concerning
the new found Well, as it is contained in a
Letter lately sent from a Cheshire man, to
a Gentleman a deere friend of his in North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton-shire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eartie commendations prefixed. You
earnestly desire me in your last letters
to impart vnto you a true report of the
<hi>New found Well</hi> here in Cheshire,
whereof you haue so many incredible
reportes in that countrey, as it would
greatly satisfie you to heare that which
were vndoubtedly true. That which
in so short a time I could gather and set downe for your satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
herein, I haue sent you inclosed. The matter it selfe would
require to be handled by some man of great learning and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
not one of my small vnderstanding, and to be published
to the world in a graue and iudiciall discourse, not barely repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in a plaine vnlearned letter: but syth you desire it, I will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture
to deliuer you my knowledge and opinion touching this
new VVell. If the length of my letter be trouble some to you, you
may thanke your selfe for vrging me to write of a matter which
my skill serueth not to containe in the limittes of an ordinarie
letter. Now I haue vndertaken it, I can be no briefer, then first
to preamble it a little: then to tell you the place, the situation, the
<pb facs="3"/>
description of the VVell, then some of the effectes and cures it
hath wrought, the credit and opinion it daily winnes, and to
doe you all the pleasure that I can in this intelligence I haue with
my penne drawne a true plot and scite of the VVell as it is
placed: so I desire to be heartily remembred to all my good
friendes at Stoke lodge.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Chester <date>the 12. of August. 1600.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your brother in law euer assured. G. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>