<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A Prophecie of Antichrist.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101368_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07146</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1755</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101368</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A Prophecie of Antichrist.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The reliques of Rome : contayning all such matters of religion, as haue in times past bene brought into the Church by the Pope and his adherentes: faithfully gathered out of the moste faithful writers of chronicles and histories, and nowe newly both diligently corrected &amp; greatly augmented, to the singuler profit of the readers, by Thomas Becon. 1563</title>
                 <author>Becon, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 144, 147-266 leaves, portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prophecy">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ A Prophecie of Antichrist.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ntichrist shall be, borne in great Ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bilon of an Harlot, that shal come of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tribe of Dā. He shalbe replenished with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> deuill in his mothers wōbe. He shalbe nourished with spirituall euils &amp; mischiefes. He shal rule ouer the whole world. He shal subdue all mākind vnto him by foure māner of wayes. First he shall bring the cōmon people vnder his dominion by terrour &amp; feare: for he shal exercise great cruelty &amp; tyrāny against the true worshippers of god. Secōdly, he shall win vnto him the noble personages, &amp; suche as be in authoritye, by geuyng thē greate gifts &amp; riches, wherof he shal haue great aboū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daūce &amp; plenty: for al the hid mony shal be open vnto him. Thirdly, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his wisedome &amp; eloquēce which shalbe wonderful and incredible, he shal make the clergy to cleaue vnto him: for he shall haue great knowledge of al arts, &amp; of the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Fourthly, thorow signes and wonders he shall deceaue such as despise the world, as mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, &amp; suche like. For he shal shew wonderfull signes and tokens. He shal be thought to cause fyre to come downe from heauen &amp; to consume his aduersaries before him, and to raise vp the dead to geue witnesse of hym. But he shall not rayse vp the dead in deede. But thorowe hys witchcraft and forcery he shall cause the deuill to enter into the body of some damned dead per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sō, &amp; this shal he cary about him, &amp; by this shall he so speake that euery mā shall thinke hym to be aliue, as it is written of hym: His comming shall be by the working of Sathā, with al lying power, signes &amp; wonders, &amp; in all deceauable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of vnrighteousnes among thē that perish.
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>
The Iewes and al misbeleuing persons out of all places of the worlde shall flock &amp; flow vnto him. But thorow the preaching of Enoch and Hely, the people shal forsake him &amp; returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the true and christē religion: wherof shal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue greate persecution and manslaughter, in so much that all in a manner shal suffer hard mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirdome. He shal rule and obtaine the monarchy by the space of three yeares &amp; an halfe. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he shall pitche his tente in the moūt Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet to the ende that he may destroy the rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. But he shall not preuayle. For in the very same mount shal he be found sodenly dead. For he shalbe slaine at the commaundement of God with the breath of the Lordes mouth, as it is written: the Lord shal cast downe Hedlong and vtterly destroye in the holy hill the stoutest gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt of the whole worlde. After these thynges peace and righteousnesses shall spryng vp, and the earth shalbe filled full of the knowledge of the Lorde, so that the Gospell of the kingdome shalbe preached in al the worlde. For there shal go vp sauiours vnto the mount of Sion to iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the hill of Esau: and the kyngdome shal be the Lordes.</p>
   <q>
      <bibl>
         <hi>Osey. 14.</hi>
      </bibl>
      <p>Who so is wise, shal vnderstand this, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e that is right instruct will regard it.</p>
      <bibl>
         <hi>Math, 24.</hi>
      </bibl>
      <p>Who so readeth it let him vnderstand.</p>
      <bibl>
         <hi>2. Timoth. 2.</hi>
      </bibl>
      <p>The Lorde geue the vnderstandyng in all thynges.</p>
   </q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>