<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101052_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05581</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1570</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101052</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe relation of certaine speciall and most materiall passages, and speeches in the Starre-Chamber : occasioned and delivered the 14th. day of Iune, 1637. At the censure of those three famous and worthy gentlemen, Dr. Bastwicke, Mr. Burton, and Mr. Prynne. Even so as it hath beene truely and faithfully gathered from their owne mouthes, by one present at the said censure</title>
                 <author>Bastwick, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Christiaens van der Boxe, Willem</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Leiden</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>CHristian Reader, I present you heere the <hi>Relation</hi> of such a
Censure (and the Execution thereof) as I dare say, all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances
layd together, cannot bee paralled in any age of man
throughout the Christian World, and I thinke I may take in even
the World of Pagans and Heathens to it. Which, though it bee not
drawne up in so eloquent a straine, as it was delivered &amp; deserved,
nor all the Heavenly words and eloquent speeches recorded, which
were uttered by these Three Worthies of the Lord, both in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
of the Lords themselves at their Censure, and also at the place
of Execution: Yet I earnestly beseech you in the bowels of Iesus
Christ, that you doe not in the least manner under-valu the glory
and dignitie, eyther of the Persons, or the cause, but rather lay
the blame upon the rudenes and meane capacity of the Composer,
who is an unfeyned Wel-wisher to them. <hi>Fare well.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>