<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ Theodore de Beze. to the Church of the Lord, grace and peace in him.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101755_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68595</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2007</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101755</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ Theodore de Beze. to the Church of the Lord, grace and peace in him.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe and piththie summe of the Christian faith : made in forme of a confession, vvith a confutation of all such superstitious errours, as are contrary therevnto. Made by Theodore de Beza. Translated out of Frenche by R.F</title>
                 <author>Bèze, Théodore de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Serle (Searl), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>23, 195, that is 185 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="16"/>
   <pb facs="16"/>
   <head>❧ <hi>Theodore de Beze.</hi> to the Church of the Lord, grace and peace in him.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the errours whiche raigne at thys daye in the worlde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout faith and Christiā religion, there be two which me thinketh bee as the springs &amp; fountaines of al the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The first is, that all which is done of a good intent is well done. The second is, that those which liue onely vpon the trafick or marchaundise of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens soules, haue persuaded the simple people that they neede not read y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> scriptures, nor particularly enquire of euery poinct of that which they are bound to beleeue for to be saued. But that it is sufficient to beléeue confused<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in a generalitie as the church of Rome beléeueth, and the rest to cōmit to the Diuines or to the conscience of his curate. Touching the first, it is
<pb facs="17"/>
néedfull to defyne what intent is good &amp; what euill. But to speak after their owne maner, for as much as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that all those which think they do well haue a good entent▪ if it so were what woulde haue let sainct P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ule to haue bene saued in his pharisaicall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing, seyng that he was an earnest fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower of the law of god giuen by Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses? And as for that he persecuted the members of Iesus christ, it was of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce, supposing to haue done god good seruice, as hee himselfe wytnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth. Yet this notwithstāding he saith he was a persecutour and a Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, so that God saued him of his sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular grace and mercy. The lyke case was of many of those which crucified Christ and stoned sainct Steuen, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge they did verye good seruice, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they estemed thē to be false pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets &amp; enimies to God. Neuertheles did their good meaning kepe them that they wer not horible murderers? But if God gaue forgiuen them, then it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb facs="17"/>
that they sinned. And who shal assure those of the lyke mercye which do as they did? I omitte the manifest textes, where such good ententes or meaninges be cursed of god, consyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring where no fayth is, ther is nought but sinne, and where there is no word of God, there is no fayth, but a lyinge and deceyuable opinion. I would fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> knowe whether there be any Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour that would be content and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for his full payment, that his det<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ur shoulde alledge, that he had drea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med that hee had payed him. Or if a Mayster had geuen by writinge hys whole mynde and wyll to one of hys seruauntes, and had gyuen hym in charge and commaundement, neither to ad to it, nor to diminish it: whether hee woulde bee content with his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt that woulde not vouchesafe to read his remembraunce, but trusting in his owne witte woulde doe al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges after his owne will and mynde. And neuerthelesse, Christendome is
<pb facs="18"/>
thus led that to reade the Scriptures for to know the will of their Maister, is heresye at this daye. And if they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge further that the common people haue no iudgemēt for to vnderstand y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> they do read, howe happeneth it then that they teach not the Scriptures to the people to remedy that? For the self same inconueniences haue bene in all ages▪ And neuertheles the prophetes. Iesu Christ, nor the Apostles, neither spake nor writ but in the commō vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar tonge, which was then vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of all the people where they vsed. And when wee saye that hee is not a Christian which knoweth not what he beleueth, nor why and wherfore he beleueth it: doo we saye that he muste read the scriptures without hearinge them syncerelye expounded of those whiche haue the charge &amp; office to doe it? No, but contrariwise, we saye and also practyse it, that the Pastours are bounde to feede theyr flockes with the worde of lyfe, and that the flocke
<pb facs="18"/>
on their parte muste vnderstande and learne that whiche they teache them to be edified and comforted ther by. Also they must take heede and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the false Prophets and wolfs. And certeinly if this Lampe hadd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes burned cleare in the Churche of God, they whiche at these dayes feare nothinge more then this lighte, and whiche woulde take it from the common people to leade them still in their blindnes, had not so muche pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed as they haue. For the kingdom of God is not a kyngedome of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but of fayth, and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of knowledge: consyderynge that a man cannot beléeue that whiche hée knoweth not.</p>
   <p>Briefelye, for as muche as all Christians bee expresselye warned of Sainct Peter, to bée in a readynesse to make aunswere to all those whyche demaunde a reason of theyr hope: So it appeareth by this, that the duetye of a true Chrystian, is to
<pb facs="19"/>
haue ready, and with him some briefe resolution and summe of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall pointes of hys Religion, and also some principall reasons, whereby hee maye on the one parte confyrme and strengthen himselfe therein, and on the other parte, repell accordinge to his callinge, the enemies of the truth, and be ready to communicate his spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ryches with all men.</p>
   <p>Wherevppon, I bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> already of that mynde, and besyde the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge required to render a reason of my faythe, by a personage to whome nexte vnto God I am moste bounde to obey: I haue of late composed and made this Treatyse which I haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tytuled A confession of the faith, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in I haue comprehended after the best order I coulde, those thinges whych I haue learned in the Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion by the reading of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Byble, with the conference of the moste faythefull Expositours.</p>
   <p>At the first I made this but for mine
<pb facs="19"/>
own vse, and to satisfie him who requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red of me. But since partly by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyse of certayne good and learned mē, and also being moued with certayne reasons whiche mee thought were of importance, I was easely persuaded to haue it set abroade.</p>
   <p>For fyrste, I knowe, that among those whiche persecute the Gospell of God in his members, there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that offende thorough ignoraunce whom it is very hard to make vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand how muche they be deceyued, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept before they be put to the reading of the textes of the scripture, they haue some brief instruction which may opē the matter playn vnto them, and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome them with the maner of speach of the holy ghost for to gather oute the true sence and meaning, &amp; referre the whole to the right vse and end. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, euen amonge those whiche haue some vnderstandinge of gods truth, I knowe that there be many verye neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and slow to read the scriptures,
<pb facs="20"/>
because they knowe not the treasures which therin be contained. And many also, although they read the scripturs diligently, as al christians ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipally to doe, and can after a sort dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e true exposition from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> false, yet neuertheles haue not so ready iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment and such capacitie, that they can aptly set &amp; agree together those textes which they fynde dispersed in diuerse places of one mater for to comprehend them w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll, to their edifyinge and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. And this is the cause why in the church of Christ so long as it was well gouerned, ther was euermore an instruction called a Cathechisme, for those that were lately comme to the knowledge of the eternall god. But this very woorde Cathechisme decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that thys Instruction was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by worde of mouth then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse▪ And I thinke that from thence dyd procéede the symbole of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles as we call it, the exposition wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was declared by mouth in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> church.
<pb facs="20"/>
After this when it pleased god to erect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>p againe the banner of his Church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hich had bene long tyme ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>en: this custome not one y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> moste <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>audable, but also moste necessarye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>as erected vp agayne, yea to more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ification then euer it was, as me thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eth, and as in verye deede experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and time must needes teache the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ysest sorte of men some thinge. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hey haue not onely sette forth the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ient maner to cathechise, that is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ay, to instruct by mouth those that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ately entred into the church of god, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rncipall poinctes of Christian rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ion orderly and briefely, but also too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uoyde many inconueniences, those Cathechismes were sette foorth and writtten for a singular profyte, bothe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> greate and small. And although <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n these beginninges of the resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>inge and repayringe of the decayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f the Churche, the synceritie of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rine and familiar manner of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hinge was not in all pointes suche
<pb facs="21"/>
as was to bée wyshed, yet no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> withstandinge these maners and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s teachinge bée verye meete for to remedy and helpe those inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which I haue spokē of heretofore. And this I dare well say that ther shal not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> found eyther in times past or to come any suche worke published and sette abroade wherby to haue a briefe and perfecte knowledge of the wholle Christian religion as is the Cathechis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of this Church of Geneua▪ god bee praysed therefore, and his faithful ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>antes labour acknowledged, which hath so happely and profitablye trauay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led in this worke Although ther be I knowe dogges both farre of and neare whiche barke after him, and except for barking they woulde bee as domme, as domme Fys<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hes: but when as they meete with beasts of their own kinde then they be at libertie to prate and ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble withoute knowledge. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to my purpose, I confesse that it was not greatly néedefull to set for the
<pb facs="21"/>
this confession after that Cathechisme wherof I haue spoken. Neuertheles because men are geuen in heauenlye foode euen lyke as they be in bodelye meats to weete that one and the same meate, shal please some in one kind of dressing, and other in an other kynde or waye: I haue enforced my selfe somthyng more to dilate and declare matters at large: as one that wold not so much teache the auditors which are alreadye bente and willyng to heare and learne in the church of God▪ as also to aunswere those which do with stand the truthe of GOD, or at the leaste those whyche bée in dowte in whyche syde to turne themselues. I hope wyth the grace of hym whose honoure I haue regarded in this little worcke, that my laboure shall not bée wythoute profite, neyther for those whiche suffer theym selues to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed in anye thynge that maye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ee inuented agaynste vs eyther in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yfe or doctryne, nor for those whyche
<pb facs="22"/>
haue alreadye some taste and féeling to encorage and sturre them vp to the viligent Reading of the seripturs, and to resorte and draw water as it were out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very head spring or fountayn from whence these brokes do run, not yet to establish and resolue thē whiche haue néede therof. True it is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> among other faults I confesse that I haue not bene so briefe as were requisit in such an argument wherein men ought on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to declare and open the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of matters without disputing, yet I hope at the length, considering y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of the enemies with whome we haue to do, it shall not be so troublous but it shall serue to some purpose, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I haue endeuored my selfe to speake of nothing but that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the very pith of the matter, and which is necessary to resolue him which should come read this treatise with some preiudise to the contrary.</p>
   <p>And this was my entent and mynde not to prescibe to anye man lyuynge
<pb facs="22"/>
a forme of confession of his fayth, but fyrst to declare myne owne to al those whiche are mynded to vnderstande it to the glory of my God. And then also to helpe according to my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> power those that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e leaste of the Churche of God. I hope also that at the least I shal geue occasion to those which without comparison haue wherew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th better then I to furnishe and set out so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable a worke in Christendome: to compile and make som more absolute and perfect worke, whose iudgements I am so farre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>m refusinge, that on the contrarye I desyre that all those which shall see this confession wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it diligently with the Scripturs whiche are the onely true touche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone to proue true doctrine by. But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> there be any thinge herein which is worthy of reprehension, which I hope shall not befounde in the substaunce of the doctrine, I am one whiche desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with all my hart to vnderstande it, to amende the fault thereof. If one
<pb facs="23"/>
the other syde, there founde anye goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thyng in it, as I would be sory if the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> were not, his be the praise which hath reueled to mée his holye trueth, and shall reuele it yet more fully when wée shall haue the accomplishe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that which we looke for.</p>
   <closer>God be praysed.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>