<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the right woorshipfull Mai∣ster Edwarde Dier, of the Court esquire, Iohn Frampton wisheth encrease of woorship and of all felicitie.</title>
           <author>Frampton, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101702_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00400</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10529</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101702</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the right woorshipfull Mai∣ster Edwarde Dier, of the Court esquire, Iohn Frampton wisheth encrease of woorship and of all felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Frampton, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse of the nauigation which the Portugales doe make to the realmes and prouinces of the east partes of the worlde : and of the knowledge that growes by them of the great thinges, which are in the dominions of China. Written by Barnardine of Escalanta, of the realm of Galisia priest. Translated out of Spanish into English, by Iohn Frampton</title>
                 <author>Escalante, Bernardino de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>46, that is 47, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>❧ To the right woorshipfull Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> Edwarde Dier, of the Court esquire, Iohn <hi>Frampton wisheth encrease of woorship and</hi> of all felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was brought mee not long agoe right woorshipful Sir, out of Spayne, a discourse in the Spanish tongue, of the Nauigation that the Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales haue to the kingdomes and prouinces of the East<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> partes of the worlde, and of the intelligence of the same Portugale Nation, which they nowe of late haue gotten in those partes of the greatnesse of the Dominion, and politike gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Famous Countrey <hi>China:</hi> And finding in the same discourse a verification, by newe, late, and present ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, of this our age and present time of many things, written long agoe by <hi>Paulus Venetus,</hi> which woorke of <hi>Paulus</hi> I did translate, and about a yeere past dedicated to your worship: I became the more desirous also to translate this into the English, &amp; the rather bycause this worke see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to haue a certaine affinitie in matter, and also con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned great varietie of thinges, not conteyned in the woorke of the sayde <hi>Paulus Venetus:</hi> And fynding now in England many excellent men in the Art of Nauigation, &amp; as well able to endure extreame heate, as extreame colde, and to crosse the burnte lyne, as also able to passe the
<pb facs="3"/>
colde Zone, and frosen Sea, and with all youth and frye of the Realme, bothe infinitly abounding: and also ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly inflamed with desire to attempte newe disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueries, I the rather decreed the translation heereof, and was fully perswaded that the great Almightie GOD hath wrought the one and the other, to the ende that hee woulde haue his sonne Iesus that hath brought salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto the worlde, knowen to nations not yet disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered. For what more pleasante Sacrifyce can wee offer in this life, vnto our GOD, then to labour in all that euer wee may, to bring the Barbarous to Ciuilitie, the Rude to knowledge, the superstitious to the true &amp; liuely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of his name, to win them from darknesse to light, frō crueltie to curtesie, from vanitie to veritie, from death vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life? If wee bee not borne to profite our selues, but to seeke the aduaūcemēt of Gods glory, how commendable an enterprise is that? how highly to be wished? how much to be furthered, which not onely encreaseth the profite of our countrey, but augmenteth the nūber of the faithful. Therfore God hauing decreed to make himselfe knowen as well by our Englishe Nation in some quarters of the vnknowen worlde, as he hath of late yeeres beene by the Spaniarde in West: and by the Portugale in the Easte. And beeyng mooued to take in hande this small transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by personnes of sundry callynges, and especially by diuerse moste excellent Pilottes, Maisters, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly young Marriners, muche exceedyng in knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and godly lyfe many of that profession that haue been heretofore: I haue, other needful busines set aparte, perfourmed theyr requeste: And the thing that I much desired, for the loue I beare to good discoueries: And now dedicate the same to your woorshyp, as a speciall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourer of all good knowledges, and of all enterpises tending too the glory of GOD, the honour of your Prince, and the publike benefite of your Countrey, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching your woorship too take the same this my tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation
<pb n="3" facs="3"/>
in good part, as a poore shew of a mynde willyng to requite some parte of your bountie and benefite recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at your handes, not doubting but that this maye geue lyght to our Nation and woorke in many respectes benefite too all suche, as shall by the Northeast, or by the Northwest attempt discoueries of Dominions and Territories, wtihin the circle Artike, or with out the same to the Tropicke of Cancer▪ And thus wishing vntoo your woorshippe the fauour of Almightie GOD with encrease of all knowledge Diuine and Humane, I take my leaue and ceasse to trouble you. </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From London <date>this first day of October. 1579.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your worships in that he</hi> may, at commaundement. Iohn Frampton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>