<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface of Thomas Paynell. Chanon of Marton to the gentell Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101610_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08438</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1876</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101610</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface of Thomas Paynell. Chanon of Marton to the gentell Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The boke of measuryng of lande : as well of woodland as plowland, &amp; pasture in the feelde: &amp; to compt the true nombre of acres of the same. Newly corrected, &amp; compiled by Sir Richarde de Benese</title>
                 <author>Benese, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Colwell, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface of Thomas Paynell. Chanon of Marton to the gentell Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is most cōmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie sene, that euery mā doth most cōmende y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thing that he is best experte &amp; sene in. And therfore some ther are y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> exfoll diuin letters, some the law, &amp; som Philosophy, with suche other lyberall sciences, in the which they are learned and exercysed.</p>
   <p>Other ther are y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> do not onely extoll thē, but after they haue so done, they dispute whither of them are moste laudable, and most worthy to be preferred aboue other Ther are lykewyse y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> after longe dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion do not onelye assygne euery sience his peculier laude &amp; praise, but all so y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusse whether that of such noble sciences are most for thy cōmon weale supposyng (and wyll) that thinge to be moste excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, that is for euerye mannes profyte, and that common vtylytye and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syte
<pb facs="3"/>
dothe none other wise ercede priuat gayn &amp; profyt than gold all other metals.</p>
   <p>These men (after my sentence) gre in a very good opinion, for the diuine Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to saith: that man is not borne onelye to profyte him selfe, or any synguler per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, but to profite the cōmon welth also The which doth then prosper &amp; floryshe, when gouerners and rulers doe tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and intierlye abiectynge all synguler affection, looke and take hede vnto it.</p>
   <p>My diligēce and study is (saith Scipio Africanus) not onelye to beware howe rome be now in my time ruled: but how I may inuent fashions &amp; meanes, that it may increase, &amp; be well gouerned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. O what an excellent worde and saynge was that.</p>
   <p>What other thynge but onely y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> welth publyke moued M. Curius to saye thus to the Samnites, offerynge hym great sumes of moneye, I desyre none of your gold (quoth hee) but I desyre that ye and your riches may be vnder the dominien of the Romaynes. O. was not that an excellent aunswere.</p>
   <p>And that O. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s conspired to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Porcenna enemy to the Romanes
<pb facs="3"/>
without any hope or sauegard of hys life was it for the cōmon welth of Rome.</p>
   <p>And did not the onelye wealth publike in force M. Regulus to perswade the Senatours of Rome that they shoulde not restore the yonge galauntes of Cartago to prolonge his lyfe withall. They are lusty (quoth he,) and in theyr floures, and apt to do vs muche sorowe, and so her re turned agayne to Cartago well assured that hee shuld neuer escape theyr handes alyue. O what synguler affection and loue had this man to the cōmon wele, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> preferred it aboue hys owne lyfe of all thynge the most estemed, and beste belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Are not suche men worthy to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerners and rulres of cyties and of the common weale.</p>
   <p>As longe as Rome &amp; Cartago, with other lyke cytyes, had suche regentes &amp; gouerners, they prospe red and had abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of all thinge. But after that syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler affection, synguler cōmodytie and profyte, ambycion, Idlenes &amp; voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pleasure toke theyr enter, then all that (wysdome, diligence, studye &amp; great labour had augmented) decaied. Then these moste excellent and ryche Cyties
<pb facs="4"/>
fell in ruyne, and were easely subdued. The which thyng doth declare and open theyr great laude, by whose gubernaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, rule and pollicie, they came to suche hyghe renowne &amp; fame. By this it doth now appeare &amp; folow y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> such politike Ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers are worthy of much laud &amp; great cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēdacion. But what cōmendadion laud, &amp; praise shall we esteme and iudge them worthy of, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ingeniouflie haue inuented &amp; cloquently discribed, how and by what subtile and politike fasshions, such places shuld be gouerned &amp; ascended to high ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure. And againe how Gouerners of a cōmon wealth shulde vse them selues in theyr offices. And not withstandinge there be that do eleuate &amp; extoll the doer &amp; the inuenter of thinngs aboue the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet after my minde, the inuenter, wryter, or expositer of other mēnes wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynges are worthye of no lytle prayse, what reason shuld defende him, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> would saye, that the executer of the Lawe (by whose ayde all cōmon weales are orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ruled) to be of more excellency then Moyses, the fyrste of all lawyers.
<pb facs="4"/>
Shuld any Phylosopher prefer hym selfe aboue Pytagoras the fyrst Phylosopher, or any Astronomer aboue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chyldren of Seth, the very inuēters &amp; foundaciō ther of, or any Musician aboue Tuball, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meths son, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fyrst y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euer gaue any study to Musycke, or any Physyciā aboue Apol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lo or any Arithmeticiā, aboue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aminus, Pytagoras, Pallas, or Algus (of whō A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rythmetike is called Agrym, (the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of nombres. Or any Geometrician a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue Cain, the which taught the Hebrici ans the maner and crafte of weightes &amp; measures? Is it not (tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w ye) more to in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uent and fynde, than to adde vnto that, that is found al redy. And as Agrym was found for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> course of marchandyse &amp; the accomptes therof, so was Geometry vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the excursions and ouerflowing of the floud Nilus whose insidaciōs and surges were suche that they confounded and so troubled the lymytes and bondes of the land of Egypt, that they knew not theyr owne Lande from other mēnes. Of this toke Geometrye hys Oryginall begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the which includeth the measuryng
<pb facs="5"/>
both of lande &amp; water, the vse of weygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and knowledge of the vniuersall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre of the bodyes aboue, the distaunce and greatnes of starres, mocyons, and reflections.</p>
   <p>Carpenters and Masons, withe suche other Artyficers doe vse Geometrye, by the which all maner of ingynes and craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye ordynaunces of warre, and other ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteynynge vnto theyr arte doe depend as hangynge roofes, and Galaryes, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, shyppes, Gallayes, Brydges, Milles Cartes, and wheeles, with the whyche, thynges of great weyght, are verye ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lye drawen and hoysed vp.</p>
   <p>Also what soeuer goeth by weyghte, water or wynde, or by cordes, as Cloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, the whych goeth by weygtes, and Organes, the whiche soundeth by the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hemence and force of the wynde, dothe longe vnto thys noble Scyence. The ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall crafte also of warre, of castynge of Belles, and Bomberdes, or Gonnes with suche other Artylery, whither they be of tymbre or metall doe for the moste parte depende of Geometrye.</p>
   <p>And did not the noble Archytas make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Doue of woode, to lyfte her selfe vpp,
<pb facs="5"/>
and to flye by Geometrie.</p>
   <p>Did not Archimenides, make an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument of Brasse, wherin men myght easely perceyue the mocyons of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nettes, withe other thynges comprysed in the materyall Speare, &amp; howe to mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sure the altitude and height of all suche thinges as man maye see and not come vnto? And those thynges also that lye playne, deepe, rounde, cornerwise, in lengthe, or in breadthe be longethe vnto Geometrye, the whiche conteyneth. iii. dyuers kyndes of measuringe.</p>
   <p>The fyrst is named Altemetria to me asure a quantytie after his lenghte only.</p>
   <p>The seconde is named Planimetrya, that is, to measure a quantitye after hys length and breadth.</p>
   <p>The thyrde is called Tercometria, that is to measure a quantytie after hys length, breadth, and deepenesse.</p>
   <p>In this Scence, are certayne quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyties, called famouse quantities, as a Fynger, a Palme, a Foote a Cubite, a Pace, a Perche, a stake &amp; a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yse, withe such other, moch necessarie to be knowen</p>
   <p>It were very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>edyous to expound all the Termes, Partes, Properties, and
<pb facs="6"/>
Vtylities of Geometrye. For notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standynge that God may, and can doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng without nōbre, measure, weyght or any poynte of Geometrye, yet when hee gaue the fyrmament the Planettes, and starres, theyr mocions, the earthe, fourme and fasshion, the Sea, withe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther riuers, theyr bankes, hee dyd it by nombre, weyght, and measure.</p>
   <p>Wherfore I may well extoll this most noble Science conteinynge these three, withe the knowledge of manye other ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall and manuall artes, ryght necesary for the cōmon weale of man, Considerig thē this lyberall Science called Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to be in euery thig much conuenient for the vse &amp; cōmon profite of all men. A Frende and a louer of myne, a Chanon of Marton, named Syr Rycharde Benese, not willing to hyde the treasure, that god hath enryched hym withall. But euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more myndinge &amp; labouringe (as the fore sayd Romaynes dyd) to encrease the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon wealth, hauinge also this saienge of the Phylosopher in memory. The more profytable a thinge is, the more it shulde
<pb facs="6"/>
be common, hee hath, (I saye) compyled this ingenyous and profytable Booke, for the common profite, and vse of euery man</p>
   <p>Wherin is sufficiently &amp; breiflie cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned the perfecte fourme &amp; rule of mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>suryng of woodlande, hilles &amp; mountay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? whersoeuer, how soeuer or in what fourme or quantitie soeuer they lye.</p>
   <p>Also of deuidinge of one acre of wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande or mo from many other acres.</p>
   <p>And of measuring of Timbre, square or rounde? Boordes, Tables, &amp; Panes of Glasse, by the foote square.</p>
   <p>He hath furthermore so exprest these intricate and harde poyntes of Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye by fygures, rules, &amp; such open exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples, that euery man, applyenge hys mynde therunto, maye wythout anye great labour attayne vnto the perfecte knowledge therof. Vale.</p>
   <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the Preface.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>