<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right hyghe and mighty Prince, the Duke of Northumberlande, hys grace.</title>
           <author>Eden, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1553</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101322_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07873</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18244</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101322</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right hyghe and mighty Prince, the Duke of Northumberlande, hys grace.</title>
                 <author>Eden, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatyse of the newe India : with other new founde landes and islandes, aswell eastwarde as westwarde, as they are knowen and found in these oure dayes, after the description of Sebastian Munster in his boke of universall cosmographie: wherin the diligent reader may see the good successe and rewarde of noble and honeste enterpryses, by the which not only worldly ryches are obtayned, but also God is glorified, [and] the Christian faythe enlarged. Translated out of Latin into Englishe. By Rycharde Eden</title>
                 <author>Münster, Sebastian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                    <distributor>Sutton, Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1553</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>204 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶To the right hyghe and mighty Prince, the Duke of Northumberlande, hys grace.</head>
   <p>I Reade in auncient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (most noble prince) how that mightie kyng and conquerour of the world, Alexander the great, at such tyme as he beheld y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tombe of fearse Achilles, &amp; therewith called to his remēbraunce howe excellently the Poet Homere had set forth his he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical factes, which notwithstāding he thoughte to be muche inferiour vnto his, he sighed &amp; sayde: Oh the most fortunate, which haste founde such a trōpe to magnifi thi doinges, meaning hereby, that the fame of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles was no lesse notable to hys posteritie by homers writing, thē it was in hys lyfe tyme by hys owne


<pb facs="5"/>
marcial affayres. Wherby we maye perceue such magnanimitie to haue ben in our predicessours, men of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; stout courage, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they thought it not sufficiente in their life time to deserue prayse &amp; honour, except the same might also redounde to theyr posteritie, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they mighte therby bee encouraged to do the like. Whyche thing truely hath ben y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cause, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in al ages, noble enterprises haue ben cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, &amp; such as haue attempted y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same, haue bene honoured. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if honest cōmendacions be a iust reward dew to noble enterprises, so much do they robbe &amp; spoyle from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dignitie therof, which in any poynt diminishe the same: no lesse confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge the order of thinges, then he whiche cloteth an ape in purple, &amp; a king in sackecloth. This I speake y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> rather, beecause there chaunsed of late to come to my handes, a shiete of printed paper, (more worthy so to


<pb facs="5"/>
bee called then a boke) entytuled of the newe founde landes. The whyche t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tle when I readde, as one not vtterlye ignoraunt hereof, hauynge before in my tyme readde <hi>Decades,</hi> and also the nauigations <hi>de nouo orbe,</hi> there seemed too me no lesse inequalitye betwene the tytle and the booke, then if a man woulde professe to wryte of Englande, and entreated onelye of Trumpington a vyllage wythin a myle of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brydge. Wherefore partelye mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the good affeccion, whyche I haue euer borne to the science of Cosmographie, whyche entreately of the descripcion of the worlde, whereof the newe founde landes are no smal part, &amp; much more by y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> good wyll, whych of duetie I beare to my natyue countrey &amp; countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mē, which haue of late to their great praise (whatsoeuer succede) attēp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> newe viages to serche y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> seas


<pb facs="6"/>
and newe found lādes, I thought it worthy my trauayle, to their better comfort, (as one not otherwise able to further theyr enterprise) to trās<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late this boke oute of latin into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishe. The which, albeit it do not so largely or particulerlye entreate of euery part, region or cōmoditie of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayd new found landes, as the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of the thing might requyre: yet sure I am that aswel they which set forth or take vpō thē this viage, as also they which shal hereafter at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lyke, may in this smal boke as in a little glasse, see some cleare light, not only how to learne by the example dāmage, good successe, and aduētures of other, how to behaue them selues &amp; direct theyr viage to their most cōmoditie, but also if dew successe herein shoulde not chaunce according vnto theyr hope &amp; expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taciō (as oftētimes chāceth in great affaires,) yet not for one foyle or fal, so to be dismayd as with shame and


<pb facs="6"/>
dishonor to leaue wyth losse, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the death to persist in a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, honeste, &amp; lawful purpose, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that wheras one death is dewe to nature, the same is more honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably spēt in such attemptes as may be to the glorye of God &amp; cōmoditie of our countrey, then in soft beddes at home, amōg the teares &amp; weping of women. Which manlye courage (like vnto that which hath ben seen and proued in your grace, aswell in forene realmes, as also in this oure countrey) yf it had not been wāting in other in these our dayes, at suche time as our souereigne Lord of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble memorie Kinge Henry the .viij. about the same yere of his raygne, furnished &amp; sent forth certen shippes vnder the gouernaunce of Sebasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Cabot yet liuing, &amp; one syr Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Perte, whose faynt heart was the cause that that viage toke none effect, yf (I say) such manly courage


<pb facs="7"/>
wherof we haue spoken, had not at that tyme bene wanting, it myghte happelye haue comen to passe, that that riche treasurye called <hi>Perularia,</hi> (which is now in Spayne in the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Ciuile, and so named, for that in it is kepte the infinite ryches brought thither frō the newe found land of <hi>Peru,</hi>) myght longe since haue bene in the towre of London, to the kinges great honoure and welth of this his realme. What riches the Emperoure hath gotten oute of all the newe founde landes, it may wel appeare, wheras onlye in the Ilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of <hi>Hispana</hi> or <hi>Hispaniola</hi> and <hi>Cuba</hi> &amp; other Ilandes there aboute, were gathered in two monethes twelue thousand poundes weyght of gold as youre grace maye reade in this boke, in the descripcion of the Ilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Yet speake I here nothynge of perles, precious stones, and spices. Neyther yet of the greate aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce


<pb facs="7"/>
of golde, whiche is engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred almost in al regions neare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>AEquinoctial</hi> line. And wheras I am aduertised y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> youre grace haue bene a greate fortherer of thys vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, (as you haue bene euer studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for the cōmoditie of your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,) I thought my trauayl herein coulde no wayes be more worthely bestowed, then to dedicate the same vnto your grace: Most humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siringe youre honoure so to accepte mine intente herein, as one whose good will hath not wanted to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie your grace with a better thing if mine abilitie were greater. Thus Almighty God preserue your grace in health and honour long to continue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>¶Your graces poore o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratour Rychard Eden.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>