<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To M. Doctor Haddon.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101135_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08567</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18887</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101135</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To M. Doctor Haddon.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An epistle of the reuerend father in God Hieronymus Osorius Bishop of Arcoburge in Portugale, to the most excellent Princesse Elizabeth by the grace of God Quene of England, Fraunce, and Ireland, &amp;c. Translated oute of Latten in to Englishe by Richard Shacklock M. of Arte and student of the ciuill Lawes in Louaine</title>
                 <author>Osório, Jerónimo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Diest (Coppens van Diest), Aegidius (Gillis)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78, 2 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="84"/>
   <head>To M. Doctor Haddon.</head>
   <p>VAlens the Emperour, as Nazianzenas
dothe wytnesse, beyng poysoned with
Arrius heresie, after he had wrytten
with his owne hand many wordes cōcerning
the banishment of saynt Basill, yet coulde not
fynishe those wrytynges, for so muche as the
pen dyd thre tymes refuse to yelde yncke. Not
withstandynge, he beyng obstinae in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed
malyce, dyd not leaue of to wryte that
wycked Decree, and to subscribe vnto it when
it was wryten, tyll a greate cramp or palsye
dyd come in to his hād, which dyd smyte such
a feare and terroure in to hys hart, that with
his owne hand he dyd teare that, which he had
once put in wrytyng. O terrible, o fearefull
example. For the loue of God remember this
history M. Doctor Haddon. And whereas it
dyd not feare you to wryte agaynst Osorius
at the fyrst, because peraduenture either you
knewe it not, or ells dyd forget it, nowe seyng
you do knowe it, and haue it freshe in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye,
despyse it not. But let it be a warnyng to
you, whether you be moued of youre owne
heade, or pricked forward with the suggestion
of other, whether you be in your priuate par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,
or publyke parlament howse, that you say
nothing, write nothing, subscribe to nothyng,
pertayning to the defacyng of the truthe, lest
<pb facs="84"/>
suche a cramp take you in the hand, when you
sholde wryte, suche a palsye come in to youre
tonge when you sholde speake, that you be a
spectacle to all them which see you or heare
you. Entre in to an humble confession of your
owne imperfectiō, that although in humanity
you can do very commendably, yet when you
come to declame in diuinitye, agaynst the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
you can no more bestirre your selfe, then
young Dauid coulde in Saules heauie helmet,
and boysterouse armoure,<note place="margin">1. Re. 17.</note> with the which he
was neuer accustomed. VVherfor I pray you,
vse that, of which you haue some skyll, refuse
that, whereof you be all together ignorant. If
you wyll not ceasse, I assure you, you shall
styrre vp so many aduersaries agaynst you,
that whereas you be M. of the Requestes, and
for that cause, ought allway to be at leasure
to heare petitions, when sueters come to you,
you shall be fayne to make them answer: I
pray you, troble me not, I must go answer O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorius
of Portugall, I must answer Hosius in
Polonia, suche a man in such a countrie. &amp;c.
And if you wyll not make them suche an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer,
yet your brayne shall be busyed with so
many bookes and letters, from so many places
of youre betters, that your mynde shall not
<pb facs="85"/>
be vpon youre charge. So that either you shal
be put oute of youre office for negligence, or
elles sent from the Court to Cambridge for
pitye, that you may haue more leasure to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
youre aduersaries. VVhiche chaunge I
thinck you wolde not willyngly chose: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I pray you, followe my former councell.
Stay your selfe, recompence your troblesome
eloquence, with charitable and quiet sylence.
But if you thinke, that I haue done you iniury
by trāslatyng O forius, you may easily reuenge
me by translating youre answer, if you thynk
it to be truer. VVhether you do translate it or
no, because you be M. of the requestes, I pray
you, graunt me thys request: Increase not I
pray you your olde fault with a new offence,
make no new resistaūce against the auncyent
veritie. And that you may be the more a feard
hereafter to abuse youre hand in writyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst
Osorius, or any other Catholyke, turn
the boke named Symbola heroica, heroicall
deuyses, where in among many pictures, you
shall fynde a shaking hand, with a pen lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng
oute of it, &amp; this posye wryten ouer it.
<hi>Vlterius ne tende odiis.</hi> Let this be in payn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
tables euer before youre eyes, let this be
your heroicall deuyse, and I trust it shal feare
<pb facs="85"/>
you from the lyke vyce. VVhich, I pray God,
you neuer cōmit agayn, whose grace I wyshe
you, that you may worthily repent for that
which you haue done all redy. Amen.</p>
   <closer>Fare you well.
From Antwerp the .27. of Marche.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>