<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Bradshaw, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101908_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08562</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18880</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101908</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A manuell or briefe volume of controuersies of religion betweene the Protestants and the Papists : wherein the arguments of both sides are briefely set downe, and the aduersaries sophismes are plainely refuted. Written in Latine in a briefe and perspicuous method by Lucas Osiander, and now Englished with some additions and corrections</title>
                 <author>Osiander, Lucas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 486 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>AS their part is the chiefest in defēding the truth vvho do sifte the full state of Controuersies, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicating the question, maintaining reasons for the truth, and answearing the opposite argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at large, as the nature of euery one doth require for the full setling of mens iudgments, vvho with sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glenesse of heart desire to bee throughly satisfied; so is their labour requisite also, who do contract those larger disputations into a briefe and compendious summ. For it helpeth the memory, in calling to minde that vvhich hath beene reade in larger discourses before; it furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the iudgment, by giuing grounds of arguments &amp; answeares, which may afterward by the learned Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be further enlarged by his owne meditations as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion shall require: it may serue for some good taste in the knowledge of controuersies for such as haue not the leisure &amp; other opportunities &amp; means to read the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger disputations; and lastly being cōprised in a small vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, it may easily be caried abroad, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e desire to read such things, vvhere wee cannot haue not the greater volumes. VVhich reasons moued our Author to pen
<pb facs="3"/>
this briefe Manuell in a perspicuous methode, and it vvere to be wished that some of our Countrey men, whō God hath furnished with iudgment and other necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for such a purpose would endeuour to do the like in our vulgar tongue, in this briefe and plaine order, In the meane time the translation of this present worke shall bee, I trust, neither vnprofitable nor vnwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. Some things are altered, vvhich I iudged might bee offensiue, or othervvise hinder the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; but they bee such a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d no moe, than, I hope, who so shall compare the translation with the Originall vvith indifferencie, will confesse there vvas reason to doe so. Some things also, vvhere neede seemed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, I haue added, and vvhereas the Author in testimonies alleadged out of the Scripture quoted the chapter onely, I haue generally throughout for the ease of the reader annexed the verses also, as the case requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. The censure heereof I leaue to the indifferent reader, and commend the successe to God, vvhose Name be glorified for euer, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>