<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Courteous Reader, this should have come in at
the 3. Question, concerning the Consecration of Churches;
Immediatly before the words of Bishop Pilkington there
cited, Page 214. Line 32.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101532_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10197</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20474</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101532</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Courteous Reader, this should have come in at
the 3. Question, concerning the Consecration of Churches;
Immediatly before the words of Bishop Pilkington there
cited, Page 214. Line 32.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A quench-coale. Or A briefe disquisition and inquirie, in vvhat place of the church or chancell the Lords-table ought to be situated, especially vvhen the Sacrament is administered? : VVherein is evidently proved, that the Lords-table ought to be placed in the midst of the church, chancell, or quire north and south, not altar-wise, with one side against the wall: that it neither is nor ought to be stiled an altar; that Christians have no other altar but Christ alone, who hath abolished all other altars, which are either heathenish, Jewish, or popish, and not tollerable among Christians. All the pretences, authorities, arguments of Mr. Richard Shelford, Edmond Reeve, Dr. John Pocklington, and a late Coale from the altar, to the contrary in defence of altars, calling the Lords-table an altar, or placing it altarwise, are here likewise fully answered and proved to be vaine or forged. By a well-wisher to the truth of God, and the Church of England</title>
                 <author>Prynne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>‘Richt Right’ Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78, 2, 358, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="39"/>
   <pb n="77" facs="39"/>
   <head>Courteous Reader, this should have come in at
the 3. Question, concerning the Consecration of Churches;
Immediatly before the words of Bishop Pilkington there
cited, Page 214. Line 32.</head>
   <p>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es Ecclesiae Brit: p. 85. 86. 87</note> Mathew Parker, <hi>the Learned</hi> Arch-Bishop of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<hi>relating the</hi> forme of Consecrating Churches, Chapples, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars,
Foundation-stones, Vestments, Chalices, and the like, <hi>out
of the ancient</hi> Missals and Saxon Pontificals, <hi>which our
Bishops at this day use; Concludes thus of them all.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <q>Who can doubt, but that Papall Rites and Ceremonies
abound with these kinde of Exorcismes, which differ
nothing at all from these anciently used in the Ordalium
and vulgar forme of Purgation, which they at length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned,
yea rather abound with more and more stupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
Conjurations then they?</q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <q>But S. Augustine, who in his time complained of the
multitude of Ceremonies, if he were now alive, what
would he thinke of that immense and prolix number of
Ceremonie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> in use?</q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <q>For writing to <hi>Ianuarius,</hi> he thus speakes of Ceremonies:</q>
Notwithstanding he hath laden with servile burthens Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
itselfe, (which the mercy of God would have to be free,
with very few and most manifest Ceremonies of Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,)
that the condition of the Iewes is now more tollerable
then that of Christians: Who although they acknowledge
not the time of liberty, yet they are Subject to the rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of the Law, not to human presumptions or Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ons.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="78" facs="40"/>
      <q>Thus <hi>Augustine:</hi> And verify the condition of this our
time is much to be deplored, that the Fathers of the
Church, either will not, or cannot with the same edge of
their minde, cut off these and such like Ceremonies, or
rather TRIFLES from the Church, where with they
discerned and corrected these former vices of Ordalium,
or triall by fire. But those being damned and abolished
as Superstitious, they still hold fast and retaine these (Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrations)
QUAMVIS PUERILIA ET DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIRIA
SINT, although they are Childish things
and Dotages framed and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>piled out of them. How
much more equall then moderne Papists, was Pope Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie,</q>
who writes; That the rules of the Holy Fathers
were delivered according to the circumstances of time,
<q>Place, person and instant busines. But these having no
regard, neither of time nor place, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> busines, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
nor of any other thing but their owne will and vaine
glory; <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> pusillis in re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>a volu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>;</hi> Will
not submit to the truth even in these triviall things.</q>
   </p>
   <p>Thus this Arch-Bishop of these Dedications, so much now
contested for by his present Successo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r; Ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of what spirit,
he hath here determined to our hands, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> not recite
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>