<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the friendly Readers, and name∣ly to such as be welwillers to the Mathematiks.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101825_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00538</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10678</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101825</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the friendly Readers, and name∣ly to such as be welwillers to the Mathematiks.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Horologiographia : The art of dialling: teaching an easie and perfect way to make all kinds of dials vpon any plaine plat howsoeuer placed: vvith the drawing of the twelue signes, and houres vnequall in them all. Whereunto is annexed the making and vse of other dials and instruments, whereby the houre of the day and night is knowne. Of speciall vse and delight not onely for students of the arts mathematicall, but also for diuers artificers, architects, surueyours of buildings, free-Masons and others. By T. Fale</title>
                 <author>Fale, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 60, 16 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the friendly Readers, and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>to such as be welwillers to the</hi> Mathematiks.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Arts Mathematicall (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) in regard of their antiquitie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie may be compared with any other of the liberall Sciences whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. For <hi>Seth</hi> who liued in the first age of the world is commēded of <hi>Iosephus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. 1. c. 3.</note> and <hi>Abraham</hi> of <hi>Berosus,</hi> to haue been skilfull masters in these mysteries. And the very name importeth, that in olde time these of all other were esteemed worthie to be taught, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called for their excellencie <hi>Mathemata,</hi> that is, Sciences<note place="margin">Aul. Gell. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oct▪ Att. l. 1 Ram. Scho. Math. lib. 4.</note> meete to be learned. These be <hi>Arithmeticke, Geemetrie,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stronomie,</hi> from which this Art of Dialling taketh his beginning: a knowledge also ancient and necessarie, and therefore practised by Princes and famous men of former ages. The first Diall that histories remember is <hi>Lib. 2. cap.</hi> 20. of the <hi>Kings</hi> in the holie<note place="margin">2. King. 20. Vitruuius de Archit. lib. 9. Munst. Hor. in praef. Lib. 2. c. 76.</note> scripture, where the Lord turned the Sunne backe 10. degrees for <hi>Hezechias</hi> sake, whereby it had gone downe in the Diall of <hi>Ahaz.</hi> This <hi>Ahaz</hi> was King of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> and reigned in the 3200. yeare after the creation of the world, and in the first O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympiade of the Grecians. Afterward as <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>e</hi> writeth, <hi>Anaxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menes Milesius</hi> the scholler of <hi>Anaximander,</hi> first found out the reason and proportion of shadowes amongst the Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, and there taught the Art of Dialling, who liued 200. yeare after the raigne of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> and was a famous Philosopher in <hi>Greece</hi> before <hi>Platoes</hi> time, as <hi>Diogenes Laertius</hi> reporteth. But some affirme that it was <hi>Anaximander</hi> himselfe that found<note place="margin">Cal. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</note> out this Art, and set forth the first Mappe of the earth.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Herodotus</hi> saith, that the Grecians learned this art, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uision<note place="margin">Lib. 2.</note> of the day into twelue houres, of the Chaldeans. <hi>Diodorus</hi> writeth that one <hi>Hyperion</hi> first obserued the houres. But if we may beleeue <hi>Macrobius,</hi> it seemeth that this Science came from the Egyptians: for they called the Sunne <hi>Horus,</hi> which by his motion limitteth to each houre his appoynted time.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Vitruuius</hi> rehearseth sundrie inuentors of this Art of Dialling,<note place="margin">Lib. 9.</note> as <hi>Berosus</hi> the Chaldean, <hi>Aristarchus Samius, Eudoxus, Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius</hi> with others, who were renowmed, and liued many yeares before the birth of Christ. I need not here remember <hi>Architas Tarentinus,</hi> who by art made a Doue of wood to flie in the ayre: neither <hi>Archimedes,</hi> who defended <hi>Syracusa</hi> against <hi>Marcellus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plutar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. in Marcel.</note> and affirmed that if he had a place to stand on, he would moue the earth with his engins: both of them no doubt skilfull in this Science.</p>
   <p>It was long after the inuention that this Art was knowne in <hi>Rome:</hi> for in the twelue tables was onely mentioned the rising and setting of the Sunne, and after certaine yeares the midday was added. Then in the first <hi>Punike warre</hi> the Romanes obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning victorie, there was a Diall brought amongst other spoyles out of <hi>Sicilie.</hi> But in processe of time they began to bee more common in <hi>Rome:</hi> for 100. yeares before <hi>Cicero</hi> his time, the parasite in a Comedie, being hungrie, spake against the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Clockes and Dials which were then in the citie, <hi>Optans vt suus cuique venter sit horologium.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plinie</hi> also telleth of a Diall placed in the field of <hi>Flora</hi> at<note place="margin">Lib. 36. c. 10</note>
      <hi>Rome,</hi> which by the space of thirtie yeares had not agreed with the Sunne: and the reason was as he thought, because that either the Sunne had taken a new course, or els the earth was slipped from his Centre, wherein at the first it stood: or the stile was put awry by the shaking of the citie. Since which times learning spreading it selfe into diuers parts of the world, this Art hath been amongst the rest in great account.</p>
   <p>Concerning the profite of this Art, daily experience teacheth how needful it is in a well ordered Common-wealth, seeing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be done in due and conuenient season, where this
<pb facs="3"/>
Science is neglected: for the diuision of the day into certaine parts or houres, (which this Art teacheth) doth limit and allot to each action his due time. This Art being then so ancient, and the vse so necessarie, I trust none will thinke this labour super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, vnlesse they be rude without ciuilitie, or such as haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies at hand a Diall of natures framing, of whom this verse see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be made:</p>
   <q>*Si tuus ad solem statuatur nasus, hianti<note place="margin">Morus.</note> Ore, bene ostendas dentibus hora quota est.</q>
   <p>Many haue promised (but none as yet performed) to write of this Science in our English tongue, which hath bin published in other languages, as <hi>D. Recorde</hi> long since, <hi>M. Digges, M. Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue</hi> with other, who if they would take the paines, I knowe could doe it with great commendation.</p>
   <p>Diuers haue written hereof in the Latin tongue, as <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, Schonerus, Orontius, Witekindus, Clauius</hi> and others: yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one differing from other in precept. Some teach the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Dials by the helpe of the Globe, as <hi>Gemma Frisius:</hi> some by the Astrolabe, as the same <hi>Gemma Frisius</hi> and <hi>M. Blagr.</hi> which Instruments euery man haue not. Some vse the table of <hi>Sines</hi> and <hi>Arithmetike,</hi> as <hi>Witekindus,</hi> which way as most plaine and easie, is obserued in this booke; though in some kinds for want of triall <hi>Witekindus</hi> deceiued himselfe. <hi>Munster</hi> vseth a <hi>Rectificatorie</hi> with a circle, which is vnfit for small plats, and fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in greater, without great heed. <hi>Schoner</hi> wandreth in a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes of lines, that a man know not where to begin, or when to end. <hi>Vlmer</hi> hath not the Delineation of all kinds.</p>
   <p>Othersome obserue the rules of Geometricall proportion: which order also we thought to haue obserued in all kinds, as we haue done in the South and North erect declining: but that sundrie precepts of the same thing would haue bred tedious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and trouble to the learner, and the cutting of the Figures would haue been very chargeable. By meanes whereof we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented our selues with this one way here set downe, not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but that euery one with small paines may attaine to the making of all kinds of Dials in this booke expressed. As for a great part of them, euery Artificer may easily vnderstand.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Onely thus much I aduertise the vnlearned, that they must acquaint themselues with some fewe Mathematicall principles, as to knowe what the Eleuation of the Pole meaneth, how a squire line is to be drawne, and such like, which (if they want a teacher) they may sufficiently learne by themselues out of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords Castle,</hi> his pathway and ground of Arts, published in the English tongue: for these tearmes could not be auoyded, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plainly described without much tediousnes.</p>
   <p>We haue here added also examples and figures to euery kind, that so the precepts might appeare more plaine and easie: so that there is no plaine plat or wall howsoeuer it standeth, or be placed either Declining, Reclining, or Inclining, but by the helpe of this booke you may drawe a Diall vpon it.</p>
   <p>If any man complaine of obscuritie, he must knowe, that <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficilia quae pulchra,</hi> and yet small paines ouercommeth all.</p>
   <p>The making of the Horologicall Cylindre, and the Ring, with some other Instruments, we haue presently omitted, partly for their curiositie in cutting and delineation, and partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause (if occasion serue) we will entreate of these kindes of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rologicall Instruments by themselues, together with the making of all kindes of plaine Dials in this booke, prescribed by the way of Geometricall proportion. In the meane while (gentle Reader) committing this booke to thy fauourable acceptation, and thy selfe to the protection of the Almightie, I end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Tho. Fale.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>