<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all grave and modest Matrons, especially to such as have to doe with women in that great danger of childe-birth, as also, to all young practitioners in Physick and Chirurgery, whom these matters may concerne, Grace, Peace, and good successe, in their underta∣kings, heartily wished.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101598_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11176</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21442</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101598</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all grave and modest Matrons, especially to such as have to doe with women in that great danger of childe-birth, as also, to all young practitioners in Physick and Chirurgery, whom these matters may concerne, Grace, Peace, and good successe, in their underta∣kings, heartily wished.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The expert midvvife, or An excellent and most necessary treatise of the generation and birth of man : Wherein is contained many very notable and necessary particulars requisite to be knovvne and practised: with diuers apt and usefull figures appropriated to this worke. Als the causes, signes, and various cures, of the most principall maladies and infirmities incident to women. Six bookes compiled in Latine by the industry of Iames Rueff, a learned and expert chirurgion: and now translated into English for the generall good and benefit of this nation</title>
                 <author>Rüff, Jakob</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Alchorn, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Burton, Simon.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 192, 120 pages, illustrations (woodcuts), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all grave and modest Matrons, especially to such as have to doe with women in that great danger of childe-birth, as also, to all young practitioners in Physick and Chirurgery, whom these matters may concerne, Grace, Peace, and good successe, in their underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, heartily wished.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit the sundry presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of bookes in this kinde, formerly publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, might free me from Apologizing for myselfe for this worke, yet will I adde to what others have said one reason of maine consequence, not observed by any that I have read, which will much strengthen these my endeavours. It is observeable that in all ages of the
<pb facs="3"/>
world and throughout all countries in the world, that the helpe of grave and modest women (with us termed Midwives) hath ever been useful for releife &amp; succour of all the daughters of Evah, whom God hath appointed to beare children into this world, which things so being, and women with all being Vniversally as all men know (for the most part) unlearned, any further then to understand their owne native language, as a french wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to understand french, a dutch wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man dutch, or an english woman en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish. And the businesse whereunto God hath ordayned them of so great and dangerous consequence as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the very lives of all such as come into the world, and withall for preventing of great danger and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold hazards, both unto the mother
<pb facs="3"/>
and unto the infant it being necessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required that the parties imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereabout, should understand the businesse which they take in hand, which cannot be without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of many particulars concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning both the mother and the Infant, which they can never attaine unto, but either by the use of bookes pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by skilful Physitians &amp; Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, or by conference with the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and skilfull (which can hardly, or not at all, in most places be had, or else by practicall &amp; long experience, which though it bee the surest mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse, yet is it the dearest, and hath cost the lives of many, both in this kinde and otherwise, before know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge could be therby obtained; these things so being, what reason hath any to seeke or debarre grave and modest
<pb facs="4"/>
women, such as God hath called to that function (or other grave and modest matrons; such as though not so precisely thereunto called, yet may bee assistant and helpefull unto the midwife in so great dangers, and whose paines &amp; labours also are of an absolute necessity, in the mid-wives absence) of the use of such meanes as may inable them to the undertaking of matters so dangerous, and so full of perill, with much lesse hazard to the patients, and paines and turmoylings to themselves; for the unskilfulnesse and want of knowledge in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife in matters both concerning the mother and the infant, doth question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse oftentimes indanger the lives, both of the one and the other, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure much unnecessary trouble to themselves, whenas, perhaps, had a
<pb facs="4"/>
skilfull midwife the matter in hand, there would be neither perill to the one, nor paine to the other: but will some (nicely precise) perhaps say, <hi>It is unfit that such matters as these should bee pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished in a vulgar tongue, for young heads to prie into.</hi> True, if by other meanes it might be effected: but the danger be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great and manifold, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned for their sex for the most part (further then their owne tongue) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all ages and in all places, (as I have said) thereunto assigned; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it better that millions should perish for want of helpe and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or that such meanes which though lawfull in themselves, yet may by some be abused, should be had and used? doe we not see in many ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, that those things which otherwise were monstrous, are yet by necessity
<pb facs="5"/>
made tollerable? Or shall we because some good things are by evill men and evill mindes abused, therefore deprive the good, of the use of good things? If such slender reasons as these might prevaile, then might there per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a great number perish, before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they saw the light, who otherwise might live and increase the number of Gods church by their off-springs, and perhaps also a great deale more worke might be made for men-mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives, then yet is, although there bee too too much already, and some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps for private profit have too farre already incroached upon womens weakenesses and want of knowledge in these their peculiar businesses. To conclude, I say onely this, my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions herein are honest and iust, and my labours I bequeath to all grave,
<pb facs="5"/>
modest and discreet women, as also to such as by profession, practise either Physicke or Chirurgery. And whose helpe upon occasion of extreame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity may be usefull and good, both for mother, child, and mid-wife. But young and raw heads, Idle serving-men, prophane fidlers, scoffers, je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, rogues; avant, pack hence; I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meant it to you, neither is it fit for you. Thus craving the favourable construction of the grave and honest, but not respecting the rash censures of the peevish. I rest at your devotion unto whom in the beginning I have inscribed these my labours, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular contents whereof, follow in the next leafe.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Fare you well.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>