<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right Reuerende father in Christe, and honorable Prince, Lorde Iohn Gebhard, of the Earles of Mansfelt. &amp;c. Archbishop of Colen, Prince elector, duke of Angaria and VVestphalia, hygh Chaunceler of the Romayne Empire. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Hannonius, Iohn Taisnier</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101247_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13348</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23659</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101247</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right Reuerende father in Christe, and honorable Prince, Lorde Iohn Gebhard, of the Earles of Mansfelt. &amp;c. Archbishop of Colen, Prince elector, duke of Angaria and VVestphalia, hygh Chaunceler of the Romayne Empire. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Hannonius, Iohn Taisnier</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A very necessarie and profitable booke concerning nauigation, compiled in Latin by Ioannes Taisnierus, a publike professor in Rome, Ferraria, &amp; other uniuersities in Italie of the mathematicalles, named a treatise of continuall motions. Translated into Englishe, by Richarde Eden. The contentes of this booke you shall finde on the next page folowyng</title>
                 <author>Taisnier, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jugge, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>84 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶ To the right Reuerende father in <hi>Christe, and honorable Prince, Lorde</hi> Iohn Gebhard, of the Earles of Mansfelt. &amp;c. Archbishop of Colen, Prince elector, duke of Angaria and VVestphalia, hygh Chaunceler of the Romayne Empire. &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE thing which to this day in maner from the beginning of the world, great Philosophers with perpetual studie and great labour, haue endeuoured to bring to effect, and desired ende (most gratious Prince) hath neuerthelesse hitherto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned eyther vnknowen, or hydde, not without great damage and hynderance of moste expert Mathematicians and Architecteurs, and al other men of lyke practicall faculties: And yf any there haue been whiche haue attayned to the experience of this continuall motion, I suppose the same to haue been vexed and noted,<note place="margin">A perpetual or continuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> with the va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne glorye of the incomparable paynter and grauer, <hi>Michael Angelo,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Michael Angelo.</note> who euen at the extreme rendryng of the spirit of lyfe, dyd not vouchsafe to disclose vnto his owne sonne the secrets of his arte, esteeming it greatly to the reputation of his fame and glory, by this ingrate hydyng of his science, falsely to obteyne a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual memorie with suche as shoulde succeede hym: Or els truely he doubted (as is commonly seene in all maner of doctrine and science) that there shoulde still ryse vp certayne malitious and enuious quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relers, and troublous wits, instigate by an euyl spirite, to deface and suppresse trueth with slaunderous tongues, especially agaynst artes Mathematikes (of whiche kinde, are Grauyng, Payntyng, and suche lyke) whiche in al ages haue euer been subiect to this inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of ignorant detractours, except they be defended by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and title of fauourable princes. And whereas suche sciences
<pb facs="6"/> vnto the ignorant seeme ridiculus and suspicious, neuerthelesse in the frame and experience of this continuall motion, ought no suspicion to be bad. And forasmuche as the same is very necessarie and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the common wealth, I was the bolder through confidence in your hyghnes clemencie vnder the grace and title of the same, to put foorth this litle booke of continuall motion. The whiche howe great profite and exercise it may bryng to excellent men of what so euer facultie, experience it selfe shal easily declare. Most humbly desiring your highnesse, gratiously to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this ray trauaile with such as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrate to the Muses, and employ theyr labours to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of mankinde.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your hyghnesse moste humble seruant and Oratour,</hi> Iohn Tais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier Hannonius▪</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>