<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101269_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13574</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23866</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101269</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A continuation of the lamentable and admirable adventures of Dom Sebastian king of Portugale : With a declaration of all his time employed since the battell in Africke against the infidels 1578. vntill this present yeare 1603</title>
                 <author>Teixeira, José</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Shaw, James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>68 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, in the entrance of this Discourse which followes, you shall find three letters written by an auncient man called Doctor <hi>Texere</hi> a Portugal, directed to a Bishop this fathers verie friend, which I haue here compiled and expressed among other proofes to veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the infortunate accidents this disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterous King hath sustained, since he was taken prisoner by the great Duke of Tuscane, vntill the last day of the yeare past <hi>1601.</hi> You may also find within this Pamphlet two Letters translated: one written by <hi>D. Raimond Marqueti,</hi> a Knight of the order of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> borne in Messina in Sicile to <hi>Dom Sebastian;</hi> the other sent from the said King to <hi>D. Prospero Baracco,</hi> dwelling in Padua. By the two last letters it will euidently appeare vnto you, that the prisoner detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned now in Naples, is not that <hi>Marco Tullio Catizone,</hi> whom the Spaniards in their libels haue so falsly proclaimed; but the very true King of Portugale <hi>Dom Sebastian.</hi> Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly after these letters followeth a discourse, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whereof there is a Preface written by father <hi>Texere,</hi> manifesting the naturall disposition of Portugals, and witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing how constantly they addresse themselues in loyaltie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Gouernours that raigne ouer them, according to the sincere word of God, and the vnfallible rules of honour.</p>
   <p>You may also behold a most ample declaration, about the
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>end of this discourse, ministring foure seuerall points, worthie the reading and obseruing; to proue vnto you assuredly, that the prisoner for whom we trauell so industriously with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuerance, is the true and lawfull King of Portugale <hi>Dom Sebastian,</hi> whom God of his diuine mercie will (I trust) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store to his former Crowne and dignitie, for the good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the peace and welfare of all Christendome: which the eternall God effect, if it be his blessed will. Amen. The <hi>26.</hi> of Feb. An. <hi>1602.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>