<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>R., M.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101594_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10774</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21045</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101594</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>R., M.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short treatise of magneticall bodies and motions. By Marke Ridley Dr in phisicke and philosophie latly physition to the Emperour of Russia, and one of ye eight principals of elects of the Colledge of Physitions in London</title>
                 <author>Ridley, Mark</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 157, 1 page, illustrations (woodcuts), tables, diagrams, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, I haue written thee a small Discourse as concerning <hi>Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Bodies and Motions,</hi> the which I hope will not be obscure vnto thee through his breuitie, because of his plaine method, and easie demonstrations, which with their pleasantnesse will proue very ready and apparant vnto thee, especially being animated from the <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> stone it selfe, as from a most liuely and perfect tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: Therefore I would aduise thee, that when thou readest this booke, that thou wouldest prouide thy selfe of such like formes of <hi>Magnets</hi> as I haue descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the first Table and figures of the second chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as also of needles, wiers, and waights of iron and steele, set forth in the second Table of the third chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this booke, which thou mayest haue made and prouided for thee by the helpe of some skilfull worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: when thou shalt be furnished with these kinds of prouisions, then thou mayest reade and practise the operations and demonstrations of this booke, which will be both easie and very pleasant vnto thee; and though that there be many precepts and practises in this Booke, which be not for example sake set downe in tables and figures vnto thy sight, because I desired
<pb facs="7"/>
to be very briefe, yet if thou shalt not be altogether vnskilfull in these demonstrations that be delineated in the Tables of this booke and their often practise, thou wilt be able inough to vnderstand and put them in vre, with these forenamed prouisions. But if thou shalt desire, besides thy instruction in this kind of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, to put in vse and make benefit of these matters <hi>Magneticall,</hi> either in trauelling or sailing vpon the <hi>Magneticall</hi> globe of the earth, then it will be very necessary for thee to be stored with the Marriners Compasse for the sea, perfectly drawne and framed, to know the way, and of what hand and point to saile and trauell, and also to haue the <hi>Inclinatory-needle</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly placed in his ring, and a <hi>Directory-needle,</hi> or a little flie <hi>Magneticall</hi> in the boxe, fastened at the bottome in his conuenient distance, for to know vnder what latitude thou art euery day of thy voyage: Likewise if I should declare vnto thee how beneficiall the <hi>Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-Magneticall-needle</hi> is for the description of Ports, Hauens, Forlands, Capes, Bayes and Riuers, for the more perfect making of Sea-cards, how necessary for the positure of buildings, directing of dials, and all Mathematicall instruments for measuring and suruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for pioners and vnderminers of forts, for sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of minerals, mettals, sea-coles, and other subte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restriall bodies, I should be too tedious vnto thee, and will rather referre thee for these matters to that which is set downe by others, because I meddle here in this booke onely with those things that be <hi>Magneticall.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In this place I thinke good to aduertise thee as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the magnitude of the seuen Planets, with their respect vnto the earth, out of <hi>Ticho Brabe,</hi> described in the top of the Title Page; that whereas their propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="7"/>
cannot be set forth truly in any types, being at too great oddes: therefore I haue deciphered that in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures; as let the <hi>Earth</hi> ♁ be but one part, the <hi>Sunnes</hi> ☉ greatnesse will be 140 times so much; <hi>Saturnes</hi> ♄ 22, <hi>Iupiters</hi> ♃ 14. And if that <hi>Venus</hi> ♀ haue 6 parts, the <hi>Earth</hi> will haue 37 parts, if <hi>Mars ♂</hi> be one part, the <hi>Earth</hi> is 13, if <hi>Mercury</hi> ☿ be one part, the <hi>Earth</hi> is 18, if the <hi>Moone</hi> ☽ be one part, the <hi>Earth</hi> will continue her 42 times. Besides, I haue drawne the <hi>Axis</hi> in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Planets, as being bodies <hi>Magneticall:</hi> for I trust that these following times will discouer whether they be paralell one to the other, or no, as also what naturall motions else they haue, because that <hi>Astra natant, auis instar in aëre, aut piscis in vnda,</hi> and here it might be sayd that we hope that many new points in Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy and Astronomy will blossome and spring out of this kind of learning hereafter,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in all affection, M. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>