<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101618_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08964</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1925</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101618</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The tranquillitie of the minde : A verye excellent and most comfortable oration, plainely directing euerye man, &amp; woman, to the true tranquillitie and quyetnesse of their minde. Compyled in Latine by Iohn Barnarde, student in the Vniuersity of Cambridge, now lately translated into Englishe by Anthony Marten</title>
                 <author>Bernard, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Norton, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 108 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O BE IT (GOOD Christian Reader) that thou hauing prouided for thy selfe, aboundaunce of wealth in this worlde, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite substaunce, plentifull commodities, with hope to augment and increase the same by large and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple gaynes: and hast setled thy heart, to builde thee a sumptuous, strong, and beautifull house; as well for the bestowing and ordering of these thy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ryches, as for the sure and safe custodie of them, saying with thy selfe: this yeare I will be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in searching out of Timber, Stone, Bricke, Lyme, Labourers and excellent workemen, for the better accomplishing of this my deuice. The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde yeare I will be furnished of all these thinges, and prepare them readie for the worke: and the thirde yeare I minde to builde and erect my house. Will not thy heart burne within thee, while the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation hereof is thus fixed within thy breast? wilt thou not imagine, that while all these thinges are in performing according to thy desire, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie day will be a yeare, and euery yeare a number? Wouldest thou not with an earnest desire seeke to bee released of this hope ioyned with feare, planted within thy breast, and with all the trauell of thy bodie, labour to see the ende of this thy deuice and
<pb facs="6"/>purpose, and that with all expedition? Whilest thou art yet casting and pondering of all these matters in thy minde, howe to bring them to good effect: If two of thy deerest friendes, who haue a speciall regarde to thy bodie least it should perish with tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and care, doe presently come vnto thee: The one of them saying: Beholde, the Timber, Bricke, Stone, Lyme, and all other necessarie thinges, for buylding, which I layde vp in store for mine owne selfe, my wife, and my children, to buylde vs an house withall, I haue ment towardes thee. And that other friend also, the sooner to deliuer thee frō thy troublesome imaginations, say vnto thee: Loe, all these things meete for buylding, I haue brought to the place where thou hast determined to lay thy foundation. The plat forme is drawne: the stuffe is excellent, and well wrought: the worke is fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and readie to be erected: and the season of the yeare verie well serueth. Therefore ease thy minde, vnburthen thy conscience, set thy heart at libertie: Now there remayneth no trauell for thee, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, that thou throughlye ouersee and suruay the whole gift, which we haue bestowed vpon thee. That is to saye: beginning with the first stone of the foundation, vewing and beholding euery thing by percell meale, till thou come to the principall Piller in the middest, vpon which, the whole work is appoynted to depende: And so continuing thy vewe and suruay, till thou come to the last part, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the roofe of the same house, there to beholde
<pb facs="6"/>the force and strength therof, for resisting the stor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie tempestes of raging Winter. When thou hast thus done, beginne thy house, and finishe the same in fewe dayes, to thy contentation, which before thou diddest feare, in many yeares coulde scarcely haue beene perfourmed. Wilt thou nowe thou worldly mynded man, bee vngratefull for this so high an earthly benifite receyued? Or wilt thou not consent, to this so reasonable and friendly a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, of such thy deare friendes? Nay, (I am sure) thou wilt not onely bee thankefull, but also wilt runne with all diligence, with great admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with louing countenaunce, and with all feast and melodie, to imbrace them, who haue deliuered thy bodie from trauell and watching, and dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thy minde from the thing whereof it stoode in feare. Yea, and I doubt not, but thou wilt with a glad and willing mynde, accomplishe and fulfill this their gentle and easie request made vnto thee. If now, thou haue thus taken carke and care, about the buylding of an earthly mancion, to repose and lay vp thy temporall treasure, to place and solace thy carrian Carkasse.: If thou haue thus taken thought for the bodie, so corruptible a thing, so loose of life, so short of lyfe, so vncertaine of lyfe, and of it selfe alone no life, which so many yeares is a growing, and so fewe houres a fading: if thou be thus discharged of thy bodily trauell, and of the feare of trauell, by these thy two speciall friendes: Howe much more circumspection, and
<pb facs="7"/>stedfast care and diligence, oughtest thou to haue ouer thy soule, so incorruptible a thing, so eternall, so heauenly, and vnspeakeable a gift, in so short a minute chaunged, from sinne to blesse, from man to an Aungell, from earth to Paradice, from mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentanie lyfe, to vnspeakable thousandes of ages, from warre to rewarde, from tryall of fayth, to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph for victorie, from continuall vexation, strife and vnquietnesse, to perpetuall consolation, securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and quietnesse: Howe much more prouident (especiallye in this wonderfull age wherein thy mynde is so mooued and tossed to and fro, to see the worlde wonder, and the Deuill rage, that Christ his true Religion is raysed vppe and published) oughtest thou to bee in puruaying for the assured knowledge of the true Tranquillitie, stay, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of thy minde: a matter sufficient and able to buylde thee a celestiall habitation, wherein thou mayest lay vp thy heauenly treasure: wherein thou shalt inioy the parpetuall fellowship of Aungelles, the continuall contemplation of Gods deuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, the fruition of euerlasting ioy and felicitie, and the liuely fountaine of eternall lyfe. If thou with this lightnesse of hearte, with this zeale of minde, and with these tokens of gladnesse, wilt accept and imbrace thy friends, which haue shewed thee of so earthly a commoditie, of so fraile a thing, and (as I maye terme it) of such a masse of Morter: With how much more feruent zeale, pure loue, and beneuolent minde, (beloued) art thou to accept the
<pb facs="7"/>Author hereof, and Translator of the same, who haue presented so singuler a benifite vnto thee as is this booke, which may so much further and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite thee for the safetie of thy soule. The one of these thy friendes, nurst and educated, in the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull lappe of liberall science: the other led (till he had seene this booke) with delightes, and trayned (from youth) to the intisementes of Courtly vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The one, alwayes fedde, with deuine foode of Euangelicall Doctrine: the other taught (till ere-whilste) with prophane knowledge of obscure darkenesse. The one practising as well by his life, as by his penne, to compile and gather togither, the deepe and secret wisedome of Tranquillitie of the minde: the other (beeing scoller to this booke, and hauing put in proufe, the Lessons therein learned) remayneth as a witnesse to the worlde, of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde consolation and commoditie reaped by the same. The one hauing layde vp in store, this mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous stuffe of building, for the edifying of hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and of all those in the vniuersall worlde which vnderstand the Latine tongue: the other for the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie he oweth to hys Countrie, hath brought foorth the same, and layde it readie before the eyes of all oure Englishe Nation and Countrie. All the thanks and recompence, which he hopeth to reape of thee, is that thou (and that for thine owne sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler pleasure, comfort, and commoditie) wylt wholye reade ouer the same, especially bycause it is one whole continued stile and Oration, depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="8"/>consequently, (yet playnly, easily, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festlye) one poynt vpon an other: And therefore, thou must of necessitie so doe, if thou wilt learne how to obtaine the true quietnesse of thy mynde. This I will assure thee (gentle Reader,) that if thou wylt, with attentiue eares pervse this booke, in such sort, as I haue declared vnto thee: of what state, condicion, or degree so euer thou bee, or howe so euer thy bodie bee inclined, or thy mynde affected, thou shalt reape inestimable and heauenly profite thereby. In such sort as if thou be high of dignitie: thou wilt not become disdainefull: If thou bee base of state: ambicious. Or if thou bee meane of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: mutable and inconstant. Neyther in prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, thou wilt shewe thy selfe vngratefull, but thankefull: not prowde, but lowly of spirite. In sodaine sadnesse: thou wilt lay holde vpon speedie merynesse. In vnreasonable merinesse: vpon dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete temperaunce. In the leaden lethargie and disease of sinne: vpon the quicke remembraunce of mercie by Christ. In aduersitie, thou wilt not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come impacient, nor pensiue: but quiet and ioyfull. In sicknesse, not murmuraunt and waywarde: but pacient and content with Gods visitation. Yea, such fruite mayst thou finde, by some small paynes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed herein, as I dare speake it, thou shalt confesse thy selfe, to stand a thousand tymes more afeard of thy three most spitefull aduersaries (I meane the worlde the fleshe and the deuill) when the worlde most flattreth thee, with the glorious and glittering
<pb facs="8"/>shew of hir vaine giftes, bestowed vpon thee, and in thy chiefest securitie of welth and happy dayes, than in the most troublesome tempestes of trying thy fayth, by affliction of the worlde, by prouocation of the flesh, or by Sathans instigation of thy minde: ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther else in the time, when God by his owne handes doth lay his gentle correction of sicknesse vpō thee. Afeard (I say) in such safe prosperitie, least God make small account of thee: glad and ioyfull in pinching aduersity, bicause he acknowledgeth thee for his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall child, and not reiecteth thee as a reprobate ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stard. That thou being thus mortified to the world, and renued by Christ, to the life to come, mayest (so long as the blessed will of God is, that thy wretched carkasse shal yet remaine vpon the face of the earth) be so light and glad of heart, so firme, calme, &amp; quiet of minde, in the true faith of Iesus Christ, and so ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uished with angelicall, and spiritual cogitation vpon deuine and heauenly treasures: as thy verie self, may be alredy seperated from thy selfe, and thy body no longer seme to beare, rule, suppresse, and Prison the spirit (as in euery carnall minded man it doth.) But the spirite altogither to direct, sanctifie, subdue and gouerne the bodie, and the same to beare, leade, and carie about with it, no lesse, than if it were alreadie chaunged, and lifted vp to the euerlasting felicitie of Gods eternall kingdome, purchased for vs by hys sonne Iesus, who with the father &amp; the holy ghost, one eternall God be blessed, praysed, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, nowe and in the worlde to come. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>