<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1564</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101757_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09907</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2017</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101757</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse wrytten by M. Theodore de Beza, conteyning in briefe the historie of the life and death of Maister Iohn Caluin : with the testament and laste will of the saide Caluin, and the catalogue of his bookes that he hath made. Turned out of Frenche into Englishe, by I.S. In the yeare of our Lorde. M.D.LXIIII. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed in the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Bèze, Théodore de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Harrison, Luke (Lucas)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1564</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>RIEND READER I offer vnto thee this present gathering or summe, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Lyfe and Death of the Faithfull seruant of God, Maister Iohn Caluin: by the which thou shalt see maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous examples of the assaultes, that he hath endured for the Doctrine of the Sonne of God, and also what assistance God doth giue to his, when his honor and glorye commeth in question. In the meane time thinke it not straunge that this discourse doth not agree with the accustomed forme of Hystorians, for the purpose of the Auctor who is Master Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore de Beza, a good seruant of God also, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of Maister Iohn Caluin in the worke of the Lorde, was not to publishe it as an Hystorie, but onely for a Preface to the Commentaries of the saide Caluin vppon the Booke of Iosue, come to light sith his death. I haue thought good to aduertise thee hereof, to the ende that thou shouldest not thinke, that the memorie of so great and worthie a perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage myght be satisfied with so smalle a discourse,
<pb facs="3"/> (albeit that it is diligently and truely set forth) the which shall serue thee onely to this purpose to make thee to hope and looke for an ample and goodly Hystorie of his actes and doings, which shall greatly profite to the aduancement of the Church of God: to whom be glory and honor for euer and euer. Sobeit.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>