<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVELBELOVED ENGLISH READER GRACE AND GLORIE IN IESVS CHRIST EVERLASTING.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101944_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11777</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2207</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101944</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVELBELOVED ENGLISH READER GRACE AND GLORIE IN IESVS CHRIST EVERLASTING.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The holie Bible faithfully translated into English, out of the authentical Latin. Diligently conferred with the Hebrew, Greeke, and other editions in diuers languages. With arguments of the bookes, and chapters: annotations. tables: and other helpes ... By the English College of Doway</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2 volumes (20, 1115, 1, 1004, 1, 1002-1124, 4 pages), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVELBELOVED ENGLISH READER GRACE AND GLORIE IN IESVS CHRIST EVERLASTING.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T LAST through Gods goodnes (most dearly beloued) we send you here the greater part of the Old Testament: as long since you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the New; faithfully translated into English. The residue is in hād to be finished: and your desire therof shal not now (God prospering our<note place="margin">The cause of delay in set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth this English Bible.</note> intention) be long frustrate. As for the impediments, which hitherto haue hindered this vvorke, they al proceded (as manie do know) of one general cause, our poore estate in banishment. VVherin expecting better meanes, greatter difficulties rather ensued. Neuertheles you wil hereby the more perceiue our feruent good wil, euer to serue you, in that we haue brought forth this Tome, in these hardest times, of aboue fourtie yeares, since this College was most happely begune. VVherfore we nothing doubt, but you<note place="margin">Anno. 1568.</note> our dearest, for whom we haue dedicated our liues, wil both pardon the long delay, which we could not wel pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, and accept now this fruict of our laboures, with like good affection, as we acknowlege them due, and offer the same vnto you.</p>
   <p>If anie demand, why it is now allowed to haue the holie<note place="margin">VVhy &amp; how it is allowed to haue holie Scriptures in vulgar ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues.</note> Scriptures in vulgar tongues, which generally is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but in the three sacred only: for further declaration of this, &amp; other like pointes we remite you to the Preface, before the New Testament. Only here, as by an Epitome,
<pb facs="3"/>
we shal repete the summe of al, that is there more largely discussed. To this first question therfore we answer, that both iust reason, &amp; highest authoritie of the Church, iudge it not absolutly necessarie, nor alwayes conuenient, that<note place="margin">Scriptures being hard are not to be read of al.</note> holie Scriptures should be in vulgar tongues. For being as they are, hard to be vnderstood, euen by the lerned, reason doth dictate to reasonable men, that they were not written, nor ordayned to be read indifferently of al men. Experiēce also teacheth, that through ignorance, ioyned often with<note place="margin">Manie take harme by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding holi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Scriptures.</note> pride and presumption, manie reading Scriptures haue erred grosly, by misunderstanding Gods word. VVhich though it be most pure in it self, <hi>yet the sense being adulterated</hi>
      <note place="margin">lib. de Prescrip.</note>
      <hi>is as perilous</hi> (saith Tertullian) <hi>as the stile corrupted.</hi> S. Ambrose obserueth: that <hi>vvhere the text is true, the Arrians interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
      <note place="margin">lib. 2, ad Gratian. c. 1. Tract. 18 in Ioan.</note>
      <hi>hath errors.</hi> S. Augustin also teacheth, that <hi>here sies and peruerse doctrines entangling soules, and throvving them dovvne headlong into the depth, do not othervvise spring vp, but vvhen good (or true) Scriptures are not vvel (and truly) vnderstood, and vvhen that vvhich in them is not vvel vnderstood, is also rashly &amp; boldly auouched.</hi> For the same cause, S. Ierom vtterly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowed,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Epist.</hi> 103. c. 6.</note> that al sortes of men &amp; wemen, old &amp; yong, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed to read: &amp; talke of the Scriptures: wheras <hi>no articene, no tradsman dare presume to teach anie facultie, vvhich he hath not first lerned.</hi> Seing therfore that dangers, &amp; hurtes happen in manie, the careful chief Pastores in Gods Church, haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies<note place="margin">Reading. of Scriptures moderated.</note> moderated the reading of holie Scriptures, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to persons, times, and other circumstances; prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting some, and permitting some, to haue and read them, in their mother tongue. So S. Crysostom trāslated the Psalmes &amp; some other partes of holie Scriptures for the Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,<note place="margin">Scriptures translated into diuers ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues.</note> when he was there in banishment. The Slauonians<note place="margin">Bibl. Sanct. lib. 4.</note> and Gothes say they haue the Bible in their languages. It was translated into Italian by an Archbyshop of Genua. Into French in the time of king Charles the fift: especially because the waldensian heretikes had corruptly translated
<pb facs="3"/>
it, to maintaine their errors. VVe had some partes in English<note place="margin">Lib. 1. Hist. c. 47 Linvvod lib. 1.</note> translated by Venerable Bede: as Malmesburie witnesseth. And Thomas Arundel Archbishop of Canturburie in a Councel holden at Oxford, straictly ordayned, that no he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical translation set forth by wicliffe, and his complices, nor anie other vulgar Edition should be suffered, til it were approued by the Ordinarie of the Diocese: alleaging S. le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roms iudgement of the difficultie &amp; danger in translating holie Scriptures out of one tongue into an other. And therfore it must nedes be much more dangerous, when ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people read also corrupted translations. Now since Luther, and his folowers haue pretended, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique<note place="margin">A calumnious suggestion of Lutheranes.</note> Romane faith and doctrine, should be contrarie to Gods written word, &amp; that the Scriptures were not suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in vulgar languages, lest the people should see the truth, &amp; vvithal these new maisters corruptly turning the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures into diuers tongues, as might best serue their owne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions: against this false suggestion, and practise, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Pastores haue, for one especial remedie, set forth true and sincere Translations in most languages of the Latin Church. But so, that people must read them with licence of their spiritual superior, as in former times they were in like sort limited. Such also of the Laitie, yea &amp; of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner lerned Clergie, as were permitted to read holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, did not presume to interprete hard places, nor high Mysteries, much lesse to dispute and contend, but leauing the discussion therof to the more lerned, searched rather,<note place="margin">VVhat part of Scriptures be most conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar readers.</note> and noted the godlie and imitable examples of good life, and so lerned more humilitie, obedience, hatred of sinne, feare of God, zele of Religion, and other vertues. And thus holie Scriptures may be rightly vsed in anie tongue, <hi>to teach, to argue, to correct, to instruct in iustice, that the man of</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Tim 3.</note>
      <hi>God may be perfect, and</hi> (as S. Paul addeth) <hi>instructed to euerie good vvorke,</hi> when men laboure rather to be <hi>doers of Gods</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ac. 1.</note> wil &amp; <hi>vvord, then readers</hi> or <hi>hearers only, deceiuing themselues.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>But here an other question may be proposed: VVhy we<note place="margin">VVhy we tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>slate the old Latin text.</note> translate the Latin text, rather then the Hebrew, or Greke, which Protestantes preferre, as the fountaine tongues, wherin holie Scriptures were first written? To this we answer, that if in dede those first pure Editions were now<note place="margin">More pure then the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew or Greke now extant.</note> extant, or if such as be extant, were more pure then the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, we would also preferre such fountaines before the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, in whatsoeuer they should be found to disagree. But the ancient best lerned Fathers, &amp; Doctors of the Church,<note place="margin">Tertulliā li. 5. cont Marcion S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brose. li. 3 deSpirit. San. c. 11 S. Ieron: li. 1. con. Iouiniā.</note> do much complaine, and testifie to vs, that both the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew and Greke Editions are fouly corrupted by Iewes, and Heretikes, since the Latin was truly translated out of them, whiles they were more pure. And that the same La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin hath bene farre better conserued from corruptions. So that the old Vulgate Latin Edition hath bene preferred, and vsed for most authentical aboue a thousand and three hundered yeares. For by this verie terme S. Ierom calleth that Version <hi>the vulgate or common,</hi> which he conferred with<note place="margin">in 49. Isaiae.</note> the Hebrew of the old Testament, and with the Greke of the New; which he also purged from faultes committed by writers, rather amending then translating it. Though in<note place="margin">li. 20. c. 24 mora. Epist. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat. ad Leandr. li. 2. Doct Christ. c. 14. lib. 6. Etymol. c. 5. &amp; li. 1 de Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin offic. c. 12.</note> regard of this amending, S. Gregorie calleth it <hi>the nevv ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siō of S. Ierom:</hi> who neuertheles in an other place calleth the self same, <hi>the old Latin Edition,</hi> iudging it most worthy to be folowed. S. Augustin calleth it the <hi>Italian.</hi> S. Isidorus wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth<note place="margin">Receiued by al Churches.</note> that <hi>S. Ierom; version</hi> was receiued and <hi>approued by al Christian Churches.</hi> Sophronius also a most lerned man,<note place="margin">Turned into Greke.</note> seing S. Ieroms Edition so much estemed, not only of the Latines, but also of the Grecians, turned the Psalter &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, out of the same Latin into Greke. Of latter times what shal we nede to recite other most lerned men? S. Bede S. Anselme, S. Bernard, S. Thomas, S. Bonauenture, &amp; the rest? VVho al vniformly allege this only text as authentical. In so much that al other Latin Editions, which S. Ierom<note place="margin">Prefat. in Iosue.</note> saith were in his time almost innumerable, are as it were
<pb facs="4"/>
fallen out of al Diuines handes, and growne out of credite<note place="margin">Al others growne out of vse. S. Ierom ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled al other Doctors in translating &amp; expounding holie Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</note> and vse. If moreouer we consider S. Ieroms lerning, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>etie, diligence, and sinceritie, together with the commodities he had of best copies, in al languages then extant, and of other lerned men, with whom he conferred: and if we so cōare the same with the best meanes that hath bene since, surely no man of indifferent iudgement, wil match anie other Edition with S. Ieroms: but easely acknowlege with the whole Church Gods particular prouidēce in this great Doctor, as wel for expounding, as most especialy for the<note place="margin">His Edition free from. partialitie.</note> true text and Edition of Holie Scriptures. Neither do we flee vnto this old Latin text, for more aduantage. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides that it is free from partialitie, as being most ancient of al Latin copies, and long before the particular Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies of these dayes beganne; the Hebrew also &amp; the Greke when they are truly translated, yea and Erasmus his Latin, in sundrie places, proue more plainly the Catholique Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine<note place="margin">Preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore al other Editions by Beza.</note> doctrine, then this which we relie vpon. So that<note place="margin">Luc. 22. v. 20. Prefat. Noui. Testam. Anno. 1556. Luc. 1. v. 1.</note> Beza &amp; his folowers take also exception against the Greke, when Catholiques allege it against them. Yea the same Beza preferreth the old Latin Version before al others, &amp; freely testifieth, that the old Interpreter translated religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously. VVhat then do our countriemen, that refuse this<note place="margin">None yet in England al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.</note> Latin, but depriue themselues of the best, and yet al this while, haue set forth none, that is allowed by al Protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, for good or sufficient.</p>
   <p>How wel this is donne the lerned may iudge, when by mature conference, they shal haue made trial therof. And if<note place="margin">VVhat is done in this Edition</note> anie thing be mistaken, we wil (as stil we promise) gladly<note place="margin">Preface before the nevv Testam.</note> correct it. Those that trāslated it about thirtie yeares since, were wel knowen to the world, to haue bene excellent in the tongues, sincere men, and great Diuines. Only one<note place="margin">Diuers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vpon, &amp; none leift in the margent.</note> thing we haue donne touching the text, wherof we are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially to geue notice. That whereas heretofore in the best Latin Editions, there remained manie places diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="5"/>
in wordes, some also in sense, as in long processe of time, the writers erred in their copies; now lately by the care &amp; diligence of the Church, those diuers readings were maturely, and iuditiously examined, and conferred with sundrie the best written and printed bookes, &amp; so resolued vpon, that al which before were leift in the margent, are either restored into the text, or els omitted; so that now none such remaine in the margent. For which cause, we haue againe conferred this English translation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed<note place="margin">They touched not present controuersies.</note> it to the most perfect Latin Edition. VVhere yet by the way we must geue the vulgar reader to vnderstand, that very few or none of the former varieties, touched Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersies of this time. So that this Recognition is no way suspicious of partialtie, but is merely donne for the more secure conseruation of the true text; and more ease, and satisfaction of such, as otherwise should haue remained more doubtful.</p>
   <p>Now for the strictnes obserued in translating some<note place="margin">VVhy some vvordes are not translated into vulgar English.</note> wordes, or rather the not translating of some, which is in more danger to be disliked, we doubt not but the discrete lerned reader, deepely weighing and considering the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of sacred wordes, and how easely the translatour may misse the sense of the Holie Ghost, wil hold that which is here donne for reasonable and necessarie. VVe haue also the example of the Latin, and Greke, where some wordes<note place="margin">Some Hebrew wordes not translated into Latin, nor Greke.</note> are not translated, but left in Hebrew, as they were first spoken &amp; written; which seeing they could not, or were not conuenient to be translated into Latin or Greke, how much lesse could they, or was it reason to turne them into English? S. Augustin also yeldeth à reason, exemplifying in the<note place="margin">li 2 Doct. Christ. cap. 11.</note> wordes <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Alleluia, for the more sacred authoritie therof.</hi>
      <note place="margin">More autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in sacred tongues.</note> which doubtles is the cause why some <hi>names of solemne Feastes, Sacrifices,</hi> &amp; other holie thinges are <hi>reserued in sacred tongues,</hi> Hebrew, Greke, or Latin. Againe for necessitie, English not hauing à name, or sufficient terme, we either
<pb facs="5"/>
kepe the word, as we find it, or only turne it to our English<note place="margin">Some vvordes can not be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish:</note> termination, because it would otherwise require manie wordes in English, to signifie one word of an other tongue. In which cases, we commonly put the explication in the margent. Briefly our Apologie is easie against English Protestantes; because they also reserue some wordes in<note place="margin">Protestantes leaue some vvordes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>translated.</note> the original tongues, not translated into English: as <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, Ephod, Pentecost, Proselyte,</hi> and some others. The sense wherof is in dede as soone lerned, as if they were turned so nere as is possible into English. And why then may we not say <hi>Prepuce, Phase</hi> or <hi>Pasch, Azimes, Breades of Proposition, Holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caust,</hi> and the like? rather then as Protestantes translate them: <hi>Foreskinne, Passeouer, The feast of svvete breades, Shevv breades, Burnt offerings:</hi> &amp;c. By which termes, whether they be truly translated into English or no, we wil passe ouer. Sure it is an English man is stil to seke, what they meane, as if they remained in Hebrew, or Greke. It more importeth, that nothing be wittingly and falsly translated, for aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of doctrine in matter of faith. VVherein as we dare boldly auouch the sinceritie of this Translation, and that nothing is here either vntruly, or obscurely donne of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, in fauour of Catholique Romane Religion: so we can not but complaine, and chalenge English Protestantes,<note place="margin">Corruptions in Protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of holie Scriptures.</note> for corrupting the text, cōtrarie to the Hebrew, &amp; Greke, which they professe to translate, for the more shew, and mainteyning of their peculiar opinions against Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques. As is proued in the <hi>Discouerie of manifold corruptiōs.</hi> For example we shal put the reader in memorie of one or two. Gen. 4. v. 7. whereas (God speaking to Cain) the Hebrew wordes in Grammatical construction may be translated either thus: <hi>Vnto thee also perteyneth the lust</hi> THEROF, <hi>&amp; thou shalt haue dominion ouer</hi> IT: or thus; <hi>Also vnto thee</hi> HIS <hi>desire</hi>
      <note place="margin">Of purpose a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique doctrine</note>
      <hi>shal be subiect, &amp; thou shalt rule ouer</hi> HIM: though the cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rēce of the text requireth the former, &amp; in the Bibles prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1552. and. 1577. Protestantes did so translate it: yet in
<pb facs="6"/>
the yeare 1579. and 1603. they translate it the other way,<note place="margin">Against▪ free wil.</note> rather saying, that Abel was subiect to Cain, and that Cain by Gods ordinance, had dominion ouer his brother Abel, then that concupiscence or lust of sinne is subiect to mans wil, or that man hath powre of free wil, to resist (by Gods grace) tentation of sinne. But as we heare in a new Edition (which we haue not yet sene) they trāslate it almost as in the<note place="margin">Against Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisedechs sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</note> first in like sorte Gen. 14. v. 18. The Hebrew particle VAV, which S. Ierom, and al Antiquitie translated ENIM (FOR) Protestants wil by no meanes admitte it, because (besides other argumentes) we proue therby Melchisedechs Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. And yet themselues translate the same, as S. Ierom doth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 3. saying: FOR <hi>she is a mans vvife.</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">And against holie Images.</note> Againe <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. <hi>v.</hi> 19. the English Bibles. 1552. and 1577. translate <hi>Theraphim,</hi> IMAGES. VVhich the Edition of 1603▪ correcting, translateth IDOLES. And the marginal Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation wel proueth, that it ought to be so translated.</p>
   <p>VVith this then we wil conclude most deare (we speake<note place="margin">This Edition dedicated to al that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand English.</note> to you al, that vnderstand our tongue, whether you be of contrarie opinions in faith, or of mundane feare participate with an other Congregation; or professe with vs the same Catholique Religion) to you al we present this worke: day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beseching God Almightie, the Diuine VVisedom, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Goodnes, to create, illuminate, and replenish your spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, with his Grace, that you may attaine eternal Glorie. Euerie one in his measure, in those manie Mansions, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and promised by our Sauiour in his Fathers house. Not only to those which first receiued, &amp; folowed his Diuine doctrine, but to al that should afterwardes beleue in him, &amp; kepe the same preceptes. For there is one God, one also Mediatour of God and men: Man Christ Iesus. VVho gaue himself a Redemption for al. VVherby appeareth his wil, that al should be saued. VVhy then are not al saued? The Apostle addeth: that they must first come to the knowlege<note place="margin">Christ redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med al, but al are not saued.</note> of the truth. Because without faith it is impossible to please
<pb facs="6"/>
God. This ground worke therfore of our creation in Christ<note place="margin">True faith first necessarie.</note> by true faith, S. Paul labored most seriously by word and writing, to establish in the hartes of al men. In this he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the Romanes by his Epistle, cōmending their faith, as already receiued, and renowmed in the whole world. He preached the same faith to manie Nations. Amongst o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the lerned Athenians. VVhere it semed to some, as absurde, as strange; in so much that they scornfully called him <hi>avvord-sovver,</hi> and Preacher of new gods. But S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin<note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>Ser.</hi> 42. <hi>de Sanct.</hi>
      </note> alloweth the terme for good, which was reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully spoken of the ignorant. And so distinguishing betwen <hi>Reapers,</hi> and <hi>Sovvers</hi> in Gods Church, he teacheth, that<note place="margin">The twelue Apostles were first Reapers, before they were Sowers▪ S. Paul at first a Sower, or Seminarie Apostle.</note> wheras the other Apostles reaped in the Iewes, that which their Patriarches and Prophetes had sowne; S. Paul sowed the seede of Christian Religion in the Gentiles. And so in respect of the Israelites, to whom they were first sent, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the other Apostles <hi>Messores, Reapers,</hi> and S. Paul, being specially sent to the Gentiles, <hi>Seminatorem a Sovver, or Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Apostle.</hi> VVhich two sortes of Gods workmen are stil in the Church, with distinct offices of Pastoral cures, and Apostolical missions; the one for perpetual gouernment of<note place="margin">Pastoral cures and Apostoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal missions.</note> Catholique countries: the other for conuersion of such, as either haue not receiued Christian Religion, or are relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. As at this time in our country, for the diuers sortes of pretended religions, these diuers spiritual workes are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, to teach and feede al Britan people. Because some in error of opinions preach an other Gospel, wheras in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie<note place="margin">New doctrine is falsly called the Gospel.</note> there is no other Gospel. They preach in dede new do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,<note place="margin">S. Aug. de v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>lit crede 1. c. Mat. 15.</note> which can not saue. Others folow them beleuing falshood. But <hi>vvhen the blinde lead the blinde</hi> (not the one<note place="margin">The seduced, &amp; externally conformable are punished with the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie▪</note> only, but) <hi>both fal into the ditch.</hi> Others conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, in external shew, fearing them that can punish, and kil the bodie. But <hi>our Lord vvil bring such as decline into</hi> (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iust)<note place="margin">Psalmo. 124.</note>
      <hi>obligations, vvith them that vvorke iniquitie.</hi> The Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques and smal flock of Catholiques in our country, haue
<pb facs="7"/>
great sadnes, and sorow of hart; not so much for our owne affliction, for that is comfortable, but for you our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and kinsemen in flesh and bloud. VVishing with our owne temporal damage whatsoeuer, your saluation. Now<note place="margin">-. Cor. 6.</note> is the acceptable time, now are the dayes of saluation, the<note place="margin">Grace in the new Testamēt more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant then in the old.</note> time of Grace by Christ, whose dayes manie Kinges &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes desired to see: they saw them (<hi>in spirite</hi>) and reioyced.<note place="margin">Luc. 10.</note> But we are made partakers of Christ, and his Mysteries; so that our selues neglect not his heauenly riches: if we receiue &amp; kepe the beginning of his substance, firme vnto the end; that is, the true Catholique faith; building theron good workes by his grace; without which we can not thinke a good thought, by which we can do al thinges necessarie to saluation. But if we hold not fast this ground, al the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding fayleth. Or if confessing to know God in wordes, we<note place="margin">Tit. 1.</note> denie him in deedes, committing workes of darknes;<note place="margin">Both wicked workes, and omission of good workes are damnable.</note> or omitting workes of mercie, when we may doe them to<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> our distressed neighbours; brifly if we haue not charitie, the<note place="margin">1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>3.</note> forme and perfection of al vertues, al is lost, and nothing worth. But if we builde vpon firme grounde, gold, siluer, and precious stones, such building shal abide, and make<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> our vocation sure by good workes. as S. Peter speaketh. These (saith S. Paul) are the heyres of God, coheyres of<note place="margin">Innumerable saued by Christ.</note> Christ. Neither is the number of Christs blessed children<note place="margin">Apoc. 7.</note> coūted, as of the Iewes, an hundred fourtie foure thousand, of euerie tribe of Israel twelue thousand signed; but a most great multitude of Catholique Christians, which no man can number, of al nations, and tribes, and peoples, and tongues, standing before the throne of the lambe, clothed in white robes, and palmes (<hi>of triumph</hi>) in their handes: hauing ouercome tentations in the vertuous race of good life. Much more those which also indure persecution for<note place="margin">They are more happie that suffer persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the truth.</note> the truthes sake, shal receiue most copious great rewardes in heauen. For albeit the passions of this time (<hi>in themselues</hi>) are not<note n="*" place="margin">Vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in dignitie.</note> condigne, to the glorie to come, that shal be reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="7"/>
in vs: yet our tribulation, which presently is momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> and light, worketh (<hi>through grace</hi>) aboue measure excedingly an eternal weight of glorie. VVhat shal we therfore meditate of the especial prerogatiue of English Catholiques at this time? For to you it is geuen for Christ, not only that you beleue in him, but also that you suffer for<note place="margin">English Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques most happie in this age.</note> him. A litle now, if you must be made pensiue in diuers<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> tentations, that the probation of your faith, much more precious then gold, which is proued by the fire, may be found vnto praise, and glorie, and honour, in the reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iesus Christ. Manie of you haue susteyned the spoile of your goodes with ioy, knowing that you haue a better and a permanent substance. Others haue benne depriued of your children, fathers, mothers, brothers, sisters, and nerest frendes, in readie resolution also, some with sentence of death, to lose your owne liues. Others haue had trial of reproches, mockeries, and stripes. Others of bandes, prisons, and banishmentes. The innumerable renowmed late English Martyres, &amp; Confessors, whose happie soules<note place="margin">The due praise of Martyres, and other glorious Sainctes exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth mortal tongues.</note> for confessing true faith before men, are now most glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in heauen, we passe here with silence; because their due praise, requiring longer discourse, yea rather Angels, then English tongues, farre surpasseth the reach of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptes. And so we leaue it to your deuout meditation. They now secure for themselues, and solicitous for vs their dearest clientes, incessantly (we are wel assured) intercede before Christs Diuine Maiestie, for our happie consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, with the conuersion of our whole countrie. To you therfore (dearest frendes mortal) we direct this speach: admonishing ourselues &amp; you, in the Apostles wordes, that for so much as we haue not yet resisted tentations to (last)<note place="margin">Patience ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie to the end of mans life.</note> bloud (and death itself) patience is stil necessarie for vs, that doing the wil of God, we may receiue the promise. So we repine not in tribulation, but euer loue them that hate vs, pittying their case, and reioycing in our owne. For
<pb facs="8"/>
neither can we see during this life, how much good they<note place="margin">Persecution profitable.</note> do vs; nor know how manie of them shal be (as we hartely desire they al may be) saued: our Lord and Sauiour hauing paide the same price by his death, for them and for vs. Loue al therefore, pray for al. Do not lose your confidence, which hath a great remuneration. For yet a litle, and a very litle while, he that is to come, wil come, and he wil not slacke. Now the iust liueth by faith, beleeuing with<note place="margin">Rom 10. Heb. 10.</note> hart to iustice, and confessing with mouth to saluation. But<note place="margin">Confession of faith before men necessarie to saluation.</note> he that withdraweth himself shal not please Christs soule. Attend to your saluation, dearest countriemen. You that are farre of, draw nere, put on Christ. And you that are within Christs fold, kepe your standing, perseuere in him to the end. His grace dwel and remaine in you, that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous crownes may be geuen you.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From the English College in Doway, <date>the Octaues of AL SAINCTES. 1609.</date>
      </dateline>
The God of patience and comfort geue you to be of one mind, one tovvards another in <hi>IESVS</hi> Christ; that of one mind, vvith one mouth you may glorifie God.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>