<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVELY VERTVOVS, AND WORTHY KNIGHT, SIR OLIVER CROMWEL, T. B. wisheth encrease of grace and all happinesse.</title>
           <author>Beard, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101599_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06106</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1658</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101599</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVELY VERTVOVS, AND WORTHY KNIGHT, SIR OLIVER CROMWEL, T. B. wisheth encrease of grace and all happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Beard, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A retractiue from the Romish religion : contayning thirteene forcible motiues, disswading from communion with the Church of Rome: wherein is demonstratiuely proued, that the now Romish religion (so farre forth as it is Romish) is not the true Catholike religion of Christ, but the seduction of Antichrist: by Tho. Beard, Doctor in Diuinity, and preacher of Gods holy word in the towne of Huntington</title>
                 <author>Beard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 543, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVELY VERTVOVS, AND WORTHY KNIGHT, SIR OLIVER CROMWEL, T. B. wisheth <hi>encrease of grace and all happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE bee many particular respects that mooue me to be bold, to set your name in the fronti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spice of this work: As first, your sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere loue to true Religion, and the Professors thereof: Secondly, your true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation of the Romish Synagogue, and
<pb facs="3"/>
the malignant influences of those wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Planets, that infect the aire of our Church, and seeke by mining, poysoning, and other deuillish practices, to turne our <hi>Jerusalem</hi> into <hi>Babel.</hi> Thirdly, for that your selfe, with your religious Lady, worthy children, and brethren, and great family, haue beene a long time the principall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors of my vnworthy ministery, wherein many of these points haue been deliuered vpon occasion, that you may see them here more fully discoursed, and so be the better confirmed in the truth. And lastly, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular obligations of loue and duty, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I am bound vnto you for many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary fauours and kindnesses recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. These be the motiues, that haue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued mee to select your selfe principally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all others to dedicate these motiues vnto. For the which I desire no more pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage and protection, then the truth of the seuerall points contayned therein doe deserue. Let them stand vpon their owne legs, or fall and perish. I know, they shall encounter with many bitter oppositions, and sharpe aduersaries, who will be ready
<pb facs="3"/>
to sift euery sentence, and to find a knot in a bull-rush: but my shelter is the buckler of truth, and the brazen wal of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science; with which being armed, I hope, through Gods aide, that I shall be as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and able to entertayne the re-encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if any assault be made, as I was willing to giue this on-set: I confesse that these are not the tithe of the arguments, that might be produced against the Romish religion, yet I doubt not, but that euen these few may serue, both to discouer the falshood thereof, and to confirme and strengthen those that stagger, and are weake in the truth: the Lord accompanying these en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours of his seruant with his blessing, as I hope, and pray that he would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to do. These motiues, such as they are, I willingly desire may be graced by your name, hoping that your name shal no way be disgraced by them: accept them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as tokens of my sincere loue to your selfe, and zeale to the truth, for which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire no other requitall, but an augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your zeale to the same truth, and a greater detestation of that Religion, which
<pb facs="4"/>
already you abhor. The Lord of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy encrease in you more and more all spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall graces for your soules health, and multiply his blessings temporall vpon your head, and crowne you with glory, and immortality eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in the life to come.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships most affectionate and deuoted,
THO. BEARD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>