<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface Magneticall.</title>
           <author>R., M.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101594_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10774</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21045</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101594</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface Magneticall.</title>
                 <author>R., M.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short treatise of magneticall bodies and motions. By Marke Ridley Dr in phisicke and philosophie latly physition to the Emperour of Russia, and one of ye eight principals of elects of the Colledge of Physitions in London</title>
                 <author>Ridley, Mark</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 157, 1 page, illustrations (woodcuts), tables, diagrams, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A Preface Magneticall.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Vrposing to deliuer a briefe and easie do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as concerning this new Art of <hi>Magneticall Bodies and Motions:</hi> I thought good here to free the same from the lustre and glosse of disputable points and other conceits, onely purposing to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle nothing in the same but the plaine matter and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations. <hi>Magneticall</hi> themselues, thinking it more fitting to place these flowers in the Preface, if any delight rather in them, then in the matter it selfe, to the end they may in some sort be prouided of both. As concerning the first finding out of the <hi>Magnet-stone,</hi> whereof I am to treate, <hi>Plinie</hi> and <hi>Nicander</hi> haue fained that a certaine Heard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man being in the fields, hauing his shoes shod with iron, and his staffe armed with an iron pike, and resting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe vpon a quantity of this stone, could not easily remoue his feete, or lift vp his staffe, whereupon he perceiued the attractiue vertue of this stone, that it did attract and hold iron. Other thinke that the pioners and diggers of met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, by their diligence and obseruances first found out the <hi>Load-stone,</hi> and his vertue of attracting iron, by which property it was well knowne to the auntient <hi>Egyptians</hi> and <hi>Graetians</hi> in times past. Some haue thought that the
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Magnet</hi> would leese this quality attractiue, if he were annointed with garlicke, or touched with a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, and of this opinion were <hi>Ptolomie, Plutarcke, Plinie,</hi> and <hi>Baptista Porta;</hi> for this mallady <hi>Ruelius</hi> hath found a remedy to annoint the <hi>Load-stone</hi> with Goates bloud, and <hi>Paracelsus</hi> with his oyle of <hi>Crocus Martis,</hi> will not onely cure him of this euill, but can make him ten times stronger then he was before, likewise <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danus</hi> and <hi>Alexander Amphrodiseus</hi> haue laboured to nouris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the <hi>Magnet</hi> with fitings of iron and steele.</p>
   <p>Many haue striued much to inquire out the cause how the <hi>Magnet</hi> should attract iron vnto it, <hi>Epicurus, Aphrodiseus, Carus, Iohannes Costaeus, Plutarke,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> do suppose this attractiue vertue to proceed from certaine motes, vnsensible parts or vapors issuing forth of the <hi>Magnet,</hi> and entring into the iron by conuenient figures, and in their retiring backe againe do attract the iron to the <hi>Load-stone.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Fernelius</hi> haue thought the cause of this at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction to be Diuine and from aboue. <hi>Thales</hi> and <hi>Anaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> say that the <hi>Magnet</hi> hath life in it, whereby it at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracteth the like substance as liuing things do. Some thinke that there is a certaine sympathie betweene the <hi>Magnet</hi> and iron, as betweene the male and female, as <hi>Orpheus</hi> and <hi>Lucretius</hi> haue sung.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Auaroes, Scaliger,</hi> and Cardinall <hi>Cusanus</hi> would haue iron to moue vnto the <hi>Magnet,</hi> as to his beginning and matrixe, from whence he came. <hi>Gulielmus Putea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Galen,</hi> and others, do iudge that by his substantiall forme he draweth iron vnto it, but Doctor <hi>Gilbert,</hi> whose labours are the greatest, and best in <hi>Magneticall</hi> Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, doth conceiue that the <hi>Magnet</hi> and iron do moue one vnto the other, not by any specificall forme, but from the
<pb facs="3"/>
essentiall forme of the <hi>Magneticall</hi> globe of the earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an essentiall part of the same, which is not so, as it shall be demonstrated in the last Chapter of this Treatise.</p>
   <p>To illustrate this vertue of attraction in the <hi>Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, Serapio</hi> and the Moores, like farre trauellers, haue reported that in the <hi>Indies</hi> there be mighty craggie rockes, all of <hi>Magnet-stone,</hi> that will stay the ships as they saile by them, and pull the iron nailes out of them; this story <hi>Olaus Magnus</hi> also confirmeth to be so in the North, and that there, least the rockes of <hi>Load-stone</hi> should pull the iron workes and nailes from the vessels and boates, they build them with wodden pins, and sowe the boords together with lines of the barkes of trees; which indeed they do both for want of our skill in building ships and barges, and for want of iron workes, whereof they haue little store.</p>
   <p>And because this stone hath vertue to attract, therefore <hi>Marbodeus</hi> a French-man, <hi>Petrus Bairus, Pictorius</hi> and <hi>Arnoldus de villa noua</hi> do faine that this stone will pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cure the loue of Princes and of women, and maintaine loue betweene husband and wife. <hi>Haly-abbas</hi> will haue the <hi>Load-stone</hi> to cure the goute, if it be held in the hand, and the East Indians say that it preserueth youth. <hi>Caelius Calcaginus</hi> saith, that if the <hi>Magnet</hi> be preserued in the salt of the sea-Lampron or Remora, that is thought to stay a ship vnder saile, that then the <hi>Magnet</hi> will draw vp gold that is fallen into the deepest well.</p>
   <p>And <hi>Fracastorius</hi> testifieth that he hath seene a <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> that would draw siluer vnto it, and chase iron from it. <hi>Cardanus, Antonius de Fantis, Petrus Perigrinus,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Taisner</hi> do deliuer that there might be made a perpetuall motion by the vertue of the <hi>Load-stone,</hi> but by the experience of many ingenious practises I find it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible
<pb facs="4"/>
to be done.</p>
   <p>Since the finding out of the Sea-compasse, which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 300 yeares ago, by one <hi>Thomas Goa,</hi> borne neere <hi>Naples,</hi> or by <hi>Marcus Paulus Venetus,</hi> who learned that skill in <hi>China,</hi> as is thought, and first brought it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Italy,</hi> there haue growne many opinions how this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe should be directed into the North and South. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilius Ficinus, Paracelsus,</hi> and <hi>Cardan</hi> thinke that the vertue of the constellation of the <hi>Beare</hi> doth gouerne the <hi>Magnet</hi> and iron, and therefore both these are dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted into the North. <hi>Petrus Peregrinus,</hi> Frier <hi>Bacon, Iohn Taisner,</hi> and many other would haue the Compasse to obserue the North pole: But since that <hi>Sebastianus Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botta,</hi> did find out that the Compasse did vary from the true meridian, it hath bene imagined that there is some place in the heauens that the Compasse should respect, as <hi>Cardan</hi> would haue it, to obserue the starre in the taile of <hi>Vrsa major. Bessardus,</hi> a Frenchman saith that it doth behold the pole of the Zodiacke, <hi>Martin Cortesius</hi> would haue an attractiue point aboue the heauens, and <hi>Robert Norman</hi> an Englishman, denieth that there is an attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue point, but affirmeth that there is a respectiue point, to the which the Compasse doth moue, especially the <hi>Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natory-needle,</hi> whereof he was the first inuent or.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Liuius Sanulus</hi> supposeth that there is a certaine <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neticall</hi> meridian, and <hi>Francis Maurolicus,</hi> that there is a <hi>Magneticall</hi> Iland, and <hi>Fracastorius</hi> holdeth that there be certaine <hi>Magneticall</hi> mountaines, which be set out in <hi>Plancius</hi> his Card, that the Compasse doth respect. But Doctor <hi>Gilbert,</hi> our friend and Collegiat, hath disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered these errors, and set forth the causes of the varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Compasse in his booke <hi>De Magnete.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Yet lately <hi>Gulielmus Nautonerius,</hi> a Frenchman, and
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Anthony Linton</hi> an Englishman haue supposed that the <hi>Magneticall-needle</hi> and Compasse do moue and turne themselues vpon the <hi>Magneticall</hi> meridian alwayes vnto their owne <hi>Magneticall</hi> poles, placed vpon the superficies of the earth that be neere, and within the circles polar, not varying at all from their owne meridian, but deuidte on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and decline from the meridians of the pole of the world, and with this conceit, these two, with many curious calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and proiects, will presently find the longitude of all Cities and Countries; but this their strong imagination hath failed them, being grounded vpon obseruations from the variations of the needle, from which these two men haue set forth different <hi>Magneticall</hi> poles; and if they should worke from 500 obseruations, they might gesse at neere halfe as many varietie of poles (for variations are not regular, but irregular, because their scattered cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses be irregular) so that these men haue found insteed of the longitude of places, a longitude of vnprofitable labors.</p>
   <p>Therefore, not purposing to dazell any ones conceit with the repetition and confutation of any opinions, termes of Art, or words whatsoeuer, I will come to the Tractate it selfe, thinking that the quiuering <hi>Magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call-needle</hi> will be trouble inough to handle for the better knowledge and delight in <hi>Magneticall</hi> experiments.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>M. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>