<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>B., S.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101608_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68508</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1862</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101608</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>B., S.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentary or exposition vpon the first chapter of the prophecie of Amos : Deliuered in xxi. sermons in the parish church of Meysey-Hampton in the diocesse of Glocester. By Sebastian Benefield</title>
                 <author>Benefield, Sebastian, 1559-1630</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Haviland, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Perry, Hugh</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 264 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese Sermons were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for the Pulpit, not intended for the Presse. Yet, sith I liue in a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall age of the world, wherein too many with their vnprofitable, if not obscene <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> doe runne<note n="a" place="margin">Ad prel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam pralium.</note>
      <hi>to the Presse,</hi> as a horse <hi>to the battell,</hi> and are entertained <hi>with applause;</hi> I haue the more willingly now published them to thy view. Thou wilt say: There is already great store of <hi>Sermons</hi> abroad; more than we can well vse. I deny it not. Yet to the fulnesse of this <hi>Sea</hi> I adde more, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent not. Is abundance a burthen to thee? If thy soule may be fed with variety, as well <hi>by the eye</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> as <hi>by the eare,</hi> hast thou any reason to finde fault? But weake stomacks may surfet at the sight of too much. Let such fauour their eye-sight. They may easily looke off, and please themselues with their old choice. There is no reason that their daintinesse should preiudice that profit, which others might reape from this abundance. Wee that are called to be <hi>labourers</hi> in the Lords Haruest, must resolue with <hi>the</hi> Lord <hi>of the Haruest.</hi> His resolution was,<note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.4.</note>
      <hi>I must worke the workes of him that sent me while it is day: the night commeth, when no man can worke.</hi> Our <hi>day</hi> is our life time; the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly time for vs <hi>to worke in.</hi> If now, in this <hi>our day time,</hi> we will in stead of <hi>working,</hi> only trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure vp knowledge in our hearts, as that Hoarder in the<note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Cap.</hi> 11.26.</note>
      <hi>Prouerbs</hi> did his <hi>Corne</hi> in his <hi>storehouse;</hi> or will wrap vp the gifts, wherewith God hath blessed vs, in waste Papers, as the slothfull seruant in the<note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.20.</note>
      <hi>Gospell</hi> did his <hi>Talent</hi> in a <hi>Napkin;</hi> the <hi>night</hi> will come vpon vs and we shall not <hi>worke.</hi> Suffer vs therefore, while it is our <hi>day,</hi> to <hi>worke.</hi> Our <hi>worke</hi> consisteth in the <hi>preaching</hi> of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell.</hi> The <hi>Gospell</hi> is <hi>preached</hi> as well<note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Ambo verbum praedicant, hic quidem scripto, ille vero voce. Clem. Alexan. stromat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>interprete Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiano Herueto, p.</hi> 57. <hi>edit. Basil. in fol. An.</hi> 1556. <hi>&amp; paulò pòst. Praedicandi sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>tia est quodam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo Angelica, vtrouis modo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uans, seu per ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>u per lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guam operetur.</hi> There is not any thing <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely notified</hi> but we may in that respect rightly and properly say it is <hi>preached, Luk.</hi> 8.39. and 12.3. <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>r Eccl Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t. l.</hi> 5. §. 18 <hi>p.</hi> 28. <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets, <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apostles were in their times all <hi>Preachers</hi> of Gods truth; some by <hi>Word,</hi> some by <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> some by <hi>Both. Hooker ibid.</hi> §. 19. <hi>pag.</hi> 29. The Apostles in <hi>Writing,</hi> are not vntruly nor vnfitly said to <hi>preach. Hooker lib.</hi> 5. §. 21. <hi>pag.</hi> 39. <hi>vide ibid. plura. Euangelizo</hi> Manu, <hi>&amp;</hi> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, <hi>Rainold de Rom. Eccles. Ido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>lat. Praef. ad Com. Essex. pag.</hi> 7.</note> by <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> as by <hi>speaking;</hi> as well by <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n</hi> as by <hi>tongue.</hi> The word <hi>spoken,</hi> for the time is most piercing, but the letter <hi>written</hi> is of most continuance. I shall account it my happinesse, if I may doe good both waies. My place in that <hi>worthy Foundation,</hi> whereof I am an vnworthy member, wearing me out in the reading of <hi>Humanity,</hi> now the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth yeere, hath hindered mee from doing that good I wished to haue done, the one way by my <hi>speaking</hi> by my <hi>tongue.</hi> If the other way, by my <hi>writing</hi> by my <hi>pen,</hi> I may redeeme the time past, and by these my poore labours may doe some good, not only to<note n="f" place="margin">The inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>isey Hampton, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston,</hi> and <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocesse of <hi>Gloce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi>
      </note> them, among whom I first <hi>sowed this seed,</hi> but also to other Congregations of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, I haue enough. If <hi>(deare Christian)</hi> thou finde in these my <hi>Sermons</hi> the same things itera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, maruell not thereat; I haue my <hi>Prophets</hi> warrant for it. He in this first Chapter repeateth the same things fiue times ouer. May not I after his ensample doe it once or twise? I must professe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee <hi>(good Christian)</hi> that my chiefe intent in this <hi>Commentary</hi> is <hi>the destruction of sinne.</hi> If to any of the <hi>learned,</hi> I seeme to haue failed of my purpose, my earnest desire is, that they will be pleased to take the paines to amend it. The rest, who to this poore labour of mine shall afford their graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="4"/> and fauourable good liking, I heartily entreat to helpe me with their godly prayers, that <hi>this worke</hi> and whatsoeuer else of like kinde I shall hereafter attempt to publish to the censure of the world, may wholly redound to the glory of God, and good of his Church. Now the <hi>God of peace, that brought againe from the dead our Lord</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, <hi>that great Shepherd of the sheepe through the bloud of the euerlasting couenant,</hi> sanctifie thee thorowout, that enioying the peace of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science in this world, thou maist hereafter haue full fruition of that eternall peace of God in Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>n.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine vnfeinedly in the Lord, for thy good,</hi> S. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>