<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101656_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68702</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21850.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101656</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first and best part of Scoggins iests : full of witty mirth and pelasant shifts, done by him in France, and other places: being a preseruatiue against melancholy. Gathered by Andrew Boord, Doctor of Physicke</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Williams, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harrison, John 4.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jackson, Hugh.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jackson, Roger</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 92 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Prologue.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>THere is nothing beside the goodnesse of God, that preserue health so much, as honest mirth, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally mirth vsed at dinner and supper, and mirth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bed, as it doth plainly appeare in the</hi> Directions for health: <hi>Therefore considering this matter, that mirth is so necessary a thing for man, I published this Booke, named,</hi> The Iests of <hi>Scogin, to make men mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: for amongst diuers other Bookes of graue matters that I haue made, my delight hath beene to recreate my mind in making something merrie. Wherefore I doe aduertise euery man in auoiding pensiuenesse, or too much study or melancholie, to be merrie with honesty in God, and for God, whom I humbly beseech to send vs the mirth of Heauen,</hi> Amen.</p>
   <p>I Haue heard say, that <hi>Scogin</hi> did come of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest stocke or kindred, and his friends did set him to schoole at <hi>Oxford,</hi> where hee did continue vntill the time he was made Master of Art, where he made this Iest:</p>
   <lg>
      <l>A Master of Art is not worth a fart,</l>
      <l>Except he be in Schooles,</l>
      <l>A Batchelor of Law is not worth astraw,</l>
      <l>Except he be among fooles.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>