<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>N.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101346_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04154</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14297</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101346</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>N.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ecclesiastes : The worthy church-man, or the faithfull minister of Iesus Christ. Described by polishing the twelve stones in the high-priests pectorall, as they were first glossed and scholyed on in a Synod-sermon; and after enlarged by way of discourse, to his two brethren. By Iohn Iackson parson of Marske in Richmond-shire</title>
                 <author>Jackson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Moore (More), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ouchsafe in briefe to understand
the occasion of bringing these <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi>
from the <hi>Pulpit</hi> to the
<hi>Presse.</hi> The <hi>Author,</hi> so neere to me,
as <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>function</hi> could allye
us, at a Synode held at <hi>Richmond</hi>
in the North <hi>sermoned</hi> upon these twelve stones. A
gratefull fame of which discourse found quicke and
safe conveyance to mee by men of severe judgments.<note n="*" place="margin">Capita libri excurro, vbi{que} summa cruditio, vbi{que} fastidij ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pultrix, blandita varietas, &amp; (quod plurimum ingenij ac laboris postulant) tot tantorum{que} Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorum testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio res agitur, vt quicun{que}; su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillare aliquid ex istis lucubra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus tuis ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taverit, canis la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trator haberi pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit non demorsor. Iac. Antiquarius in Miscell. A. Pol.</note>
Whereupon I desired of him a copy, which upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest
he was pleased (repriving a while his more serious
studies) to transcribe, fyling and burnishing it over
againe, and adding hereunto <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> &amp; <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundam
manum.</hi> He is my brother, and therefore
<hi>love</hi> will not suffer me to <hi>dispraise</hi> any thing, nor <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty</hi>
to <hi>commend</hi> much: let this <hi>small peice</hi> speake
for him; yet thus farre I dare charge my judgement,
(if I may be allowed to judge,) The conceit is new, and
the proper birth of his owne braine, the matter likewise
partly of his owne fresh invention, and his <hi>readings</hi>
(which may commend him the more) clad with the
mantle of his owne <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>phrase.</hi> He is throughout
<hi>curt, cult,</hi> and <hi>methodicall.</hi> The whole smelling of
<pb facs="3"/>
the <hi>oyle</hi> of his lampe, and (which is much better) of
the <hi>anoynting</hi> of Gods Spirit.</p>
   <p>And tho the<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Burton</hi> in his Preface to his booke of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>forwardnesse</hi> and <hi>ambition</hi>
of some is justly complained of, who the better to
put forward themselves, put forth their Sermons:
A sermon preached at the <hi>Court,</hi> A sermon
preached in the <hi>Vniversity,</hi> A sermon at the <hi>Crosse,</hi>
A sermon at an <hi>Assizes,</hi> A sermon at a <hi>Visitation,</hi>
A sermon before the <hi>Right Honorable,</hi> A sermon
before the <hi>Right Worshipfull,</hi> A sermon in <hi>Latin,</hi> A
sermon in <hi>English,</hi> A Mariage sermon, A Funerall
sermon, A sermon, a sermon, a sermon, &amp;c. Yet in
lieu thereof take the <hi>Censure</hi> and <hi>Sentence</hi> of a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
and learned<note n="*" place="margin">The L. <hi>Veru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam</hi> in his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Learning <hi>ad finem. Emanationes scripturarum in doctrinas posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> Gentleman speaking definitively: to
wit, that if the choise and best of those Observations,
that have beene made dispersedly in sermons, within
his Majesties Ilands of <hi>Britaine,</hi> by the space of these
40. yeares and more (leaving out the largenesse of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations
and applications thereupon) had beene set
downe in a continuance, it had beene the best worke in
Divinity which had beene written since the Apostles
time; and I doubt not but some things in this discourse
may worthily be cast into that volume. This little
bee spoken by way of <hi>Apology,</hi> not for him but my
selfe, lest any charge mee with unnecessary intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.
Thus committing the Author, the booke, and
the publisher to thy kind love and acceptance, I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ,
<hi>N. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>