<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>C., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S101392_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07423</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1781</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S101392</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>C., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The masse displayed. VVritten in French by Mr Iohn Bede, advocate to the Parliament of Paris, and now translated into English</title>
                 <author>Bédé de la Gormandière, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Short, James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 112 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO <hi>THE READER.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Uch hath ever beene the opinion of the Church of God concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Liturgies, that the wise and provident establishers of religion in all places, haue iudged it imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to plant knowledge in the pulpit, vnlesse they founded also devotion in the assembly, and supplied it with a due fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture of prayers and thanksgiuings sutable to all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences that might befall. I need not search other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords for confirmation and proofe hereof, then those remnants of Liturgies, and ruines, rather then perfect images of primatiue zeale, which antiquitie hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath'd vnto vs; whereof some passing through the mists of ignorance haue lost their names, and beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted into wrong families, others sliding through the chanails of superstition, haue enterlarded their first materials with much slime. Amongst the former, I ranke those Liturgies falsely attributed to S. <hi>Peter,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Vide Mornay. l. <hi>1.</hi> de Missa. c. <hi>2.</hi> Rivet. critic. sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cri specimen. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Coc. censur ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> S. <hi>Iames,</hi> S. <hi>Mathew,</hi> and S. <hi>Marke,</hi> amongst the later <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil's</hi> entertain'd by the <hi>Syrians, Chrysostomes</hi> vsed in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople, Isodores,</hi> receau'd in <hi>Spaine,</hi> as also <hi>Ambroses</hi> in <hi>Millayne, Gregories</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> besides other which are
<pb facs="3"/> recounted to haue taken place in <hi>France, Germanie,</hi> and other countries. Which later sort, I stile not by the names of these fathers,<note place="margin">Bel. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Missa c. <hi>19.</hi> §. Voi il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud etiam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum &amp;c.</note> as if I acknowledged them to be their naturall children, since our adversaries them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues will not so farre make them legitimate, but that whereas impregnable reasons may bee alleadged to proue those Missalls which ware the Apostles liueries to be the brood of an after age; these which shelter themselues vnder the patronage of the Fathers may probably haue receaued either some approbation or reformation from them, though not in the same sort and fashion as time &amp; blindnesse hath since deformed them.</p>
   <p>But to speake more particularly of the Romane Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, of which the succeding tract may require some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be delivered, wee must vnderstand, that it was not of one mans composing, but by sundry persons, partly augmented, partly changed, partly corrupted. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alloweth a sufficient portion of time, even 800 yeares for the perfecting of this building,<note place="margin">Bel. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Missa c. <hi>20.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>17.</hi>
      </note> and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing it as high as the roofe, and yet in another place hee confesseth fiue prayers to haue beene added within the space of these last 500 yeares, which were taken out of the French Missals and inserted into the Roman: I need not rehearse in order how and by whom each part of this Liturgie tooke its beginning, seeing my author hath throughout his worke eased mee of that labour, one thing notwithstanding wee may take notice of by the way, that howsoever the allowance of the Bishops of Rome might be required (so farre as their proper diocesse did extend) for inserting of Canons into the body of the Liturgy, yet that they were not the onely
<pb facs="3"/> authors or penners thereof,<note place="margin">Concil. Trident. Plat. in vita Xisti <hi>1.</hi> Greg epist. l <hi>2.</hi> ep. <hi>54.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>9.</hi> ep. <hi>14.</hi>
      </note> (as the Tridentine Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell seemes to intimate) for <hi>Platina</hi> attributes the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell and Epistles to <hi>Hierom,</hi> the <hi>Alleluia</hi> to the Church of <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> the symboll to the <hi>Nicen</hi> Councell, as likewise <hi>Gregory</hi> allowes a good part to one <hi>Scholasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bell. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Mis. c. <hi>20.</hi>
      </note> neither can <hi>Bellarmine</hi> otherwise defend the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of it, then by saying that many parts thereof may be found in the writings of the ancient fathers.</p>
   <p>Touching the often changes to which this Canon hath beene subiect, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> notes three maine ones;<note place="margin">Bell. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Mis. c. <hi>19.</hi> Greg. lib. <hi>7.</hi> epist. <hi>73.</hi>
      </note> The first of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, who abbridged the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasian canon</hi> as himselfe confesseth, saying, <hi>that hee resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red some things, and tooke other things away.</hi> This refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med canon for a long time contained it selfe within the narrow bounds of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Patrimony in Italy,<note place="margin">Greg. decret. ad interrogat. Aug.</note> and was not imposed vpon forraine countreyes as a rule to which they ought to conforme themselues, as may appeare by the question moued by <hi>Austen</hi> the Monke vnto <hi>Gregory,</hi> viz. why Masses were celebrated in one manner in France, and in another in Rome;<note place="margin">Cassand. praefat. ad ord. Rom.</note> But when <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> was lifted vp into the imperial throne by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the third, in requitall of that good seruice done him, hee compelled not onely the French (which his father <hi>Pepin</hi> had begunne) but also all the Clergie subiect to him, partly by threats, and partly by punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to embrace and admit of the <hi>Gregorian office. France</hi> it seemes soone yeelded, and not long after <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many;</hi> But the <hi>Spaniards</hi> as they are euer obstinate in a custome once entertained, continued for many yeares most resolutely their ancient Lyturgie,<note place="margin">Hist. gen. Hist. &amp; Roderic. Tolet.</note> which was ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by them the <hi>Mosorabique office,</hi> because the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians mixt with Arabians (which in those dayes pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest
<pb facs="4"/> a good part of Spaine, had obserued it from the time of <hi>Isodore Archbishop of Seuill, and of Hildefonse Archbishop of Tolledo.</hi> At the length, <hi>Gregory the</hi> 7, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pope, <hi>Alphonsus the</hi> 6, who recouered <hi>Tolledo</hi> from the <hi>Saracens,</hi> at the earnest request of the French queen, constrain'd his Cleargy, after many debatings of the matter, to condescend to the Roman rites, yet could he not so farre preuaile against an inveterate custome, as wholly to extirpate it, but that at this day the <hi>Mosora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bique office</hi> is vs'd in some Churches and Chappels v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon certaine festiuals. Neither is this done without the consent and allowance of the Pope himselfe,<note place="margin">Bell. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Mis. c. <hi>18.</hi>
      </note> who permits (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confesseth) not onely the <hi>Mose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabique Missall</hi> in <hi>Tolledo,</hi> but also the <hi>Ambrosian</hi> in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Saint <hi>Ambrose,</hi> in <hi>Millaine</hi> where he was bishop, <hi>Basils and Chrysostomes in Rome, and other parts of Italy,</hi> in fauour of the <hi>Grecians,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Roccha in bibl. Vatican. p. <hi>162.</hi>
      </note> which reside there; and another suppos'd to be <hi>Hieromes</hi> in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> as being of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Roman Missall is not absolutely necessary to consecrate the Eucharist. Thus did the Gregorian Missall get ground wheresoeuer the Pope did inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle; for as touching <hi>England,</hi> howsoeuer <hi>Gregory</hi> gaue <hi>Austen</hi> the Monke liberty to vse his owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in establishing divine seruice in that Island, yet one may guesse how easie a matter it was for the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Liturgie to find welcome entertainment there, when such a trusty servant of the Popes, and one so af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the Romane ceremonies as was this <hi>Austen,</hi> (though withstood by the Brittish clergy) was receiued by many of the kings of the land, with such applause.</p>
   <p>The <hi>second reformation</hi> noted by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> was of <hi>Gregory the</hi> 7,<note place="margin">De consec. dist. <hi>5.</hi> can. In die.</note> who liued about the yeare 1200, and as
<pb facs="4"/> himselfe confesseth <hi>reformed,</hi> or rather deformed the <hi>Church offices.</hi> For hee which shall with an equall eye compare the Missals which from his time haue raigned in the Church, with those which sure registers doe certifie vs to haue beene vsed in the daies of <hi>Gregory the</hi> 1, may perhaps see these later to resemble them some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in the outward gestures, and forme of words, but to be destitute both of their simplicity, (wherein nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Masses for the dead, nor rubicks the directions for the superfluous ceremonies now vs'd, are to be found) as also depriued of the soul and reason which they had, which was, that the people did pray with the Pastour,<note place="margin">Greg. lib. <hi>7.</hi> epist. <hi>56.</hi> &amp; l. <hi>11.</hi> ep. <hi>56.</hi>
      </note> nor onely pray together, but communicate too, as out of <hi>Gregory</hi> himselfe may be gathered. Nay how many things were then vsed to a quite contrary purpose then they were afterwards, which if my Preface might not seeme to swell with bils of accusation, I could easily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Pag.</hi> 52.</note> For what could that phrase imply <hi>sacrificiū lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> this sacrifice of praise, &amp;c: but an Eucharistical sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of praise and thankesgiuing for the redemption of our soules purchased by the crosse of Christ, which is now wrested by the Priest to a propitiatory sacrifice for sinne, meriting a Iayle-deliuery out of Purgatory? To what end was that which followes,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>53.</hi> Aug. de ciuit dei lib. <hi>22.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>memoriam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerantes,</hi> honouring the memory, &amp;c: instituted, but to commemorate the Saints (saith <hi>Austen</hi>) as men of God which in their confessions ouercame the world, and not to invocate them, which now is directed by new additions, wholly to their merits? In what sense could the Priest,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Pap.</hi> 55.</note> speaking of the oblation in the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, say, <hi>vt nobis corpus &amp; sanguis fiat,</hi> that it may bee made vnto vs the body and blood, &amp;c: if <hi>opus operatum,</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/> (which is the onely string now harp'd vpon by the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites) were then thought security enough for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>57.</hi>
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, Arist. de Memor. &amp; Reminisc. c. <hi>1.</hi> Pag. <hi>79.</hi>
      </note> and no farther seale of the Spirit required to make it good? why was <hi>vnde memores,</hi> wherfore being mindfull, &amp;c: placed after the consecration, if Christ were in those dayes thought to be locally present in the Sacrament, seeing memory is a facultie busied about things absent and not present? How could <hi>supra quae &amp;c: respicere digneris ac accepta habere,</hi> vpon which things let it please thee to looke with a propitious and fauourable countenance, &amp;c: be applyed to the sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Christ, seeing the Priest is no more ambitious then to procure it as good acceptatiō with God as the sacrifice of <hi>Abel</hi> had,<note place="margin">Cassand. Liturg. cap <hi>8.</hi>
      </note> and Saint <hi>Basils Liturgy</hi> referres it onely to the offerings to the poore? Lastly in what congruity of speech could <hi>Gregory</hi> or any other haue inserted these Phrases into the Missall,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Pag.</hi> 80. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 96.</note>
      <hi>Quotquot sūpseri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> all we which shall take, &amp;c: or <hi>Quod ore sumpsimus,</hi> that we haue taken, &amp;c: if the Priest alone had commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated in those dayes, whereas now the Priest forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himselfe what he is, vsurpes the Phrase of an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour or King, and saith <hi>We</hi> in the plurall, as if he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out more associates were in saying a priuate Masse in danger to make a riot.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ius <hi>5.</hi> praefat. Rom. breuiar. reformat. Praefat. offic. B. Mar. Virg.</note>The third correction of the Roman Missall mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> is that of <hi>Pius Quintus,</hi> who finding the Roman seruice bookes so fraught with <hi>things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine and inconvenient</hi> (as he tearmes them) that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most all Primmers, yea the Latine too were stuffed full with vaine errors of superstitions, he set the <hi>Tridentine Councell</hi> on worke, to reforme both the <hi>Breviarie</hi> and <hi>Missall.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Decret Pii <hi>5.</hi> ad Missal. Trid.</note> But how these new Missalls of the Tridentine
<pb facs="5"/> correction were accepted of in the world, may be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stioned. For to omit those parts which either had sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, or did never vndergoe the papall yoke,<note place="margin">Ierem. Patriare. constant. Resp. <hi>1.</hi> ad Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manos c <hi>13.</hi> Vers. a Grid. Fabritio. Posse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>in. in Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parat. sacr. verb. Maronitae c. <hi>11. 12, 13, 14, 15.</hi>
      </note> al which haue proper Liturgies of their owne, as the <hi>Grecians</hi> which on common dayes vse the ancient Liturgie of <hi>Chrysostome,</hi> on festivalls that of <hi>Basil,</hi> the <hi>Cophti</hi> in <hi>Aegypt</hi> which vse the Liturgie of <hi>Seuerus Patriarch of Alexandria.</hi> The <hi>Maronites</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> which stick to the <hi>Liturgies of Peter, Iames, and Sixtus,</hi> the <hi>Habassines, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menians, Moscovians,</hi> all which haue their proper and distinct offices as Geographers doe relate,<note place="margin">Thevet. Cosmog.</note> the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants within the hemisphere of Popery, though they had long before giuen passage to the <hi>Gregorian Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,</hi> and swallowed downe most of the errors, which in processe of time crept into it without difficultie, yet when the Pope calld their old copies into the inquisiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and would with an high <hi>Mandamus</hi> force new edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon them, they began to start somewhat at the motion. <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Germanie</hi> indeed, made no resistance the Clergie of the one being a profest servant to the Pope, the other through opposition to the Protestant more plyant, the maine repugnancies were in <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and those vpon severall grounds. The Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards hauing intermixt the vse of the Gregorian of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice with the <hi>Mosorabique</hi> in some places, and general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly almost throughout made a medly of them both, were much discontented that such showers of innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (as they conceau'd them) should poure down on a suddaine vpon their land and wash away those stepps which they had beene accustomed in their blind devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to trace. <hi>Philip</hi> therefore, the father of him that now raigneth, receauing sundry complaints of this
<pb facs="6"/> matter from his subiects, deputed certaine to consider of the businesse, and in the end solicited <hi>Pius 5,</hi> by <hi>Ludo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicus de Torres</hi> a clearke of the Apostolicall sea to miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate somewhat that rigorous decree of the Councell,<note place="margin">Vide Decret. Pij <hi>5.</hi> &amp; Greg. <hi>13.</hi> init. Missall. Trident.</note> which forced a new Missall vpon his Clergie. Which request the Pope forthwith yeelded vnto, dispensing, that for a great part, they should follow the vse of the Church of <hi>Tolledo;</hi> and this grant his successor <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13, enlarged not only with sundry additions touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the holydaies, but also with an exposition, that whereas the Provinces of <hi>Spaine</hi> singly were nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the former decree, his intent and meaning was that the benefit of this dispensation should extend also to the <hi>Ilands</hi> and <hi>Indies</hi> subiect to the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi> As for <hi>France,</hi> it renouncing the authoritie of the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentine</hi> Councell as being neither lawfully summoned nor iustly proceeding, but manifestly violating the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the French Church,<note place="margin">
         <hi>See</hi> Les libertes de l'eglise Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane.</note> could never bee induced to receaue formally the <hi>Missall</hi> corrected by it. But how much the more resolutly the eight Parlements of the kingdome and the <hi>Sorbone</hi> schoole (which are the propps and pillers of the French libertie) did keepe this Councel from being incorporated amongst the edicts of the land, by so much the more eagerly, did the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats sollicite the Princes in the behalfe of it. And at length, perceauing that they prevailed little in their suit, being resisted with no lesse reason then authority, they invented a new plot to effect their enterprise.<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>chel. prefat. ad decret. Eccles. Gallican.</note> For hauing procured Congye to call Synods in every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular diocesse, they by a wile effected that in each Province by it selfe, which in an vnited assembly of the three estates they could not doe. Each of these Synods
<pb facs="6"/> was begunne with this profession. <hi>Also all other things deliuered, defined, and declared by the sacred Canons, and Oecumenicall Councell, especially the holy Tridentine Synod I doe vndoubtedly receaue and professe &amp;c.</hi> In these more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over they did establish the Missall and Brevearies cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Councell of Trent,<note place="margin">Bochel. lib. <hi>1.</hi> tit. <hi>9.</hi>
      </note> as may appeare by the Councell of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> celebrated in the yeare 1583. That of <hi>Burges,</hi> 1584. That of <hi>Rouen,</hi> 1581. That of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux,</hi> 1582. That of <hi>Aix,</hi> 1585. Yet are not these Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall decrees touching the Missall, of such validitie, that they are field authenticke farther then the Clergy out of a voluntary subscription or particular respects to their Bishop shall condescend to admit them, as is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident by a suit commenced by the Canons of the Church of the <hi>holy Trinitie in Angiers,</hi> against the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of the same place, for changing by his decree the <hi>Breviary</hi> vsed formerly in that citie, and introducing the corrected <hi>Tridentine,</hi> where they procured of the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> an inhibition against the Bishop,<note place="margin">Ex curiae Paris. Regestis. an. <hi>M.DCIII.</hi>
      </note> whereby he was forbidden to alter any thing in the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of divine service, without the speciall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the King. As also may bee gathered by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Missall which my author followeth, with the Tridentine, wherein we may discerne some differences which notwithstanding being not very materiall, I thought good to insert into my translation onely the <hi>Tridentine,</hi> both for that it is most generally receiued by our adversaries; as also least in transporting my author out of his natiue lists (where the <hi>Goliah</hi> he is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke appearing in his French habit is not alike vallued as at home) I should be thought to make him encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an enemy alreadie slaine in the censure of his spec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators,
<pb facs="7"/> or to gaine the spoiles where there is made no resistance.</p>
   <p>Out of that which hath beene already delivered tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the beginning and progresse of the <hi>Romane Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie,</hi> may an answer be drawne to satisfie those which conceaue a dislike in our common praier booke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they finde many things the same in them both, perswading themselues that this conclusion might frō thence be deduced, that our service booke is nothing else but the popish Liturgie translated.<note place="margin">An Apolog. of Brownists. p. 38.</note> For the <hi>Missall</hi> was not (as I haue shew'd) brought in at once, both in respect of the parts and of the abuses annext to them. The parts some of them are takē out of the Scriptures, and introduced by the Fathers in the purer age of the Church, others crept in with their abuses in after times. Now whatsoever is found in this Missall which we also haue admitted into our Church booke, being as it is now cleared from all superstition, may evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be demonstrated, both to haue his foundation in the Scriptures, and to haue beene vsed also by the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church, and that within the space of 600 yeares after our Saviour. That<note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 5. 2. Tim. 4.18. Heb. 13.21. Theod. hist. l. 2 c. 24. Soz. lib. 3. c. 19. where they relate how, when at the ending of Psalmes the Orthodoxe Christians did say, <hi>Gloria patri &amp; filio &amp; sp sancto,</hi> the Arians turned it thus, <hi>Gloria patri, per filium, in sp. sancto.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Gloria patri &amp; filio,</hi> Glory bee to the Father, is of this condition, the Scripture phrase iustifies it on the one part, and <hi>Sozomen, Theodoret,</hi> and <hi>Basil</hi> on the other. That<note n="b" place="margin">It is taken partly from the forme of saluting amongst the Iewes, Ruth. 2 4. Iud. 6. as Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n on the 132. Psal. saith religious men in his daies vsed, <hi>Deo gratias,</hi> and S. Hierome in the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e of Paulina, that in call ng together the Virgins, she vsed this word <hi>Alleluia:</hi> &amp; Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine, l. 2. de Miss. c. 16. that Nunnes in saluting one another in their Nunneries say <hi>Ave Maria.</hi> Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tly from the 2. Tim. 4.22. as Cassander thinketh. Liturg. p. 42. Chrysost. <hi>Vbi nos c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>pimus lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ui, cum sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>bs respondet.</hi> in 1. Cor. hom. 36.</note>
      <hi>Dominus vobiscum,</hi> the Lord be with you, &amp;c. is the same, the Bible witnesseth for
<pb facs="7"/> the first, and <hi>Chrysostome</hi> for the second. That<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 2.14. Bel. de Miss. l. 2 c. 16. Innoc. l. 2. de Myst. Miss, c. 20.</note>
      <hi>Gloria in excelsis:</hi> Glory to God on high, &amp;c. is no lesse, we haue the Angels song at the birth of our Saviour, the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rosolymitan Liturgie, and <hi>Innocent</hi> the third to testifie. For<note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Coloss. 3.2. Chrysost.</hi> Quid sacis o homo, no promisisti sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doti qui dixit sursum corda, &amp; dixisti habemus ad dominum? <hi>Homil. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist. Aug.</hi> Quod in sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis fidelium. dicitur, vt sursū corda habeamus ad dominum, munus est domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, de quo mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ipsi domino Deo nostro gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias à Sacerdote, post h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nc vocem quibus hoc di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur, admone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur &amp; dignum &amp; iustum esse respondet. <hi>de bono persev. c. 13.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Sursum corda:</hi> Let vs lift vp our hearts on high, &amp;c. We haue <hi>Paul, Chrysostome,</hi> and <hi>Austin.</hi> For <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> sanctus &amp;c.</hi> the Angels hymne, the Jewes canticle, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d the Liturgies of <hi>Basil,</hi> and <hi>Chrysostome.</hi> For<note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23. Chemnit. exam. Conc. Trid. part. 2. c. 4.</note>
      <hi>Qui pri die quam pateretur:</hi> The day before he suffered, &amp;c. The Apostles owne words, and <hi>Chemnitius</hi> opinion, that it was inserted into the Canon in the yeare 110. Lastly, for the<note n="g" place="margin">Es. 6.3 Theodoret attributes the beginning of this custome to Diodorus and Flavianus. lib. 2. hist. c. 24. where he saith, <hi>Hi primi in duas partes divisi coetibus psalmos accinentium, instituerunt alternis Davidicam melodiam decantare, quod Antiochiae fieri coeptum pervagatum vs{que}, qua{que} est, &amp; ad fines orbis terrarum perve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit.</hi> And Basil. ad cler. Neoces. <hi>Et nunc quidem in duas partes divisialternis succinentes psallunt.</hi> To which may be ioyned, <hi>Corpus Domini nostri Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>u &amp;c.</hi> which besides the congruity which it hath with sundry phrases of the Scriptures, Phil. Mornay acknowledgeth it to haue been vsed in Gregory the greats time. lib. 1. de Miss. c. 5.</note> manner of singing the verses of the Psalmes interchangeably we may alleage the Angelicall melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in <hi>Esay,</hi> and also the testimony of <hi>Theodoret</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sill.</hi> These are the principall parts which so farre as I haue obserued. (besides the creede and the Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, of whose antiquitie there is no doubt) are found both in our <hi>English Lyturgie,</hi> and this <hi>Roman Missall,</hi> here examined, which being not intēded by the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of our Seruice booke to bee a translation of the Masse booke, but onely inserted as prayers vsed by the Fathers, and deriued out of holy writ, and being by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of their paucity, as also for that they are now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of the<note n="*" place="margin">Arist. l. 2. phys. text. 11. vnde collig. Forma dat nomen &amp; esse.</note> forme of Popery, which is superstition, vnsufficient to denominate, I see no reason why wee<note n="e" place="margin">Es. 6.3. Mat. 21.9. Liturg. Basil. Chrysos.</note>
      <pb facs="8"/> should be branded to haue a Masse booke translated. Nor could the reformers of our Religion bee heerein iustly taxed, though they reiected not all things which they found practised in Poperie;<note place="margin">Solem è mundo tollere videtur, qui vsum prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abusum tollit Cic.</note> For first they did but what Christian libertie warranted them to doe, which ties vs not to abrogate a good or indifferent thing for the abuse, but rather to preserue the substance, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to pare off the corruption. Secondly, they did no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> but what necessitie in a manner constrained them to doe. For seeing it is agreed by all parties, that the Church of God is termed <hi>Catholike</hi> or vniuersall, not in respect of <hi>place</hi> only, but of <hi>time</hi> also; &amp; that there is no one argument more buz'd into the eares of men by the Papists, then that we professe a new and vpstart Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion whereof there are no prints extant in antiquitie, why should we depriue our selues of such a <hi>medium,</hi> to proue the cōformity of our disciplin to that of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue Church, as is the forme and manner of seruing God in publique, established amongst vs, because the Papists in many of the same things are the Fathers Apes. Neither doth this any way helpe the Papists, or may they therefore boast that their Missall is the same Liturgie as was anciently in vse, because many of the words and sentences are the same, any more then he, which taking the Image of <hi>Iupiter</hi> wrought by the hand of a cunning artificer,<note place="margin">Sim. Iren.</note> and dissoluing it, makes thereof the image of a dog, can brag that in his custody he hath the excellent portraicture of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> because hee hath the matter or stuffe of which that supposed deity was formerly composed.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>E. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>