<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102468_Bo1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15342</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20088</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102468</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatie of iustification. Founde emong the writinges of Cardinal Pole of blessed memorie, remaining in the custodie of M. Henrie Pyning, chamberlaine and general receiuer to the said cardinal, late deceased in Louaine. Item, certaine translations touching the said matter of iustification, the titles whereof, see in the page folowing</title>
                 <author>Pole, Reginald</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fowler (Fouler), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 98, 2, 77, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="89"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>TO the intente, Christian Reader, thou maiest vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande, both that, the doctrine of Mans Iustification, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto thee in this Treatie, is consonant and agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the assured and vndoubted doctrine of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes Catholique Churche, by long and mature deliberation, by most exact and diligent<note n="*" place="margin">Aboute this onely mater, the Bisshops and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, had lxxx. seue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges and conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, before they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</note> trauaile, expressed and sette forth to the worlde, in the late General Councell holden at Trent: and also that the saied moste Reuerende and Learned As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblie of Bisshops, Doctours, and Fathers, defined nothing in this matter, but suche as most expressely agreeth with the holy Scriptures, and consent of the Auncient Fathers, here in this Treatie laied before thee: to this intente I saie, and for these causes, thou haste here to this Treatie annexed, the Sixt Session of the saied Councell, with the Canons of the same, translated into English, worde for worde: In the which, the whole doctrine of Iustification, is most exactly, plainely, and withal shortly, taught, declared, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>