<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO SIR HENRY CROFTS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102573_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09644</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19909</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102573</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO SIR HENRY CROFTS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vertues anatomie. Or A compendious description of that late right honorable, memorable, and renowned Bedfordshire lady, the Lady Cheany, of Tuddington. By Charles Pierse</title>
                 <author>Pierse, Charles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>TO SIR HENRY CROFTS.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F that my lines may be at all respected,</l>
   <l>And not for their vnworthinesse reiected,</l>
   <l>Which, though too meane, faine would remember yet</l>
   <l>The loue I owe, which many doe forget,</l>
   <l>The seruice and the dutie which desires,</l>
   <l>(Though your desarts farre greater worth requires)</l>
   <l>To yeeld some thankes by meane endeauors prest,</l>
   <l>You in your better iudgement know the rest:</l>
   <l>From Shepheards cells, expect no more to finde,</l>
   <l>Then what may please the best contented minde.</l>
   <l>Our tables are not furnisht with such cost</l>
   <l>For sumptuous cheere, or lofty faire to boast:</l>
   <l>Such as we haue we giue, on trust we goe not,</l>
   <l>To entertaine you, Sir, with that we owe not:</l>
   <l>Nor yet by stealth doe seeke to winne your loue,</l>
   <l>To beare the name of that we cannot proue:</l>
   <l>Though intertainment, house and cheere be small,</l>
   <l>The heart is true which doth inuite you all;</l>
   <l>And will in better wishes more content yee,</l>
   <l>Then in this booke my barraine braine hath lent yee.</l>
   <l>I cannot fly in learned loftie phrases,</l>
   <l>But doe adorne my stile with truth, not praises:</l>
   <l>Nor passe I for conceits, which are precise,</l>
   <l>But only write to please the vertuous wise:</l>
   <l>For I haue read, that true and noble mindes,</l>
   <l>The best content in willing natures findes.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="8"/>Honor receiues no fall, by want of skill</l>
   <l>If Gentle doome doe fall vpon my quill:</l>
   <l>Then, worthy Knight, since that you are some ayme,</l>
   <l>And not the least hopes that my Muse doth clayme,</l>
   <l>Accept and pardon what amisse is found,</l>
   <l>That built this frame vpon so weake a ground;</l>
   <l>Nor let not duety, wanting learned lore,</l>
   <l>Be counted folly, nor my seruice poore;</l>
   <l>But be receiued, wherein it comes farre short,</l>
   <l>Respecting more my will, then my desart.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>