<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right worshipfull and godly Gentlewoman Maistres Mary Harrys Wyddow.</title>
           <author>Y., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102773_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01300</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11422</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102773</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right worshipfull and godly Gentlewoman Maistres Mary Harrys Wyddow.</title>
                 <author>Y., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A comfortable sermon of faith, in temptations and afflictions : Preached at S. Botulphes wythout Aldersgate in London, the .xv. of Februarye. 1573. By Maister VVilliam Fulke, Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Fulke, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Awdely (Sampson), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right worshipfull <hi>and godly Gentlewoman</hi> Maistres Mary Harrys <hi>Wyddow.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue alwaies liked well (as you know) the plaine dealing of our friend Maister Fulke wyth the Scriptures of God, which is so much the more commendable in him, as he is berter able to make a shew in the perswasible wordes of mans wisedome, if he were disposed, For although he be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of no kynde of learning, by which a man might set forth him selfe vnto the world, and vnderstandeth more straunge languages then a great number of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: yet when he sheweth the testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of God, he taketh not vpon hym to know any thing as saint Paule sayrh, but Iesus Christ, and him crucified. For by this foolishnes of preachyng the wyse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, power, and goodnes of God appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth greatest, and woorketh most essectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="3"/>
in them that are the children of God. And therefore I maruail not, if you which haue heard hym and others that vse the same simplicitie in teaching, do couet ro heare them still, where as many are more desirous of variety to delight their itching eares, then carefull of sound doctrine, to conuert their synfull hartes. But where as you wer not onely content to haue heard this Sermon preached once at Saynt Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulphes without Aldersgate in London, but that you did instantly desire to haue the copy thereof, that you might reade it often: As it was godly for you to require it, so it was hard for me to obtayne it. For our friende wyll sooner be intreated to preach ten Sermons, then to wryte one. Neuerthelesse at the length by many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions hee was ouercome to put it in writing, so that I got the copy out of hys handes, which now I send vnto you, not doubting but you wyll vse it, both to the renuing of your own remembraunce, and
<pb facs="3"/>
to the profit of many others.</p>
   <p>I neede not to adde any commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the matter, especially to you which knoweth it, and as to any others, I wysh them first to reade it, and then to iudge of it as they shal finde it. Thus I commit you to God.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to commaund in the Lord. I. Y.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>