<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The exposition of certaine
termes or principles of
Geometrie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102547_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16221</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3146</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102547</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The exposition of certaine
termes or principles of
Geometrie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>M. Blundevile his exercises : containing sixe treatises, the titles wherof are set down in the next printed page: which treatises are verie necessarie to be read and learned of all yoong gentlemen that haue not bene exercised in such disciplines, and yet are desirous to hau knowledge as well in cosmographie, astronomie, and geographie, as also in the arte of navigation, in which arte it is impossible to profite without the helpe of these, or such like instructions. To the furtherance of which arte of navigation, the said M. Blundevile speciallie wrote the said treatises and of meere good will doth dedicate the same to all the young gentlemen of this realme</title>
                 <author>Blundeville, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 350 leaves, 3 folded plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="exposition_of_geometrical_terms">
   <pb facs="136"/>
   <pb n="127" facs="136"/>
   <head>The exposition of certaine
termes or principles of
Geometrie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Inding to treate of the principles of
Cosmographie, and especially of the
Sphere, I thinke it good first to expound
vnto you certaine termes of Geometry,
without the which the vnlearned shall
hardly vnderstand the Contents of this
Treatise, which tearmes are certaine
principles of Geometrie, called defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:
For there are but thrée kinds of
principles, whereon the demonstration of all Geometricall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions
dependeth: that is, definitions, petitions, and maxims,
but I mind here to deale onely with certaine definitions, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
I will set downe as many as I thinke néedful for this purpose,
in such order as followeth.</p>
   <p>1 A point called in Latine <hi>punctus,</hi> is
a thing supposed to be indiuisible, hauing
neither length, breadth, nor deapth, as the
point or pricke a.</p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>2 A line called in Lataine linea, is a
supposed length, hauing neither breadth nor
thicknesse, as the line a. b.</p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>3. The ends or bounds of a line, are
two points, and of lines some be right, and
some be crooked.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="137"/>
      <figure>
</figure>
   </p>
   <p>4 A right line is that which goeth right
from one point to another, and not bowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
as doth the line <hi>c. d.</hi> but so straight as is
possible, as the line <hi>a. b.</hi> Againe the crooked
line is either a whole Circle, or portion of a
Circle, or else goeth winding in and out, as
a serpent called in Latine <hi>Linea tortuosa,</hi>
or else winding about like the shell of a
Snaile, called of the Latines, <hi>linea Spira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi>
as these figures here doe shew.</p>
   <figure>
      <p>A whole Circle</p>
   </figure>
   <figure>
      <p>A Portion of a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</p>
   </figure>
   <figure>
      <p>Linea tortuosa.</p>
   </figure>
   <figure>
      <p>Linea spiralis.</p>
   </figure>
   <p>5 Superficies or vpperface, is that
which onely hath length and breadth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
deapth, which is twofould, that is to
say, plaine and crooked.</p>
   <p>6 The bounds of superficies are lines.</p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>7 A plaine superficies is that which ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
straight betwixt his lines, as the figure
a. &amp; a crooked superficies is that which goeth
bowing and lyeth not straight betwixt his
lines as the figure <hi>b.</hi> Againe superficies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
considered in an hollow body, as a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell,
tunne, or vault, may be deuided into
two other kinds, that is Conuexe, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caue,
for the vpper part of such vault is said
to be conuex, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> inward part cancaue as
the figure <hi>b.</hi> sheweth.</p>
   <figure>
      <p>Conuex. Concaue.</p>
   </figure>
   <p>8 A plaine Angle is when two lines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
drawne vpon a plaine superficies not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly
one against another, but so as by mée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
or touching one an other in one selfe
point, they may make a plaine Angle, as the
Angle <hi>a.</hi>
      <figure>
</figure>For if two lines be drawne directly
one against another, though they méete in
one point, yet they make no Angle, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
one selfe line as the two lines <hi>a. b.</hi> mée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
in the point <hi>c.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
      <p>Right. Crooked. Mixt.</p>
   </figure>
   <p>9 Of plaine Angles, some are called
right line angles, because that both the lines
whereof it consisteth are right, and some are
<pb n="128" facs="137"/>
called crooked line angles, because that both
lines are crooked, &amp; some are said to be mixt,
because the one line is crooked and the other
right, as you may perceiue by the thrée sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
shapes thereof made in the Margent.</p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>10 If one right line standing vpon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
right line do make two equall angles,
that is to say, of ech side one, then eyther of
those Angles is a right Angle, and the line
so standing vpon his fellow, is called the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular
or plumbe line, as the line <hi>a. b.</hi>
standing vpon the line <hi>c. d.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>11 A blunt Angle, is that which is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
then a right Angle, as the Angle <hi>e.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>12 A sharpe Angle, is that which is lesser
then a right Angle, as f. so as there be in all
thrée Angles, that is right, blunt, and sharpe,
in Latine <hi>rectus, obtusus, &amp; acutus:</hi> And
besides these Angles, there be also certaine
Sphericall, that is to say, round Angles,
which consist of two circular lines, drawne
vppon a Sphericall superficies, which doe
crosse one another in some point, eyther
rightly, or obliquely: if rightly, then they
make right Angles, on ech side of the point
where they crosse, as the figure <hi>E.</hi> sheweth,
if obliquely then they make sharpe Angles of
the inside, and blunt Angles on the out side
of the point, where they crosse as the figure
<hi>F.</hi> doth partly shew, for such Angles cannot
be so well described in <hi>Plano,</hi> as vpon the
superficies of some Sphericall body.</p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>13 A terme called in Latine <hi>terminus,</hi> is
the bound or linute of any thing, as points
are the bounds of lines, &amp; lines the bounds
of superficieses, and superficieses y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bounds of
a body, which is that which hath imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely,
but not materially, both lēgth, bredth,
and depth, and if such body haue many faces
<pb facs="138"/>
or sides, then it is bounded with many su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficieses,
as the figure <hi>g.</hi> made like a sixe
square dye. But if such body be round as a
bowle, Sphere, or Globe, then it is bounded
or couered with one superficies onely, as the
figure <hi>H.</hi> doth shewe.</p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>14 A figure is that which is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
within one bound, or many bounds.</p>
   <figure>
      <p>Circumference.</p>
   </figure>
   <p>15 A Circle is a plaine figure bounded
with one circular line, which is called the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference,
vnto the which as many right
lines as are drawne from the point standing
in the midst, are all equall one to the other,
that is to say, one is as long as another, as
the figure <hi>I.</hi> here doth shew.</p>
   <figure>
      <p>diam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ter.</p>
   </figure>
   <p>16 And the middle point of a Circle is
called the Center, as the point <hi>A.</hi> in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
<hi>I.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>17 The Diameter of a Circle, is a
right line passing through the Center, from
one side of the Circumference to the other,
which deuideth the Circle into two equall
parts, as the line <hi>B. C.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>18 A Semicircle is a figure, contayned
within the Diameter and halfe the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
of a Circle as the figure <hi>D. C. E.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
      <p>The cord.</p>
   </figure>
   <p>19 The portion of a Circle, is a part of
a Circle, greater or lesser than the Semicir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,
as the figures <hi>F.</hi> and <hi>G.</hi> doe shewe, the
right line in eyther of which figures is called
in Latine <hi>chorda,</hi> in English the string, and
the Circular line in Latine is called <hi>arcus</hi>
in English the bowe, but the Diameter is
alwayes the greatest cord in any Circle.</p>
   <figure>
      <p>The cord.</p>
   </figure>
   <p>20 Right line figures, are those which
are bounded with right lines.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="129" facs="138"/>
21 Triangles or thrée cornerd figures,
are those which are bounded with thrée right
lines as the figure <hi>H.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>22 Foure square figures, are those
which are bounded with foure right lines,
as the figure <hi>I.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>23 Many square figures, are those
which are bounded with more right lines
then foure as <hi>K.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>24 Of Triangles or thrée cornerd fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures,
there be sixe kindes, whereof the first
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s called <hi>Isoplurus,</hi> hauing thrée equall
sides and thrée equal Angles as <hi>A.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>25 The second is called <hi>Isosceles,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing
but two equall sides and angles as <hi>B.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>26 The thirde called <hi>scalenos</hi> hauing
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o side equall, one with the other, but one
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>horter or longer then another as <hi>C.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>27 The fourth is called <hi>Ort hogonius,</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>auing one right Angle, as <hi>D.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>28 The fift is called <hi>ampligonius,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
it hath one blunt Angle, as <hi>E.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>29 The sixt is called <hi>oxigonius,</hi> because
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> hath thrée sharpe Angles, but not equall
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>des as <hi>F.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>
      <pb facs="139"/>
30 Of foure square figures there is one
iust foure square, hauing foure equall sides,
and is right angled as <hi>G.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>31 Another is called a long Square,
which is right angled, but not hauing foure
equall sides, as <hi>H.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>32 There is another called <hi>rombus,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
is to say a Turbut, in shape like to Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant,
which hath foure equall sides, but is
not right angled, as <hi>I.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>33 There is another called <hi>romboides,</hi>
which though it hath sides and Angles one
right against another, yet hath it neither
foure equall sides, nor yet is right angled,
as <hi>K.</hi>
   </p>
   <figure>
</figure>
   <p>34 All other kinds of foure squares are
called <hi>trapezia,</hi> as <hi>L.</hi> or such like.</p>
   <figure>
      <p>Right line paralels.</p>
   </figure>
   <figure>
      <p>Circuler paralels.</p>
   </figure>
   <p>35 Paralels are two right lines equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
distant one from another, which béeing
drawne foorth infinitely, would neuer tou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
or méete one another in any part, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
two lines <hi>M. N.</hi> And though the lines be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
circular, yet if they be equally distant in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
places one from another, they are also call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
paralels, as the figure <hi>P.</hi> sheweth, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
though the lines be winding in and out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
Serpents, yet if they be equally distant in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
places one from another, they are paralel
as well as if they were right lines as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
<hi>Q.</hi> sheweth.</p>
   <figure>
      <p>Serpentine paralels.</p>
   </figure>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>