<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102567_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09947</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20204</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102567</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godly and holsom preseruatyue against disperacio [n] : at al times necessarye for the soule: but then chiefelye to be vsed and ministred when the deuil doth assault vs most fiersely, &amp; doth approcheth nieste</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 <publisher>Copland, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kele, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hys preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue (gētle rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der) is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for thy pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite: y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure maist chose oute suche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable sentences as may bothe staye thi owne cōscience in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> time of tēptacion: &amp; also quiet othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s when y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Deuil shalbe busie with them.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2</note> For we be not ignoraunte of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thoughtes of satan, howe he continually furnisheth hym selfe to bende his ordinaunce agaynst mā. And now w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the cōsideratiō of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> greatnes &amp; multitude of syn Now with the terrour of death &amp; dampnaciō.<note place="margin">Ephe. 6</note> do labour to beate y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> buck let of fayth out of our han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,<note place="margin">1. Tess. 5</note> to strike y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> helmet of hope frō our head.<note place="margin">Ephr. 6</note> And to wrest frō vs the swerd of the spriit, which is gods word</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>But here christyan reader is thy swerd and buckeler deliuered vnto the, here is thy helmete put vppon thy heade here thou shalte find suche armoure and weapon, wherbi thou shalt both be able to withstand the force of oure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men enemy the Deuell: and also (by the counsell) to rescue others that they perysh not, Yea heare y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> shalt find choise of most comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table sentences, wherby mans cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>science may be stayed from damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable desperacion.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.</note>Watche therfore, stand sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faste in faithe, play the man, and be of good comfort.<note place="margin">Iacob. 4.</note> Resist the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uell, and he wyll flee frome the Not for feare of thy owne power strength or holynes: but for feare of Chryste: in whome by faythe thou art ingraffed,. For it is crist through whome god hathe geuen<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Cor. 15.</note>
      <pb facs="3"/> vs vyctory agaynst synne, deathe hell, &amp; the deuyll.<note place="margin">Acto. 4.</note> Nether is there ani other name vnder heuē geuen vnto man wherin we maye be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but the name of Iesus Christ our lorde. To whome with the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, and holye ghost, be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory. AMEN</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>