<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Introduction to the Dialogues.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102692_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01291</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11414</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102692</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Introduction to the Dialogues.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pandectes of the law of nations : contayning seuerall discourses of the questions, points, and matters of law, wherein the nations of the world doe consent and accord. Giuing great light to the vnderstanding and opening of the principall obiects, questions, rules, and cases of the ciuill law, and common law of this realme of England. Compiled by William Fulbecke</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wight, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 90 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>The Introduction to the <hi>Dialogues.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Gentleman by name <hi>Nomomathes,</hi> with the riches, fortunes &amp; reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes of this world very plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully furnished, being liberally minded, and willing that his foūtains should flow forth to the benefit of others,<note n="a" place="margin">Prouerb. 5. vers. 16.</note> being a great fauorer of learning, &amp; desirous by all means to increase &amp; aduāce it, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined &amp; kept with him continually in his house 3. learned men, &amp; greatly addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the studies of the laws; one of thē named <hi>Canonologus</hi> a Canonist, the other <hi>Codicgnostes</hi> a doctor of the ciuil law, and the third <hi>Anglonomophylax</hi> a Barrister, and professor of the cōmon law of this realm of England: of them he made great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, &amp; of their learning aboue all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane sciēces, as being most fit &amp; pertinēt to the guiding &amp; administration of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like affaires: and as the famous <hi>Cofimus, Medices,</hi> and <hi>Laurentius</hi> his nephew<note n="b" place="margin">Machia. lib. 7. &amp; 8. Flor. hist.</note>, did harbour in their houses at seuerall times, &amp; with many benefits pleasured the two excellent men and stars of learning <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silius
<pb facs="11"/> Facinus,</hi> and <hi>Iohannes Picus Miràndula,</hi> being in their houses the nurseries of good learning, as two faire flowers in their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral root &amp; as <hi>Cato</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Plut. in Cat.</note> the Vtican a lōg time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the family of Medices was known in Florence, or Florence was knowne by the name, had cōtinually in his cōpany 3. wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy philosophers <hi>Apollonides</hi> the Stoike, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius</hi> the Peripatetike, &amp; <hi>Cleanthes</hi> a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Phisitian, many times cōferring with thē, alwaies profiting by them: so this gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of whō I speak, reaping much good and benefite by the persons abouesaid did vse them exceeding kindly, &amp; many times proposed diuerse questions of the law vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, wherein he had good resolution; and hauing sequestred himselfe from the multitude of priuate affaires, wherwith he was often molested, hauing attained to a conuenient dispatch &amp; conclusiō of them, hee allotted certaine times of purpose for the hearing of matters of law handled and debated: and sometime in his parlor, and chamber, sometime in his garden, and gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, he would giue diligent eare &amp; atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to such disputation &amp; discourse, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="12"/> set downe certain rules, &amp; as it were, a good platforme of the exercise. The rules were but 2. in nūber, which were great in weight. 1. He willed thē to exclude all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuillng, to yeeld vnto the better reason, and with ioint indeuor to search out the truth of euery matter proposed: for he said that <hi>nimiùm altercando amittitur veritas.</hi> 2. Hee would not (sithence comparisons wer of al things most saucy and malepert) that they should enter into any disdainful compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the lawes which they professed, but should rather vse them as brethren, then as enemies, &amp; should reuerence the greatnes of knowledge, where they found it, &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the weaknes when they had discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it, without bitternesse of tongue or ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom of heart, assuring themselues that the meanest of these lawes might in some par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular things profite the greatest of these Lawyers: for as he obserued the sayings &amp; doings of <hi>Cato</hi> in stead of a Law, so one of <hi>Catoes</hi> sententious and iudicious oracles he had alwaies in his mouth. <hi>Alienā artē temerè ne contēnito:</hi> hauing by these rules as by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits bounded the order &amp; maner of their
<pb facs="12"/> conference, he proposed certain things di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctly, &amp; in order to be discussed, which were thus by him marshalled. Because in raūge of all humane affaires subiect to the contēplation of law, contracts haue frō an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient time bin the ground of vesting &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the property of things, hee would therfore first haue thē to begin with a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of cōtracts: &amp; because there be two things following after cōtracts concluded much in vse, namely, 1. a gift or graunt; 2. a bargain or sale, he would therefore of these two haue thē diligētly to argue: &amp; because gifts haue bin often made to raise &amp; create a tenure, his desire was that in the 4. place they should discourse of Seignories and seruices: &amp; for that grants or gifts be made sometime ioyntly, or by moities, he would haue them to speake somewhat of ioynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, or tenants in common: and because they that haue things by gift &amp; grant doe often exchange them, his minde was they should handle the nature &amp; manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes, and sithence the last disposing of all worldly things is by the last will &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament of the party, he therfore requested
<pb facs="13"/> them to be painfull herein: after as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cōueiances of lāds, which be in the realty he would haue them to proceed to personal things, as namely to treat of bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing and lending, and of the bailement or deliuery of goods and chattels: because such things were much in vse. And because these and the precedent matters were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times occasions of action, therefore he thought it conuenient that they should speake somewhat of the forme and maner of ordinary proceeding in matters of law, and when they had finished this taske a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouesaid, hee prayed them to discourse of penall and criminall matters, of common trespasses and wrongs, and other offences against the peace, the order of which hee would hereafter set downe. The method of their conference being thus digested, and respit of studie and deliberation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giuen, <hi>Nomomathes</hi> thus spake to <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicgnostes.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>