<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE YOVNG AND WORTHY KNIGHT, SIR IOHN HARE, SONNE AND heyre apparant to the Right Worshipfull Sir RALPH HARE of Stowe Hall in the County of Norfolke: And to the vertuous yong Lady, the Lady ELIZABETH his Wife; and to her brother, the hopefull yong Gentle∣man, Mr THOMAS COVENTRY, eldest Sonne to the Right Worshipfull his MAIESTIES Attorney Generall before mentioned. Long life, and good dayes, with in∣crease of all spirituall blessings, in heauenly things.</title>
           <author>Frewen, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102653_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01263</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11379</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102653</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE YOVNG AND WORTHY KNIGHT, SIR IOHN HARE, SONNE AND heyre apparant to the Right Worshipfull Sir RALPH HARE of Stowe Hall in the County of Norfolke: And to the vertuous yong Lady, the Lady ELIZABETH his Wife; and to her brother, the hopefull yong Gentle∣man, Mr THOMAS COVENTRY, eldest Sonne to the Right Worshipfull his MAIESTIES Attorney Generall before mentioned. Long life, and good dayes, with in∣crease of all spirituall blessings, in heauenly things.</title>
                 <author>Frewen, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine choise grounds, and principles of our Christian religion : with their seuerall expositions, set forth in way of questions, and answers: wherein the people of the parish of Northiham, in the county of Sussex, haue beene catechized, and instructed, for the settling o their hearts and mindes, in the mysteries of saluation, and for their better preparation to the Lord's Supper. Now published for their sakes, and for the futher vse of the Church of God. By Iohn Frewen, minister of the Word of God, in that particular congregation</title>
                 <author>Frewen, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Pott (Potts), Roger.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 384, 16 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>TO THE YOVNG AND WORTHY KNIGHT, <hi>SIR</hi> IOHN HARE, SONNE AND heyre apparant to the Right Worshipfull <hi>Sir</hi> RALPH HARE of <hi>Stowe Hall</hi> in the County of <hi>Norfolke:</hi> And to the vertuous <hi>yong Lady, the Lady</hi> ELIZABETH <hi>his Wife;</hi> and to her brother, the hopefull yong Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> THOMAS COVENTRY, eldest <hi>Sonne to the Right Worshipfull his</hi> MAIESTIES Attorney Generall before mentioned. Long life, and good dayes, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of all spirituall blessings, <hi>in heauenly things.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had finished the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Epistles (welbeloued in the Lord) I considerd with my selfe, that, seeing they were Principles, and grounds of Christianity, which I had expounded, and was ready to publish: I might doe some further seruice pleasing God, acceptable and profitable vnto you, (being as yet but nouices and younglings in Religion:) if in some speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="15"/> manner, I should commend them to your meditations.</p>
   <p>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>owsoeuer to you, Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> I am but a stranger, and in that respect, might haue been discouraged: yet such is, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies hath been mine vnfained loue &amp; good affection t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wards her, who now (by Gods prouidence) is become yours: that this could n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t hinder. For I cannot otherwise rest perswaded, but that all good offices of true loue now done to her, or vnto you for her sake, will as kindely in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uery degree be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, as if they directly aimed at your selfe alone.</p>
   <p>And, good Madame, doe you for your part, cherish by all good meanes, all good motions and affections in your kinde and louing Husband. And as it is a principall end of your Creation, to be an Helper: So in the feare of God, apply, and endeuour your selfe, to bee cheerefull, comfortable, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lpfull indeed. And as in all duties and respects which concerne this life: So especially in those things that concerne
<pb facs="15"/> Gods glory, and your owne saluation, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the good and saluation of such, as may any way belong vnto you, or depend vpon you.</p>
   <p>And for you (welbeloued <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Thomas</hi>) as you haue hitherto by your godly Parents, been carefully traded and trained vp in the feare and nurture of the Lord: and haue shewed your selfe docible, tractable, and towardly, (which I am able to report vpon some good experience,) by yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, by your gestures, by your speech, and by the course of your practices, making your selfe knowne, to haue vprightnes and good meaning in you without dissimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: According to that of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.11.</note>
      <hi>Pro. 20. Euen a child will make knowne by his conuersation, whether he be pure, and whether his worke bee right:</hi> So settl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> your s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lfe to grow forward in grace and goodnes, as in yeeres and dayes. And then, shall you be sure, as well as the an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, to be rewarded with saluation in the life to come, and honoured among all good
<pb facs="16"/> men with praise and estimation, whiles you are heere.</p>
   <p>To you all I say with <hi>Salomon, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastes 12.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.1.</note>
      <hi>Remember your Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the dayes of your youth, whiles the euill dayes come not,</hi> that is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore old age commeth. For you must know, that God requires the seruice of youth, as well as the seruice of old age. Nay, this, before the other. And if you looke into the Scripture, or into experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, you shall hardly finde any who haue accustomed themselues to vanity, and prophanenesse in the time of their youth, that doe become truely and vnfainedly repentant when they are old. As <hi>Ier. 13.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ier.</hi> 13.23.</note>
      <hi>Can the Blackamore change his skinne, or the Leopard his spots? then may yee also doe good, that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed to doe euill.</hi> And therefore <hi>Prou. 22.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 22.6.</note>
      <hi>Teach a childe in the trade of his way, and when hee is old, hee shall not depart from it.</hi> And <hi>Psalme 119.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 119 9.</note>
      <hi>Wherewith shall a young man
<pb facs="16"/> redresse his way? In taking heed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, according to thy Word.</hi> Thus you see, that the Word of God ought to bee the rule and direction of yong mens liues, as well as of those that are old. <hi>Let the Word of God therefore dwell in you plenteously in al wisdome,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.</note>
      <hi>&amp; spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall vnderstanding. Search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Psal.</hi> 1.2.</note>
      <hi>and take delight to meditate in them day and night:</hi> yea, <hi>make them the Lanterne for your feet,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.105.</note>
      <hi>and a light for your pathes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And not onely for my sake, and at my request; but for your owne good, and for the better settling and establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your hearts and minds in the truth, take a serious view of this little Treatise. Lay these Principles in your hearts, as a foundation for other higher points of Doctrine to bee builded vpon. Imprint them in your memories, bee zealous in the profession of them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being ashamed. <hi>Consider,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 7. 2. <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.17</note>
      <hi>what I say, and the Lord blesse you, and giue
<pb facs="17"/> you vnderstanding in all things, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort your hearts, and establish you in euery word and good worke.</hi> And so I take my leaue at <hi>Northiham</hi> in <hi>Sussex. September the 20. 1621.</hi> Resting</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all Christian duties, IOHN FREVVEN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>