<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen Readers, Health.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102439_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13377</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23685</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102439</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen Readers, Health.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tarltons newes out of purgatorie : Onely such a iest as his iigge, fit for gentlemen to laugh at an houre, &amp;c. Published by an old companion of his, Robin Goodfellow</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 <publisher>Newman, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 53, that is 52 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen Readers, <hi>Health.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, the Horse when hee is first handed to the warres, starteth at the cracke of euery peece; and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery coucht Launce is a censure of death to a fresh water Souldier: So fareth it with mee, for neuer before being in print I start at the sight of the Presse, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing not dared to looke into the open light, I feared with the Owle to fly before it be twylight: yet I haue heard others whose bookes haue past your view, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count you so fauorable, curteous and affable, shrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding euery scape with silence; that I presumed the rather to experience with them the hope of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours: which if I finde as they haue done, though I bee blinde Bayard, yet I will in the thickest of the mire plunge vp to the Saddle for your sakes. Virgill afore he wrote his <hi>Aeneidos,</hi> wrote his <hi>Culex;</hi> and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saide in trifles, afore he attempted in Triumphs. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can wrote <hi>Quaedam Lirica,</hi> before he began with <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumper Emathios plusquam Ciuilia campos.</hi> Roome was not builded on a day, and men that venter little, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard little: So gentlemen, I present you with a toy of Tarltons, called his newes out of Purgatory; which I
<pb facs="3"/>
desire you accept as curteously as I offer willing to to please: Though they be <hi>Crepundia</hi> yet reade them, and if you find any pleasant <hi>Facetia,</hi> or <hi>Quicquid Salis▪</hi> thinke all sauory, and so pleasde without being satiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally peremptory: for Momus will haue a mouth full of inuectiues, and Zoilus should not be Zoilus if hee were not squint eide. Therefore leauing their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours to the wordmongers of mallice that like the Vipers grew odious to their owne kinde, hoping of your curteous censure, I bid you farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>