<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader, health
in the Lorde.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1572</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102020_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00718</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10848</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102020</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader, health
in the Lorde.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An admonition to the Parliament</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stroud, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1572</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_Christian_reader">
   <pb facs="19"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader, health
in the Lorde.</head>
   <p>WE haue thoughte good, in this latter end of our
booke, for sondry consyderations, to certify you
(beloued brethrē) of the reasons that haue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
vs, who are the authors of these treatises, to kepe
back our names, and also to suppresse the name of the
Printer of them, because peraduenture it may seeme
strange otherwise, and also because we meane not by
our example to alow such as might abuse you w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> leud
matter vnder any such coulor. For we do vtterly mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> ther is not in euery cuntry more straight loking
to the Printers in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> respect, because our time is much
corrupted with ouer much license there in. Then thus
it is, that in deede we are the least able among many,
to speake of these matters: and therfore we wold not
haue it seeme by setting to our names, that we toke v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pō
our selues singulerly to teach any thing that none
other can doe, hath done, or doth, but we. And yet we
wold wish, and in the name of the Almightie doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
those y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e the greater giftes of God, shortly to
make some larger discourse, then hetherto, eyther we
or they haue, concerning these necessarie matters of
Christes church. Againe, thoughe these matters haue
ben resolued vpon already in al y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> best reformed chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches:
and also haue ben by sundry in this our coūtry,
in theyr sundrie lectures and sermons vrged: Yet he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
they are not allowed such fauour, as to be with
out perill any way propounded &amp; set forth. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
though we wil not refuse to put forth our selues
to perils for suche causes, yet we feared it woulde the
m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re exasperate and prouoke thē that we deale wyth
if we shoulde haue set to our names: besides that, we
feared lest we shoulde not yet, haue done wel to haue
betrayed our selues vnto them. And further, because
we were &amp; are content, not to be thought suche as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
would come in trouble, and yet we woulde not
<pb facs="19"/>
leaue y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> vnvttered, which it is our duties to vtter, and
which is many wayes cōmodious for y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> whole estate
of this our country to be put in mynde of, hauyng re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specte
also to the presente Honorable assent of thys
high court of Parliamēt. Moreouer because we could
not haue had any that wold haue printed our bookes
if they so lightly should haue ben brought in danger,
our former reasons also semīg to them to haue weight
to the contrary. Furthermore, because without preui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
also to haue sette too our handes, had not ben so
much material, and it was not possible for vs to haue
that, because the bishops haue y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> matter in theyr hāds,
&amp; therfore haue hindred bookes which came nothing
neare to displease them, lyke as these of oures: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
our bookes should not seeme to be against the
Queenes proceedings, For shee seemeth none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse,
but that shee wolde haue Gods matters to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede.
And last of all, because if we fynd it profytable
for y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> church to vtter our selues, we are ready so to do.
For these seueral respects we say; haue we yet hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
forborne, &amp; we trust that that which we haue sayd
wil seeme reasonable to you. But would to God these
matters wer reformed, and in the meane while, for as
much as if we might without peril (vntill we may be
disproued) set forth that which we shoulde learne out
of the scriptures, submitting oure selues to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the best churches, we thinke it were far better
that we were suffred. And it is hard dealing, that we
shoulde be abridged of suche lawfull libertie. For if
they shall obiecte any inconuenience againste vs, it is
none other but suche, as mighte stoppe the lawfull
course of all good bookes: seeing there is none ledde
with better reason to sette foorthe theyr bookes, than
we are, and seeing far better men are stopped of theyr
course by this inhibition. But we appeale to oure so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne,
and the whole state, that we may not so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally
be dealt with, that they which are parties (we
meane our bishoppes, and the rest of that sort) should
<pb facs="20"/>
only be hearde, &amp; be iudges in theyr owne cause too, &amp;
the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of God stopped of the course in all others.
At theyr handes we haue litle hope to fynde so much
vprightnesse: for it is to be doubted, they wil<note n="a" place="margin">Lu. 11. 52.</note> kepe
backe the key of knowledge, as they haue done, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
entring in them selues, and yet (as to this daye
they do) forbidding them that doe come in. God of
his gracious goodnesse, blesse them that take this his
cause into theyr handes,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10. 4. 5</note> and so directe them in the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
of his spirituall weapons, that they being migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
thorowe hym, to caste downe holdes, maye ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe
the imaginations, and euerye high thing
that is exalted againste the knowledge of
God, and bring into bondage eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
thoughte, to the obedience
of Christ, that he ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
may be glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
his church
comforted and continued vnto
eternall glory.
Amen.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>