<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>G., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102905_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01511</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11633</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102905</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>G., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Monotessaron : The evangelicall harmonie, reducing the foure Evangelists into one continued context; and in it the entire historie of the acts and sayings, life and death of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ: duely ordered according to the distinction of times. By Henry Garthwait</title>
                 <author>Garthwait, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Buck, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Daniel, Roger</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 262, 2 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the sunne shine in its full brightnesse, yet if either the eye be defective, or the medium unfit, or the object too remote, we see but imperfectly: So though truth be most resplendent in it self, yet if either we be uncapable in apprehending, or tho means unapt to convey, or the truth to be known too farre distant either in place or time, it seems not to be such to us as it is indeed in it own nature. The God of truth, willing to acquaint us with that truth which it most concerns us to know, hath provided his Spirit to enlighten our understanding; his Sonne and ministery, the means to convey it; and his written word, to bring those things which were done many ages before our time, and in places farre distant from us,<note place="margin">Galat. 3.1.</note> so neare, as if we had seen them acted before our eyes. To this end our Saviour Christ did choose from among the Jews certain men,<note place="margin">Luke 1.2.</note> which had known his life and doctrine from the beginning, to be witnesses thereof, to the Jews and Gentiles; and sele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted two from among his apostles, and from his disciples other two, to commit them to writing,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.6. and 19.15.</note> and transmit them to posteritie: That if in other cases the witnesse of two or three were sufficient, this of foure might abundantly satisfie any that should doubt of that truth, which in times past did shine full bright among the Jews. Especially having received what they deliver, not onely by their own knowledge and experience;<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.21.</note> but writing, as they spake, the dictates of the Spirit of God. The writings therefore of one of these whom we call Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16.</note> being the testimonie of the holy Spirit (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>) is of more value, and ought rather to be credited, then the testimonie of many, nay, of all men: but all of them agreeing in one and the same truth, their testimonie is so much the more enforcing, as implying so many severall acts of one and the same Spirit, producing in divers subjects one and the same effect, even <hi>The mysterie of our Salvation by Jesus Christ.</hi> For though every one of them follow his own pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
<pb facs="4"/>method and order in the context of his historie, and sometimes deliver the same thing in the same or other words, or adde some cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance to that which another had written, or new matter altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther omitted by the rest, and now and then seem not so much to respect order and method, as faithfully to record things done: yet in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth both of Christs speeches and actions, there is admirable consent and celestiall harmonie.</p>
   <p>For the more cleare demonstration of this, the learned (from the very primitive times through all ages to this of ours) have bestowed much labour and extraordinarie industrie in comparing of their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies together: as, <hi>Tatianus</hi> the scholar of <hi>Justin Martyr; Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monius, Origens</hi> master; <hi>Theophilus, Antiochenus, Epiphanius</hi> contra Alogos, <hi>S. Augustine</hi> in his foure books of the consent of the Evangelists: After them, <hi>Petrus Comestor, Bonaventura, Ludolphus de Saxonia, Joannes Gerson:</hi> And of late, <hi>Andreas Osiander, Codomannus, Molineus, Jansenius, Barrhadius, Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Selmatterus,</hi> and many others: by whose labours in that kinde the Church of God hath been much enlightned and adorned. Yet this, as it was performed by severall men, so was it done in a diverse manner. Some of them reduced all the foure Evangelists into the method &amp; text of one: the manner whereof appeares by those Canons yet remaining &amp; extant in <hi>S. Hierome.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Tom. 6. <hi>in initio.</hi>
      </note> Others placed the severall texts collaterally in one page; leaving it to the reader to judge, what was added, or delivered otherwise by any one of them. And this order the most of later times have followed, <hi>Calvin</hi> excepted, who harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizeth onely the three first, placing <hi>S. John</hi> by himself, as hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible to the other three. Others again have reduced all the foure into one continued context, bringing in every one in his due place and own words, delivering his part of the historie of Christ. Of this sort, among the Romane Catholicks, <hi>Jansenius;</hi> among the Catholick Protestants, that incomparable Divine <hi>D<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> Chemnitius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Helvic. <hi>chron.</hi>
      </note> who departing this life in the yeare <hi>1588,</hi> when he had onely finished the two first books, it was continued by <hi>Lyserus:</hi> but he likewise lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it unfinished, there was not any found that durst put his hand to the perfecting of that table of <hi>Apelles;</hi> till after fifteen yeares it was undertaken, and in few yeares made compleat, by the incessant labours of the learned and famous <hi>D<seg rend="sup">r.</seg> John Gerhard</hi> in the yeare <hi>1626.</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>Which being so exactly performed, and received with such generall applause by the best; I thought it the most fit and most worthy to be the rule and square (for order <hi>ratio</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>) by which I might guide my self in this Harmonie which I have published: some few chapters onely excepted, which they left as indifferent. If any man therefore shall require a reason of the placing of any part of this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie, why this or that precedes or follows; I doubt not but if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult what they have written of that particular, he shall receive abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant satisfaction. What hath been my part herein, with the reason of this new form in which I have placed it, shall appeare in the following direction.</p>
   <p>The benefit which will accrue to the intelligent reader by this kinde of harmonie, will be infinitely more then I can acquaint him with. For there is no one word or sentence of any of the Evangelists omitted, nor any redundant in this; but a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall and continued connexion of the historie in their own words: save onely such, as in all translations be inserted to make compleat the sense of the authour. If any phrase or word did expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the rest, though it were to the same sense, there both be put in. Whence to unforestalled judgements these things will easily appeare:
<list>
         <item>
            <hi>1.</hi> What speeches or actions of Christ go before, what follow and succeed.</item>
         <item>
            <hi>2.</hi> In what yeare of Christs life or ministerie every thing was spoken or done.</item>
         <item>
            <hi>3.</hi> The circumstances of any actions omitted by one or two of the Evangelists, are in this reduced to their due place, and that historie perfected.</item>
         <item>
            <hi>4.</hi> Many places of the Evangelists, which seem to a heedlesse reader to contradict one another, are by this connexion more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiously reconciled, then by any glosse whatsoever.</item>
         <item>
            <hi>5.</hi> The joynt consent of them foure in one testimonie concerning Christ, appeares more illustrious.</item>
         <item>
            <hi>6.</hi> And lastly, from the whole thus compacted, ariseth a most compleat historie of our Saviours life and death, with the whole foundation of Evangelicall doctrine: which is not so clearely pourtraicted by one, two, or three of the Evangelists,
<pb facs="5"/>as by them all together. Mine intention in this work (if any shall desire to know it) was first mine own information; then the help of the weak; and lastly the benefit of all that would make use of it. Which if any shall hereby receive, let God have the glory, me their prayers.</item>
      </list>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>