<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRAeFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1024_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17357</idno>
           <idno type="STC">42</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1024</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRAeFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iesus præfigured: or A poëme of the holy name of Iesus : in fiue bookes. The first, and second booke</title>
                 <author>Abbot, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 110, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PRAeFACE.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>SOme vvill perchance object it is not fitt</l>
      <l>That verses should by such as I be vvrit:</l>
      <l>I ansvvere vvhen the subject holy is</l>
      <l>VVho e're make Verses shall not doe amisse,</l>
      <l>That Volume vvhich <hi>IOBS</hi> patience doth rehearse,</l>
      <l>For no small quantitie doth speake in verse.</l>
      <l>Of other Scriptures is not a great part</l>
      <l>Compos'd according to Poeticke Art?</l>
      <l>And if vve to the after times descend,</l>
      <l>The sacred Catologue shall neuer end.</l>
      <l>Hovv many auntient Fathers Hymnes haue vvrit,</l>
      <l>In one combining pietie and vvitt</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>They erre vvho thinke a Poet hath no straine,</l>
      <l>Vnlesse the subject of his Muse be vaine.</l>
      <l>For vvhy hath <hi>Pegasus</hi> his vvings to flie?</l>
      <l>If he must still keepe earth, ne're mount on hight.</l>
      <l>Is it not pittie such a noble Horse</l>
      <l>In Boggs and durtie vvaie should spend his force,</l>
      <l>And manag'd by loose Venus vvanton Son</l>
      <l>In paths of obsceane loue, his vvhole course run?</l>
      <l>Recall your selues braue vvits: such vvaies to passe,</l>
      <l>Better becomes an <hi>Apuleian</hi> Asse.</l>
      <l>And though the Iades you ride on, do not tire</l>
      <l>Yet doe they vvant the true Poetike fire</l>
      <l>Fetcht from that Mount vvhere Virgins on a Hill</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>
VVrite loftie Odes vvith a Parthenian quill.</l>
      <l>There, there take horse: Nor are you streightned vvhen</l>
      <l>You make faire virtue object of your Pen.</l>
      <l>God, virtue, sins hate are a spatious field,</l>
      <l>And vvell-tild can abundant matter yeild.</l>
      <l>VVrite vvith a modest Pen such holy laies,</l>
      <l>That <hi>Phoebus</hi> may vvith ouerlasting baies</l>
      <l>Your tempells Crovvne: els knovv that chaster times,</l>
      <l>Shall sacrifice to Vulcan your loose rimes</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And thou my <hi>Pegasus</hi> vvhom I shall vse</l>
      <l>As <hi>Palfrie</hi> in this progresse of my Muse,</l>
      <l>VVhilst of great <hi>IESVS</hi> name thy Ladie sings,</l>
      <l>Mount vp aloft vse thy best paire of vvings,</l>
      <l>VVhen thou art forc'd to trampel here benea'th,</l>
      <l>Be it a moment onelie to take breath,</l>
      <l>And in the vvaie plaie not the Iade and tire,</l>
      <l>But as thy journey, so increase thy fire,</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>