<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Poem]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102895_Fr1_11</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09492</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19775</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102895</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Poem]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Egluryn phraethineb. sebh, dosparth ar retoreg, vn oʿr saith gelbhydhyd, yn dysculhuniaith ymadrodh, aʿi pherthynassau</title>
                 <author>Perry, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Danter, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 103, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dialectics and rhetoric</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <l>IF of their <hi>Thalmud Iewes</hi> made much, if <hi>Turks</hi> their <hi>Alcoran</hi> boast,</l>
   <l>If Priests of <hi>Egypt</hi> did commend their <hi>Memphia</hi> Chronicles most:</l>
   <l>Then <hi>Brittaines</hi> may their <hi>Bardi</hi> brag, and yeeld them gwerdon due;</l>
   <l>which pend their praise, advanc'd their fame, &amp; did their names renue.</l>
   <l>Had Bookes not crowned <hi>Rome</hi> with fame, and set their <hi>Cæsars</hi> out;</l>
   <l>Of <hi>Romane</hi> state, and <hi>Cæsars</hi> name, small praise had beene (no doubt)</l>
   <l>If <hi>Caldeans</hi> by <hi>Berosus</hi> are, extold to loftie spheares,</l>
   <l>And <hi>Persians</hi> praise by <hi>Ctesius</hi> pend, to feede the <hi>Persians</hi> eares:</l>
   <l>Then <hi>Perry</hi> presse and pleade for praise, who left no praise vnsought:</l>
   <l>And now to praise his Country more, a worke of praise he wrought.</l>
   <l>He Rhetoricke taught; the Atticke Tonge, with Kings in Court to talke,</l>
   <l>He broght such flowers from <hi>Phrigia's</hi> fields, as furnisht <hi>Cambers</hi> walk.</l>
   <l>He quickened <hi>Cambria</hi> halfe being dead, and gaue to <hi>Cambria</hi> Marts:</l>
   <l>He shadow'd <hi>Greece</hi> in <hi>Cambria</hi> soile, &amp; broght frō <hi>Greece</hi> their Arts</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Dardania</hi> is by him renude, and <hi>Troy</hi> revivde againe;</l>
   <l>To giue a glasse to glory lost, it is no losse but gaine.</l>
   <l>The Hebrue <hi>Rabbins</hi> deeme no man sit, their Hebrue bookes to reed;</l>
   <l>And <hi>Greeks</hi> thoght barbarus al the world, but such as <hi>Greece</hi> did breed.</l>
   <l>But <hi>Iewes Iudea</hi> lost thereby, and <hi>Greeks</hi> their <hi>Greece</hi> haue lost;</l>
   <l>Now <hi>Brittaines</hi> bath in <hi>Brutus</hi> blisse, in auncient <hi>Albions</hi> Coast.</l>
   <l>VVhere old <hi>Anchises</hi> broode did breede, where <hi>Dardans</hi> stocke remaine,</l>
   <l>VVhere <hi>Troians</hi> sayld, where <hi>Bryttaines</hi> dwelt, to Queen <hi>Eliza's</hi> raign.</l>
   <l>Thus <hi>Perry</hi> prou'd and pend his Booke, and puts his booke in viewe;</l>
   <l>To see what may be seene or sayd, of him that wrote so true.</l>
   <p>Lodowicke Lloid Esquire.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>