<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Richarde Ferris Sear∣geant Chirurgian vnto the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, vnto his louing frende maister Gale sendeth greting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102805_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11529</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102805</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Richarde Ferris Sear∣geant Chirurgian vnto the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, vnto his louing frende maister Gale sendeth greting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine vvorkes of chirurgerie, nevvly compiled and published by Thomas Gale, maister in chirurgerie</title>
                 <author>Gale, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gale, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hall, Rowland</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 53, 7, 5, 58, 1, 3, 19, 2, 4, 90, 8 leaves, 5 folded tables, illustrations, portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="81"/>
   <head>Richarde Ferris Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant Chirurgian vnto the Queenes most excellent Maiestie, vnto his louing frende maister Gale sendeth greting.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>VVO thynges there be at this present vvhiche moueth me to addresse my letters to you maister Gale, of vvhich the one is the auncient and famous art of Chirurgerie, vvhich vvas in tymes past not an art of it selfe, but one portion of the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue part of Phisicke, called Therapeutice: the other is my natiue countrey. These tvvo by your labours and paynes: I truste shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue no smale profite and gaine, and these make me to vvryte my letters gratulatorie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. First that the art of Chirurgerie, vvho being novv so decayed, vvhose fame so obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, her beauty eclipsed &amp; vtilitie of it dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, shal by you be somevvhat brought to her vvonted &amp; pristinat state. For it is in far vvorse case novve in this our furious and raging sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son (in vvhich good artes are contemned, or els lytle estemed and had in price) then it vvas in the tyme of Mantuan the Poet, vvho ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clameth
<pb facs="82"/> in this vvyfe.</p>
   <q>Fama quidem manet, vtilitas antiqua recessit.</q>
   <p>The Poet speaketh of Phisicke generally vvaying the excellēcie of it, &amp; the great vtilitie that hath come to mankynde by it in the olde tyme, as the vvorkes and volumes of the Greke vvryters, do testifie and beare vvitnesse: and conferring further theyr testimonies vvith the poore fruites of it that did spring in his tyme, as one lamenting the decay of so noble a sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and great gifte of God to mankynde, sayde in effecte.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Her noble fame yet styll remayne,</l>
      <l>But few doth health by her attayne.</l>
   </q>
   <p>He speaketh it in the vvaye of comparation, that there did not so many by the benefite of Phisick receyue their health as did in the olde tyme. But I leaue Phisicke, and vvill speake of Chirurgerie both our professions. Surely I dare boldely affirme that if Mantuan vvere novve liuing and did beholde the state of Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, he vvould not say that her fame did yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, but rather that nother fame nor yet great vse remained: I had almost sayde that it vvas knovven but only by name. And vvhat be the causes that she is broughte to this miserable estate? If I shall saye that vvhich I knovv there
<pb facs="82"/> be tvvo principall enemies. The one is the Chirurgian himselfe, vvho neither knovveth nor yet laboureth to learne his arte, but being inflamed vvith the loue of turpe lucrū, rudely and blyndely exerciseth his arte. The other enemie is the Pacient vvho hath need of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeries ayde. For he vvill haue in lyke esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, a Cobler, a Ioyner, a Minstraile, a vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, yea a Horseleache, that he vvill an expert Chirurgian, yea and revvard them as vvell, if it be not better. The remedies for one of these mischiefes you haue, I hope, in tyme prouided. I meane in setting out your Enchiridion. For there shall those that in deed are licensed to exercise Chirurgerie, finde no smale portiō of this art compendiously and faythfully gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together. VVherefore leauing other their authours in vvhich many errours are hidden, I doe exhort them that bothe for the fame of Chirurgerie, vvhich they ought to their vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moste to maintaine: and also for their ovvne gaine and profite they vvill not only read this Enchiridion: but read and read it againe, not leauing vntill they be made vvell acquaynted vvith the same. And if any places do remaine obscure and darke: they yet haue you the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour to resort vnto, vvho vvill as gladly I am
<pb facs="83"/> sure open the meaning of them, as he hath vvillingly for their gaine and profite compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the same. As for the other enemie I meane the sick pacients, it doeth not muche force, for they are enemies chiefly to them selues, vvhen as they fall into the handes of suche rude and bussardly clouters. And although the pacients being maimed and brought in perill of death by such, do exclame against Chirurgerie and Chirurgians: yet if the Chirurgians themselfes study to be learned &amp; excel such rude Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rikes, the slaunder shal returne to the authours therof again. The second cause of my vvriting vvas for my natiue countries sake, that lyke as you haue labored frō the tyme that you vvere in my gouernaunce &amp; teaching to profite the same, and haue novv shevved an euident signe and token thereof in this your Enchiridion: so you vvill not cease to continue in these your good enterprises, and your country shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard you vvith honest report and perpetuall fame. Thus I cease to trouble you further, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king shortlye for the publishing of this and other your vvorkes.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>At my house in Paddinton, <date>the seconde of Iuly. 1563.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>