<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Maister Gabriel Armestrong Esquire, and to the vertuous gentlewoman Mi∣stris Margaret Armestrong his louing Wife.</title>
           <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102480_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14003</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24313</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102480</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Maister Gabriel Armestrong Esquire, and to the vertuous gentlewoman Mi∣stris Margaret Armestrong his louing Wife.</title>
                 <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pictvre of a true protestant: or, Gods house and husbandry : wherein is declared the duty and dignitie of all Gods children, both minister and people. Written by Thomas Tuke</title>
                 <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Archer, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 232 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT worshipfull Maister <hi>Gabriel Armestrong</hi> Esquire, and to the vertuous gentlewoman <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stris</hi> Margaret Armestrong his louing Wife.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, many, large and admirable are the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits wherwith the Lord hath honoured vs these fifty by-past years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He hath borne vs, as an <hi>Eagle</hi> doth her <hi>Birds</hi> vpon his wings,<note place="margin">Deut. 32.11</note> and walled vs in with
<pb facs="3"/>
his loue. He hath giuen vs his <hi>Word,</hi> and his <hi>Sacraments</hi> of grace; he hath sent vs his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and <hi>Embassadours:</hi> he hath compassed vs with <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>prosperity,</hi> making vs <hi>to eate the fruites of the fields,</hi> and causing vs to <hi>sucke hony out of the stone,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Deut. 32.13</note>
      <hi>and oyle out of the rocke.</hi> He hath set most <hi>noble Gouernours</hi> ouer vs: he hath filled our hearts with the <hi>ioyes of victories,</hi> &amp; hath put the <hi>songs</hi> of <hi>deliuerances</hi> into our mouthes.</p>
   <p>But lamentable is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement, which his loue hath found amongst vs, who (like those ancient <hi>Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi>) haue <hi>corrupted our selues to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="3"/>
him by our vice</hi>;<note place="margin">Deut. 32.5 15.21.</note> a peruerse and tortuous generation, who being laden with fatnes, haue spurned with our heeles, and prouoked his <hi>Highnesse</hi> with our vanities.</p>
   <p>For first, if we consider the transcendent profanenes and affected ignorance of the <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,</hi> &amp; the flagitious irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities of many desperate <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theists, Epicures, Nullifidians,</hi> as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festant as the <hi>frogs</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ex. 8, 3.14.</note> which made the land to stink; it may be truly said of them (vngratefull wretches) that they cast the filth of their feet in his face, they recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence his grace with grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesnesse,
<pb facs="4"/>
and presse him with their sins as a <hi>Cart</hi> with sheues not <hi>Men,</hi> but <hi>Monsters,</hi> which (like <hi>Moles</hi>) digge groueling in wickednes (as in the ground) and ceasse not till they haue cast vp a <hi>Mountaine</hi> of hatefull enormities against the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens.</p>
   <p>Secondly, if we call to mind &amp; seriously perpend that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilent and prodigious <hi>Powder-plot,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Nouem. 5. An. 1605.</note> and some other execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vnnaturall attempts and machinations of some of our <hi>Italianated Catholiques</hi> in spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, &amp; the incorrigible ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinacie of them all in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, (like the <hi>Sycamore,</hi> which
<pb facs="4"/>
the more it is moistened, the drier it waxeth) it wil appeare impossible for thē to purge themselues of palpable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude and disloyalty; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aduersaries to his truth, setled vpon the lees of their owne feculent opinions, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doring the <hi>Idols</hi> of their owne distempered braines, pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his worship with su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious aditions, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring no good will vnto his people.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, if we do well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue the preposterous &amp; dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astrous studies of many schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall and refractarious spirits, their heate, their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,
<pb facs="5"/>
and vncharitablenes, how vnnaturally they do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect &amp; reuile their <hi>Mother,</hi> how passionately they doe blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the <hi>Church,</hi> which God hath planted with his owne hand, and with what morosity they haue ab-alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated themselues from their <hi>Bretheren</hi>; they can by no pretext acquit themselues of great vndutifulnes vnto God, being so <hi>turbulent</hi> in his <hi>House,</hi> so <hi>disobedient</hi> to their <hi>Mother,</hi> &amp; so farre <hi>exorbitant</hi> in all their courses; not much vnlike to <hi>mothes,</hi> that fret the cloth, wherein they breed; to <hi>water-boughes,</hi> which hurt the tree,
<pb facs="5"/>
from which they sprang.</p>
   <p>And finally for the more hopeful and ingenuous, if we doe but consider the remis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of too-too many, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traits, the standings, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractions, the doubtes, that are too common, too conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous (arising partly from the corrupted fountaine of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is not drained dry till death; and partly procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the vicious ensam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and scandalous d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure of hypocrites &amp; profane <hi>extrauagants</hi>; and partly also through the differences of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and the vnbrother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>hanging-off</hi> and <hi>flying off</hi> of
<pb facs="6"/>
many <hi>Romanists</hi> &amp; other <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rists,</hi> al <hi>Nouelists</hi>) if these things (I say) be well considered, we cannot but confesse that we are behind in duty, and haue not made such vse of Gods mercies, as wee should haue done.</p>
   <p>What remaineth for vs then to do? Surely we should all repent, all, <hi>All</hi> without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. We should <hi>examine</hi> our selues, rectify &amp; <hi>settle</hi> our iudgements, and <hi>turne</hi> the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of our harts &amp; liues, &amp; <hi>sue</hi> for pardon, bewaring that we be not (like <hi>Bowles</hi>) ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaied with the wrydrawing <hi>Byas</hi> of our owne conceited<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="6"/>
and home-bred concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence; lest the Lord being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asperated against vs, our day be turned into <hi>darknesse,</hi> our <hi>light</hi> into <hi>night,</hi> our <hi>fame</hi> into <hi>shame,</hi> &amp; so be made the <hi>spect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle</hi> of his <hi>wrath,</hi> and <hi>scorne</hi> of the <hi>world.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>We are Gods <hi>House,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.16.</note> and the <hi>Receptacles</hi> of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> which is the <hi>author</hi> of holinesse, &amp; the <hi>source</hi> of perfection: we are his <hi>Fleld,</hi> his <hi>Vineyard</hi> and <hi>Garden</hi> of delight; our duty therefore is to cleanse &amp; adorne our harts to be faire and fruitfull, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing and not offensiue. The <hi>Sunne</hi> of righteousnesse hath shone long amongst vs with
<pb facs="7"/>
exceeding brightnesse (in the <hi>Gospell</hi>) and with his heat hath moulten the <hi>Cloudes</hi> aboue vs, which haue emptied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues like <hi>bottles</hi> vpon vs; and therefore to testify our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santnesse and fertility for the remōstratiō of our gratitude, we should abound in grace, increase in knowledge, and perfume the aire about vs with our fragrant sauors, and not poison it with filthy fumes, like stinking dunghils.</p>
   <p>To further this both deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and desired duty, I haue penned, and now am bold to publish this <hi>Tractate</hi> folowing, which I haue presumed to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
and present vnto your <hi>VVorships</hi> in this plight you see, (partly for that great respect, which you haue euer had of Gods faithfull Ministers) wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing it may find but quiet <hi>house-roome</hi> in your hearts, and so I shall enioy my wish, and it no meane reward.</p>
   <p>Now the very <hi>God of peace</hi> sanctify you both through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,<note place="margin">1 Thes. 5.23</note> and so honour you with his grace, that hauing fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished your race in this world, you may <hi>rest</hi> and <hi>reigne</hi> for euer in the world to come.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>London, <date>October 28. 1609.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your VVorships in Christ Iesus, <hi>THOMAS TVKE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>