<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧To the noble and gallant Dames of the Cittie of Castale in Mon: Ferrato Gabriel Giolito.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102851_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16255</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3179</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102851</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧To the noble and gallant Dames of the Cittie of Castale in Mon: Ferrato Gabriel Giolito.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Amorous Fiammetta : VVherein is sette downe a catologue [sic] of all and singuler passions of loue and iealosie, incident to an enamored yong gentlewoman, with a notable caueat for all women to eschewe deceitfull and wicked loue, by an apparant example of a Neapolitan lady, her approued &amp; long miseries, and wyth many sounde dehortations from the same. First wrytten in Italian by Master Iohn Boccace, the learned Florentine, and poet laureat. And now done into English by B. Giouano del M. Temp. With notes in the margine, and with a table in the ende of the cheefest matters contayned in it</title>
                 <author>Boccaccio, Giovanni</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Newman, Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 123, 4 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧To the noble and gallant Dames of the Cittie of Castale in Mon: Ferrato <hi>Gabriel Giolito.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst the finest and vulgare prose of that most excellent &amp; learned Clarke, Master <hi>Iohn Boccace,</hi> wrytten for your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and consolation, there is none (moste noble Ladies) which you ought to hold more deere, and esteeme more preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, then this present work, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled <hi>(Amorous Fiammetta.)</hi> Because contayning in it the sighes, the teares, &amp; prolonged miseries of an ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured yong Gentlewoman forsaken of her Louer, who doth not conceiue this very same to be set foorth as a soueraigne example, and sole instruction for you all. Not, that by the condemned ingratitude of one yong man, you should learne, generally to despise all men, but rather because knowing by another, howe daungerous a thing it is, lightly and quickly to giue credence to euery one his promise, Loue beeing a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural fire to burne the brauest &amp; most gentle minds, &amp; enclyning your selues to loue, you may select &amp; chose out such a subiect, that afterwards the like repentance, and a worse condition perhappes then <hi>Fiammetta</hi> had, may not befall vnto you.</p>
   <p>VVhereuppon my selfe, who was borne to doo you all the seruice I canne, hauing with all diligence corrected thys Booke, and committed it to the presse,
<pb facs="4"/> I thought it most beseeming my deuoyre to bring it to light, authorised vnder your worthy names, and sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed (I hope) vnder the fauourable winges of your assured ampare and defence. Reade it therefore, &amp; dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursing amongst your selues the dolorous cōplaints of that miserable and haplesse Ladye <hi>Fiammetta:</hi> by her desastrous and aduerse Fortune, learne you (fayre Ladyes) to be wyser and better aduised. And hauing the name and tytle of the fayrest and noblest Ladies in Italy, assume also the prayse and commendation vppon you of the wysest and moste pittifull Gentlewomen in the same. Because a womans ornament is not in her cruelty enclosed, or in her peeuish austernes, and none amongst them was euer commended for an vnworthy enemy to mens affections. In the meane whyle I wyll not omitt (gracious Ladies) hereafter to offer vppe to your high and sacred thoughts, more noble matters, &amp; of greater consequence.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>