<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, CHARLES PRINCE OF VVALES, DVKE OF CORNE∣VVALL, EARLE OF CHESTER, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Abbot, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1024_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17357</idno>
           <idno type="STC">42</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1024</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, CHARLES PRINCE OF VVALES, DVKE OF CORNE∣VVALL, EARLE OF CHESTER, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Abbot, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iesus præfigured: or A poëme of the holy name of Iesus : in fiue bookes. The first, and second booke</title>
                 <author>Abbot, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 110, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, CHARLES PRINCE OF VVALES, DVKE OF CORNE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VVALL, EARLE OF CHESTER, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Great CHARLES</salute>
   </opener>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
         </hi> Doe not thinke the Verse I write,</l>
      <l>VVorthy the honour of your Princely fight;</l>
      <l>(And should you read no lines, but worth your view,</l>
      <l>Men knew not what to dedicate to you)</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But hauing nothing els to shew my zeale,</l>
      <l>VVith VViddow, what I haue, I freelie deale: <hi>Marc.</hi> 12▪</l>
      <l>To giue rich Donatiues great Princes vse,</l>
      <l>T'is also greatnesse badge not to refuse</l>
      <l>Smal presents; els how should meane persons showe</l>
      <l>That duty, which to Potentates they owe?</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="3"/>
To you my <hi>PRINCE</hi> I consecrate my booke,</l>
      <l>Reward my Muse: with what? your gratious looke.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Vouchsafe to read our Poëm, vvherein all</l>
      <l>Is written without malice, without gall:</l>
      <l>VVee are not bitter at the Present time,</l>
      <l>Onelie wee saie Rebellion is a Crime.</l>
      <l>Aud auntient sectaries our verse doth strike,</l>
      <l>VVho so shall doe your <hi>Highnesse</hi> needs must like.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And though wee speake in rime, as Poets vse,</l>
      <l>Yet sacred veritie attends our Muse.</l>
      <l>Truth on our Poëm waits: (an vpright cause,</l>
      <l>To set it fourth needeth no lying clause:)</l>
      <l>In all our building there is not a stone,</l>
      <l>But wee dare justifie to be our owne.</l>
      <l>Certes now wee haue perfited our frame,</l>
      <l>Casting reflections eie vpon the same</l>
      <l>VVe doubt much vvhether vvee haue anie vaine</l>
      <l>In Poetrie, because wee doe not faine.</l>
      <l>Vouchsafe then Mighty <hi>CHARLES</hi> my Booke to view</l>
      <l>VVhich is all Innocent, all smooth, all true.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Highnesse humble seruant 
IOHN ABBOT.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>