<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶Peter Boaystuau to
the Reader health.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102736_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16241</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3168</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102736</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶Peter Boaystuau to
the Reader health.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Theatrum mundi : the theatre or rule of the world, wherein may be sene the running race and course of euerye mans life, as touching miserie and felicity, wherin is contained wonderfull examples, learned deuises, to the ouerthrowe of vice, and exalting of vertue. wherevnto i added a learned, and maruellous worke of the excellencie of mankinde. Written in the Frenche &amp; Latin tongues by Peter Boaystuau, and translated into English by Iohn Alday</title>
                 <author>Boaistuau, Pierre</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>304 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>¶Peter Boaystuau to
the Reader health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
sodenlye after
that I had made of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
to the traduction
of <hi>Chelidonius,</hi> and
wyth other fayre
treaties of mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention,
being aduertised how willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
thou hast receyued my workes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I thought good to gratifie thée with
a greater thing (being pricked forward
by) I know not what néedle of vertue to
flie more higher, and to set forth some
certaine worke of more weight and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor.
So that after an infinite number of
diuers and sundry things méete &amp; neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary.<note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor doth intraduct the Citie of GOD in our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.</note>
There was none to my iudgement
more worthy for a Christian weale, than
this chiefe or head worke of Sainct Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine
in his Citie of God, wherein he
hath reared such a furious combat or
fight against the Ethnickes, that with
<pb facs="7"/>
their owne armors he hath vanquished
and ouercome them. In consideration
thereof, I haue boldened my selfe to lay
this fardell on my weake shoulders, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
by the grace of God to set it forth
&amp; bring it to light in our vulgar tongue,
with such a facilitie that it shal serue for
a buckeler, against the incursions of an
infinite number of sectes, that are spred
this day throughout the worlde. Nowe
therfore I leaue thée to iudge how many
Authors I haue turned ouer, Gréekes &amp;
Latins for to bring this my enterprise to
his desired effect, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> reading of which Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
hath not ben staked nor letted. For
besides the great cōfort that I haue had
in thē, for to opē the meaning of my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
(which of it self is very dark and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure)
I haue drawen out an other fruit
and particuler profit, for of all their best
sentences I haue founded (this Rule of
the world) which now I do presēt to thée
(gentle and louing Reader) assuring thée
(to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ende I wil not defraud none of his
glorie) that I haue left no Author sacred
<pb facs="7"/>
or prophane, Gréeke, Latin, or in our
vulgar tongue, but that I haue bereft
him of a leg or a wing, for the more soū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
decking and furniture of my worke.
In such sort that if thou wilt impose this
worke a rapsodie, collation or gathering
togither of diuers authorities, thou shalt
doe it no wrong. The which I haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprised
so much the more boulder than
such matters (which are almost anota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
&amp; foreshewings of vices.) It should
the rather treat by graue sentences and
examples of our Magistrates, than by
anie other stile. As touching the reast I
am assured that certaine daintie or deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
worldlings, will auouch, that there
is in this worke, I know not what wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
to be read, but that among these
swéete Roses, there are manye other
things, sowre, seuere and bitter: but such
gald horses that feare to be touched, and
that are so tickelish in their affections,
that they woulde faine haue libertie for
their wickednesse, and that defence
were made that none shoulde correct or
<pb facs="8"/>
admonish them of their yll doings. I
beseche them before passing further that
they will beholde with what authoritie
and rigor the auncient Fathers, as S.
Ambrose, Sainct Ierome, Sainct Iohn,
Chrisostom, Sainct Augustine, Origen,
Tertulian, Eusebius and Lactantius,
haue reproued the vices that reigned in
their time, and with what boldenesse S.
Bernarde writ to Pope <hi>Eugenius,</hi> and
how he withstoode the wicked Prelates
in the sermon which he made at the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node
of Pastors, and in the .xxxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>j. sermon
of Canticles, when as he shewed them
their vices, cōplayning of their pompes,
and superfluous deliciousnesse, and in
the meane time the poore shepe and flock
of Iesus Christ remained desart. What
thornes were these if they had heard the
malediction of S. Peter vpon <hi>Ananias</hi>
and <hi>Saphira,</hi> the which tempting the
holie ghost the spirit of God, died soden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
for feare. Let them remember howe
Sainct Paule spake vnto the hie Priest
calling him filthye Sepulcher. Sainct
<pb facs="8"/>
Iohn vnto the Publicans and sinners,
calling them a generatiō of Vipers. Let
them consider howe <hi>Epimenideus</hi> the
Gréeke spake to the <hi>Candians,</hi> calling
them cruell and abhominable beastes,
brainelesse liers. Let them also consider
with what sharpe and poynted wordes
Helias and Esaie did reproue the <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi>
though they were two sage and
graue Prophetes.</p>
   <p>But what iust occasion should the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Fathers haue had, auncient Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,
Prophetes and Apostles, if they
had had such a worlde as ours, which is
so depraued and broken in all kinde of
vices and abhominations, that it sée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
to be a place that hath receyued all
the filthinesse and purgings of all other
worlds and ages. But as for me I will
not make the office of censur or refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
of vices, knowing my selfe to be a
man as others, although that somtimes
I cal them by their name: but with such
modestie, that I onely rebuke the vices
and not the persons. And I doe not only
<pb facs="9"/>
discouer the abuse of the world, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> end
y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the simple &amp; ignorant should beware,
but incontinently I shewe the vse and
remedy for things. And by this meanes,
those that cannot support libertie, and
compasse of writing. Let them hereafter
learne so well to reforme them selues,
and lead the estate of their life that they
be not a iesting stocke to others, and to
themselues for euer a reproch, knowing
that the time is come, that being in this
worlde, as in a fielde of libertie, we can
not so well cloke and dissemble our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
but the smoke and smell thereof wil
breake out. Receyue therefore (louing
Reader) this present treatise, the which
I thought good to set forth in two lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages,
Latin and French, for to make
thée vnderstand that I will not lead
the rest of my life, but that it
shall bring forth some
publicke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite.</p>
   <trailer>Farevvell.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>