<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102042_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06013</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1640</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102042</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The diocesans tryall : Wherein all the sinnews of D. Dovvnams Defence are brought unto three heads, and orderly dissolved. By M. Paul Baynes</title>
                 <author>Baynes, Paul</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 89, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>MAny writings, and sermons also have cause to wish that the men from whom they come were lesse knowen then they are. For then should they bee free from much prejudice, and finde better accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with those that they come to. But I wish nothing more unto this Treatise, which now is comming into the world, then that the Author of it were throughly known unto all those that shall meet with it; for then his worke would need no borrowed commendation, the title it selfe carrying autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with it, even to force respect from every honest Reader, if either the sharpnesse of wit, variety of reading, depth of judgement, aptnesse to teach, holy and pleasant language, heavenly conversation, wise cariage, or any fulnesse of grace will so farre prevaile with him. I doe not abuse good words, or load one with them whom they doe not belong to, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny painters of Sepulchres in their funerall Orations use to doe: but speak that in short, which M. Baines his person did largely preach unto all such as came neere unto him: and that which his incomparable writings will sufficiently witnesse to future generations.</p>
   <p>Neither is this all that the Authours qualitie may suggest unto the considerate Reader: but he may arise from this to more important thoughts; especially if the remembrance of M. Baynes his worth doe occasion him to thinke of many others like unto him: such as M. Deering, M. More, M. Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, M. Perkins, M. Rogers, M. Cartwright, M. Fenner, M. Brightman, M. Parker, M. Philips, M. Hieron, &amp; M. Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaw &amp;c. to speake nothing of those which yet liue, nor of D. Reinolds, D. Fulk, and D. Whitakers with many others. For all these being apprehended as men agreeing in one spirit, and having had indeed the spirit of glory resting on them, as their workes doe shew, together with those letters testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall
<pb facs="3"/>
which they left written in the hearts of many thousand Christians, it must needs cause at the least an inquirie, what the reason should be, that such famous men of God, could never like well of our Bishoply courses in England, nor ever be favoured of them. The case is plaine to all: and the cause is as evident to those that haue eyes to see: but no where more apparant then in the person of M. Baines, and the place where hee, and others like him were made signes of this antipathie. Cambridge is or should be, as an eye to all our land: so that the alterations that fall out there cannot but bee felt of all parts. It is the place of light; the spirituall oppressions which in other corners are covered with darkenesse (as all the works of darknesse would be) when past all shame they come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front the Sunne it selfe, how can they then be hidden?</p>
   <p>When M. Perkins had there for many yeares held forth a burning and shining light, the sparkes whereof did flie abroad into all corners of the land, and after he had served his time was taken up into heaven, there was none found so meet for to receive, as it were, the torch out of his hand, and succeed him in that great office of bearing it before such a people, as this M. Baines, upon whom also the spirit of that Elias, was by experience found to be doubled. In this station he so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaned himselfe for some years, that impietie onely had cause to complaine: for all that favoured the wayes of God, rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and gloried in him and his Ministerie, as a spirituall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. But at length the howre of darknesse came from Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, when Arch. Bancroft sent M. Harsenet to visite, as they call it, that is (if termes may be interpreted by common practise) to picke the purses of poore men, and to suppresse those that are not friends to the Bishops Kingdome. For though in that circuit there were a multitude of unable and notoriously scandalous Ministers, yet none were found wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of censure, but onely M. Baynes, of whom the world was not worthy, and one other Preacher like unto him. Now it is hard to say, whether the silencing of him was more odious, or the manner of it shamelesse. There must be a Sermon (yee know) at such visitations, for fashion sake, though the Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter himselfe can seldome find leasure to make it. This part was
<pb facs="3"/>
therefore appointed to M. Baynes by the Visiters, that he might either be insnared in his words, if he did not apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to their humours, or else grace their ungracious cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, if he did. But it did not succeed handsomely either way: For he delivered wholesome doctrine appertaining to the present audience, in such warie manner, that no specious occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion could be taken thereby of questioning his libertie. Yet fairely or fouly the mischievous intention must not faile. M. Baines having heat his weake body by straining to speake unto a great audience, retired himselfe presently upon his comming down from the Pulpit to provide for his health, which otherwise would have bene indangered. They in the meane time going on with their businesse, as they are wont in the masterly forme of a muster, called for M. Barnes among the rest, and upon his not answering, though he was not cited thither as to a Court, but onely intreated to preach, as hee did, yet for not appearing, he was immediately silenced. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward in deed, the Chancellour being informed of that grosse nullitie, which was in that sentence, urged him about subscription and conformitie; and so to make sure worke, silenced him over againe: In which businesse he was so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scious unto himselfe of unreasonable and ridiculous dealing, that when M. Baynes standing to receive the sentence of a corrupt man, did lift up his heart and eyes unto God with a heavenly smiling countenance, as he used, he interpreted that gesture to be a skorning of his authoritie. This being done, M. Baines was perswaded by his friends to try the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishops courtesie, unto whom, when he presented himselfe, at the very first salutation, the gravitie and severitie of B. Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft led him sharply to rebuke the good mā for a little black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, which was upon the edges of his cuffes, asking him how he durst come before him with such cuffs, telling him ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bishoplike, that it were a good turne to lay him by the heeles for so doing. After this he would have no more to doe with such absurd unreasonable men: but preached sometime where he might have libertie, as his weakenesse of bodie would suffer; and spent the rest of his time in reading, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating, praying and writing, saving that upon occasion he did
<pb facs="4"/>
instruct or comfort those which came to him in private, wherein he had a heavenly gift. He was indeed all his life af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, beside the weakenesse of his bodie pressed with want, not having (as he often complained to his friends) a place to rest his head in: which me thought was an upbraiding of the age and place where he lived with base regardlessnesse of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and learning: yet he never so much as consulted with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe of denying his sinceritie by pleasing the Bishops, of whom and their courses he was wont to say, <hi>They are a generation of the earth, earthly, and savour not the waies of God.</hi> Which saying of his, they, and some Doctors of Cambridge have since made good, in that they could not indure, that the place from whence they thrust him, should be supplyed by other honest men, though they were conformable, but with absolute au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie at length forbad it, alledging that Puritanes were made by that lecture: whereas the truth is, that one lecture hath done more good to the Church of God in England, then all the doctors of Cambridge: though I doe not deny, but some of them have wrought a good worke.</p>
   <p>By this one instance (of which kind I would there were not a hundred in our land) it may easily appeare to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding Reader, that there is as much agreement betwixt our Bishops in their managing of Religion (except some two or three, which went out of their elements, when they vente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on those places) and those powerfull Preachers who haue bene the chiefe meanes of revealing Gods arme unto salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as there is betwixt the light which commeth down from heaven, and that thick mist which ariseth from the lowest pit.</p>
   <p>But we need not seeke for demonstrations of the spirit which worketh in our Hierarchie from this opposition, look but at the fruits of it, where it hath all fulnesse of consent, as in Cathedrall Pallaces, or Parishes of Bishops and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishops residence, such as Lambeth is, where all their canons are in force, and haue their full sway without contradiction: nay come neerer unto them, and take a view of their families, even to them that wayt in their chambers, and see what godlinesse there is to be found. Haue there not more of God and his Kingdome appeared in some one Congregation of
<pb facs="4"/>
those Ministers which they haue silenced for unconformity, then in all the Bishops families that are now in England? Was there ever any of them that could endure such a Parish as Lambeth is, if they had such power of reforming it as the Archbishops haue?</p>
   <p>To returne therfore unto our Authour: whilst he lived a private life, being thus strucken with the Bishops Planet, he had time to apply his able wit and judgement unto the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussing of many questions, which if the Prelates had not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced such leasure upon him, it may be he would haue passed by with others. And among the rest, by Gods providence hee vvas directed to these Ecclesiasticall Controversies which concerne our Diocesan state in England: wherein, as in all other questions which he dealt in, he hath shewed such dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct and pearcing understanding, together with evidence of truth, as cannot but give good satisfaction to him that in these things seeketh light.</p>
   <p>He might in deed have chosen other particular corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to have vvritten on, if it had bene his purpose either to haue taught men, vvhat they daily see and feele, or to haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured about the branches, and leaue the root untouched: But it vvas no delight unto him, for to proue that vvhich no man doubted of, as that the common course and practise of our Prelates their courts, their urging of subscriptions, with humane superstitious ceremonies, are presumptuous insolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies against God and his Church: or preposterously to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne at the end of the streame for to cleanse the vvater. He chose rather to search the fountaine of all that foulnesse vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith our Churches are soiled: vvhich he judged to be found in the constitutions here in this Treatise examined. And if these fevv questions be vvell considered, it vvill appeare that a multitude of pernicious abuses doe depend on those positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vvhich in them are confuted. One fundamentall abuse in our Ecclesiasticall oppression is in the disposing of charges, or placing of Ministers over Congregations: It is called u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually bestovving of Benefices or Livings, in an earthy phrase vvhich savoureth of the base corruption commonly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. For Congregations ought not to be bestovved on Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters,
<pb facs="5"/>
but Ministers on Congregations: the benefit or bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the minister, is not so much to be regarded, as of the Congregation: It is the calling and charge which every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister should looke at, not his living and benefice. Now these Benefices are bestowed ordinarily by the Patron (whether Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish, prophane, or religious, all is one) and the Bishop, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regard of the peoples call or consent: so as no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mariage is made; no servant placed: against all Scripture, Councels and ancient examples. Whereby it commeth ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily to passe, that Lawyers must determine of Ministers cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, after long suits and great charges; as if Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Farmes were held by one title and right. And some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it is found that the Minister is a continuall plague unto his people, living in contention, spight and hatred with them, as many law-suits doe too too plainely witnesse. What is the reason? Because Parishes are esteemed as no Churches, that ever were ordeined by Christ, or recived any power and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges from him, but as mans creatures, and by man to be ordered as it pleaseth him. Another practise of like nature with the former, is that the Minister being called to one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, becommeth a Pluralist by taking another, or more livings, in spight of that Congregation, to which hee was first and is still personally tied. And after all this he may be a non-resident, abiding or preaching at none of his many livings. Nay he may chop and change, sell and buy like a marchant, so he doe it closely; which is such an abomination, as Rome and Trent condemneth, and hell it selfe will scarse defend. What is the ground? Because (forsooth) Christ hath not appointed Parishes, their officers, and offices, and therfore no man is bound further in this kinde, then mens Lawes, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, customes, and injunctions doe prescribe unto them. For a grave Doctor of Cambridge answered one that questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him for his grosse non-residencie, <hi>viz.</hi> that Parishes were divided by a Pope: insinuating as it seemeth that he accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it a point of Poperie, for to tie Ministers unto their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular charges,</p>
   <p>A third grosse corruption is, that the officers in Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Ministers, Church-wardens, &amp;c. are made servants to
<pb facs="5"/>
the Bishops, Chancellours, Archdeacons, &amp;c. being, as it were, their promotors, informers, and executioners, in all matters of jurisdiction and government, for to bring in money into their purses: for performance also of which service to them, the Church-wardens upon every occasion are enforced to take such corporall oathes as not one of them doth ever keep. What other ground of this, beside the fore-mentioned, that particular Congregations are no spirituall incorporations, and therefore must have no officers for government within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves?</p>
   <p>Now all these confusions with many other of the same kinde, how they are condemned in the very foundation of them, M. Baines heere sheweth in the first question, by main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the divine constitution of a particular Church, in one Congregation. In which question he maintaineth against his adversaries a course not unlike to that which Armachanus, in the daies of King Edward the third, contended for against the begging Friers in his booke called <hi>The Defence of Curates</hi>: For when those Friers incroached upon the priviledges of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochiall Ministers, he withstood them upon these grounds: <hi>Ecclesia Parochialis juxta verba Mosis Deut. 12. est locus electus a Deo, in quo debemus accipere cuncta quae praecipit Dominus ex Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis. Parochus est ordinarius Parochiani: est persona a Deo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta, vel mandato De<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> ad illud ministerium explendum electa:</hi> Which if they be granted, our adversaries cause may goe a begging with the fore said Friers.</p>
   <p>Another sort of corruptions there are, which though they depend upon the same ground with the former, yet immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately flow out of the Hierarchie. What is more dissonant from the revealed will of Christ in the Gospell, even also from the state of the Primitive Church, then that the Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Christ should be managed as the Kingdomes of the world; by a Lordly authoritie, with externall pompe, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding power, contentious courts of judgement, furnished with chancellours, officials, commissaries, advocates, proctors, paritors, and such like humane devises? Yet all this doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily follow upon the admitting of such Bishops as ours are in England: who not onely are Lords over the flock
<pb facs="6"/>
but doe professe so much in the highest degree, when they tell us plainely, that their Lawes or Canons doe binde mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences. For herein wee are like to the people of Israel, who would not have God for their immediate King, but would have such Kings as other Nations: Even so the Papists, and we after them, refuse to have Christ an immediate King in the immediate government of the Church; but must have Lordly Rulers with state in Ecclesiasticall affaires, such as the world hath in civill.</p>
   <p>What a miserable pickle are the most of our Ministers in, when they are urged to give an account of their calling? To a Papist in deed they can give a shifting ansvver, that they have ordination from Bishops, which Bishops were ordained by other Bishops, and they, or their ordeyners by Popish Bishops: this in part may stop the mouth of a Papist: but let a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant which doubteth of these matters move the question: and what then will they say? If they flie to popish Bishops, as they are popish, then let them goe no longer masked under the name of Protestants. If they alledge succession by them from the Apostles, then (to say nothing of the appropriating of this succession unto the Popes chaire, in whose name, and by vvhole authority our English Bishops did all things in times past) then I say they must take a great time for the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying of a poore man concerning this question, and for the justifying of their station. For untill that out of good records they can shew perpetuall succession from the Apostles unto their Diocesan which ordained them, and untill they can make the poore man which doubteth, perceiue the truth and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of those records (which I wisse they will doe at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure) they can never make that succession appeare. If they flie to the Kings authoritie, the King himselfe will forsake them, and denie that hee taketh upon him to make or call Ministers. If to the present Bishops and Arch-bishops, alas they are as farre to seeke as themselues, and much further. The proper cause of all this misery is the lifting up of a lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prelacie, upon the ruines of the Churches liberties.</p>
   <p>How intollerable a bondage is it, that a Minister being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to a charge, may not preach to his people except he hath
<pb facs="6"/>
a licence from the Bishop or Arch-bishop: Cannot receiue the best of his Congregation to communion if he be censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the spirituall Courts, though it be but for not paying of sixe pence which they required of him in any name, be the man otherwise never so innocent: nor keep one from the communion, that is not presented in those Courts, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing presented is for money absolved, though he be never so scandalous: and must often times (if he will hold his place) against his conscience put back those from communion with Christ, whom Christ doth call unto it (as good Christians if they will not kneele) and receive those that Christ putteth backe, at the command of a mortall man.</p>
   <p>What a burthen are poore Ministers pressed with, in that many hundreds of them depend upon one Bitshop and his Officers: they must hurrie up to the spirituall Court upon every occasion, there to stand with cap in hand, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Bishop, but before his Chancellour, to be railed on ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times at his pleasure: to be censured, suspended, deprived, for not observing some of those Canons, which were of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose framed for snares, when far more ancient and honest ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons are every day broken by these Iudges themselues for lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre sake, as in the making of Vtopian Ministers, who haue no people to minister unto; in their holding of commendams, in their taking of money, even to extortion, for orders and institutions: in their symonie, as well by giving as by taking: and in all their idle, covetous, and ambitious pompe? For all these and such like abuses, we are beholding to the Lordli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of our Hierarchie: which in the root of it, is heere overthrowen by M. Bayne in the conclusions of the second and third Question. About which he hath the very same con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie, that Marsilius Patavinus in part undertooke long since, about the time of Edward the second, against the Pope. For he in his booke called <hi>Defensor pacis,</hi> layeth the same grounds that here are maintained. Some of his words, though they be large, I will here set down for the Readers informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Potestas clavium sive solvendi &amp; ligandi, est essentialis &amp; inspa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilis Presbytero inquantum Presbyter est. In hac authoritate, Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus
<pb facs="7"/>
a sacerdote non differt, teste Hieronymo, imo verius Apostoi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, cuius etiam est aperta sententia. Inquit enim Hieronymus super Mat. 16. Habent quidem eandem judiciariam potestatem alii Apostoli, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet omnes Ecclesia in Presbyteris &amp; Episcopis: praeponens in hoc Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteros, quoniam authoritas haec debetur Presbytero, in quantum Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, primo, &amp; secundum quod ipsum. Haec nomina Presbyter &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopus in primitiva Ecelesia fuerunt synomina, quamvis a diversis proprietatibus eidem imposita fuerint, Presbyter ab aetate nomen imposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum est, quasi senior: Episcopus vero a dignitate, ceu cura super alios, quasi superintendens.</hi> Many things are there discoursed to the same purpose, dict. 2. c. 15. It were too long to recite all. Yet one thing is worthy to be observed how he interpreteth a phrase of Ierome so much alledged, and built upon by the Patrones of our Hierarchie. Ierome sayth ad Evagr. that a Bishop doth nothing, excepting ordination, which a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may not doe. Of this testimonie D. Downam avoucheth, that nothing can be more pregnant then it, to prove that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops were superiour to Presbyters in power of ordination. But heare what this ancient Writer saith, <hi>Ordinatio non signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat ibi potestatem conferendi, ceu collationem sacrorum ordinum: sed oeconomicam potestatem regulandi vel dirigendi Ecclesiae ritus, atque personas, quantum ad exercitium divini cultus in templo; unde ab an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquis legumlatoribus vocantur Oeconomi reverendi.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>It would be overlong to declare all the use which may bee made of this Treatise, which being it selfe so short, forbiddeth prolixitie in the Preface. If the Authour had lived to haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished his purpose in perfecting of this worke, he would (it may be) have added such considerations as these: or at least he would haue left all so cleare, that any attentive Reader might easily have concluded them from his premisses. For supply of that defect, these practicall observations are noted: which with the dispute it selfe, I leave to be pondered by the conscio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Reader.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>