<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE ROMANE Catholicke Readers.</title>
           <author>L., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102883_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05176</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15311</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102883</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE ROMANE Catholicke Readers.</title>
                 <author>L., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The anatomie of the Romane clergie: or, a discoverie of the abuses thereof. Written in Latine by sundrie authors of their owne profession. And translated into English verse by G.L</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_Catholic_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE ROMANE Catholicke Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Readers, let it not offend you, that I haue put forth in our Countrie language those things which long ago were published by men of your owne Religion and societie: It is not vnknowne to you what <hi>Ariosto</hi> that famous writer and learned Poet, borne in <hi>Lombardie,</hi> hath written in his Satires of the Court and Clergie of <hi>Rome,</hi> being familiar seruant for the time to Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth: likewise <hi>Francis Petrarch</hi> Arch-Deacon of <hi>Parma</hi> a <hi>Florentine</hi> borne, who liued in the time of <hi>Benedict</hi> the twelfth, and being great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly esteemed in his Court, was earnestly sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited by the said Pope, who offered to giue him a Cardinals Hat, if he would perswade his sister, a very faire young woman, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in <hi>Auignion</hi> to prostitute her bodie to his
<pb facs="3"/>
desire, who was desperately in loue with her, the honest man abhorring his desire and the offer, made answer, that such a filthie Hat was not to be receiued vpon such an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honest condition; and if it were not for the reuerence he bore to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> he would make his penne paint forth his kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie. After that being desired by some of his friends (who had left the Citie) to let them vnderstand the estate of the Towne there, he did write certaine Epistles <hi>sine ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo,</hi> not daring either name the writer, or to whom he wrote; out of which I haue gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the most remarkable things, and put forth to your reading in the best sort I could, as likewise the order of the Friers, written ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Virgils</hi> verse in forme of a Cento by <hi>Lelius Capilupus</hi> a Catholicke Romane: sundrie other verses are translated out of your owne Poets, such as <hi>Mantuanus</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingenius,</hi> both famous men of your owne Religion. Now seeing I giue you no inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, made either by my selfe or any other of your aduersaries, but that which was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten many yeares since by men of your owne profession, most highly addicted to your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb facs="4"/>
I doubt not but you will excuse me, who lets you see by your owne writers, what abuses haue euer bene in that Church from the beginning, and daily do increase. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider therefore with your selues, how misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly you are blinded by that Romane Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ, and pray to God to giue you the light of his Spirit, that you may see all those filthy errors, &amp; turne to his true worship. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your wellwiller and friend, G. L.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>