<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Tho. Gale Chirurgian, to the Frindly readers Salutations in Christ Iesus, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102805_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11529</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102805</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Tho. Gale Chirurgian, to the Frindly readers Salutations in Christ Iesus, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine vvorkes of chirurgerie, nevvly compiled and published by Thomas Gale, maister in chirurgerie</title>
                 <author>Gale, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gale, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hall, Rowland</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 53, 7, 5, 58, 1, 3, 19, 2, 4, 90, 8 leaves, 5 folded tables, illustrations, portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>Tho. Gale Chirurgian, to the Frindly readers Salutations in Christ Iesus, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was not without great skil &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, that the wise &amp; lerned Greciās did cal man by the name of <hi>Microcos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> which is as much to say with vs, as the lesser worlde. for the greater worlde (in Greke, <hi>cosmos</hi>) doeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist of the heauenly, &amp; elementarie region. And the lesser worlde (being man) doth vnder God, reule &amp; gouerne what so euer is them conteyned. &amp; applieth them to his vse and profite, &amp; if we shal begin firste, with that most meruaylous hande worke of God, I meane the beautiful heauenes, so woūderfully ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned &amp; decked with most confortable lightes: what els shall we iudge, but that he ruleth them, whan being placed so farre frō them distant, doth diligētly &amp; truly note &amp; obserue, not only ther motions, ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, discentions, progressions, retrogradations, stations, deuiations, declinations, coniunctions, &amp; sondry configurations: but also marketh what mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, alterations, &amp; effectes, they cause in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie region, wherby he is taught to take that which may be to his profit &amp; gayne: &amp; eschew, or els mitigate and equally beare, what is therto cōtrary. and here of it came to passe, that the great Astrota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian, <hi>Claudius Ptolomaeus</hi> durst boldly affirme that
<q>
         <pb facs="10"/>
         <l>The wise, by Prudence and good skyll.</l>
         <l>Shall rule the sterres to serue his vvill.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Yea, &amp; the wyse Philosophers and Poetes, which did deapely, and with no small iudgement beholde the figure and shape of man: howe he only among all liuyng creatures loked vpwarde to the heauens, they dyd constantly affirme, that only for that cause he had gyuen to him suche countenaunce, and that right eloquently the Poete sitteth out in theis fewe verses.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Pronaquè cum spectant animalia caetera quaequè</l>
      <l>Os homini sublime dedit, caelúm{que} videre</l>
      <l>Iussit, &amp; erectos ad Sydera tollere vultus.</l>
   </q>
   <q>
      <l>Where all thynges that doe breath,</l>
      <l>Doe on th'earth ther lookes cast:</l>
      <l>God vvhan man he dyd make</l>
      <l>gaue him so greate a grace:</l>
      <l>On Sonne, Moone, and eke Sterrys.</l>
      <l>That he his eyes might fast:</l>
      <l>Also to vein the skye.</l>
      <l>And that with vpright face.</l>
   </q>
   <p>And here by the way I gather, that this counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was not gyuen man only to gape, gase, stare, &amp; toote an the heauens: but wyselye to consider the wounderful forme &amp; frame herof, how incessantly it torneth, &amp; moueth abought the center of the yearth. &amp; that the heauens are as freshe &amp; lustie at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to fulfil ther course, as at ther first creation. and that he by considerynge them, might confesse that ther is a God, who ruleth them, &amp; hath made them to his vse &amp; profit. but let that past &amp; cume we vnto
<pb facs="10"/> the elementarie region. What thing is ther in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned which he gouerneth not, and taketh of them profit. the wyndes he gathereth in a smal cōpasse, &amp; by the forse of them, he romneth &amp; walketh on the hough Seas as on the lande. The fyshes in the greates depes he bringeth to his handes. the foules of the ayre for al ther swyfnes of winges, he getteth for his pray. Yea he subdueth one foule, &amp; teacheth it to bringe diuers others vnto hym. Example of the hauke, &amp; the partrich. suche is the diuine wisdome, &amp; greate poure giuen to this litle worlde, man, what? doeth he not subdue the most stronge &amp; ferse beastes, &amp; ouer runne those that are most swyfte? the horse beinge a coragious &amp; proud beast, for all his strenth, swyftnes, and forse in his houys, doth he not bridle and tame, and rydeth on hym like an Emperour &amp; gouernour? The mightye Lyon for all his strength, is made captiue &amp; subiecte. the hart, and hare, for all ther swyfnes, he ouertaketh. and to conclude, what beaste is it whom man hath not, or can not bryng in subiection? What saye you to the venemous ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentes, scorpions, toades, and such as are poyson to humaine nature, whiche man doth not onely van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quishe: but of them maketh healthful medicines to expell greuous infirmities. I omit for breuitie, the innumerable trees, plantes, frutes, herbes, rotes, gummes stowes, mettalls, and earthes, whose se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret natures he hath founde out, whose vertues he hath tried, &amp; whose substance he doeth rightly vse for his commoditie &amp; welth. What artes hath he inuented, what scienciens founde, and misteries
<pb facs="11"/> set out? so that of right as I suppose, I may cal man <hi>microcosmos,</hi> and the lesser worlde. But me thinke I heare one demaunde, to what ende is this longe tale of man set out. Forsoth that you may riply and duely consider what a noble and excellent substance man is of, who is the subiecte and matter on which the Phisician and Chirurgian doe worke. but as touchynge the Phisician I haue nothynge to saye, and therfore of the Chirurgian I purpose somwhat to vtter. both to warne this <hi>microcosmos</hi> man, of those who vnder the name of Chirurgians be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge els but open murtherers, and also to deface theis rude Emperikes, and to pricke fowarde the righte Chirurgian. and that you maye the easelier conceyue that which I go abought, it behoueth you to knowe, that chirurgery is moste harde and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultye to attayne vnto, and is also a longe arte, and requireth longe tyme in lernynge, and also exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syng: as both the princes of Phisicke <hi>Hippocrates &amp; Galen</hi> do testifie: and all wyse men doe also con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse. for howe can it be but difficil and longe, whan the Chirurgian must consider so many diuers tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratures of men, and hyd and secret effectes, and properties of nature in them grafted. Wherefore doeth one loue porke, an other hateth it as poyson. some abhorre chese, some frute, &amp; other some wyne? Wherfore doeth one concocte and digest meat most harde to concocte: an other is not able wyth out longe tyme to digest the easiest and lightest meates? Wherfore is one by drinkinge of wyne made loose bodied, and soluble: wher an other man can not
<pb facs="11"/> haue that benefite, no not with strōg &amp; vehement la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xatiues? furthermore, Chirurgirie for the greater part consisteth in right vse of profitable experimēts: whiche require both longe tyme in the findynge of them out, &amp; also in obteynyng ther right vse. &amp; leste you may obiecte that one may receyue experiments of other that are lerned, &amp; so easely obteyne the arte: I must say that the right vse can not so easely be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned. for to that, is required that both the Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian hymselfe be lerned &amp; wyse: and furthermore that he seeth other Chirurgians of longe experience worke, &amp; put those experimēted medicines in other right vse. This also maketh the arte longer, for that ther spring new infirmities in our dayes vnknowen to them before our time. What say you to <hi>Chamae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leontiasis,</hi> vulgarly named <hi>morbus gallicus?</hi> Who euer haue written of the nature cause, &amp; accidentes of it? which is the occasion that so many miserablye haue dyed, &amp; daily perishe of it: &amp; those that haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued helth, haue bene so small a numbre. againe the art is longer to vs Englishe men, then to other, whan as we are first constrayned to learne the latine tongue before we can attayne the myndes of those who wright of Chirurgirye. there be diuers other thinges which also maketh the arte longe: which for that I wyl not be tedious, I comit to thy discretion to consider. Nowe this I conclude, if the subiecte of Chirurgirye be so noble and excellent a creature: the arte must also be noble &amp; excellent, whiche tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to worke on it. if the art be excellent, then it
<pb facs="12"/> foloweth that it is difficult and hard. again, if it be longe: then it requireth a lōg tyme in the obteyning therof, if then that the subiecte of Chirurgiry be so noble, the art so excellent &amp; difficill: &amp; so long a time required in the gettynge therof: thou mayst easelye iudge that the rable of theis rude Emperikes (and drosse of the yearth whiche whan they can not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyse lyue choppe strayst ways in to the arte of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgirye) be no Chirurgians: but manquillers, murtherers, and robbers of the people: suche are some hosiers, taylours, fletchers, mynstrelles, sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, horsheches, Iuglers, wiches, sorceres, bandes, &amp; a rable of that secte: which wolde by lawes be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from so diuine an art, the exercise of whiche for want of knowledge, bringeth some tyme losse of member, some tyme of lyfe, and some time both of lymme &amp; life. Wherfore I do admonishe the frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reader, what so euer thou arte, that hast nede of Chirurgirye, not to trust euery runagate, &amp; him that called him selfe a Chirurgian: but consider whether he be lerned or not, demaunde of him some questiōs of his art (which if thou canst not do of thy selfe, thou shall finde diuers in my booke intitled, the Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Chirurgian) whiche if he answereth them thou mayst be the boulder to commit thy selfe to to hym. otherwyse trust hym not, though he sayth he haue cured an hundred of that infirmitie. for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentū fallax, experimētes are deceyuable. now seing by theis fewe liues, you may coniecture what a diuine and excellent art Chirurgirye is, and how thou mayst discerne and know the right Chirurgian
<pb facs="12"/> from the murtherynge and bursserly Emperike, I thinke it good in fewe wordes to set out vnto thee, what caused me to publishe theis fewe and symple labours of mine. Ther ware two thynges whiche moued and styrred me hereto (louyng reader) the first was the discharge of my talent towarde God, and dutie to my natiue countrye: the second was to helpe my Brethren Chirurgians who althoughe they are desirous to attayne ther arte, yet both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is so long, and not set out in our vsuall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, they are frustrat of ther desire, and the comon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>welth vnfurnished of men of this profession. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore musinge longe with my selfe, what parte of the art I might best set out, as most necessary for them, and most spedely to attayne the art: I founde none more conuenient then first to wright an institution of a Chirurgian, in which he myght lerne y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> theorike parte and principles of the art: which whan as I had finished and brought to an ende: I dyd not thinke good ther to stay, but thought also it a necessarye thing to compile fourme tretise, comprehending the practise of some partes of the art. Wherfore I dyd set penne to paper, &amp; wrotte an Enchiridion of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgirye, contaynyng the methode and way to cure woundes, both in similer and instrumental partes, and eke fractures and luxations, wyth a newe way, of stanchyng flux of blod with out cauterizen yrons by a pouder diuisyd by maister Perpoint &amp; me, whā as any membre is taken of from the body, &amp; is now in the hospitalles of London vsed to the great cōfort of the sicke people, and sauegarde of ther liues, wher
<pb facs="13"/> comonly before they perished and decayde. and whil I thought heare to haue stayed, behoulde warres folowed, and controuersie arose wether the cure of woundes made with comon gonnepouder &amp; shotte ware like to inuenomed woundes, or els woundes contused, whiche controuercye to decyde I thought for the tyme necessarye. and haue compiled a litle volume confutynge the aduersaries opinions, and establishynge myne owne, and yet further wayeng what want the Chirurgians had of good and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued medicines belongynge to ther arte, I dyd take out of the best authours, suche as might serue herein ther necessarie vse, addinge therto suche ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perte medicines as I had both inuented and proued. and this booke I haue called my Antidotarie. all whiche .iiij. bookes, I shall require thee hartelye to take in so good part, as I doe offer wyth free harte, and loue to profit, both the &amp; other. and heare, I may not forget maister Doctour <hi>Cunnyngham,</hi> who was no smal helpe to me in diuising the argumēts, &amp; perusynge the copies written, whose trauelles in this behalfe I cōmende to thy thākful minde louing reader. ther now reasteth no more, but to committe my woorkes with my selfe vnto thy Iudgement prayeng thee wher the errours haue escaped, both to pardon the same, &amp; also to gyue me warnynge of them. thus Doinge thou shalt encorage me duringe lyfe accordynge to my small knowledge, to trauaile in this my vocation.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Fare hartelye well louynge Reader,</salute>
      <dateline>at my poore house in London, <date>the .xij. day of September. 1563.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>