<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen Readers, Health.</title>
           <author>M., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102714_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06682</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17139</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102714</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen Readers, Health.</title>
                 <author>M., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The generall practise of medecine : Comprehending the most remarkable maxims appertaining to the diagnosis, where, by everie disease is knowne, the prognosis, whereby the issue is foreshowne, and therapie, which poynteth out the methodick, proceeding in the cure. Collected out of the most famous, both ancient and moderne wryters, for the use of such as be ignorant of the Greeke and Latine tongues. By Philiatreus</title>
                 <author>Philiatreus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wreittoun (Scribonius), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen Readers, Health.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>PAN</hi> blowing upon an oaten Pipe a litle homely musick, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring no man dispraise his simple cunning, began both to play so lowd and so long, that they were more wearie in hearing his Musick, then hee in shewing his skill, till at last to claw him and excuse themselves, they said, his Pype was out of tune. So Gentlemen, because I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tyme rashly reacht above my pitch, and yet your courtesie was such as none accused mee, I have once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine adventured upon your patience, but (I doubt) so farre as to be read of my folly, you will at the last say, as <hi>Augustus</hi> said to the Graecian that gave him oft times many rude
<pb facs="4"/>
verses: Thou hast need (quoth hee) reward mee well, for I take more paines to read thy workes, then thou to write them. But yet willing to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide this quip, because I may coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervaile it with your former courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, I put my selfe to your patience, and commits you to the Almighty. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>