<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, HENRY Lord DANVERS, Baron of Dauntesey.</title>
           <author>Garrard, Edmund</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102860_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01503</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11624</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102860</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, HENRY Lord DANVERS, Baron of Dauntesey.</title>
                 <author>Garrard, Edmund</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The countrie gentleman moderator : Collections of such intermarriages, as haue beene betweene the two royall lines of England and Spaine, since the Conquest: with a short view of the stories of the liues of those princes. And also some obseruations of the passages: with diuers reasons to moderate the country peoples passions, feares, and expostulations, concerning the Prince his royall match and state affaires. Composed and collected by Edm. Garrard</title>
                 <author>Garrard, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 67, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Heraldic works and genealogies</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, <hi>HENRY Lord</hi> DANVERS, <hi>Baron of Dauntesey.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I (poore and infortunate) should say, that I can no more forget your Noble house, I so long followed, and many Noble fauours from thence receiued: then the children of Captiuity, could forget their owne <hi>Ierusalem:</hi> if I should tell your Lorship how much I honour you, ioy at your sight, memory, and happines, liberally protesting all this, and much more; it may be thought but superficiall, and the common phrase of indigent men: But God that knoweth the secrets of all mens hearts, can witnes frō mine, it sincerely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth: If I could doe any thing worthy accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, I humbly acknowledge, it is due to your Lordship; yet howsoeuer, I here make bolde to put out vnder your Honourable Patronage, these my poore endeuours.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p> First, the Title is some way sutable to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition your Lordship now liueth in, as being (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede) more a Country Lord then a Court: If the Fate and State shall please to haue it otherwise, <hi>(Tam marti quam Mercurio)</hi> for the seruice of the King, and Countrey, amongst the rest of the Starres placed in that Spheare, your Lordship would at least contribute light: but your daily relieuing of many poore in the Country, where and for which your renowne is, done more to Gods glory then your owne; your Lordships preferment will be in a better Kingdome.</p>
   <p>Secondly, the Subiect &amp; Treatise are likewise agreeable to your Lordships loyall disposition, which is only desiring God may be truly honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, all things sute and succeede to the compleat comfort, contentment, &amp; good of the King, Prince and Kingdome: if they amongst their serious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, shall vouchsafe to looke into this worke. I humbly desire the motiue thereof might bee as from your Lordship, receiuing your fauourable acceptance, pardon for this my boldnes, and to liue esteemed</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lordships euer deuoted seruant,</hi> Edm. Garrard.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>