<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE LADIE MILDMAY.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102573_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09644</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19909</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102573</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE LADIE MILDMAY.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vertues anatomie. Or A compendious description of that late right honorable, memorable, and renowned Bedfordshire lady, the Lady Cheany, of Tuddington. By Charles Pierse</title>
                 <author>Pierse, Charles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>TO THE LADIE MILDMAY.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam, some strangenesse may possesse you, when</l>
   <l>You looke on these, and thinke vpon my pen,</l>
   <l>What vaine and high conceit my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some haunted,</l>
   <l>That would not be with such great honor daunted.</l>
   <l>Yet, kinde and vertuous Lady, let me craue</l>
   <l>What others in the like attempts may haue:</l>
   <l>You which doe represent to me her name,</l>
   <l>How can I hold you guiltlesse of her fame?</l>
   <l>But they must both concurre within your breast,</l>
   <l>To keepe for euer their most bounteous feast:</l>
   <l>No small affection shee could beare to you,</l>
   <l>Giue Honor and your owne Desarts their due:</l>
   <l>Shee lou'd you liuing, and with many graces</l>
   <l>Did fill your soule, which vertue now imbraces:</l>
   <l>VVhere Nature hath so well the workeman plai'd,</l>
   <l>And her full due to euery member pai'd;</l>
   <l>That nought doth want within her bounteous store,</l>
   <l>But lent it you to grace her glorie more.</l>
   <l>Then, faire and worthie Ladie, condescend</l>
   <l>To reade these humble lines, and fauour lend</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="10"/>To what may with your iudgement disagree,</l>
   <l>Your liking lent, can grace both it and mee:</l>
   <l>For such rare mindes with noble deeds insue,</l>
   <l>VVill aske no little wit to sing them true:</l>
   <l>'Tis no small worke, nor sleight, nor easie taske,</l>
   <l>VVherein her vertues doe so dimly maske.</l>
   <l>VVhat my defectiue pen doth want of skill.</l>
   <l>Your vertuous minde accepting, may fulfill.</l>
   <l>To whose cleare bosome I doe leaue the rest,</l>
   <l>VVhich owes you more, then can be heere exprest.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>