<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir WILLIAM WHITMORE, of Apley in Salope, Knight; And Mr. GEORGE WHITMORE of London, Alderman; Saving Health, true Honour, and eter∣nall Happinesse.</title>
           <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102969_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01537</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11662</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102969</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir WILLIAM WHITMORE, of Apley in Salope, Knight; And Mr. GEORGE WHITMORE of London, Alderman; Saving Health, true Honour, and eter∣nall Happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iacobs thankfulnesse to God, for Gods goodnesse to Iacob : A meditation on Genesis 32. 10. VVherein by the way also the popish doctrine of mans merite is discussed. By Thomas Gataker, B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith</title>
                 <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Clifton, Fulke</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 97, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir WILLIAM WHITMORE, of <hi>Apley</hi> in <hi>Salope,</hi> Knight; And M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. GEORGE WHITMORE of <hi>London,</hi> Alderman; Saving Health, true Honour, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight VVorshipfull, I stood obliged to the <hi>Stock</hi> you both sprang frō, before I was able to apprehend what such obligatiō meant. Your worthy <hi>Mother</hi> was one of those that presented mee to the <hi>sacred Laver,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
and that undertooke there in my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. Shee answered there for mee, <note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>am respon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere possem: uti Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius vert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>alm.</hi> 119.67.</note> when I could not answer for my selfe; and did further also then seale up her free affection to me with a reall testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of her Love. Neither did her kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse towards me then and there expire; but as it was oft renewed in her life time, when occasion thereof was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, so it ceased not untill her selfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased. Shee performed one of the <hi>first religious offices</hi> for mee soone after <hi>my birth</hi>: and it was one of her <hi>last pious workes</hi> to remember me, among others whom shee had performed the like <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> for, at the time of <hi>her decease.</hi> Some <hi>monument</hi> of my thankfull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement hereof being desirous to have extant, whom should I addresse it unto rather than yourselves; the onely two <hi>Principalls</hi> now left of that <hi>Family?</hi> Being therefore moved to make publike two of my weake <hi>Discourses,</hi> containing the explication of two portions of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> of some neere relation the one to the other; the one of them relating a
<pb facs="3"/>
memorable <hi>example</hi> of the <hi>performance</hi> of that that is <hi>promised</hi> in the other, to wit, <hi>of Gods blessing</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> those with <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> things, that are carefull to looke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>spirituall:</hi> This of the twaine I chose the rather to present your <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships</hi> withall; partly, because at the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the one of you,<note place="margin">The Worshipfull Company of Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdashers.</note> being then <hi>Head</hi> of that <hi>worthy Societie,</hi> which I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my selfe also <hi>a debtor</hi> unto, it was by word of mouth at first delivered; and partly also, that it may helpe (for the best also, even <note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Genes.</hi> 35.1.</note>
      <hi>Iacob</hi> himselfe, in this kinde need helps) to egge you on, whom <hi>God</hi> hath blessed with so large a portion of his bounty, unto those <hi>religious offices,</hi> that by occasion of <hi>Iacobs example,</hi> men of your rancke are therein encited unto, whether risen from meane estate, as with him here it had beene, or from the first largely and liberally endowed, as your selves. The <hi>Worke</hi> indeed is growne much larger, than at first was delivered, by reason that a <hi>Question</hi> betweene us and the <hi>Romanists,</hi> concerning <hi>Mans Merit,</hi> is therein now discussed, which
<pb facs="4"/>
was then but touched upon and poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at only; neither the streights of <hi>time</hi> admitting over-long <hi>discourse</hi> then, nor such matter of <hi>controversie</hi> so well befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>occasion</hi> that then was. The rest, without any <hi>materiall alteration</hi> or <hi>addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> is the same for <hi>substance</hi> that then it was. Which recommending entirely, as now it is, to your <hi>Worships,</hi> together with my <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Christian service</hi> to you both, and mine heartie <hi>Prayers</hi> to <hi>God</hi> for the <hi>well-fare, spirituall</hi> especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of you and yours, with the rest of the <hi>Branches</hi> of that <hi>Family,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever now transplanted; I take leave of you for the present, and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships ever in the Lord, <hi>THOMAS GATAKER.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>