<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Right Honourable HENRY Earle of Huntingdon, Lord Hastings, Hungerford, Botreaulx, Molins and Moules, and Lord Lieutenant of his Majestes County of Leicester, and Rutland, my Honoured Lord.</title>
           <author>Parkes, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102532_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09013</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19303</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102532</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Right Honourable HENRY Earle of Huntingdon, Lord Hastings, Hungerford, Botreaulx, Molins and Moules, and Lord Lieutenant of his Majestes County of Leicester, and Rutland, my Honoured Lord.</title>
                 <author>Parkes, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The rose, and lily : Delivered at the lecture, in Ashby de-la-zouch in the county of Leicester. By William Parks, Master of Arts, and curat of Chelaston in the county of Derby</title>
                 <author>Parks, William, curat of Chelaston</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Norton, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wilne, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wilne, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 48, 4, 44, 8, 44, 8, 41, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ To the Right Honourable <hi>HENRY</hi> Earle of <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> Lord <hi>Hastings, Hungerford, Botreaulx, Molins</hi> and <hi>Moules,</hi> and Lord Lieutenant of his <hi>Majestes</hi> County of <hi>Leicester,</hi> and <hi>Rutland,</hi> my Honoured <hi>Lord.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right HONOVRABLE,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not any want of Bookes in these daies of ours, wherein they doe so much abound, that moves mee to publish these my weake labours, nor yet any desire I have to shew myself
<pb facs="3"/>
in <hi>Print,</hi> J am too sensible of mine owne imperfections, to be desirous to shew them to the World. But consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering my engagments (es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to your <hi>Honour</hi>) and not willing to be altogether guilty of that hatefull sinne of ingratitude, but know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other way to expresse my thankefulnes J have pitched upon this, choose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather to shew my selfe a weake man, then ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. J must confesse I had rather be silent, then be seen in <hi>Print.</hi> And my small for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, had made me as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected in person as J was in place, untill it pleased your
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Honour</hi> to cast the beames of your countenance on mee (in giving mee part of this <hi>Lecture</hi> where these <hi>Sermons</hi> were preached) which made me a little <hi>erigere caput,</hi> to peepe up, and shew my selfe, if to no other end then this (to expresse my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes it were a sufficient cause to move mee to it. J have heere endevoured to give unto your <hi>Honour</hi> not only what <hi>Aeschines</hi> gave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Socrates</hi> (<hi>me ipsum</hi>) but even <hi>Deum ipsum</hi>: for it is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folding of some part of those Mysteries that concerne <hi>Christ</hi>; of whom your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> is a livelie member in
<pb facs="4"/>
his <hi>Church</hi> militant, and will be untill you are a full par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of all his benefits in the <hi>Church</hi> triumphant, which that your <hi>Honour</hi> may be is the prayer of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships dayly <hi>Orator,</hi> and most humbly devoted Chaplaine. WILLIAM PARKES.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>