<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102233_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10086</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2034</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102233</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Psalmes of Dauid : truly opened and explaned by paraphrasis, according to the right sense of euerie Psalme. With large and ample arguments before euerie Psalme, declaring the true vse thereof. To the which is added a briefe table, shewing wherevnto euery Psalme is particularly to be applied, according to the direction of M. Beza and Tremellius. Set foorth in Latine by that excellent learned man Theodore Beza. And faithfully translated into English, by Anthonie Gilbie, and by him newlie purged from sundrie faultes escaped in the first print, and supplied wit the principal pointes of euerie Psalme, summarilie set downe in a table at the end of the booke</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 357, 13 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO <hi>the Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>EEING among humane affaires, those men which haue good causes and sound reasons for their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prises, are of greater authoritie, and more able to persuade a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable man, than they that can render no other account, but either their owne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate opinion for a cause sufficient, or their selfe wil, how vnreasonable soeuer, for an inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible argument, or in a word, their headie rashnes for a lawe that may be in no wise gainesaied. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Translator thinketh meete to shew some reason of his doings, that that thing which was most forceable to drawe him to this translation, (who otherwise for his age is verie vnfit to take such paines) might somewhat preuaile, both to moue other that are more apt for such matters to do the like, and thee also the Christian Reader to a more attentiue consideration of those things, that are most diuinelie set foorth in this Booke. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore these two causes especiallie brought him to take this worke in hand. First loue to his vnlearned countriemen. Secondlie, the excellencie of the worke it selfe. For considering that the Psalmes in English are in manie places read rather for taske as it were, and for fashion sake, than for good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion and with vnderstanding, which the spirit of God commandeth in al partes of diuine seruice: and because that to reade that which a man nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet vnderstandeth, nor seeketh ordinarie meanes whereby hee may vnderstand, is a plaine contempt of the thing that is read, in that it noteth want of care, and therefore defect of loue, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequentlie the hypocrisie of him that serueth God careleslie. Againe (such is the miserable state of
<pb facs="6"/> our nation) seeing that euerie congregation hath not a sufficient pastor to explane and interprete these Psalmes, (as also other places of scripture) with liuelie voice of man (the principal and chiefe way that ought to be in the Church to edifie the conscience, and to build the faith,) therefore the Translator receiuing this Booke, which was come from farre, euen from a strange Countrie, and in a language vnknowne to the multitude, he was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued none otherwise than as a louing friend is wont to impart to his louers that thing, which he kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth may be profitable to manie, and so set forth in our vulgar speach that thing wherof otherwaies they that haue greatest neede, should haue reaped the least commoditie, in so much as now euen the simplest poore man for a smal peece of monie, may by diligent reading in this Booke of that rare man THEODORE BEZA, atteine to a better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of these holie Psalmes of Dauid, than in old time (by the report of the ancient) the great learned men were able, by the perusing of manie of the great Doctors of the Church. Further, sith we see this also by dailie experience, that what so euer we knowe, whether it be in flieng newes tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this or that matter, whereof mans mind is so desirous, or else euen in the Artes and Sciences which are gotten by great exercise and long pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise, a man taketh a little or no pleasure in them, so long as he keepeth them to himselfe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no man priuie to them: but so soone as he vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth them to others whome he loueth, then his ioy and pleasure increaseth, and he accounteth his owne knowledge so much the greater, the more that he hath participated it vnto other. Euen so this Translator, hauing viewed this Booke through out, could not be silent, but receiuing so great comforts himselfe thereby, tooke in hand (God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thereto good successe) to make it manifest al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
<pb facs="6"/> to the common sort, that they might al reioice together in the Lord, hauing found so precious a iewel, which hath afore time bene hid from our forefathers, and is in our daies reuealed vnto vs by the goodnes of God. And he thinketh his labour wel bestowed, and his knowledge and comfort greatlie augmented, and aboundance of fruite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounding to himselfe, if his godlie purpose be wel accepted, that is, if it be generalie receiued, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerentlie embraced (as by right it ought) of them of whome chiefelie in his trauel he had respect. Now as concerning the matter that is translated, we neede not speake manie words, it of it selfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing plentifullie garnished with most heauenlie sentences, as with most precious margarites, and furnished with al things necessarie, either for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction touching this present life, or for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to the world to come, is sufficientlie able to commend it selfe to the godlie Reader: onelie this I saie, that whereas there be two special kinds of explaning the Scriptures, one in long Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, another by Paraphrasis, that is, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ful sense and meaning of the holie Ghost in other words, as briefelie as may be, this later is verie ancient (as we may see by that most ancient Chalde Paraphrast, who seemeth to haue written before anie of the Hebrew Rabbines) and most safe to certifie the consciences, when euerie thing appeareth plainelie to answere the verie text and original, and must needes be most profitable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it giueth that matter in few words, which manie times can not be learned by long Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries. Therefore I do exhort you, good Christian Readers, deepelie to consider, and thankefullie to receiue this Paraphrasis of that great and godlie learned man THEODORE BEZA, as a most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Booke for the vnderstanding of the Psalmes. So shal both your owne knowledge rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="7"/> of the labours of others be much augmented, and manie to take the like paines wil be encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, when they shal perceiue a godlie commoditie arising, to counteruaile and recompence their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel emploied for the increase of the kingdome of Christ, whome I beseech to direct al his poore flocke in the whole time of their pilgrimage, to cleaue vnto him their shepeheard and safe keeper, and that he would send it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort sufficient, to strengthen the hearts of his children against al the miseries and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>