<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Rea∣der, and Especially to all such as haue any Coppies of the workes of Maister Perkins, or intend any of them to the Presse.</title>
           <author>Evans, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102894_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09445</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19733</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102894</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Rea∣der, and Especially to all such as haue any Coppies of the workes of Maister Perkins, or intend any of them to the Presse.</title>
                 <author>Evans, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the calling of the ministerie : two treatises, discribing the duties and dignities of that calling. Delivered publickly in the Vniuersitie of Cambridge, by Maister Perkins. Taken then from his mouth, and now dilligently perused and published, by a preacher of the word wit a preface prefixed touching the publishing of Maister Perkins his workes, &amp; a catalogue of all such particulars thereof, as are to bee expected</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Welby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>76, 127, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and Especially to all such as haue any Coppies of the workes of Maister Perkins, or intend any of them to the Presse.</head>
   <p>FOrasmuch as there hath beene lately signification made, of diuers of Maister Perkins his workes heereafter to bee printed, in an Epistle to the Reader prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised before the Treatise of <hi>callings,</hi> and that signification beeing but generall, might peraduenture giue occasion to some, to set out some particulars (without the consent of Maister Perkins his assignes) as imperfectly as are these two bookes, intituled <hi>The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of couetousnesse,</hi> &amp; <hi>The prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of faith,</hi> iustly and truly (for ought that I see) censured in the aforesaid Epistle: It is therefore now thought good, to mention the particular Treatises, and workes of his, which shall heereafter (if God will) be published, for the benefit of Gods Church: I doe therefore heereby make knowne to all, whom it any way may concerne, that there were found in the studie of the deceased and are in the hands of his Executors, or assignes, and preparing
<pb facs="7"/>
for the Presse.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1</hi> His Expositions on the Epistle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> the <hi>Galathians.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2</hi> on the Epistle of <hi>Iude.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2</hi> His Booke of the <hi>Cases of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3</hi> His Treatises <hi>1</hi> of <hi>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>chcraft.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2</hi> of <hi>Callings.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>All these he had perused himselfe, and made them ready for the presse, according to which coppies by himselfe so corrected, some of them already are, and the rest will be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished in due time: And heereuppon we desire all men who haue coppies of these, or any of them, not to offer that wrong to that worthy man of God, as to publish any of their owne, seeing the coppies heereof which are to bee printed, are of his owne correcting: but rather if they can helpe to make any of them more perfect by their coppies, they may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doe a good worke to the benefit of many, and much comfort to themselues.</p>
   <p>And further, I doe heereby make knowne, that I haue in my hands at this present, of his workes, taken from his mouth, with my owne hand, heereafter (if God will) to bee pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, with the allowance of our Church, and for the benefit of his children, these particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <pb facs="7"/>1 His Expositions or readings, on the 110 <hi>Psalme.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2</hi> On the 32 <hi>Psalme.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3</hi> On the 11 Chapter to the <hi>Hebrewes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4</hi> on the <hi>1, 2,</hi> &amp; 3, Chapters of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="5">5 on the 5, 6, and 7 Chapters of Saint <hi>Mathew.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2 His Confutation of <hi>Camsius</hi> his little Popish <hi>Catechisme.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">3 His Treatises 1 of <hi>Imaginations</hi> out of Genes. 8, 2.</p>
   <p n="2">2 of <hi>Temptations</hi> out of Mathew 4.</p>
   <p n="3">3 of <hi>Christian Equity</hi> out of Phillip, 4, 3.</p>
   <p n="4">4 of the <hi>Callings of the Ministerie,</hi> out of 2 places of Scripture.</p>
   <p n="5">5 of <hi>Repentance</hi> out of <hi>Zephaniah</hi> 2, 1.</p>
   <p>Besides many other particular <hi>Sermons,</hi> and short discourses made vpon seuerall, and speciall occasions: of all which seme are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie published by others, and some by my selfe: and all the rest that remaine, as they be the Iewels of Gods Church, so doe I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly dedicate them to the publicke and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall good. Iudging it were a foule sinne in me, or any other, to <hi>impropriate</hi> to our selues,
<pb facs="8"/>
or our owne priuate vse, the labours of <hi>This</hi>▪ or any other learned man, which are in my opinion, parts of the <hi>Treasurie</hi> of the mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Church: And as it were wrong <hi>to the Church,</hi> if I should conceale them, so doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse were it <hi>to him</hi> and his children: if I should publish them for my owne alone, and not for their benefit. If I doe, I thinke it may bee iustly sayd vnto me, or whosoeuer doth so, <hi>Thy monie perish with thee.</hi> And what heerein I haue sayd for <hi>my selfe:</hi> I knowe I may boldly and safely say, for those his Executors or assignes, which haue or had in their hands, any of those which were found in his study: In the publishing of all which, as we doe intend to deale truly with the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader, and not to commit any thing to the presse, which hath not either beene <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> or <hi>corrected,</hi> by <hi>the Author</hi> himselfe, or faithfully <hi>penned</hi> according to the truest coppies taken from his owne mouth, and since by others of sufficiency &amp; integritie, diligently perused: so we purpose to referre them to the benefit of the <hi>Authors</hi> wife and children, as much as may be, wishing that vpon this caue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at man would not be so hastie (as some haue beene) to commend to the world, their <hi>vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect notes,</hi> vppon a base desire of a little
<pb facs="8"/>
gaine, both to hinder the common good of the Church, and to defraude the sayd parties of their priuate benefit, to whom in all equity &amp; Conscience, it doth principally appertaine: And desiring all, who haue any <hi>perfect</hi> Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of such as are in my <hi>owne hands,</hi> that they would either helpe <hi>me</hi> with theirs, or rather take <hi>mine</hi> to helpe them. That by our ioynt powers and our forces layd together: the walls of this worthy building, may goe vp the fairer and the faster. And so I commend them all to Gods blessing, who endeuour to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themselues, and their labours to God and to his Church.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your brother in the Lord. W. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>