<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST RE∣VEREND FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE Lord Archbishop of Canterburie his Grace, Primate of all England, and Metropolitane; And one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Councell: All sauing graces, wished in this life, and all during Glorie in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102313_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07286</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17681</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102313</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST RE∣VEREND FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE Lord Archbishop of Canterburie his Grace, Primate of all England, and Metropolitane; And one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie Councell: All sauing graces, wished in this life, and all during Glorie in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Grieving of Gods spirit : Contayning the summe of a sermon preached at Saint Maries in Oxford. The chiefe points intreated on are, Viz. I. Of grieuing of Gods Spirit. II. Of resisting of Gods Spirit. III. Of blaspheming of Gods Spirit, in the highest degree commonly called, the sinne against the Holy Ghost. By Radford Mauericke, minister in Devon. Reade iudiciously, but iudge charitably</title>
                 <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 24 pages, coat of arms, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE Lord Archbishop of <hi>Canterburie</hi> his Grace, Primate of all <hi>England,</hi> and Metropolitane; <hi>And one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuie</hi> Councell: All sauing graces, wished in this life, and all during Glorie in the life to come.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MOST REVEREND,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow much the Ministers of the Gospell within your Graces Prouince, haue and doe continually reioyce of your preferment to this place, and how many zealous Prayers are made vnto God, for your Graces long and happie continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance therein, I the least, and one of the lowest among them, can partly report: But my purpose is not to prayse, but in all humilitie to pray your Grace, so farre to bee pleased, as to permit with your accustomed fauour, This poore Mite, of a Ministers good meaning, to be cast into the rich Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surie of our English Church; And with more speciall
<pb facs="3"/>regard, to suffer these two first Sermons, preached long sithence in your Graces presence, to passe vnder the wings of your fauourable protection, being not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imboldned hereunto by your Graces late remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them, but euen incouraged to publish them in print, which the importunitie of some this long time could hardly gaine at my hands.</p>
   <p>But now old age hauing taken hold on mee, and my selfe hauing no children, by naturall generation, I haue thought it meet to collect together, into one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, or Continent, my little Babes or Bookes, which yet wander abroad in the wide World, single by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues; with such other, as my little leisure, and lesse learning could bring forth, to keepe them companie: hoping they may yeeld me some comfort, in the shutting up of my dayes, aswell as profit others (if please God) so long as this day of saluation lasteth.</p>
   <p>Thus commending my poore endeuours to Gods rich blessing, and your worthy Grace, to Gods gracious protection; with bended knees, I most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly take my leaue; and euer remaine,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces, in all humble dutie at command, RAFFORD MAVERICKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>