<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Introduction to the se∣cond part of the Parallele, or conference of the Ciuill Law, the Common Law &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102691_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B13659</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11415a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102691</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Introduction to the se∣cond part of the Parallele, or conference of the Ciuill Law, the Common Law &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the Parallele, or conference of the ciuill law, the canon law, and the common law of this realme of England : Wherein the agreement and disagreement of these three lawes touching diuers matters not before conferred, is at large debated and discussed. Whereunto is annexed a table contayning the principall Questions, matters, and pointes of the Dialogues ensuing. Handled in seauen dialogues, by William Fulbecke</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wight, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 74, 8 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Introduction to the <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of the Parallele, or</hi> conference of the Ciuill Law, <hi>the Common Law &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Omomathes,</hi> when the first con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the three Lawes was finished, gaue himselfe to his recreation, which was the hunting of the Bucke, an exercise commendable for Gentlemen, and vsed in auncient time of them, whose high estates had entitled them with the names of <hi>Heroes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Semidei.</hi> But when winter began to shed his cold influence, and to replenish the aire with congealing vapours, to make the earth as it were a naked beldam, and to cause the dugges of the sea to swell with surg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing billowes, <hi>Nomomathes</hi> retired to his bookes, and gaue a farewel to the fields, betrothing himselfe that winter to his studie. And because the iuice of the late conference of the Lawes had turned to good bloud in his mind, he meant to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continue the conference, of which he had a more strict regard then of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer:
<pb facs="4"/> For when it was rumord in the countrie where <hi>Nomomathes</hi> dwelt, that such a conference was had: and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward certain copies were dispersed, and diuulgated, some were wel pleased, some were discontented with the Dialogues: <hi>Pro captu lectoris habent sua fata libelli.</hi> Amongst the rest that were discontēted was a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, a plaine countrie man, and a gentle man not vnlearned, who when they had heard, that <hi>Nomomathes</hi> meant to reuiue and recontinue the conference, purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to go to his house, and to open their mindes as they conceiued of the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. Their purpose they followed, and to the house they came, where beeing kindly and curteouslie entertained of <hi>Nomomathes,</hi> and in their by-talke glaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing at the Dialogues: <hi>Nomomathes</hi> willed them to spare no speech, and professed that hee would willinglie admit their censures, and that he would heare them in order: They seeing his patience pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, deliuered in few words their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate conceits. And first the gentleman
<pb facs="5"/> tooke exception to the discourses of <hi>Codicgnostes:</hi> for that he in the first Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, discussing matters of common weale, and of the Ciuill Law, did forget to handle verie important matters, and to his profession not impertinent. The first was because hee did not treat of Dettes, a thing in the Ciuill Law not omitted: and yet in no Law sufficiently debated. Secondly, he speaketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Accompts or reckonings, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as that is a large and frequent title in the Ciuill Law. Lastly speaking <hi>ex professo</hi> of the originall of Tenures and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices in the fourth Dialogue, he spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth verie little of Conditions, which verie often are the constituent causes of these Seruices: With this he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and then spake the Parson, who did expostulate with the <hi>Canonist</hi> some iniuries, because the Canon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so full and pregnant in matter of Tythe, hee did not vouchsafe to speake anie one woord of Tythes: And whereas we haue Parsons said he,
<pb facs="5"/> haue much impediment by <hi>Prohibitions,</hi> and many times wrong, when they come to triall: for the countrie people which are the Iurors, who haue no more desire to paie their Tythes, then the Diuel hath to lose his entercourse with the seauen deadly sinnes; the Pope to be a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, and a Beare to go to the stake. If any Prohibition concerning Tythes come to be tried by them, ar as sure to passe against the Parson, as an old chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is sure of blacknes. But let any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter come to be tried touching common, which concerneth themselues, and their owne profit, they will as surelie go with the commoner, as the cloudes goe with the Northeast wind: Therefore it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to him to be verie conuenient, that because the Canon doth so much fauour Parsons, that therefore the Canonist es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially should haue debated at large of these matters: And he thought the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonist speaking so little of them in the whole discourse, was much troubled with the tooth-ache, (the Canonist here
<pb facs="6"/> being somewhat cholericke interrupted him, and said he iangled: for he said there were manie thinges proposed in the Dialogues, which the Canon Law neuer medleth with all, neither hath it so much tasted of them, as the dogge licking of <hi>Nilus:</hi> And in some thinges which were in the Dialogues, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law hath nothing els, but which the Ciuill Law hath: so that he should not haue kept <hi>decorum,</hi> but should haue thrust his sicle into the haruest of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicgnostes,</hi> if he should haue encroched vpon such thinges, as the Canon Law hath as it were at the second hand strei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the Ciuill. But, said he, as touching Tythes, if any question had been proposed, I would not haue been defectiue in the handling them at large. Then the poore Countrie man made a lowe conge, and <hi>Nomomathes</hi> bowed vnto him, as being willing to heare him. Sir (quoth he) I am by your worships fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour a poore countrie yeoman, dwelling neare a place called <hi>Aitipolis:</hi> and my
<pb facs="6"/> yeares are more then my knowledge, my patrimonie better then my education, and my hand more nimble then my toong: And I haue had a verie great desire to haue some vnderstanding of Lawe, because I would not swim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the streame, nor be vnlike vnto my neighbours, who are so full of Law-points, that when they sweat, it is nothing but Law; when they breath, it is nothing but law; when they neese it is perfite law; when they dreame it is profound law. The booke of <hi>Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons tenures</hi> is there breakfast, their din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, their boier, their supper, and their rere-banquet: Euerie plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swayne with vs may bee a Seneschall in a Court Baron: Hee can talke of Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soines, Vouchers, Withernams, and Recaptions: And if you controll him, the booke of the Groundes of the Law is his portesse, and readie at his gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to confute you. Surelie sir, my neyghbours are full of sension and tention, and so cunninge, that they
<pb facs="7"/> will make you beleeue, that all is gold, which glistereth: So that for a man to be amongest them, and to haue lyuing and want Law: is as if a man should haue bread to eate, and want teeth to chew it: Which occasions mooued me at the first to seek for some skill in Law, and amongest other bookes, I bought <hi>The Conference of Law,</hi> whereof hath been spoken, and casting mine eie vpon the diall of common wronges, and tres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passes: I wondered that he which main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth the Common Law, amongest his common wronges and trespasses, he spoke nothing of Wast done in a mans ground: and verie little of an Action vpon the case, which is a wheele much turned about in the place where I dwel. And though hee hath deliuered much of Iointenants, and Tenants in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, he speaketh either little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all of Parceners. Now manie of vs countrie people marrie verie often with landed women, and therefore would gladly be seene in that learning.
<pb facs="7"/> Truely Sir I bought the booke for my more vnderstanding of the law, and for the noueltie, and because it was in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish: yet there is a vengeance deale of Latin in it, which put mee to the cost to buy a <hi>Thomases</hi> Dictionarie, but it is no great matter for that, for it wil serue my sonne <hi>Reginold,</hi> when he shall bee tenne yeares olde, or thereabout: But I pray you sir at the next conference let vs haue somewhat of these matters, which I haue mentioned vnto you: When hee had ceased to speak, <hi>Nomomathes</hi> grauely and with aduise censured their censures, and spoke in this manner. I see now (saide he) the prouerbe to be verified <hi>Quot ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines tot sententiae.</hi> there be as many minds as there bee men; And though ye haue deliuered your exceptions in sportfull manner, which as I doe not greatly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, so I do not greatly delight in, yet I must confesse euerie of them doth flie to the marke, and the blame resteth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, who might haue proposed these matters to be discussed; but because the
<pb facs="8"/> lucre, or losse of the conference, was to redownd wholly to mee in all corres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondencie of reason, and not to others, but by my curtesie: I thought it a more conuenient course, and more free and ingenious to follow the threed of mine owne choise, then the vncertaine winge of popular conceit. Againe, all things cannot be handled at all times, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to be intruded into such a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference which doth not relice to the sū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie palates, and tastes of these seuerall lawes. For many things there be in the common law which hath not any affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie with any thing in the ciuill or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. But because your motions are so cōsonant to reason, &amp; so directly respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue to your vocations and functions, which in no well ordered cōmon weale ought to be loosely regarded: therfore I protest vnto you in sinceritie, that if all these things, which you haue mētioned may be cast in the molde of a tripartite discourse, the secōd cōferēce shall bring forth that which you haue before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited,
<pb facs="8"/> they thanking him for this kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse departed, he immediatly questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Lawyers, whether they could bring into the compasse of their seuerall reckonings all these matters abouesaid, who anusweared that they could. Then said he, because the <hi>Canonist</hi> hath bene so deeply charged, we will begin with tiths which he is reproued for omitting. Thē the <hi>Canonist</hi> said, that they might be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursed vpon according to the seuerall lawes vnder the title of prohibitiō. That title thē said <hi>Nomomat.</hi> shal be the first: the second of actions vpō the case: the third of debts, the fourth of accounts, the fift of wast, the sixth of parceners, and the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth of cōditions, wherfore bend your selues wholly to this taske, and let these things be diligently searched &amp; conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of you, and for this purpose take the deliberation of twentie daies: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had, and the twentie daies being run out, <hi>Nomomathes</hi> did thus parle with <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologus.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>