<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY WOR∣THILY RESPECTED FRIENDS, NATHANIEL FINCH, IOHN FORD, Esquires; Mt. HENRY BLVNT, Mr. ROBFRT ELLICE, and all the rest of the Noble Society of Grayes Inne.</title>
           <author>Ford, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102509_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01055</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11163</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102509</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY WOR∣THILY RESPECTED FRIENDS, NATHANIEL FINCH, IOHN FORD, Esquires; Mt. HENRY BLVNT, Mr. ROBFRT ELLICE, and all the rest of the Noble Society of Grayes Inne.</title>
                 <author>Ford, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The louers melancholy : Acted at the Priuate House in the Blacke Friers, and publikely at the Globe by the Kings Maiesties Seruants</title>
                 <author>Ford, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 86, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THILY RESPECTED FRIENDS, NATHANIEL FINCH, IOHN FORD, Esquires; M<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. HENRY BLVNT, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. ROBFRT ELLICE, and all the rest of the Noble Society of <hi>Grayes</hi> Inne.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Honour'd Friends,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>THe account of some leisurable houres, is here summ'd vp, and offered to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. <hi>Importunity</hi> of Others, or <hi>Opinion</hi> of mine owne, hath not vrg'd on any confidence of running the hazard of a censure. As plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath reference to a Multitude, so, I care not to please Many: but wh<gap reason="illegible: under-inked" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re there is a Parity of condition, there the freedom of constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, makes the best musicks. This concord hath equally held betweene <hi>YOV THE PATRONES,</hi> and <hi>ME THE PRESENTOR.</hi> I am cleer'd of all scruple of dis-respect on your parts; as I am of too slacke a Merit in my selfe. My presumption of comming in Print in this kind, hath hitherto been vn-reprooueable. <hi>This Piece,</hi> being the <hi>first,</hi> that euer
<pb facs="3"/>
courted Reader; and it is very possible, that the like complement with Me, may soone grow out of fashion. A practice of which that I may auoid now, I commend to the continuance of <hi>your Loues,</hi> the memory of <hi>HIS,</hi> who without the protestation of a seruice, is readily your Friend,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN FORD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>