<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Author to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Wright, Leonard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102797_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15762</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26032</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102797</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Author to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Wright, Leonard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pilgrimage to paradise : Compiled for the direction, comfort, and resolution of Gods poore distressed children, in passing through this irkesome wildernesse of temptation and tryall. By Leonard Wright. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Wright, Leonard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 58, 2 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Author to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a true saying (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) man doth purpose, but God doth dispose. For I had no sooner determined in discharge of my dutie to frame this litle volume: but that vpon speciall occasion offered by some of Satans broode (who vnder an hipocriticall shew of Religion, sought to corrupt the pure doctrine of the Gospell, deface the ministerie, and subuert the state of Ecclesiasticall gouernement:) I was moued in zeale of conscience to stay my former pretence. And rather (as time then required) to apply my indeuours to the preuenting of eminent daungers: as in my late published labour intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>A Sommons for sleepers: A Patterne for Pastors: A Display of dutie: and The Hunting of Anti-christ: with A friendly admonition to Martin Marprelate, and his Mates,</hi> may plainely appeare. Tending chiefely to awake and stirre vp to repentance and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, such wicked and notorious offenders as are most grieuous to the Church, and noysome
<pb facs="4"/>
to the common wealth. And to put all states and degrees of people in minde of their office and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to God, their Prince and countrie. And now to proceede as one alwayes willing and desirous what in me lyeth, to further the glorie of God, and profite his children: I haue at length fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed this my first pretended worke: as a meane to incourage, strengthen &amp; direct in the right path to eternal felicity, such weary wādring Pilgrims: as yet are weake in faith, doubtfull in conscience, or distressed in minde. Crauing thus much at thy handes (courteous Reader) that if it shall please the Lorde in mercie so effectually to blesse and fructifie these my simple trauailes, as by the helpe and meanes thereof, thou shalt conceiue in thy soule that spirituall comfort and heauenly conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which in heart I wish thee: then yeelde dutifull thankes to the highest, and charitably pray for me.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>vale in Christo. L. Wright.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>