<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102097_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14660</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24962</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102097</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English pharise, or religious ape : Being the weekes worke of a poore vnlearned professor of the gospell of Christ, zealously and truely checking the counterfeit professor, but open persecutor of Christs true doctrine and disicpline. By Iohn Walker, dwelling at Leeds in Yorkshire</title>
                 <author>Walker, John, dwelling at Leeds in Yorkshire</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>50, 187, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="22"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE</hi> or vngentle Reader, I am to tell thee no strange thing, onely to tell thee of that which hath been from the beginning, which is now at this present, and which shall be vnto the worlds end; how that as <hi>Esau</hi> hated his brother
<pb facs="23"/>
      <hi>Iacob</hi> in the beginning of the world, how that the Israel of God is ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted still, and that the members of Christ shall be hated, so long as the Sunne and Moone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth. Faithfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, I was enbolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Spirit of G O D, to write this little Booke for thy good, it was intended chiefly for thy profit, and so many as l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ve the peace of Sion. And
<pb facs="23"/>
whereas by Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, wee are liuing in the very latter ende of the world, and left here by Gods prouidence, as a very few Sheepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst many Woolues, I haue onely, by the helpe of Gods Spi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> it, set down vnto thy view, not only what great danger thou art in, but likewise let thee see, how that thou mayest escape the same. And although our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are many in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb facs="24"/>
and at the first sight not easily discer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, because they goe in sheepes clothing; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue set downe in plaine and few wordes, the difference of the Spirit of truth from the spirit of error, whereby thou ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>st truly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the tree by his fruite: for he that hath a true and liuely faith in Christ, is alwaies rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to manifest the same by loue and charitie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="24"/>
the Brethren. Now for him that saith, hee hath faith, &amp; yet wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth this duty of loue and charity, <hi>his faith is but a dead faith,</hi> and as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> saith, shall preuaile nothing, <hi>Iam. 5. 14.</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee that doth not practise this second les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of charitie, let him bee what hee will, and flatter himselfe neuer so much, hee is no better then a breaker of that
<pb facs="25"/>
vnion and fellowship, which ought to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Christ; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> saith, <hi>such is gone from vs, 1.</hi> Iohn <hi>2. 19. being,</hi> as S. <hi>Iude</hi> saith, <hi>separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> Iude 9. verse. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising,</hi> as S. <hi>Peter</hi> saith, <hi>libertie vnto thēselues, 2.</hi> Pet. <hi>2. 19. Hauing,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>but a shew of godlinesse, denying the power thereof,</hi>
      <pb facs="25"/>
      <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>3. 5. Therfore,</hi> saith he, <hi>turne away from such.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faithfull Christian, whose number is but small, let mee intreate thee, as thou tenderest thy owne soule, to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carefull and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, to keepe in this candle of loue, especially vnto thy brethren, then shalt thou haue peace of conscience in this world, and euerlasting peace in the world to come: but
<pb facs="26"/>
deferre no time, for our time is but very short, and if thou profit any thing herein, giue God praise, and thou hast gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me good satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and thus vnto all those that truly loue the Gospell, the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and guide with his grace. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thine in Christ,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I. W.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>