<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>B. G. To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102867_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01507</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11629</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102867</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>B. G. To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A newyeares gifte : dedicated to the Popes Holinesse, and all Catholikes addicted to the Sea of Rome: preferred the first day of Ianuarie, in the yeare of our Lorde God, after the course and computation of the Romanistes, one thousand, fiue hundreth, seauentie and nine, b B.G. citizen of London: in recompence of diuers singular and inestimable reliques, of late sent by the said Popes Holinesse into England, the true figures and representations whereof, are heereafter in their places dilated</title>
                 <author>B. G. (Bernard Garter)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, folded plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="another_preface_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>
      <hi>B. G.</hi> To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou séest (right gentle Reader) in the fourtéene short lines last before written, the argumente of the Booke or Letter whiche was written to Cardinall <hi>Poole,</hi> which my right Worshipfull and approued good friend, when he had perused, and ioyed to sée and reade, desired greately to perticipate his benefite vnto thée, chiefly bycause the wéede whiche at that time choked the minds of the subiects of the triumphant King of immortal memorie, <hi>Henry</hi> the eyght, our late Soueraigne Lorde, touching the Supremacie, now eftsoones breaketh forth, to the intollerable annoy of the déere and louing sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of our most dread, naturall, and soueraigne Lady <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> by the grace of God, Quéene of <hi>Englande, France,</hi> and <hi>Irelande,</hi> defendor of the faith, and in earthe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> next and immediately vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Christ, the sole, and alonely supreme head, the daughter and vndoubted heire of hir saide late father, King <hi>Henry</hi> the eyght. But what haue I said? <hi>Supreme head in earth, of the Church of England and Ireland next vnder Christ?</hi> Yea forsooth, what make you then of the <hi>Popes</hi> holynesse may be your demaund: I aunswere, that I make of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Rome</hi> (so farre forthe as he be a Christian, and the seruaunt of God) the like and as large accompt for his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit (though not with so great dutie, bycause I am an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishman, and not of his Dioces) as I make of any Bishop in <hi>Englande</hi> within his iurisdictiō, vnder oure sayde Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lady, so long as the same Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> kéepeth him within his compasse, and acknowledgeth himselfe sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the King of that Territorie: but so farre forth, as he standeth harlot like vpon the type of hys worldly pompe, I take him to be that <hi>Antechrist,</hi> whiche <hi>Paule</hi> calleth the man of Sinne, and child of perditiō. You may further aske me, <hi>howe if</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> himselfe be King there? I answere, that <hi>how if,</hi> with <hi>how if not:</hi> for if Christ, whose Uicar on


<pb facs="8"/>
earth the <hi>Pope</hi> claymeth to be sayth, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 18. <hi>My King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is not of this world:</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> (if he be not <hi>Antechrist</hi>) can not haue kingdome in this world. Me thinkes I sée the Papist smile in his sléeue (for in déede he is a smooth faced fellowe) at this my simple conuersion, saying, that I haue framed a goodly argument, that is, bycause the Kingdome of Christ is not of the world, therefore the <hi>Popes</hi> holynesse may not be a King in Christendome, as if it should be said, bycause y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Kingdome of <hi>HENRYE</hi> the eyght reached not ouer <hi>Europe,</hi> therfore <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> his right heire, may not be Quéene of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> Let me smile wyth him againe (I pray you) for I will yéelde him that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in Christendome, which Christ did weare the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Crowne of: let him likewise yéelde to euery King roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie in his owne Kingdome. That I will yéelde it, the Papist laugheth agayne, and so must I to, for in déede, for me to yéeld to the <hi>Pope</hi> a terrestiall Crowne in earth, and for the <hi>Pope</hi> to yéeld vnto me a celestiall Crowne in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, haue both like warrant, and like follie, and may be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually laughed at, if damnable things include iest: for I, without treason to my Prince, can not thinke the one, nor he, without Treason to Christ, grant the other: for Christ hathe reserued the Spirituall Supremacie of his vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall Churche vnto himselfe, and the terrestiall gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his people to earthly Princes, vnder whome they are gouerned, and tryed as golde in the furnace: and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie is that lande and people, whyche haue a godly Prince on earthe, to beare the sway, and haue Supremacie héere nexte vnder God: and amongst the happyest, we English<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men most happie, in our gracious Quéene <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> whose lyfe and Supreme gouernemente, I beséeche the almighty Lorde long to continue ouer vs. And the same God, for hys Chrystes sake, hathe bestowed that supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie on oure Quéene within hyr owne Realmes, whiche the <hi>Pope</hi> falsely chalengeth, through all Christian Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.


<pb facs="8"/>
For there is no power but of God, and therevppon Sainte <hi>Peter</hi> sayeth in hys firste Epistle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> the seconde Chapter, as in the former Preface is allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, <hi>Be yee subiect to all humane ordinance for the Lords sake, whether it be vnto the King, as to the most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lente. &amp;c.</hi> Nowe if the Kyng bée most excellente, who maye bée hys supreme? If <hi>Peter</hi> (whose successoure the <hi>Pope</hi> claymeth to bée) dothe putte it from hymselfe to the Kyng, howe then can the <hi>Pope</hi> wythout shame, chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge it? sithence in the spirite of truth, <hi>Peter</hi> (foreséeyng the Pryde of the <hi>Pope</hi>) séemed, before any <hi>Pope</hi> was, to forewarne of the incomprehensible Pryde of the same <hi>Pope.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thou mayest aske of me, by what authoritie the Kings of the earthe holde thys supremacie? I saye, the wordes of Saincte <hi>Peter</hi> graunte it. Thou sayest agayne, that texte is often alleadged. I aunswere, thys little Booke following wyll shewe thée manye other authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to that purpose it is imprinted agayne. But by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause thou shalte not runne emptie so farre, lette mée demaunde of thée a question or two. Who delyuered to the <hi>Israelites</hi> the Lawe of God? <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieste thou wilte saye, and true. Of whome dyd <hi>Aaron</hi> receyue it? of <hi>Moyses</hi> thou knowest. And of whome dyd <hi>Moyses</hi> take it? euen from the holy hande of Almightie GOD. When Idolatrie fell amongst the <hi>Israelites,</hi> who redressed it? not <hi>Aaron</hi> I warrante you, but <hi>Moyses</hi>? who directed the Arke of God I pray you? no Priest of them all I assure thée, but Kyng <hi>Dauid</hi> hymselfe. And thus from tyme to tyme, and at all tymes, the Kyng from the hande of God, and the Priest from the King, receyueth authoritie. <hi>Vnus est enim Legislator &amp; Iudex, qui potest perdere &amp; liberare. For there is one Lawgiuer, which can destroy and saue.</hi> He wil not varie, his word is permanēt. He hath appointed al earthly power to the Kings of the earth, &amp; their hearts are


<pb facs="9"/>
in his hande. Then reade this little booke, and be fully sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the premises. But bycause the grauity of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, only admonish an Archtraytor to renoūce his follie, &amp; againe, to become subiect to his liege soueraigne Lorde, whose bounty the traytour had largely felte, and whose li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitye he had with treacherie requited: I summon thy déepe iudgement, perfectly to ponder both the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to satisfie thy selfe in that, whiche the touchstone of truth, the sincere word of God, shall be thy warrant in, and giue me leaue, sithence my calling claymeth not so sage direction, to touche his Papacie, and the paltrie thereof, in playner tearmes, without <hi>Premunire:</hi> for I promise thée, I wil obserue the lymits of humanitie, to my vttermost en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor, &amp; wil not be long in that I will write, reade them as thou likest, &amp; way thē as thou wilt, always remembring, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the marke thou must hit, is set and fully expressed in thys booke, &amp; the reste is but a worke gathered by a lesse skilfull workeman, only set down, bycause an olde matter shal not come out, without some new addition. I make no argumēt of my worke, bycause I will not stande long vpon any one thing: neither doe I will thée to reade more than thou well likest of, bycause y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> old worke is it, which only is cōmended to thée. But if thy grauitie will permit thée, thou shalte finde in some of my pamphlets matter to delight thée, &amp; yet not digressing frō the pretended purpose. If frō the same y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> falshood of the <hi>Pope</hi> be any thing at al detected, my laboure is not lost. If Christ be at all glorified, I haue wonne a cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest. If thou accept it, I haue to thanke thée, and am here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after at thy request, to do for thée what I can. In y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meane space I commend thée to the almightie, and praye thée and all men to rest humble peticioners to the euerlasting God, to length y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prosperous raigne of our most merciful Quéene his seruaunt and our supreame soueraigne on earth, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect health of bodie and Soule, twice natures course to rule and raigne ouer vs. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>