<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102973_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11605</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21846</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102973</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three sermons preached by VVilliam Sclater Doctor of Diuinity, and minister of the word of God at Pitmister in Sommersetshire. Now published by his sonne of Kings Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Sclater, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Crooke, Andrew 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 16, 8, 17-39, 11, 19, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="31"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued in Christ Iesus, we are met together this day to performe the last office and duty of Charity to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian brother, an aged and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend gentleman, a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate of eminent and best place amongst vs. And though I know the principall end of such sermons be the instruction of the liuing; yet I take it there is a lawfull and warrantable commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vertues, and deserued praises of the dead, as well to stirre vp to praise God for his graces that shined in them, as to prouoke others to imitate their holy example. Concerning this worshipfull Gentleman deceased, these thinges I can speake neither for fashion, nor for flattery. For Religion, the principall commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all men, of meaner, or higher place in the world, this testimony we can all giue him;
<pb facs="32"/> that he was an ancient, and constant professor of the truth, now taught and maintained in this Church of England; yea a man delighted in the title of a professour of the strictest sort; a thing that most great ones throw of with that odious nickname of Puritanisme. For loue of this truth these worthy euidences he gaue of it, while health lasted, an ordinary, attentiue, delightfull, and, as I perswade my selfe, a profitable hearer. In this kind that one thing is eminent, his care to furnish this place where himselfe was an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary hearer, with a Minister of some compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ability to instruct the people, and free from scandall in life. And herein how free he was from all Simoniacall practises, my selfe am a thankefull witnesse; and the same testimonie can many others giue him touching my predecessor whose soule is now with God, a rare and worthy example. And if such vertues were capable of bequeathment, I could wish he had left this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable part amongst others for a Legacy to men in his sort; to see the cunning couetous dealing of most men in this kind it is lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, such reseruations and annuall gratuities, such curtolling of Ministers maintenance, as
<pb facs="32"/>
      <hi>Hanun</hi> vsed the garments of <hi>Dauids</hi> seruants, they are cut off by the middle. And <hi>Michas</hi> his wages, ten shekells of siluer, a liuery, and meate and drinke, a large allowance for a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, and indeed fit maintenance for such Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines, but yet a filthy practise in such Patrons. For practise of life, subiect to frailties, and who is free? But for aught I know cleare from noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious crimes; If any haue beene so credulous as to censure him vpon bare rumour, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that such credulity agrees not with charity, and let him feare, least the hard mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures he hath mete vnto this gentleman, be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> rendred him double in Gods iust iudgement. For state and calling, a Magistrate of highest place amongst vs; employed in affaires of weightiest importance; a good argument of his tryed fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity: For loue of his Country conspicuous; for dispatch of businesse speedy, and painefull, yea euen in time of weakenesse: And as I haue heard, bewailing his weakenesse for noe one thing more, then that it disabled him for seruice of the Country. Come we to behauiour in sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, it pleased God to afflict him with a long, violent and painefull disease; yet this hath bin
<pb facs="33"/> obserued in him, that he neuer vttered any one speech of impatience, and discontentment at the hand of God. So great patience vnder so great afflictions argues (me thinkes) some apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Gods loue euen in afflictions. And that we might see his constancy in loue of the truth, when God had debarred him from the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be was not onely willing, but desirous to heare in priuate; often melting into teares, as well at the propounding of Gods sweete mercies, as at reproofes and denuntiations of iudgements. In priuate conference desirous and glad to be farther informed touching his owne estate, and meanes of Saluation, answering with teares to most things propounded; to me a good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>argument of a contrite heart, which God hath promised not to despise. In the last agony so long as God gaue memory often calling on that sweete name of Iesu for helpe, mercy, pardon of sinnes. Yet when some distractions were on him through violence of paines, able and ready to giue a reason of his hope, being demanded of the ground of his hope of Saluation he professed to cleaue only to the merits of Christ: demanded againe a reason of his hope to haue part in
<pb facs="33"/> Christs merits; he thus answered; because I seeke him: and surely, saith <hi>Dauid,</hi> thou Lord neuer failest them that seeke thee in sincerity. Yea after vse of outward senses was gone, we often heard passionate callings on the name of Iesu (I doubt not but he found sweetnesse in that name) to help him, and haue mercy on him. These so many, and so worthy prescriptions, methinkes must needes wring from the most vncharitable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs at least a hopefull perswasion that he dyed Gods Child. And for mine owne part I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but professe more then a hope that his soule is with God. If any man thinke I haue beene too prodigall of his prayses, let him thus iudge, that Christian charity as it loues not to tenter the sins of others, but euer to extenuate human fraileties, so is it delighted to amplifie to the vtmost the iust praises of them it respects. Yet this withall; if I haue any way faulted; I feare it is rather in omissions through forgetfulnesse, then in any sort by ouerreaching thruogh flattery.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>