<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, Mr. Richard Holworthy Maior, Mr. William Cann, and Mr. William Hobson, Sheriffes of the Citty of Bristoll: To Captaine Taylor, Captaine Aldworth, Captaine Elbridge; Captaines of the Traine Bands. To Mr. Richard Long.At the time of my Preach∣ing. then President: Mr. Walter Ellis, now President of the Military Garden: And to all the rest of that Martiall Societie.</title>
           <author>Palmer, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102339_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08873</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19155</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102339</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, Mr. Richard Holworthy Maior, Mr. William Cann, and Mr. William Hobson, Sheriffes of the Citty of Bristoll: To Captaine Taylor, Captaine Aldworth, Captaine Elbridge; Captaines of the Traine Bands. To Mr. Richard Long.At the time of my Preach∣ing. then President: Mr. Walter Ellis, now President of the Military Garden: And to all the rest of that Martiall Societie.</title>
                 <author>Palmer, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Bristolls military garden : A sermon preached unto the worthy company of practisers in the military garden of the well governed citie of Bristoll. By Thomas Palmer, master of arts, and vicar of St. Thomas, and St. Mary Redcliffe in the same citie</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg>
      <hi>Richard Holworthy</hi> Maior, M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg>
      <hi>William Cann,</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg>
      <hi>William Hobson,</hi> Sheriffes of the Citty of <hi>Bristoll:</hi> To Captaine <hi>Taylor,</hi> Captaine <hi>Aldworth,</hi> Captaine <hi>Elbridge;</hi> Captaines of the Traine Bands. To M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Richard Long.</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">At the time of my Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> then President: Mr. <hi>Walter Ellis,</hi> now President of the Military Garden: And to all the rest <hi>of that Martiall Societie.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Worshipfull,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hould the exercise of Armes be generally laid aside, that Respond in our English Liturgie, might bee taken in the strictest acception of a literall Sense. <hi>There is none that fighteth for us, but onely Thou O God.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Moses</hi> wished that all the Lords People were Prophets: So Gods Prophets
<pb facs="4"/>wish that everyone of the Lords People were a <hi>Moses,</hi> An able Souldier, a compleat Warriour to fight the Battels of the Lord of Hosts. His Maiesty hath granted, and by his Counsell confirmed a Freedome unto your City, for your practise of Martiall Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline: It was your owne Petition. Then let not your Omission of Exercise returne a <hi>Quod petit spernit</hi> unto so gratious a Commission. <hi>Saul</hi> armed <hi>David,</hi> as you shall finde in this discourse. And <hi>David</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately put himselfe into action Our King hath in like manner armed you, that you may gird on your Swordes, and exercise your Armes with safety. You that are Starres to fight in your course against <hi>Sise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> prove not falling Starres: Fall not from the diligent prosecution of such an Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble intendment. A house begunne, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver finished, is called the Founders folly. Proceede then upon this Honourable founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Least that become your folly, which is your Glory. Let your <hi>Councell house</hi> give incouragement to your <hi>Campus Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius;</hi> your field of Martiall exercise. Let
<pb facs="4"/>it not bee said of any in your Cittie, Hee is a good Merchant, but a bad Souldier. As they pay unto their King the Custome of their Goods; let them pay unto their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, the Custome of their Bodies, in the Customary Practice of Armes. It is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that they that will not, dare not beare Armes. And when neede requires, will prove rather a burthen, then a help unto their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.<note n="*" place="margin">Judg. 5.23.</note> Liable unto the curse of <hi>Meros,</hi> and the Inhabitants thereof, because they come not out to help the Lord against the mighty. Improve your service on the Land, to be answerable to your experimented dexterity on the Sea; and J shall not easily finde your Parallell. I am sure thas in your Spirituall Service,<note n="*" place="margin">Especially <hi>Redcliffe,</hi> which for a Parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Chappell is not paralleld by any Church in our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumvmnium pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochialium (quas unquam vidi) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legantissima. Cambden.</hi>
      </note> for the state<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of your Churches,<note n="*" place="margin">For our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, we are generally obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged unto the religious care of our Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Diocaesan.</note> and the generall cofor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity both of Clergy and Laity, you give place unto none. Both your Policy and Religion have imboldned mee to dedicate this sling of <hi>David,</hi> to your Nursery of Armes. And my selfe to be</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your fellow Souldier in the Lord: THOMAS PALMER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>