<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HOPE∣full light of true Nobility, the right honorable Iames Lord Matreuers.</title>
           <author>Wynne, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102798_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15799</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26060</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102798</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HOPE∣full light of true Nobility, the right honorable Iames Lord Matreuers.</title>
                 <author>Wynne, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Morall obseruations : By W.W. Gent</title>
                 <author>Wynne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HOPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full light of true Nobility, <hi>the right honorable</hi> Iames <hi>Lord</hi> Matreuers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT honorable, the increase of yeares in mans life, hath the best comparison to the succee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding perfections of the worlds age: Wherein (if reuelations, and reuealed teachings be excepted) wee finde by obseruation of Historie deriued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, a waxing, and waining in all Arts and actions: A breeding, an infancie, a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlines, a perfection and state, and then a
<pb facs="3"/>d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>clyning, so that such inspection of the worlds storye, is a fit representation to be considered for the formatiue trayning of our particulariti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s from the first, and weakest capacitie of instruction, to the last and strongest abilitie of performance: which will produce the best, and most enabled endurance of vnderstanding vigor in the declining yeares: which though natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally they breede decay in strength, and power of naturall functions, yet with such Custome of vse, in the long and constant exercise of a vertuous minde, cannot want sufficiencie of all possible support<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that may be expected from the true groundes of a well tempered vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Those things wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch full yeares hauing attayned can teach others, are not fit to be presented vnto such yeares, but serue as fruites allready rypened, to be layed, and kept in store, at seasonable times to be bestowed on children and younger yeares. Such be these obseruations, which I present to your honor, desiring therein nothing
<pb facs="3"/>more, then the commending of ready will to doe all honest and seruiceable duties to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors humbly to be commaunded <hi>William Wynne.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>