<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE BAPTIST Lord HICKS, Baron of Ilmington, Vicount Camden; Health, Honour, Happinesse, both in this, and a better Life.</title>
           <author>Gaule, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102992_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01560</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11689</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102992</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE BAPTIST Lord HICKS, Baron of Ilmington, Vicount Camden; Health, Honour, Happinesse, both in this, and a better Life.</title>
                 <author>Gaule, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Distractions, or The holy madnesse : Feruently (not furiously) inraged against euill men; or against their euills. Wherein the naughty are discouered to themselues, and others: and may here see at once, who they are; what they doe; and how they ought. Somewhat delightfull, but fruitfull altogether: as ordered to please a little; but aymed to profit much. By Iohn Gaule, vtrusque olim Academiæ</title>
                 <author>Gaule, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 489, 489-490, that is 491, 4 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE BAPTIST Lord HICKS, Baron of <hi>Ilmington,</hi> Vicount <hi>Camden;</hi> Health, Honour, Happinesse, both in this, and a better Life.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Honourable good Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> THVS (as I am bound) bethink me. Whose ought
<pb facs="3"/> Mine to be, but whose I am my selfe? To accept the Parent, is (I presume) not to refuse the Brood. It is but my Duty, to beget any thing to your seruice: and shall bee your Goodnesse, to vouchsafe it enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment. I must confesse, it had bin better, this win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb facs="3"/> Egge should haue beene pasht in the Shell; than been hatcht vnder your Lordships Wings. It is a common Fault; and some beside me, bewaile I toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with me: Ah that such our worthlesse Brats, so wontedly creep into so honourable Bosomes! What
<pb facs="4"/> ouer-insolence is it of ours; that we dare to shroud vs there, where wee ought rather feare to bee detected? This is more than Boldnesse, that I presume now a Patron for my Worke: It shall be but Duty, that I endeuour once a Worke for my Patron. What
<pb facs="4"/> haue I here set before you; but what your selfe (before me) haue not onely noted, but hated also; Mens Vanities, and Euils? Oh pardon, that I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with what you like not to behold: I shall so be tied to make amends with what
<pb facs="5"/> (I know) you loue to embrace.</p>
   <p>To Praise you (as they vse) for your Pietie, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, Bountie, Clemencie; would be thought to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you: To haue named you is (in all these) to haue praised you. Yet will I (maugre all such their imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or exception)
<pb facs="5"/> pray for you. May your Lordship liue long dayes, and good: yea, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing now attained to a good age; let it yet be added to your dayes. May your iustest Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour (maugre the mutability of these rolling Globes, &amp; Times) neuer be destitute of Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance with En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement.
<pb facs="6"/> May you lastly, for Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour terrestriall, and fading; enioy an Happinesse ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestiall, and with eternity. So praies, and vowes</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours deuoted and dutifull Chaplaine, IOHN GAVLE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>