<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE the Ladie WENTWORTH</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102573_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09644</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19909</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102573</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE the Ladie WENTWORTH</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vertues anatomie. Or A compendious description of that late right honorable, memorable, and renowned Bedfordshire lady, the Lady Cheany, of Tuddington. By Charles Pierse</title>
                 <author>Pierse, Charles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE the Ladie WENTWORTH</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable ere I doe begin</l>
   <l>I pardon craue, presumption is a sinne,</l>
   <l>Lest I too much vpon my selfe relying,</l>
   <l>May <hi>Icarus</hi>-like perhaps repēt my flying.</l>
   <l>The plague of many Poets, which do think</l>
   <l>Their owne to be the pure immortall drinke,</l>
   <l>But I that farre inferiour am to them,</l>
   <l>Ascribe no such vain-glory to my pen,</l>
   <l>Nor yet will ouerprize, what I do know</l>
   <l>Is past my skill to iudge, or power to show.</l>
   <l>If ought within this little volume lies,</l>
   <l>A worke too weake for your iudicious eyes,</l>
   <l>Which might 'gainst me the smallest fire incense,</l>
   <l>I should be loath to giue so much offence:</l>
   <l>Yet doe not fixe your wrath before you trie,</l>
   <l>And heare great Lady my Apologie.</l>
   <l>Perchance my meannesse barres me of that fauour,</l>
   <l>Which others gaine in as vnworthy labour,</l>
   <l>If that it doth or bare originall birth</l>
   <l>In sight of heauen, is nought or little worth:</l>
   <l>Hee's no accepter of the noblest blood,</l>
   <l>Aboue the meaner persons which are good,</l>
   <l>All's one to him, his power created all,</l>
   <l>Hee's great'st with him, that on his name doth call.</l>
   <l>The abiects and the out-casts of all things,</l>
   <l>In this prerogatiue may compare with Kings:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>Heauens are not partiall, all's alike respected,</l>
   <l>None for their greatest honor are elected,</l>
   <l>If this be not the cause, another yet</l>
   <l>May hazard what this former could not hit,</l>
   <l>And bid me call in question straight my pen,</l>
   <l>That hath not writ so learn'd as other men,</l>
   <l>Hauing a subiect so repleate with honor,</l>
   <l>And could not shew no better skill vpon her.</l>
   <l>This plunges deeper, and hard claime doth lay</l>
   <l>Vnto my thoughts, I know not what to say:</l>
   <l>But since thou can'st not paint, nor steale no wit</l>
   <l>With borrowed shapes, or Artes to furnish it,</l>
   <l>In plainest colours thou hast truely pen'd them,</l>
   <l>Vertue and honor need no arte to mend them.</l>
   <l>Besides, it was her pleasure, minde and will,</l>
   <l>To haue her vertues vnderualued still;</l>
   <l>For it is not so true, as common knowne,</l>
   <l>The purest vertues neuer seeke their owne,</l>
   <l>And heauens agree, and with their names dispence</l>
   <l>To grace the truth, and leaue out eloquence:</l>
   <l>For he respects the heart more then the tongue,</l>
   <l>Or else we all should doe his Godhead wrong.</l>
   <l>Then if that heauens in this from blame doth free mee,</l>
   <l>Why should not mortals through his glory see mee?</l>
   <l>And set mee free from any scorne and hate,</l>
   <l>Since heauen in all things, all should imitate.</l>
   <l>It may be yet another may arise</l>
   <l>And show it selfe vnpleasing to your eies;</l>
   <l>And that is this: the want of wealth and state,</l>
   <l>Which holds too many in disgrace and hate,</l>
   <l>Yet in the sight of heau'ns the poor'st are grac'd,</l>
   <l>And are not for their want of meanes displac'd:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="7"/>If the small'st mite or sparke of grace he findes</l>
   <l>Doth worke at all, within their hearts and mindes:</l>
   <l>Nor doth he cast away the poorest slaue</l>
   <l>From entring in, if grace be found to saue;</l>
   <l>But like vnto decayed plants, doth cherish</l>
   <l>Their dying roots, and will not let them perish,</l>
   <l>Then noble Lady, if that these may claime</l>
   <l>The least respect, and shelter me from blame,</l>
   <l>I shall be glad: when first I vndertooke</l>
   <l>To write to such great minds, this little booke;</l>
   <l>Where my too worthlesse duetie more affords,</l>
   <l>Conceal'd within, not to be tould in words.</l>
   <l>Accept it (Honor) then since 'tis the first,</l>
   <l>Your greatnesse soone may grac't, or make it worse:</l>
   <l>But whether 'tis my fortune or my fate,</l>
   <l>I now must take't, repentance comes too late:</l>
   <l>Yet many fauours, farre aboue my merit,</l>
   <l>I haue receiu'd from your most noble spirit:</l>
   <l>Which makes me hope, that now I shall not misse,</l>
   <l>But likewise be receiu'd and grac'd in this,</l>
   <l>For which Ile studie by my best endeauer,</l>
   <l>In faithfull seruice, bound fast yours for euer.</l>
   <l>Then, noble Ladie, deigne to take a view</l>
   <l>Of those faire vertuous parts, and honors true,</l>
   <l>Which faire example left so rich behinde,</l>
   <l>To fill the vertuous storehouse of your minde,</l>
   <l>Whose worthie branches from that tree descended</l>
   <l>Make honors goe with vertues rich attended:</l>
   <l>Where some of them, if all you doe not finde,</l>
   <l>Ingrauen in your honorable minde.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>