<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTIS∣MENT TO THE READER ABOVT A FOR∣MER ANSWERE OF M. M. Ar.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102241_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00908</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11016</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102241</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTIS∣MENT TO THE READER ABOVT A FOR∣MER ANSWERE OF M. M. Ar.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of the Catholyke cause : contayning a treatise in confutation of sundry vntruthes and slanders, published by the heretykes, as wel in infamous lybels as otherwyse, against all english Catholyks in general, &amp; some in particular, not only concerning matter of state, but also matter of religion: by occasion whereof diuers poynts of the Catholyke faith now in controuersy, are debated and discussed. VVritten by T.F. With an apology, or defence, of his innocency in a fayned conspiracy against her Maiesties person, for the which one Edward Squyre was wrongfully condemned and executed in Nouember ... 1598. wherewith the author and other Catholykes were also falsly charged. Written by him the yeare folowing, and not published vntil now, for the reasons declared in the preface of this treatyse</title>
                 <author>Fitzherbert, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Conincx, Arnout</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 71, 1, 4, 51, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="76"/>
   <pb facs="76"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT TO THE READER ABOVT A FOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MER ANSWERE OF M. M. Ar.</head>
   <p>AFter I had set downe to my self this defence or Apologie in the forme that here it goeth, there came to my hādes a certayne breif pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet writen in Rome by M. Mar. Ar. presentlie vpon the execution of Squier in England, which confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thoughe for the substance of the matter it seemed to me very sufficient to giue any man satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by shewing the whole matter of Squyers accusatiō, condēnation, and execution to be a very fiction and deuised for certayne endes which there are touched; yet thought I not amisse to let this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie passe also as it was made, partly for that it conteyneth my owne particuler defence which the other toucheth not, but hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the whole action in general, and partly also for that the māner of both our proceedings is different, he shewing the whole subiect and argument to be a fayned thing, and I that albeit some occasion had byn geuen of suspition yet the forme of proceeding against Squyer &amp; the rest to be vniust &amp; against all reason, equitie, law, and conscience.</p>
   <p>M. Mar. Ar. to proue his intent layeth downe the historical narration of all the whole matter and men touched in the same, to wit how Squyer and Rolles were taken vpon the sea and brought prisoners to Siuil, and had their liberty there by Father Parsons meanes, and how afterwards geuing newe occasion of offence in matters of religiō they were taken agayne at S. Lucars, &amp; brought back to Siuil, and there agayne after certayne monethes impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonment, deliuered out of prison &amp; put in different Monasteryes for to be instructed, whence they fled away to the sea syde, and
<pb facs="77"/>
excused their flight afterwards by letters to Father Walpoole that was most in daunger by that flight which letters are yet extant.</p>
   <p>It sheweth also the improbability of the deuise, to wit, that Father Walpoole (being the man he is) should euer haue thought of such a fond way of sending poyson into England by such a fellow as Squyer was, suspected stil to be a dissembled protestant, as afterwards he proued, and that thing could not be wrought, nor the poyson caryed so farre but that Rolles his compagnion must know somewhat thereof, who being at that present in the Towre of London, and neither brought foorth, nor mentioned, nor yet made partaker of the fact, was a token that matters went not wel, nor were directly handled.</p>
   <p>Besides this that book declareth by many examples the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises of Protestants in these our dayes for making Catholykes odious, especially Iesuites of which order Father Walpoole is, who was fayned to be the contriuer of this conspiracy which is shewed to be as farre from the condition of the man, as the matter it self is from all probability of truth, to wit, any such poyson to be made, bought and sold in Siuil proued by the death of a dog, sent into England by sea in bladders of leather, poured vpon the Quenes Sadle, as also vpon the chayre of the Earle of Essex without hurt to the sitter or ryder, the matter discouered by one Stanley, that neyther sawe Squyer in Spayne, nor spoke with him, and it was denyed by Squyer first at the barre, and after at his death, and since his death called in dowt by Stanley his first detector, (as by some hath byn written from the place where he abydeth) the force also of that poyson (yf any such had byn) is declared by reasons and authoritie both of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick and Philosophie that it could not worke any such effect as was ymagined, or pretended, &amp; consequentlie that those applauses &amp; congratulations both by woords, sighs, &amp; teares which a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of flatterers shewed foorth at Squyers arraynment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation for her Ma<seg rend="sup">ties.</seg> so miraculous escape was most ridiculous and vayne.</p>
   <p>This is the summe &amp; effect of that answere as breifly set downe, as I can gather it, and it maketh the fiction most euident to all such as without partiality wil read it, though I heare say that it may chance come out agayne more ample in a secōd edition, with many Autentical letters, as wel of the citty of Siuil, as of the courte of Inquisitiō in that place, to shew the manner of Squyers and Rolles
<pb facs="77"/>
running away from those partes with some other circumstances to improue the probabilitie of the deuised slander in England, which letters and instruments I thought not good to insert heere to my Apologie but to leaue thē to M. Mar. Ar. now at his returne hither from Rome to ad to his former Answere if so he shal think good, for that he maketh mention thereof in the same, and as for this my defence (gentle reader I shal not need to aduise thee of the substance, manner, method, or argument therof, for that the breife chapters ensuing wil sufficiently setfoorth the same, only I would admonish thee to consider maturely with thy self how rhow mayest be vsed in matters of Religion which do most import thy soule and saluation, when in matters of fact and open action thow shalt fynd thy self so egregiously abused.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>