<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶A VVARNING TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1558</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102452_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13870</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24174</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102452</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶A VVARNING TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A vvarning to England to repente : and to tvrne to god from idolatrie and poperie by the terrible exemple of Calece, giuen the 7. of March. Anno. D. 1558. By Benthalmai Outis</title>
                 <author>Traheron, Bartholomew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Zuttere (Hyperphragmus, Overdhaeghe), Pieter Anastasius de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Wesel</pubPlace>
                    <date>1558</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="15"/>
   <head>¶A VVARNING TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>VVHo soeuer thou art, whose lotte it shalbe to reade this admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thinke not fondly that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor hereof, wold serue his affections in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing mennes vices, or thereby delight him selfe, or other mennes eares, or procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hatred to anie state, or anie person, and blow a trompette to malice. For so with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubte thou shalt fowly begile thy sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, displease god highly, and leese the frute of his trauail in writing, and of thy time in reading. But assure thy selfe, that he hath spared no condition, and state in this great, and weightie matter, for none other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, saue only to moue al sortes to repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce, seing plainly the hole staie of the realme now shaking, and threatening a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, to rest therevpon. And if thou shalt vse this nedeful warning to anie other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, than to amende thy selfe, and to stirre other to amendment of life, and to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of goddes glorie, thou shalt tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente the herte of the writer, disturbe the holie desires of the gdolie, &amp; pulle the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance
<pb facs="16"/> of god vpon thine awne head. Nether on thother side be thou so weake, as to thinke that the autor shuld haue forbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to haue vttred al that he ether knew him selfe to be true, or had lerned of other, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the nobilitee of the personages, but considre that it becamme him in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des cause, and in a matter touching the safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or vttre ruine of his coūtree, to haue re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garde rather to the welth, &amp; preseruation, than to the honor of the persons, with whō if thei continue in their wickednes, the hole realme must certainly comme in daunger of goddes wrath, and vnrecouerable des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction. Walke thoue therefore vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; be nether to wordly wise, nor to word<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly foolish, nether hastie to hate, nor slacke to redresse bothe thy selfe, and other, but praie with this writer that god of his infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te goodnes wil vouchsafe to cōuerte the, thy ruler, thy nobilitee, and al other thy countre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men from wickednes of life, &amp; from al po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pishe superstition, and idolatrie vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe that yet his people maie be herboured in Englande, that yet his gospel maie sounde, and haue free course in Englan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, that yet his holie name maie there be
<pb facs="16"/> magnified, and aduaunced in peace, and quietnes.</p>
   <trailer>FIN.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>