<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfull and Reuerend Iudges, Sir Iohn Sauile Knight, one of the Barons of his Ma∣iesties Exchequer: and Sir Christopher Yel∣uerton Knight, one of the Iudges of his Ma∣iesties Court of Kings bench, the late worthy Iudges of our Northeren Circuite. The spirit of wisedome, zeale and courage be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Fenton, Roger</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102894_Bo1_2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09445</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19733</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102894</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfull and Reuerend Iudges, Sir Iohn Sauile Knight, one of the Barons of his Ma∣iesties Exchequer: and Sir Christopher Yel∣uerton Knight, one of the Iudges of his Ma∣iesties Court of Kings bench, the late worthy Iudges of our Northeren Circuite. The spirit of wisedome, zeale and courage be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Fenton, Roger</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the calling of the ministerie : two treatises, discribing the duties and dignities of that calling. Delivered publickly in the Vniuersitie of Cambridge, by Maister Perkins. Taken then from his mouth, and now dilligently perused and published, by a preacher of the word wit a preface prefixed touching the publishing of Maister Perkins his workes, &amp; a catalogue of all such particulars thereof, as are to bee expected</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Welby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>76, 127, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="36"/>
   <head>To the right worshipfull and Reuerend Iudges, <hi>Sir Iohn Sauile Knight,</hi> one of the Barons of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties <hi>Exchequer</hi>: and <hi>Sir Christopher Yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerton Knight,</hi> one of the Iudges of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties Court of <hi>Kings bench,</hi> the late worthy Iudges of our <hi>Northeren</hi> Circuite. The spirit of wisedome, zeale and courage be multiplied.</head>
   <p>RIght worshipfull, it is sayd in other Nations, and <hi>written</hi> in some of their bookes, that there are three <hi>disgraces</hi> of the English Nation: The Ignorance, or (that I may so call it) the Vnlearnednes of our <hi>Gentry and Nobility,</hi> the Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gery of our <hi>poore,</hi> and the Basenes of the body of <hi>our Ministery.</hi> The <hi>first</hi> blot, our Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and Gentrie haue well wiped off, since the first daies of blessed Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> partly by <hi>stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi> at home, partly by <hi>trauell</hi> abroade, and I hope they will doe it more and more: The <hi>second</hi> hath beene well l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssened by good lawes of late, and wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d be more, if the <hi>Execution</hi> were as good as our lawes bee, and it were much honour to our <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and more to our <hi>Religion,</hi> if it were quite taken away: for he that tells vs there shal be <hi>poore</hi> euer with vs,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>h. 26, 11. Dent. 15.</hi>
      </note> saith also, there shall not be a <hi>begger</hi>
      <pb facs="36"/>
amonst vs; If there were no <hi>poore,</hi> what should become of <hi>Charitie:</hi> for it is charitie to relieue <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie,</hi> not to maintaine <hi>beggery:</hi> Pouerty may be a <hi>Crosse,</hi> but it is no <hi>Curse:</hi> but <hi>beggery</hi> is a fearefull <hi>curse, threatned</hi> on the enemies of God: and <hi>Dauid</hi> saith not,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal. 109, 10 Psal. 37, 25.</hi>
      </note> bee neuer sawe a righteous mans child <hi>poore,</hi> but that he neuer sawe him <hi>begge his bread.</hi> The dayly <hi>cries</hi> in our streetes, <hi>cry</hi> for yet further reformati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that the <hi>impotent poore</hi> may be sufficiently prouided for, that he neede not, and the <hi>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>urdy begger</hi> compelled to worke, that hee may not bee <hi>suffred to begge.</hi> Happie you, or whosoeuer can haue a hand, in effecting this blessed w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rke, <hi>wee,</hi> who can doe little else shall pray for it, and for them that labour in it. But now f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r the <hi>third,</hi> I feare none but the very hand of God, can wipe out that staine from our Church: The bas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nes of the generall body of our <hi>Ministerie,</hi> whence is it, but either from the vnworthin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sse or <hi>pouerty</hi> thereof: and the vnworthines thereof, whence is it but from the <hi>pouerty,</hi> and base maintenance of our <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterie,</hi> which was once robbed by the <hi>Abbies,</hi> and after worse by some in our owne State: and Popery that stands so much vpon <hi>Non dimittitur peccatum nisi restituator ablatum,</hi> yet for all that, would not <hi>restore</hi> vnto the Church <hi>her tenthes</hi> againe. But as Popish Abbies <hi>stole
<pb facs="37"/>
them,</hi> so a popish state <hi>kept them,</hi> and to their shame some of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se good Professors of <hi>our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> haue restored such as were in their bands, and there is hope that all our Professors, (vnlesse they care not to be accounted hipocrits) will make some conscionable restitution. We doe not craue that they wold with <hi>Zacheus restore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>old</hi> (though it is apparant,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luke, 19, 8, &amp;c.</hi>
      </note> that the <hi>Tenthes</hi> were got from vs in old time, by most false and <hi>forged Cauillati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>) we onely craue our owne, we would aske no <hi>more,</hi> nor willingly take <hi>lesse:</hi> for our <hi>whole dutie</hi> is still required, then why should not our <hi>whole due</hi> be payd. And yet that the world may learne of vs <hi>contentednes,</hi> as well by our prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise as our doctrine, we would for the present, take in good part, and rest contented with a part of our owne, and some competent portions out of the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations,</hi> (proportioned to the quantitie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f the <hi>charge imposed,</hi> and the gifts and <hi>paines required</hi>) would for a time bee a reasonable sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to our <hi>Ministerie,</hi> vntill our state found it selfe, either better enabled, or more straight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tied in Conscience to full restitution. But as I sayd, this is a worke of <hi>God</hi> himselfe, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r if man could doe it, so many <hi>Parliaments</hi> would not haue slipt it, but some of them would haue ete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed it selfe, with this honorable name to all posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. <hi>The Parliament that restored Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations,</hi>
      <pb facs="37"/>
but <hi>till that,</hi> or some other course (as good) be taken, it is both <hi>vnseasonable,</hi> and <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable</hi> to complaine of the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> or to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aue a <hi>learned Ministerie.</hi> For <hi>shall the Oxes mouth be mousled,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>1 Corinth. 9, 7, 9, 14.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>which treads out the corne,</hi> or <hi>shall a man goe to warre at his owne cost?</hi> and hath not <hi>God ordained</hi> (marke it is his <hi>Ordinance) that those who teach the Gospell, shal liue of the Gospel?</hi> But alas, how shall the Ministerie of England liue of the Gospell, when my small experience can showe, that in one Corner of one <hi>County</hi> of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, wherein there are some <hi>150.</hi> parishes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>The East-Riding of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Yorke.</hi>
      </note> or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochiall Chappells, almost a <hi>100.</hi> of them, (if not a full <hi>100</hi>) are <hi>Impropriate,</hi> and amongst them I can showe the most parishes haue but <hi>10.</hi> pound or thereabouts, some <hi>8.</hi> li. some <hi>6,</hi> li. some 5, li. some <hi>4,</hi> pound, some not <hi>4,</hi> pound yearely liuing for the Minister, and those impropriations worth some <hi>300,</hi> pound, many <hi>200,</hi> pound, almost all <hi>100,</hi> pound, per an: yea there is one worth <hi>400,</hi> pound, per an: where there were but <hi>8,</hi> pound left for the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> vntill of late with much adoe, <hi>10,</hi> pound more was obtained for a preacher, and so there is out of <hi>400,</hi> pound, <hi>8,</hi> pound shared for a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> and <hi>10,</hi> pound carued for a <hi>preacher,</hi> in that parish where there are <hi>2000, Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants.</hi> Of all the rest, the Crowne hath some <hi>100,</hi>
      <pb facs="38"/>
pound rent, or not so much, and the remainder of <hi>280,</hi> pound (being a rich liuing, for a worthy lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Minister, a <hi>competent</hi> liuing for <hi>2,</hi> and more then some <hi>7,</hi> painfull and able Ministers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>) I knowe not what becomes of it, vnlesse it goe to the feeding of Kits and Cormorants. Are not these goodly liuings for <hi>learned</hi> men, and may not wee expect a <hi>learned Ministerie,</hi> where there is such <hi>maintenance</hi>? and I hartely wish that other countries, be not able to showe the like Presidents▪ haue the rather made relation heereof, that our high Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> may see how great cause they haue, to goe forward with that motion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready by them made, for the establishing of a <hi>lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Ministerie.</hi> But if they bring it not to passe, what then remaineth, but to hope that the great <hi>God of heauen,</hi> will put into the hart of the <hi>God on earth,</hi> our noble King (into wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se hands he hath put the sword of soueraigne authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) an irreuocable and vnresistable, resolution to execute his supreme power, for the reformation of this <hi>euill,</hi> which (as Maister Perkins saith in this treatise) may well be called the <hi>Kings euill,</hi> for it will hardly be healed, but by the <hi>will and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were of a king.</hi> In the meane time, this <hi>Treatise</hi> of that worthy man, may be a motiue to our zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louse professors, who haue any impropriations in their owne hands, to excite and prouoke them to a
<pb facs="38"/>
conscionable restitution, in whole or in part, as their <hi>estates</hi> may beare, or their <hi>conscience</hi> shall mooue them. For heerein are layd downe and mixed together, both the <hi>duties</hi> to be done by faithfull <hi>Ministers,</hi> and the <hi>Dignities</hi> due vnto them for their duties: and so seeing the <hi>dignities</hi> of that calling to bee most honorable, and the <hi>duties</hi> so chargeable, it cannot but grieue their Christian harts to see the <hi>maintenance</hi> so miserable.</p>
   <p>This Treatise I first of all send <hi>to you,</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your names to the world, and to you first, for as I am sure you loued the Author, and honored those excellēt gifts of God in him, so you cānot but accept this after birth of his, (as a fatherlesse child for the <hi>fathers</hi> sake). And for my selfe, (to conceale all personall and priuate respects) in the name of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousands in the <hi>Northeren Countries,</hi> I praise God for the good done in those parts, by your painfull courses, and religious care, not doubting, but if <hi>your selues,</hi> or the <hi>like</hi> be imployed there, to asist our Honourable and Religious <hi>Lord Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident,</hi> that the multitude of Popish Priests there lurking, will bee daily <hi>lessened,</hi> the <hi>number</hi> of painfull preachers <hi>augmented, Poperie</hi> put d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wne, and the <hi>Gospell</hi> maintained more and more. Which blessing God grant to that and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Countries</hi> of this Kingdome, for his mercies sake: &amp; giue vnto <hi>you</hi> &amp; all others in your <hi>place,</hi>
      <pb facs="39"/>
the spirit of courage and constancie, in these de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining daies, that beeing faithfull in your great charges, vnto the end, you may receiue the Crowne of life: for which he hartily prayeth, who will euer rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships in the Lord,</hi> W. Crashawe.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>