<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND VVORSHIPFVL, THE STVDENTS of the Common Lavv in his Maiesties Innes of Court. THE PREFACE.</title>
           <author>R., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102371_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01006</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11111</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102371</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND VVORSHIPFVL, THE STVDENTS of the Common Lavv in his Maiesties Innes of Court. THE PREFACE.</title>
                 <author>R., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ouerthrovv of the Protestants pulpit-Babels : conuincing their preachers of lying &amp; rayling, to make the Church of Rome seeme mysticall Babell. Particularly confuting VV. Crashawes Sermon at the Crosse, printed as the patterne to iustify the rest. VVith a preface to the gentlemen of the Innes of Court, shewing what vse may be made of this treatise. Togeather with a discouery of M. Crashawes spirit: and an answere to his Iesuites ghospell. By I.R. student in diuinity</title>
                 <author>Floyd, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>328, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND VVORSHIPFVL, THE STVDENTS <hi>of the Common Lavv in his Maiesties Innes of Court.</hi> THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F many seduced soules in our (in this respect) vnhappy Kingdome, had no more need to read refutations of idle Babels, then any trayned vp in true learning can take delight to refute friuolous falshoods: If as on <hi>M. Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shawes</hi> Sermon few men of vnderstanding can looke without pittying the Preachers folly; so likewise there were not troupes of common, and ignorant people,
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>who like weake, and silly flyes caught in the cobwebs of such slaunders, are therin kept prisoners from the bosome of that Church, out of which none can be saued: If whom nature or education hath left simple, heresy did not make prowd, to be tampering with too<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les that may cut their fingers, and to venture into the web of hereticall fraud, which they want strengh of wit to breake through: If (I say) such were the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of our Country, I might to my great comfort haue beene excused from the taske of this tedious labour of directing an Answere to this Bachelours Babell, and haue saued some peeces of a rich and irrecouerable Iewell<note n="(a)" place="margin">Res omnium pretiofissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma tēpus, quam ne grat{us} qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dē potest reddere. <hi>Senec.</hi>
      </note>
 to haue imployed them in a more gaynefull, and comfortable purchase. But seeing the world is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so perfect; as not to haue many<note n="(b)" place="margin">Quid obest par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulis tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niū, dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo in nido Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiae tuti plumescāt? <hi>Aug. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Cōfess. c.</hi> 16.</note>
 simple, nor the simple alwayes so happy, as to keep themselues se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely humble, nor the humble in this life so fully secure, as not to be subiect to the deceipts of the crafty, nor the crafty so carefull of credit, or moderate in malice, that they will forbeare to vtter euen open falshoods, to intangle the ignorant, when they want stronger argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to encounter with the learned; the earnest in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty of diuers friends haue wonne me to preferre publick profit before priuate comfort, and neglecting the perfection of my intended studyes, and the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my owne nature, to encounter with false and open slaunders, the very sound wherof cannot but be noysome to any learned eare, though an answere be necessary to preuent the dreadfull danger of eternall perdition in the lesse intelligent Readers.</p>
   <p n="2">2. Yt is now one yeare and more, that a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man then lyuing in one of your Courts, brought me this Sermon of <hi>M. Crashaw,</hi> togeather with his <hi>Iesuits
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>Ghospel,</hi> desyring I would bestow theron an Answere, assuring me, that howsoeuer the same might seeme ridiculous or contemptible to men of learning, yet many <hi>wauing Babes</hi> were carryed away with<note n="(c)" place="margin">
         <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</note>
      <hi>the blast</hi> of such slaunders, and by the <hi>waues of such raging</hi>
      <note n="(d)" place="margin">Flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus feri maris. <hi>Iudae</hi> 1.3.</note>
 inuectiues beaten and broken against the rocke, on which Christ built his<note n="(e)" place="margin">
         <hi>Matt.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 18.</note>
 Church; I beganne then to peruse his Sermon, and note some manifest slaunders, and places of our Authors corrupted by him: yet to confesse the truth, I did so loath this warre against wordes, and against Babels, seeming moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes and monsters to the eye, but wynd and vanity in very truth, that I was glad of any colourable oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to fly from the combat. Wherefore a rumour being spread, that by publishing his <hi>Iesuits Ghospell</hi> the folly and intemperancy therof had offended all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants of Iudgment, and temperate Disposition, that the Gentlemen of the <hi>Temple</hi> for this respect, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so in regard of his marriage which many iudged no conuenient quality for their Preacher, did resolue to discharge him of his office forthwith: I began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and soone after quite gaue ouer the intended An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere to his Sermon, hoping that without my help togeather with the body, the shaddowes would vanish, the beames of cleare truth entring in their place. But it seemeth, men spake of <hi>Maister Crashaw,</hi> rather what themselues thought he deserued, then what others intended, since neither any publick dislike was shewed against his intemperate writing, nor the sweetnes of his marriage did any way mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate the bitternes of his tongue; but still both in print, and pulpit, according to the vttermost of his skill and power, he imployeth his forces, to darken and
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>obscure with a mist of slaūders the light of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church.</p>
   <p n="3">3. Wherefore hauing notice therof, and vrged againe by the renewed request of some friends, I resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to make no further delay to finish and publish my formerly intended discouery of this Minister, specially out of griefe, that so many of my deare Countreymen should be kept from the cleare water of Catholike do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and deluded with empty bug-beares, which slaunderers set vpon the banks therof, &amp; that the smoke of falshood should (in the inueighled eye of the simple) transforme the very pillars of Christianity into snakes &amp; adders of blasphemy, causing seely soules that looke not into things, to abhorre the faire, and goodly chā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Christ his Spouse, as a den of Serpēts. The trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise being finished, I did lesse repent my labour, hoping the same might serue not only as a priuate discouery of this Preacher, abusing his credit and small learning, to the perdition of many by faire shewes of sanctity, and greatest promises of exact truth, when he meaneth most deceipt; but also for three other more generall v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, which I intend briefly in this Preface to declare, by which you will easily perceaue the reason of the title therof, and togeather lay open vnto you the motiues vrging me to offer the same vnto you.</p>
   <p n="4">4. First, this Treatise may serue for a compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diary answer to a good part of many Protestant books which euer cōmonly are farsed with these very slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,<note place="margin">The vse of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.</note>

 That we thinke the Pope to be God; that he can deliuer soules out of hell, and the rest, which this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister to make them more vendible doth offer as <hi>rare Iewells, and no triuiall things.</hi> For though I doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to haue read in any Protestant writers, slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>so thick, and threefold as in this Sermon, nor lyes placed in such good order and method according <hi>to the tables of the law;</hi> yet looking into their best Authors, you shall find that they euer did, and still doe make these slaunders their <hi>Triarian</hi> Legion, in which they put their chiefe and last trust, and which, when the better weapons of Scriptures or Fathers are wrested out of their hands, they choose to fly vnto, rather then yield: which may be shewed by the example (to omit diuers others) of two English writers of singular cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, in bookes which they write of two grauest argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The one <hi>M. Doctour Iewell</hi> (to whose name I need add no other Epithete, to make him seeme peere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse vnto Protestants) in his booke of the <hi>Apology of the Church of Englād,</hi> who doth not blush, into a Treatise of so graue a subiect, to insert trifles known to be false; <hi>of our thinking the Pope to be our Lord God, allowing fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and such like of <hi>M. Crashawes</hi> trumpery scattered here and there in his<note n="(f)" place="margin">Espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>4.</hi> part.</note>
 booke, as the penury of better weapons forced that great captayne to fight with ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes. The other is <hi>Doctour Andrews,</hi> now Bishop of <hi>Ely,</hi>
      <note place="margin">In his Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura Torti.</note>
 who lately summoned to fight with the learned Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, doth often woūd his Latin stile, worthy of better matter, with <hi>M. Crashawes</hi> wounds, vrging ould and worme-eaten glosses against vs, who being a man of so knowne learning, &amp; euer thought of a stayed iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and temperate spirit; neither we, nor the world did expect Babels from him, nor that he would staine his learned pen with triuiall slaūders, seeking to crack the credit of our cause with men of meane iudgment, by the losse of his owne among those of better lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. But necessity is a forcible weapon with which were those learned Protestants driuen to fight, of whō
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>
      <hi>Doctour Field</hi> doth<note n="(g)" place="margin">in his Epistle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory to the L. of Cāterbury.</note>
 complayne (that forbearing to write themselues, laugh in their<note n="(h)" place="margin">With many a scornefull looke, simile at the follies of others writings.</note>
 sleeues, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes more openly at others labours) would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance be forced to speake these very Babels, which now they laugh to behould in <hi>Doctour Field</hi> and others, finding by experience that not want of learning, or weakenes of iudgment, but the nakednes of their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise indefencible cause driueth these Doctors to make Babels, bulwarkes of their Church.</p>
   <p n="5">5. VVherefore it might in a manner haue been wished by vs (his sinne excepted) that <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> should, as it were sweep the writings of his learned Authors, raking all their ordure into his Sermon, as into a dunghill, or stable of such stuffe which one of farre lesse strength then <hi>Hercules</hi> might cleanse, by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the pure streames of truth the Catholicke Church teacheth in those points, which cannot but clearely carry away from her doctrine the dung of those slaunders in the iudgment of any indifferēt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Against which slaunders had we conceiued (as we might iustly) so great a hatred, as euer that<note n="(i)" place="margin">Caligu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</note>
 Tyrant had against <hi>Rome</hi> (who wished the heades of the people stood all vpon the same shoulders to cut thē off at a stroke) <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> may seeme very sufficiently to haue satisfied our desire, who hath gathered these slaunders into heades, &amp; layd those heads, as you shall see, very orderly togeather in his owne head, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that all their chiefe slaunders, togeather with his, may be cut off, and cleared by one, and that not very long Answere.</p>
   <p n="6">6. But besides this first vse of this Treatise, the same may also serue for an Answere vnto many Sermōs that are continually made against the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>
      <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>M. Crashawes</hi> rayling tune, falling &amp; ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing vpon the same notes of falshood; <hi>That the Pope is our Lord God; that he can do more then euer God did,</hi> and the rest. Often also singing vnto their false notes the very same ditty of this misapplyed text: <hi>We would haue cured Babel</hi> &amp;c. By which clamorous rayling, they put their ignorant Auditors into such rage, &amp; fury against vs, that as<note n="(k)" place="margin">Erasm. in spongia aduersus Hutten.</note>
      <hi>Erasmus</hi> noted long ago, they come frō sermons no lesse fierce, &amp; fiery, then souldiers from the warlike speach of a Captaine exhorting them to fight. I remember I haue read of the Cittizens of<note n="(l)" place="margin">Lucian. Quomodo scribēda sit historia.</note>
      <hi>Abdera,</hi> that once hearing a furious Tragedy in a hoat day of summer, they were all stroken into such a fit of frenzie, that many dayes after they did nothing but act the same tragedy with furious gestures in their streets. The like doth often happen in <hi>England</hi> by the Tragicall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayming of Ministers against vs, specially when the persecution is hoatest, they seeke to kindle the same fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery impressions of hatred in others, wherwith thēselues are inraged: the Monsters wherwith they thus fright poore men out of their wits, against the faith of their Ancestours, being euer cōmonly <hi>M. Crashawes</hi> Babels, that, <hi>We teach the Pope to be God,</hi> that, <hi>with the Virgin Marie God hath deuided his Kingdome;</hi> that, <hi>Images are better bookes then Scripture;</hi> that, <hi>we pray vnto stockes and stones,</hi> and the rest.</p>
   <p n="7">7. VVherin they do liuely imitate the<note n="(m)" place="margin">Diu multum{que} de imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorib{us} la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissimè ac vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissimè dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putabant. <hi>Aug. de vtil. cred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> c.</hi> 1.</note>
      <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees,</hi> who seeme to haue exceeded all other Heretikes in their slaunderous charging the Church of Christ with senslesse, and prodigious doctrine, as with teaching, that, <hi>God is enuious, furious, mutable, subiect to passion, cruell,</hi> and the like, declayming bitterly against such blasphemies, citing some words of the old Testament
<pb n="10" facs="6"/>that might sound to that sense. And two reasons as <hi>S. Augustine</hi> noteth, moued them to this course, the very same that make our Ministers follow the same deceipt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full course. First to affright ignorant people from the bosome of the Cath. Church, by setting fearfull bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beares of horrible blasphemy vpon her, that not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whither else to go, they might in a manner be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to fly to the <hi>Manichean</hi> Conuenticles, like Fowlers (saith this<note n="(n)" place="margin">Ita{que} nobis faci ebāt quod solent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidiosi au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupes, qui viscatos surculos propè a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figunt, vt sitientes aues deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piant: ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruunt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim, &amp; quoquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periunt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias quae circa sunt aquas, vel inde etiam prodigio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis moliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onib{us} de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrent, vt in eorum dolos, non electione, sed inopia decidatur. <hi>Aug. de vtilit. credend. c.</hi> 1.</note>
 Father) who hauing laid their lime-twigs by some water side, seeke to stop other waters thera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, or set some dreadfull scar-crowes ouer them, that the poore birds not knowing where els to find water, not out of choice, but out of meer necessity come at last to light in their snares. Secondly, not to want matter in their Sermons, which they might copiously dilate vpō, to get with men of small iudgment the name of great Preachers, by making large &amp; graue inuectiues, which any man (saith<note n="(o)" place="margin">Quod cuiuis mediocriter erudito esset facillimum. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>S. Augustine</hi>) though of very meane learning may easily do against such palpable fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, as are, <hi>God his being mutable, passionate, furious</hi> &amp;c. In confutation of which Babels the <hi>Manichees</hi> did vse to spend long sermōs, with almost as much stayed gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity, as <hi>M. Crashaw,</hi> and other Ministers do vse in their pulpits, to rayle at vs, for teaching <hi>the Pope to be God, the Virgin Marie more then God,</hi> and such stuffe</p>
   <p n="8">8. Against which manner of dealing, I will set downe the saying of this learned Father, intreating the Reader to marke the same, which may serue him for an Antidote against, and an Answere vnto all this kind of
<pb n="11" facs="6"/>Sermons: (p) <hi>In has, &amp; huiusmodi nugas grauiter, copio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sé{que} inuehi soletis</hi> &amp;c. Against these and such like toyes you make graue, and large inuectiues, which do no wayes concerne vs; you speake only against old wiues tales, and childish Babels. In confutation of which, the more earnest you are, the more you shew your selues to want iudgmēt. By which clamors whosoeuer is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to turne vnto you, he condemneth not the doctrine of our Church, but sheweth himselfe ignorant therof. Wherfore if you haue any thing of men left in you, if you haue any care of your selues, seeke diligently in what good and pious sense these things may be spoken. For such a faith as belieueth of God absurd, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient things, we do more vehemently, and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully accuse, then you; and when by any of our Church these things are vnderstood as the letter soundeth, their ignorance we instruct, their pertinacity we deride. Thus <hi>S. Augustine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="9">9. The third vse that may be made of this Answer, is yet more generall, and vniuersall, and of greater importance, and sequele, at which I confesse I haue principally aymed, to wit to shew that the English Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistry cannot be a true Church, nor among them sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing truth be found, which doth practise, &amp; patronize both in pulpit, and print most notorious lying, and furious rayling. For this to be a manifest, and sensible signe of a false Church, themselues doe graunt<note n="(q)" place="margin">Nos inuectio vestra non tāgit, sed aniles quasdam vel pueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les etiam opiniones eò inepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore quò vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiore ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellitis; qua quis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetur &amp; ad vos trā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit, non Ecclesiae nostrae dā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinam, sed eam se ignorare demōstrat Quamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brem si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de geritis, si curae vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis vos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metipsi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stis, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite potiùs diligenter &amp; pie, quo modo ista dicantur. Quaerite miseri: nam talem fidem qua de Deo inconueniens a liquid creditur, nos vehementiùs &amp; vberiùs accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>samus. Nam &amp; in illis quae dicta sunt cùm sic intelliguntur, vt littera sonat, &amp; simplicitatem corrigimus, &amp; pertinaciam deridemus. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de mor. Eccl. c.</hi> 10.</note>
      <note n="(q)" place="margin">See the way to the true Church, of M. VVhite in the Preface. n. <hi>12.</hi>
      </note>
      <pb n="12" facs="7"/>which without shame they cannot deny, seeing this sinne Nature doth so detest, that no Nation, though barbarous, durst euer openly allow it; a sinne <hi>most hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and abhominable</hi>
      <note n="(r)" place="margin">
         <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 22.</note>
      <hi>vnto God,</hi> most shamefull in the<note n="(s)" place="margin">Seruile vitium, nec in ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo quidē tolerabile. <hi>Plutarch.</hi>
      </note>
 eye of the world: in so much that the <hi>Wisemā</hi> saith:<note n="(t)" place="margin">
         <hi>Eccl. c.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 27. potior est fur quàm assiduitas viri men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacis.</note>
      <hi>Better is familiarity with a theefe, then with a lyar:</hi> which sinne is euer the indiuiduall mate, &amp; companion of heresy, as <hi>Iob</hi> doth signify, speaking to his friends that were the type of hereticks, as<note n="(v)" place="margin">L. <hi>11.</hi> moral. c. <hi>15.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>S. Gregory</hi> noteth: <hi>I will shew you to be</hi>
      <note n="(x)" place="margin">
         <hi>Iob.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>coyners of lyes, and maynteyners of false doctrine:</hi> where you see lyars, and hereticks shake hands. Whom likewise the holy Ghost doth couple to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather in this sentence:<note n="(y)" place="margin">
         <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</note>
      <hi>Loquitur mendacia versi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellis.</hi> Turne-coates (such as change the first faith wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were cloathed in Baptisme) do vse to speake lyes, and vntruths. So that this is a blemish not in face and finger, for such woundes <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> would not sticke to graunt<note n="(z)" place="margin">
         <hi>Pag.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>2.</note>
 in the Church of <hi>England:</hi> but such as doth eat vp the very hart of a Church (to vse his owne phrase) which cannot be thought Christian, nor the Church of truth, being treacherous and false, seeking to delude the world with lyes.</p>
   <p n="10">10. But you will say, though I might proue that <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> is guilty of this cryme; yet I should be vniust to lay his lying properly on the whole Church of <hi>England</hi> for his sake, vrging the fault of one as the practise of all. To this I answere, that had <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> published this Sermon as a priuate iustification of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, his want of sincerity therein could not without some violence haue beene wrested vpon his Church; though truly the permitting in print of so many and so palpable falsehoods might giue some cause to sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, that their Church did giue at least a tacite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<pb n="13" facs="7"/>to such iniurious dealing. But the case now stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth otherwise about this Sermon, and in such termes that the Church of <hi>England</hi> cannot seuer her publick disgrace from his priuate shame. For whereas Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks haue often complayned of Ministers iniurious dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with them in pulpit, to make them odious vnto the people, by declayming slaunders against them, but specially of <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> in this his Sermō at the Crosse, which they thought so exorbitant, as they gaue out (as he himself<note n="(a)" place="margin">In his Epistle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory to the Princes Highnes.</note>
 saith) that he was called before au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for his immodest excesse in this kind, which you shall see by the examination thereof, they had great cause to thinke: Whereas I say these complaynts were made, and this expectation had, that some signe of publick dislike would be giuen against such intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate preaching, <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> to shew that Authority did not mislike, but allow his dealing, did not condemne, but patronize it, after some moneths taken to thinke of the matter, to view ouer his Sermon, and perchance to leaue out some more notorious and shamefull vntru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes which he durst vtter in pulpit though not in print, at last makes the same publick, bringing his owne shame to light. But to what end? Heare it in his owne words in the Epistle dedicatory to the Princes High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: <hi>Not so much to cleare my self</hi> (sayth he) <hi>as to honour the truth, and to shew, that it is no trick, nor policy of our State (as it is in Popery) to set vp men with authority to rayle, and licence to lye, therby to make our enemyes odious.</hi> Thus he. And in his<note n="(b)" place="margin">This dedication was the first, but his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship discar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Sermon.</note>
 Epistle to the Lord Treasurer, he addeth, that he did publish his Sermon to honour truth, but much more to iustify the State: such desire doth this Minister shew to be rather a Statesman then a true man. But if by the State he vnderstand those of
<pb n="14" facs="8"/>his Maiesties most honorable Counsell, he needeth not to iustify whom none accuse, whom their owne Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour doth sufficiently cleere from any suspition of allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing such dishonourable dealing, who cannot be stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with these Ministeriall crymes, seeing they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the charge, to see they bring not such foule thinges into pulpit, vnto their Bishops, and Prelates, on whom this disgrace must lye, and from them redound vnto their Church. For this their publishing of the Sermon to be a patterne of their truth, and modesty, &amp; to shew that our complaints against them are vniust, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cause, was as much as to say vnto the Church of <hi>Rome, ab vno disce omnes,</hi> by this one Minister learne all the rest; see how sincere in accusing, modest in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending, solide in reprouing your errours, iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in producing, diligent in perusing, faithfull in quoting your Authors we are: finally how far from any lying, and rayling, which you falsely lay to our charge. By which also you may see, that the credit of the Church of <hi>England</hi> lyeth vpon <hi>M. Crashawes</hi> head, which must needs be crackt in peeces, if in this very Sermō which they made publike to iustify themselues, we find rayling and lying, in very exorbitant, or rather impudent manner.</p>
   <p n="11">11. As for his recrimination, that it is a trick in Popery to set vp men with authority to rayle and lye, the proofes he bringeth are so poore, that they will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther serue to discouer his fraud and falshood, and make his impudency more apparent, compared with the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of our proceeding.<note place="margin">See his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to the Earle of Salisbury.</note>
 For wheras we charge him with many hundred of manifest and vnexcusable slaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, vttered in this one Sermon, he <hi>that hath spent the whole course of his studies to peruse our Records,</hi> could bring
<pb n="15" facs="8"/>but three examples, and those neither to the purpose, nor true. Nay therin he doth shew his owne false dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as will appeare by the examination of them, as they are set downe in his Epistle Dedicatory to the Princes Highnesse. <hi>A Booke</hi> (saith he) <hi>was printed in the English Colledge at Rome, wherin it is affirmed, that we take Catholikes, and draw vpon their legs bootes full of hoat boyling liquour, and vpon their feet hoat burning shoes: &amp; do put them into Beares skins, and cast them to the dogs to be pulled in peeces. All this, and many such other set down in pictures.</hi> But first it is false that any such book was prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the English Colledge, in which since the first e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectiō therof neuer any book was printed. Some things indeed are painted vpon the walls of their Church, which booke perchance the Bachelour meaneth: so that insteed of Preachers set vp in pulpit, he accuseth Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hyred to make pictures vpon walls, which is great folly, seing all graunt vnto them<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoribus at{que} Poetis quidlibet audendi sēper fuit aequa po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testas. <hi>Horat.</hi>
      </note>
 licence to deuise and faigne without charge of falsehood. And if a Catholike painter to expresse how Priests in <hi>England</hi> are traduced as Traytors; how disguised with the vgly terms of enemies of the State, they are made hateful, did paint thē in the forme of a man in a Beares skin, no lesse meeke and innocent within, then dreadfull and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble without; if to represent the fury and violence of Purseuants in hunting after, seeking out, and abusing these men, he did expresse thē vnder the shape of bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds, or mastiues: truely I see no reason why this may not be aswell excused, as their ordinary painting the Pope in the shape of vgly Monsters, and <hi>Iohn Fox</hi> his filling his lying Acts &amp; Monuments with such Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants, and ridiculous deuises, to fright fooles, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was Father. Secondly I say, that these things are
<pb n="16" facs="9"/>not our deuises or inuentions, but true storyes, that at <hi>Louth</hi> in <hi>Lincolneshire</hi> a Catholike was put into a beares skinne &amp; torne in peeces by doggs in King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. his dayes, whether by publick authority or popular fury it is not certayne; which answere was made long since to <hi>Syr</hi>
      <note n="(c)" place="margin">See the warn-word to Syr F.H. watch-word <hi>2.</hi> encount. <hi>c. 2.</hi> pag. <hi>6.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Frauncis Hastings,</hi> and not yet refuted. As touching bootes of boyling liquour, a venerable By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Ireland</hi> had bootes annoynted with oyle put on his leggs, and set to the fire, was put to cruell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. So that they accuse vs of speaking fables, when we doe but rehearse their furyes, and belying vs to feygne what their cruelty forced vs to feele.</p>
   <p n="12">12. The second instance or charge is more vayne, and false then the first. <hi>Feuardant a famous fryar</hi> (sayth he) <hi>wrote in latyn seauen yeares agoe, that we reuile, and reiect that prayer to the holy Trinity,</hi> Sancta Trinitas vnus Deus, miserere nobis: <hi>what will not he say, that dare say this?</hi> Thus he. But indeed the Bachelour doth abuse that famous, and learned Fryar, who doth only say, that the errour against the inuocation of the <hi>Blessed Trinity,</hi> was<note n="(d)" place="margin">Feuar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant. in <hi>1.</hi> Petri. c. <hi>1.</hi> fol. <hi>140.</hi> edit. Paris. <hi>1600.</hi>
      </note>
 restored by <hi>Caluinists</hi> in <hi>France, Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> who cauill at, and reiect the former prayer. Where you see he doth not charge with that er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour all heretikes, or Protestants in those Countryes, but <hi>Caluinists</hi> only; nor all <hi>Caluinists</hi> neyther, but some, to wit such, as are of the purer strayne, that mislike all words in prayer that are not found in Scripture, and follow <hi>Caluin</hi> exactly in all points, who doth wish buried in obliuion the name of <hi>Trinity,</hi> and such like, as<note n="(e)" place="margin">Feuar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant. vbi supra pag. <hi>36.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Feuardant</hi> proueth. Wherefore I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of <hi>M. Crashaw,</hi> when he saith, <hi>Feuardant doth write, that we reiect the prayer</hi> &amp;c. whom doth he meane by that <hi>(we?) We</hi> State Protestants, or <hi>We</hi> Puritans?
<pb n="17" facs="9"/>for I think his conscience is not so stiffe vnto one, but it may extend to the other. If Protestants, <hi>Feuardant</hi> doth not charge them. If Puritans, the Bachelour doth vainly seeke to iustify them by the booke of Common Prayer which they are knowne to hate and detest. So that this trick <hi>of setting vp lyers,</hi> commeth to fall vpon his owne head.</p>
   <p n="13">13. In the third charge of falsehood, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Gretzerus</hi> his narration, concerning Father <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> and <hi>Ouen</hi> his man, he doth neither cite the words, nor quote the place, nor name the booke, and at most it is but an Historicall vntruth, wherunto men are sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, as <hi>Iohn Fox</hi> was in his Calendar of Martyrs, who reporteth of some that were<note n="(f)" place="margin">Iohn Marbecke the singer of winde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sore and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>Acts and mon.</hi> 115.</note>
 burnt into ashes vnder Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> which liued and drunke merrily in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes many a faire day after Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> her cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Crowne. But our Controuersie is about wilfull, and malicious falsehood, which the Authour could not but know to be such when he wrote or spake it, wherof we accuse <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> and his Church. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue they cause to wonder, though strangers doe not giue great credit vnto their publike Acts, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords against Priests and Iesuits, against whom the State professeth emnity, which may giue cause to feare, and suspect partiall<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessae ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micitiae suspitionē habent mendacij <hi>Hieron.</hi>
      </note>
 dealing, specially when the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons condemned are well knowne vnto strangers, and their learning and sanctity highly esteemed. But this Minister that doth so declayme against the contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of their publick Records concerning the Powder-treason, doth he beare respect vnto them himself, when they restrayne his tongue from railing against the Pope? No truly: which you may ghesse by this one example: euen in this very Sermon<note n="(h)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 43.</note>
 speaking of a
<pb n="18" facs="10"/>certayne forme of prayer for the conuersion of the Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> to the Catholick faith set out by Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Eight in the yeare 1603. as euen he doth confesse, vpon newes of the late Queens mortall sicknesse, before his Ma<seg rend="sup">ties</seg> cōming to the Crowne: speaking I say of this Letany, &amp; the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors therof, he saith: <hi>when these men had conceiued and hatched at</hi> Rome <hi>the Powder-treason, then to make vs se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and belieue they loued vs, they framed prayers for vs.</hi> Thus he. What respect doth this Minister beare vnto their publike Records, by which it appeareth, that, that execrable Treason was conceaued &amp; hatcht in <hi>Englād,</hi> and when, where, and by whome? Neither was any the least suspition of that bloudy intendment cast vpon the former Pope, which slaunder the best in <hi>England</hi> knew he did little deserue. And is contradicting publik Records reprehensible in a stranger, and not punisha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in a subiect? Or is it lawfull against the Pope, and not in the behalfe of Priests? This bould vttering of shamefull vntruths against so graue &amp; venerable men, and euen Princes, doth make our Countrey infamous with strangers, that some sticke not to say, that our I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, if Ministers pens may haue liberty still, will in tyme dispossesse <hi>Crete</hi> of her<note n="(i)" place="margin">Non hoc, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis sit mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dax Creta, neque po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test. <hi>Ouid.</hi>
      </note>
 Syrname: might it please the Lords of his Maiesties Counsell, to call this Minister to accompt, and vrge him to proue what he doth so peremptorily affirme, that the Powder-treason was conceaued and hatcht at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 1603. or before, by the Authors of that Letany, wherof Pope <hi>Clement</hi> was chief, it were a thing not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of their knowledg. And if the Bachelour cānot proue what he hath written, let him be punished as he doth deserue, for putting in print such open vntruths,
<pb n="19" facs="10"/>to the infamy of the State that may seem to permit thē, specially this Sermon being also translated<note n="(k)" place="margin">See the Frankford mart of the <hi>1610.</hi>
      </note>
 into La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin. This example of equity would moue strangers, &amp; forraine Princes to beare more reuerence vnto their publike Records, the neglect of which cannot be iustly misliked in strāgers, whiles it is permitted in Subiects.</p>
   <p n="13">13. Thus I haue shewed how vayne, and false the Bachelours instances are to proue it a trick in popery to set vp men to rayle and lye against Protestants, who hath not brought so much as one Preacher that v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed such lying in pulpit, much lesse a Sermon of sole slaūders, as the ensuing discourse doth clearly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate his to be, beginning at the very first sentence of his second Part, which first sentence, to wit, <hi>that</hi> Bellarmine <hi>doth graunt the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>to be my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall Babylon,</hi> is so notorious false, and so contradicted by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> almost in euery word of his writing, that I much wonder how the man could so far forget him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe as to thinke it, hauing thought to preach it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing preached print it, and some yeares since the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting being past, neuer yet reclayme it; I must thinke it was Gods speciall prouidence, that such an eminēt fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shood should be placed in the forehead or first sentence of his inuectiue, by which the iudicious Readers might perceaue, that fury and passion against the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> so blindeth the Minister, that he doth vnderstād neyther what he readeth in others, nor what he saith himselfe. And from the same prouidence of God, that taketh the wise in their wisdome, and turneth their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>icy into folly, we may thinke proceedeth the blindnes of their Bishops, and Ministry, that haue chosen or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted this Sermō of <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> to be printed for their iustification, and to stop our complaints that they rayle
<pb n="20" facs="11"/>and bely vs in pulpit. For if this Sermon be more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate, &amp; rayling then any other they vse to make, their want of iudgment is admirable to let the same passe to the print for a patterne. But if the same be more modest, and sober then many which he and his fellowes vse to make in this kind (as perchance it is) truly their dealing must needes be most detestable, and hatefull; whereof this Sermon is the fayrest and best, which is nothing els, but a long cob-web of foule and fond slaunders wouen of no other matter, then the venyme of the preachers bowels, howsoeuer he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to gather it out of the sayings, and sentences of our Authors.</p>
   <p n="15">15. For though he protest in his Preface to the Reader vpon his conscience, to haue forged no new Author, to haue falsyfied none, to haue corrupted none, to haue brought no quotation of any Author of ours, which he hath not diligently perused aforehand, &amp; the whole scope of the place, stopping against him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe the starting hole, to which<note n="(l)" place="margin">In his preamble to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter pag. <hi>100. 104.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>M. Morton,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ministers fly for defence, when they are charged with witting falsification of our Authors, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the same vpon the credit of <hi>Iohn Stock,</hi> or by the suggestion of <hi>R. C.</hi> yet is there scarse any quotation of any of our Authors cited in this Sermon, which is not very notoriously corrupted, either by putting in words of his owne, or leauing out words of theirs, or ioyning togeather the wordes that are deuided in the Authors, into the same sentence, or by peruerting the scope and drift of the place; or finally which is his ordinary and common trick, by false translating their sentences into English, wresting them vpon the rack of his large con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, till they reach to the length of his false slaūder,
<pb n="21" facs="11"/>many tymes forcing them by torture to say in English what they detest in Latin. Which manner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in him that perused diligently the places, cannot be excused from wilfull falsehood, &amp; wicked desire to deceyue his Auditours &amp; Readers, in the most impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant affayre of knowing the true Church, wheron their eternall saluation doth depend. Of which treacherous dealing this Sermon doth affoard so plentiful examples, that I say againe, that few places are by him cyted (if any) that haue not some notorious marke of falshood printed vpon them: and scarse is there any sentence frō the first page of his second part, where he begins with full mouth his rayling Inuectiue, to the last therof (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue a hundred in number) which is not eyther notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously false, or extremely foolish. Which dealing though it may seeme incredible in him, after the former prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station of truth often reiterated in his Sermon, and this censure, bitter and harsh to them that haue chosen him to be the Patterne and Patron of their sincerity, &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty: yet I desire not to be belieued, but vpon euident proofe therof, which followeth in this Treatise, where Protestants may learne that falshood can neuer be defēded with truth, as crafty Ministers that haue made <hi>Machiauel</hi> a witnesse of their<note n="*" place="margin">Catalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus testium veritatis l. <hi>19.</hi> col. <hi>1916.</hi> edit. ann. <hi>1608.</hi> ex offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Iacobi Stoeret Chouet.</note>
 Ghospell, haue long since learned that <hi>Machiauelian</hi> Principle of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous <hi>Theban: Children are deceyued with Apples, and men with Oathes.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="16">16. VVhich protestations of truth, and shewes of Godlynesse haue bene so strong to deceiue, that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flyes, and seely people, but also some other (in their owne conceipt) neither flyes nor small fooles, haue byn caught in this cobweb. Nay euen that<note n="(m)" place="margin">Syr Edward Hobby.</note>
 Knight whose pen is more famous then his sword, and whose
<pb n="22" facs="12"/>wit, were it answerable to his name, or his learning so high as his owne cōceipt therof, might be well thought a soaring bird, doth commend this Sermon<note n="(n)" place="margin">In his letter to T.H. <hi>pag.</hi> 54. &amp; 55.</note>
 speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to proue that we do degenerate from the doctrine of ancient Fathers in twenty particulers, insulting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, that we haue not hitherto made answere vnto them. But if it may please him to peruse this Treatise, he will perchance both be ashamed of his boast &amp; his fluttering in a web of so weake slaunders, &amp; neuer trust his trencher-schoolmaisters, or Ministers herafter, that cast flyes, and follyes vpon his trencher, wherwith he hath stuffed his vnlearned Letter, as he may see an exā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or two, which we haue examined in<note n="(o)" place="margin">In the first Part chap. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note>
 this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise.</p>
   <p n="17">17. Now the reason that hath moued me to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this Treatise vnto You (HONOVRABLE COVNTREYMEN) you may easily imagine, to wit, a carefull respect of your saluation, and of your honour, both which this Minister, who still styleth himselfe Preacher in one of your Innes of Court, doth bring into eminent danger: your saluation, by preaching false and execrable slaunders; your honour, by publishing in print many ridiculous follyes. The care of your saluation did moue me to present this coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-poyson specially vnto them, into whose breasts the Spyder may be thought to haue more plētifully infused his venyme; to offer You this fan of truth to cleanse your Temples, which more then any other place haue bene filled with these cobwebs, where the deceyuer hath hid himselfe these many yeares in a fayre shew of feygned Godlynesse, to intangle his credulous Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, in wicked &amp; dānable hatred of that faith, which our Forefathers did most gloriously professe. Did you
<pb n="23" facs="12"/>well vnderstand, and seriously consider, what horrible hatred against Catholike Religion he doth breath out in his Sermon, and seeke to inspire into your harts; I cannot thinke, but that your Wisdome, Conscience, &amp; Christianity is such, as you would detest it.</p>
   <p n="18">18. For though we had euer iust cause to suspect secret Atheisme, and small Christianity in many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, that they do hate Catholikes more thē Atheists, that they desire rather the ouerthrow of all Religion, then the bringing in of the Roman: yet none before Your Preacher (that I know of) durst make such open profession therof, who doth, and dareth giue vs many cleare signs of this his holy hatred. What shall we think was the reason that making lawes for <hi>Virginia,</hi> in his new yeares-gift vnto<note n="(p)" place="margin">In the latter end of that Sermon.</note>
 her, against them he most ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or would seeme to hate, nameth first <hi>Papists,</hi> then <hi>Atheists,</hi> and lastly <hi>Brownists?</hi> And of Papists he saith, <hi>that the Pope for Popery, be not so much as heard of in Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia:</hi> but for Atheists he will let them be named. Nay the <hi>Virginian</hi> Church shalbe honoured by hauing their names in her first Law. And good reason, seeing the first men sent, and intended as her Apostles, were for the most part Atheists, and prophane fellowes, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe doth partly confesse. But you see this wise Law-maker out of his hatred vnto Papists, will haue them first excluded from the Common-Wealth of his owne head and hart before Atheists, though he will not vouchsafe to name them, as <hi>Solon</hi> out of extreme ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of Parricides left them out in his <hi>Athenian</hi> lawes. But will you heare him yet more clearly professe togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at once his little loue vnto God, and huge hatred against the Pope in this very Sermon? Hauing found a worme-eaten saying of an old Glosse left out in all later
<pb n="24" facs="13"/>Editions as he cannot deny, which he thought did sound of blasphemy, he doth openly confesse, <hi>that</hi>
      <note n="(q)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 73.</note>
      <hi>he will not conceale the same, but discharge his duty to the truth, though he may giue vantage to the Atheists, and Libertines.</hi> The truth is, he doth discharge his duty not to God, but to the Diuell, not to truth, but falshood, by falsifying the meaning of the Glosser, as I haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in that place. But suppose it had been a true errour, was that blasphemy of such importance (thinke you) to be knowne, that <hi>Atheisme</hi> must be set forward and aduaunced, rather then that errour of the Glosse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed? God throwne downe, rather then the Pope spared? Can any religion be in him that will ioyne with the Atheist against God, rather then (I doe not say become a Papist, or speake a good word for the Pope, for he will perchance rather be a Diuell then do it) but so much as forbeare speaking a thing that may seeme to disgrace the Pope, the vttering of which did not import the worth of a rush? I am content any Christian, or any man that doth feelingly belieue there is a God, be iudg in this case. For that your Christianity and Cōscience doth detest such hatred of any religion whatsoeuer, I cannot without doing you wrong mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strust.</p>
   <p n="19">19. Doe you desire yet another, and a more cleare argument of your preachers Atheisme, that secretly harboureth in his hart? You may find one very noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in <hi>his</hi>
      <note n="(1)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 26.</note>
      <hi>Iesuits Ghospell,</hi> which ioyned with the former by cōparing the two different shewes of zeale togeather, will make his impiety apparent through the veyle of hypocrisy, though he double the same with neuer so many fouldes, and fayre shewes of zeale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Pope. You haue heard how dutifull the
<pb n="25" facs="13"/>man is to the truth, how scrupulous to conceale the same, though by vtterance thereof he may giue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage to the Atheist to deny God. But what if a seeming zeale of Gods honour may giue him a colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable occasion (in his fond conceipt) to conceale the truth of the dignity of Gods Mother; will he thinke it a sinne not to discharge his duty to the truth? Will he thinke it reason to condemne them, that in shew of zeale to Gods honour shall speake vntruth, and <hi>giuing passage</hi> to their passions, breake the Mother of God in peeces with lyes, and slaunders? Marke his doctrine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this matter, and then admire the scrupulous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of the man. Whereas Catholikes obiect vnto Protestants, that diuers principall writers of their sect haue spoken irreuerently, and blasphemously of Gods blessed Mother, your preacher not denying the fact, but iustifying the same as done in laudable zeale, sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vs this answere, if any shape can be in such a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster. <hi>If any of our religion</hi> (saith he) <hi>hath giuen any words of her that may giue the least blemish to her blessed state, it was not done in any the least contempt of her, but in the zeale they bare to the honour of their Sauiour, whom they held dishonoured by the vnequall comparing of her with him. For what will not a Christian mans zeale cause him to doe</hi>
      <note n="(2)" place="margin">Not to slander any man, nor to blasphem any Saynt though hypocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall zeale will giue aduantage to Atheists against God.</note>
      <hi>when he seeth his God dishonored? Who would haue thought that Moyses would haue cast so carelesly out of his handes so precious a Iewel, as were the two tables written with the finger of God? And yet when he heard the name of the Lord blasphemed, he forgot himself, and them, and as though he remembred none but God, he threw them away, and brake them in peeces. If Moyses zeale makes his hastines excusable,</hi> no reason to condemne them whose zeale gaue passage to their passions, <hi>and caused them for the honour of their
<pb n="26" facs="14"/>Creatour, to forget the priuiledge of a creature.</hi> Thus he? In which words few Readers I thinke can be so simple or blind, not to espy a wolfe whose teeth water with desire to teare in pieces the <hi>immaculate mother of the lamb of God,</hi> though he would faigne couer himselfe, and do it in <hi>a sheeps skin of zeale,</hi> which wil not serue his turne; the example of <hi>Moyses</hi> the meekest of men, being too short &amp; little by much, to hyde the least particle of such monstrous fury, as is <hi>giuing passage to passions against Gods Mother,</hi> specially so full of blaphemy, and falshood as theirs are.</p>
   <p n="20">20. And first to discouer his faygned zeale, marke (as I touched before) how it is hoat or cold as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, sometimes dutifull to truth against Gods honour; somtymes zealous of Gods honour against truth, as the taking vpon him a shew of eyther of these zeales may best serue his turne to giue, vnder pretence of piety, a passage to his passions against the Pope. Somtimes his zeale to Gods honour is so calme, that he is content God be euen denyed, not caring though his discourse <hi>may giue aduantage</hi> therunto. At other times so hoat in the spirit, and zealous of Gods honour, that the least sound of a blasphemy (though but in a poeme) will put him into a traunce, where forgetting the true priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a creature, to honour the Creatour, he will thinke it no sinne to speake vildely and irreuerently of his Mother, vttering slaunders that <hi>may giue blemishes to her blessed state.</hi> Is any man so blind that doth not see this zeale to be coūterfayt, true neither towards truth, nor God, which he can make hoat and cold, sweet and sower, carefull &amp; carelesse of the same thing as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth? Can any thing be in that hart sincere, from which both hatred, and neglect of blasphemy, both reuerence
<pb n="27" facs="14"/>and contempt of truth, both zeale and carelesnesse of Gods honour doth flow? Secondly, heere you may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the impiety of Ministers, and the true cause why they so curiously search into our writings, to find some speaches concerning the Blessed Virgin that may seeme blasphemy, which when they haue found, wrapping their woluish intentiōs in a sheeps skin of zeale against it, they straight fal into a traunce, forgetting thēselues, and giuing passage to their passions, against her whom they hate the more, because the Church of God doth highly honour her.</p>
   <p n="21">21. In this zeale we cannot deny, but <hi>Iohn Caluin</hi> the <hi>Moyses</hi> of their new Law, did forget himselfe and the Virgin (how he remembred God her Sonne, let the Reader iudge) whē he wrote, that in the birth of Christ she was so broken and weakened, that the fourty daies before her Purification, were not sufficient for her to recouer her forces, but God did yet spare her, <hi>donec ex</hi>
      <note n="(3)" place="margin">Caluin Harmon. in cap. <hi>2.</hi> Matth. v. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>puerperio conualesceret,</hi> that she might gather vp her strength lost in the labour of child-birth. In this zeale doe diuers Protestants giue passage to their passions, accusing her to haue committed as great sinnes as <hi>Eue</hi>
      <note n="(4)" place="margin">Cētur. l. <hi>1.</hi> cēt. <hi>1.</hi>
      </note>
 the Mother of mischiefe vnto all mankind, making her the very type of Heretikes, and Infidels, carnall<note n="(5)" place="margin">Sarceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in Euā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel. de festo annunciat. apud Cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sium. l. <hi>4.</hi> de Deipar. c. <hi>7.</hi>
      </note>
 and prophane men. In which passion a Lutheran prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vpon her answere to the Angell, <hi>How can this be done,</hi> called her <hi>Zuinglian,</hi> and<note n="(6)" place="margin">Georg. Muller. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin. <hi>2.</hi> p. fol. <hi>390.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Caluinist,</hi> whom they hate no lesse (if not more) then<note n="(7)" place="margin">
         <hi>Insata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized, su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persatani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, persa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanized.</hi> Luther. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Tigur. in tract. <hi>3.</hi> cōt. suprē. confess. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theri.</note>
 Diuels. But no man more like <hi>Moyses</hi> in forgetting himselfe, and breaking in pieces the tables of the Law, then our English Minister<note n="(8)" place="margin">In his booke of Christian exercise p. <hi>669.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>M. Buney,</hi> who dareth to write, that when that innocent, &amp; sorrowfull LADY stood at the foot of the Crosse, <hi>she brake foure commaundements
<pb n="28" facs="15"/>of God at one clap, the first, the fifth, the sixt, the ninth,</hi> by this blasphemous slaūder breaking into pieces both the tables of the Law in her Virginall hart, where Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an antiquity did euer belieue they were<note n="(9)" place="margin">De Sā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta Maria Virgine nullam habere volo, cùm de pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis agitur, mentionē, quae gratiā habuit ad vincendū omni ex parte pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum. <hi>Aug. de nat. &amp; grat. c.</hi> 36.</note>
 inuiolably kept. In this pretēded zeale <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> practising him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, what he doth patronize in others, thinking (or making a shew to thinke) that we compare <hi>her breasts and milke with the wounds and bloud of Christ,</hi> doth like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise forget himselfe, saying, <hi>that no extraordinary</hi>
      <note n="(10)" place="margin">In his Iesuits Ghospell pag. <hi>44.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>blessednesse doth belong to the wombe of the Virgin, none to her breasts</hi> in this regard only, that they did breed, and feed the Sonne of God, that she whome we do so exalt, is <hi>no more then another</hi>
      <note n="(11)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 91.</note>
      <hi>holy woman,</hi> but <hi>a belieuing</hi>
      <note n="(12)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 36.</note>
      <hi>Iew.</hi> And giuing further passage to his passions, he doth not only beate her sacred wombe and breasts into dust &amp; wormes, by scoffing at her assumption into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen<note n="(13)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag</hi> 95.</note>
 but also carelessely casteth them out of his hart into a lower place then wormes &amp; magots, by a foule comparison of them &amp; her milke, with other<note n="(14)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 92</note>
 wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens; not excepting the most impurest Strumpet. What <hi>Seneca</hi>
      <note n="(15)" place="margin">L. <hi>3.</hi> de ira. c. <hi>14.</hi>
      </note>
 said of the arrowes which a barbarous<note n="(†)" place="margin">Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byses.</note>
 Tyrant did fasten in the hart of a child, making the same his marke, praysed by the flattering<note n="(¶)" place="margin">Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xaspes.</note>
 Father of the child that stood by, we may say of these blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that do so deeply penetrate into the hart, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Christs Mother, iustified by <hi>M. Crashaw,</hi> that they are <hi>sceleratiùs laudata tela, quàm missa,</hi> not so barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously discharged, as commended, that the tongue is more blasphemous that doth prayse such passions, then the pen that wrote them.</p>
   <p n="22">22. And as for <hi>Moyses</hi> his example of breaking the tables of the law, the Bachelour doth wrong that great Prophet, by accusing him to haue bene <hi>hasty, carelesse,
<pb n="29" facs="15"/>forgetfull</hi> in that fact which he did aduisedly &amp; piously, not dishonoring the tables, but honouring them rather, thinking them to be ouer worthy Iewells to be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to drunken people, as <hi>S.</hi>
      <note n="(16)" place="margin">Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctissimus indignum existima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, vino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lētū popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum à Deo legem ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere. <hi>Ser.</hi> 1. <hi>de ieiunio ante mediū.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Basile</hi> sayth; as Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes honour the Images of Christ which they put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire, rather then permit them to fall into here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes handes that will abuse them. But had <hi>Moyses</hi> (pretending zeale) fell into a rage against to Tables, calling them the law of sinne and the Diuell, whose Slaue heretickes in their passions make the Virgin in whose hart God with his owne finger wrote his law; had <hi>Moyses</hi> in a faigned traunce reuiled <hi>Abraham,</hi> or <hi>Isaac,</hi> or any deceased Saynt; had he falsly slaundered the meanest woman lyuing, as Ministers doe the <hi>most blessed of women,</hi> and the most glorious of all Sayntes; I thinke no Christian would haue dared to speake a word in defence of that zeale, as I doe not know that any man pretending the name of a Christiā before this Bachelour, did euer iustify against Gods mother con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed blasphemy, <hi>that may blemish her blessed state.</hi> And verily I doe somewhat wonder in what a slumber Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Bishops were, when they did permit such a defence of passions passe to the print, full not only of blasphemy against the Virgin, but also of discredit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their owne writers, giuing such a censure of them, which if it be true, the man that shall beare respect to their writinges may iustly be thought worse then mad. For how can any well in his wits belieue such bookes whose authours euen by their best friendes are confessed to haue written, forgetting themselues, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing passage to their passions without exact care of truth? How can we thinke that doctrine deserueth credit which they did deliuer, not knowing what they
<pb n="30" facs="16"/>said, thinking of one thing, and speaking of another, <hi>remembring none but God,</hi> when they rayle on his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: carelessely casting from their pen sentences that might breake and beat her honour into dust? Let <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> answere me this argument if he can. If the <hi>men of his religion</hi> wrote about the Virgin remembring thē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selues, &amp; without passion, why doth he slaunder them that they gaue passage to their passions in such wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings? If they did indeed write in a passion, forgetting themselues, how can any man of iudgmēt beleiue thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> doctrine in this poynt, or in any other, when they speak against the supposed blasphemies of our Church? seeing of men so zealous, we may iustly thinke, that their zeale doth still make them forgetfull of truth, mouing them to giue passage to their passiōs against the Pope, whom they will seeme to belieue, that we cōpare with Christ, against whome the zeale of their passion is no lesse fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, then against the Bl. Virgin. So that you clearly see the suite of <hi>Moyses</hi> his zeale in breaking the tables of the Law doth not fit, nor can hyde the monster of Ministers fury against the Mother of God. Neither hath it, to couer their impiety, any more proportion then the skinne of the least lamb, to hyde the mightyest wolfe. By which it is apparent that not only excesse of loue, but of hatred also doth bereaue men of their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is the cause that hypocrisie could not keep <hi>M. Crashawes</hi> huge hatred against the Pope, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his loue to God, or the best thing vnder God so within the compasse of shew of piety, but it hath broken out into such open tokens of secret Atheisme, that the discreet Reader may iustly wonder to behould them in his writings, that doth not know Atheisme to be in truth the very spirit of the new Ghospell, mouing
<pb n="31" facs="16"/>men <hi>to hate</hi>
      <note n="(17)" place="margin">Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t{us} reijcitur, &amp; Christo nomina nō dātur, iuuentus ferè nil Dei habet. <hi>Gaspar Hedio Ep. ad Melāct.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Popery, but not imbrace christianity, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ing them without loue or feeling of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="23">23. From this hatred doth proceed the bloudy drift of his Sermō: <hi>The scope wherof</hi> (saith he) <hi>is to discouer that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hese would but deceyue vs, who speake or write, that Popery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> now well reformed in manners, and refined in doctrine: &amp; therfore they, &amp; we by a reasonable mediation might well be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>econcyled.</hi> You see this Minister is all for war, he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ot heare of peace, no mediation, no reconcilement, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ough reasonable, shall be thought or spoken of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ongst vs, but fight we must one against the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ith irreconciliable, and mortall hatred:<note place="margin">In his epist. dedicatory to the Prince.</note>
      <hi>burning with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>e, and deuouring each others flesh, and dashing heads a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ainst the stones.</hi> In all which Metaphors he doth vtter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e intent, and finall scope of his Sermon, which is so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>oudy, and so vnchristian, that I cānot thinke charity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>so dead in any among You, that they do not euen ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orre the same, as proceeding from the canckered ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e of a venemous spyder. These men know well and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ele the weaknes of their cause which they mantayne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ecause they haue no other way to liue, but by keeping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>enefices (first appoynted vnto Catholike Priests) for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>emselues, their wiues, and children, should a reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>able mediation, or toleration betwixt them and vs be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ought of, such as <hi>Hugonots</hi> enjoy in <hi>France,</hi> vnder a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>atholike Prince, that we might haue any tolerable li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erty to speake for our selues, &amp; discouer their fraudes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd slaunders, their guilty conscience doth make them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>elieue, and excesse of feare somtymes, that in such a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>se they would be forced to shut vp their Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oores, and be soone forsaken of all. Nay they feare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e discouery of their grosse lying, might perchance stir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>o the people, that were before deluded by them, to take
<pb n="32" facs="17"/>some violent reueng vpon them. This is their feare, which to preuent, they buzze slaunders into peoples heades, that they may not thinke of any peace, media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or reconcilement, but still pursue vs with sword and fire to incite them. Whereunto the Bachelour deuised in his chamber, preached at the Crosse, publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in print, finally presented to the Princes Highnes this Sermon, of the most odious slaunders that wit of man could possibly inuent, seeking by hooke &amp; crooke to fasten them vpon the Church of Rome.</p>
   <p n="24">24. Now to vnderstand how farre he doth endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger your eternall saluation by this dealing, I doe wish you would seriously ponder, what<note n="(r)" place="margin">De vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi c. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>7.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>S. Augustine</hi> teacheth: That it is an offence &amp; sinne very damnable, not only in preachers to vtter, but also in the auditors to belieue against the Church (<hi>that beareth away the name of Catholicke, by the consent of the world,</hi> and, <hi>hath the fame and opinion of great learning, &amp; sanctity with humane kind</hi>) horrible and heynous blasphemyes, wicked and senseles doctrines, vpon the credit, and clamors of her knowne enemyes. And so hard of beliefe in this point ought Christians to be, in <hi>S. Augustine</hi> his iudgment, that they should scarse belieue their owne eyes, though they should see some wordes that may seeme to yield a blasphemous sound, but read againe, and againe the place to vnderstand the true meaning thereof. And if thou canst not excuse those wordes from blasphemy nor giue them a good sense by thy owne learning<note n="(*)" place="margin">Ibid. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>seeke</hi> (saith he) <hi>some learned, and godly man that may instruct thee. Cannot such a man be found with ease? Seeke him with labour. Is he wanting in thy owne Country? What better reason canst thou haue to trauaile? Canst thou meete with no such man in the Continent? Sayle beyond the seas,
<pb n="33" facs="17"/>beyond the seas, if thou canst not find any neare the sea, passe further into the country, and euen into those parts where the things were done their bookes speake of.</hi> This diligence doth <hi>S. Augustine</hi> require to be vsed before we fasten vpon the whole Catholicke Church any imputation of false, and blasphemous doctrine. Whereupon he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuseth himselfe, and his friend <hi>Honoratus</hi> for hauing belieued such slaunders against the Church vpon the <hi>Manichees</hi> report, not hauing first vsed such diligence to find out the truth. <hi>What</hi>
      <note n="(s)" place="margin">Quid tale fecim{us} Honorate? &amp; tamen religionem fortasse sanctissimā (adhuc enim quasi dubitandū sit loquor) cuius opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio totum terrarum orbem oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupauit, miserrimi pueri pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nostro ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrio iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio{que} damnaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>de vtilit. cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend. c.</hi> 7.</note>
      <hi>like thing haue we done friend Honoratus? And yet (wretched yong men) haue we presumed vpon our iudgment and fancy to cōdemne a religion perchance most holy (for yet I speake as though the matter were doubtfull) whose fame hath filled the world.</hi> And more earnestly in another place: <hi>We</hi>
      <note n="(t)" place="margin">De vtil. cred. c. <hi>6.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>witty, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned yong men forsooth</hi> (saith he) <hi>and deep searchers into truth, not hauing so much as once turned ouer their bookes, not hauing sought any to declare them vnto vs,</hi> non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quantum nostra tarditate accusata, non vel mediocri corde ipsis cōcesso, <hi>neuer fearing or mistrusting the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our wit, nor graunting so much as meane iudgment, &amp; cōmon sense vnto those men that haue permitted such bookes to be read ouer the world for so many ages: laying aside (I say) all these respects, we haue resolued to belieue nothing what those men teach, moued thereunto by the clamours of their enemyes, who with false promises of cleare truth, haue brought vs to belieue many thousands of their owne fables.</hi> Thus <hi>S. Augustine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="25">25. VVho seemeth vnto me liuely to describe the miserable estate of many thousands now in <hi>England,</hi> that rashly condemne so glorious a Church, as the Roman <hi>(whose fame hath filled the world)</hi> of most hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible blasphemyes, belieuing them vpon the word and
<pb n="34" facs="18"/>clamours of her professed enemyes, such as Ministers are knowne to be, especially <hi>M. Crashaw,</hi> who feareth not to say as you haue heard, that he will not spare the Pope, <hi>though</hi>
      <note n="(†)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 74.</note>
      <hi>therby he may giue vantage to the Atheist,</hi> resoluing to pluck down the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> though God, and all godlines fall with it: vpon whose wordes they haue belieued the Roman Church to teach; <hi>that the Pope is God;</hi> that, <hi>he can deliuer soules out of Hell;</hi> that, <hi>one may appeale from God to the Virgin Mary;</hi> that, <hi>we do pray vnto, and call vpon a wodden Crosse;</hi> that, <hi>those which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the blessed Sacrament, must haue a wife, or else keep a whore in her place,</hi> and the like paradoxes &amp; senselesse doctrines, which euen children know to be hated by vs. Now, what diligence haue his credulous Auditors vsed to find out the truth before they yielded their as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent vnto these slaunders? What seas haue they passed? What Coūtreys haue they trauailed? What long search haue they made after learned teachers, to declare some speaches &amp; sayings that may seeme more harsh? How many that neuer so much as read the sentēces they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill at in our Authors? And if they haue done none of these things, how can they be excusable with God in their confident condemning so famous a Chistianity, vpon so sleight examination of matters?</p>
   <p n="26">26. The secōd reason of my presenting this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise vnto you, was a care of your honour, which the Bachelour doth much abuse, by publishing his grosse folly and ignorance, vnder the name of the Preacher of your Temple, who doth so farre surpasse any meane or mediocrity therin, printing absurdities so voyd of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sense, and so intollerable to any learned eare, that your long forbearāce to take notice therof, harbouring him in one of your Courts, doth make many wonder,
<pb n="35" facs="18"/>and thinke they may iustly apply vnto you the wordes of <hi>S.</hi>
      <note n="(§)" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 19.</note>
      <hi>Paul: Libenter suffertis insipientes, cùm sitis ipsi sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientes:</hi> you gladly suffer fooles, being your selues wise, I will not lay that title on <hi>M. Crashaw,</hi> though his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance may seeme to deserue it, except by his lauish be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowing the same on learned men, it do from the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond wall of their excellent wisdome reflect on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, wherof I am content to make you Iudges.</p>
   <p n="27">27. First, as for the learned Catholike Writers of this age, <hi>Bellarmine, Valentia, Vasquez,</hi> &amp; many others, he doth rate, and reuile them at his pleasure, tearming them, <hi>Patrons of</hi>
      <note n="(u)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 88.</note>
      <hi>damnable Idolatry, loud</hi>
      <note n="(x)" place="margin">
         <hi>p.</hi> 115.</note>
      <hi>lyars,</hi> &amp; the like reproachfull tearmes without any respect. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>osseth and turneth them vp and downe, as himselfe thinketh best, making now <hi>Bellarmine</hi> chiefe, now <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia,</hi> now <hi>Vasquez:</hi> &amp; somtymes putting <hi>Chrysostomus</hi> a <hi>Cistercian</hi> before them all, vsing them as counters which stand somtymes for ten, somtymes for twenty, somtymes for a thousand, somtimes for nothing at all, as it pleaseth the caster of the account. Secondly, all the learned Deuines successiuely since the dayes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas,</hi> and namely that Angelicall Doctour, he doth charge to haue taught, that a <hi>stocke or stone representing Christ, is to be worshipped as God;</hi> and a wodden Crosse <hi>to be</hi>
      <note n="(y)" place="margin">In his <hi>8.</hi> wound.</note>
      <hi>prayed vnto; that they brought wodden arguments for their Idolatry; were blind in their vnderstandings; and drūken with the whore of Babylons spirituall abhominations.</hi> Thirdly, Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the sixt, who before his aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>S. Peters</hi> Chaire, was a learned Doctour, and Reader in <hi>Louaine,</hi> Maister vnto <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memory, and Gouernour of the Kingdomes of <hi>Spaine</hi> in his absence, this Pope, I say, the Wiseman of your Temple tearmeth<note n="(z)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 163.</note>
      <hi>foole</hi> in plaine tearmes. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
<pb n="36" facs="19"/>the noble nation of <hi>Italians</hi> he doth not blush to affirme that they are eyther<note n="(a)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 111.</note>
 Atheists, or fooles (some priuy Protestants excepted) which priuy men what they are, Atheists, or Protestants, or fooles, or all three, who can tell but himself, who hath a nose to smell them into <hi>England</hi> from their <hi>Italian</hi> priuy Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. But if <hi>Italians</hi> whose workes of piety shew they are not <hi>Athiests,</hi> whose learned bookes do witnes they are not <hi>fooles,</hi> see this shamefull reproach in print (as they may, this Sermon being turned into latin) they will perchance attribute such speaches without salt or wit, to the clownishnes of our Countrey, and grossenes of the northern climate, and apply vnto <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> the verse with some allusion to his name,
<q>
         <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratius.</note>
Bootem Crasso iurares äere natum.</q>
   </p>
   <p>Now if it be the property of a foole (as the holy<note n="(c)" place="margin">In via stultus ambulans cùm ipse insipiens sit, omnes stultos aestimat. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.3.</note>
 Ghost saith it is) to iudge rashly, that others are fooles; you will easely see the stones of reproach cast vp at others, fall foole on his owne head.</p>
   <p n="28">28. But no where doth this Minister shew greater want of iudgment, then in his Iesuits Ghospell, which in truth is such a peece of worke, as I do much meruaile, <hi>that such an owle</hi> (to vse his owne phrase) <hi>was let fly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the dayes of light,</hi> and in the fayrest day of som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, though that booke was likely to be written (as it was indeed) vnder the hoatest influence of mid-som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer moone. I doe not thinke any are liuing in your Courtes which doe not blow away such light stuffe with contempt; yet will I speake a word or two therof that no seely fly or foole, may be entangled therin, and that you plainly may see the notorious folly of your Preacher, which is such, as the sweet, and diuine muse of the graue, learned, and venerable Father that wrote
<pb n="37" facs="19"/>that excellent &amp; mellifluous poeme may seeme to haue wrought with the Minister, as some sound of musick doth with the<note n="(†)" place="margin">Tigres tympano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rū sonitu aguntur in rabiem <hi>Plutarch.</hi>
      </note>
 Tiger, wherewith enraged, her fury wanting other matter to worke vpon, teareth out her bowells, as the Bachelour with raging and rayling doth his braynes, which I will make playne by three, or foure examples of such folly, as are long in him, lasting from the first beginning, to the end of his Ghospell, though I shall dispatch them in few wordes.</p>
   <p n="29">29. The first is to gather a Ghospell out of a Poeme, and that not written historically, or doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, but in patheticall verse, full of metaphors Metonomi's, Apostroph's, Prosopoper's, and other aswell Rhetoricall figures, as poeticall flowers, which to take in a proper and rigorous sense is folly, to vrge them as points, and articles of faith is such a solemne foolery that it may seeme the next degree vnto madnes it self, which was to present the figures and flowers of the Poeme to be condemned in <hi>the</hi>
      <note n="(d)" place="margin">in the end of his Iesuits Ghospell.</note>
      <hi>Parlament,</hi> as heresyes, &amp; Catholicks in that respect to be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced hereticks. Truly I thinke midsommer moone had neuer the like influence in any Minister or mad-man, Bachelour, or Bedlame before. And yet doth he vrge these points of our doctrine, as most authenticall, and substantiall things, much more credible, and certaine, as he saith, then the knowledge they haue of Iesuits and their doctrine and practises, <hi>from</hi>
      <note n="(e)" place="margin">Iesuits Ghospell pag. <hi>18.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>the report of their merchants, or intelligence of their Embassadours, or from the writing of their owne men,</hi> which is the truest point in his whole Iesuits Ghospel, though Iesuits need not faith to belieue it: they see and feele it. For the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations which their Merchants, and Embassadors giue, the storyes their men write of them are such, as no
<pb n="38" facs="20"/>patheticall exaggerations, no poeticall figures, fables or fictions, can be more false, as many late books can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, specially a late Pamphlet dedicated to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Highnesse, called the <hi>Diuell</hi>
      <note n="(†)" place="margin">The Diuels pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage to the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. <hi>printed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1611.</note>
      <hi>his pilgrimage,</hi> where this lackey or footman of the Diuell telles many false stories, naming persons that were neuer heard of, spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of actions that neuer any dreamed of, as (to omit foule matters) <hi>that on</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Quàm multis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trandi (in Ecclesiam) aditum obserabāt rumores maledico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, qui nescio quid aliud nos in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare Dei ponere ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitabant. <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 48. <hi>ad Vincent.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>the Altar of our Lady at Sichem a sheep was sacrificed,</hi> and a long poeticall narration of the cause of the Iesuits expulsion from <hi>Venice,</hi> abusing the knowledge of the whole Christian world; and that in their Colledge straight vpon their banishment was found such a summe of money, as all Merchants hauing taken whatsoeuer they would challenge vpon their owne words (which we may imagine was no small quantity) the remnant was fiue hundred millions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides plate &amp; vestures: and yet he saith he telleth not these things vpon heare-say, but what he saw with his eyes. Now what Poet could haue told a more lusty lye? So that this part of his Ghospell is very true and credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that their reports &amp; rumors, and printed relations about Iesuits, are more false, incredible, and fuller of exaggerations and fictions, then any poeme.</p>
   <p n="30">30. Now if you desire to see how wittily, &amp; hād<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somely the Ghospeller doth gather his Ghospell out of the Poeme, I will present you a faire patterne, by which you may ghesse the rest. In that poeme the Authour in in his meditatiōs doth imagine a familiar dialogue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Virgin and Christ, and saith vnto Christ:
<q>
         <l>Say to thy Mother, see my brothers thirst,</l>
         <l>Mother, your milke would ease him at the first.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Which speach is imagined to shew the great fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity betwixt Christ, and his blessed Mother, that she
<pb n="39" facs="20"/>hath a speciall interest in the ioyes and comforts (me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorically tearmed milke) that flow into the soule by deuout contemplation of her blessed Breasts, which comforts are not graunted but to whome she doth sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly fauour, nor giuen without her consent; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the Sonne of God would not be borne in her wombe. Now what doctrine doth this Bachelour ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of this poeticall imagination thinke you? Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that Popery doth make Christ a mediatour to his Mother: which againe he deuideth into diuers bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, opposite to the Ghospell of Christ, grounded vpō the first mistaking, vnto the fifth and sixt generation,<note place="margin">Ies. Gosp. pag. <hi>87.</hi>
      </note>
 in this sort.</p>
   <p>
      <table>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>Christ saith of himselfe as man.</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
               <hi>Romish doctrine makes him say.</hi>
               <note place="margin">He that will, may see ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like Ghospell, that we teach, that Christ this present yeare a sucking child at Hall in Brabant, opposed in like mā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner vnto the Ghos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Christ. <hi>pag.</hi> 64.</note>
            </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>My Father is greater then I.</cell>
            <cell>My Mother in some respects is greater then I.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>Christ saith of himselfe as God.</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
               <hi>Romish doctrine makes him say.</hi>
            </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>I and my Father are one.</cell>
            <cell>I and my Mother are one.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>Christ saith.</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
               <hi>Romish doctrine makes him say.</hi>
            </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>Come to me all that are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; I will ease you.</cell>
            <cell>Come to me, and I will send you to my Mother for ease.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>The Scripture saith.</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
               <hi>They make him say.</hi>
            </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>No man commeth to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by me.</cell>
            <cell>No man commeth to my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by me.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>The Scripture saith.</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell>
               <hi>They make him say.</hi>
            </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>Whatsoeuer you aske my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my name, he will giue it you.</cell>
            <cell>Whatsoeuer you aske my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my name, she will giue it you.</cell>
         </row>
      </table>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb n="40" facs="21"/>All this Ghospel doth he gather only from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer verses without any other ground, which I haue heere set downe, both for the recreation of some Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes that may peruse this Treatise, that they may see both how malice against truth putteth their Aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes out of their wits, and with what empty shewes many seduced soules are frighted from the Catholike Church; &amp; that some of you may see how grossely this Bachelour doth abuse them, who cannot I thinke but see, and grieue that their Preacher should publish such follyes, vanityes, or rather baberyes in print.</p>
   <p n="31">31. This then is the first mistaking or folly, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he runneth on to the very end of his Ghospell, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no difference betwixt an Euangelist, and a Poet, a Ghospell, and poeme, rigid truth &amp; figuratiue speach, articles of faith,<note place="margin">à pag. <hi>37.</hi> ad <hi>60.</hi>
      </note>
 and poeticall fancyes. And the second is no lesse notorious thē this, to wit, to put no differēce betwixt contemplation, and the obiect therof, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and the matter, the thought and the thing we thinke of, betwixt the breasts and milke of the Virgin, and deuout considerations vpon them. Because <hi>Scriba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> compareth his meditations vpon the breasts of the Virgin, with his meditations vpon the woundes of Christ; the Minister doth inferre, that he doth equall her breasts to his woundes, the milke of the Mother with the bloud of the Sonne, which is grosse mistaking, and misconstruing of things. Often may contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be equally full of comfort or profit, though there be great difference in their obiects. What greater di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance then betwixt heauen and hell, the ioyes of the one, and the paynes of the other? yet many tymes may one, through Gods speciall grace, find as profitable, yea sometymes as comfortable meditations vpon hell,
<pb n="41" facs="21"/>as vpon heauen. When we say that hell maketh men auoid sinne, we doe not vnderstand that hell hath a certayne power to infuse grace into a mans soule, by which he may auoid sinne, but only that it is an obiect which may (Gods grace concurring) awake such a good purpose in a man. The like is when we say, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen doth make men serue God with great comfort, we doe not vnderstand, that heauen hath any vertue or quality to infuse grace, but only to be an obiect or motiue of ioyfull going on in Gods seruice. So when it is sayd, that the breasts or milke of the Virgin do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the soule, heale the diseases thereof, appease anger, enuy, pride, and other raging sinnes, the sense is, that her breasts, and the mystery of her blessed milke is an obiect of such deuotion and piety, as deuout contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation on them may bring forth in a soule these and many other more admirable effects. Moreouer, when one doth meditate on the Virgins breasts, as she is Gods Mother, the obiect is equall to the obiect we thinke of in the wounds and bloud of Christ; because in the breasts of the Virgin as she is Gods Mother, we must needes behould, and contemplate Christ in her virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall armes, &amp; sucking her blessed breasts, who though not in bignes of body, yet in Maiesty, power, wisdome, sanctity, both as God and man, is equall to himself blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on the Crosse. Now which obiect is more sweet, tender, and able to styr vp deuotion in a soule, Christ sucking in the armes of his mother, or bleeding on the armes of the Crosse is a doubt, which did perplexe <hi>S. Augustine</hi> long agoe, that he brake out into these wordes. <hi>In medio positus quo me vertam nestio: hinc pascor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> vulnere, hinc lactor ab vbere;</hi> placed betwixt these two pledges of mercy, I know not which way to turne my
<pb n="42" facs="22"/>selfe: on the one side I am fed with bloud from the wounds, on the other, with milke from the breasts. This is the doubt which that learned Iesuit, whom this Bachelour tearmeth, Annoynted with the oyle of mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe aboue all his fellowes, doth excellently expresse in Latin verse, which beginneth:
<q>
         <l>
            <hi>Haereo, lac inter meditans, inter{que} cruorem;</hi>
         </l>
         <l>Meditating betwixt the milke &amp; bloud, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p n="32">32. By which first verse you see, that he doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his thoughts and meditations on the one, with his thoughts and meditations on the other, doubting by which of the two, greater deuotion did accrew to his soule. That he saith he will lay his left<note n="(*)" place="margin">Rem scio pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sabo, si fas erit, vbera dextra: lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua prensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, si dabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note>
 hand on the woundes, and on the breasts his right: by this meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phore he doth shew, his purpose is to meditate on the Virgins milke, or Mystery of Christs Child-hood in the tyme of prosperity, signifyed by the right hand, for which tyme it is fittest to weane vs from the milke of vayne pleasures, and that he will thinke on Christs wounds, and passion when he is pressed with aduersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which the left hand doth expresse: and for which sorrowfull tyme of crosses, the Crosse, and bleeding wounds of Christ, are considerations of highest com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. This is the pious meaning of that metaphoricall speach, which this Bachelour doth expound at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, crying like a calfe at the bug-beare of his owne braine, out of meere ignorance, not able to discerne the right hand from the left in a mysticall sense. No lesse pious is the<note n="(†)" place="margin">Lac Matris miscere volo cum sanguine Nati: Non pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doto no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliore frui.</note>
 metaphore of mingling the milke, and the bloud togeather into one compound; which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but to cōpare those two mysteries togeather and mingle them in our thoughts, conferring his pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="43" facs="22"/>in the armes of the Crosse, with his playing in the armes of his Mother; his shedding bloud in the one, with his sucking milke in the other, with the like sweet differences betwixt them. Which compound, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiue consideration of these two mysteries may iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stly be thought the sweetest meditation the soule can enioy vpon earth. Behould what true, pious, and sweet conceipts the metaphors haue, which this Bachelour draweth to most blasphemous senses, raging against his owne fancyes, as against the Iesuits faith, like fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Aiax,</hi> that scourged an heard of his own swyne, for the Army of <hi>Grecian</hi> Princes.</p>
   <p n="33">33. And in this folly doth he goe<note n="(§)" place="margin">
         <hi>pag.</hi> 60.</note>
 forward, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging at shaddowes, till he come to that dystich of the poeme:
<q>
         <l>Sweet child in mothers armes that playing rests:<note place="margin">Paruule maternis medi{us} qui ludis in vlnis: Qui tua iam com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples vbera iam vacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as.</note>
         </l>
         <l>Now sucks as child, now fills as God her breasts.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Where this learned and deuout Religious man doth begin to set downe in verse, a meditation on Christes childhood, much vsed by Iesuites, as doth appeare by their bookes, which is called by them <hi>applicatio sensuum,</hi> an applying of the internall senses of the soule, to the mysteryes of Christs life. By which, when they medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on Christs childhood, they do imagine themselues to be in <hi>Bethleem,</hi> or <hi>Nazareth,</hi> and there behould with the eyes of their mind, that venerable, &amp; amiable child in his Virgin mothers armes, to heare with their eares the words that passe betwixt them, to tast, smell, and feele internally the things that are obiects of these sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, as far as they may serue to awake deuotion, and stir vp a liuely apprehension of the mystery in their harts; in the meane tyme speaking with the Bl. Child, or Virgin mother, framing vnto them mentall &amp; ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary
<pb n="44" facs="23"/>discourses, and petitions according as the holy Ghost the teacher and guide of such high, and extati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call contemplations shall<note n="(f)" place="margin">This (I dare say) is a strange language to <hi>M. Crashaw.</hi>
      </note>
 direct. This manner of contemplation you shall find most frequently practised by ancient Fathers, and learnedly declared by<note n="(g)" place="margin">In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct. de modo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditand.</note>
      <hi>Riccius,</hi> and<note n="(h)" place="margin">Part. <hi>2.</hi> tract. <hi>7.</hi> of mentall prayer, in the Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</note>
      <hi>Puentez,</hi> two Fathers of this Order, in their Treatises of contemplation, and mentall prayer. And such imaginations, conceipts, and discourses are neyther false nor vayne: not false, because as the Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians teach (and it is the first lesson in Logicke, which this Bachelour of diuinity doth not yet vnderstād) that there is neyther falsity nor vntruth in our thoughts, or imaginations, when we stay in the first operation of vnderstanding, which is to apprehend a thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iudging that it is so, as wee apprehend: as when we apprehend (as <hi>S.</hi>
      <note n="(i)" place="margin">Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustin. l. <hi>7.</hi> Confess. c. <hi>5.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Augustine</hi> did) God as an infinit light, or sea of glory, without bound, in which the world like a sponge floateth, though God be not indeed as we apprehend; yet are not such apprehensions erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous or false, because we only apprehend him, as such an infinite materiall light, not iudging him to be so: nay, we iudge the contrary, yet we must so appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend him, because our thoughts can reach no other higher conceipt of him. When we apprehend, and imagine our selues in prayer to be before the throne of God, to be kneeling in heauen among the blessed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, as<note n="(k)" place="margin">lib. <hi>2.</hi> de oratione.</note>
      <hi>S. Chrysostome,</hi> and other Fathers exhort, this apprehension is not false, because we do not iudg, and thinke that indeed we are in heauen, but so frame our imaginations, thoughts, affections, prayers, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward speachs vnto God, as if we were in heauen. And thus may wee make our selues present in <hi>Bethleem,</hi> or <hi>Nazareth,</hi> vnto the mistery of Christs sacred Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
<pb n="45" facs="23"/>or in Mount-Caluary vnto the mystery of his Crosse, behoulding him with the eyes of our mynd, as bleeding and dying for vs, which thoughts are not vayne, but causes of piety, deuotion, and tender affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction vnto Christ, and his holy life, and therefore of singular profit, which any that will make triall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, shall vndoubtedly feele.</p>
   <p n="34">34. Hence doth appeare the falsehood, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of the Bachelours new doctrine, not taught by any Christian (that I know of) before, to wit, that we must not now imagine Christ as sucking his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers breasts, nor speake vnto him, as to a child, nor as dying vpon the Crosse, nor conceyue him as a mortall man; to which purpose he citeth <hi>S. Paul,</hi> saying: <hi>We know not Christ now according to the flesh,</hi> that is, saith he, not as a meere, and mortall, but as glorifyed man: this doctrine I say is the bane of piety and deuotion, and a perpetuall banishment of contemplation of the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of Christs life out of mens harts. For how can they liuely apprehend loue, and imbrace Christ as dying vpon the Crosse for their cause, if they may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, or apprehend him as a mortall man. How can they in contemplation wash his woundes with their teares, or bath themselues in his bleeding wounds? How can they enter as doues into the holes of that Rock, if they may not so much as apprehend death or mortality in him? <hi>S. Pauls</hi> meaning is, that we must not belieue nor iudge, nor thinke that Christ is now mortall in very truth, and subiect to misery as once he was, as <hi>S. Chrysostome</hi> expoundeth; but he doth not deny but we may conceaue Christ and speake, and pray vnto him, as to a child, or as crucified, or as represented in any other mystery of his life, imagining thinges past so liuely, as if
<pb n="46" facs="24"/>we saw thē present with the eyes of our mind; though the more litterall sense of the Apostles words, <hi>Now we know not Christ according to the flesh,</hi> be, that he had not now a carnall, and fleshly conceipt of the <hi>Messias</hi> &amp; his Kingdome, as he had once with other Iewes before he was conuerted; so he saith, <hi>that now we know none ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the flesh,</hi> that is, we beare not carnall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto any, wishing them carnall and temporall bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings. For though we once (saith he) <hi>knew Christ accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the flesh,</hi> that is, expected his carnall, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Kingdome; now we know him not in that manner, nor consequently doe we loue carnally any, whom we loue in him, and for him. This now is the third folly of this Bachelour, wherin he spendeth the rest of his Ghospell, making no distinction betwixt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending and iudging of a thing, betwixt imagining &amp; belieuing. We do apprehend Christ in our thoughts, as a child, we mentally see him, kisse, imbrace him, speake vnto him: yet do we not iudge, that he is a child, or a sucking babe this present yeare at <hi>Hall</hi> in <hi>Brabant,</hi> as this Wise Man obiecteth, but that he was once a child. Which mystery that we may know, loue, &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the better, we set it before the eyes of our mind, not as a thing past, but present, and behaue our selues in our imaginations, thoughts, and affections, as we would doe indeed, were he truly, and really present before vs. This is the manner of meditation, most pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, deuout, and profitable, which to Protestant Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters seemeth (I dare say) a new Ghospell, though it hath euer bene practised by all spirituall men: but no wonder at their ignorance heerin, seeing the sensuall or carnall man conceaueth not the things of the spirit of God.</p>
   <p n="35">
      <pb n="47" facs="24"/>35. A fourth example of folly, is his fury against Iesuits, because this Poet, in his imaginary contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and application of the internal senses vnto the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of Christs childhood, doth feare to approach vnto the sacred, and venerable breasts of the Virgin, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing himself vnworthy of such an honour &amp; fauour, in regard of his grieuous sinnes: wherfore he doth in his contemplation &amp; thoughts, rather run to be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by Christes bloud, begging one precious drop for that end, which he doth expresse in a most diuine sweet and admirable verse. Heere the Bachelour keepeth a great styr, &amp; rageth for many leaues<note n="(l)" place="margin">From the pag. <hi>66.</hi> of his Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell, to the <hi>77.</hi>
      </note>
 togeather, that the Iesuits thinke the Virgins milke to be more pure, &amp; precious then Christs bloud, to which they dare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, though not to her breasts. Where he is so void of iudgment, as he would haue a sound, &amp; solide rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son which in rigour of Diuinity may subsist of a poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call conceipt, which may be raysed of small ground, or fancy, as all men know. And the ground of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, is, not because the milk of the Virgin is more pure and precious then Christs bloud, but because the mā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of approaching vnto it, may seeme to carry a shew of pride and presumption. For a man to run to Christs bloud which was shed to cleanse sinners, is a token that he doth acknowledge himselfe a sinner, and a needy supplyant: but to approach the Virgins breasts, which were not filled with milke, but only to nurse the Sōne of God, and comfort the specially deuoted to Christs blessed childhood, might seeme to sauour of pride and arrogancy. This may be declared by an example. Which is of more worth, a thousand pounds out of the Kings Exchequer, or an ordinary dish of meate set on the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the Kings refection? Doubtlesse, the thousand
<pb n="48" facs="25"/>pounds: yet is it a greater honour to sit at table with the King, and eate with him in the same dish, then to haue a thousand pounds out of the Exchequer; and many that dare aske the second, will not presume of the first. The like is in this poeticall imagination. Christs bloud is more precious then his mothers milke, yet in contē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation to sit, as it were, at the same table with Christ, and to be fed with the same Virginall milke, miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously prepared for him, doth carry a greater shew of honour, then to be bathed in his bloud, and washed with his woundes, which sinners are admitted vnto. And this is a sufficient ground to build a pious poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call conceipt, not vnbeseeming a Christian Poet, as any man of vnderstanding will graunt; &amp; admyre the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelours madnesse, who spendeth many leaues in ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling against Iesuits, for this only respect, calling them, <hi>a generation of Vipers, bred of an old and sinfull world, who as they haue Christ most in their mouth, so they haue him lesse in their hart;</hi> and, <hi>that they haue herin more dishonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the bloud of Christ, then euer it was by any Sect, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession whatsoeuer, Turke or Heretike, Iew or Atheist, Diuell or Man, since the world began.</hi> Thus he declaymeth against Iesuits, who do daily conuert vnto the desire to be saued by Christs bloud, many of all the sects by him named besides Diuells, whome they leaue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with <hi>Luther</hi> and his learned Schollers. But these in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiues (as <hi>S. Augustine</hi> saith of the like) are by so much the more sottish, by how much they are more earnest, and proue, that one only point Iesuits must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily belieue of their long Ghospell, penned by <hi>M. Crashaw,</hi> to wit, that the wryter therof, when he wrote it, was not well in his wits.</p>
   <p n="36">36. Which doth further appeare, in that he doth
<pb n="49" facs="25"/>obiect in his fury, euen the elegancies of the Latyn lā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which he doth not well vnderstand, as blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to be condemned in Parliament. For example, the Iesuite in this Poeme saith to Christ:<note place="margin">Ergo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptore monstrate iure vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari; Nobilior reliquis si tibi san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis inest.</note>
      <q>
         <l>A Sauiour shew thy self to soule opprest,</l>
         <l>If thy bloud be more noble then the rest.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>This Minister will needes accuse the Iesuits of doubting whether Christs bloud be more noble then any other, because the Iesuite maketh an <hi>(if)</hi> thereof which implyeth doubt. But would it please you to send your preacher to some Grammer schoole of Iesuits, he should be taught that <hi>(si, if)</hi> is not euer a doubting particle but sometymes most asseueratiue, specially in obsecrations, in which that particle vsed of something which is certayne, doth with great force affirme, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the speach more elegant, and the obsecration more earnest. To giue him an example out of a poet, <hi>Dido</hi> doth thus beseech <hi>Aeneas,</hi>
      <q>
         <note n="(m)" place="margin">Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil. 4. Aeneid.</note>
 Si bene quid de te merui, fuit aut tibi quicquā dulce meum miserere.</q>
   </p>
   <p>Did <hi>Dido</hi> doubt whether she had bestowed great good turnes on <hi>Aeneas?</hi> shee knew them well, and could tell them also:
<q>
         <l>— Eiectum littore egentem</l>
         <l>Excepi, &amp; regni demens in parte locaui.</l>
      </q>
And yet she maketh an <hi>(if)</hi> of what she made no doubt, saying: <hi>Si bene quid de te merui,</hi> with an elegant and complete speach, putting him in mynd of what he knew and was apparent, and she did much desire he should remember. And this elegancy is vsed in this verse most sweetly, representing vnto Christ the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="50" facs="26"/>of his precious bloud aboue all other, and obtesting him by the same, to blot out therwith the multitude of his sinnes.</p>
   <p n="37">37. Pardon me (learned and iudicious Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) that I trouble your eares with such trifles, where if I haue cause to say with <hi>S. Paul,</hi>
      <note n="(n)" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 11. Fact{us} sum insipiens, sedvos me coegistis.</note>
      <hi>I am become a foole,</hi> you will remember your Preacher <hi>hath forced me ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,</hi> by printing these follyes, to deceiue seely peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who might out of the former ignorant, and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious cauill, haue thought that we doubt of the inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable value of Christs most precious bloud. And truly seeing you are not altogeather out of fault, who suffer fooles, though your selues be wise, you may be cōtent to beare part of the pennance, to read a refutation of the follyes printed by your owne Preacher, with which I will now weary you no longer in this place, if it may please you to take notice of his last folly, vpon the last verses of this Poeme; wher the Poet cōplayning of the great drynesse of his owne meditations on the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of Christs passion, and chidhood, wheras cloaths were wet with the milke of the one, and bloud of the other, concludeth with this deuout dystich.</p>
   <q>
      <l>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>pag.</hi> 98.</note>
I am more then clouts, yet these more rich then silke</l>
      <l>wet with Sonnes bloud, wet were with Mothers milke.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Heere this sucker of venome out of flowers, first frameth a long enditement of pride against the Iesuite, wondering, <hi>that he dare come before the Lord his God in his prayer, making himselfe better then these cloaths, specially hearing the Prophet cry before: O Lord, all our righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is like a menstruous clout.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 72. <hi>v.</hi> 23.</note>
 Thus he. Where we may likewise wonder, how this Bachelour in the sight of God dare make himselfe wiser then that Asse Christ
<pb n="51" facs="26"/>rode on, specially hearing the Prophet cry before him, <hi>I am become like a iument, or Asse before thee:</hi> and being no wiser in the sight of God, how dare he thus babble, if not rather bray in the eares of men that can vnderstād his solemne foolery, to make it a sinne for a man, to thinke, and say in the sight of God, that he is more precious, and deare vnto him then any clout, euen the best that euer was: which though this ridiculous Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant say, that he doth prize aboue gold, and therefore much more then Iesuits soules:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.13.46.</note>
 yet that heauenly Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant doth make another estimate of such Iewels, <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all that he had to buy one.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="38">38. And if you examine the other part of his cauil at the Iesuit, for enuying the clouts that were wet with that milke and bloud, you will find he doth shew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selft to be a braying creature indeed, not onely in the sight of God, but euen in the iudgment of euery reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable man. <hi>If</hi> (saith he) <hi>the Iesuite meane the materiall, and reall bloud and milke, that were in the bodyes of Christ and his Mother, then is he more then mad to enuy the clouts, for they did touch them, and he cannot.</hi> Thus he. And is not this a fit discourse (thinke you) to discouer a mad man? What if he cannot touch those sacred bodyes, that Virginall milke, and precious bloud? May he not therfore without madnesse, wish that he had byn in the time when he might haue touched thē, enuying the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of the clouts, that were so happy, &amp; more happy in this respect, then he now can be? May he not grieue &amp; cōplayne, specially in a patheticall poeme, that he is depriued of the possibility of such a comfort, therin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring his deuotiō vnto these sweet pledges of mercy? But the Poets complaint is not in this respect, but hath an higher &amp; sweeter conceipt, grieuing that he is not
<pb n="52" facs="27"/>so happy in his kind, as those cloutes were in theirs. They were corporally wet, and moystened with the bloud and milke of the Sonne and Mother, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test honour and felicity such creatures could haue, wheras his soule, his vnderstanding, his meditations, as he complayneth are not wet with a fresh and liuely remembrance of that milke, &amp; bloud, nor his thoughts &amp; affections drowned in these two mayne seas of ioves, nor he absorpt by contemplation of those two sweet mysteryes, from the loue, and care of all other inferiour thinges. This is the complaint, which whether it be pious or no, let any man iudg, and of the vanity of such cauills.</p>
   <p n="39">39. But it is worth the noting, that though your Bachelours drift was to beat in the morter of malice, with the pestell of his pistilent wit, euery flower of this flagrant poeme, to get out venemous iuice of some blasphemy; yet hath he omitted some, at which he might haue cauilled with far more shew of reason: for example, at this verse:
<q>
         <l>Parce Deus, magno si te clamore fatigem.</l>
         <l>Pardon me Lord, if thee my cryes doe tyre.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>Where he might haue obiected pride vnto the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit, as to one thinking himself such a stout prayer, as he can euen tyre God; and blasphemy in teaching that God may be tyred: and hence haue deduced the Popish practise of praying vnto Saynts, which they doe (so might he cauill) to giue some respite vnto God that he may breath. Also when he saith:
<q>
         <l>Lancea{que} erubuit sanguine tincta suo.</l>
         <l>The launce did blush imbrued in thy bloud.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb n="53" facs="27"/>Seeing no creature can blush which is not endued with reason. By this Iesuits doctrine he might inferre, in his fashiō, that the launce was a reasonable creature, man, or woman, rather a woman, because the latyn is the feminine gender, perchance mother to the famous Knight Syr <hi>Launcelot Du-lake;</hi> but doubtles a Saynt, seeing she was washed with Christs bloud, the vertue whereof made her blush for her sinnes. These dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions (as I am content to refer to the Readers iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) are no more iniurious against truth, and haue more wit and shew of reason in them, then the cloutes of the cauills, wherewith your Bachelour botcheth vp his Ghospell. And yet should any man obiect these things in good earnest, as things of moment and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, that mans wits might be thought more wodden then the very wood of the launce, howsoeuer his malice may be more sharp then the point: to which point of malice the Ministers may seeme arriued, who are more sharp set, and beare a greater tooth against Catholick deuotion and piety, then Atheisme, and prophanesse; as your Bachelour did openly professe, and they all shew it in workes. For so many wanton and lasciuious verses come dayly forth, and such workes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes are harboured euen in Preachers bosomes and breasts: but this pious poeme full of so many sweet, and deuout conceipts both towards Christ and his Mother, which malice only can misconster, and draw to blasphemous senses, you see, how these birds (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth) of the light, cry, and cackle, and keepe a stirr at it, as if it were an owle, among whom your Preacher is leader. Nay he only playeth the foole in print for all the rest, <hi>who are</hi> (he sayth) <hi>many millions more.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="40">40. Had a lasciuious Muse set out a patheticall
<pb n="54" facs="28"/>Pamphlet, shewing his affection to the breasts of some woman, this Tigre who only rageth at sacred musick; would not haue stormed thereat, for he doth shew good affection to such obiects. And that he is better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with other womens breasts, thē the Virgins, doth sufficiently appeare, in that he dareth auouch that it cannot be proued eyther to reason, or faith, that the Virgins milke excelleth other womens, in any eyther corporall, or spirituall operation whatsoeuer; raging against this learned Father for saying, that her breasts are <hi>diuitiora,</hi> more rich, and full of diuine and heauenly comfort, haue more vertue to styr vp faith, loue of God, and pious thoughts in the deuout contemplant, then those of any other. Which base conceipt of the breasts of Gods mother may be the cause that he think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> it no sinne, for a man full of sinne, without any care or respect, to approach &amp; touch them by imagination: <hi>he dareth stand to it, it is no euill:</hi> &amp; no meruaile, seeing her breasts in his cōceipt are no better, &amp; so no more to be honoured &amp; respected, then those of other women, with which to play eyther imaginarily or indeed, it may seeme he thinketh no great euill, learning this deuotion of his Father <hi>Luther,</hi> who writeth in this sort of his cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations of this kind:<note n="(o)" place="margin">Loci commun. Martini Lutheri, p. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Mihi quidem</hi> (saith he) <hi>saepe magnae voluptati, &amp; admirationi est, quòd video corpus muliebre totum ad id factum, vt foue at infantes. Quàm decore etiam paruae puellae gestant in sinu infantes! Ipsae má<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres quàm aptis gestibus ludant, quoties placandus est infans vagiens, aut in cunis ponendus.</hi> These were <hi>Luthers</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout contēplations vpon womens breasts, laps, armes, and bodyes: his words I will not turne into English, but such as vnderstand Latyn will not wonder, that such meditations brought him in the end to marry a
<pb n="55" facs="28"/>Nunne; nor that <hi>M. Chrashaw</hi> and the rest of his Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers find not much comfort, feele no great vertue in meditation on breasts of the Virgin, more pure then the heauens, who full of grosse, and carnall imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations dare approach to her sacred closet, more rudely then they would to their owne Wyues cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, thinking <hi>it no euill</hi> to defile with their swynish imaginations, the most pure, and sacred mysteries of our faith.</p>
   <p n="41">41. I will heere set downe an example of their meditations in this kind, not written in verse, but in prose, &amp; in an exposition vpon the Ghospel, by a Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speller<note n="(p)" place="margin">Ioān. Agricola apud Cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sium. l. <hi>3.</hi> de Maria Virg. c. <hi>12.</hi>
      </note>
 of great name and credit, who expounding the Angelicall Embassage to the Bl. Virgin, doth thus grauely meditate on the matter: <hi>Ingressus</hi>
      <note n="(q)" place="margin">An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in cap. <hi>1.</hi> Luc.</note>
      <hi>cubiculum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uellae Gabriel</hi> (saith he) <hi>adolescentis forma, amatorium quiddam &amp; nuptiale orditur, virginem, vt apparet, pellici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>urus ad concubitum:</hi> Gabriel entring the maids chamber in the forme of a yong man, begins a nuptiall and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ory speach &amp;c. my pen blusheth to put the rest into English. And is not this (thinke you) a fit meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for <hi>Luthers</hi> Ghospell, which makes the Ghospell of Christ begin with a nuptiall song, enticing a Virgin to marry, or to do worse. And yet this contemplant will not haue his Readers passe ouer the matter sleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but insist vpon it, &amp; apply their internall senses vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t: <hi>Meditetur apud animum suum qui volet pia curiositate, quid sit videre comptulum adolescentulum solum cum puella clauso cubilis ostio, dulciter alloquentem virginem, quam se ambire nihil obscurè &amp; gestu &amp; oratione demonstrat.</hi> Let him that wil meditate with pious curiosity in his mind, what it is to see a trym yong man with a yong maid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>one in a chamber, the dore shut, speaking her fayre,
<pb n="56" facs="29"/>to whome both by gesture, and speach he doth clearly shew himselfe to be a woer. Do you perceiue the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous curiosity of these Ghospellers, that will not rest with their thoughts, till they know the <hi>Quid sit,</hi> the very essence and quiddity of the locking vp of a try <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> yong woer, with a fayre yong virgin togeather alone in a chamber? These owles, they doe not harbour in the barne of their braynes, nor keepe in some corner of their chamber, but let them fly abroad in print, in these dayes (as they terme) of light. Nay they passe among them without wonder, as sweet and deuout conceypts. By which this marrying Mynistry, that cannot liue chast, turne the pure virgin water of diuine Scripture into the wanton wyne of lasciuious fancyes, to keep the wedding feast of their woing Ghospell.</p>
   <p n="42">42. They that thus turne the Ghospell of Christ into a wanton Comedy, what meruaile though they change a Iesuits poeme into a Ghospell of their foule fancyes, as grosse and carnall as womens breasts, the obiects of <hi>Lutheran</hi> deuotion, can make them? What wonder though the diamond of a deuout cōtemplation set in golden verse, be stayned by such<note n="(r)" place="margin">Cast not Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels vnto swine, least they tread thē vnder feet, and rising a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you, rend you in peeces, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 6.</note>
 swyne, who neuer yet could raise their thoughts out of mud? what meruaile that hauing defiled the Iewell, they teare in peeces those that cast it before them, with all manner of foule and despicable reproaches? as this Minister tearmeth Iesuits, <hi>annointed with the oyle of mischeef about all their fellowes;</hi> that, <hi>they bynd their Nouices prentises vnto Beelzebub,</hi> and the like, not hauing any leafe or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most lyne not adorned with some such rare Iewell of contumelious termes, though the most vsed by him, is <hi>Vipers,</hi> which was a title <hi>Luther</hi> did leaue, togeather with his loue, in his last<note n="(s)" place="margin">
         <hi>See</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>last will</hi> in lib. de coena. Ego Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther{us} alterū iam pedem habens in sepulchro &amp;c.</note>
 will vnto the <hi>Caluinian</hi>
      <pb n="57" facs="29"/>brood, whose nature he doth so describe by the meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phore of Vipers, that I am content to make you Iudges whether he may not seeme to describe the Preacher at the Temple. <hi>The</hi>
      <note n="(t)" place="margin">Apud Theodos. Fabritium in locis cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mū. Mart. Lutheri p. <hi>4. Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l{us}.</hi> &amp; ibid. p. <hi>5.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>nature</hi> (saith Luther) <hi>of these vipers</hi> (the Caluinists) <hi>is such, as they cauill deceiptfully at wordes proceeding from a pious, and ingenuous hart, and turne them altogeather to another, and to a quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry sense, then they were meant. In which art they are admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Doctours, surpassing in this point the skill &amp; wit of all the Rhetoricians in the world: for they are gouerned by a malignant spirit, which doth possesse, and betwitch their wits, that inraged with Satanicall virulency against pious, and godly men, they cannot but maliciously interprete their wordes, and writings. Wherein they are for all the world like spiders that suck poyson out of fayre, and fragrant flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, the venime not being in the flowers, but in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues.</hi> Thus far <hi>Luther.</hi> In which wordes he doth so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iuely describe <hi>M. Crashaw,</hi> that whosoeuer shall read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>his Iesuits Ghospell, will confesse that <hi>Luther</hi> did know him, and the nature of a Caluinist, as if he had spit him &amp; them out of his owne mouth, from whence indeed this late swarme of Spyders, and Vipers did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally proceed.</p>
   <p n="43">43. The folly and falshood of your Preacher, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus proued already in this Epistle, but more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this Treatise, to the discredit of that Church that durst set him vp in Pulpit, and out in Print, I might speake vnto you in his owne words, and what he saith against the Iesuits vnto the Catholikes of <hi>England,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iesuites Ghosp. p. <hi>72.</hi>
      </note>
 ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply against him vnto you. <hi>O my beloued Countreymen, be not seduced by such impostors, let not such Vipers eat out your harts, but discouer the hypocrites, and send them home to hell vnmasked, where they were hatched: for they that
<pb n="58" facs="30"/>dare thus dally with God, no meruaile though they be bold with your soules, consciences, your children, and your estates, and all that belongs to you.</hi> I might (I say) present a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>M. Crashaw</hi> this Bill indyted by himselfe, turning the rayling tearmes, and cruell request vpon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. But for sending him to hell, I haue such horrour of that place, that I cannot intertaine such an vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table wish: nay I would willingly vndertake any la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and vndergoe any danger to saue him from it. Neyther would he wish the Iesuits vnto that place, did he as often thinke therof, and as deeply, as they do, which maketh them so ready to venture their liues to saue men from that lake of vnquenchable fire. I feare he will go thither too soone, though no man send him. The day, when perchance he shall least dreame of such a dreadfull cast, his Lord and ours shall appeare, and cast him, that trode vnder foot those of his family, vnto fire where with hypocrites he shal burne for euer. I wish he may liue many a yeare in this world to doe pennance for this heynous slaundering the Church &amp; Spouse of Christ, and recant his falshoods according to his promise; though hauing often found him false of his word, we can giue no credit to his profers.</p>
   <p n="44">44. But for the other part, that you be not se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by such Impostours, nor permit such Vipers to eate vp your hartes, nor Spyders to build in your Temples; my request herein against him, is so reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable after manifest proofe, and conuiction of so heynous a cryme, that the strongest reasons both of honour, and conscience, doe bind you vnto it. You may remember that a late worthy<note n="(u)" place="margin">The Earle of Salisbury Lord high Treasurer of Englād.</note>
 Peere of the Realme, for Wisdome, and Counsell renowned in most Countreys of the world, did refuse to patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize
<pb n="59" facs="30"/>his Sermon: you know the Parlament House commaunded the Epistle Dedicatory of his Iesuites Ghospell vnto them, should be suppressed, who by their Graue, and Honourable reiecting his workes, gaue you to vnderstand, what you in honour ought to do with the Author, though the danger of saluation you incurre by his meanes, be far greater. For as you see by this Treatise, that the first part of a sentence of <hi>S.</hi>
      <note n="(x)" place="margin">Apud prophāos &amp; extra Ecclesiam positos es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se aliud nō potest, nisi mens praua, &amp; fallax lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua, odia venenata, &amp; sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacia, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b{us} qui cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, cum ijs reperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse est, cùm dies iudicij ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerit. <hi>Cyp. l.</hi> 1. <hi>ep.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>Cyprian</hi> is true in <hi>M. Crashaw,</hi> to wit, <hi>that among them that are prophane, and out of the Church, nothing is to be expected, but a depraued mind, a deceipt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tongue, cankred malice, and sacrilegious lying:</hi> so likewise you may feare, one day will proue the truth of the second part of his speach, which is very dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to wit, that, <hi>whosoeuer giueth credit vnto such slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, shall share with the slaunderers in their sentence of damnation at Christs comming to iudge the world.</hi> You know that not only the Authors, and Actors of sinne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut also such as consent therunto, deserue punishment: and a consent to <hi>M. Crashawes</hi> slaunders they may be thought to giue, who, though perchance they doe not belieue them, yet they grace the slaunderers Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons with their presence. And to Your charge, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>osse of so many soules for which Christ gaue his life, will be layd, a strict account exacted, for making your Court the place, where such seely flyes, and fooles are caught by your example, as with a stale, drawing others into the snare. Which thing being of such moment, I will referre to your more serious conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, wishing your resolution may be such, as you may find comfort therof <hi>one</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Dies vna in atrijs Domini super mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia. <hi>Psal.</hi> 85. <hi>v.</hi> 11.</note>
      <hi>day, which shalbe worth a thousand.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="45">45. Wherefore now, without further Preface, I
<pb n="60" facs="31"/>will hoise vp sayle, with the gale of your fauour, and enter vpon his Sermon, which may be fitly compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a stormy sea. For what are so many raging inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues against the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but so many gusts of wind, to drowne in disgrace the Ship of <hi>Peter?</hi> What are his deuised wounds, but raging waues that batter her? What are his peeuish, and malicious slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, but shelfes and shallows wherin men do stick more stiffely, because vttered without proofe, they cannot be clearely refuted? What are the sentences of our Authours corrupted by him (yet couered with great protestations of sincere dealing) but so many rockes, the more dangerous because hidden, vpon which whosoeuer runneth a rash &amp; credulous course, without suspecting falsehood, incurreth shipwrack, and is drowned in damnable errour? What are the vgly blasphemyes which he layeth to our charge, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> horrible monsters? What the brags of his Churches salues, but <hi>Syrens</hi> songes? What finally his fond ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and vnlearned discourses, but foame and froath of this sea? Such waues against the <hi>Roma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> Church haue neuer wanted in any age, who by bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering her, haue broken themselues; yet will not the latter learne of the former, nor feare their endes whose courses they follow, but with a new rage of fury ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to their ruyne. This Church, as she is a ship to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey her passengers vnto heauen, flying by the sayle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of Sacraments, and filled with a gale of the holy Ghost, which shee hath a promise neuer to want: so is shee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> rock against her enemyes, that swell like waues against her; whose end, though they rage for a tyme, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> proue foame, and froath, into which others before them no lesse proud and swelling are vanished.</p>
   <p n="46">
      <pb n="61" facs="31"/>46. To quiet and pacify these waues we haue small hope: they are, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> saith,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Tit.</hi> 5.10.</note>
      <hi>condemned by their owne iudgment:</hi> like <hi>Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abyron</hi> they descend into hell aliue, that is, <hi>suam perditionem sentientes,</hi> as Saint<note n="(y)" place="margin">Epist. 48. ad Vincent.</note>
      <hi>Augustine</hi> expoundeth, feeling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to perish, and yet will not reclayme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues; such is the hatred that hell hath inspired into their harts, though many tymes they continue in their wicked courses out of shame, searing if they should leaue off, that men will say to them:<note n="(z)" place="margin">
         <p>Vti{que} hoc timēt ne dica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eis: Quare nos dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistis? Quare: tanta ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la &amp; falsa dixistis? Eterubes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitati, &amp; non erubescūt inuictissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati.</p>
         <p>
            <hi>August. ser.</hi> 22. <hi>de verbis Apostoli.</hi>
         </p>
      </note>
      <hi>Why then did you deceyue vs so long? Why did you seduce vs? Why did you tell vs so many false things? Regarding more the weaknes of men, then the inuinciblenes of truth?</hi> But for these that are but deceaued, who not out of pride swell, but are tossed in the rage of others, whom <hi>Saint Paul</hi> tearmeth, <hi>paruulos fluctuantes,</hi> wauing yong ones: for these, I say, I haue sent out the Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of this Treatise, into which if they please to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and read, and peruse the same, I make no doubt, but they will see the folly, and falshood of the slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which tosse and dryue them against the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man faith, and the wicked fraud and malice of them that vtter such vntruthes, and be moued to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Arke of the CATHOLICKE CHVRCH, singing with Saint<note n="(†)" place="margin">l. <hi>6.</hi> Cōfess. c. <hi>11.</hi> Nos falsis rumoribus terreba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trare, quos falsos esse nesciremus nisi intra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remus. <hi>So S.</hi> Augustine <hi>maketh Catholikes reioice, cōming from Donatists to the Church,</hi> Epist. <hi>48.</hi> ad Vincent.</note>
      <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine,</hi> hauing discouered the <hi>Manichees</hi> falsehood; <hi>Non docet Catholica quod putabamus, &amp; vani accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bamus:</hi> The CATHOLIKE CHVRCH doth not teach, as we did imagine, and were made belieue, and full of vanity did accuse her of. Into
<pb n="62" facs="32"/>which Ship of saluation, if this little Treatise may serue to conuey any out of the raging waues of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resy, I shall thinke my time well spent in the buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therof: this being the onely comfort of my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, that I desire in this life.</p>
   <p>AND so I commend the same to YOVR reading, wishing YOV may make that vse ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which God in his infinite goodnesse hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all Christian duty, <hi>I. R.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>