<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102403_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12168</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22477</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102403</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A breathing after God. Or a Christians desire of Gods presence. By the late reverent and worthy divine Richard Sibs, Doctor in Divinity, master of Katherine Hall in Cambridge, and sometime preacher of Graies-Inne</title>
                 <author>Sibbes, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Slater (Slaughter), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 240 pages, portraits, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AN in this world (espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially since his defection from God) standing at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance from his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse
<pb facs="4"/>
in respect of full possession; it is not the least part of his blisse to be happy in expectation. Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse being by all men desireable, the desire of it is naturally ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in every man, and is the Center of all the searchings of his heart and turnings of his life. But the most of men, like the men of <hi>Sodome</hi> grope and finde not the right dore: onely to a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb facs="4"/>
(by a supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall light) is discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both the right ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and the right way to felicitie. Vpon this discovery, finding himselfe (while hee is here) a stranger to his happinesse hee desires to take leave of this sublunary condition, that he may enjoy him who is <hi>The desire of all</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hag. 2. 7.</note>
      <hi>Nations.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now although God cast common bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings promiscuously
<pb facs="5"/>
upon good and bad, yet hee holds his best favours at a distance as Parents doe Cherries or Apples from their children, to whet their appetites the more after them. And indeede the best per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of a Christian in his military condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, in desire and expectation, and it is enough to him that, for that he hath Gods acceptation, who knowing whereof
<pb facs="5"/>
wee are made, and how unable to hold waite in the ballance of the Sanctuary, takes his best Gold with grains of allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
   <p>The soule of man is like a Cipher, which is valued by that which is set before it: if it wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it selfe in the desire of earthly things, like the Silke-worme, it finisheth its worke with its owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction: but if on
<pb facs="6"/>
things above, when this earthly Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle is turned to Ashes, there shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult a glorious <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix</hi> for immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
   <p>There are no Cha racters better distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing a Christian, then those that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward (hipocrisie like sale-worke may make a faire shew outward, an hypocrite may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme external works but cannot dissemble
<pb facs="6"/>
inward affections) and amongst them, none better discovers his temper, then the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the pulse of his desires, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Author (who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted not without being much desired, and no lesse lamented hath most lively set forth in the ensuing Treatise, which a Christian holding as a Glasse before him, may discerne whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee have life
<pb facs="7"/>
or no by these brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things.</p>
   <p>For the obiect here propounded, what more desirable then the chiefe good? for the place, where can it bee more desired, then in his house, where his presence is manifested? what bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end to bee in that house, then to behold God in the beauty of holinesse? what terme of happinesse better then for ever? This
<pb facs="7"/>
was the desire of the holy Prophet <hi>David,</hi> and that it may be thy desire, is the desire of</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thy Christian Friend,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>H. I.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>