<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In Laudem Authoris.</title>
           <author>Gunson, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102016_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00649</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10784</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102016</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In Laudem Authoris.</title>
                 <author>Gunson, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fennors descriptions, or A true relation of certaine and diuers speeches : spoken before the King and Queenes most excellent Maiestie, the Prince his highnesse, and the Lady Elizabeth's Grace. By William Fennor, His Maiesties seruant</title>
                 <author>Fennor, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Gibbs, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>In Laudem Authoris.</head>
   <l>WHy hath thy penne beene hid in obscure shades,</l>
   <l>or thy lines lockt in the darke wombe of night,</l>
   <l>Which being publish't, when thy body fades,</l>
   <l>in earths deepe <hi>Cauernes</hi> may giue others light?</l>
   <l>Thy Muse the loue of Noble-men perswades</l>
   <l>to shelter her, by their protecting might,</l>
   <l>Gain'st pining enuy, who with rusty blades,</l>
   <l>stands opposite against good workes to fight;</l>
   <l>With belching hate, who her full gorge vnlades,</l>
   <l>to make wit loathsome in the vulgar sight</l>
   <l>Of men illiterate, and <hi>Mechanicke</hi> trades,</l>
   <l>that scarce can iudge betwixt the wrong and right,</l>
   <l>Of thy indeauours which the heart inuades</l>
   <l>of worth (to praise thee) what though Criticks byte,</l>
   <l>And through the gulfe of base disliking wades,</l>
   <l>so farre vntill she drowne her selfe in spight</l>
   <l>Of all mans succour, other winching iades</l>
   <l>can like of nothing, but all things indight,</l>
   <l>To their owne censures; but bright fame shall spread</l>
   <l>hir leaues, where thou shalt liue, when thou art dead.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Tho. Gunson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>