<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue or argument.</title>
           <author>Dering, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102875_Fr4_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01514</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11636</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102875</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue or argument.</title>
                 <author>Dering, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The posies of George Gascoigne Esquire</title>
                 <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Smith (Smyth), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, clviij, 2, 4, 36, 45-76 pages, 77-86, 85-106 leaves, 107-173, 3, 175-290, 10 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="100"/>
   <head>The Prologue or argument.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Suppose you are assembled here, supposing to reape the fruite of my trauayles: and to be playne, I meane presently to presente you vvith a Comedie called Supposes: the verye name vvherof may peraduenture driue into euery of your heades a sundry Suppose, to suppose, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our supposes. Some percase vvill suppose vve meane to occupie your eares vvith sophisticall hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of subtill Suppositions. Some other vvil suppose vve go about to discipher vnto you some queint con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptes, vvhich hitherto haue bene onely supposed as it vvere in shadovves: and some I see smyling as though they supposed vve vvould trouble you vvith the vaine suppose of some vvanton Suppose. But vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, this our Suppose is nothing else but a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staking or imagination of one thing for an other. For you shall see the master supposed for the seruant, the seruant for the master: the freeman for a slaue, and the bondslaue for a freeman: the stranger for a vvell knovven friend, and the familiar for a stranger. But vvhat? I suppose that euen already you suppose me very fonde, that haue so simply disclosed vnto you the subtilties of these our Supposes: vvhere other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvise in deede I suppose you shoulde haue hearde almoste the laste of our Supposes, before you coulde haue supposed anye of them arighte. Let this then suffise.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>