<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, CHARLES, LORD HOWARD, BARON OF EFFINGHAM, KNIGHT OF THE MOST NOBLE ORDER OF THE GARTER, LORD high Admirall of England, and one of hir Ma∣iesties most Honorable priuie Councell: A. R. wisheth long life in perfect health, with great in∣crease of ho∣nor.</title>
           <author>Ryther, A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102649_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14164</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24481</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102649</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, CHARLES, LORD HOWARD, BARON OF EFFINGHAM, KNIGHT OF THE MOST NOBLE ORDER OF THE GARTER, LORD high Admirall of England, and one of hir Ma∣iesties most Honorable priuie Councell: A. R. wisheth long life in perfect health, with great in∣crease of ho∣nor.</title>
                 <author>Ryther, A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse concerninge the Spanishe fleete inuadinge Englande in the yeare 1588 : and ouerthrowne by Her Ma [ies] ties nauie vnder the conduction of the Right-honorable the Lorde Charles Howarde highe Admirall of Englande: written in Italian by Petruccio Vbaldino citizen of Florence, and translated for A Ryther: vnto the w [hi] ch discourse are annexed certaine tables expressinge the seuerall exploites, and conflictes had with the said fleete. These bookes with the tables belonginge to them are to be solde at the shoppe of A. Ryther beinge a little from Leaden hall nex to the signe of the Tower</title>
                 <author>Ubaldini, Petruccio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ryther (Rither), Augustine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 27, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, CHARLES, LORD HOWARD, BARON OF EFFINGHAM, KNIGHT OF THE MOST NOBLE ORDER OF THE GARTER, LORD high Admirall of England, and one of hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties most Honorable priuie Councell: A. R. wisheth long life in perfect health, with great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> AM BOLD, RIGHT Honorable, to present this booke vnto you &amp; to craue your fauora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble patronage therein, bicause there are many reasons which mooue me so to do. First, the subiect matter of the booke, which is your selfe especially, and the rest of the leaders, vnder whose happie conduction hir Maiesties nauie preuailed against the Spanish fleete. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="4"/> the time, which I haue spent in the grauing of the seueral Tables belonging to the booke, whereby the reader shall haue not onely the report, but the sight as it were of what notable thing soeuer was performed by your Honor in that high and honorable seruice. Thirdly, the booke it selfe, which as it hath beene kept backe these two yeeres almost from our men in an vnknowen toong, so (as I gesse) it had lien hid for euer, had not the good foreseene giuen iust occasion of the publishing thereof. Last of all, the time it selfe doth mooue to that which I haue done, which being the beginning of the new yeer, calleth for by custome a NEW YEERES GIFT, that is, as I construe it, a signe as abilitie permitteth, of that dutiful thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which I acknowledge my selfe to owe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Honor. The which my thankfulnes, bicause I had none other more conuenient signe, I was inforced to shew in presenting you this booke. Forsomuch therefore as it is now come abroad to the view of the world, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated and printed at my cost, I was mooued by the reasons aforesaid, to craue your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors patronage, that thereby I might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="4"/> withstand, both the malicious toongs of such as carpe, and the manifest iniurie of such as are readie vnaduisedly to counterfet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans worke: The which your Lordships fauor obtained (as my hope is) shall binde me foreuer to praie for your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors daily increase in all good things.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your HONORS most humble, A. RYTHER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>