<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WISE, and Good, a few Words before-hand; and they in their owne Words, the Words of Sobernesse and Truth.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102992_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01560</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11689</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102992</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WISE, and Good, a few Words before-hand; and they in their owne Words, the Words of Sobernesse and Truth.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Distractions, or The holy madnesse : Feruently (not furiously) inraged against euill men; or against their euills. Wherein the naughty are discouered to themselues, and others: and may here see at once, who they are; what they doe; and how they ought. Somewhat delightfull, but fruitfull altogether: as ordered to please a little; but aymed to profit much. By Iohn Gaule, vtrusque olim Academiæ</title>
                 <author>Gaule, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 489, 489-490, that is 491, 4 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE WISE, and Good, a few Words before-hand; and they in their owne Words, the Words of Sobernesse and Truth.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OƲ, the recouered Sons of a once-Fallen Father; yea, the recounted Sonnes of a Father
<pb facs="7"/> euer-liuing: whose Soules hee hath so Gratiously inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, so inflamed; and so made you, as J said (in your Manner, and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure) both Wise, and Good. You are (J beleeue no lesse, and as much reioyce) as fresh Fish, in this salt Sea; as tried Gold, to this cankred Drosse; as purging
<pb facs="7"/> Fires amidst these noysome Dunghills. You are indeed pickt out for <hi>Fish;</hi> yet is there (you know, and grieue) much <hi>Soyle</hi> beside you: You are sowne for <hi>Wheat;</hi> and (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las!) what <hi>Tares</hi> come vp among you? Woe, woe! There will bee <hi>Goats;</hi> though you be mark't for <hi>Sheepe.</hi> To you
<pb facs="8"/> I come (so please you bid me, for you need me not) in the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Meeknesse:</hi> The <hi>Rod</hi> only is laid vpon the Backs it was made for; the Backs of <hi>Fooles.</hi> Nor to those come J thus only; but euen otherwise, as I see oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion. The Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian of the Body v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth not the same Meanes to heale all:
<pb facs="8"/> Nor, with that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and better of the Soule, is there one way to winne all. <hi>To yeeld to Some, is (by that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>anes) to gaine them to our selues.</hi> That J come to Men in their owne Words; is to bring Men to your Minds. Tis but my Bait I haue somewhat ordered to their Appetite: you
<pb facs="9"/> see how my Hook is, it hangs vpon. Let my aiming excuse me; and not my Saying, or Seeming only cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure mee before you. <hi>Neuer was it but allowed, by none but lauded euer; so to stoope to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as thereby to raise them vp.</hi> Our <hi>Holy Lord</hi> vouchsafed himselfe to be made like vs;
<pb facs="9"/> so to make vs like vnto himselfe: would take vpon him our silly Offices; so to bring vs to his holy Mysteries. What said that <hi>Great Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> of himselfe? <hi>To the weake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came I as weake, that I might gaine the weake: I am made all things to all men, that I might by all means
<pb facs="10"/> saue some.</hi> What should J say of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Authors,</hi> of holy <hi>Fathers;</hi> that haue writ of weake things, of graue things weakly; and both to instruct the Weake? Besides their loue to Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and Truth; it was some Art of theirs: so to bend themselues to others, as to draw on others
<pb facs="10"/> to themselues. To hit a man home a little in his own humour; hath oft beene the way to stoop to his Capacitie, to touch his Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Let it then be at leastwise excusable, so to let a Man vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand what he is; as thereby to bring him to what he ought to be. Let no man iudge mee light, by my Lookes; my Face
<pb facs="11"/> (J meane) and Forefront: A more weighty, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founder Title of a Booke, the Subiect and Stile according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; J obserue (for J haue already been so occasioned) haue soone tired, nay quite deterred a Common Reader: Let not the Better bee against me, sith I thus would winne on the Worse.
<pb facs="11"/> What euer the Most may mutter against mee; my hope is, the Best will say somewhat for mee; against whom J ought, J can say nothing: J know (through the impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibilitie of pleasing all) I cannot but dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>please some. <hi>Who can say so well, and warily, which all will approue of;
<pb facs="12"/> nay which many will not euen mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like?</hi> Let no reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father, no lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Brother (whom J humbly obserue, whom heartily I em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace) say me male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moued: (as haue also beene many in this Minde, and Mood.) Against or besides our State, and Church; nor haue J
<pb facs="12"/> read, haue J obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; doe I iudge, doe J acknowledge any; so iustly Humane, so religiously Diuine. Accept my Words vpon my Faith; J labour to looke to, and satisfie mee with my selfe: J enuy no Man, J inueigh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst no more. Nor shall the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Cauiller vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid vs with our
<pb facs="13"/> selues: J say not so of this our Land a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. No: I am a better Bird than so; to defile mine owne Nest my selfe, by saying it so foule. I dare say, other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and their Manners; doe (in a manner) instifie vs, and ours. Yea and our <hi>Publican Sins</hi> (J perswade me) in this our Church, shall
<pb facs="13"/> rise vp in Iudgement against the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saicall Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> of that other, of theirs. Yet are not wee the Better; that they are the Worse: Nor are wee the lesse to be blamed; though they be the more to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred. Let me then disclose to them their Abominations, in our Infirmities.
<pb facs="14"/>
      <hi>VVee may toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shame O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and blame our Selues.</hi> And now, you againe the Wise ones and Good! if J shall doe (in any whit) well, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy you; afford it your Fauour: if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, be pleased yet to Pardon it. So J leaue you, whom J humbly craue; and come to those, whom
<pb facs="14"/> J rightly challenge to be my Readers.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>