<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS BEST, worthy, and most endee∣red Friend, Mr. Iohn
de Hem, Merchant of this Honourable Cittie of London, Edward
Popham wisheth all terrestriall blessings in this world, and the
fulnesse of all celestiall blessings in the Life to come.</title>
           <author>Popham, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102083_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09850</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20115</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102083</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS BEST, worthy, and most endee∣red Friend, Mr. Iohn
de Hem, Merchant of this Honourable Cittie of London, Edward
Popham wisheth all terrestriall blessings in this world, and the
fulnesse of all celestiall blessings in the Life to come.</title>
                 <author>Popham, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A looking-glasse for the soule, and a definition thereof. Written by Edward Popham Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Popham, Edward, gentleman</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 48 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS BEST, worthy, and most endee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Friend, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Iohn
de Hem,</hi> Merchant of this Honourable Cittie of <hi>London, Edward
Popham</hi> wisheth all terrestriall blessings in this world, and the
fulnesse of all celestiall blessings in the Life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y most loued and best estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Friend, I haue read, that
mongst that little labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="3"/> Common-wealth of Bees, they haue a law, that if a
Drone hauing lost his sting (which gaue him spirit to labour, because
being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with that hee was able to encounter with his aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary) &amp;
now giuing himselfe to sloth, and sucke the honey from the rest, he is
(by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall consent) presently thrust out, and banisht, or put to
death, as an vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table member: To auoyde which imputation, I haue
<pb facs="3"/> gathered vp some remnants of time, to meditate vpon
an euerlasting subiect (which is the <hi>Soule)</hi> a subiect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
created to serue her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall King, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting, because a
blessed euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting life is her reward if she perseuere in her
Creators seruice to the end. I confesse it is a large field, whereon in
expert Artist may frame and build a goodly Cittie;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut I being but a simple
la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ourer, dare not presume
to
<pb facs="4"/> speake of <hi>Colossus,</hi> or build pyramides
(wonders of the world) lest in piercing too high, I meete with
<hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi> and so fall to ruine. Yet as the poore widdow in the
Gospell, amongst the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great superfluous gifts did not doubt but her
mite would be accepted; so I doubt not but mongst those many huge vollumes
that swarme in the world, some well-iudging Christian may cast his eye
on my poore
<pb facs="4"/> worke, &amp; so may giue a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle conclusion,
saying, this poore man hath cast in his Mite into the treasury, and
brought one little stone to the eternall building. To giue a better glosse
to my small commodity, I haue thought good (my deere Friend) to patronize it
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your protection, coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you by all the lawes of friendship, not to
refuse the guardiance of this poore In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, but nourish it with
<pb facs="5"/> your best loue, for which you shall be sure to
finde double requitall; first, you shal bind my poore loue and labour to
your seruice; and last, (which is best) you shall find Gods blessing
to your soule and body; to whose prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I leaue you, and rest yours,
euer deuoted</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Edward Popham.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>