<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface to the true Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102282_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11041</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102282</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface to the true Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The diamond of deuotion : cut and squared into sixe seuerall points: namelie, 1 The footpath to felicitie. 1 2 A guide to godlines. 81 3 The schoole of skill. 181 4 A swarme of bees. 209 5 A plant of pleasure. 245 6 A groue of graces. 283 Full of manie fruitfull lessons, auaileable to the leading of a godlie and reformed life: by Abraham Fleming</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William, Assignee(s) of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 320, 4 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="95"/>
   <pb n="183" facs="95"/>
   <head>A Preface to the true <hi>Christian Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the custome of parents, disposed to traine vp their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in learning and knowledge of tongs, artes, and sciences: first in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie to commit them to some ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest schoolemaister, vnder whome they might be taught the principles of their owne naturall tongue, and afterwards in tract of time, as their capacitie increased, the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> of foraigne speeches. For he that determineth to erect and build a dwelling house, beginneth not at the roofe, but at the foundation: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, as it were a preposterous kinde of attempt, so all the world would iudge it fond &amp; ridiculous.</p>
   <p>Againe, we see, and experience
<pb facs="96"/>
teacheth no lesse, that the expertst and valiantst Captaine that euer fought in field, was not a perfect warriour borne, though peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture there was in him some vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inclination to martiall poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and prowesse, but first he had his slender beginnings, and simple trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings vp, fit and conuenient for the nature of his age, which trainings vp in militarie knowledge, &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like actiuitie continued, the learner becommeth more skilfull and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, and at last, by frequenting the field, and envring himselfe to trials of valiantnes, proueth a pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing souldier.</p>
   <p>Euen so we, whome nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede hath adorned with a goodlie likenes, with amiablenes of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and with apt proportion of bodie, but yet thrust out into the world with polluted soules, if we be desirous to please God, and not to offend man, we must endeuour our selues to leade a life agreeable to the written word of the Lord. The
<pb facs="96"/>
waies and meanes to atteine here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, do stand vpon certaine prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, or positions, whereof some being affirmatiue, and some nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, dooe iointlie teach vs what we ought to followe, and what to es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chue.</p>
   <p>These principles or rules leading vs to the knowledge and practise of a godlie and vpright life, I haue thought good to call <hi>The Schoole of skill.</hi> For, as to neglect the due ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation of such precepts, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie to contemne the vse of so wholesome counsels, is a manifest reason and argument of follie: so, to esteeme of them, as of acceptable treasures, and to order the course of life, according to their prescription and platforme, is an euident signe and token of good skill.</p>
   <p>Now the Schoolemaister, whose Schoole I entitle this to be, is such a one indeede, as being taught by the holie Ghost from aboue, hath had the vse and practise of a godlie and blamelesse life: the commoditie
<pb facs="97"/>
whereof, and incomparable sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse issuing from thence, when he had tasted, and sawe that the end of the same was the reward of eternall life, he pitied the miserable state of men walking in blindnesse, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and destruction: and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke them, or rather instruct and teach them knowledge, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might amend their inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate trade of life, he professed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a teacher in this Schoole, to the end that others, as well as he, might perceiue what aduantage a well disposed life affordeth.</p>
   <p>This Schoolemaister we must pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suppose to be such a one, whose hart the finger of the Lord had touched, and into whose vnderstanding the sunne of sanctification had shined. He was not one that walked in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall libertie, neither in the concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscence of the eie, neither in the vanitie of the mind, for then should there be a repugnancie and dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betweene his conuersation and profession, which ought to agree
<pb facs="97"/>
like musicall concords. Take him therefore to be such a one, as being renewed in the spirit of the inner man, is able to teach, to instruct, to rebuke, and to informe, that the man of God might be made perfect in all righteousnesse. But now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering into this Schoole of Skill, let vs like good scholers with full pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose (Gods grace being our gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) to profit and go forward in that we professe, learne by hart our A, B, C, in this Schoole, and according to our les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons frame the course of our life.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Abraham Fleming.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>