<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER whosoever.</title>
           <author>Perkins, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102079_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09473</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19758</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102079</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER whosoever.</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo treatises· : I. Of the nature and practise of repentance. II. Of the combat of the flesh and spirit</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 <publisher>Kitson, Abraham.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER whosoever.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD hath bestowedon vs great prosperitie and peace with plenty of all temporall bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings that heart can wish for many yeres in this land.</p>
   <p>Prosperity abused hath bin the occasion of many grievous sinnes against the first and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condtable: specially of Atheisme, neglect of Gods worship, contempt of the word, prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sabbath, abuse of the Sacraments, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>These and such like sinnes have long called downe for iudgements from heaven upon us: &amp; the rather, because the preaching of the worde hath litle prevailed to bring vs to any amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>Whereupon God hath now begun to cause his iudgements to seaze upon vs, specially by plague and pestilence: &amp; that even in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry principall part of this land: whereby he him selfe doth (as Iob saith) <hi>round us in the eare,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iob. 36. 15.</note> and preach repentance to vs.</p>
   <p>Wherfore it stands vs now in hand if ever, to looke about vs: and if we have not repented to begin to repent: if we have in former time repented, to doe it more earnestly.</p>
   <p>If so be that we shall harden our hearts both against his word and iudgements, &amp; put farre from vs the evill day: undoubtedly we must needs looke for iudgements far more terrible then ever we felt as yet; if not eternall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. Let vs be advised by the old world, who made light of Noahs warning, and were drowned in the flood: by Lots sonnes in law, who<note place="margin">Gen. 19. 14.</note> tooke their fathers counsell for mockage and were burnt with fire and brimstone from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: by the foolish virgins, who were sleeping when they should have bene furnishing their lampes, and were shut from the mariage of the lambe.</p>
   <p>And to direct thee somwhat in the practise
<pb facs="3"/>
of repentance, I haue penned this small trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise: vse it for thy benefite, and see thou be a doer of it: vnlesse thou wilt be a wilfull mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer &amp; shed the blood of thine owne soule.</p>
   <p>And whereas there have bin published here to fore in English two sermons of Repentance, one by M. Bradford Martyr, the other by M. Arthur Dent: sermons indeed which haue done much good: my meaning is not to adde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, or to teach any other doctrine, but only to renew &amp; revive the memory of that which they have taught.</p>
   <p>Neither let it trouble thee that the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall divines of this age, whom in this treatise I follow, may seeme to be at difference in trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of repentance. For some make it a fruite of faith containing two parts, mortification, &amp; vivification: some make faith a part of it, by deviding it into contrition, faith, new obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. The difference is not in the substance of doctrine, but in the logicall maner of han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling it. And the difference of handling ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth of the divers acception of repentance. It is taken two wayes generally &amp; particularly. Generally for the whole conversion of a sinner,
<pb facs="4"/>
and so it may containe contrition, faith, and nevv obedience under it. It is taken particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly for the renovation of the life and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicur: and so it is a fruite of faith. And this only sense do I follovv in this treatise.</p>
   <p>I have added hereto a fevv lines of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat betvvene the flesh and the spirit: because repentance and this combat are ioyned togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; the one is not practised vvithout the other, as appeares by resolving Psalme 51.</p>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Spirit.</speaker>
      <p>Haue mercy on me, O God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note place="margin">vers. 1.</note> to thy louing kindnes.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Flesh.</speaker>
      <p>Yea, but this thine adultery compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends infinite sinnes: therfore looke for no pardon.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Spirit.</speaker>
      <p>According to the multitude of thy compassions put away mine iniquities.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Flesh.</speaker>
      <p>This sinne hath taken such deepe place in thee: that it will be hardly pardoned.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Spirit.</speaker>
      <p>Wash me throughly from mine<note place="margin">vers. 2.</note> iniquity, and clense me from my sinne.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Flesh.</speaker>
      <p>Thy speciall trespasse is against man.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Spirit.</speaker>
      <p>Against thee, against thee, only haue<note place="margin">vers. 4.</note> I sinned, &amp;c.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <speaker>Flesh.</speaker>
      <p>Except this one sinne, thy life is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable.</p>
   </sp>
   <sp>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <speaker>Spirit.</speaker>
      <p>Behold I was borne in iniquity, &amp;c.<note place="margin">vers. 5.</note>
      </p>
   </sp>
   <p>Yea, the best man that is, in the practise of godlinesse often appeares to be unlike him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe: the cause is this spirituall combat. The flesh other whiles makes him waile and mourne and goe drooping: presently after the spirit puts into him (as we say) the heart of grasse, and makes him triumph against the flesh, the devill the world. Moses was couragious at the<note place="margin">Exod. 14. 13. Num. 20. 11, 12. Iob. 1. 21. &amp; 3. 1. Psalm, 6. 1, 8. &amp; 10. 17. &amp; 41. 9, 10, 11.</note> red sea; but he failed at the waters of strife. Iob first praiseth God, and after blasphemeth. David is often fainting in miserie, yet by and by revived. Wherefore there is good cause why the consideration of repentance and the combat should go togither: that no man, after he hath begun to repent, might dreame of ease to his flesh; as though we should goe to heaven in beds of downe: but rather that we might be resolved, that when we begin to doe any thing pleasing unto God, then wee must looke for nothing but continuall molestations from our vile and wicked natures.</p>
   <closer>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <dateline>Written <date>Anno 1593. the 17. of Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</date>, which is the Coronation day of our dread Soveraigne Queene ELIZABETH; whose raigne God long continue.</dateline>
      <signed>William Perkins.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>