<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISMENT OF THE PVBLISHER OF THIS TREATISE to the Reader.</title>
           <author>B., A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102862_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18305</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102862</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISMENT OF THE PVBLISHER OF THIS TREATISE to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>B., A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Bishop of London his legacy. Or certaine motiues of D. King, late Bishop of London, for his change of religion, and dying in the Catholike, and Roman Church : VVith a conclusion to his bretheren, the LL. Bishops of England</title>
                 <author>Musket, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>iiij leaves, v-xvj, 24, 33-174 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="ij" facs="2"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISMENT OF THE PVBLISHER <hi>OF THIS TREATISE</hi> to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Reader, It is an appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Methode both of aunciēt &amp; moderne VVriters, after they haue made choyce of the <hi>Subiect</hi> by thē to be intreated off, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes by a Poeticall Conceite, particularly to tye and apply the sayd <hi>Subiect,</hi> to some one peculiar person, or other circumstance; as if the Truth, and Verity thereof, did really exist only in the same Person, or Circumstance.</p>
   <p>Thus (for Example) <hi>Xenephon</hi> fashioning in his <hi>KYPO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ANAEIA,</hi> or Institution of <hi>Cyrus;</hi>
      <pb n="ji" facs="3"/>what a Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> ought to be, doth person<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e all his Precepts therin in <hi>Cyrus:</hi> Not that <hi>Cyrus</hi> was such a Prince, as he is there described; but that according to the judgmēt of <hi>Xenophon,</hi> is Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, or King is wished to be so instructed and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as he feygneth <hi>Cyrus.</hi> And thus his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty</hi> (whom God long preserue) following in part the like Methode, doth delineate, and draw with his learned Pencil, the true portraiture of a good Prince in his <hi>Basilicon Doron,</hi> a worke of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall memory, and worthy to be written in letters, not of gould (too base a mettall) but euen in letters of Diamonds, if so they could be melted and resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Thus also doth <hi>Homer</hi> in his <hi>Odyssees</hi> (as it were) incorporate all his instructions and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumēts of a subtile and wyse traueller, in the persō of <hi>Vlysses.</hi> The like may improportionably be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerred of <hi>Plato</hi> touching his Cōmonwealth, of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristotle</hi> touching his Felicity, and lastly of that most glorious Martyr S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Thomas More</hi> in his <hi>Vtopia.</hi> All or most of which Authours for their better warrant, do challenge to themselues a Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call liberty, in feyguing that really to be, which indeed is not.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="iij" facs="3"/>Now to apply this to our present matter in had, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>hing the deceased <hi>Bishop</hi> of London, D. <hi>King.</hi> That he altered his Religion before his death, and dyed Catholike, is most certaine, (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer his F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ries labour to suppresse the truth,) seeing if liberty were giuen, it would infallibly be made euident by many vnanswerable reasons. That he did write in tyme of his sicknes, &amp; deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to others before his death any reason, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyues of such his change in Religion, I will be spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring peremptorily to affirme; for I will not exas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate his Friends, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d other great Protestant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages, more then necessity inforceth. For see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they could not endure to heare, that he dyed Catholike, what tragedyes &amp; troubles would they attempt to rayse, if it should be auerred, that the <hi>Bishop</hi> did wryte any <hi>Motiues</hi> of such his alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in Fayth and Religion. Only I say, seeing it is most certayne, that he dyed Catholike: And seeing no learned Man changeth his Religion, but vpon some Inducements and Motiues: And lastly seeing in the iudgment of the Publisher heerof, no Motyues are more forcible for a Protestant (&amp; perhaps particulerly for the <hi>Bishop</hi>) to change
<pb facs="4"/>his Religion, and imbrace the Catholike Fayth, then these set downe in this Treatise: Therfore the Publisher, as being warrāted by the former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Xenophon</hi> and others aboue mētioned, wisheth, that Himselfe may be heere taken to haue written these <hi>Motiues,</hi> as a Precedent, or Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erne, warranting any Protestant in the change of his Religion, though by a Poeticall freedome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly applyed to the <hi>Bishop,</hi> in regard of his like change of Fayth; and so accordingly the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise is styled, <hi>His Legacy.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And therfore to keepe the better <hi>Decorum,</hi> where the <hi>Bishop</hi> in the Epistle Dedicatory, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumeth the wryting therof to himself: VVhere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so in the Booke it selfe, there is some enterchange of speeches betweene the <hi>Bishop</hi> and others: And lastly, where the <hi>Bishop</hi> in the end thereof wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to the rest of the <hi>Bishops</hi> his Brethren: All these passages, the Reader may (if it please him) with my full consent and allowance, suppose to be <hi>fictiones Personarum,</hi> and warranted by the figure <hi>Prospopcia:</hi> And that the Publisher heerof performeth no more, (if so much) then <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> doth in his <hi>Parallels</hi> of the Romans with
<pb n="iiij" facs="4"/>the Grecians: That is, to appropriate certayne Speeches, or Orations to certayne Men; and such speeches only, as are most fitting to proceed (with due consideration of Circumstances) from the same parties, to whom they are by supposall so ascribed.</p>
   <p>Thus Good Reader, seeing matters must be cautelously carried in these dayes, thou seest, I will thee not, to take this Treatise, as written by the <hi>Bishop,</hi> and deliuered ouer to others in his life tyme, but (in Gods Name) repute it as Myne. For I am not desirous to father any thing vpon the dead (nor doth the Catholike Cause need any such Pretence) but what is acknowledged for such, by the iudgment of all Men; &amp; I know well the B<seg rend="sup">•</seg>. Friends are farre from any such acknowledgment. But howsoeuer, if thou reape profit heerby, I shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be glad; but if neyther the <hi>Bishops</hi> change in Religion, nor these present <hi>Motyues</hi> (by whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer written) can withdraw thee from the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies of these tymes, I can but commiserate the poore and dangerous estate of thy Soule.</p>
   <p>If any of the <hi>Bishops</hi> neerest Friends, shall by answere impugne this Treatise, let him take heed, that the byrth of such a future worke become
<pb n="iiii" facs="5"/>not <hi>viperous,</hi> as not regarding whose sides it la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth before it can take is being. But aboue all, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing to cauill at the Method, let him be carefull to answere the <hi>Motyues</hi> in particuler, &amp; this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and plainly, and to all the authorityes, as heere they do lye, without affecting any obscurity in Methode, or long and tedious Discourses, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to diuert the Readers mynd frō the point heere handled, and to turne it to other by-matters. Thus much is expected at his hands, and the rather, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aforehand he is premonished heereof only, for the better manifestation of the truth. And thus (Good Reader) wishing thee to take (at least) in good part, the publishing of this <hi>Legacy,</hi> which indeed had been sent to the Presse instantly vpon the <hi>Bishops</hi> death (and so had then imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately come forth) were it not, that it hath been stayed till now, vpon some iust and vrgent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, I bid thee hartily farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy louing Friend <hi>A. B.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>