<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE REVEREND AND RIGHT WORSHIPFULL, JOHN BARKHAM, Doctour of Divinitie, &amp; Dean of BOCKING.</title>
           <author>Garthwait, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102905_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01511</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11633</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102905</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE REVEREND AND RIGHT WORSHIPFULL, JOHN BARKHAM, Doctour of Divinitie, &amp; Dean of BOCKING.</title>
                 <author>Garthwait, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Monotessaron : The evangelicall harmonie, reducing the foure Evangelists into one continued context; and in it the entire historie of the acts and sayings, life and death of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ: duely ordered according to the distinction of times. By Henry Garthwait</title>
                 <author>Garthwait, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Buck, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Daniel, Roger</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 262, 2 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE REVEREND AND RIGHT WORSHIPFULL, <hi>JOHN BARKHAM,</hi> Doctour of Divinitie, &amp; Dean of BOCKING.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving had the honour and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse for some yeares to live under your roof, I have often observed your constant love and respectfull care to advance &amp; further any thing tending to publick good. The desired imitation of this pattern first kindled in me the sparks of an ambitious reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to exercise my self (besides my ordinary sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred task) in some such labour, as might, if not in the event prove beneficiall to all, yet at least shew
<pb facs="3"/>my willingnesse to employ my utmost abilitie to that end. I fastened therefore upon this Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and by Gods assistance have finished it, in this form, wherein none was ever yet extant in our own language, nor (to my knowledge) in any other. Yet because the best things, published with the best intent, seldome scape the lash of censorious readers; these my first fruits, as by right due to the Church, I present to your self; that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the shelter of your name I may adventure. them to the view of these curious times. You have the patronage of the father: this his infant therefore, having been conceived in your house, and brought forth by your advice, now stepping first into publick, craves the priviledge of your protection: and that as you were a daily encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of my proceeding, a witnesse of my care and faithfulnesse in the work, &amp; pleased to commend it to the Professours in the Universitie, who have the examination of what is made publick: so this way also you would please to commend it to the world. And besides (which is the chief) having no other means to expresse my gratefull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of your continuall favours, accept, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you, this dedication of my labours to the memorie of your lasting name: for if the gods (as
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Plinie</hi> saith) accept a plain cake of meal and salt offered in pure devotion by such as have no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter incense, then I doubt not you will accept of this, as the free oblation of him who hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated and devoted himself</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships ever obliged to do you service, <hi>HENRY GARTHWAIT.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>