<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
           <author>F., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102016_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00649</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10784</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102016</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen Readers.</title>
                 <author>F., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fennors descriptions, or A true relation of certaine and diuers speeches : spoken before the King and Queenes most excellent Maiestie, the Prince his highnesse, and the Lady Elizabeth's Grace. By William Fennor, His Maiesties seruant</title>
                 <author>Fennor, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Gibbs, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen Readers.</head>
   <p>WOrthy gentlemen, of what degree soeuer, I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose this Pamphlet will hap into your hands, before a play begin, with the importunate clamour, of <hi>Buy a new Booke,</hi> by some needy companion, that will be glad to furnish you with worke for a turn'd Teaster. I rest well assured some of you will know mee at the sight of the infant, to such I commend it for acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance sake; others (I make no question) haue heard of me, to those I send it, in hope of better acquaintance; A third sort (it may be) neuer knew mee, nor I thinke care not whether euer they doe or no: To them I present it as carelesly as vnthrifts spend their anuities. Last to Criticks, I wish it may hap as seldome into their hands, as Vsurers giue almes, or Lawyers plead <hi>pro nihil.</hi> If any chance to say my inuention runs low, in regard I sell relations for demonstrations, to such I answere, not like a light hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife, that will be wonne before she be wooed; but like a chaste virgin that would be scarce wonne with wooing: as for example, it is three yeeres since I spake some of these speeches, and since that time I haue beene earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreated by noble personages (who haue had priuate copies for their owne vse) to print it for publike delight, at length I consented, &amp; since I am won, haue amongst you gallants, let it speed as it will. This is my comfort, how ere it proue in the reading, it was well lik't in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearsing, by that Imperiall power; for whose prosperous continuance we are all in dutie bound to pray, <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in honest mirth, W. F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>