<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE Francis Lord 틀erulam, Lord High Chancellor of England, and one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuy Counsell, grace, peace, and mercy from GOD the Father, and his Sonne IESVS CHRIST our Lord, by the operation of the holy Ghost.</title>
           <author>Fowns, R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102490_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01103</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11216</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102490</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE Francis Lord 틀erulam, Lord High Chancellor of England, and one of his Maiesties most Honorable Priuy Counsell, grace, peace, and mercy from GOD the Father, and his Sonne IESVS CHRIST our Lord, by the operation of the holy Ghost.</title>
                 <author>Fowns, R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Trisagion or, The three holy offices of Iesus Christ, the sonne of God, priestly, propheticall, and regall : how they ought of all his Church to be receiued. VVith a declaration of the violence and iniuries offered vnto the same, by the spirituall and Romish Babylon ... Reuealing many blasphemous mysteries vnknowne to the vulgar. By Richard Fovvns, Doctor of Diuinitie, and chaplaine domesticall to the late illustrious Prince Henry</title>
                 <author>Fowns, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>44, 346, 8, 347-504, 6, 503-782, 2 pages, illustrations, 4째</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="291"/>
   <pb facs="291"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE <hi>Francis</hi> Lord <hi>틀erulam,</hi> Lord High <hi>Chancellor of</hi> England, <hi>and one of his Maiesties</hi> most Honorable Priuy Counsell, grace, peace, and mercy from GOD the Father, and his <hi>Sonne</hi> IESVS CHRIST <hi>our Lord,</hi> by the operation of the holy Ghost.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Honour may perhaps demand of me, as once <hi>Antigonus</hi> the great Prince did of <hi>Bias a</hi> poore philosopher, <hi>Whence</hi> and <hi>Who?</hi> since vncouth and vnknowne I presume to present the harsh and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasing lines of my rude labor vnto your patronage. To this, my Apologie is, If your Lordships facilitie had beene lesse, my presumption would not haue been so great: But now as the long wandring Pinnasse desireth to put into the fairest Hauen, and Souldiers euermore choose the most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensible shield: so I am bold with all humility to dedicate vnto your Honour these poore endeuours of mine against the common enemy; both in regard of your gracious disposition, as also your great autho itie: of which the one doth promise mee good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, and the other assured protection.</p>
   <pb facs="292"/>
   <p>Surely if the blasphemie of the Romish Antichristian Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue were like vnto other Hereticks, whereof, one denieth the Manhood, as <hi>Ebion:</hi> another the Godhead as <hi>Arius:</hi> some the distinction of his Person from the Father, as <hi>Sabellius:</hi> others his humane soule, as <hi>Apolinaris,</hi> or the truth of his Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, as <hi>Manicheus;</hi> The confutation of their impietie would be more easie: but confessing the natures, Papistry ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the offices, not openly &amp; plainly as other Hereticks but crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and secretly. So that vnder the name of Christ, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> saith, they confound the Religion of Christ; and as <hi>Tully</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth of <hi>Epicurus</hi> that he left gods vnto the people in words, but tooke them away in deeds: So the Romish schoole hath the forme of godlinesse, but denyeth the power therof. And though they outwardly confesse Christ, yet they spoile him of all the offices to which by the eternall counsell of God, for the repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankinde he is ordained. To this end therefore should all Ministers imploy their Studies, all States their Policy, all Magistrates their Power, all common-weales their Wisedome, that these Wolues disguised in Lambe-skins, these Messengers of Satan in the habite of Angels of light might bee vnmasked, and the mystery of iniquitie which walketh in the darknesse discouered to euery eye, and so all <hi>Israel</hi> should flee from <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and euery simple Sheepe vnderstand the collusion of the Foxes.</p>
   <p>Of the Priestly and Propheticall parts in the former bookes I haue entreated; in this I shew what violence, what treachery they vse toward the supreme King of Kings and Lord of Lords; and withall against worldly Potentates and Princes, whom God hath ordained to be his Vice-gerents, and vnder him to exercise power in the earth.</p>
   <p>Vnto your worthinesse therefore I offer this last Booke, wherein according to the talent giuen vnto me, I defend the
<pb facs="292"/> dignitie and maiestie of the Regall power against the wicked vsurpation of the Romish Bishop. First, because I know how deere and precious vnto you the honour and dignity of our most Royall Soueraigne is: and secondly, if from your great wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and learned censure these simple leaues shall receiue any approbation, I shall little regard the venimous aspersions of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting tongues, or the poysoned teeth of any <hi>Zoylus</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer.</p>
   <p>The Lord God of all power and might blesse your Honour in your high place of Iustice and of Gouernement so happily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne, that your brightnesse and your light may encrease more and more vntill the day be full; And at last as full of honours as of dayes you may be gathered to your Fathers in peace, and to the bosome of <hi>Abraham</hi> replenished with euerlasting ioy and glory: Which the Lord grant vnto you, thorow Iesus Christ our onely Mediatour and Aduocate.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Seauern Stoke in Worcester-shire,</hi>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Honours most humble Orator, <hi>R. FOWNS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>