<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONO∣ GENTLEMAN, SIR Thomas Gerrard of Brinne, Knight Barronet, and one of his Maiesties Iustices for the Countie of Lancaster, AVGVS∣TINE TAYLOR wisheth all pros∣perity in Happinesse.</title>
           <author>Taylor, Augustine</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102628_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13412</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23722</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102628</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONO∣ GENTLEMAN, SIR Thomas Gerrard of Brinne, Knight Barronet, and one of his Maiesties Iustices for the Countie of Lancaster, AVGVS∣TINE TAYLOR wisheth all pros∣perity in Happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Augustine</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Epithalamium vpon the all-desired nvptials of Frederike the fift, Prince Palatine of Rhene, chiefe elector, Duke of Bauier, and arch-sewer to the Romane Empire : And Elizabeth, the onely daughter of Iames, by the grace of God, King of Great Britain, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. VVritten by Augustine Taylor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Augustine</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Marchant, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Rand, Samuel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>11 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Wedding pamphlets</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> GENTLEMAN, SIR Thomas Gerrard of Brinne, Knight Barronet, and one of his Maiesties Iustices for the Countie of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> AVGVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TINE TAYLOR wisheth all pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity in Happinesse.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN all the excellent admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wits of this so capable Age, in the spring of thicke furnitur'd inuentions, bestow paines to giue my Patrons a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect blazon, I willing to thrust my dutifull loue into the Presse, longing to see the shape of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Print; <hi>Credo vt est dementia,</hi> Seeing so many swelling Muses, and of such apprehension, that read theirs and mine next together, and you will say, my ill worke makes their good labours to appeare better then (indeed) they are. <hi>Vt sementem feceris, ita &amp; metes:</hi> Apply not that Rule to mee, but right worthy Sir, of what I offer willingly, vouch to accept courteously, as a Monument of my loue, which
<pb facs="3"/> time hath borne to the generous family of the <hi>Gerrards,</hi> and my affection to your worthy selfe. Knowing you to come from the best worth of that Aierie, and one of his Maiesties respected, grace my ill-tempered Muse: and hauing so worthy a refuge, you shall hereafter see it start out of Cinders <hi>(vnus dies non sat estad parandam eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionem)</hi> and liue an age that ere-while waxt old with a Sommers day. Vouch to allow of this, till time present you with some greater token of my loue: I commit your deseruing worthinesse to wished continuance.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in loue and dutie, AVGVSTINE TAYLOR</signed>
   </closer>
   <trailer>Volenti nihil est graue.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>