<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the learned and vnlear∣ned Reader.</title>
           <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102286_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00941</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11049</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102286</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the learned and vnlear∣ned Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A panoplie of epistles, or, a looking glasse for the vnlearned : Conteyning a perfecte plattforme of inditing letters of all sorts, to persons of al estates and degrees, as well our superiours, as also our equalls and inferiours: vsed of the best and the eloquentest rhetoricians that haue liued in all ages, and haue beene famous in that facultie. Gathered and translated out of Latine into English, by Abraham Flemming</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 <publisher>Middleton, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 448 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the learned and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oe, learned Reader, whose minde is beautified with the amiable iuelles of knowledge, and iudgement, to thee I present this Panoplie of Epistles, to reade for thy recreation, and peruse at thy pleasure: for I am taught by experience of my selfe, that the tediousnesse of studio, is to be assuaged with some intermingling of delight. To the vnlearned I doe likewise offer it, as sufficient furniture to arme and enable them against ignoraunce, the aduersarie and sworne enimie of vnderstanding: so that, from the communicating of this necessarie labour, a double benefite doth spring: namely, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure and profite: pleasure to the learned, whome if I had not made partakers of the same, I had shewed my selfe imurious: and profite to the vnlearned▪ to whome if I had denied the fruite of this my trauèll, they might well thinke and take me to be hatefull and enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous▪ Beeing carefull therefore of the one, and not negligent of the other, I am well content, that the commoditie of my labour, (which the learned lead by integritie and vprightnesse of iudgement, can but allowe▪ and the vnlearned, by cause on the vse thereof, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the increase of their knowledge, must needes commend: for that which is honest and also pleasant, who is so mad as to mislike: and that thing from whence profite proceedeth, who is so witlesse as to contemne?) should be common. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suading my selfe therefore indifferen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ly of both, I will touche in breuitie, the benefites that issue from this booke. As it is not for a naked and vnarmed souldier▪ to encoūter his enimie being harnessed at all pointes, and to the proofe prouided, except his intent be, wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to incurre daunger of violence: so it is not for any m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n, to tye the vse of his penne, to the vanities of his owne imagination, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly be preposterous &amp; carelesse in keeping order; vnlesse his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning be▪ of set purpose, to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>pe reprehension for his securitie and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence▪
<pb facs="6"/>
Hee therefore that is to play the part of a warriour, ought with his force and valliauntnesse, to ioyne substantiall furniture, that the seruice of his naturall abilities, and the vse of his instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall powers, may concurre and goe together, making him the more venturous to withstand his enimies assault, and fuller of force also to giue him the discomfiture. So he in like manner, (that I may rather shew my selfe a Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>curialist, then a Martialist: for I haue not to deale with war, nor yet with warlike weapons, otherwise then by way of application.) that loueth orderly to indite, &amp; plausi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to occupie his penne, in deuising and disposing as well both meete matter, as also fit wordes, in any kinde of letter, (for of letters <note n="*" place="margin">Exhortato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Accusato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Interces<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>o rie, Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datorie, Excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>atorie, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulatorie, Responsorie, Consolatorie, Criminatorie, Nunciatorie, Lamentatorie, Mandatorie, Laudatorie, Conuictorie, Obiurgatorie Interrogatori, Dehortatorie, &amp;c. reade Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, De episto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teribus.</note> there be sundrie sortes) must make meanes and prouision, for him selfe in this case, that those wantes and imperfections of Art &amp; cunning may be supplied. To such a one I giue counsel to passe &amp; repasse, to view &amp; reuiew, to take down and put on, to exercise and vse, such weapons as he shall finde in this our Panoplie or house of furniture, &amp; he shall feele him selfe in shor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> space, fenced and strengthened to the purpose, against ignoraunce that ougly monster of many heades, an enimie to order, and a friend to confusion. For, there shall be no kinde of letter, but in framing the same, thou shalt (though the gifts of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherewith thou art indued, be but weake and slender) haue knowledge, cunning, iudgement, and experience suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient: be the person to whō thou writest neuer so princely, neuer so learned, neuer so woorthy, neuer so noble, neuer so friendly, neuer so frowarde, neuer so gentle, neuer so angrie, neuer so vertuous, neuer so wicked, neuer so prudent, neuer so witlesse, neuer so heauie, neuer so ioyfull: finally, be his qualities of this kinde or that kinde, what so euer. So that, as the Physician, to heale many and sundrie maladies, wherewith his weake patients are infected, vseth many and sundrie sortes of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines: in like manner, to write formally to persons diuers in degree, thou haste here ready to serue thy turne, many presidents and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, not broched in the seller of myne owne braine, but drawne out of the most pure and cleare founteines of the finest and eloquentest Rhetoricians, that haue liued and flourished in all ages, euen from the verie first, that wonne fame by that noble facultie, to the laste
<pb facs="6"/>
whose names for the same cause, shall neuer weare out of memorie. What should I say more: <note n="*" place="margin">The varietie of methode in this Panoplie of Epistles.</note> wilt thou write grauely, wilt thou write wisely, wilt thou write sweetely, wilt thou write smoothly, wilt thou write harshly, wilt thou write darkly, wilt thou write gladly, wilt thou write sadly, wilt thou write largely, wilt thou write briefly, wilt thou write lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly, wilt thou write angerly? wilt thou complaine, wilt thou accuse, wilt thou rebuke, wilt thou commend, wilt thou threaten, wilt thou pardon, wilt thou displease, wilt thou reconcile, wilt thou commaunde, wilt thou intreate? what so euer thou art disposed to do by letter, eyther to thy friend, or to thine enimie, thou hast this Panoplie to guide thy head in deuising, and thy penne in disposing. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, many, and (in manner) innumerable are the benefites which this booke bringeth, which we wish no lesse profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thee the Reader, then it was pleasaunt to me the gatherer &amp; translator. Fare you well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine for thy benefite. Abraham Flemming.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>