<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST MIGHTY MONARCH, MY MOST GRATIOVS SOVE∣RAIGNE LORD, IAMES KING OF GREAT BRITAINE, FRANCE, AND IRELAND, DEFENDER OF THE FAITH, &amp;c. GRACE AND PEACE, WITH ALL INCREASE AND CONTI∣NVANCE OF HAPPY AND ROIALL STATE FROM GOD THE FATHER IN OVR LORD JESVS CHRIST. THE KING OF KINGS AND LORD OF LORDS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102414_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68061</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11149.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102414</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST MIGHTY MONARCH, MY MOST GRATIOVS SOVE∣RAIGNE LORD, IAMES KING OF GREAT BRITAINE, FRANCE, AND IRELAND, DEFENDER OF THE FAITH, &amp;c. GRACE AND PEACE, WITH ALL INCREASE AND CONTI∣NVANCE OF HAPPY AND ROIALL STATE FROM GOD THE FATHER IN OVR LORD JESVS CHRIST. THE KING OF KINGS AND LORD OF LORDS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exquisite commentarie vpon the Reuelation of Saint Iohn : VVherein, both the course of the whole booke, as also the more abstruse and hard places thereof not heretofore opened; are now at last most cleerely and euidently explaned. By Patrik Forbes of Corse</title>
                 <author>Forbes, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hall, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Burton, Francis</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 248, 20 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST MIGHTY MONARCH, MY MOST GRATIOVS SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGNE LORD, IAMES KING OF GREAT BRITAINE, FRANCE, AND IRELAND, DEFENDER OF THE FAITH, &amp;c. GRACE AND <hi>PEACE, WITH ALL INCREASE AND CONTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVANCE</hi> OF HAPPY AND ROIALL STATE FROM GOD THE FATHER IN OVR LORD JESVS CHRIST. THE KING OF KINGS <hi>AND LORD OF LORDS.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or a token, though</hi> poore in my part; yet that gratefullie I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> Princely mind, in keeping mee an eare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst sinistrous delati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and giuing so gentle warning of your good pleasure therein, this part of my misreported paines, I humbly present vnto
<pb facs="3"/>
your <hi>Maiestie:</hi> to whose Souer aigne skill in these diuine secrets, (by your royall writings well wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessed to the world) besides common allegeance, all pens, and of all men imploied on this Prophecie, owe proper homage: as not only to the most glorious patrocinie, but therewith also the most learned cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. In both which, I doe yet more relye on your Maiesties experienced benignitie, then I presume either of merit for the one, or sufficiencie against the other. I know the too iust complaint of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest, vpon the great abuse of that excellent gift of printing, both to the disgrace and detriment of learning, while (each man dotting after the brood of his owne braine, and vainly promising to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self the same applause of others, which his own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall heart yeeldeth him) <hi>no end is of making many books:</hi> so as the inexpert student, in search of letters weilding amidst infinite variety, is cast in such doubt of choise, that, tasting about, before he happilie fall on oughtworthy to feed on, appetite is spent, and he filled with he cannot tell what. I know also that as it was not permitted each Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to practise his skill on the roiall Effigie of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> so were it intollerable presumption for
<pb facs="3"/>
each Pamphlet to vsurpe the shadow of your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse Name. Neither hath selfe-weining so ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siled mine eies from the sight of mine own slender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, but that sincerely I acknowledge, in this so learned an age wherein much is excellently well written, and yet infinitely more paper miserably spoiled, that hundreths more gifted then I, might well be pardoned to put vp their pennes, and, so, much lesse to currie credit to their vnsutable works, by shrowding them vnder the shelter of so sacred a vaile: yet how great soeuer be my impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to so high attempt, the subiect of this my labor is of such a surpassing eminency, as, if it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God onelie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wise by my weakenesse to bring forth any one sparkle of new and true light for more cleare vnderstanding thereof (wherein, for ought that hithertils hath been said of any, the most learned yet acknowledge an vntried depth of which anie one point opened may bee a competent recompence of much paines) I hope it shall some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what excuse me of too great temerity, either in writing or in vowing, what I write, so highlie: and shall heerewithall encourage the better gifted soberlie to search out what heerein hath escaped
<pb facs="4"/>
me also. Now heereof as your Maiestie can best of all men iudge, so am I the bolder to vndergoe the hazard of so high a sentence, for that of your Maiesties knowne clemence I am certaine to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port either praise or pardon.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties <hi>humble Subiect</hi> PATRIK FORBES <hi>of Corse.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>