<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>PREFACE OF THE AUTHOR, TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102457_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01038</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11142</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102457</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>PREFACE OF THE AUTHOR, TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A peaceable vvarning, to the subjects in Scotland : given in the yeare of God 1638</title>
                 <author>Forbes, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Aberdeen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="5" facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>PREFACE OF THE AUTHOR, TO THE CHRISTIAN</hi> READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N some Few written Copies of the first sudden draught of this <hi>WARNING,</hi> before it was perfected, some haske speaches were found, and haue beene verie hasklie interpreted. I loue not to bee offensiue to anie; and I doe playnlie and openlie disallow all other Copies, and holde to this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perfect Edition, in a meeke and calme stile: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching my de we Countrey-men, to pardon what was amisse in anie Copie, or what perhaps may bee yet amisse in this first publicke and onlie true Edition; which I doe presens vnto them, with a loving and peaceable heart, ayming onlie at Trueth and Peace.
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
And let not anie exception agaynst anie weaknesse of the <hi>Warner,</hi> hinder them from vnpartiall conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Warning</hi> it selfe. The Apostle hath tolde vs, that <hi>the wrath of man, worketh not</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 20.</note>
      <hi>the rigteousnesse of GOD.</hi> Therefore, let vs all laye asyde wrath, and bring our best concurrance to cure this miserable division, and in all singlenesse and humblenesse of mynde, contribute therevnto the best overtures which it shall please GOD to put into our hearts, if possibly this fearfull rupture may be solidlie and peaceablie remedied. Which to obtayne, let vs all search and trye our wayes, and turne agayne to the LORD. Let vs lift vp our heart with our handes vnto GOD in the Heavens. Now, the <note place="margin">Lam. 3. 40.</note> LORD GOD of Trueth and Peace, who hath tolde vs by His holie Prophet, That Hee will restore <note place="margin">Ierē. 30.</note> Health vnto His CHVRCH, even when Her sore is vncurable, bind vp this breach, which is great lyke <note place="margin">Lam. 2. 13.</note> the Sea: But GOD dryeth the Sea, and to Him all thinges are possible. Blessed bee the LORD. His Grace bee with thee, that thou mayest loue Trueth and Peace.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>
         <hi>Augustinus Epist. 7. ad Marcellinum.</hi>
      </bibl>
      <q>Ego fateor, me ex eorum numero esse conari, qui pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiendo scribunt, &amp; scribendo proficiunt.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>