<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Translator to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102710_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14882</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25185</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102710</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Translator to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A compendious chyrurgerie: gathered, &amp; translated (especially) out of Wecker, at the request of certaine, but encreased and enlightened with certaine annotations, resolutions &amp; supplyes, not impertinent to this treatise, nor vnprofitable to the reader: published for the benefite of all his countreymen, by Ihon Banester maister in chyrurgerie</title>
                 <author>Wecker, Johann Jacob</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 <publisher>Harrison (Harison), John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 530, 10 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Translator to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F two thinges (as it seemeth to mee) the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will require a reckoning at my handes: in both which like<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ise, I am readie to render mine accountes. Of the one, as by the waye of talke and treatie: of the other (as more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant) necessarily. The first is, why I lab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ured in this translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the other, why I haue in this sort brought it f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orth. To the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>irst I protest, it was vndertaken by the earnest re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uest, and importunitie of such friends, as I, in no wise was able therin to resist: my self being, though not vnwilling to doe good, yet vnwilling at this time, to haue
<pb facs="6"/>
vndergone such a burthen. Of this sort perfourming it, my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons thus I render. And first for setting that downe, in a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed tenor of stile (but sorted into Chapters) which standeth in diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions and tables in the Author, whence I haue it: The occasion was in the mouers of this transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ion, who made that choyse for the benefite of the greater number: for that (as they said truely) fewe Chirurgians otherwise could vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande, that they should reade therein. Thus when I had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed a space in the traslation, and founde that parte of <hi>Wecker</hi> committed vnto mee, defectiue in many points, pertaining hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o, I thought good (that this worke might be the fuller) partly from other his bookes, partly from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ost approued Authors, olde
<pb facs="6"/>
and newe, (in this point, taking to my selfe some larger libertie) to supplye that wanted. In which doing I haue neither so curiously take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vpon mee, to prosecute eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie point, as that no perticuler shoulde bee wanting, that might come in question in this arte: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet (I trust) so loosely labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as that manie things of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, shalbe founde to haue ouerslip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped me. From whence, an equall minde may see, I haue aymed both at comelines and profit. And ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I iudge him of too mean capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, for this calling, that cannot, by the light of these things, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede into further particulers, when neede requireth. For the cataractes and manuall admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations about the eyes, I referre the Reader to a treatise of olde <hi>Penemicus,</hi> inserted and lately
<pb facs="7"/>
published in <hi>Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ip Barroughes</hi> booke. The french disease needeth a particuler treatise: which wee shall see (I doubt not) in all parts accomplished by master <hi>Clowes</hi> our countriman, who hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to not vnfrutefully labou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed in it. Thus much for the Supplies. In my resolutions, I haue giuen some addresse to the Reader in things, otherwise (perhaps) not so perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous. My Annotati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ns are both to giue light to the vnderstanding of the texte, to furnish further with medicines where I thought it needefull, &amp; to preserue sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of doctrine, where I sawe it not ynough regarded. And let no man here saye, I goe beyonde the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>chet: but rather with iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and an vpright eye, weigh, and consider the things I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended togither with the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
<pb facs="7"/>
annexed thereunto. For I protest, there is nothing on the earth, hath carried mee into this course saue onely, a iust and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest care of the readers commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. As for that learned man <hi>Wecker,</hi> if I haue any where ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rested his meaning, vnreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently taken him, or censured him without cause, then is there wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I should iustly be blamed for him. But if in all these things, I haue caried my selfe in a reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble course, let not that be imputed to mee for a fault, which is (if I could deserue any) my commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. Neither can any man greatly marueile, that so much vnsoundnesse shoulde be founde in <hi>Wecker,</hi> considering that (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in the preparation of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines) he hath too much tyed him selfe to antiquitie. I found cause
<pb facs="8"/>
ynough likewise, to haue dealt with his methode, but leauing that to the censure of <hi>D. Brights</hi> arte, (a worke of more learning &amp; iudgement, than manie will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse) I content my selfe, in this treatise, to haue looked on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y to the matter: and therein to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, to my power, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full patient reape not the bitter fruites of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>