<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102319_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15975</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2734</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102319</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>All the French Psalm tunes with English words : Being a collection of Psalms accorded to the verses and tunes generally vsed in the Reformed churches of France and Germany. Perused and approved by judicious divines, both English and French</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Standish, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>—English Stock</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 264 pages, music, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He remarkable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of many Languages to the French in their Psalmody or Psalm tunes and verses, hath appeared so gracious and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine (in regard no humane power commanded them thereunto) that it hath affected many of our Nation with wonder and emulation; Inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that some Personages of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent quality and fame, haue not only desired, but also endeuored that those so celebrated tunes might bee sung with English words, and that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish people in French or Dutch
<pb facs="4"/> Cities or Families might sing En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Psalms in those tunes which they vse among whom they liue. To this &amp; other purposes all the Psalms of <hi>Dauid</hi> are composed with all care and diligence, principally to expresse the genuine sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> of the originall He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew text, as near as might be attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto, by the help of the best Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positers, without respect to any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie which hath bin, or is now in agitation. As also that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be alike disposed of in euery cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plet, staue or line agreeable to the French. In euery verse (which are of as many kindes, almost, as the tunes) is obserued the same accent in the beginning, continuance, and end of the line. Note that some long lines should be set in two, and accordingly accented in reading them. The reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancies are as many, so disposed; and so many of the same kinde, as in the
<pb facs="4"/> French, by which rimes (and in some Psalms by Alphabeticall letters) the lines and staves are knit together for better help of memory. The seuerall kindes of tunes being in number a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>124,</hi> and formerly expressed in <hi>6</hi> systems or cliffs, are now reduced into <hi>2</hi> for more facility in learning them, and are placed, for the most part, where the Psalm is most in sight. Other obseruations for breuity are omitted. To conclude, it is wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that not any Christian would spend their leisure worse then in singing these or such like Psalms, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we all together in heauen sing praise to the Eternall, to whom bee all honor, thanksgiuing and glory for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>