<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102829_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01466</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11592</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102829</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An explicatio [n] and assertion of the true catholique fayth, touchyng the moost blessed sacrament of the aulter : with confutacion of a booke written agaynst the same. Made by Steuen Byshop of Wynchester, and exhibited by his owne hande for his defence to the Kynges maiesties commissioners at Lambeth</title>
                 <author>Gardiner, Stephen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 <publisher>Caly, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Caly, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 152 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶The preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or asmuch as amōges other mine allegations for defence of my selfe in this matter, moued agàynst me by occasion of my Sermon made before the kynges moost excellent Maiestye, touchyng partely the. Catholique faith of the moost precious sacramēt of thal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, which I see now impugned, by a booke set furth, vnder the name of my lord of Caun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torburies grace: I haue thought expediēt for the better opening of the matter, &amp; cōsideryng I am by name touched in the sayde boke, the rather to vtter partely that I haue to say by confutatiō of that boke, wherein I thinke ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerthlesse no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> requisite to directe any speache by speciall name to the person of him that is entitled autor, because it may possible be that his name is abused, wherwith to set furth the matter, beyng him selfe of such dignitie &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorite in the cōmen welth, as for that respect should be inuiolable. For which cōsideracion, I shal in my speache of suche reproufe as the vntruth of the matter necessariely requireth, omitting the speciall title of the auctor of the boke, speake onely of thauctor in generall, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng a thing to me greatly to be me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>ed at, that such matter shuld nowe be published out of my lord of Cātorburies penne, but because he is a man, I wil not wondre, &amp; because he is such a mā, I will reuerērly vse him, &amp; forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng further to name him, talke onely of the auctor by that generall name.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>