<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To The Reader.</title>
           <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102090_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14435</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24753</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102090</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To The Reader.</title>
                 <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A very Christian, learned, and briefe discourse, concerning the true, ancient, and Catholicke faith, against all wicked vp-start heresies : seruing very profitably for a preseruatiue against the profane nouelties of papists, Anabaptists, Arrians, Brownists, and all other sectaries. First composed by Vincentius Lirinensis in Latine, about twelue hundreth yeares ago. And now faithfully translated into English, and illustrated with certaine marginall notes. By Thomas Tuke</title>
                 <author>Vincent, of Lérins, Saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Becket, Leonard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 71, that is 83 leaves, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To The Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE are three sorts of men, for whō I haue trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated this little booke. The first are they, that heare their fathers instruction, and despise not the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their mother: whom I desire God vpon my knees to keepe free from the poyson, and peruersnesse of all Heretickes, and Schismatickes whatsoeuer. The second are they, that are mis-led by <hi>Romish</hi> Impostors into many grosse and nouell er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,
<pb facs="8"/>
such as the Scriptures and antient Doctors vtterly condemne, as may easily be seene by viewing sundry workes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers learned men amongst vs, either written, or turned into <hi>English.</hi> The chiefest cause of of whose erring, partly consists in an incredible credit, which they giue vnto their Teachers, and partly in their owne won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ignorance of the holy Scriptures, which might inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten their eies, and informe their iudgements. It is written of <hi>Naash,</hi> that he would make a couenant with the men of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>besh Gilead</hi> vpon condition <note place="margin">1. Sam. 11. 2.</note> that he might thrust out all their <hi>right eies:</hi> euen so surely the Diuell delights in nothing
<pb facs="8"/>
more, then in putting out mens eyes, and in captiuating their vnderstanding (which is as the <hi>right eye</hi> of the soule) that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blinded, he may leade them at his pleasure. But if it would please them to search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <note place="margin">Iohn. 5. 39.</note> (as Christ exhorteth) and to consider of the Catholicke do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the antient Church e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the times, wherein this our Author liued, I doubt not, but that the scales of ignorance would fall from their eyes, and that those mists would be soone dispersed, which Satan casts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. The third are such, as are not much offended at the doctrines of the Church, but condemne her gouernment, and stumble at her Ceremonies,
<pb facs="9"/>
which yet are neither vndecent, nor superstitious, or numerous, and such as neither Gods word forbiddeth, nor any approued Church in the Christian world condemneth, <hi>as they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by this Church, &amp; entertained.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now see heere what strange conceipts and doctrines are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised, and defended of them, such as haue no foot-step in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> no fellowship with <hi>Antiquity, 1.</hi> It is affirmed that <hi>The true and right go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Christian Churches is a certaine De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocratie. 2.</hi> That a prouinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Church is <hi>Contrary</hi> to the testament of <hi>Christ.</hi> Hereupon <hi>Henry Iacob</hi> in an Epistle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed
<pb facs="9"/>
to a booke lately printed at <hi>Leyden,</hi> labours for a <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 3.</hi> That humane ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies being once abused, cannot bee purged but by vtter aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion. <hi>4.</hi> That <note n="o" place="margin">Indeede Christ lay at the Pass. but that he did so at the last Supper, the Scripture sayes not.</note> it is out of all doubt, that Christ sate or lay at his last Supper: or thus, that it is not only possible or probable, but <hi>certaine</hi> that he vsed a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gesture at that his last Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. <hi>5.</hi> That because <hi>Christ</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed a table gesture; therefore it is vnlawfull for vs to vse any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a table gesture. <hi>6</hi> That to receiue the bread and wine kneeling is vnlawfull, is <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Kneeling at Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, as it is required of the Church of England, lawfull.</note> Which me thinkes is very strange. For what is the <hi>Idoll?</hi> wee kneele not vnto the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but vnto God, in testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb facs="10"/>
of reuerence and humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of spirit. Secondly if wee <hi>Must</hi> receiue the Sacrament with reuerence and humility of heart (as who dare gainsay?) thē vndoubtedly wee <hi>May</hi> receiue it with a reuerend and humble gesture. Thirdly, if our kneeling be idolatry, then are wee idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (as if oppression bee theft, and oppressors are <hi>Theeues:</hi> if to take the <hi>Cure</hi> of soules, and to take no <hi>Care</hi> of soules be murder, then they, that take the <hi>Cure</hi> of soules, and take no <hi>Care</hi> of soules are <hi>Murderers)</hi> yea and <hi>resolute</hi> Idolaters: for we do not onely kneele, but stand to defend it, and we practise it daily, yea and charge them with ignorance that do condemne it
<pb facs="10"/>
as vnlawful. Now what wil fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low? If we be idolaters, then they must not eate with vs. <hi>If any,</hi> (saith S. <hi>Paul) that is called</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 5, 11.</note>
      <hi>a brother, bee an Idolater, with such one eate not.</hi> And againe, If wee be Idolaters, how dare they communicate with vs? What? with Idolaters? Either therefore these conceits must be for saken, or else I see not how wee can but swarme with <hi>Iacobites.</hi> But I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded better things of many of them: such as accompany <hi>Saluation,</hi> and tend not to <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. A. Fuluius</hi> once sayd to his sonne: <note n="*" place="margin">Ego te non Catilmae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersus patriā, sed patriae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer sus Cauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam gonui.</note>
      <hi>I begat thee not for Catiline against thy Country, but for thy Country against Catiline:</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
so may I say, they were not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by the Gospel, for <hi>Iohn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> for <hi>Iacob,</hi> for any turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and phantasticke Doctor against the Church, but for the Church against them. And be they well assured that this sleight stuffe will shrinke when it comes to wetting, this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit coine will not indure tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. The greatnesse of men, their learning, their godlinesse, are no arguments to moue vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their owne conceipts for doctrines. No, an Angell must not be heard against the truth. But mee thinkes I heare some <note place="margin">Quest.</note> man say, How may I be resolued in this difference of opinions? what shall I doe to finde out the truth? I answer. First giue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent <note place="margin">An.</note>
      <pb facs="11"/>
care to the voyce of God in the Scriptures: what it saith, that receiue, though it crosse thee neuer so much, and where it hath no tongue, haue thou no care. Do not first entertaine a conceit, and then look out Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to draw it by the haire to thee. Secondly, be not ouercari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any preiudicate opinion of thine <hi>Opposite:</hi> neither let the reuerend conceit of thy Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, that hath taught thee such a doctrine, couer thine eye from beholding reason: and do not thinke that, because hee is a good man, therefore all must needes bee good, that hee hath taught thee; or that his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are sounder thē another mans, because his life is better.
<pb facs="12"/>
Thirdly, be not proud, or <hi>selfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceited,</hi> For <note n="*" place="margin">Iam. 4. 6.</note>
      <hi>God resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth the proud.</hi> God and Pride (saith <hi>Bernard)</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dwell together in the same heart, which could not dwell in the same heauen. And the History of the Church sheweth that <hi>Arrius</hi> of very pride fell into wicked and open heresie. But the Lord <note n="*" place="margin">1. Pet 5. 5. Psal. 25. 9.</note> giueth grace to the humble, and teacheth him his way. <hi>If yee aske</hi> (saith <hi>Augustine) what is the first step in the way of truth? I answer Humility. If yee aske what is the second? I say Humility, If yee aske, what is the third? I say the same, Humility.</hi> fourthly, pray earnestly with <hi>Dauid</hi> that
<pb facs="12"/>
God would bee pleased to <note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 119. 34. 66.</note>
      <hi>Giue thee vnderstanding, and to teach thee good indgement and knowledge.</hi> Finally, bee not easily perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to beleeue Doctrines speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally against the vnanimous consent of a true Church, which neither the ancient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, neither are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any present <hi>approoued</hi> Church, but are the conceipts of some particular persons. In one word, I pray thee diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to read this <hi>Treatise</hi> ouer. For it teacheth how to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the faith, against all the fraudes and fallacies of Imposters. It is not great, but good: learned, though but litle: and as sweete to them,
<pb facs="13"/>
that are intelligent, as short. The Lord blesse it to thee, and giue thee an vnderstanding head, and an obedient heart.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>April. 14. 1611.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thine in Christ,
THOMAS TVKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>