<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the righte honora∣ble, sir Nicholas Bacon knight Lord keper of the great Seale of Eng∣lande, and one of the Queenes most honorable priuye Counsayle, Iohn Veron wys∣sheth grace, peace of conscience, and increase of godlye ho∣nour, from god the father, throughe hys son Ie∣su Christ oure Lorde.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1562</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102670_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14368</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24686</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102670</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the righte honora∣ble, sir Nicholas Bacon knight Lord keper of the great Seale of Eng∣lande, and one of the Queenes most honorable priuye Counsayle, Iohn Veron wys∣sheth grace, peace of conscience, and increase of godlye ho∣nour, from god the father, throughe hys son Ie∣su Christ oure Lorde.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A stronge battery : against the idolatrous inuocation of the dead saintes, and against the hauyng or setting vp of images in the house of prayer, or in any other place where there is any paril of idolatrye, made dialoguewise by Iohn Veron</title>
                 <author>Véron, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1562</date>
                 <publisher>Hacket, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sutton, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 71, 70-108, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the righte honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, sir Nicholas Bacon knight Lord keper of the great Seale of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and one of the Queenes most honorable priuye Counsayle, Iohn Veron wys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth grace, peace of conscience, and increase of godlye ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, from god the father, throughe hys son Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su Christ oure Lorde.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome be of this opiniō, right honorable sir, that those thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges that bee in controuersie, betwixt vs &amp; the Catholikes are not of so greate weighte and importaunce that wee ought therfore to stirre vp suche tragedies, or make so muche a doe, syth that they confesse one true lyuinge God with vs, and his sonne Iesu Christe,<note place="margin">The commō complaintes of many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> do alowe the scriptures of the old and new testament, and all the articles of our beleue: But yf al thinges be considered a right, and wayed with the euen balaunce of gods worde, it shalbe easie for any man to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande that it is not without a iuste cause that we do bothe dissente from them, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>so moste earnestly impugne their pernitious and damnable doctrine: and al their abhominable
<pb facs="3"/> erroures and diuel she opinions. For first and foremost,<note place="margin">They do not confesse god which do not confesse him as he do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth reueale himself in his worde.</note> it can not iustly be sayde, that they do confesse the onely true liuing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>od, sith that they do not confesse him as he doeth setforth and reueale him selfe in his holye and sacred word, but do so cōfesse him, that thei do make of him a plaine e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dole Herin then do we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from them: that we do acknowledge and confesse him, as he doeth reueale himself vnto v in his holy &amp; sacred word where he fetteth forth him self vnto vs an omnisufficient god, and in whom only we ought to seke all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of thinges that are necessarye both for our bodyes and soules.<note place="margin">Psa. 89</note> The heauens are thine (say the scriptures) the earth also is thine,<note place="margin">Psal cxlv.</note> thou haste layed the foundacion of the world, and all that therein is:<note place="margin">How god re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueleth hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in his word.</note> all the kingedomes of the earth are thine. And thy kingome is an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastinge kingdome, and thy dominion endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth throughout all ages. Thou fittest on the rounde bale or circle of the earthe, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes of it are as Locustes in thy sight. Thou makest to stande, and doest putte to flight. And onlesse thou kepest the citye, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> watcheth in vaine, that doth kepe it. Al coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayles and helpes are from thee. But do not ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> aduersaries most sacrilegiouslye,<note place="margin">The sacrilege of the aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>saries.</note> robbing go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of his glorye, attribute al those thinges to hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> dead creatures, I mean, to those that be already
<pb facs="3"/> departed out of this worlde? what haue they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eft vnto god? what help what aid and succour that they haue nede of, doe they not craue at the deade: handes? The Frenche men in their perillous warres and battayles, do rather cal v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Saint Denyle, than vpon the mightye Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h, the lorde god of hoostes.<note place="margin">Saint denis of Fraunce Saint George of England. S. Andrew of Scottland. Saint Iames of Callycia.</note> The Englysh men had in stede of god Mars, whom the heathen worshipped for the god of Battailes, that lustre knight Saint George of Cappado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia. The Scotes, their Saint Andrew. The Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niardes and Gallycians, haue yet at this houre their holy Saint Iames, whom they do rather call vpon, then vppon the eternall and euerly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing god, in their moste perillous affayres. They that trauaile by the Sea, haue in stede of Castor and Pollux, their Saint Nicholas,<note place="margin">The gods of idolatrous Marinets.</note> vnto whome they ioygne fo a felowe helper that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itle pretye one Sainct Christophore, who by their description maye bee likened vnto that mounstruous Poliphemus, which Virgill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth speake of. Do they not worshippe Saint Valesiane (as they do communely call him) as the heathen had in times paste woorshipped their Acolus,<note place="margin">Valesian.</note> whom Iupiter had appointed to be king &amp; ruler of stormes and tempestes? For they persuade them selues,<note place="margin">Acolus.</note> that if they do dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently worship him, he wil kepe of the haile from their corne, and from al other fruites of
<pb facs="4"/> the earthe, he will cease the ragiouse windes, and appease the tempestes. Some other do at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute this office vnto Iohn and Paul.<note place="margin">Iohn &amp; Paul.</note> Saint A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gathe must se their houses to be preserued frō fire.<note place="margin">Saint Agathe</note> And therfore when there is any ieopardy of fire they do rather call vpon her, than vpon him that hath all his creatures at his beck and commaundement. But bicause she is a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and therefore frayle and timorous,<note place="margin">Saint Flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian.</note> they haue associated vnto her saint Florinian, who being in complet harneyse, doeth hold a paile for to cast water vpon the fier, for to quenche the burninge?<note place="margin">Sebastian &amp; Rocke do heale the pes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilence and potches.</note> when god doeth by his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgement punish the world with pes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilence haue they not their Saint Sebastian? And when they be smyttē with botches sores and boyles haue they not their Saint Rocke? more trust haue they in those dead creatures, of whō we do doubt whether they be in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen or not, than they haue in the liuyng god, the on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly autour of al health both of body &amp; soule in their agues and seuers saint Petronil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le.<note place="margin">Petronille. Peters daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter.</note> Peters daughter must be their phisition. And no maru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>le. For▪ when our Sauiour Iesus Christ did heale her grand dame, she cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in vnawares did learne the arte of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cin.<note place="margin">Appoleyne Otilia.</note> Touthlesse Appoleyne must helpe the touth ache▪ as blynd Otilia bearinge her eyes vpon her booke, being sallen out of her head▪
<pb facs="4"/> must help sore eyes. To be short, they haue for all the partes of the body certain appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Saints, as they haue for euery kind of cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel. Which thing they would not do, if they did confesse and acknowledge god, as he doth reueale himself in the scriptures. For,<note place="margin">Deut. vi.</note> there we learn, that the Lord our god, is one God: That he doth al things with his diuine prouidēce, and that as all thinges, are of him by him and in him, so he is the onely autour of lyfe and deathe, of rychesse and pouerty, of wisedome and foolyshnes, of health and sickenes. And sith that we are bothe hys creatures and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, and do owe our selues whollye both body &amp; soule vnto him:<note place="margin">How god ought to bee confessed.</note> is it not against al rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, that we should turne out selues from the creatour vnto the creatures? The heathen do the same. But we ought to be Christians, and to cleaue onelye to Christe, and by him to be made one with the father. If the saintes do all thinges, yf they haue the gouernement, tuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on defense &amp; protection of cities and townes, if the standing manfullye in battaile, the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng awaye, and victory, if the curinge of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, if the benefit of health be in their hāds, if they haue power ouer the windes stormes &amp; tempestes, if they possesse al the lymmes of a mannes body, what doth god in the meane while? Where is his diuyne prouidence? will
<pb facs="5"/> they say that god being wearye, doeth cōmit the gouernement of his creatures vnto other? But no suche infirmities is god subiect vnto. It is euident and pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne then, right honorable sir, that they doe make of him a plaine Idole, yea they make of him no god at all. For take his diuine prouidēce away or make him sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to any infirmities, and then he is no god. It is farre otherwise with vs.<note place="margin">Howe the faithful do confesse god.</note> For beinge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed by the scriptures and worde of god, we do wholly depend vpon his fatherly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, vsing with most harty thankefulnes, all those lawful meanes that he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ordeyned for vs, and so gyue him onelye the whole glorye of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of al thinges, for the commoditye and profit of his chosen and electe people.<note place="margin">A denial of god.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: is not this a denial of god, to go aboute to worshippe and serue him otherwise then he himself doeth appoint, and prescribe in his holy and sacred word? Socrates being an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,<note place="margin">Socrates</note> doeth plainlye say, that in religion it is requir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d, that euery god be worshipped after his own wil, and not after the wil of his wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shippers. If this did take place in false religiō, howe muche more ought it to take place in true religion? I meane in that religion, that god hath set fourth vnto vs by his eternal and euerlasting wisedome?<note place="margin">Deut. xii</note> These are his wordes:
<pb facs="5"/> Ye shal not do euery man that thing that see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto you best. I am the Lorde my god, that thing only, that I commaunde thee, se that thou doest it add nothing vnto it, and minish nothing from it. Again:<note place="margin">Math xv</note> They worship me in vaine teaching the doctrines and preceptes of men. But howe wel these thinges haue bene and are obserued of our frends the catholikes, let your honour be iudge. Those wayes that god wilbe worshipped and serued, they haue stoutly contemned, &amp; chose eueri day straunge kindes of worshipping and seruice, which the Lord doeth not once mencion of in the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. This then is an other differēce betwixt them and vs,<note place="margin">How the god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y do worship god</note> that we will haue god to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured worshipped and serued, accordinge to his worde, and as he himselfe doeth appointe and prescribe in his sacred scriptures, submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our selues wholy, our wit and reason, &amp; al the wisdome that can be in vs, vnto his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sercheable wisdome and cōtenting our selues with that fourme and maner of religyon, that he hath sett fourthe vnto vs by his sonne Iesu Christ, whom he hath appointed, by his holy spirit to be the only teacher &amp; scholemaster of his church,<note place="margin">Mat. xvii</note> we do study &amp; labour to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of our power &amp; with al due submission and obedience, to kepe our selues within the limites and boundes, of his prescribed rules &amp;
<pb facs="6"/> Canons, hauing alwayes this saying of Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell before our eyes:<note place="margin">Samu. xv</note> Hath the lord as great plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in burnt offeringes and sacrifices as when the voice of the Lord is obeyed? Behold to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beye is b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ter then sacrifice: and to hearken is better then the fatt of Rammes.<note place="margin">Mat xv.</note> Whereas they neglect nge g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>des commaundementes, that so they may set vp their owne traditions, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about moste vngodlye to sett the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of god to schoole do bring in, all maner of tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssh tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssh, shippes full of dombe and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly ceremonies, whiche they vrge with fire and sworde,<note place="margin">Wherin do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisterie outwarde worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of god</note> and maintain them, with al kinde o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> cruel t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nye. Whereby the externe and outward worshippinge of god whiche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth in the preaching of the doctrine and in the right and due ministration of the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes accordinge to the institution and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deynaunce of our sauiour Iesu Christe, and in the faythful prayers of the church, is clen ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olyshed and put downe.<note place="margin">Read the ouerthrow of the iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of workes for that.</note> Howe peryllous a thinge it is to attempte to serue god other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise than he himself doth appointe, it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sye to see in the x. Chapyt. of Leuiticus, and in the ij. booke of Samuel and syxt chapt. and in the .i. boke of Cronicles, &amp; xiii chapyter, well this is most sure and certain that they do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farre their wisedome before the wisdome of god▪ which is a playne denial of god. For yf
<pb facs="6"/> he be not of a perfect wysdome, he is no god. Againe, this that they do, is a manifest forsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the couenaunt of the lorde,<note place="margin">A forsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte of god. Howe the aduersaries do cōfesse christ Math. viii. What it is to confesse Christe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</note> as it may be proued by manye places of the scryptures: but specially by the xxij. chap. of Ieremy the Prophete. But now let vs come to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of our sauyour Iesu Christ. How do they confesse him, I pray you? Euen as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean spirytes did, who euery where acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledged him to be the sonn of god, the sonne of the highest. To confesse Christe a right, then, it is not onely to confesse him to be true and naturall god, equall and of one substaunce with the father, and to be true &amp; natural man equal and of one substaunce with vs, beyng in al thinges lyke vnto his bretherne, synne only excepted: But to confesse and acknowledge him, to be an omnisufficyent, and moste per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Sauiour of all those that beleaue in hys name, and put their whole trust in the mery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of his death passion and bloudsheddinge, and to be the onely mediatour betwixt God and men. For, therefore did he come,<note place="margin">Wherfore Christ came into the flesh. Ioa. iii. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>moth i Hel iu. vii. Actes. iiii.</note> and did take vpō him our fraile nature that destroiyng the works of the diuel, he should saue sinners, most perfectly and to the vttermost, I meane as manye as come vnto God by him, so that there is none other name vnder heauen geuen vnto men wherin we muste be saued, but the
<pb facs="7"/> name of our sauiour Iesu Christe. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is oure confession and beleue, that by the merites onelye of the death passion and bloodshedding of oure sauiour Iesu Christe, being apprehended and taken holde vpon by faythe, we obteyne full saluation, forgeuenes of our synnes, and deliueraunce from eternal, and euerlasting damnation. Whefore we do attryhute vnto him the whole glorye of the saluation of mankinde, acknoweledgynge hym, to be oure onelye mediatoure ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate and intercessour, accordinge to these scriptures: I am the waye, the trueth, and the life▪<note place="margin">Iohn. xiiii. Io. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>vi</note> no man cometh vnto the father but onely by me: Whatsoeuer ye aske my father in my name it shalbe geuen vnto you: It is Christe, which is deade yea,<note place="margin">Rom. viii.</note> rather whiche is risen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: who is also att the right hand of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and maketh intercession for vs: There is one god, and one mediatour betwixte god and man,<note place="margin">i. Timot. ii</note> which is the man Christ Iesus, who gaue himself a raunsome for all men the is able perfectly and sullye to saue theym that come vnto god by hym, syth that he euer ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to make intercession for them. Christe is not entred into the holy place,<note place="margin">Hebr. vii</note> which is made with handes, but in to heauen, there to appeare in the sight of god for vs.<note place="margin">Hebr. ix.</note> And againe: These thinges do I write vnto you,<note place="margin">i. Io. ii</note> that ye sinne not,
<pb facs="7"/> and if any man doeth sinne, we haue an aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the father, Iesu Christe the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.<note place="margin">Wherunto the aduersa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es do at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute their saluacion.</note> But as for our aduersaries without anye warrant of gods worde, yea, against all scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, they doe attribute the best parte of their saluation, to their owne merites, and to the workes of their own handes, yea, to such kind of works, as neuer were commaunded of god, and for asmuch as thei can not be of faith, they are mere sinnes in the sight of god, Is not this most blasphemous against the blood of christ, that they be wont to singe in their seruice? Tu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per Thomae sanguinem quem pro te impen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,<note place="margin">O plasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mination</note> fac nos Christe scandere, quo Thomas as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendit. That is: O Christ, do by the bloode of Thomas, which he spent for thee, make vs to ascende thether whither Thomas is ascended. But why shoulde I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e to tedious vnto youre honour, in rehersing many suche thinges, sith that all theyr bookes are full of such damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blasphemies? Doe they not attribute more vnto their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oly father the Pope,<note place="margin">More is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the pope than vnto our sauiour Iesu chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st.</note> than vnto our sauiour Iesu Christe? for they doe plainlye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that through fayth in our sauioure Iesu Christ we do onely obtain forgeuenes of the coulpe, fault, or giltines, but not of the pun sh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is due vnto vt for our sinnes. For that do they reserue to their holy father, who alone for a pece of money is able to geue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done
<pb facs="8"/> a poe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et culpa, that is of the punishe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of the fault. Yf this be not a denial of Christe, I can not well tell, what we maye call a denial of Christ for, therfore came he in to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>leshe that he might be our perfect and ful sauiour They then that denye hym to be a perfecte and full sauiour do deny him to be come into the fleshe,<note place="margin">i. Ioa. iiii.</note> and so by good right ought to be takē for Antichristes. I do here let passe that by their sacrilegious and damnable sacrifice of the masse,<note place="margin">The sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Christe is omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufficente and can be offered no more.</note> wherein they saye, they offer dailye oure sauoure Iesu Christe bothe god &amp; man they doe all that euer they can, to abolyshe annichilate and put downe the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cēt sacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fice of our sauiour Iesu Christ, which as it hath ben from the beginninge, is now and shalbe to the worldes end, of a most perfect efficacy vertue, strēgth &amp; power to saue al those that put their truste in it or take hold vppon it by faithe:<note place="margin">Heb. ix.</note> so can it not be reiterated or offered any more. For, Christ is not entred into verye heauen there to appeare in the sighte of god for vs, to the ende that he shoulde offer him self any more, for then he must haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed often lens the world began. He is that high priest that it became vs to haue, which being holye,<note place="margin">Heb. vii.</note> harmelesse, vndefiled, separated, from sinners, and made higher than the heauens, neded not daily, as those high priestes, to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="8"/> vppe sacrifice, first for his owne sinnes and then for the peoples: for that he did once, when he offered vp him self.<note place="margin">How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatoures the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries haue</note> How many me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatours haue they imagined and sourged vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them selues besides Christe the onely me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour betwixt god and man. So many as they doe imagine to be saintes in heauen, so many mediatours haue they sourged vnto thē selues, puttinge more confidence in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercession▪ wherof they haue no currentye or assuraunce at all in gods booke, than in the mediation of the onely begotten son of god. Which in so many places of the scriptures we are certified of, that onles we be worse then brute beastes, we ought to content ourselues <hi>w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      </hi> it, &amp; to seke no farther. Adde therūto,<note place="margin">To denye christ to be come into the fleshe.</note> that to acknoweledge more mediatoures besydes him, it is also to deny him to be come into the flesh. For, he dyd not only come into the flesh for to be our omnisufficient and most perfecte sauyour: but also for to be our only mediatour betwixt god and vs.<note place="margin">Howe the aduersaries do alow the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the old and newe testament.</note> And as for the scriptures of the old and new testament, yf they did frō the bottome of their hartes acknowledge thē to be the worde of god, then would they also confesse and acknoweledge that all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges partaynynge to saluation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>are conteined in the same. Whiche thing they will neuer do, lest their whole religion which cōsisteth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb facs="9"/> in mens traditions, and vain doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of diuels should be quite ouerthrowen.</p>
   <p>Nowe to deny that all thinges peretining to our saluation are comptised in the scriptures, It is to denye that they be the word of god yea they that do so,<note place="margin">They deny the holy ghost to be god that say that all things par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to saluation, are not conteyned in the scriptures.</note> do vtterly deny the holy ghoste by whole inspyratione the scryptures haue be a set fourth and wrytten, to be true and naturall god. For it is agaynst the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of god to make any worke of imperfectiō. But that all things pertaining to our saluation be not fully conteyned in the scryptures then are they a worke of imperfection, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the autour of them, which is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghost, is no true &amp; natural god Do thei not besides all this, assubiectize the scryptures &amp; worde of god to the vayne glosses, and found e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>positions of their holye father the Pope? so that although their exposityons be neuer so vngodly, neuer so contrary, to the true sense and meanyng of the holy spirit of god: yet we must receyue and alowe theym for curraunt money▪ except we wil fry a fagot. Euen after the same sorte, do they confesse the articles of our beleue, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>king what gloses they lust vpō thē, although it be nothing according to the analogie of fa th, from the which they do as fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re deferre, as the heauens are hyghe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the earth. It is then euidence and playne
<pb facs="9"/> that we do not withoute a iuste cause dissent from the Catholikes and so earnestlye im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne their damnable and wicked opinions. But nowe to come to our pourpose, here in thys my booke, I do mayntayne and defende agaynste theym, that god onelye in the tyme of oure trouble, ought to be called vppon and that therefore they that in their necessyty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es do by prayer flye vnto deade creatures, doe robb god of his glory, and do committ most damnable sacriledge which thing hath ben sufficientlye proued by manifest textes of the scriptures, and by strong authorityes of the auncient fathers of the primityue Church, all the obiections that the aduersaries can make beyng mightily auswered and confuted.<note place="margin">The hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> argumēt of the booke.</note> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly it hath bene plainely shewed, that we ought to acknowledge none other mediator betvvixte God and man, but oure sauiour Iesu Christ onely, whom the scriptures do appoint vnto vs for the omnisufficient sauiour of man kynde, and for our only intercessour aduocate and mediatour. Making no mention at all of the intercession or mediation of the dead fain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, which thing the holye ghost woulde not haue omitted, yf the saintes departed oute of this world, had bene either appointed or alow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed of god to be intercessours vnto god for vs.
<pb facs="10"/> Thirdly it hath ben declared, that as the saints that be already in glory with god ought in no wise to be called vpon, nor to be takē for our mediatours: so no godly honor ought to be ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uē vnto thē forasmuch as it is a seruice, which is only due vnto god. Wher I had an occasiō to shew how many ways the true &amp; faithfull ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uantes of god, being departed in the faith of his son Iesu Christ ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> be honored, &amp; that the greatest honor that we can do vnto them, is to obey their godly and sound doctrine, wherby they haue instructed vvin the true religion &amp; worshipping of the true liuing God, and also to folow their faith, and other heauenly ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, wherby they did glorifye God, whilest they lyued here in this worlde This also hath ben done by the infallible worde of god, &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies of the holy doctours of the true ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike churche, all the obiections of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries: as before beyng quite ouerthrowen by the same. Last of all it hath ben proued that no figure ymage or likenes of god, nor of his son Iesu Christ, nor of the holy ghost nor yet of the Saintes ought to be had in the house of praier, nor in any other place whersoeuer ther i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> any peryll of idolatry, and that there can be no vse of them in the Oratories or praying pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of the Christians▪ but rather that they doo most hurte whersoeuer they be vsed and kept
<pb facs="10"/> where by the waye I haue shewed, what is the true crosse, that we ought to embrace and haue a pleasure in, and that as for material cros<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ses they do more hurte, than good, &amp; that ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore for auoiding of offences they ought to be taken away. These are the chiefe and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall contente, of this booke, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch I do most humbly, and with all due submission de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate and offer vnto your good lordship desiring your honour to accept and take it in good part, which thing if ye do: it shall encorage me to attempte greater thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges▪ for the aduancemēt of gods glory▪ and for the edifieng of his churche.</p>
   <p>Thus the lorde god of hostes, the autour of all goodnes, vouchsafe to preserue your honour, my good lady your wife, and all your good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie and householde.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>