<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣shipful, syr VVilliam Cordell knight, Maister of the Queenes Maiesties Rolles &amp;c. health, wealth, and happi∣nesse euerlasting.</title>
           <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102286_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00941</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11049</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102286</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣shipful, syr VVilliam Cordell knight, Maister of the Queenes Maiesties Rolles &amp;c. health, wealth, and happi∣nesse euerlasting.</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A panoplie of epistles, or, a looking glasse for the vnlearned : Conteyning a perfecte plattforme of inditing letters of all sorts, to persons of al estates and degrees, as well our superiours, as also our equalls and inferiours: vsed of the best and the eloquentest rhetoricians that haue liued in all ages, and haue beene famous in that facultie. Gathered and translated out of Latine into English, by Abraham Flemming</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 <publisher>Middleton, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 448 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipful, syr VVilliam Cordell knight, <hi>Maister of the Queenes Maiesties</hi> Rolles &amp;c. health, wealth, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse euerlasting.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Assing of late (right worshipfull) thorough many a peece of land, pleasaunt in view and profitable▪ in vse, it was my happie chance to haue entrance into a goodly Gardene plott, which as it was large and of an exceding great compasse, so was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>t beautified with flowers of all sortes, both delightsome to the eye; in consider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>tion of their variable colours: and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the nose, in respecte of their excellent sweetenesse. And no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>uaile though this Garden plott were so goodly and so great: for, as in number they were (in manner) infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, which had recourse thereunto▪ so the <note n="*" place="margin">The names of those cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Garde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which did sett and sowe these flowers, are conteined in a Catalogue in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this booke not vn ceslarie to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> vnderstoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>▪</note> multitude of cunning and skilfull Gardeners, (whose most luckie handes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>owed the singular feedes, of which these fine flowers tooke roote in the ground, sproūg &amp; spread with leaues and blos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soms of glorious hewe) was innumerable. After I had sett my foote within the fen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>es of this riche and coastly Garden, (passing for pleasantnesse, &amp; excelling for largenesse, all the Gardens that are to be seene in this our age, albeit the heades of people were neuer so in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>entiue and curious, &amp; their hands at no t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>me so artificiall and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>▪) I sawe a footepathe
<pb facs="4"/>
before mee, not verie plaine to perceiue, because it was not much vsed and troden, yet not so ouergrowne with greene grasse, but that it might easily enough be seene: then pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing a space, as being in doubt to goe forward, considering the greatnesse of the Garden, the manifold corners, the croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked turnings, and the compassing arbours of the same, least by presuming to farre▪ I should loose my selfe, as it were in a Labyrinthe: and museing thus in minde, as burthened with vncertaintie, what were most auaylable for me to attempt, a soudeine cogitation concerning the present vse and benefite of this pleasant plott, ouercame me as it were with inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, insomuch that I, feeling in mee selfe no abilitie to withstand so forceable an assault, as one amased, leasurly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to foote it forward: anon, haueing gone a litle ground, mine eyes were fead with most delectable appearaunces, &amp; my nostrells with most comfortable sauours, so that there began to kindle in mee a certaine affection of ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and therewithal sprang, to the increase of my courage, a <note n="*" place="margin">Hope ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men har <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ie and ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ous.</note> hope of good happ after to insue: whereuppon I waxed venturous, and like a confident fellowe amended my pase, persuading my selfe, that in so heauenly a paradise there was no daunger, and alwayes as I did proceede, so new and fresh delights, were plentifully offered. Then, hauing called home my wandering witts, I weighed the worthines of the soile, which lay open and manifest in sight, and falling into an vn measurable loue &amp; liking of the same, for my further solace I walked too and fro, taking a viewe of the goodly woorke which was there to be seene, &amp; marking the great choice of flowers, as wel for their kinds, as also their colours: whiles I was thus occupied, a soudeine desire bred in mee, to take a tryal of those delights (though not of all, yet at least, of some, that my labour &amp; my longing might not be frustrate) which were before and round about mee on euery side: in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire there was such efficacie and force, that I was not able to resist the woorking of the same: whereuppon (for I percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the nature of it, and sawe wherewith it was to bee sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied,) I buckled my selfe to a newe kinde of buisinesse.
<pb facs="4"/>
For, <note n="*" place="margin">Pleasant ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes can not but comfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> and delight the sense<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>▪</note> whereas before, the sense of seeing was delighted, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> sense of smelling comforted, now the sense of feeling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnes to put in execution his office: and thus pleasure vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pleasure most plentifully is reaped. For, that whereon at first I fixed myne eye, and the sweetenesse whereof pierced into my nose, the same I am nowe bold to touch, to handle, to gather, and to beare away. Among many and sundrie sortes of flowres therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>, (the very woorst of all beeing of great vertue and value) such as in my fancie, bare the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest hewe and gallantest glosse, I gathered with a certaine greedinesse, esteeming highly of the opportunitie of the time, which was then presently ministred, and fearing least another should take my labour out of my hande: whiche caused me with so much the more speed (though hast, as the olde prouerb sayth, makes waste) to finish that which I had begunne. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> (right worshipfull) these fewe flowers, which I haue pickt and chosen from among many, (yea, myllians I may say, and not amisse) according to my homely handling (for where knowledge hath but a certain infancie, and where experience is very yong, what Art cā be shewed, what cunning can be declared?) I haue tyed vp together in a Garland, with course thred, for want of fine silke, placing each flower in suche order, as my skill gaue me leaue: and the same grosly bounde vp together, with their naturall stalkes and leaues, euen as they were hastily gathered out of outlandish gardens, (for, <hi>the most part of these flowers,</hi> and if I sayde in manner al, I were not to be accused of an vntru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>h, <hi>grewe in forreigne countries: as in</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">A particular rehearsall of a fewe goodly countries, wherein these flowers grewe and prospered</note>
      <hi>Mac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>donia, in Athens, in Miletum, in Thessal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>a, in Tarentum, in Sic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>lie, in Venice, in Padua in Rome, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, in Louane, and diuers other fruitfull soiles within the compasse of heauen: from farre were they fet, and therefore the more deintie.)</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to your person, confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, that in consideration of the gatherers vnskilfulnesse, it is nothing agreeable to your singular worthinesse: but yet in respect of the excellencie of the thing it selfe (for beeing examined and weighed with aduisement, it deserueth high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee had in estimation) beeing simply considered, it is
<pb facs="5"/>
most worthy of acceptation▪ Wherfore, if it shall pléase you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> a fauorable countenance, to receiue my po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>re present, which I acknowledge to be rusticall, but yet not deseruing refusall: (for in former ages of our auncients, the Goddes them selues, and the Goddesses also most gratious,</p>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <note n="*" place="margin">Plinie in pro log. lib. 1. Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius lib. 1. Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uar. and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other.</note> Of mylke, of meale▪ and crop of countrie ground▪</l>
      <l>Of peares, of plummes, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>uts and other frute,</l>
      <l>Of purpledgrapes on vines that did abound,</l>
      <l>Of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>en cakes, when simple folke made sute,</l>
      <l>Of little things right well they did rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>te:</l>
      <l>And frankince<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>se of clownes required not,</l>
      <l>But wel in woorth tooke what was to be got.)</l>
   </lg>
   <p>I shall see sufficient occasion of ioyfulnesse min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>stred to my heart: and my hands shal be the more readie and quick, to gather such another, and in hope of like luck in curteous acceptance, to be circumspect and aduised in seeing it besto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed. Thus hauing ben ouertedious▪ I cōmit your worship to the protection of that God, <hi>whose feate is heauen▪ &amp; whose footstoole is the earth,</hi> beseeching him of his gratious goodnesse, to crowne you and yours with al maner of blisfull bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. <hi>Abraham Flemming.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>