<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface to the true Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102282_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11041</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102282</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface to the true Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The diamond of deuotion : cut and squared into sixe seuerall points: namelie, 1 The footpath to felicitie. 1 2 A guide to godlines. 81 3 The schoole of skill. 181 4 A swarme of bees. 209 5 A plant of pleasure. 245 6 A groue of graces. 283 Full of manie fruitfull lessons, auaileable to the leading of a godlie and reformed life: by Abraham Fleming</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William, Assignee(s) of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 320, 4 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="48"/>
   <pb n="83" facs="48"/>
   <head>A Preface to the true <hi>Christian Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the meanes which God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined to bring man to the state of bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednes, I finde praier to be pretious, profitable, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie. Pretious, because it is the incense which we are commanded to burne vnto the Lord in the san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie of our harts: pretious I saie, because thereby we obteine at the hands of God, whatsoeuer tendeth to the good estate of the soule: and yet once againe pretious, because the Lord God, at the ascending thereof vp into heauen, stretcheth foorth his bountifull hand, and largelie bestoweth vpon vs what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer is beneficiall for our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall bodies.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="49"/>Profitable, because it procureth vnto vs the ministration of all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner commodities behoofull for this life. For it is the onlie instrument, which we are commanded by Christ in the Gospell to vse, if we stand in neede of anie thing, either temporall or spirituall, during our pilgrimage in this life, as the verie words of our sauiour seeme to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in this sense, saieng: Whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ye aske of the father in my name, it shall be giuen you. Againe, Aske, and ye shal haue: as if he said, If ye aske not, ye are worthie to want, because you neglect the vse of the precept.</p>
   <p>Now, who is so ignorant, but knoweth, that the asking, which Christ meaneth, is praier. For to aske of God, is not to aske after the maner of men, with a kind of carnal and corruptible affection, the end where of is to staie the force of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiscence, or desire, and the obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that which is required: but it is an inward, secret, heauenlie,</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>