<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE Protestant Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102373_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01007</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11112</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102373</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE Protestant Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A paire of spectacles for Sir Humfrey Linde to see his way withall. Or An answeare to his booke called, Via tuta, a safe way : wherein the booke is shewed to be a labyrinthe of error and the author a blind guide. By I.R</title>
                 <author>Floyd, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Courant (Fournieres), Marie</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 208, 207-334, 333-530, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="20"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE Protestant Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Gentle and iudicious Reader.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough in my precedent dedicatory or rather answeare to Sir Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrey's dedicatory Epistle I haue had occasion to say what is wont to be deliuered by way of preface concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the occasion, intention, scope, and manner of writing, yet because my cheife end next to the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is <hi>the good</hi> of thy <hi>soule</hi> I cannot omitt to addresse my self vnto thee in a word declaring on my part the good intention and purpose I haue in this writing, and on thine crauing the like acceptance, but especially that for thyne owne good thou wilt come to reade and peruse the same not with any preiudicate conceit either of one side or other but rather with an indifferency of mind ready to incline that way that the light of truth shall shew it self. <hi>Sir Humphrey</hi> I confesse hath some things, which at first sight may draw away an honest minded man who is not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly acquainted with the fashion of such men of the Ministery as he is ledd by. For besids a little lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="21"/>
which in a secular man maketh a great shew, (as for the increase of his owne glory he toucheth once or twice in his dedicatory,) the very title of his booke being VIA TVTA, A SAFE WAY is a very pleasing thing to many in these dayes, wherein men for the most part rather desire to find security in their owne wayes, then forsaking them, to seeke it where indeede it is to be found. But the cheife thing is this that he vndertaketh to proue his intent out of our owne authors, calling also both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse his sincerity in the citation and translation of such and such places as he bringeth.</p>
   <p>Which though it may moue a man a little at the first yet is it not sufficient to praecipitate the discreete Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's iudgment and carry it away wholy to the full beleife of what he saith without farther examination especially when he shall vnderstand that such specious titles and faire promises are the common baites of Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques.<note place="margin">Hilar. de Trin. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
      </note> Of whom <hi>S. Hilarius</hi> saith that <hi>Ingerunt nobis primum nomina veritatis vt virus falsitatis introeat.</hi> They first set before vs the names of truth that the poyson of falshood may enter in with them. And S. Aug. soe well acquainted with their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning practizes,<note place="margin">Aug. contra ep fundam. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
      </note> saith: that <hi>the promise of truth which they are continually making is nothing but a vaile to couer their errors, or a goodly fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re gate for errour to enter in stealingly into the minds of the vnskilfull.</hi> Which S. <hi>Paul</hi> himself also witnesseth saying that <hi>by sweete speeches and blessings they seduce the harts of innocent and harmelesse people.</hi> Now for the learning whereof he makes shew, whether it be his owne or noe I will
<pb facs="21"/>
not question, though I might, since some that know him doubt whether he euen vnderstand Latine: but presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that he hath a little because he was once a Scholler of Westminster and after of <hi>Christ Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford</hi> being by his Father deputed and putt into the common rode of the Ministery though he be since stept out of it, I know not ho, w into the way of Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. I onely say this that it is farre short of what is requisite for writing of a booke of this kind as shall manifestly appeare: besids that though it were a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand tymes more, I may say with the <hi>Wiseman. Non est Sapientia, non est prudentia, non est consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium contra Dominum. There is noe wisedome, noe prudence noe councel against our Lord.</hi> But of this I shall not heere say more, this being my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent onely in this place to aduise thee soe to come to the reading of this my answeare that thou suffer not thy self soe to bee wholy praeoccupated and ouerswayed from that indifferency which is most necessary for fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a right iudgement of any matter in controuersy. With which preparation of minde if thou shalt come and with attention reade, but most of all craue the speciall assistance of Almighty God's grace, I hope thou shalt not haue cause to repent thee of thy paines: Whereto without longer delay I shall heere leaue thee.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>