<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shifull, HVFREY VVHARTO of Gillingwood, Esquire, Receiver Generall of his Majesties Rvnues within the Arch-Dea∣conry of Richmond the Bishopricke of Dur∣ham, and Northumberlad, my mch respected Patron, Gace and Peace bee multiplied.</title>
           <author>Birckbek, Simon</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102067_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16161</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3083</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102067</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shifull, HVFREY VVHARTO of Gillingwood, Esquire, Receiver Generall of his Majesties Rvnues within the Arch-Dea∣conry of Richmond the Bishopricke of Dur∣ham, and Northumberlad, my mch respected Patron, Gace and Peace bee multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Birckbek, Simon</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Protestants evidence : taken out of good records; shewing that for fifteene hundred yeares next after Christ, divers worthy guides of Gods Church, have in sundry weightie poynts of religion, taught as the Church of England now doth: distributed into severall centuries and opened, by Simon Birckbek</title>
                 <author>Birckbek, Simon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>40, 248, 206, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>full, HV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>FREY VVHARTO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of <hi>Gillingwood,</hi> Esquire, Receiver Generall of his Majesties R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nues within the Arch-Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conry of <hi>Richmond</hi> the Bishopricke of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Northumberla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d,</hi> my m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch respected Patron, G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ace and Peace bee multiplied.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Sir,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He free accesse which you made mee, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of my Ministerie within your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, (what time, besides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sutors, you had a sonne of your owne, whose sufficiencie of Gifts might have anti-dated his yeares, and made him ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
<pb facs="3"/>
of greater Preferment, had God been pleased to have continued his life) hath so farre engaged mee unto you, that I have laid hold on the first oportunitie, whereby I might manifest my thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse unto you; which I could not better expresse, than by Dedicating this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise to your Name and Memory, besee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching God, that as hee hath hitherto done great things for you, and given you a <hi>Benjamins</hi> portion above your brethren,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> 3.34.</hi>
      </note> so hee would still continue his favours to you and yours, and blesse you, both in your owne person, and in your fruitfull &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising off-spring. Now if this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise seeme not no sutable a Present either to your yeares or disposition, which call you indeed rather to a poynt of Devotion, than Disputation; the truth is, it is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversall Treatise, yet it is withall a just and Defensive War, which I have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, rather for the clearing of our owne (cast, than the infesting of others; and the end I aime at, is to discover the truth,
<pb facs="3"/>
and guide others therein; And I know it would please you at the heart, to see such as have gone astray, reduced into the old way,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ierem. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note> which the Prophet calls the <hi>Good way.</hi> If any shall reape benefit by this Worke, and thanke the Authour for his paines, I shall foorthwith take them up, and bestow them wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re they are due, namely, next under God, upon your selfe, upon whose Gleabe these first Fruits of mine grew, and are now (in such sort as you see) gathered into this Store-house, and sequestred into severall Centuries, for the Churches use and benefit, by one of her meanest Proctors, but</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your much bounden Kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and Beneficiary, SIMON BIRCKBEK.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>