<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian cour∣teous Reader, increase of all spiritual blessings and tem∣porall benefits.</title>
           <author>Wilmot, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102527_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15500</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25765</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102527</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian cour∣teous Reader, increase of all spiritual blessings and tem∣porall benefits.</title>
                 <author>Wilmot, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Syrophænissa or, the Cananitish womans conflicts : in twelue seuerall tractats discouered, sectio prima. At Horndon on the hil, in the countie of Essex. 1598. Dulcescit Christus, amarescit mundus R.W</title>
                 <author>R. W. (Robert Wilmot)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the Christian</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader, increase of all spiritual blessings and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall benefits.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ountrymen, and my beloued, in the bowelles of Christ Iesus, these Chips (for so they haue beene tearmed) of Diuinitie, I neuer purposed should haue come to the open light and sight of this worlde; but being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly taken (when they were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered) from me and then promised to the Presse, I (rather than they shoulde come foorth so maymed) was resolued (too rashly) to peruse, and so to publish them: with what labour they are wrested and wrung from me, and with what difficultie now at the last they are authentically allowed your sight, I am coniured,
<pb facs="6"/> not to discouer<hi>:</hi> such as they are, I humbly commend to the successe of Gods blessing, and your fauora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acceptance. Onely this I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not passe ouer, which mightily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled with me, a Sentence which I then called to minde I had somtime read in
<hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> If (saith hee) the godly minded Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian may not publish his holy wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, wherfore were Letters inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? May the Epicure send abroad dishonest things? The Macheuilian his Policies, and the base Ballet-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker his Rithmes, and shall not the simple learned (but true hearted Christian) set foorth such things as may for euer be profitable?</p>
   <p>Againe, saith <hi>Seneca</hi> in his sixt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle, If Wisedome her selfe were graunted vnto me, on this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to shut her vppe fast, and make my priuate vse of her, but neuer to publish her, I woulde vtterly refuse her, for priuate wisedome is but se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb facs="6"/> singularitie.</p>
   <p>Heerewithall somewhat anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet I could not but maruel, that in the church of God heere in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where there are so many, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with such singular gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Gods holy Spirite, there should be too many found, that will not be perswaded to publish, their most excellent and exquisit labors, to the common benefite of others; whereas they see, and may marke, the principall cause whereby the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> beginnes to seem glorious at this day, is, for that they that haue the most plausible wittes, and pleasing gifts amongst them, as <hi>Bellarmine, Granatensis▪ Stella, Ferus</hi> and our
<hi>Parsons,</hi> with such others, whatsoeuer they haue laboured in, they haue published and dispersed abroade.</p>
   <p>But our admirable Diuines, hold it a base indignitie, that their graue studies shoulde come to the censur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="7"/> of euery Lay mans reading: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I iustly blame them, for what through the swarme of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ists that increase by the heate of the Sunne, like Frogges in Summer, harted on too much, by some of too good calling.</p>
   <p>And what for the number of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy prying Papistes, that generally mislike all the Treatises of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie whatsoeuer, that by any of the Ministers of the Gospell are publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed.</p>
   <p>And what for the crowde of our purer Puritanes, that allowe of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what they of their owne brotherhoode shall broach. And lastly, what through our prating Protestants that neuer commend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Treatise of Diuinitie, longer than they shall runningly reade it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and marke the mans methode and wit that made it: thou heauenly Theologie mayest be perchaunce reuerently regarded, whilest thou
<pb facs="7"/> arte for an houre, with sweet vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and graue gesture deliuered: but if euer thou com to the publike Presse, thou shalt feele and finde thy selfe too publickely oppressed, by the multitude of these thy malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ennemies.</p>
   <p>Neuerthelesse, I could wish from my heart, that in these diuine Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, if any things iustly mislike the Reader (as many things may) he woulde remember Saint <hi>Paules</hi> counsell, to followe the trueth in loue, considdering, as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> saith, In many things we may erre all of vs.</p>
   <p>The God of all trueth (I hope) will so blesse these Labours in the trueth, that whosoeuer commeth not with a preiudicate contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conceit, to the reading of these Conclusions, hee shall, wyth the strength of this small Cake, and wyth the comforte of this colde wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, walke foorth with <hi>Elias,</hi> euen
<pb facs="8"/> to <hi>Horeb,</hi> the Mountaine of GOD: And thus I leaue thee, committing these my first fruites vnto the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of Gods holy Spirite, who grant vs a right vnderstanding hart, wyth a charitable friendly iudgement in all things.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>R. Wilmott.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>