<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE OCCASION OF this Old Man's being brought out of Shropshiere to London.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102639_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13482</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23781</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102639</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE OCCASION OF this Old Man's being brought out of Shropshiere to London.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The olde, old, very olde man: or the age and long life of Thomas Par : the sonne of John Parr of Winnington in the parish of Alberbury; in the country of Salopp, (or Shropshire) who was borne in the raigne of King Edward the 4th. and is now living in the Strand, being age 152. yeares and odd monethes. His manner of life and conversation in so long a pilgrimage; his marriages, and his bringing up to London about the end of September last. 1635. Written by Iohn Taylor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Gosson, Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE OCCASION OF this Old Man's being brought out of Shropshiere to <hi>London.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>AS it is impossible for the Sun to be without light, or fire to have no heate; so is it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable that true Honour is as inseparably addicted to Vertue, as the Steele to the Load-stone; and without great violence neither the one or the other can be sundred. Which manifestly appeares, in the conveying out of the Countrey, of this poore ancient Man (Monument I may say, and almost Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of Nature.) For the Right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundell</hi> and <hi>Surrey,</hi> Earle Marshall of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. being lately in <hi>Shropshiere</hi> to visit some Lands and Maners which his Lordship holds
<pb facs="4"/>
in that County, or, for some other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of Importance, which caused his Lordship to be there. The Report of this Aged Man was certified to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; who hearing of so remarkable a Piece of Antiquity, his Lordship was pleased to see him, and in his Innated No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Christian Piety, hee tooke him into his charitable tuition and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; Commanding that a Litter and two Horses (for the more easie carriage of a man so enfeebled and worne with Age) to be provided for him; Also, that a Daughter-in-Law of his (named <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye</hi>) should likewise attend him, and have a Horse for her owne riding with him; And (to cheere up the Old Man, and make him merry) there was an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique-fac'd-fellow, called <hi>Iacke,</hi> or <hi>Iohn the Foole,</hi> with a high and mighty no Beard, that had also a Horse for his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. These all were to be brought out of the Countrey to <hi>London,</hi> by easie Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes; the Charges being allowed by his
<pb facs="4"/>
Lordship, and likewise one of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours owne Servants, named <hi>Brian Kel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> to ride on horseback with them, and to attend and defray all manner of Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konings and Expences; all which was done accordingly, as followeth.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Winnington</hi> is a Hamlet in the Parish of <hi>Alberbury,</hi> neere a place called the <hi>Welsh Poole,</hi> eight miles from <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> from whence hee was carried to <hi>Wim,</hi> a Towne of the Earles aforesaid; and the next day to <hi>Shefnall,</hi> (a Mannour House of his Lordships) where they likewise staied one night; from <hi>Shefnall</hi> they came to <hi>Woolverhampton,</hi> and the next day to <hi>Brimicham,</hi> from thence to <hi>Coventry</hi>; and although Master <hi>Kelley</hi> had much to do to keepe the people off that pressed upon him in all places where hee came, yet at <hi>Coventry</hi> hee was most opprest: for they came in such multitudes to see the Olde Man, that those that defended him, were almost quite tyred and spent, and the aged man in danger to have bin stife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led;
<pb facs="5"/>
and in a word, the rabble were so unruly, that <hi>Bryan</hi> was in doubt hee should bring his Charge no further; (so greedy are the Vulgar to hearken to, or gaze after novelties.) The trouble being over, the next day they past to <hi>Daventry,</hi> to stony <hi>Stratford,</hi> to <hi>Redburn,</hi> and so to <hi>London,</hi> where he is well entertain'd and accomodated with all things, having all the aforesaid Attendants, at the sole Charge and Cost of his Lordship.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>One Remarkable Passage of the Old mans Pollicie must not bee omitted or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, which is thus.</head>
      <p>His three Leases of 63. yeares being expired, hee tooke his last Lease of his Landlord (one Master <hi>Iohn Porter</hi>) for his Life, with which Lease, hee hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved more then 50. yeares (as is further hereafter declared;) but this Old Man would (for his wives sake) renew his Lease for yeares, which his Landlord
<pb facs="5"/>
would not consent unto; wherefore old <hi>Parr,</hi> (having beene long blind) sitting in his chaire by the fire, his wife look'd out of the window, and perceiv'd Master <hi>Edward Porter,</hi> the Son of his Landlord, to come towards their house, which she told her husband, saying, Husband, our young Land-lord is comming hither: Is he so, said old <hi>Parr</hi>; I prethee wife lay a Pin on the ground neere my foot, or at my right toe; which, she did; and when yong Master <hi>Porter</hi> (yet forty yeares old) was come into the house, after salutations between them, the Old Man said, Wife, is not that a Pin which lyes at my foot? Truly husband, quoth she, it is a Pin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, so she tooke up the Pin, and Master <hi>Porter</hi> was halfe in a maze that the Old Man had recovered his sight againe; but it was quickly found to be a witty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, therby to have them to suppose him to be more lively than hee was, because hee hop'd to have his Lease renew'd for his wives sake, as aforesaid.</p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="6"/>Hee hath had two Children by his first wife, a Son and a Daughter, the Boyes name was <hi>Iohn,</hi> and lived but ten weekes; the Girle was named <hi>Ioan,</hi> and shee lived but three weekes. So that it appeares hee hath out-lived the most part of the people that are living neere there, three times over.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>