<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST GRATI∣ous and reuerend Father in God IOHN by the prouidence of God Lord Archbishop of Canterburie, Primate and Metropolitane of all England, and one of the Lordes of her Maiesties most honorable priuie Councell.</title>
           <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102689_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01292</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11415</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102689</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST GRATI∣ous and reuerend Father in God IOHN by the prouidence of God Lord Archbishop of Canterburie, Primate and Metropolitane of all England, and one of the Lordes of her Maiesties most honorable priuie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A parallele or conference of the ciuill law, the canon law, and the common law of this realme of England : VVherein the agreement and disagreement of these three lawes, and the causes and reasons of the said agreement and disagreement, are opened and discussed. Digested i sundry dialogues by William Fulbecke. At the end of these dialogues is annexed a table of the sections or diuisions of the principall points, matters, and questions, which are handled in euery dialogue</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wight, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 104, 9 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST GRATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and reuerend Father in God IOHN <hi>by the prouidence of God Lord Archbishop</hi> of Canterburie, Primate and Metropolitane of all England, and one of the Lordes of her <hi>Maiesties most honorable priuie Councell.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Reuerend, right</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, and my singular good Lord, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more comfortable to the Mariner, or Sea-man, then after a great tempest to possesse a pleasant calme, and gratefull se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renitie: so nothing is more plausible and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, to them that haue employed, and exercised themselfes in any parte of learning, then after theyr long and laborious trauaile, to enioy the warmth and bright reflexion of an honorable countenance, this partly, and (if the great arrearage of duetie, and thankfulnes, which I owe to your Grace, doe not cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge prioritie) especially hath moued and enforced me, to present to your honorable view and patronage these tripartite <hi>Dialogues,</hi> to whom her sacred Maiestie hath committed the executing and maintenance of the Ciuill and Canon lawes, in these <hi>Dialogues</hi> by my slender pencill rather delineated, then described: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Common lawe cannot otherwise be diuided from these twaine, then the flower from the roote and stalke, therefore this
<pb facs="3"/> entier discourse I haue wholy submitted to your <hi>Graces</hi> tuition and disposall: in which I sought rather to profite the vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, then to please the sense with a plausible, copious, and polished stile, or with foreyne conceyts not belonging to the titles of the Lawe, which I handle: assuring my selfe, that as verball delites and affected, vanities are to your Lordship odious, irksome, and of no accompt: so they are in truth to the gaping eares of this curious age, very snares, and Sirens. Wherfore humbly referring my selfe to your <hi>Graces</hi> excellent wisedome, and abundant clemencie, for the imparting of a fauourable regarde and countenaunce to these my vnworthy labours, I beseech the almightie God with the most submisse deuotion of my harte, that the dayes of your lyfe (which the Lorde of life multiplie) may be the degrees of your happines, to the great good of this Church, and Common-weale, to the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding comforte, and contentment of such as be studious of vertue, Lawe, and equitie, and to the immortall propagation of your fame and memorie thorough all ages, and times, vntill the last time of all ages.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and bounden William Fulbecke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>