<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface of
the Translator.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102015_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00709</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10840</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102015</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface of
the Translator.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exact and curious suruey of all the East Indies, euen to Canton, the chiefe cittie of China : all duly performed by land, by Monsieur de Monfart, the like whereof was neuer hetherto, brought to an end. VVherein also are described the huge dominions of the great Mogor, to whom that honorable knight, Sir Thomas Roe, was lately sent ambassador from the King. Newly translated out of the trauailers manuscript</title>
                 <author>Feynes, Henri de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Arundell  (Arondell, Erondell), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 40, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A Preface of
the Translator.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>ET WAS I NOT SO</hi>
much the <hi>Translator,</hi> as
the Fashioner of this worke.
It was my good hap in my
last iourney into <hi>Fraunce,</hi>
to bee acquainted with that
braue Spirit, the right <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>
and performer therof;
who, a right <hi>French Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman</hi>
withall, howsoeuer indowed with <hi>Courage</hi>
and other <hi>Martiall</hi> qualities, (yet as though learning
were a staine to a Noble blood, with vs) the truth is, he
cannot very well write; strongly possessed, with that
actiue humor of ours, so much bent to <hi>Doing,</hi> as can
little curbe it selfe to <hi>Musing;</hi> and with that preiudicat
opinion, (the Ship-wracke of all our young <hi>Nobilitie)</hi>
that it is onely for a <hi>Gentleman</hi> to ride, not to reade,
and rather handle a bad sword, then a good booke, but
a Pen least of all. Which hath euer beene the vnluckie
<pb facs="4"/>
cause that our worthiest counsels, and most generous
exployts in peace, or warre, would lye for euer buryed
vnder the dust of forgetfulnesse, with the same bodyes
that performed them; If euen they who haue felt most
smart by vs, had not set them downe to our owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
and of all nations, to diminish their shame by the
valor of their <hi>Enemies.</hi> So then this <hi>Gentleman</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
onely taken some notes of his iourneyes, still as hee
went, not able to make a right treatise of them, for want
of a fit writer in those barbarous <hi>Countries,</hi> being as
he thought, at his trauels end, and happilie landed in
<hi>Christendome,</hi> hee found it in this case farre more
<hi>Barbarous.</hi> For there he was taken himselfe, and in one
of the most rich, and famous Sea-citties of the world,
kept foure yeeres in pryson, watching him care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
with an intent, so to keepe him all his lifetyme,
least by a full discourse he should make other <hi>Nations</hi>
acquainted with these his obseruations, thereby to giue
them an entrance into that Earthly <hi>Paradise,</hi> which
they so enuiously barre from all notice, and entercourse
of the whole world, by the flaming <hi>Mouth</hi> of so manie
<hi>Cannons,</hi> and the <hi>Sun-burnt</hi> Garisons of their blacke
<hi>Angels,</hi> the dearer to sell vnto vs those delightfull
fruits of life, which we could fetch our selues at a better
rate: In that plight, our <hi>Traueller</hi> was faine to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
all his knowledge to his best memorie (a qualitie
wherewith God hath largely requited his not being a
great <hi>Rethoritiā)</hi> &amp; principally to his notes, which yet
in the middest of all his troubles, and no small losses, he
was more careful to keepe then his treasure. So as soone
as by a very extraordinary and much vnlooked-for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb facs="4"/>
from <hi>Heauen,</hi> hee had made meanes, in fauour of
two great mariages intended, to get out; and finally,
being arriued at <hi>Paris,</hi> I was chosen for the framing
and setting together this dis-ioynted Treatise, enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
his notes from his owne mouth (as sometimes one
doth after a Sermon) and was allowed my owne <hi>Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie</hi>
for my labour. The like whereof I may safely auouch
is but in three hands besides, through all the world; the
one in the Closet of our most Noble and hopefull young
King, (whom God for euer blesse:) the other, with a
great <hi>Prince;</hi> the third, with the <hi>Author</hi> himselfe.
Now the truth is, that as soone as I had but the first
sight thereof, I immediatly, according to my former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution
and profession, whollie to applie my selfe, my
studies, my life, and best endeuours to the seruice and
benefit (as farre as I can) of this noble Kingdome, my
second and substitute <hi>Country,</hi> after that which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
first binds me vnto, purposed with my selfe to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish
it here, as a witnesse of my true and auncient loue.
A loue indeed not humorous, nor new, but trulie bred,
euenwith nature in my childhood, &amp; before my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
vnder the tender care of an <hi>English</hi> mother, now
of late in my riper and best yeeres, vppon good triall &amp;
iust reasons, (or such at least as I doe flatter my selfe
to be so) growne by habitude to such a poynt of bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,
as euen I content my selfe to forbeare my right
<hi>Countrie</hi> and <hi>Kindred,</hi> with all my hopes, perhaps
not altogether vnlikelie, (or but meere hopes vnbegun)
of higher preferment in the multitude of so many
friends, great and small, and of both <hi>Religions</hi> (as I
dare say, and withall prayse God for it,) I haue yonder.
<pb facs="5"/>
Neyther is that loue of mine hid or vnknowne to the
world. There are bookes extant in more then one Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
to testifie it, which I might very well haue kept
back, if it had beene otherwise; since euen many of
mine owne <hi>Country-men</hi> haue taken some exceptions
at it, as though (God forbia) I would in some sort dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue
the bands of nature, farre, farre, from my meaning
and which scarce can be effected at my very dissoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
Yet did not my loue so much carry me away, as that
I would witnesse it in superfluous things. Therefore
least I should runne amisse, I was carefull both to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
and peruse all such <hi>Bookes,</hi> and <hi>Pamflets,</hi> as are
to be found in <hi>English,</hi> concerning <hi>Asia-Trauailes,</hi>
which in all doe not amount to fiue or sixe. And finding
the most part speakes of nothing els then of <hi>Graecia, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia,
Syria,</hi> with some stale tales of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> so
contrary one to another, and so much beaten, and beaten
againe, as it is both shame and losse that such toyes
should be vttered, (but that euer some prettie wit must
get money by making others loose their tyme) I thought
this <hi>Author</hi> could not but proue profitable, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come:
Seeing that with no other end, but onely to see &amp;
learne, he did vndertake his trauell; without loade,
or engagement of marchandise, or of any priuate end, or
company, ranging still vp &amp; downe, and curiously pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
and peircing as far as he could into euery <hi>Iland,</hi> or
<hi>Continent;</hi> yea, neuer by water, where hee might by
land, hath discouered in yonder world more <hi>Nations,</hi>
more <hi>People,</hi> more <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> more <hi>Townes,</hi> more
<hi>Fashions,</hi> more <hi>Particularities,</hi> then euer any man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
or since, to our knowledge. Now for the Style, this
<pb facs="5"/>
man doth not stand vpon flowers, nor I my selfe; who do
follow him as neere as I can. Neyther doth hee fill the
paper with idle talkes of a Tempest, or a Ship-wracke;
a Robberie here, a Disgrace there; or shamefully recount
how many Kicks, how many Knocks, and Bastinadoes
hee had this way, or that way; a thing more then most
common among <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi> He sweares vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
his credite he had none. Neyther doth he stand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
any other vayne particulars; but directly goeth to
the maine; saying what hee can, and what hee knoweth
goes to the heart, and life of whom he intends to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged,
not onely for his long imprisonment, but also
for somewhat more then he dares write for this present.
Whereof neuerthelesse, he will giue an inkling in his fit
place, before he end; sufficient enough to enforme
of the whole, such as are not altogether
blind, or deafe. But nowe it is
high tyme to heare
him speake.
∴</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>