<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>I desire thee (courteous reader) to beare with the faultes in printing, which be very many through the composers ignorance in our language: the gros∣ser are to be amended thus.</title>
           <author>Benefield, Sebastian, 1559-1630</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102326_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16171</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3094</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102326</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>I desire thee (courteous reader) to beare with the faultes in printing, which be very many through the composers ignorance in our language: the gros∣ser are to be amended thus.</title>
                 <author>Benefield, Sebastian, 1559-1630</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A disproofe of D. Abbots counterproofe against D. Bishops reproofe of the defence of M. Perkins reformed Catholike. The first part. wherin the now Roman church is maintained to be the true ancient catholike church, and is cleered from the vniust imputation of Donatisme. where is also briefly handled, whether euery Christian can be saued in his owne religion. By W. B.P. and D. in diuinity</title>
                 <author>Bishop, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Morel, Claude</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 423, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="217"/>
   <head>I desire thee (courteous reader) to beare with the faultes in printing, which be very many through the composers ignorance in our language: the gros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser are to be amended thus.</head>
   <p>For, page read. wo, 10. who. Psel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues 31. themsel: Ther est, 64. the rest. wr 69. warning. wr, i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid. writ. boo 70. book. desirer, 75. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire. wn, 76. own. thee, 77. the. Gods ir 76. good sir. 851. 78. 85. donasti, 88. dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist. chook, 92. cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. construct, 118. consumat. de, 119. fide 51. 123. 1. hom: 1. ibid. 9. disco, 132. diosco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus. And 138. to be put out. mise 144. 155. ipse. cap 99. 158. 9. flock, 164. flock. Alhi, ibid. Alchimist. tost and 172. to stand. courto 171. court. lest 172. lost. ditous, 173. ditious. others 180, other. dipro, ibid. dispr. boh, ibid. both these, ibid. the. Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centin, 16. tius. iustly 189. iustly. nous, ibid. house. or 214. of. ane ony, 226. any one. no 250. yea. yea ibid. no. bith 241. both. popes the 273. the popes. both in, 284. in both. in 287. l. 2. to be put out. ferneut, ibid. fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. suto, 288. into. biet his ibid. bie this word 300. world. se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etes, 301. sectes. haue, 307. hanc. qui 328. to be put out. qua ibid. quae do 336. doth. do 342. do not. church a, 350. a church. wholy 367. whot. ofo 308. of. dat, 320. orat. cem 225. catum. ibidem (in his successors) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be put out.</p>
   <pb facs="217"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>