<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Holbrooke, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102568_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10394</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20678</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102568</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Holbrooke, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Saint Pauls triumph, or cygnea illa &amp; dulcissima cantio : that swan-like and most sweet song, of that learned and faithfull seruant of God, Mr. Iohn Randall, bachelor of diuinitie: vttered by him (in an eleauen sermons, vpon the eight chapter of St. Pavl his epistle to the Romans, vers. 38.39.) lately before his death, in the time of his great and heauy affliction, and vpon the Communion-dayes, either altogether, or for the most part. And now published for the glory of God, the edification of his church and people, and the hononrable [sic] memoriall of the author, b William Holbrooke, preacher of the word of God</title>
                 <author>Randall, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Newbery, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Redmer, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 239, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nderstand (Christian Reader) that these following Sermons, were giuen by the Author (as they were written by his owne hand) to his louing friend <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Edward Misselden,</hi> Merchant, who most Christianly, and willingly, vpon the first motion deliuered them vnto me, and condiscended to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing of them, knowing that <hi>bonum, quo commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, eo melius,</hi> a good thing the more common it is, the better it is, for which thou art much beholding to him, for by this meanes thou hast these Sermons as they were penned and preached by the Author, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out addition or detraction. Reade and meditate throughly vpon them, thou shalt not (I assure thee) repent thee of thy labour, for thou shalt finde therein much deepe, and necessary heauenly doctrine, and (through Gods blessing) be furnished with armour of proofe against all dangers and troubles whatsoeuer, that are vpon thee, or may befall thee in this life. Be thankefull to God, for this, and all meanes of thy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall good, which he affordeth thee, and forget not to pray for him, who forgetteth not to pray for thee and the whole Church of God, and who will euer bee thine in the seruice of the Lord,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>William Holbrooke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>