<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Williams, Gr.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102808_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15445</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25716</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Williams, Gr.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The delights of the saints : A most comfortable treatise, of grace and peace, and many other excellent points. Whereby men may liue like saints on earth, and become true saints in heauen. First deliuered in a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the second day of December, being the second Sunday of the Parliament. And in other sermons within the Cathedrall Church of Saint Paul, London. By Gryffith Williams, Doctor of Diuinity, and Parson of Lhan-Lhechyd. The contents are set downe after the epistle to the reader</title>
                 <author>Williams, Gryffith</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 448 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Gentle and Christian Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>Must confesse this little Treatise, though it was not in a short time <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed,</hi> (for I preached it all in the Cathedrall Church of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in my ordinary lectures there) yet came it in haste to be <hi>printed;</hi> for after I had preached the chiefe heads of most part of it at <hi>Pauls Crosse,</hi> it was requested for the Presse, and I had not time <hi>lambere foetum,</hi> to ouersee it againe as I would: and because my bookes and all my notes (saue only a few scattering papers that I brought with me) were farre from me, almost two hundred miles from <hi>London,</hi> I was faine to let it passe without any diligent search for the quotations either of the Scripture places, or of Fathers, saue only what I bore in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, and what were in my notes I
<pb facs="7"/> brought with me. And by reason of my <hi>absence from the Presse.</hi> I finde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie faults committed in the printing, I gathered some of them together, and I pray thee (sweet Christian brother) take thy pen and mend them, and where thou findest any other, doe the like, and I will take it kindly at thy hands, and my praiers shall be euer readie for thee. I hope the <hi>matter will proue profitable,</hi> and that is my greatest desire. For I take God to witnesse, who is <hi>fidelissimus testis,</hi> the most faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full witnesse, that my aime hath beene alwaies <hi>non scire vt scirem, nec scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam vendere,</hi> not for any gaine, either of credit or of profit, but for the gaine of soules, which is <hi>vberrimus quaestus,</hi> the greatest gaine in the world, to studie and preach, and to doe all that lieth in me, to discharge my dutie; and therefore I euer affected <hi>verum magis quàm verba,</hi> soundnesse of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rather then nicenesse of words. If any man say I did but collect the same out of other mens workes: I say so too. And I wish, he that saith so, would doe so too: <hi>quia facilis est</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>obliuio boni.</hi> I gathered my stones out of many quarries, but I composed my frame my selfe. And I reioyce in this, that <hi>I deliuer what I learned, and not what I inuented,</hi> as <hi>Lyrinensis</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. To the censures of maleuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent mindes, I doe expose my selfe. Let them goe on; say what they will: <hi>Ego sic viuam vt illis fides non habeatur,</hi> I hope God will giue me grace; to feare him, and not them: and I hope the godly Reader of this little Tract of mine, will finde some profit by it; for the <hi>most necessary,</hi> and the <hi>most frequent</hi> points of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity,</hi> that doe meet vs almost in <hi>euerie passage</hi> of the Scripture, are here <hi>fully handled.</hi> Scarce <hi>any Text</hi> of the <hi>New Testament</hi> can be found, but some part of this Treatise will affoord some matter fit for some part thereof What profit it will bring, I leaue it to the euent: If none, I hope God will esteeme my labours <hi>non ex euentu, sed ex af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu,</hi> not according to what it did, but according to what I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire it should doe: so praying to
<pb facs="8"/> my good God for thee, and for all men, and desiring thee and all Saints to pray for me, I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy true brother in Iesus Christ, <hi>GR. WILLIAMS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>