<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102448_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13585</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23875</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102448</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Temporis filia veritas : A mery devise called the troublsome travell of tyme, and the daungerous delivery of her daughter trueth. Interlocutours, Bennion the button-maker: and Balthesar the barber</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>After such tyme as I had considered the many-maner of Religions, Sects, and Opinions, (gentle Reader) that are now risen vp out of mens high knowledge and goodthinking▪ and whereout (for the most parte) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seedeth also all contention, Envy, Disobedience, Rebellion, Lying, Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byting, Slaundering, Imprisoning, Killing, &amp; Murdering, &amp;c, together with al liberty of life in committing wickednes, which is now frequented (without feare or shame) among the children of men. I tooke this deuise in hand for six speciall causes.</p>
   <p>The first was for that the Magistrats (who are Gods ministers on earth) mought the better remember their office and calling, and how that they are appointed of the Lord to suppresse euill, Disobedience, Falshood, and wickednes: and to maintayne Gods obedience, Trueth, or godlynes of lyfe.</p>
   <p>The second was for that all simple and ignorant people, mought see how easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men may be seduced [now in these dangerous dayes] through faire speeches, and outward shewes of holines: yet neuerthelesse I am not against the right Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>li{que}, the true Protestant, or the perfect Praecisian, so long as they holde them to Obedience in the holy life aforesayd.</p>
   <p>The third was for that my hope standeth in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lorde, there are many good willing hearts to the righteousnes yet remayning vpon the earth,<note place="margin">
         <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>5.</hi> c.d. <hi>6.</hi> c. Rom. <hi>8.</hi> a. c.</note> who once knowing the Trueth, (and what euerlasting felicitie it bringeth with it) will not (by any sinister meanes of the disobedient and rebellious route) be drawne away therefrom (whether it be then by theyr smothe speeches, cruell threats, feare of Persecution, Blasphemyes, Tyranous handling, Imprysonments,<note place="margin">
         <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>10.</hi> a. b. c. <hi>1.</hi> Pet. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> Vnjustice, or most cruell death that they can deuise (but will rather indevour them still to liue vnder Obedience to God and gouernours &amp; so exercise them dayly in the godly life (that right Religion, fast grounded on the vnconfutable Trueth) wherein the Lord had alwayes, still hath, and for euermore shall haue his pleasure and delight.</p>
   <p>The fourth cause was this,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>b.</hi>
      </note> for that all men [if it were possible] mought see or vnderstande that the good life is not so slight a thing as many men make accompte of. For the Lorde looketh not so mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h vpon the outward oblations, Sacrifices, Seruices, or Ceremonyes, which the man offereth or vseth for to serue him withall, as he doeth vpon the single heart of the man,<note place="margin">Psal. <hi>51.</hi> d. Ioh. <hi>4.</hi> c. Mar. <hi>12.</hi> c.</note> in his Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and good lyfe [for the Lorde will be honoured onely (of his) in spirit and Trueth] therefore the Oblations, Seruices and Ceremonies, are respected of the Lorde for the good hearts cause and nor the euill hearted respected for the Oblations, Seruices, or ceremonies cause: Example by Cain and Abell,<note place="margin">Gen <hi>4.</hi> a.</note> they both offered sacrifice to the Lord: The one (for the bloudynes of his heart) his
<pb facs="10"/> Oblation was refused. And the other (for the singlenes of his heart) his Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was accepted. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>The fift cause was for to answere and satisfie all such as praesently stand (at the gaze as it were afarre-of) wayghting what will come of this my Religion, or els doubting of the goodnes and contynuance thereof. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi>
      </note>And the sixt or last cause is this, for that I (who haue bin these many yeres most Injuriously slaundered and defamed: most cruelly persecuted, and Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned, as also most dispitefully spoyled and Impouerished to my vtter discredit and vndoing: Like as some that be honourable (if they remember it) can part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell) am still ready (during lyfe) to answere boldly for my felfe: beleefe, and Religion in the Trueth: And therefore (for the clearing of my selfe) and for the recouering of my good name [which I esteeme aboue golde and syluer] I am bolde to dedicate this my deuise to her Majesty, and to make knowne (there through) my Religion openly: And moreouer I meane hereafter [by Gods grace] and vnder correction and submission of my Prince, to perswade all my friends, and acquaintance, whether they be then <hi>Catholi{que}s, Protestants, Puritans,</hi> or what other Religions soeuer [so much as I may in the Lorde] to inclyne theyr hearts wholely to lyue vnder such obedience and godlynes of lyfe, as is aforesayde: Also to pray for the <hi>Queenes Majesty</hi> and al the honourable of his priuie Counsell, for that they mought so maintayne the gospell of <hi>Iesus Christ,</hi> whereby the <hi>Trueth</hi> mought get the victorie in all our hearts: To the end all mought become one in <hi>Christ,</hi> And <hi>Christ</hi> one in all. AMEN.</p>
   <pb facs="10"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>