<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRI∣STIAN READER.</title>
           <author>Symson, A.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102416_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12258</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22566</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102416</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRI∣STIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>Symson, A.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Heptameron, the seven dayes: that is, meditations and prayers, vpon the vvorke of the Lords creation : Together with other certaine prayers and meditations, most comfortable for all estates, &amp; c. By M. A. Symson, minister at Dalkeith</title>
                 <author>Simson, Archibald</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 207, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle and Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, sith yee receiued so tenderly my first Booke, <hi>Of the seuen words which our Lord spak vpō the Crosse,</hi> I haue taken courage to present this Booke, <hi>Of the Creation,</hi> also to your consideration: which suppose it preceed the other in time, so long as the Creation of the Worlde doeth Mans Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption purchased by the death of Christ, yet they succeede in effect and woorth: for it had beene farre better that neither the World for vs, nor wee for our selues, had beene made,
<pb facs="6"/>than that wee should not haue beene redeemed by him.</p>
   <p>This, if yee peruse diligentlie, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate consideratiuelie, I doubt not but that yee shall see the Lord more clearelie in his owne workes: this beeing, as it were, a mirrour and looking Glasse, wherein wee may perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie beholde Himselfe, his Omnipotencie Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Loue, Goodnesse, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>By this also yee may draw nearer and nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer vnto the Lord your God, and become more frequent and acquainted with him, by daylie meditating vpon his woorthie Workes, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing him, giuing him thankes for the same, and praying vnto him to continue his graces towardes you still vnto the ende.</p>
   <p>I did reade Sainct <hi>Ambrose</hi> his <hi>HEX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AMERON,</hi> and the woorthie <hi>D. BAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAS:</hi> and I trust yee shall perceiue the direction of one Spirit, guiding vs all vnto one and the selfe same Ende.</p>
   <p>I perswade my selfe that there are manie well minded Christians, who will likewell of this Booke; and againe others will perhaps dislike of it, euen such as esteeme of nothing but that which is forged in their owne Shop: yea, they know no better means to grace them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
<pb facs="7"/>than by disgracing others, as Sainct <hi>Hierome</hi> sayeth in his Epistle vnto Sainct <hi>Augustine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But I craue at thine handes (most courteous Reader) that (since in anie mans worke there will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ee some Drosse amongst Golde) thou wouldest choose the best, (if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> were but in the Dongue-hill) and passe by the other with a cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itable construction: in the meane time ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting this in good part: and if it please God to continue his graces with mee, thou mayest expect more. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A. Symson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>