<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE APPARITION to his Friend.</title>
           <author>Rawleigh, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102372_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05370</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15523</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102372</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE APPARITION to his Friend.</title>
                 <author>Rawleigh, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ravvleigh his ghost. Or a feigned apparition of Syr VValter Rawleigh : to a friend of his, for the translating into English, the booke of Leonard Lessius (that most learned man) entituled, De prouidentia numinis, &amp; animi immortalitate: written against atheists, and polititians of these dayes. Translated by A. B</title>
                 <author>Lessius, Leonardus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Seutin, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 445, 456-457, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prefatory_letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE APPARITION <hi>to his Friend.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>EARE Friēd, whome I much prized, whiles my soule was inuested with Flesh, &amp; my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy enioyed the Ayre, which now thou breathest. My Spirit is, at this tyme, permitted by the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to appeare to thee, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat a Boone, or Fauour. Thou well knowest, that the World (whose dialect is euer deliuered in the blacke notes of Obloquy and Reproach,) hath at sundry
<pb facs="3"/>
tymes, cast a foule, &amp; most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iust aspersion vpon Me, for my presumed deniall of a <hi>Deity.</hi> Frō which abhominable and horrid crime, I was euer most free. And not any man now liuing, better knoweth the same, thē thy selfe, in whose presence (if thou doest remember) I was often accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med highly to praise and esteeme the Booke of <hi>Lessius,</hi> written in proofe of the being of a <hi>Deity,</hi> &amp; entituled, <hi>De prouidētia Numinis.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Since then, that Treatise euen frustrateth with shame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>susion, all the impugners of so il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrious and euident a Principle (Charactered in our Soules by Gods owne seale;) therefore my humble, and earnest request is, that thou wouldst take the paines
<pb facs="3"/>
to translate the said treatise into English; and let the Title beare my Name, that so the Readers, may acknowledge it, as done by my sollicitation. In the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of which labour (besides the accomplishmēt of my desire heerein) thou payest some small Tribute of that Homage to him who gaue thee &amp; me our Being: <hi>In ipso</hi> enim <hi>viuimus, mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mur, &amp; sumus.</hi> So wishing thee true feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and the world more charity in its Censures, I am in hast to leaue thee, since my Spirit is not suffered to stay any longer vpon earth; but must returne with speedy wing, to the place from whence it came.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The Ghost of W. Rawleigh.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>