<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR HENRY YELVERTON Knight, one of the Iustices of his Maiesties Court of Common Pleas.</title>
           <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102880_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01523</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11647</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102880</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR HENRY YELVERTON Knight, one of the Iustices of his Maiesties Court of Common Pleas.</title>
                 <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Abrahams decease : A meditation on Genesis 25.8. Deliuered at the funerall of that worthy seruant of Christ, Mr. Richard Stock, late pastor of All-Hallowes Bread-street: together with the testimonie then giuen vnto him. By Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith</title>
                 <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Clifton, Fulke.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 62, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR HENRY YELVERTON Knight, one of the Iustices of his Maiesties Court of <hi>Common Pleas.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OVR <hi>speciall interest</hi> in that <hi>worthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> whom this <hi>weak work</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth, by your <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular fauours</hi> to him and his deseruedly procured, cānot but giue you <hi>interest</hi> in the <hi>worke</hi> it selfe before any. Vnto your <hi>Worship</hi> therefore I addresse
<pb facs="3"/>
and direct it, as to one that may iustly lay <hi>best claime</hi> to it: Not doubting but that, as you did in more than ordinary manner <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect</hi> his <hi>person</hi> while he <hi>liued,</hi> so you do no lesse <hi>honour</hi> the <hi>memory</hi> of him now <hi>deceased.</hi> The <hi>worke</hi> I wish were <hi>worthy</hi> either <hi>you</hi> or <hi>him.</hi> But, how little time I had for the <hi>compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing</hi> and <hi>peecing vp</hi> of these <hi>broken Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> cannot be vnknowne to those, &amp; from them may be made knowne to others, that either <hi>sent</hi> or <hi>brought</hi> me the <hi>first word</hi> of his <hi>decease,</hi> being newly allighted from a <hi>wearisome iourney,</hi> not aboue <hi>two daies</hi> before the <hi>Funerall</hi> was to be performed. Besides that so <hi>sudden</hi> and vnexpected <hi>tidings</hi> of the <hi>losse</hi> of so deare a <hi>Friend,</hi> causing much <hi>griefe</hi> and <hi>distractiō,</hi> could not but produce with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all as great an <hi>indisposition</hi> to the minding of that that this <hi>office</hi> imposed on me did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily require of me; and defeat conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that <hi>second</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Diligentia sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium. Cicero pro Quinct.</note>
      <hi>helpe</hi> of <hi>redoubled di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,</hi>
   </p>
   <p> which others are wont to vse (as the <hi>sea-man</hi> his <note n="b" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>oares,</hi> when the <hi>wind</hi> slacketh or scanteth) to redeeme the want of <hi>time</hi> with. That which made me (as conscious of the <hi>rawnesse</hi> of it) the more backward at
<pb facs="3"/>
first to yeeld to the importunitie of those, (not a few) who both by <hi>letters</hi> and by <hi>word</hi> of mouth were very instant and vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent for the publishing of it. Nor haue I had much <hi>loisure</hi> since to <hi>reuise</hi> and <hi>digest</hi> my <hi>confused notes;</hi> nor yet <hi>desire</hi> to <hi>adde</hi> or <hi>alter</hi> much, lest (to those that then heard it) it might seeme not the same. One short <hi>pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage</hi> or two onely I haue inserted, that my <hi>memory</hi> then failed me in. Else the <hi>substance</hi> of all here was then deliuered. Which if, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the <hi>Testimony</hi> then giuē vnto him, whom this <hi>office</hi> was performed vnto, it seeme <hi>slight</hi> and <hi>slender,</hi> to that it ought or might haue beene: Besides the former <hi>consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations,</hi> which might well sufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, let it be remembred; what a great <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> sometime said, that <note n="c" place="margin">Pictores pulchrā absolutam{que} faciem rarò nisi in peius ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingunt. Plin. Sec. lib. 5. epist. 10.</note>
      <hi>An exact face is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry seldome drawn but with much disaduantage:</hi> how much more when <hi>a bungler</hi> but hath it in hand? I may well say of him, as he some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time of <hi>Basile,</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Greg. Naz. in Basil.</note>
      <hi>There wanted but his owne tongue to commend him with.</hi> A <hi>better</hi> I wish there had been employed therin than mine owne; or that mine owne (if but for his sake) had (at least then) been <hi>better.</hi> But the
<pb facs="4"/>
best is, <hi>The Sea needs not the Riuers, that</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Ibid.</note>
      <hi>yet runne into it;</hi> nor he either mine, or any other mans <hi>praise;</hi> that due <hi>honour</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent <hi>estimation</hi> of him remaining in the <hi>mindes</hi> of so <hi>many,</hi> that neither mine, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other mans, <hi>commendation</hi> of him, either need to adde ought, or can adde much ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Howbeit this may bide, when they are gone. Which whatsoeuer it is, presuming that <hi>your Worship</hi> will <hi>accept</hi> of, if not for it owne sake, yet for his, who <hi>liueth</hi> yet with you, and you desire (I know) should doe so also with others, I <hi>recommend</hi> it to your <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage,</hi> and <hi>your selfe</hi> with <hi>all yours</hi> to the <hi>protection</hi> of him who hath promised to be <note n="f" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Sol &amp; Seutum. Psal. 84. 12.</note>
      <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Shield</hi> to all those that sincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>rely</hi> on him; and rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships to be commanded in the Lord Iesus, THO. GATAKER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>