<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102039_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14107</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24417</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102039</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The figure of Antichrist : with the tokens of the end of the world, most plainly disciphered by a Catholike and diuine exposition of the seconde epistle of Paul to the Thessalonians, collected out of the best and most approued diuines, both olde and new, very profitable for all men in this age to reade: published by Thomas Tymme, minister</title>
                 <author>Tymme, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 <publisher>Coldock (Coldoke), Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>93 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Argument.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ECAVSE the Apostle Paul could not conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niētly returne any more to see the <hi>Thessaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> he confirmeth their mindes by this Epistle, that they might constantly beare and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure affliction for Christes sake, for the which they shold receiue their reward, and their aduersaries also their iust Iudgment from the Lorde. This is the content of the first chapter. Furthermore, because he had written vnto them in the former Epistle, that the last day woulde come vnawares, and had for the same cause also admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed them to watch, &amp; not to be carelesse: the <hi>Thessalonians</hi> thought that they should liue to see the last day. Wherfore in the seconde chapter, hee doth confute that vaine and false opinion, concerning the comming of Christ at hand (which with most men at that time had preuayled) by the argument, because first there must be a departing awaye in the church, and a great parte of the worlde must fall from God: and Antichrist must reigne in the
<pb facs="5"/> Temple of God: vpon the which sonne of perdition, the Lorde Iesus will at the last take vengeance, and wil also kil him with the breath of his mouth. The comming &amp; kingdom of which Antichrist, the Apostle doth plainly discipher, that the latter age being forewarned therof, might take heed of the pestilent cup of that <hi>Babilonicall</hi> purple coloured strumpette. In the thirde chapter, after that hee hath commended himselfe vnto their prayers, &amp; hath bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly incouraged them to constancie, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth that those men be seuerely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished which through idlenes and curiosi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie troubled the common wealth: vvhom he vvould haue to be excommunicated, if so be they vvould not bee admonished and vvarned. Finally, he finisheth his Epistle by recommending them to the Lorde of peace. The vvhich Epistle although it be breefe, yet a contayneth vvoonderful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and learning. In style it is nothing dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the former Epistle, neither in any thing inferior. That it vvas sent from Rome (as commonly the Greek books reporte) it is not like: for had it beene so, he vvould haue made some mention of his
<pb facs="6"/> bondes, according to his vvoonted man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Furthermore, he shevveth that hee is in present perill of vnreasonable and euill men. Whereof it may be gathered, that he did write this Epistle as hee vvas in his iourney tovvarde <hi>Ierusalem.</hi> And the Latines haue a long time beene of opinion that it vvas vvrittē from <hi>Athens.</hi> Some also thinke that it vvas sent by <hi>Titus</hi> &amp; <hi>Onesimus.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>