<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Right honorable and mine espe∣ciall good Lorde, The Lorde Greye of VVylton.</title>
           <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102875_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01514</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11636</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102875</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Right honorable and mine espe∣ciall good Lorde, The Lorde Greye of VVylton.</title>
                 <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The posies of George Gascoigne Esquire</title>
                 <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Smith (Smyth), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, clviij, 2, 4, 36, 45-76 pages, 77-86, 85-106 leaves, 107-173, 3, 175-290, 10 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="74"/>
   <head>¶ To the Right honorable and mine <hi>espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall good Lorde, The Lorde</hi> Greye <hi>of</hi> VVylton.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Singular good Lorde: I am of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that long before this time your honour hath throughly perused the booke, which I prepared to bee sent vnto you somewhat before my comming hyther, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall I doe lykewise coniectour that you haue founde therein iust cause to laugh at my follies forepassed. So that I am partly in doubte whether I were more ouerseene in my first deuising, or in my last dyrecting of the same? But as fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasticall humours are common imperfections in greene vnmellowed braines: So hope I yet that your good Lordshippe wyll rather winke at my weakenesse in generallitie, then reproue my rashnesse in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularitie. And because I would bee glad, to drawe your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe into forgetfulnesse thereof, by freshe recorde of some more martiall matter, as also for that I would haue your Honour perceaue that in these lyngering broyles, I doe not altogeather passe ouer my time in ydlenesse: I haue therefore thought meete nowe to present you with this Pamphlete written by stelth at such times as we Loyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from seruice. And the sobiect thereof being warre, I could not more conuenientlye addresse the same vnto any Marshiall man, then vnto your good Lordshippe: VVhome I haue heard to be an vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall patrone of all Souldiours, and haue found to bee an exceeding fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourour of mee your vnworthy follower. The verse is roughe. And good reason, sithence it treateth of roughe matters, but if the sence be good then haue I hyt the marke which I shote at: Knowing that your Lordshippe can winne Honny out of the Thistle. And such as it is, I dyrect it vnto your Honour. Beseeching the same, to take it in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gree, and to perceaue that I am and euer wyll continew.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most bounden and assured. <hi>George Gascoigne.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>