<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102803_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01395</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11517</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102803</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The glory of England, or A true description of many excellent prerogatiues and remarkeable blessings, whereby she triumpheth ouer all the nations of the world : vvith a iustifiable comparison betweene the eminent kingdomes of the earth, and herselfe: plainely manifesting the defects of them all in regard of her sufficiencie and fulnesse of happinesse. By T.G</title>
                 <author>Gainsford, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Norton, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 331, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <head type="sub">Nec Adulatori. Nec Detractori.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough there is no end of writing books (as saies the Preacher) and the vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our very soules ariseth from the desire of knowledge, especially when we steppe a little into vaine-glory, the last thing laide away of the wisest men: yet either custome, or some particular purposes doe still traduce many in this kinde, who otherwise walked with sufficient reputation, and like the foole in the <hi>Prouerbes</hi> might haue beene counted wise, if they had held their peace. So that it cannot chuse, but I must incurre the like imputation, yea peraduenture ridiculous contempt; when I haue nothing to say, but for the glory of my Countrey, and seeme to maintaine a Position, which few English<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men deny, and that I doe herein no more, then the <hi>Swizer</hi> or <hi>Sauoian,</hi> who preferreth his snowy hils, before the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">All nations loue their owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey best.</note> of <hi>Lombardy,</hi> and rageth in his disceptation, if you ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vilipend his barren Mountaines and dangerous pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages, or preferre any other glorious nation before him. But againe, when I striue to mount a little higher, and tune out this harmony to a reach of excellency, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue
<pb facs="5"/>
ouer all kingdomes, and people in such things, wherein God doth blesse any Nation, you now would a little procrastinate my iourney, and cannot but suppose me ouer-liberall and ouer-partiall in my iudgement, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, if 1. either you are a stranger: 2. Or haue beene a Traueller: 3. Or looke no further, then on the bescar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and deformed face of antiquity as Authours haue wounded the same: 4. Or liue discontented through par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular greeuances in your Countrey: 5. Or are wilfull and irregular by the impostures of superstition: 6. Or affrighted at the power and greatnesse of other Princes: 7. Or transported with a poore opinion of our wealth: 8. Or to conclude, are meerely ignorant, and vnderstand no more, then is conferred vpon you by relation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: wherein you must needes resemble certaine empty trunkes in Court remoues, who onely fill vp a place: but vnderstand not, wherefore, nor by whom they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied: yet because I would also satisfie these, and corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate my Hypothesis with probable reason, I will lead them by the hand into the faire fields of this discouerie, and neuer desist, vntill they are conduced to safe harbour, and there Eccho out the truth in security; though it seeme a Panegyricall applause, and carry a phantasticall burthen of flattery. Onely the methode I would vse is somewhat intricate, and the desire I haue to shunne confusion, will make a greater confusion like a true and modest Louer, who fearing to disclose her affection by her lookes, doth in that restraint make the next looke more passionate.</p>
   <p>But to the purpose. If you be a stranger, which you <note place="margin">1 Strangers.</note> may be either by ignorance, or nation: then peraduenture you looke no further, then what you see, or know, and not vnderstanding the honourable secret of our Countrey,
<pb facs="5"/>
suppose nothing comparable to the ostentous brauery of some few stones, and dead things of those Cities, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you are reziant: but TACITVS, and other famous Authors can tell you, that Cities are not glorious with emptie houses, and lime and stone compacted for show, and subiect to ruine and breuiary demolition; but in the wisedome, wealth, and resplendant eminence of noble Citizens, and well ordered men: so that no man, vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the secrets of a Kingdome, can compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely subiect it either to vilipending, or insufficiency.</p>
   <p>If you are a Traueller? Then carried away with present shadowes, or transported with a cursory vanity of some <note place="margin">2 Traueller.</note> stately edifices, braue Curtezans, entertainement of stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers (recommended by some speciall Councellour of State) strong castles, new ramparts, conuenient harbours, well furnished Arsenalls, some prety gallies, and hearke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after euery report to please the Hearing, or rauished with some comicke sight to moue admiration, you go no further, then present contentment, nor will once remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, what a mother you haue of your owne, and how a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate childe ought to be louing, dutifull, and aduised. <note place="margin">3 B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reader:</note>
   </p>
   <p>If you search for no better secrets, then what absolute Authors haue locked vp in their storehouses, who many times filled their papers with extraneall reports, and when they were possessed with a nouelty exciting astonishment, they then enlarged the same, setting downe euery thing as authenticall, which onely carried the show of probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity by some enforcing circumstances, howeuer it sauour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of detraction, and calumny: Thus I confesse haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny written of BRITANY, as of a strange and barbarous nation, naked people, painted, enraged, liuing vpon roots and herbes, eating raw flesh, and remote from the brauery
<pb facs="6"/>
of populous Cities, and courtly pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>aces: whereby a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued impression is so made, and lest to posteritie, that in many places they suppose the same still. Wherein I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not compare them better, then to some poore Farmer, who liuing in an old cottage, thatcht, and deformed, is compelled at last to go into another Countrey, as dispos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed by some wealthy Lawyer, or Citizen, and so rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to his new acquaintance, what a pittifull house hee came from, and how miserable hee left the same, little knowing, how delicately, yea stately it is reedified, and holdeth vp such a contrary face of Maiesty, that if he were to returne, and view it againe, he could not imagine it the same, nor that any policy of man, or worldly meanes had contriued the alteration.</p>
   <p>If you liue discontented at home, then out of a sullen and dogged humour you spare not any accusation of your <note place="margin">4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>me-bred discontents</note> countrey, whether for deficiency of blessings, or gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but hearken after euery report of strangers, and are contented to be cosoned with the deceit of forraine relations, and so from a wilfull neglect of our worthines, wilt neither beleeue the maiesty of our honour, the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificense of our structures, the variety of our happinesse, the decency of our Cities, the exaltation of officers, the beauty of women, the glory of conuersation, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particulars tending to an absolute demonstration of our worth: but dost vnkindly weigh it downe with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison, saying there are some slender commendable things amongst vs, but farre inferiour to other nations.</p>
   <p>If you are superstitious, or would seeme affectionate to religion, then vnder a pious show of deuotion, you abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely <note place="margin">5 Patisis.</note> condemne all other things, and sweare they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualuable to the pacification of the conscience, and setling
<pb facs="6"/>
the soule to peace, and vnderstanding the way to saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and so without either desire, or endeauours to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a further truth, you not onely deny those allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which may diuert you from falshood, but are an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie to all commemorations of temporall matters, which may giue you light to conduct you to the acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of ENGLANDS merit, and high exalted desert.</p>
   <p>If you are terrified with the strength and warlike prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of forraine Princes, because you heare of well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified <note place="margin">6 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> places, armies on foote, treasure amassed, shippes rigged, Countries subiugated, garisons dispersed, Princes affied, and the Pope blessing them. Then peraduenture you may suppose, that we cannot propulse such aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, nor haue sufficient meanes to rebate the insolencie of so high exalted Monarchs; because you are either faithlesse in heart, traiterous in loialty, simple in apprehen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ion, of ouer-reached by cunning inferences of others, and so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine confounded at some common wants amongst vs, disabling all things, which may tend to strengthen the hopes and loue to your owne Countrey.</p>
   <p>If you are desirous of wealth, and corrupted with the <note place="margin">7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> filthinesse of lucre, then it may be hearing of the infinite treasures of the GRAN SIGNIEVR, the Venetian riches, the many millions comming out of India into Spaine, so many crownes of the sunne coined in France, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall entradoes of diuers Countries, and Principates, and troubled at home with strange rumours of penuries and wants, with exportation of our gold and coine into for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine parts, and some forcible convulsions of priuate men to enrich themselues: you are amazed, and cannot be set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with any opinion of our sufficiency, and will scarce be helped with better information.
<pb facs="7"/>
uide possessions by way of contribution to their children; reward their seruants, and endeauour to bee neere the Prince? would you dispute of ciuill conuersation, of a Land that floweth with milke and hony, of eating vnder thy owne vineyard, of receiuing the temporall blessings of encrease, of solemnities at feasts, of burials and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings for the dead, of martiall exequies, of triumphant marriages, and priuate reioycings, of honest and friendly visitations, of mutuall commerces, of powerfull presents? of detaining vs within the limits of naturall obseruation, as <hi>quod tibi fieri non vis, alteri ne feceris,</hi> and in truth of all fundamentall principles of gouernment in the hands of the Scriptures is lifted vp a mirror to looke into without specke, staine, base composure, or counterfeit foile.</p>
   <p>Would you haue directions for maintaining a magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, for adapting you to reciprocall duties of releeuing the poore, succouring the fatherlesse and widowes, suppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the proud, restraining the offensiue, imparting of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, acknowledging of friendlinesse, with such like? would you be thankefull when your cuppe doth ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow, reposed when necessities knocke at the doore, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient when aduersitie deiecteth, moderate when prosperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>lateth, free from repining at the glory of thine aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, sparing insulting ouer the misery of inferiours, and remember, who is the distributer of all good gifts, like the Master of a Comedy, who sorteth out his Sceanes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the inclination of his schollers, making a poore mans childe to personate a Prince, and the sonne of a lord to acte a meaner part? In the Scriptures shineth the light of such vnderstanding, and liueth the soule, and life of the truest wisedome.</p>
   <p>In a word, would you know the duty to God and man,
<pb facs="7"/>
the hope of saluation, the mysterie of religi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n, the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishments of faith, the preeminence of truth, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> sanctified calling of all Gods seruants; from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ariseth the fountaine and swelling spring flowing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to riuers, yea seas of abundance, which in some are of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tast, but inward sweetnesse; in others pleasant in the mouth, but wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>mewood in the belly: so that if from thence proceede all lawes, statutes, and ordinances touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the supreame godhead, the spirits vnder his throne, the nature of things visible and inuisible, the power of Deuils, the glory of the firmament, the diuision of the earth, the bonds and limits of the sea, the secrets of hell, and the terrors of the last dissolution: what neede wee more, or go any further for a marking stone to colour any kingdome with, whereby it may be known to come neere and enioy most of those blessings, wherewith God hath sealed and ratified the glory of Countries, then out of the storehouse of the Scriptures.</p>
   <p>To this purpose I dare be bold to aduance our <hi>England</hi>
      <note place="margin">Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nd comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> into the highest chaire, as if she were to triumph for some notorious victory; and that I may bring vp my forces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to a close encounter, and connect my reasons with probability, I will discouer at large, what I haue learned out of industrious Authors, obserued by my owne indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours: <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
            <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> knowne as <hi>oculatus testis</hi> in most countries of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, and since determined in a combat of comparisons, not that I meane to rippe vp the bowels of antiquity, and call in question so many thousand volumes, which haue consumed as many thousand yeeres in discouery of ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals, and as it were tormented Time with strange dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses: so that if you should take off the vaile, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with diuers Authors haue ouermantled both Countries,
<pb facs="8"/>
Kingdomes, and Cities, you would stand amased at their deformed shapes, and remaine confounded to veiw now their disparity. I will therefore leaue all maligne circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of my quiet, and shew you with what countenance they looke vp to heauen at this instant, and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they seeme proud of their establishment, whereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> that are willing to be impartiall, shall be the better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ed to yeeld vp a verdict of truth against all adulterate sophistication.</p>
   <p>Yet must I adde with all this lesson of morality, that in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> kingdome, where vnderstanding hath pleasured the people with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of ciuility (as for barbarous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> onely make vse of their names) <note n="a" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
            <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>Sol vitae est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>: <note n="c" place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
               <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> Antidotus vitae patientia: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
            <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
         </gap>: <seg rend="sup">c</seg> Vita vitae conscientia: <seg rend="sup">c</seg> &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ntia.</hi> For with wealth your entertainement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ght w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>th Princes; attonement made with Tyrants; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ed amongst strangers; adoration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and such as know not ciuilitie will stand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> at thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rauery, and florishing: By wealth are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>gated, imperfections remitted, scandals re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> pardoned, follies excused, and the frowns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ed. For wealth, beauty yeeldeth to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>es are in opposition, enforced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, men transported to exorbitant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> for strange vndecencies, and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ounded with contraries. But this is a pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> part of my worke, or meaning; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> for feare of longing after that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="4 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>l as the Dutchman, who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Now to conclude: The whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> into two seuerall Bookes:</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>
In the first, you shall ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Countries of the world, by way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> plana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>on, as they are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
   </p>
   <p>In the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 line">
         <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
      </gap> as Drapers doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> clot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="5 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊◊◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> whereby the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and prerog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> made appar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>