<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE of the Authour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102372_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05370</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15523</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102372</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE of the Authour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ravvleigh his ghost. Or a feigned apparition of Syr VValter Rawleigh : to a friend of his, for the translating into English, the booke of Leonard Lessius (that most learned man) entituled, De prouidentia numinis, &amp; animi immortalitate: written against atheists, and polititians of these dayes. Translated by A. B</title>
                 <author>Lessius, Leonardus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Seutin, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 445, 456-457, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE of the Authour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Treatise following we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to discusse two questions: The first is touching <hi>a diuine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer;</hi> to wit, whether there be any <hi>diuine power or God,</hi> who with his prouidence sterneth, and gouerneth mans affaires, and demandeth an account of his actions after this life. The other, concerneth the <hi>Soule of man,</hi> that is, whether it be immortall, or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risheth &amp; is▪ vtterly extinguished with the body: Poynts worthy to be disputed of, most claborately &amp; succinctly; since of all things whatsoeuer, which become the obiect of our vnderstanding, these are most necessary to be knowne. And touching the first▪ supposing that there were no <hi>God</hi> (of whō this whole <hi>Vniuerse</hi> and all negotiations of man were to be gouerned) but that all things, either by a certaine force of nature, or casuall concourse of
<pb facs="7"/>
causes had their euents; then should we be freed of great feare for the things to come, and might se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely and without all impunity do whatsoeuer were best pleasing to our owne dispositions. For then no man were obliged to yield an account (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of the body) for things done in his life time; no man for his sinnes should hereafter be punished; neither should any reward attend the faithfull and veriuous. Finally, neither of what comportment, carriage, and conuersation a man is, should it be (after the dissolution of the body from the soule) either preiudiciall, or beneficiall vnto him. Since sinne then, should be nothing, but a certaine aery, imaginary, and a false conceit, of a law violated, &amp; a <hi>diuine power offēded.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But now, once acknowledging that there is <hi>a God</hi> (through whose prouidence and prescience all things are guided and measured) then it ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitably followeth, that we ought greatly to feare and reuerence him, and be most cautelous, and wary, that we do not infringe his lawes &amp; sācti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Since it is most certaine, that he will exact an account after this life, and will inflict due pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments vpon sinners. For it is a point princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally iucumbent and belonging to a gouernour, to giue a iust retaliation and retribution to men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compensing their enormities and vyces with pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments, and their vertues with honours and rewards. All kinds of Gouerments, aswell of the
<pb facs="8"/>
worser sort, whether they be <hi>Tyrannicall, Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garchicall,</hi> and <hi>Democratical,</hi> as of the better, as <hi>Monarchicall, Aristocratical, or Political,</hi> or any other kind of Regiment compounded of these, do vnanimously confirme &amp; warrant this assertion. For it is most euident, that all these haue euer set downe rewards and punishments, grounding themselues vpon these, as vpon certaine foundations, without the which they cannot in any sort subsist or continue Therefore admitting that there ought to be proposed both rewards and ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>tis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s, thereby to debar men from vice▪ &amp; incyte them to vertue; It also followeth, that this diuine power is mightily to be feared, of al mē, least they do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>urre his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, &amp; least they purchas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to themselues his iust reuenge. For no man is able to resist him; no man of power to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde his power; to be short, no man there is, which liueth not within the boūd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> his dominatiō.</p>
   <p>Wherefore euery one is chiefly to be most cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspect, that he doth not deny the existence &amp; being of this power, and that he seeke not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue it of prouidence in the disposall of the world, and of all things comprehended therein; except it euidently aforehand can be euicted by conuincing &amp; solid reasons, that no such Diuinity or Power there is; but that the being thereof is suggested &amp; supposed out of a humane conceit, only for Policy sake: for in the intertaining a rash conceit herof,
<pb facs="8"/>
a man exposeth himselfe to the perpetrating of the greatest offence that can be imagined, since grā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the being of such a <hi>Deity,</hi> the denyers therof stand culpable of a most heinous blasphemy, and of spirituall treason against so great a Matesty: for as that subiect extremly wrongeth his King, whō he denyeth to be King, or his kingdome to be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto him; though this his denyall be grounded vpon some outward shewes of probability: Euen so, who auerreth the not being of a <hi>supreme po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer</hi> (by the which the world and the things ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are ruled) committeth a most heinous cryme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God, and resteth guilty of the highest disloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty against so powerfull a <hi>Deity,</hi> though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise he may seeme to shadow such his blasphemy vnder the tecture of some weake &amp; feeble reasōs. Which point being so, what then remaineth for such a man to expect, then a most heauy reuenge to be inflicted vpon him, for his dentall of so <hi>so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne,</hi> and so <hi>supreme a Power.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now then, from this it appeareth, how abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutly necessary to man is the indubious and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine confession and acknowledgment of the being of <hi>a God.</hi> And indeed the knowledge of the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and nature <hi>of mans soule</hi> is not much lesse to be searched after: for if it could be proued that the Soule of man were mortall (as the soule in beasts is) thē should we not need to stand in feare of what hereafter might fall vpon vs; but we
<pb facs="9"/>
might securely lead a carcles &amp; pleasurable life. best <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing to our owne desires and sensuality.</p>
   <p>Now, if the contrary hereto shalbe demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be most true (as infallibly it will) thē haue we reason to be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st anxious, fearfull and solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous, least by our wicked life, and Conuersation our soule after death may i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>curre most dreadfull and eternall torments. Of both these points I dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course in this treatise; to wit, in the first booke of the <hi>Being of a God &amp; a supreme diuine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</hi> In the second of, the <hi>Soules Immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> The contemplation of both which is most grat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pleasing, and comfortable For the presence of a <hi>Deity</hi> &amp; his prouidence wonderfully sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>neth both in the whole fabrick of the world, and in the creatures contained therein; as also in the most wise disposall and gouernment of the same things. The <hi>Immortality of the soule</hi> is made demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strable by force of many irrefragable and conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing arguments. Both these shalbe disputed off, with as much breui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y and perspicuity, as possible I can; omitting diuers curious and subl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me points, which might otherwise serue to en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>āgle the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and to diuert his iudgment from the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall scope intended by me; since my desire herein i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>▪ that what is here vndertaken, may not be performed out of any idle ostentation, and vanity, but only for the spirituall fruite and benefit of the studious Reader.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>