<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Introduction.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102769_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16303</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3215</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102769</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Introduction.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo letters or embassies : The one sent by the states of Bohemia, to the Elector of Saxony: the other from the Popes Holines to the Emperour, concerning the troubles of Germany</title>
                 <author>Bohemia (Země), Sněm</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Jones, William 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Introduction.</head>
   <p>RVmor hauing played a true womans part through the Citty of <hi>Prague,</hi> concerning the Duke of <hi>Bauaria's</hi> comming to <hi>Lintz,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Saxonyes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratiue Letters to the Emperour, that the Marquesse <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nola</hi> was approaching with a formidable preparation to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist him, and hee himselfe would not be behinde in any duty, which belonged to his obseruation, or the Dignity of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: thrust herselfe at last into the presence of the King, and the greatest Councellors of Estate, but in such a manner, as if she durst iustifie her lauish tongue, and tooke a pleasure in the ampliation, which yet briefly had these maine passages:</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1</hi> First, that <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Bauaria</hi> combined themselues to illustrate the glory of the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> and by no meanes to leaue either Emperour, or Empire in the cruell hands of reuolters, if either they could procure their deliuery, or by any prouidence conserue their renowne:</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2</hi> That the Marquesse <hi>Spinola</hi> had more forcible rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in his approaches, as resoluing to reduce the Subiects of <hi>Bohemia</hi> (whom hee termed Rebels to the Emperour) to their pristinate obedience, wherein if hee found any retar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, hee would shew them the angry faces of <hi>20000.</hi> men, so prouided out of the storehouse of Power and Pollicy, that the world should record it as a remarkable president, and they be confounded to vnderstand, what their wilfulnes had incurred.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3</hi> That presently <hi>Don Lewis de Velasco,</hi> hauing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified <hi>Wesell,</hi> and left a sufficient Garrison both in it and other Townes subiect to surprises vpon the aduantage of his
<pb facs="4"/>
absence, should follow him, as a second in the prosecution of greater Designes.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4</hi> That the Catholicke Bishops, and other secular Princes, would fill vp this well bound sheafe with their Arrowes, and make the <hi>Hierogliphick</hi> an absolute resemblance of indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solluble and vnresistable strength.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5</hi> That these free Cittyes of the Empire would open their Gates, yea breake downe their walles, rather then this <hi>Sinons</hi> Horse should stand without, and not offer sacrifice in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Pallas.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus was this <hi>Mattachene</hi> of report danced euen in the Kings Castle and Pallace, and if mischiefe had had a tricke to affright them indeed, or startle their resolutions from standing in their firmnesse, it so fell out, that it ranne like a voyce of Thunder, and meant to follow one another in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. But it should seeme, no arme of Flesh could turne the frame of Heauen about: and there was a stronger hand ready to throw a stone to strike <hi>Nabuchadnezars</hi> Image in peeces: For they were all so farre from being daunted, or terrified with imposturing apparitions, that they were rather exasperated, and encouraged to Opposition: Yea it is saide, that the inuincible and Heroyick Queene kneeled downe with lifted handes to Heauen, desiring God to accept of her, as a propitiary Sacrifice, rather then his Iustice might not haue her prosperous course in the punishment of sinnes, or the now glory of her Husband suffer diminution, or so much as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll from the Enemies of the Gospell, and aduersaries of the Kingdomes prosperity: To this (besides the admiration at her magnanimity) both King and Nobles, Cittizens and Commons, Gent. and Souldiers, Protestants and Papists, Priests and Cleargie men, yea all that had participated with
<pb facs="4"/>
the particulars, combined themselues to shake off these drops of threatning rumor, and be sheltred from the greater storme of a publike Enemy.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding it was thought conuenient to send an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacy to <hi>Iohn George</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and Prince Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, to put him in minde of the auncient League and amitie, which euer continued betweene the <hi>Bohemian</hi> State and the House of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and to knowe from a personall infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, how he stood affected in this Warre, or disposed to the assignation of his Forces, or what might bee the cause of his desertion in this so great a busines, which concurred with the propagation of the Gospell, and the Liberty of oppressed people. Whereupon there were two out of each of the three States of <hi>Bohemia</hi> deligated to this imployment with an orderly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of attendants, besides a Secretary of eminency, who came in good time to <hi>Presula,</hi> and there found the Duke.</p>
   <p>It is said, that at the first, there was some difficulty in their entertainment and admission, as from a King indeed: For <hi>1.</hi> whether priuate emulation against the <hi>Palsgraues</hi> aduancement, whom before hee held in equall rancke with himselfe. <hi>2.</hi> Or sinister occasions like vntoward weedes cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vp the growth of better Corne, <hi>3.</hi> Or neernesse of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanguinity drawing his loue to the Emperour. <hi>4.</hi> Or a iealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie concerning the diminution of the greatnesse of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, beeing thus dilacerated and diuided. <hi>5.</hi> Or a superstitious blindnes in the case of the Roman Religion wrought him out of the possession of better thoughts, or diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him from that respect so meritorious a Prince excited, I will not now dispute: onely I am sure hee would neither wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly allow them the titles of such a Kings Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors; nor affoord them that audience, which their message
<pb facs="5"/>
both imported and deserued, till at last his Councell beeing most of them well affected to the King, and his Religion, ouer wrought him to condiscend to the Law of Nations and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of all royall Prouinces: So they had a Day of audience, and the Duke for all his minde was intangled with an intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate businesse, and farre reaching Proiects, yet heard them the sooner, the sooner to bee ridde of them, and so the Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary thus began:</p>
   <p>
      <hi>FREDERICKE</hi> by the grace of God King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> Palatine of the <hi>Rhine</hi>: and so as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his Maiesties iust Titles, with the three States of the Common-wealth of <hi>Prague,</hi> and Protectors of the Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated <hi>Prouinces,</hi> sendeth greeting to the High and Mighty Prince <hi>IOHN GEORGIVS,</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony, Iuliers,</hi> and <hi>Cleues,</hi> Elector of the Sacred <hi>Empire,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>