<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all that desire the sin∣cere Milke of the WORD, Grace and Peace bee multiplied.</title>
           <author>Traske, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102652_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13873</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24176</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102652</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all that desire the sin∣cere Milke of the WORD, Grace and Peace bee multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Traske, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A pearle for a prince, or a princely pearle : As it was deliuered in two sermons, by Iohn Traske</title>
                 <author>Traske, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Matthew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 39, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all that desire the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Milke of the WORD, Grace and Peace bee multiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue sent you heere a Princely Pearle, as a helpe to supplie your many wants: the price is very small, the commoditie may proue exceeding great: to those that purchasing, pray: hauing prayed, read; and hauing read, receiue: that which the word approues. I desire no more, the word requires <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> lesse. But in reading this, or any other such: beware no conceit of the man preuaile more, then the truth of the matter: lest thou make Man a God, and God an Idoll: but be sure thou search the
<pb facs="3"/> Scriptures diligently, whether these things be so, for the neglect of this is the cause of many fearefull errors, and of much grosse ignorance. Wherefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing once read it ouer, at the second rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, trie euery Scripture whether they be pertinent, thus shalt thou reape much benefit, and this short Sermon will proue a large Volume vnto thee. And knowing that if thou be one of those little ones, for whose sake I penned it, thou shalt haue cause to praise God for it, and that thou wilt continue to help with feruent praier, that the Gospell may haue free course, and bee glorified, as also desiring thee not slightly to consider of this aduise in thy course of reading mens writings, as thou tendrest thy soules escape, the rocks of so many dangerous errors, as are now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, especially in writing. I r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st <hi>Mar. 30. 1615.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours that be the Lords, IOHN TRASKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>