<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Praeface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102772_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01289</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11412</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102772</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Praeface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An historicall collection of the continvall factions, tvmvlts, and massacres of the Romans and Italians : during the space of one hundred and twentie yeares next before the peaceable empire of Augustus Cæsar. Selected and deriued out of the best writers and reporters of these accidents, and reduced into the forme of one entire historie, handled in three bookes. Beginning where the historie of T. Livivs doth end, and ending where Cornelivs Tacitvs doth begin</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ponsonby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 20, that is 209, 7 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Praeface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ourteene yeares are now runne out sithence I fully ended and dispatched this historicall labour: for departing from the Vniuersitie of Oxford in the yeare 1584, and addressing my selfe to the studie of the Law, I thought it more conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and reasonable at once to finish and perfect this worke, which I had already begun, then breaking my course with delaies to be still striking on the anuill, knowing that things begun, are more easily conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded then thinges interrupted can be conioyned; wherefore in that very yeare and some few daies fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, I did begin, continue and consummate the three bookes of this historie, since which time it hath lyen in the couert of my studie, of my selfe seldome looked on, of others some times read, who by vrgent perswasion would haue mooued me to offer it to the publike view of my countreymen, to which I would in no wise condiscend, alleaging for reason that it would be thought a blemish of impudencie in me to assay the discription of such things, which by <hi>Appian, Plutarch, Paterculus,</hi> &amp; others haue bene excellently deliuered; which I tooke to be a sufficient fortresse and support of my excuse and refusall, but againe I heard that all the Romane writers which haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported the accidents of this historie, are either in
<pb facs="5"/>
their narrations too long and prolixe, or else too harsh and vnpleasant, or else so exceeding briefe that the coherence and mutuall dependance of things could hardly be discerned or coniectured in the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row compasse of so strict desciphering. This I heard with patience, and answered with silence, for I durst not oppose my blunt arguments to their daintie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite: the truth standing so in the middle way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt bs both, that I could not with safe conscience in all these allegations dissent from them, nor with sound opinion in all consent vnto them, wherefore weighing more precisely in minde, and ballancing with vnaffectioned thoughts the state of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt vs, and beholding the naked pourtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing it selfe without shadow of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, I perceiued that the great prolixitie and the too exceeding breuitie of the Romane historiogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers could not well be couered with the veile of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reasonable excuse: and further the obiection of others could not well be confuted, who do condemne in their writings great disagreament and contrariety of narration, wherefore remembring my first intent in the collecting of these historicall reports, which was to single and sequester the vndeniable truth of the historie from the drosse and falshood which was in many places intermixed and enfolded in it: and to do this in such sort, that my speciall care in auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the extremities of length and breuity, two loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some faults, from which notwithstanding few writers be free, might fully and manifestly appeare: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering likewise that histories are now in speciall
<pb facs="5"/>
request and accompt, whereat I greatly reioyce, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging them to be the teachers of vertuous life, good conuersation, discreete behauiour, politike gouernement, conuenient enterprises, aduised pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, warie defences, grounded experience, and refined wisedome. And being again solicited by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasible meanes, to commit the censure of this my historicall collection to the curtesie of others, I haue at last yeelded to this motion, reposing my selfe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon kinde construction, then rigorous desert. The vse of this historie is threefold, first the reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the mischiefes of discord and ciuill discenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in which the innocent are proscribed for their wealth, noblemen dishonored, cities become waste by banishment and bloodshed: nay (which is more) virgins are deflowred, infants are taken out of their parents armes, and put to the sword, matrons do suffer villanie, temples and houses are spoyled, and euery place is full of armed men, of carcasses, of bloud, of teares. Secondly the opening of the cause hereof, which is nothing else but ambition, for out of this seed groweth a whole haruest of euils. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the declaring of the remedie, which is by humble estimation of our selues, by liuing well, not by lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king well: by conuersing in the light of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale with equals, not by complotting in darke conuenticles against superiors: by conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our selues with our lot, and not contending to our losse: by hoping without aspiring, and by suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring without conspiring. Let Rome in this history be a witnesse, that a slipperie ascending was alwaies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied
<pb facs="6"/>
with a headlong discent, and that peace is a great deale better then triumph, which will be an occasion I trust to my countreymen of England to be thankfull to God for this sweete quiet and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renitie of this flourishing estate, in which England now standeth, wherein the day striueth with the night whether shall be calmer: and let it mooue thee whosoeuer thou art, courteous Reader, to pray with the earnest endeuor of thy hart, that the Iris which is the pledge of our peace may still shine amongst vs, that the happie Virgin which is the starre of safety in the Zodiacke of this common weale may continue immoueable, that our <hi>Halcyon</hi> may still sit in this <hi>Albion,</hi> on this white rocke to make the seas calme, and the waues silent, and to preserue the league of heauen and earth, I meane true Religion amongst vs. From my Chamber in Graies Inne 13. Octob. Anno Dom. 1600.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in all sincere affection, WILLIAM FVLBECKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>