<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE
RIGHT HONORABLE,
and vertuous Ladie, the La∣die
ANNE, Coun∣tesse
of OXENFORD:
much honour, with in∣crease
of godlinesse
and vertue.
⁂</title>
           <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102723_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02916</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13057.8</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102723</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE
RIGHT HONORABLE,
and vertuous Ladie, the La∣die
ANNE, Coun∣tesse
of OXENFORD:
much honour, with in∣crease
of godlinesse
and vertue.
⁂</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The epistle of the blessed apostle Saint Paule : which he, in the time of his trouble and imprisonment, sent in writting from Rome to the Ephesians. Faithfully expounded, both for the benefite of the learned and vnlearned, by Nicholas Hemming ... Familiarlie translated ou of Latine into English, by Abraham Fleming. Heerein are handled the high mysteries of our saluation, as maie appeare by the table of commonplaces necessarilie annexed by the same A.F. Perused and authorised</title>
                 <author>Hemmingsen, Niels</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 234 + pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE
RIGHT HONORABLE,
and vertuous Ladie, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
ANNE, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesse
of OXENFORD:
much honour, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
of godlinesse
and vertue.
⁂</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL THE</hi>
gouernement,
(Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable)
of the
true, holie,
and Catholike
Church, which
hath ben from
the creation of
the world, vntil
this present age
is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
in fiue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
or degrees: the first of the Fathers, beginning at
Adam, &amp;c: the second of the Patriarches, beginning
at Abraham: the third of the Prophets, beginning
at Samuel: the fourth of the high Priests, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
at Iehoshua, otherwise called Iesus: the fift and


<pb facs="3"/>
last of the Apostles, beginning at Saint Iohn Baptist.</p>
   <p>Among all which Apostles, none was more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfullie
called to the preaching of the Gospell, than
S. Paule, who being a bold &amp; common blasphemer,
a bloudie and mercilesse persecuter, afflicting the
flocke of Christ with most terrible torments, was
notwithstanding euen in the fire of his furie reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
and became the great teacher of the Gentiles,
deliuering vnto them such heauenlie doctrine, as he
receiued by diuine inspiration, apt to instruct, exhort,
rebuke, correct, and reforme, that the man of God
might be made perfect in all good workes.</p>
   <p>This Apostle, as before the time of his conuersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
which was in the verie yeare of Christs ascensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
he shed much innocent bloud, making hauocke
of the members of the Church, with the sword of
persecution: so after the renouncing of his apostati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
tyrannie, he saued manie thousand soules, by the
preaching of the Gospell, &amp; word of reconciliation.</p>
   <p>For he taught the truth of the eternall God, whose
minister and vessell of election he was, ordeined to
set forth his glorie before the face of the mightie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantlie,
in season and out of season, by the space of
thirtie sixe yeares, to manie nations, profoundlie and
zealouslie, beginning in the nineteenth yeare of Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius
at Damasco: continuing it through out a great
part of the world, as appeareth by his painfull pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grination:
and finishing that good worke of his, in
the thirteenth yeare of Nero, whose prisoner he was,
and at his commandement put to death in Rome,
for the testimonie of the truth, which he sealed with
the losse of his life, vnto the glorie of the great God.</p>
   <p>This blessed Apostle Saint Paule, was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der


<pb facs="3"/>
of the Church of Christ at Ephesus, where he
preached the Gospell of peace most sincerelie: and
instructed the Ephesians in the necessarie doctrines
of their saluation, and in the deepe points of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion:
as in predestination and election, in faith and
iustification, in praier and inuocation, in grace and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption,
in manners and conuersation, &amp;c. as doth
manifestlie appeare in his Epistle, written to this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
out of bonds and imprisonment.</p>
   <p>The exposition wherof (Right Honorable) M. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas
Hemming, a learned, godlie, &amp; excellent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine
vndertaking, &amp; accomplishing, hath so orderlie
&amp; plainlie opened al the principal points therin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined,
that nothing can seeme doubtfull or difficult,
no not to the simple and ignorant: besides that, so
briefelie, that the memorie of the reader shall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to carrie awaie both his method and matter.</p>
   <p>Whose worke when I had read and perused, I tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
familiarlie into our English tong, because I sawe
it was a booke verie like to be beneficiall vnto euerie
priuate person. And hauing ended mine honest tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell,
I remembred (among diuers fauourers of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
and louers of godlinesse) your good Ladiship:
whom as I honor for the same respects, so finding in
your Ladiship, among your other vertues, a zealous
loue to religion, and to the sincere seruing of GOD,
(rare things in the multitude, what then in the hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable?)
I haue bene thereby induced, and thus bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
haue presumed, to prease with this my poore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
vnto your Ladiship, in waie of dedication: and
doe praie your fauourable protection of the same.
Beseeching, euen with humblenesse, that this my
homelie handeled Expositor, a straunger borne, and


<pb facs="4"/>
newlie araied with course English cloth, maie finde
such fauour in your Ladiships presence, as to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terteined.</p>
   <p>Not doubting, but the Author for his excellent
learning, and profound knowledge vttered therein,
shall thereby be able to withstand all seditious Scis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes,
quarelling Sycophants, impudent Papists,
pestilent Pellagians, blasphemous Anabaptists, licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
Libertines, whose perillous opinions are by him
confuted: and finallie, all the malicious members
of Sathan that old serpents synagogue: to the
preferring of the truth, and the increase of
Gods glorie, vnto whose protection I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
your good Ladiship: whose hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse
God graunt maie be such,
both heere and aboue, as your
owne heart would wish, and as
my continuall and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
praier shalbe,
Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honourable Ladiships
Most humblie to be commanded,
Abraham Fleming.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>