<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE IMPARTIALL AND indifferent Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102573_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09644</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19909</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102573</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE IMPARTIALL AND indifferent Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vertues anatomie. Or A compendious description of that late right honorable, memorable, and renowned Bedfordshire lady, the Lady Cheany, of Tuddington. By Charles Pierse</title>
                 <author>Pierse, Charles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>TO THE IMPARTIALL AND indifferent Reader.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>REader whatsoeuer thou art accept, if may be,</l>
      <l>These humble verses clad in shepheards weeds,</l>
      <l>My subiect is an honourable Lady,</l>
      <l>And of her vertuous life and sacred deeds.</l>
      <l>Therefore I would intreat thee when thou reads</l>
      <l>Vomit no venome forth, nor poysoned gall,</l>
      <l>Lest that the like vpon thy pen befall.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Perchance thou lookst for, that I cannot giue,</l>
      <l>Some ouer-flowing phrase of eloquence,</l>
      <l>Wherein her high deserts might better liue,</l>
      <l>And yeeld the curious artist lesse offence:</l>
      <l>But with his itching vaine I can dispense</l>
      <l>And tell him this, pure vertue loues to weare</l>
      <l>Not all rich stuffe, but sometimes Camels haire.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I doe not know thy nature nor condition,</l>
      <l>Be what thou wilt Ile nere orerunne thy fauour,</l>
      <l>I onely write to gentle dispositions</l>
      <l>And may as well respect the meanest labour</l>
      <l>Then doe not shew thy selfe of rough behauiour</l>
      <l>As sharply for to censure what is written,</l>
      <l>Mad dogges they are when none can scape vnbitten.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then passe thy verdit gently on my lines,</l>
      <l>Shew not thy selfe more cruell then the rest,</l>
      <l>I write not for to please disordered times,</l>
      <l>But those to whom time hath mark'd for the best,</l>
      <l>Then take thy course or yeeld to my request,</l>
      <l>For I do stand indifferent rightly then</l>
      <l>Speake what thou wilt speake and blame not my pen.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>