<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY JAMES, BY the grace of God, King of great BRITAINE, FRANCE and IRELAND, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Wilkinson, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102764_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15375</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25652</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102764</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY JAMES, BY the grace of God, King of great BRITAINE, FRANCE and IRELAND, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Wilkinson, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Barvvick bridge: or England and Scotland coupled : In a sermon tending to peace and vnitie. Preached before the King at Saint Andrewes in Scotland. Anno Domini. 1617. Iulij 13. By Robert Wilkinson Dr. in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to his Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Aspley, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY</hi> JAMES, <hi>BY the grace of God, King of great <hi rend="smallCaps">BRITAINE, FRANCE</hi> and <hi rend="smallCaps">IRELAND,</hi> &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Enowned and Beloued of God and man: As the Wisemen followed the starre in the East, so haue wee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed your Maiesty into the North, at your appointment wee haue preacht, and now at your command I haue put my selfe into the presse; To which I might haue answered, as one of the sons in the Gospell, yea, as one of your Presbyterian spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits lately answered you; <hi>Nolo,</hi> in flat terms I will not obey you; for why should so many men, the choise of two famous Churches, of so much greater learning of more and more excellent gifts, whom you haue heard not with attention only, but with admiration too, why (I say) should such and so manie escape the
<pb facs="3"/> publishing, &amp; I only to be set vpon the stage? yet I aske it not of your Maiestie, but of my selfe; and I thinke I haue found the reason of it, for as <hi>Izaak</hi> could not but know, that <hi>Iacob</hi> was better then <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sau,</hi> and yet loued <hi>Esau</hi> for the meat which hee brought him, so your Maiesty knoweth that there be in our society, who like <hi>Rebecca</hi> can make bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter venison of a kid, then I haue done of venison, &amp; yet you haue thus designed on me; therfore it was not I, but the argument, euen the peace (I spake of) which so affected you; especially to heare of peace in <hi>Scotland,</hi> but more especially to heare of peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland,</hi> the very meat vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly which your soule loueth: and therefore while I seeme to publish my Sermon, I print vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares your Maiesties praise, and make knowen to the world how highly your Highnes apprizeth peace; yea we haue lately seene it with our eies, that <hi>Iustice</hi> &amp; <hi>Peace</hi> are met in you, we haue seen you sitting in Parliament ten daies together, &amp; we are witnesses that once you sat from one at noone to ten at night; so much is Iustice beholden to you; And we haue hard from your Maiestie nothing here soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding but loue &amp; peace, you haue in your open Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament professed your loue to our English Nation;
<pb facs="3"/> you haue proclaimed great punishment on such as should abuse the meanest of our nation; you haue been of nothing more carefull then of our entertainment, &amp; such as haue kindly entertained vs, you haue open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thanked, you haue knighted &amp; honoured them for it; that as the <hi>Babylonians</hi> said of <hi>Cyrus, The King is become a Iew,</hi> so your Maiestie at this time hath been whollie English but it is your loue, as in <hi>England</hi> to cherish Scots, so in <hi>Scotland</hi> to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs, and euerie where to be kinde to strangers, &amp; it is your wisdom so to loue vs both, that your example might worke loue &amp; peace in both. And since we are returned in peace, first, with <hi>Iacob</hi> we set vp a piller of thanks to him who hath kept vs in our iourney; &amp; next to your Maiestie we giue, at least we repay the thankes which you your selfe vouchsafed your owne Subiects in our behalfe▪ &amp; for those your Subiects, we reioice to thinke that in all this time of our intercourse &amp; abode amongst them, we haue had no combate, but of kindes with them, &amp; in kindnes (we confesse) they haue euercome vs: yea, from the great <hi>Lo: Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of Scotland</hi> to the Colledge hals &amp; Burgers houses, we are debters &amp; prisoners, &amp; for entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that quality, as if anie man shall depraue it, he is like those men which raile on the Sun, &amp; like the
<pb facs="4"/> dogs which bark at the moone; yea, if any man shall embase what wee haue found so honourable, if hee were partaker of the iourney, I say, he is wilfully mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, but if he speak by heare-say, his heare-say is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie, &amp; he is falsly &amp; vncharitably credulous, yea if <hi>Scotland</hi> were as barren, as some report, which haue not seen it, we might report it for a wonder, that <hi>God hath prepared vs a table in the wildernes,</hi> for euery where we haue found cheerfull welcome, willing attendance, and of all things such abundance, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could bee complained of, but excesse, or if any thing were worse then that excesse, wee our selues brought it with vs, it was our owne vnthankfulnes: yea if our beasts could speake, they would acknowledge fulnes of the crib, &amp; say out of the Prophet <hi>Esay, we haue eaten cleane prouander winnowed and fanned,</hi> and shew themselues more thankfull to their benefactors, then many of their owners haue beene to God. That God, who hath euery where abundantly fed vs, who hath kept vs abroad, &amp; brought vs safely home, that God make vs thankfull to himselfe, &amp; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to them who haue well deserued of vs, and vpon your Maiesty (we beseech him) so to deriue the peace-makers blessing heere, as you may bee called eternally the sonne of God heereafter.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Maiesties euer most obliged and dutifull Chaplaine</hi> Robert Wilkinson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>