<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLATOVR TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102617_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01209</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11323</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102617</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLATOVR TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the loue of God. Written in french by B. Francis de Sales Bishope and Prince of Geneua, translated into English by Miles Car priest of the English Colledge of Doway</title>
                 <author>Francis, de Sales, Saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Pinchon (Pinson), Gerard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56, 790, 2 pages, 1 leaf of plates, portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="26"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLATOVR TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough it be true (courtuous Reader) that where honour is not aymed at, censure is not dreaded; yet that I might neither wrong my authour, nor come short in any point of ciuile regard to thee, I thought good, partly to implore thy fauour, partly to facilitate thy rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, by the ensuing aduertisements. Be pleased therefore to know, that our Authour, being one of the greatest Diuines of his tyme in France, speakes now and then in schoole tearmes
<pb facs="27"/> and formalities, which our English will scarcely beare, especially in the highest and hardest matters of diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as predestination, the Trinitie &amp;c. And againe I desired, that so worthy an Authour, should rather be heard speake in his owne words, then in my translation, esteeming FAITH, not SMOOTHNESSE the grace therof. Hence as farre forth as the language would permit, I haue ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred his owne words, turning BOVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIE Bountie (saie the like of diuers other words) which notwithstanding in the rigour of the schoole, should often rather haue bene turned GOOD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESSE, as being the obiect of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Will Hence also, AMITIE I haue translated, friendship, which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the approued custome of the schooles, should rather haue bene turned, LOVE, in the 212. pag. where
<pb facs="27"/> it signifieth the holy Ghost. But the learned Reader, will fauorably ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodate them according to the matter, and not reproue such words as necessitie, or fidelitie, made me ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, though they haue not yet gotten so free and knowen course in our English tongue. If I put for the rest of the faults, in sense or words, myne owne little skill, and lesse ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; and for the faults in the print (especially comma's, which as they are frequent, and serue diuers times for parentheses, so being omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or displaced, in lieu of clearing, they violate, or at least trouble the smoothnesse of the periode) the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters totall ignorance in the tongue (so that he will put as soone, TVB for, but, as BVT) my excuse will be as full and entire, as sincere. Some of the cheife faults you may find
<pb facs="28"/> in the end of the Booke; the rest, your discretion and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisie, will supplie and pardon. Adieu.</p>
   <pb facs="28"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>