<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the godly and peaceable Readers herof, grace and peace be multiplyed abundantly in CHRIST IESVS.</title>
           <author>Forester, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102530_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01074</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11187</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102530</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the godly and peaceable Readers herof, grace and peace be multiplyed abundantly in CHRIST IESVS.</title>
                 <author>Forester, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The marrovv and iuice of tvvo hundred and sixtie scriptures. Or Monas tessaragraphica : that is: the foure holy Scriptures of the Old and New Testament, appointed euery Sonday to be read in our Church of England, combined and brought vnto one chiefe head and point of doctrine: together with the rest of the holy Scriptures, set out also for the principall solemne Feasts of the Natiuitie, Circumcision, and Epiphany of our Lord and Sauiour Christ Iesus, of his resurrection, ascension, and sending downe the holy Ghost vpon his apostles, and the rest of the Church assembled (in vniformity) in Ierusalem, at the Feast of Pentacost. With 1 A generall harmony and connexion of all these together: and 2 A particular analyse of euery one of them: ... Extracted by Iames Forrester, minister of Gods word at Enderby neere Bullingbrooke in Lincolnshire, chapleine to th Queenes most excellent Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Forester, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 293, 11 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the godly and peaceable Readers herof, grace and peace be multiplyed abundantly in CHRIST IESVS.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE blessed, and most sacred Scriptures of God, penned by those holy <hi>Theopneusts,</hi> may well be resembled to the water os the sea, which is farre sweeter in the bottome then in the vpper part, and superficies. Whosoeuer meanes to partake the sweete relishing water of this euerliuing and euerlasting fountaine, must haue a bucket to draw with, for the well is deepe.</p>
   <p>The more linckes of graces, vertues, and godly diligence, that the chaine of this bucket containeth, and the more capacious that the bucket of his lowly heart is, in humility to come to the owneand founder of this well, the better hee shall speed at this inexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stible Ocean.</p>
   <p>If thou compare Scriptures with Scriptures, pondering all things, weighing and considering them well in thine heart, as the holy virgin <hi>Mary</hi> did: then shalt thou <hi>proue by the Scriptures, that Iesus is the Christ,</hi> that <hi>hee is waters,</hi> in the plurall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to quench the heate of thy thirsty soule.</p>
   <p>There shalt thou finde that hee is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> of the masculine gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the best wine of all, to comfort and exhilarate thy wearyed and sorrowfull heart. Then shall thou know that his word and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is that <hi>sincere, pure, vncorrupt, and vncurdled milke,</hi> wherewith, by his grace, thou shalt grow and increase from grace to grace, and vertue to vertue, till thou become an absolute man in Christ Iesu, ready for euery good worke. Then shalt thou be able to reproue the gaine-sayers, to conuince the contradictors and lyers against the truth.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>That this holy water drawne out after this manner, is of these most rare and inexplicable vertues, nothing can better teach thee then true experience in the Patriarches, <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> in <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Ioshua</hi> his successor, in <hi>Iosiah</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> in zealous <hi>Eliah</hi> and <hi>Micaiah.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In the cheerfull and vndaunted spirits and administrations of all Gods Prophets before <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> and of the <hi>Baptist</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, as also in the effects of the Apostles labours: In the peoples reuerent hearing, and diligent practising of Gods truth, in sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Scriptures for their further confirmation. In their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied labouring, toyling and paines taking, to grow and increase in their cōmenced knowledge. In louing and embracing the word of the kingdom aboue all other things. In their entertaining the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters as the Embassadors of Christ, as Christs faithfull stewards and vicegerents, as men vnreproueable, yea as the Angels of God.</p>
   <p>Oh that there were such an heart in the people of our lands, in the members of Christs Church in <hi>Great Brittaine,</hi> in the most strict and curious professors of Christs blessed Gospell. Then should the sonnes and children of the Church be as the flourishing plants growing and fructifying in grace and knowledge. Then should the daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> which attend vpon their Queene-mother the Church, be as the pollished <hi>corners of Salomons pallace,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 144.12.13, &amp;c.</note> and of <hi>the Temple Ierusalem.</hi> Then should Gods graniers be full and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding with all manner of good corne, the fruits of an holy profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. Then should the sheepe of Christ bring forth thousands and ten thousands of holy workes and good fruits, both in publicke and in priuate in the sight of God and men. Then should Christs Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, the true labouring oxen which tread out the corne, be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to take paines and strong vnto labour. Then should we haue no such rents, schismaticall factions, or diuisions, which cause ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny leadings into captiuity, and much complaining in our streets.</p>
   <p>But alas, I may cry out with <hi>Ieremy, My belly, my belly, I am pained at the very heart,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ieremy 4.19.</note>
      <hi>mine heart is troubled within me, I cannot be still, for my soule hath heard the sound of the trumpet, and the alarme of the battell.</hi> For amongst vs here in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> in stead of solacing our soules among the
<pb facs="7"/> sweet trees of Mirtles and Cinamon, the most odoriferous sents of the flowers of holy Scriptures, gathered out of the garden of Gods Booke: We haue our delights in the loathsome stinking <hi>Henbane</hi> (I must not say <hi>Tabacco</hi>) of smoking and fretting diuision. Soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out the Trompets, and striking vp the Alarme of carnall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention amongst our selues: Scorning our publicke seruice of God; because it is not after their owne humors: Scorning the Ministers of Gods Word and Sacraments, which are conformable to this Administration. Yea, and, which is most fearefull of all, scorning and loathing that sweete Dew and Manna which comes downe from heauen to vs by their ministery.</p>
   <p>For as there is one sort of Recusants among vs, which will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come to our publicke Assemblies, nor vnto the priuate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles of the factious:<note place="margin">
         <hi>H Barrow</hi> in his Discouery of the false Church.</note> So haue we another sort, who are Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, and will neither come to Seruice nor Sermons; because (say they) both Seruice, Sermons, Ministers, Administrations, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Gospel, yea Christ himselfe are adulterate, Popish &amp; Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Lamen. 2.10.11.12, &amp;c.</note>Godly gracious <hi>Ieremy</hi> was full of passions in beholding the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solations of the city Ierusalem, and the miseries of the inhabitants thereof, for that the children and sucklings were ready to die for bread in the streets of the city. His eies failed with teares, his bowels sweld, his liuer was powred vpon the earth. In his passionate maner he crieth out, Mine eye casteth out riuers of waters for the destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the daughter of my people,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.48.49.50, &amp;c.</note> Mine eye (saith he) droppeth without stay, and ceasseth not till the Lord looke downe and behold from heauen.</p>
   <p>I, that am the meanest among thousands of my coate, do wish with <hi>Ieremy</hi> that mine head were of water,<note place="margin">Ierem. 9.1.</note> and mine eies a fountaine of teares, that I might weep day and night, because of our yong &amp; old Ministers, and because of others that are not Ministers, both yong people and old of both sexes. For they with the desolate and wofull people of Ierusalem,<note place="margin">Lam. 2.12,</note> do cry out for bread and drinke spirituall, as they did for corporall food, to feed their swoning carcases.</p>
   <p>Those hunger-starued soules &amp; pining creatures had cause to cry for bread, being ready to giue vp the ghost in their mothers bosome.
<pb facs="7"/> The silenced Ministers, and the vndiscreet children and people of our Church, if they (with the orthodoxe Ministers and people of other reformed Churches) will enter into a true and due conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all circumstances; hauc little or no cause to cry out for the bread and drinke of their soules; sith God did neuer more bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully yeeld and bestow it then he hath in these our dayes.</p>
   <p>But bread from heauen will not serue the Israelites turne,<note place="margin">Numb 11.4.5.6.</note> their soules loathed Manna, they longed for Quailes, though they payd deere for their Lust and for their Quailes.</p>
   <p>The godly zealous and effectuall prayers in our booke of Common Prayer, conceiued and penned vpon sundry occasions, they be too grosse for our nice and daintie stomackes, which can away with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but their owne conceited (I should say) conceiued prayers, to be spoken and pronounced vpon the sodaine and ex-tempore. As though stinted and set formes of prayers, both in the time of the Law and Gospell, had not bene commanded by God the Father to the Priests then liuing, by Christ his sonne, to his Disciples, or that our Lord Iesus himselfe had not prayed and vsed the same prayer three seuerall times in the same words.<note place="margin">Math. 26.44. Marke 14.39.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Those holy and Canonicall Scriptures set out for most speciall vses to confirme the maine fundamentall points of Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (as our Censorians say) are wronged and wrung,<note place="margin">
         <hi>H. Barrow</hi> in the Discouery. &amp;c. and the most of our factious heads.</note> mangled and diuided to serue our superstitious vses of Dayes, Fasts, and Feasts.</p>
   <p>But beside the answers that I haue yeelded to this, and the like cauilling obiections and slanders, in my Proeme vnto this Booke, and those answers which Maister <hi>Hooker</hi> maketh in his booke called <hi>Ecclesiasticall Policie,</hi> I shall (if God giue life and meanes) in the Sermons which I intend to publish first, vpon the parcels of holy Scriptures appointed for the Gospels for euery Sonday, and all the great Feasts in the yeare, deliuer my mind at large to the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of euery one, except he be of his mind that sayd, <hi>Etiamsi suadeas, non persuade bis tamen.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Meane while, I beseech you to reade that briefe generall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion (in the end of the booke) of all the holy Scriptures, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to be read in our parish Churches and Congregations
<pb facs="8"/> for all the Sonnedayes and Feasts aforesayd: As also I pray you be pleased to view the <hi>Index</hi> or <hi>Table</hi> of all the two hundred and sixty Scriptures. Where it shall appeare vnto you, that the most of the Bookes, and the chiefe of the Chapters of the old Testament induced for the sound confirmation of Christians in the holy myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of godlinesse, are by a speciall direction of Gods spirit in those that culled them out, annexed vnto the Bookes, Chapters, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Applications of Scriptures in the new Testament.</p>
   <p>All which do so consequently and concordantly, and in so sweete an Harmony sound and agree together: as vnto euery plaine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest Christians view it shall appeare, That as <hi>Moses</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets spake of these things darkly and somewhat a farre off (as may beseene in the two first Lessons:) So our Lord Iesus Christ, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed all things in Action by his Preaching, Miracles, Death, Resurrection, &amp;c. which were fore prophecied of him, as is shewed in the Gospel. In like manner the Apostles and Euangelists ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts vs vnto the vs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and practise of all holy documents and instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as may be perceiued in the Epistles.</p>
   <p>Now that with one accord, in peace and vnitie, we may make vse of the diuine Scriptures sweete and most comfortable Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, let vs intreate the God of peace to knit our hearts together, that with one minde and mouth we may pray to God, and praise him in thought, word and deed. In this commendable Harmonie of soule, heart and voyce, let vs be glad and reioyce, and giue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Lord God Almightie, who hath raigned. Let vs with our spirituall musicke giue glory to him: because the mariage of the Lambe is come, and his wife hath made her selfe ready. <hi>And to her was granted that she should be arraied with pure fine linnen and shining: for the fine linnen is the righteousnesse of Saints.</hi> Euen so let vs all say (which loue that his appearing) <hi>Come Lord Iesus, come quickly.</hi> The grace of our Lord Iesus Christ be with our spirits, Amen. Farewell, From mine house this <hi>8</hi> of Ianuary <hi>1611.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friend to vse, IAMES FORRESTER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>