<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE Wandering-Jew, To the Wandering-Christian.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102802_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B13675</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11512</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102802</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE Wandering-Jew, To the Wandering-Christian.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvandering-Jew, telling fortunes to English-men</title>
                 <author>Gad ben-Arod, ben-Balaam, ben-Ahimoth, ben-Baal, ben-Gog, ben-Magog</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raworth, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 67, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE Wandering-Jew, To the Wandering-Christian.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or a <hi>Jew</hi> to wander it is no wonder, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are a scattered <hi>Nation:</hi> But a wandring Christian is a wonder indeed, for true Christians are, or ought to be fixed Starres, <hi>Errantes Stellae</hi> shine but dimly in <hi>Europes</hi> firmament, the other brightly; To sollid Okes then, that stand up and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver stirre, to Cedars whose heads knocke at the roofe of heaven, to the sacred trees on mount <hi>Libanon,</hi> whose branches reach to Paradice, to Rocks and Quarries whose roots cannot be pluckt up from their center, to Christians who are setled constant and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute I write not, nothing have I to doe with them; but because I am called the wandring <hi>Jew,</hi> I walke up and downe to finde out wandring Christians, are there any such Christians? No sure, (why then I write to no body.)</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>To wander, properly signifies, That the party (so walking) has gone right, but then stayes, as she pe doe, leaping out of their fold; If it be so? then sure there be wandring Christians: but how many sorts of wandring Christians are there, almost as many as there are men: For go no further then this kingdome, all that are called men, are not Christians, and all that are called Christians, are not men.</p>
   <p>Wandring Christians there are then, yes: how many great men have in this land wandred from their Loyalty? yet their heads met it in the end sleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on a blocke, how many brave Souldiers have wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from the true noble Discipline military, in stain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the glory of their victories with the barbarous effusion of too much blood, where mercy cryed aloud to sheath their swords; how many profound Schollers have been walking Candles, (not lighted) or if light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, have put out their owne flames and gone away stinking? how many deepe Lawyers have left the pathes of equitie to wander in the way of Bribes? how many rich men at this houre wander in the crooked windings of Extortion? how many (borne beggers) have by knavery, subtilty, basenesse, false weights, false measures, darke Lanthornes (false lights) wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred into wealth? how many wisemen wander to the
<pb facs="4"/> house of folly? how many husbands wander from their wives beds? how many wives from their husbands: and are not all these Christians? yes: wandring Christians. Art thou a Courtier? art thou a Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? art thou a Merchant? art thou a Shop-keeper? art thou a good man? art thou a bad? Reade what is written in the Iews face, and thou mayst prove a set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Christian, be what thou wilt: If thou desires to foresee what shall befall thee upon this Booke, if thou canst not finde the full weight of thy fortune yet in one scale or other there lies a dramme; there's a Iewes Lottery, and lots of severall valuations: No blanks, all prizes; Injoy them, and the love of him who bids thee draw, and wishes thee a noble fortune.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy wandring Friend, Gad Ben-arod, Ben Balaam, Ben-Ahimoth, Ben-Baal, Ben-Gog, Ben-Magog.</signed>
      <salute> Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>