<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE COMPASSIONATE, THAT IS, TO THE TRVLY CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
           <author>Fitz-Geffry, Charles</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102148_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00816</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10937</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102148</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE COMPASSIONATE, THAT IS, TO THE TRVLY CHRISTIAN READER.</title>
                 <author>Fitz-Geffry, Charles</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Compassion towards captives : chiefly towards our bretheren and country-men who are in miserable bondage in Barbarie. Vrged and pressed in three sermons on Heb. 13.3. Preached in Plymouth, in October 1636. By Charles Fitz-Geffry. Whereunto are anexed an Epistle of St Cypria concerning the redemption of the bretheren fromthe bondage of barbarians; and A passage concerning the benefits of compassion, extracted out of St Ambrose his second booke of Offices, cap. 28</title>
                 <author>Fitz-Geffry, Charles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Forrest, Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 50, 10 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE COMPASSIONATE, THAT IS, TO THE TRVLY CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>MONG all the workes of mercy there is none more comfortable to the receiver, more acceptable to <hi>Christ,</hi> the great <hi>rewarder,</hi> and consequently none more profitable to the <hi>doer,</hi> then the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Christians</hi> from the bondage of <hi>Infidels.</hi> If to visit them only, to afford them some comfort by presence, by kinde speaches, be a worke whereof the <hi>Iudge</hi> himselfe in the last day will take speciall notice, as done unto himselfe, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I was in prison and you visited me;</hi> how much more so to visit them as to procure their freedome? In so much that the <hi>Redeemer</hi> himselfe shall say, <hi>I was in prison and you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed mee.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>See S.</hi> Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>Epistle at the end of the last sermon.</hi>
      </note>
   </p>
   <p>What better worke can <hi>man</hi> performe for <hi>Christ</hi> then that which was the best worke which <hi>Christ</hi> performed for <hi>man.</hi> And what was that but <hi>Redemption.</hi> Had he created us and not redeemed us, it had bin better that he had never crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us. Had he come from heaven to earth (as he did) to bee incarnate for us, had he wrought never so many miracles, taught never so heavenly doctrine, had he made us never so rich, never so wise, never so great in this world, had he made us Kings over so many Kingdomes as the Devill once shewed
<pb facs="5"/>
him, what had all this profited us if he had not redeemed us? How can that worke but be most acceptable unto him, which is the best resemblance of the best worke he ever did for us? <hi>Redemption! Redemption!</hi> The greatest benifit we receive by <hi>Christ,</hi> the best worke of mercy wee can extend to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For performance of which worthy worke, and consequently of ensuring unto us the promised reward, what a faire oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity is presented unto us in these calamitous times? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it pleased God that many of our bretheren should be mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that we may be happie in being charitable; and that some should grone under the intolerable burthen of Turkish bondage, to try whether <hi>Christians</hi> will be so kinde unto <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> as Turks are reported to be unto unreasonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to whom (in this kinde) they are said to be strangely cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Bidduph.</hi> Travells.</note> If they see one who hath caught a bird they will give twice the price of it while it is alive to that which it will yeeld being dead only to give it liberty and life. And some of them are said to give mony to men and boyes to take and bring unto them living birds, that the birds may be beholding to them for their freedome. With what face shall wee looke upon our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer,</hi> if we be not as charitable to our bretheren under <hi>Turks,</hi> as <hi>Turks</hi> are to birds, to reasonlesse creatures, who are (upon the matter) unreasonable creatures themselves?</p>
   <p>What heart can chuse but relent, if not rend a sunder at the relation of these intolerable pressures indured by <hi>Christians</hi> under these savage <hi>Barbarians</hi>? their Faires and markets ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of our men then ours are of horses and cattle: Christians there bought, sold, cauterized, scared, as wee doe beasts, by those who are <hi>bipedum nequissimi,</hi> of all too footed beasts most brutish: yoaked together like oxen; their owne oxen and horses keeping <hi>Holy-day,</hi> while our miserable bretheren doe beare their burthens and plough the fields to favour them; yet not allowed, when they have thus laboured the whole day, as competent sustenance &amp; convenient lodging as we doe our hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses &amp; oxen, but more cruelly beaten when they have done their
<pb facs="5"/>
worke, then our beasts are by us when they worke not as wee would: Sometimes layd flat on their bellies, and receiving an hundred blowes or more on their backes: sometimes on their backes, and so belly-beaten that they seeme tympanous, and bladders rather then bellies: sometimes balled with tough cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels on the soles of their feet, untill their feet be swolne unto foot-bals, and so left to crall away, vsing as well as they can, their hands insteed of feet. how many upon slight suspition and false suggestion of a fault, have beene dragged through the streets on the hard stones by ropes or coards fastned into their bored feet? The very pictures of which torments, what eyes, save those which stand in Turkes heads can behold with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out teares? I will not aggravate those grievances which are already too great by inserting reports how they are aggravat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by some of our nation, who should rather with every true hearted Christian, endevour to ease them, not adding more affliction to such heavie bonds. Charity bids me to be incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of that, which griefe and passion causeth some of ours bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to divulge, that there are among us who for their private gaine doe not a little advance the prevailing of the common enemy against their country-men and brethren; that ours are surprised with our owne powder and shot, and afterwards la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in <hi>Barbarie</hi> with English gyves and yrons. God forbid that it should be so; but if it be so, may it not be probablie conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (at least conjectured) that those incestuous arrowes which have dispersed the noisome Pestilence have come out of this quiver of not compassionating our woefull brethren, but rather augmenting their woes?</p>
   <p>God (I hope) will raise up some happie hand to exhibite to our gratious <hi>Soveraignes</hi> eyes &amp; eares <hi>Danmoniorum gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> as our predecessors the old <hi>Brittons</hi> pressed by the <hi>Picts,</hi> presented unto the <hi>Consul Boëtius, Britannorum gemitus;</hi> (but with better successe.)</p>
   <p>Neither will that illustrious <hi>Peere,</hi> the Oracle of Iustice in our land, faile to performe what he is said to have promised at <hi>Plymouth</hi> with tearefull eyes (the evidences of a tender and
<pb facs="6"/>
truly religious heart) to the mournfull wives and children of these oppressed captives, that when he returned to the Court, he would become their advocate unto the Majestie of the King. <hi>Remember him ô my God concerning this, who is so vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant in doing justice at home, that he is not dormant in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending mercy to those who suffer extreame misery abroad.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If any doe aleadge that our owne wants will not suffer us to succour them in theirs, I say so too: I acknowledge it that our wants who are at libertie doe restraine us from releiuing our brethren, who are in barbarous captivity. But what wants? <hi>Want of charity,</hi> want of the <hi>bowels of mercy,</hi> want of <hi>Christian compassion,</hi> want of feeling our brethrens wants, and consequently of true <hi>Christianity,</hi> these these are the wants that doe hinder us. How much hath beene lavishly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended in <hi>Pompes,</hi> in <hi>Playes,</hi> in <hi>Sibariticall-feasts,</hi> in <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leon sutes,</hi> and <hi>Proteus-fashions,</hi> besides other vanities, and yet there is no complaining of want? How many soules might have beene ransommed from that <hi>Hell</hi> on <hi>Earth, Barbarie,</hi> with halfe these expences? Yet heerein doe men only complaine of want. Of all others let us beware of this want of compassion toward our lamentable captived Brethren; of whose insuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table bondage if wee have no feeling, we our selves are in a farre worse thraldome, as one passage in these ensuing <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> will shew us.</p>
   <p>Neither am I singular in this sentence: sweet <hi>Salvian</hi> doubteth not to affirme so much of the men of <hi>Carthage</hi> (while <hi>Carthage</hi> yet was <hi>Christian</hi>) who frequented stage-playes, feasted, froliked, while some of the Brethren were slaine by the enemy, others carried away into captivity. As sometimes King <hi>Ahasuerus</hi> and <hi>Haman</hi> sate drinking in the Palace, while the City <note n="†" place="margin">
         <hi>Hest. 3.15.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Shushan</hi> was in perplexity▪ so among them, <note n="*" place="margin">Circumso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>abant armis muros Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis populi Barbarorum, &amp; Ecclesia Carthaginen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis insaniebat in circis, luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riabat in thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Alij fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris jugulaban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, alij intu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> fornicabantur. Pars plebis erat foris cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiva hostium, pars intus cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiva vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m: Cujus sors pejor fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit incertum est. Illi qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem erant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinsecus in carne, sed isti intus mente captivi; &amp; ex duobus le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talibus malis, levius, ut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, captivita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem corporis Christianam, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m captivitatem animae sustinere. An credimus fortè quòd captivus animo pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus iste non fuerit, qui l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tus tum in suorum captivitatibus suit? captivus corde &amp; sensu non fuit, qui inter suorum supplicia vivebat, qui iugulari se in suorum jugulis non intelligebat▪ qui morise in suorum mortibus non putabat? <hi>Salvian. de Guber. Dei▪ l. 6.</hi>
      </note>while the walles of their City were surrounded with the sound
<pb facs="6"/>
of the armour of the barbarous beseiger, some of the Citizens (yea of the Church) were mad-merrie at the Theater. Some were slaine without, others committed fornication within. Part of the people without the City▪ were made captive by the enemy, part of them within made themselves captives unto vices. And these of the two deadly evills underwent the worst, it being more tolerable to a true Christian to sustaine the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of the <hi>body,</hi> then of the <hi>soule,</hi> as our <hi>Saviour</hi> affirmeth the Death of the <hi>soule</hi> to be more formidable, then the Death of the body. Can we be perswaded that such a people was not captived in minde, who could be so merrie in their brethrens captivity? Is not he a captive in minde and understanding, who can laugh among the slaughters of his brethren, who understands not that his owne throat is cut in theirs, who thinks not that he himselfe dyes in their Deathes? Thus or to this purpose that elegant authour. Whose words were they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven (as I wish they were) in the hearts of our sin-enslaved <hi>Libertines,</hi> there were some good hope, that they would first strive to be freed themselves from their spirituall bondage, and then they would be more sensible of their brethrens cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall thraldome. In the midst of their myrth they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their mercy, and account that they should dearely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere for every penny lavisht out in vanity, which ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have beene employed in procuring their Christian coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-mens liberty. And as the Elder <hi>Plinie</hi> said to his nephew, when he saw him walke out some houres without studying,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Plin. l. 3. ep. 5.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Poteras has horas non perdere</hi>: so would these say to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of their wastfull and, commonly, sinfull expences, I might have chosen whether I would have lost this mony: I might have saved it by bestowing it either towards the redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of my enthralled brethren in <hi>Barbarie,</hi> or on the reliefe of their wreched Wives and Children at home; and so have made a more advantagious returne, then any of our Merch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants doe by their most thriving adventures into any parts of <hi>Barbarie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To perswade men to this heavenly improovement of some
<pb facs="7"/>
part of their meanes, are these poore meditations sent abroad by him who inlie compassionates his brethrens importable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, wishing all blessings to those charitable soules, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their abilities doe endevour to support them; And for all his travells herein craveth nothing but your prayers for himselfe, and your charity towards them, for whom he inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth, professing himselfe</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>His distressed Brethrens</hi> dayly sollicitour <hi>CHARLES FITZ-GEFFRY.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>