<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO THE RIGHT Honorable my singular good Lorde and Maister, the Earle of Lennox, Dauid Rowland wisheth a happie increase of Honour and yeares in this life.</title>
           <author>Rowland, David</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102582_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11087</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21356</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102582</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO THE RIGHT Honorable my singular good Lorde and Maister, the Earle of Lennox, Dauid Rowland wisheth a happie increase of Honour and yeares in this life.</title>
                 <author>Rowland, David</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A comfortable ayde for scholers : full of varietie of sentences, gathered out of an Italian authour, by Dauid Rowland</title>
                 <author>Grifoni, Giovanni Andrea</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 140, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ TO THE RIGHT <hi>Honorable my singular good</hi> Lorde and Maister, the Earle of <hi>Lennox, Dauid Rowland wisheth <hi>a happie increase of Honour and</hi>
      </hi> yeares in this life.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsideringe with my selfe (right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and my singular good Lorde) howe in respect of time well imployed, no Iewell can be thought precious or comparable, nor any thinge more vnpleasant to the vertuous minde, then the remembrance of the euill and idle bestowyng therof: I haue thought good as well for the auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of Idelnesse (Mother of all
<pb facs="3"/>
vice) as also, for the zeale I beare to this my natiue Countrey, to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect these Sentences, varied many waies, out of the Jtalian Authour Intituled in that toungue <hi>Spec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chio de la lingua Latina,</hi> and to English them al vnder the name of <hi>A Comfortable ayde for Scholars,</hi> whiche I haue chiefly done in the fauour of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippes noble and towarde Sonne, trustinge that by healpe hereof, he may more easely attaine to a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowledge in that tongue: wherin as your honour is most desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous he should profite, so, (thāks be
<pb facs="3"/>
to God) he is now already well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered: and now that I haue finished my labour, supposinge some younge studientes may (if they will) reape commoditie therby, and that being published, it may rather doo good, then harme: J haue presumed thus rudely and simply to set foorth the same, determinyng for diuerse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations to bestowe it (beyng the first fruites of my trauell) rather vpon your Honour (as dutie bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me, beynge my good Lorde and Maister) then vpō any other persone: because I knowe none whome I thought would more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorably
<pb facs="4"/>
accept my doinge, nor who of dutie might more iustely clayme the same then your Lordship, vnto whome I do now moste humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate this my trauell, as a token of my true and affectionate seruice, meanynge hereby outwardely to shewe, what the inwarde desire is willinge to doo, if power and habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie were therunto correspondent. And nowe, for full accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and perfection of this meane woorke, resteth no more behind but your Lordshippes Honorable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to protect the same, whiche J most humbly beseche you to receiue
<pb facs="4"/>
into your noble tuition, as well to geue countinance and credite to the same, as also goynge forth in your Lordships name, to be an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion vtterly to depresse the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant and sclaunderous tongues of the simple and vnlearned sorte: agaynste whose iniuries neither good will nor labour is able to with stande, but only the maintenance of my cause by your Honorable protection thereof, pleasinge to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in good parte this poore at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of mine, whiche doinge your Lordshippe shall hereafter incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage me to bestowe my trauell in
<pb facs="5"/>
matters of greater importaunce, and to acknowledge my self much bound to your Honour, vnto whom I nowe moste humbly submitte my selfe and my doynges, besechynge Almighty God fauourably to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende, and gouerne your Lordship in this life, and after that, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to cōduct you to the vnspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ioyes of his kingdome. Anno <hi>1568.</hi> The <hi>.16.</hi> of May.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>By your L. most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and bounden Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt <hi>Dauid Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>