<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface to the true Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102282_Fr7_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11041</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102282</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface to the true Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The diamond of deuotion : cut and squared into sixe seuerall points: namelie, 1 The footpath to felicitie. 1 2 A guide to godlines. 81 3 The schoole of skill. 181 4 A swarme of bees. 209 5 A plant of pleasure. 245 6 A groue of graces. 283 Full of manie fruitfull lessons, auaileable to the leading of a godlie and reformed life: by Abraham Fleming</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William, Assignee(s) of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 320, 4 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="143"/>
   <pb n="285" facs="143"/>
   <head>A Preface to the true <hi>Christian Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the benefits of God are manifold, or rather infinite, bestowed vpon man, from the time of his creation, euen so ought the fruites of his obedience &amp; thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse to be aboundant and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull. For, if a man hauing diuers good friends, but some more bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall than othersome, sheweth himselfe most officious and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to them, of whome he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued most commoditie: by how much the greater reason ought we so to behaue our selues in all kinde of holie seruice towards God, who hath heaped vpon vs more bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, than the tongue of anie man can vtter, or his memorie conteine?</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="144"/>We see that all things are created by God, all things nourished by him, all things increased by him, all things multiplied by him, and all things preserued by him, for the vse of man, vnto whose gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he hath committed them, put him in full possession, and giuen him a lordlie title ouer them, to vse and dispose at his pleasure: requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at his hands for this singular bountifulnesse, nothing but an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding hart, a renewed mind, and religious lips, which might tell abroade the great goodnes of so lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a God, and stir vp others to magnifie his name.</p>
   <p>And although we ought to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God at all times, according to the continued course of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion and kindnesse shewed vnto vs, from the daie of our birth, vntill this present houre, sundrie and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie waies, as well in clothing vs, as also in nourishing and feeding vs, besides other inuisible graces, which not appearing to the world,
<pb facs="144"/>
can not so well be remembred: yet, because my purpose is particular, and stretcheth no further than to Christian dutifulnesse, proper vnto God for his dailie blessings presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs all vpon our ordinarie tables, I would not wish thee (good Reader) to looke for anie other matter at my hands, than the verie title of this treatise doth import, which I haue called by the name of <hi>A Groue of Graces.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>For as in a Groue there do growe manie plants of great varietie and choice, the weakest and slenderest whereof may in due and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time do some good and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie seruice: euen so (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) thou hast heere in this Groue sundrie good Graces put into thine hands, some in verse, and othersome in prose, all and euerie of them tending to Gods glorie, as blessings and thanksgiuings vnto his diuine Maiestie, for his vnspeakeable cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, and fatherlie prouidence, which he hath ouer vs sinfull and
<pb facs="145"/>
wretched creatures, whereof the Lord giue vs grace to continue mindfull, and keepe vs in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent vse of his good gifts, for Iesus Christes sake, our onlie mediator and aduocate, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Abraham Fleming.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>