<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>F., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102003_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00627</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10763</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102003</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>F., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fennes frutes : vvhich vvorke is deuided into three seuerall parts; the first, a dialogue betweene fame and the scholler ... The second, intreateth of the lamentable ruines which attend on vvarre ... The third, that it is not requisite to deriue our pedegree from the vnfaithfull Troians, who were chiefe causes of their owne destruction: whereunto is added Hecubaes mishaps, discoursed by way of apparition</title>
                 <author>Fenne, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Oliffe (Olive), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 91, 20 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight curteous, gentle, and learned Reader, as dutie bindeth mee, I am determined to inuite thee to a base and simple banquet: for knowing that thou art dayly inuited &amp; bidden to manie more curious and daintie dishes, that thy appetite is sufficed with all kinde of delicates: therefore, in mine opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, by staying thee from thy delicious meates, by inuiting thee to more homelie fare, thy stomacke may be the more whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; sharpned to take thy repast of those dainties, when occasion serueth. It may be, that when thou shalt perceiue my principall and chiefest Guest, for whom this banquet was first proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, (whose mouth is daylie vsed to the sweetest delicates, and whose tongue is of sufficient iudgement to make a difference betwixt the sower taste of vnpleasant cates, and the sweete relish and sauer of well seasoned meates:) for manner sake to commend the dishes, and gratefully accept the good will of the inuiter: that then thou wilt accordingly take in good part and well like of such homely cheere, as the willing bidder hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for thee. But if it should so fall out, that thy mouth being so often accustomed with the sweete taste and relish of daintie fare, that thy sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke can hardly digest the homelines of my reare supper: yet I assure thee, that the cates themselues be as daintie &amp; neweltie as the best, thogh not so well dressed by the vnskilfulnesse of the Cooke. Therefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to vse the part of a friendly guest, in taking it in good woorth and reporting the best: and further I request thee, if thou findest fault or mislikest anie dish, being not well dressed, rather to winke priuelie at the Cooke, than openly to discredit his workmanship Perhaps, it may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obiected to the discredit of the workman, saying, It was great pitie that such daintie delicates hapned to be bought of so simple a cater, to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to so homely a cooke, to be dressed in so smokie a kitchin: wherby the dishes haue not their right, and their taste and relish spoyled, by reason of the basenesse of the roome. To which obiection, with reason I thus may reply: that the vnskilfull cooke may sometime take in hand to dresse the daintiest dish, as well as the cunning and finest workman to learne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience: for he that ventreth not the marring or making, shal neuer attain to good workmanship. Thus (gentle Reader) hauing inuited thee to this base banquet, play thou not like the dogge in a manger, that will eate
<pb facs="5"/>
no hay, nor suffer those that would: wherefore I pray thee either fall too thy selfe, or giue others leaue to satisfie their hunger, whose stomackes are sufficiently prepared to feed. I would not haue it thought, that I tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough a vainglorious minde, goe about to edifie and instruct the learned, whose ripe iudgements, wise conceipts, and learned experience, is of suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient force to teach better Schollers than my selfe, for then should I goe about, <hi>arenas in littus fundere:</hi> but for that I right well know, there are diuers, whose learning is not of that profunditie, but they may take both pleasure and profite, by reading this homely worke. Is it not reported, that <hi>Aeneas</hi> comming to <hi>Carthage</hi> (there viewing and perusing the destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Troy,</hi> being painted on the wall of <hi>Didoes</hi> pallaice) with his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full companion <hi>Achates,</hi> to haue more imaginations and thoughts in his minde concerning the effect and substaunce, than the wall by painting could signifie, yet notwithstanding the picture first caused those thoghts (by representing the matter) to reuolue in his experienced minde: so that the setting downe of a part, causeth the wise to conceiue the whole: and by penning a briefe, the learned coniectureth a volume. Therefore (curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader) I am content to appeale to thy learned iudgement: for <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles</hi> setting foorth his picture to heare each mans opinion in his worke begun, was verie wel content, when the shoomaker found fault with the shooe, and the taylor with the hose: knowing these men to be artificers in the Science which they had reprehended, did willingly reforme his errour. But when the vnskilfull intruded themselues to the iudgement of the legges, armes, and other parts of the bodie: then he drewe in his pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, knowing that hee should neuer please and satisfie the humour and fancie of all men. Thus, Fare thee well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy friend in what I may. <hi>T. F.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>