<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣nourable
THOMAS Earle of
Arundel, primer Earle of England, and
one of his Maiesties most honou∣rable
Councell, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Gainsforde, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102839_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01405</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11525</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102839</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣nourable
THOMAS Earle of
Arundel, primer Earle of England, and
one of his Maiesties most honou∣rable
Councell, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Gainsforde, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true and vvonderfull history of Perkin VVarbeck, proclaiming himselfe Richard the fourth</title>
                 <author>Gainsford, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 112, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
THOMAS Earle of
Arundel, primer Earle of England, and
one of his Maiesties most honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
Councell, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch as my poore selfe, that am
only a looker on of your vertues,
as a Passenger in a streete behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
the Frontispice of some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate
Edifice, but debarred the
entrance and search into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
roomes, must be contented,
or if you please indebted to the
opinion and report of others; which I haue found so
ample and enlarged concerning your great <hi>Honour,</hi>
and greater worthinesse, that I will forbeare any further
insinuation, least I step into a kind of flattery, a vice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident
to most men, refused of none, yet in all fortunes
to be disclaimed of a Gentleman: only I must adde
this, that I am proud of mine owne assurance, that you
are borne to adorne our Country, and illustrate our
Court, wherein your industrie, loyaltie, and immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
truth shall make your vertues compleat and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant.
Therefore <hi>great Lord</hi> haue I chosen out this
<pb facs="3"/>
History, meerely for the strangenesse, and <hi>charactred
you the Patron</hi> of my endeauours for the obseruations,
that the remarkeable passages heerein proposed, of
which euen <hi>Scotland</hi> had a part, may serue for all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
in such dignity and eminent places, both for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept,
and caution.</p>
   <p>For <hi>Precept,</hi> to florish in their owne honours, and
moue in their owne orbes, sticking close to the glory
of their Countrie, and clinging to the sides of Maiesty,
that the King may aske, what shall be done to the man,
whom he would honour, and the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
them with <hi>Panegyricall</hi> applauses, who preserue
her peace from the rauishing, and deforming of stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
be the hopes to the contrary neuer so probable,
or inductiue.</p>
   <p>For <hi>Caution,</hi> not once to put any confidence in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers,
nor belieue the Diuell himselfe, though he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise
to giue the Kingdomes of the World, which are
none of his: yet, I confesse him <hi>Prince</hi> of the same,
that is, of the abuses and impieties therein both raging,
and raigning: and the rather, because the end hath euer
beene perdition of body, soule, honour, estates and
posteritie: nor can the pleading of simplicitie in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction,
or ignorance in the credulity serue the turne:
For though <hi>Princes</hi> ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y times haue beene drawne to
pardon the offences of Subiects, and refractary delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents,
wallowing or rather sunk ouer head &amp; eares in
the mierie bogs of such conuulsions: yet are they not
alwaies to be presumed vpon, nor will the <hi>Common-wealth</hi>
endure the indignitie, or giue way to any person
whatsoeuer in vilipending the gouernment.</p>
   <p>I humbly therefore request your <hi>Honour</hi> to reade
<pb facs="3"/>
ouer this true and strange Story, and take in worth my
good meaning, which presenteth the same vnto you
I protest without any other motiue, then to see you flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish,
as a supportation of our <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and iewel
of our kingdome. As for the faults and my presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
I expect, that that vertue and goodnesse, which
must make you famous in this world, and happy in the
world to come, will extend but her owne properties to
my pardon and admission, knowing that if I haue done
ill; wisdome is not bought in the market, and yet God
bids vs come without money; if well, it is in your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
fauour, and noble acceptation.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours humble obser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ant
<hi>THOMAS GAINS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ORDE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>