<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102468_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15342</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20088</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102468</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatie of iustification. Founde emong the writinges of Cardinal Pole of blessed memorie, remaining in the custodie of M. Henrie Pyning, chamberlaine and general receiuer to the said cardinal, late deceased in Louaine. Item, certaine translations touching the said matter of iustification, the titles whereof, see in the page folowing</title>
                 <author>Pole, Reginald</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fowler (Fouler), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 98, 2, 77, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S all Scripture inspired by God is profitable to teache and instructe in rightuousenes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note>
      <hi>to the ende that a godly man maie be perfecte, instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to al good woorkes:</hi> so is there no pointe or article thereof more expediente for a Christian man to seeke, more necessary to find and know, more comfortable rightly to vnderstand, and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to remember and practise, then is the trewe and right knowledge of his Iustification, and the maner how the same is atteined. We are sure by the Scripture, that <hi>a wicked man and his wickednes</hi> bothe like <hi>are hateful vnto God:</hi> Neither can there be looked for any other thing,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Sap.</hi> 14.</note> then heauy punishement and iust damnation, where the anger and displeasure of God is vnpacified once iustely deserued, and not taken awaie by some meanes to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation. We doubt not also, but that all men are borne <hi>naturally the children of anger,</hi> that is to saie,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.</note> in Gods dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure and indignation, as branches of a condemned stocke, a thral kinde and bonde race of one man,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note>
      <hi>by whom sinne entred into the world, and by sinne death, and so wente through all, in whome all haue sinned.</hi> And what can be so pleasaunt to a captiue, as to vnderstande truely the way and meanes of his deliuerance, or so comfortable to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son bonde and thrall, as to know, not onely how he maie be made free, but also how he maie be brought in speciall fauor with his Lorde, by whom onely he must liue, or els perish? Finally how he maie be made a childe, <hi>a sonne,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>and heire to him,</hi> vnto whom he was a stranger before.</p>
   <p>And bicause no man,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.</note> be he neuer so rightuouse and
<pb facs="3"/> iuste,<note place="margin">Aug. de ciuitate Dei. li. <hi>21.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi> Galat. <hi>5.</hi> Ioan. <hi>5.</hi> Cypria. de Elcemos.</note>
      <hi>liueth here without sinne,</hi> and fewe there are of that happy estate, that fal not into damnable and mortal sinne, <hi>the doers whereof shall not possesse the kingdome of God:</hi> sith also a law is appointed vs by our Physition, that once made vs hole, who saied: <hi>Thou arte made hole, nowe sinne no more: we were,</hi> as S. Cyprian saieth, <hi>driuen to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>arowe straite, hauing a precise lawe of innocency prescribed vnto vs, neither coulde the weakenesse of mannes frailtie, tell what to do, if God of his mercy had not appointed a waie and meane, how man, that by sinne falleth from iustice after his Baptisme, may be restored to rightuousnes and iustice againe.</hi> Further it suffiseth not a Christian man to be made righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouse, and to be set in the state of iustice, vnlesse he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinewe and perseuere in the same:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 24</note>
      <hi>for he shal be saued, that continueth vnto the ende.</hi> Also he muste increase in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuousenes:<note place="margin">Apoca. <hi>22</hi> Leo Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. <hi>8.</hi> de passio. Do.</note> for so the Scripture teacheth vs: <hi>Let him that is iuste, be yet iustified:</hi> for trewely is it saied: <hi>Quantumli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet quisque iustificatus sit, habet tamen dum in hac vita est, quo probatior esse possit &amp; melior: Qui autem non proficit, deficit: &amp; qui nihil acquirit, non nihil perdit.</hi> Euery man, be he neuer so much iustified, yet maie he while he is in this life be more tried and better: and who so encreaseth not, faileth and goeth backeward, and he that getteth nothing, loseth somewhat. For whiche causes it behoueth vs, not onely to knowe how we are made iuste and rightuouse, but also how we be restored to Iustice when we fal: and how we maie continewe and increase in rightuousenes, when we be restored: and finally attaine to saluation and glory, which is the ende of Iustification, and without the which all Iustification in this life auaileth nothing, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther turneth to a heape and increase of our damnation:
<pb facs="3"/> bicause as Oecumenius saith,<note place="margin">Oeco. in <hi>2.</hi> cap. Iaco.</note>
      <hi>Like vnprofitable seruantes we receiue our maisters mony, and make no gaine thereof:</hi> that is to saie, <hi>we receiue his grace in vaine.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This being vnderstanded,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.</note> how necessary and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the knowledge of this Article is, and seing also, that a man, runne he neuer so fast, yet if he runne out of the way, he neuer commeth to the right end of his iourney, to the intente thou be not induced to iudge amisse in so greate a matter, and to thee so necessary, I haue (Christian Reader) with the hope of Gods helpe indeuoured my selfe to laie before thine eies particularly as briefely and plainely as I coulde, the maner of our Iustification in Christ with the circumstances belonging to the same. Grounding my selfe chiefely in al pointes through the Treatie vpon the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and holy Worde of God.<note place="margin">
         <hi>2.</hi> Petr. <hi>1.</hi> Aug. lib. Confess. <hi>12</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi>
      </note> And bicause the same <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, nor ought to be of any mannes priuate interpretation, (for he that goeth abowt to drawe it to his owne priuat sense, shall be depriued of it)</hi> I haue taken suche construction thereof, as the holy Ghost hath deliuered and taught his Church, and suche as the auncient Fathers of sundry ages and places agreeing togethers haue lerned in the Church and vttered in their writinges to teach other. Emong whom I haue especially and moste of all other folowed the auctoritie of S. Augustine, as wel for that he hath wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten most largely of this matter, as also bicause suche as be of the contrary parte in moste credite,<note place="margin">Luthe. Philip. Melan. Calui. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitut. cap. <hi>18. 1.</hi> Tim. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note> and haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in this time, confesse, <hi>that in the Doctrine of the Churche he is a moste faithefull declarer of antiquitie:</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending therby to discharge my selfe, as teaching nothing but that I haue learned <hi>in Goddes Church the state and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of truthe,</hi> and geeuing thee thereby good occasion I
<pb facs="4"/> trust, readily to beleue that thou shalt heere reade.</p>
   <p>But as I haue declared vnto thee, that the right know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of this pointe concerning our Iustification, is to a Christian man most necessary and comfortable: so must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> aduertise thee, that the mistaking and wrong vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereof,<note place="margin">Aristo. Ethic.</note> is most dangerouse. For as the Philosophers saie, that euery vertue is besette of eche side with a vice contrary to it: so S. Augustine writeth, that <hi>the true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Iustification,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug. in Praesa. Psal. <hi>31.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>hath of eche side of it, a deepe and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouse fall, so that who so goeth out of the streight waie thereof on the right or lefte hand, falleth downe hedlong, and casteth awaie him selfe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Into the one danger, and of the one side they fall, that presume of themselues, thinking to be iustified by them selues, by their owne strength and rightuousnes, without the helpe and grace of God.<note place="margin">August. suprà.</note> Of them he saith: <hi>Si se in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciam quandam, &amp;c.</hi> If a man lift him selfe vppe vnto a boldenes of presumption, <hi>and presume of his owne strength and iustice, and purpose in his minde to fulfil iustice, and to doe all that is commaunded in the lawe, offending in nothing, and thinke to haue his life in his owne power, that he slide no where, faile no where, stumble no where, see darcke and dymme nowhere, and attribute this to the power of his owne will, although peraduenture he fulfil al things that seeme iust in mennes sight, so that nothing be founde in his life that may be blamed of menne, yet God condemneth the very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption and vaunting of pride.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The other hedlong fall is on the contrary side, and into it suche men fall, as pretending their owne infirmitie and weakenes do no good deedes, and trust and presume one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be saued by Gods grace and mercie though they liue vngodly, of whome also S. Augustine saith in the same
<pb facs="4"/> place: <hi>Si se infirmitati, &amp;c.</hi>
      <note place="margin">August. vbi suprà.</note>
      <hi>If a man yelde himselfe vppe to his owne weakenesse fully and wholy, and bende himselfe to this cogitation to say, bicause the mercy of God is readie for all sinners vnto the ende, in what so euer sinnes they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, if they beleue that God deliuereth, God forgeueth, so that no wicked men that haue faith and beleue, shal perish, that is to say, none of them shall perish, that say to them selues, what so euer I doe, with what so euer outrages and shamefull dedes I be distained, sinne I neuer so much, God of his mercy deliuereth mee bicause I haue beleued in him: he then that saith no such menne perish, by that euil thinking is moued to sinne freely. And the iust God, vnto whom mercy is songe and iudgement, not mercy onely, but iudgement also, findeth man yll presuming of him selfe, and abusing Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to his owne destruction, and of necessity such a one must be damned.</hi> And somewhat after that he saith: <hi>Quid igitur fit?</hi> What shall we then doe? <hi>If a man iustifie him selfe, and presume of his owne iustice, he falleth. If a man conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and thinking upon his owne weakenesse, and presuming of the mercy of God, haue no care to cleanse his owne life of his sinnes, and drowne him selfe in all the goulfe of lewd doinges, he falleth also. Presumption vppon his owne iustice, is as it were the right hand. The thinking that sinnes escape vnpun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisshed, is like the left hand Let vs heare the voice of God saying to vs: Turne not aside to the right or left hand.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Prouer.</hi> 4.</note>
      <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume not to come to the kingdome by thine owne iustice, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume not to sinne through the mercy of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These be, good Christian Reader, the two perilouse and deadly daungers, that men may fall into, if they doe not rightly vnderstande the true doctrine of Iustification. Whiche falles being so dangerouse, God graunt all men
<pb facs="5"/> carefully to eschew. Wherin to helpe thee iudge vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I haue taken in hande this trauaile, trusting by Gods grace, so to leade thee <hi>Via Regia,</hi> that is, in the true and high waie, that thou shalt not nede to fall of either side, if thou wilt vprightly waie, and with the feare of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider such thinges, as thou shalt finde here alleaged.</p>
   <p>And bicause I can not hope to atteine any good, much lesse so great a good, but by his geuing of whom commeth al good, I wil beginne with the prayer, which S. Augustine intending to preache of the same matter made, desiring thee to pray for mee, as he did his hearers for him selfe. <hi>Primùm infirmitatem meam, &amp;c.</hi> First of al saith he, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende my weakenesse <hi>to your prayers,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6.</note>
      <hi>as the Apostle saith, that woordes may be geauen me in opening my mouth, so to speake vnto you, as it be not perilouse for me to speake, and may be holesome for you to heare.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And this request I make vnto thee, Gentle Reader, not onely for mine owne sake, who neede the same, but for thine also, that thou maist perceiue, howe great helpe and assistance thou needest at Gods hand for thy parte, if thou wilt profitably reade or speake of this matter, of whiche so vertuouse and excellently lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a Bishop thought him selfe not able nor meete to speake, without the healpe of godlie prayers.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>