<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102348_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68937</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2783</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102348</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sions elegies. Wept by Ieremie the prophet, and periphras'd by Fra. Quarles</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Helme, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Washington, William</publisher>
                            <distributor>Dewe, Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Dewe, Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the ruines of <hi>Troy, Rome, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes,</hi> or <hi>Carthage</hi> haue been thought a subject, worthy the imployment of more serious Pennes, to entayle the remembrance thereof to Posteritie, how much more worthy the paines of a liuelyer Pen then mine, is this ancient, most true, and neuer enough to be lamented desolation, and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of <hi>Ierusalem, Ierusalem,</hi> the holy Citie of God, <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> the type of the Catholike Church?</p>
   <p>After eighteene moneths siege in the eleuenth yeere of <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> the ninth day of the fourth moneth, (which was the eighteenth yeere of <hi>Nebucadonozor</hi> ouer <hi>Babylon)</hi> the Princes of <hi>Babylon</hi> surprized and tooke this braue Citie of <hi>Ierusalem:</hi> presently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, <hi>Nebuzaradan</hi> the Generall of the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Armie commanded by <hi>Nebucadonozor)</hi> spoyled the Temple, carried away the Vessels of gold and sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that were consecrated to Gods seruice, and the great Lauar giuen by King <hi>Salomon,</hi> and burned the Temple, the first day of the next moneth, which was one and twentie dayes after the surprizall: <hi>470.</hi> yeeres sixe moneths, and ten dayes after the foundation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; <hi>1062.</hi> yeeres, sixe moneths, ten dayes after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture <note place="margin">Reade <hi>Iosephus de Antiq. Iud. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> of the people out of <hi>Egypt; 1950.</hi> yeeres, sixe


<pb facs="5"/>
moneths, ten dayes after the Deluge; and <hi>3513.</hi> yeeres, sixe moneths, ten dayes after the Creation of <hi>Adam.</hi> Thus, and then, was this Citie of <hi>Ierusalem</hi> taken, and for seuentie yeeres, remayned the Iewes in this Captiuitie: And this, in briefe, is the generall occasion why, and the time when these Lamentations were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed. Reader, I tender to thy consideration, two things; First, the Pen-man: secondly, the Art and Methode of this <hi>Threnodia.</hi> As for the first, It was penn'd by <hi>Ieremie</hi> the Prophet, the sonne of <hi>Hilkiah</hi> a Priest; and vndoubtedly endighted by the Spirit of God; some thinke it was written, when the Prophe: was in prison; others, when hee was with <hi>Godoliah</hi> at <hi>Maspath:</hi> but whither at the one place or at the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is not much materiall to discourse.</p>
   <p>Secondly, as touching the Art and Methode, it is short and concise, as being most naturall to so lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table a subject: <hi>Cicero</hi> sayes, <hi>Lamentationes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent esse concisae, &amp; breues, quia cito lachryma exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rescit, &amp; difficile est, auditores autlectores, in illo affectu summae commiserationis, diu tenere.</hi> The Methode is truly elegious, not bound to any ordinarie set forme, but wildly depending vpon the sudden sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that new griefes present; and indeed the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest sorrowes can not be, but distracted from all rules of methode, the neglect of which, is veniall in such ejulations as these, as which, in all the Scriptures, there is none so copious, none so ardent, concerning which <hi>Gregorie Nazianzene</hi> confesses, <hi>Threnos Ieremiae nunquam à se siccis oculis lectos esse.</hi> Yet some think there is a methode kept, but too fine and intricate, for our grosse apprehensions; touching this point, Saint


<pb facs="5"/>
Ambrose <hi>lib. 8. Epist. ad Iust.</hi> sayes, <hi>Demus, cas se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum artem non scripsisse, at certè secundum gratiam scripsisse fatendum est, quae omn em artem longe supera<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> and with this I rest.</p>
   <p>You shall obserue, that the foure first Chapters of these Lamentations carry a strict order, in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, for euery Verse throughout euery Chapter begins with a seuerall letter of the Hebrew Alphabet, except the third Chapter, wherein the first and euery third Verse onely is tyed to a Letter, and continues the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet through, which forme the Prophet vsed, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Eloquence, partly for Memorie sake, meaning either literally thus, that it ought to be perfect as the Alphabet, in Memorie, or Hieroglyphically thus, that as the Alphabet is the Radix of all wordes, so the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series of the Iewes, were the combination of all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series.</p>
   <p>For the same Causes, I likewise here in my Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrase, haue obserued the same forme, and continue the Alphabet, in English, as the Prophet did in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, desirous to be his shaddow, as much as I can.</p>
   <p>It appeares by the strictnesse of the order, that these Lamentations were Originally writ in Verse, and as some thinke, in Sapphicks, but many of our learned Neotericks denie, that any writings of the Iewes carry, now, any direct, or certaine Lawes of Poesie, though (they confesse) some ruinous Accents, here and there discouered, makes them imagin, they writ some things in verse, but now, it seemes that God in disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing them, hath likewise dissolued, and strucke dumbe their musicke.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>