<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader, Grace and Peace.</title>
           <author>Smith, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102599_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12472</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22797</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102599</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader, Grace and Peace.</title>
                 <author>Smith, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The doctrine of praier : in generall for all men, that is, vniuersally for all mankind: Proued 1. By the true sence of the words of the Apostle 1. Tim 2. 2. By the reasons, why all men in that sence should be praid for. 3. By the doctrine establishing such praier. 4. By th practise of churches, concerning that kind of praier. 5. By the obiections, ansuered. Against the position of those that say and preach, that all men are not to be praid for. By I. Smith, minister of Gods word at Reading</title>
                 <author>Smith, John, minister at Reading</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Islip, Adam</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 115, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader, Grace and Peace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou hast of late (right Christian reader) giuen foorth vnto thy view, a little Treatise concerning <hi>Praier for Almen,</hi> for thy confirmation that way, if thou be established: for thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, if thou doubt: as is meant by the writer and the author of the same. Which for my part should haue gone on, and passed without any my speeches, or writings, if it had passed in innocencie and simplicitie of it selfe. But because it so deepely reprooueth the contrarie minded, argueth their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, confuteth their opinions, impaireth the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of S. <hi>Augustine</hi> alleaged, the Author knoweth by whome: I thought good, being one of the simplest of those that preach that doctrine, yet most touched in the said Treatise, to deale towards thee after this sort. First I haue sent thee here, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine hereof, namely, of <hi>Praier for All men</hi>; se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly
<pb facs="5"/>
I mean to send thee (as God shall giue time) the full answer vnto that former Treatise, that thou maist discerne where the truth and where the error is. I must confesse, if the disquieted minds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this doctrine had not mooued me; and the oft soliciting of such whose I am in the Lord, also pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked me; and the learned my friends, oft told me how I was dealt withall in the said Treatise, I had not taken this seruice in hand. For I beare this mind alwaies, in most readie sort being aduertised, to reclaim that I speake amisse, euen in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, much lesse would I heare of it in Print. For what is the estimation of a minister in the Lord, if he be bereaued of the truth? None surely in my iudgement, any way. First therefore iudge thou of my doctrin: secondly thou shalt, if God giue grace, vnderstand our faults and imperfections laid to our charge. And the Lord Iesus in the meane season giue thee vnderstanding in all things, to thy euerlasting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in him. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> Iohn Smith.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>