<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102284_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16170</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3092</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102284</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A courteous conference with the English Catholickes Romane : about the six articles ministred vnto the seminarie priestes, wherein it is apparantly proued by their owne diuinitie, and the principles of their owne religion, that the Pope cannot depose her Maiestie, or release her subiectes of their alleageance vnto her. And finally, that the bull of Pius Quiutus [sic] pronounced against her Maiestie is of no force eyther in lawe or conscience, all Catholicke scruples to the contrarie beeing throughly and perfectly cleared and resolued, and many memoriall matter exactly discussed, which haue not beene handled by man heeretofore. Written by Iohn Bishop a recusant papist</title>
                 <author>Bishop, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradock, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dexter, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 84 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Booke (Christian Reader) was written by one <hi>Iohn Bishop</hi> a recusant papist, what sufficient reason there is (notwithstanding) to commit it to the presse, and from thence to the open veiw of all men, in the diligent perusing, &amp; consideration ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thou maist plainely perceiue and vnderstand. It is a booke which (in the iudgement of many godly and learned men) is very necessary to come abroad, neither hath anie obiection bene made against the publishing of the same, but onely this, that it is to be feared, it will be a meanes to bring the papistes into more fauour, as discouering them to be nothing such dangerous enemies to the state, as of the greatest part they are reputed: but surely I see no cause to stand in feare of any such effect, but rather to rest fully resolued vpon the contrarie, that for asmuch as, howsoeuer some one of them being astonished with the light of Gods trueth, and looking backe to the former times, sheweth himself nothing so absurd as other, yet seeing the professed doctrine of their Church is otherwise, and the continuall practise of the Pope, &amp; all his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes is directly to the contrarie, by murders, treasons, and rebellions, and by the inuasions &amp; open force of cruell enemies seeking the vtter destruction of the Queenes most excellent Maiestie (whom God manie yeares yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue) and of all others that professe in trueth the glorious Gospell of Iesus Christ: accounting the Popes Bulles a sufficient warrant for the ouerturning of Gods ordinances, and his pardons, a strong bulwarke against the wrath of God, against hell &amp; condemnation. These things I say considered, I see no reason to feare anie encrease of their fauour and credit by this meanes, but rather to hope (as there is iust cause to desire) the encrease of their discredit, and more straiter lawes for the restraining of them. The magistrate hath had too much experience, that howsoeuer the iudgements of some of the best learned among the papistes may peraduenture agree with the author of this booke, yet the profession &amp; practise of them all, both learned &amp; vnlearned is farre otherwise, as by open and outragious attempts there wants no good will in them to testifie more plainely vnto the whole worlde, if the day were once come they haue so long looked for, &amp; if they saw any likelihood of preuailing, but as the Lord for <hi>Sions</hi> sake hath hitherto defeyted their purposes, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned their mischieuous imaginations to their owne cunfusion, so I nothing doubt, but he will continue for vs a brasen wall of defence from time to time heereafter euen vntill the second comming of his sonne in the cloudes.</p>
   <p>Whether the author would himselfe haue published this booke, it is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that at the writing hereof he was so determined, it is very probable by that part of his preface which is come to our hands, where he beginneth thus.
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Whē I saw two or three years past many seminary priests:</hi> that which next ensued after these words was rent off and cānot be found, but on the other side of the paper it followeth thus. <hi>And whiles I, following</hi> Horace <hi>his counsaile</hi> nōnunquā premitur in annū: <hi>did let this treatise lie by me in seasoning, that it might at length passe abroad perfect, fully refuting all obiections of moment which old shops had shapened, or new forges had framed, &amp;c.</hi> By this I say it appeareth that at the time of the writing therof, he was fully determined to imprint this booke, but afterwards it should see me his mind was altred, perswading himselfe that the publishing would greatly tend to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence &amp; disquieting of his Catholick brethrē. For how is it possible, that they should take it patiētly to see one of their owne professiō, so eagerly fight against thē, &amp; put thē to the foile with their owne weapons, &amp; by the exprsse testimony also of the holy scriptures, &amp; by so many approued authorities &amp; examples, discouering to the world, the tyranny, the malicious, the proud &amp; arrogant practises of their holy father. Surely so far would they haue bene from taking it in good part at his hand whiles he was aliue, that I am fully perswaded, they neither can, nor will, with hold their tongues frō exclaiming against him now he is dead, either accounting him to be an Apostata, or els making themselues bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue that this worke is falsey fathered vpon him. But to put them out of doubt both of the one, &amp; the other. That he was no backslider frō their religiō but vnto his dying day continued a recusant papist, it is so wel knowen at Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel in <hi>Sussex,</hi> where he was borne &amp; often cōuersant, &amp; at <hi>London</hi> where he spent a great part of his time, as also in all the country neare vnto Battel, as that there nedeth not any further testimony. And that he was in very truth the author of this booke, &amp; of euery part therof, is manifestly, to be proued by his owne hand writing, so well knowen at Battel &amp; in the cuntry therabouts &amp; also of many in <hi>London,</hi> as that there is no neede to feare the clearing also of this scruple. Let any mā that knoweth his hand, &amp; is desirous to be resolued of the trueth, repaire to <hi>Northhiham</hi> in <hi>Sussex,</hi> &amp; at the house of <hi>George Bishop</hi> brother to the deceased author, he shal at his pleasure haue a sight of the same. To conclude, this also wisely &amp; diligently is the reader to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that although he write very directly against the Pope &amp; popery, yet in many respects doth he shew himself a papist, as in following of corrupt transla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, in the places of scripture which he alledgeth, &amp; in misapplying many of them, contrary to the true sense &amp; meaning of the holy Ghost, wherein al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though some warni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>g is giuen by a few marginall notes added of purpose and signed wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> this letter, yet cannot the godly reader for all that be too wearie and circumspect in the particular consideration of the same.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>