<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102687_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01284</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11406</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102687</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Courteous Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The evaporation of the apple of Palæstine: that is, The sifting of the answeres and rescripts, lately given, in the cause of the restitution of the Palatinate : Together with a briefe demonstration of the nullities of the clandestine dispositions, by which, the electourship and the Palatinate hath beene transferred on the house of Bavaria. Translated out of Latine</title>
                 <author>Rusdorf, Johann Joachim von</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Anne</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <distributor>Norton, Joyce (Jocosa)</distributor>
                            <distributor>Whitaker, Richard</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>160 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S he who afarre off beholds Brasse or Tinne, cannot easily distinguish the one from Silver, or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from Gold, unlesse hee comes neere them; And as to one having the crystalline humors of his eyes darkened, or using spectacles, the object beheld, appeares lesser, or greater, than in trueth it is: So, for the most part, those, which are possessed with an over-weaning opinion and conceit, or led away by ignorance, or a false perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, or stirred up with a troublous passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="7"/>
or sudden motion of the mind, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine things sleightly, not prying into the more hidden secrets of the matter, and touching onely (as I may so speake) the shell, but not at all attaining the kernell; they judge and determine farre otherwise, of mens actions, counsells, intentions, opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, words and writings, than is lawfull and agreeable to trueth.</p>
   <p>That fatall Palatine Cause, so generally knowne through the whole world, affords a notable and lively example hereof. <hi>Cui non dictus Hylas?</hi> Where is the man to whom this sad newes hath not beene rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? But who (I beseech you) amongst so many thousands, doth at this present, sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and faithfully, and uprightly judge thereof? who among so many doth well know and understand it? For who, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to trueth and equity, without hatred or affection, doth rightly conceive, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand and judge of the proscription promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated against King <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour?
<pb facs="7"/>
of intrenching upon, the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the alienation of the Electorall Palatine Dominions, and the Dignity and Offices thereunto annexed, and an entire, totall remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall of these, unto the Bavarian Family? of the Ordainances made by the Emperor, the Bavarian and the rest of their Confederates, of their pronounced Opinions, Decrees, Rescripts, Conditions made knowne, agreed on, Covenants drawne, and the like? It is decreed in the Law, <hi>That every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance ought to be narrowly looked into, before the proceeding to sentence:</hi> So also in things of so great consequence, no sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ought to be pronounced, untill all things be exactly weighed, aswell for circumstances and reasons, quality of the times, conditions and intentions of men, and finally with a full understanding of words, sentences and causes, things being examined by constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and intreaty.</p>
   <p>If we should deduce these things particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, and one by one, as they ought to bee
<pb facs="8"/>
weighed and diligently examined, it would require large volumes; we having reserved the greater part of those things untill another time, and for another labour and worke, which (by Gods assistance) wee shall shortly publish; for the present, we thought it worth the labour, to bring into the light, and expose to view, the intent and meaning of those answeres, rescripts and decrees only, which the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the <hi>II.</hi> the last yere (in which the most Royall King <hi>Charles</hi> of great Britaine, sent a solemne Embassage unto him, for gaining the restitution of the Palatinate, and of His Nephewes descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from his onely Sister the Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) had determined &amp; delivered: as also a briefe manifestation of injustice and the nullities, with which, those alledged de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Emperour, concerning the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring and firme alienation of the Electorall dignitie, and revenues thereunto belonging granted to the Bavarians, doe (as it were) groane, and are stuffed; both because
<pb facs="8"/>
Wee were commanded and required there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, by them who had authority to doe it; as also, that they may give some light, or at least open a gap, and prepare the way for those my treatises which shall ensue: And to conclude, that out of these, some conjecture and ghesse maybe had, what is to be thought of the other things performed in this matter in question, by the adverse part, either vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently or fraudulently practised. Perhaps some may say, that I ought to have beene more large and accurate concerning those dispositions, and in setting down the nullities of them. But I would have them know, that I would willingly have done that, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly have handled the particulars, if it might have beene lawfull to have taken a view of those dispositions, as they were first penned, the which (as it appeareth) never yet came to publike light, but alwayes were kept privately and in secret, as, at the first they were composed. And concerning the nullities of the urged pacification at Prague, whereby
<pb facs="9"/>
it is pretended that those dispositions are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and confirmed, wee thought it a matter of incogitancie and indiscretion, to make a long and tedious discourse, not, because wee deemed it not so much appertaining to Our purpose, as that, because wee have found the same argument purposely handled by others, with exactnesse of diligence, and no small commendation. Should I also have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to have made a strict search, and full discovery of the same matter, with my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure pen, what other thing should I have attempted, Than,
<q>
         <l>
            <hi>Stellis nebulam spargere candidis?</hi>
         </l>
         <l>— to over cast the Heavens most bright,</l>
         <l>With exhalat'ons that obscure the light?</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>For Conclusion, Curteous Reader, I would intreat thee, to afford a favourable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation to these my extemporarie la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, for so you may give encouragement to
<pb facs="9"/>
my endeavours, that I may with cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse accomplish (which) I yet forbeare) the Manifestation of things affected, and almost effected by the adversaries, and expose them also speedily to thy judgement and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing. Farewell heartily. From the Vbit the Nones of <hi>March. 1637.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>