<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Admonition to the Reader.</title>
           <author>S., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102598_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12120</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22427</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102598</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Admonition to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>S., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The countryman vvith his houshold : Being a familiar conference, concerning faith towards God, and good workes before men; fitted for the capacitie of the meanest. By R.S. preacher of the word at Arley. See the contents more particularly before the booke</title>
                 <author>Sherrard, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Bartlet, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 256 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>An Admonition to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Presume thou knowest very well (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that as the gifts of Teachers in deliuering are diuers, so are those of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers for conceiuing and profiting. For which cause the Christian Scribe must (as the great Diuinitie-Reader teacheth)<note n="a" place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.52,</note> bring forth out of his treasure things both new and olde, that is, as I vnderstand it, fit his setting forth of sauing truth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sundry good sorts to the estate and capacitie of the Learners;<note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.1. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. i. <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimè lubricum.</hi>
      </note> and for them it is safe to write the same things vnto them. Thinke me not then to tautologize ouermuch in this Booke, neither yet blame me for lacke of exact method therein. For, besides that a familiar Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb facs="4"/> especially of the Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with his Houshold (for whose sake chiefly I publish these my country-meditations) is not so ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely freed from the one, nor so strictly tyed to the other; note (I pray thee) that my studie and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour herein hath beene purpose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to convey the truth to the more ignorant and ruder sort in such forme and so many words as I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed them able to receiue it;<note n="c" place="margin">
         <hi>Esai.</hi> 28.9, 10, 11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.22. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.11, 12, 13.</note> and if they should not rightly conceiue and lay hold on the truth in one place, speech or passage of the Booke, yet in another they might attaine to it, if it shall please the Lord. To which end I haue retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (chiefly in the weightiest prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples) some common phrases and kindes of speech vsed in Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chismes, because I take them to be plainest &amp; more generally knowne. Namely, I haue here and there
<pb facs="4"/> vsed some answers out of Master <hi>William Perkins</hi> (of worthy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) his Catechisme. And in some three or foure places also I haue imitated others a litle in some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects. The reasons against Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>substantiation, and many of those Questions and Answers about fit and worthy Receiuers, and some few about Receiuing worthily are the labours of that judicious man and mine especiall frend M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> A. N. All the rest (so far as I remember)<note n="*" place="margin">Neither yet hath my paines beene the lesser in those few things that I haue taken from others, as the discreet Reader may easily perceiue by my man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vsing them.</note> are my poore indeuours, togither with the frame of the whole, so sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped as I thought fittest for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. Indeed when I began with this Worke, I intended onely some briefer thing, as a short Catechisme, but afterwards partly considering the great and manifold necessities of the ignorant, and partly follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the aduise of diuers godly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons whom I consulted withall, I
<pb facs="5"/> haue inlarged my selfe to so many matters as you may see. The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and substance I assure my selfe is sound, and (I am priuie) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from a heart that is willing to promote the common saluation,<note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>vers.</hi> 3.</note> as <hi>Iude</hi> calleth it. Let it not want therefore (judicious Reader) thy Christian good word, at least let it be free from thy blame, though (it may be) there shall be found some shew of Reason for such censure, considering not onely my defence premised, but also the cause and honour of Him who is too often pierced through the sides of his poore seruants, and fearing the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the weake, who (God knoweth) are soone turned out of the way. Albeit, I take, it had bin no great difficultie for me to haue made it both shorter and more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodicall, saue that (if I do not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake) I iudge this often repeating
<pb facs="5"/> the surest or likeliest way to effect my intent and desire. And if God shall moue any few of those Housholders (hearts) who haue hitherto vsed litle or no meanes in this behalfe, to vse this, so that it be with conscience, I haue inough. And why should they alwayes<note n="e" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 2.3.</note> breake Christs bands asunder and cast away his cords from them? Now the Lord of his deere mercy conueyed vnto vs by the blood of of his onely Sonne, by his all-working Spirit, blesse my simple labour, thy fauourable allowance, and euery ones Christian vse of it, vnto his owne praise in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his Church. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> R. S.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>