<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102366_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01005</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11110</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102366</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Church conquerant ouer humane wit. Or The Churches authority demonstrated by M. VVilliam Chillingvvorth (the proctour for vvit against her) his perpetual contradictions, in his booke entituled, The religion of Protestants a safe vvay to saluation</title>
                 <author>Floyd, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>193, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HOSOEVER hath attentiuely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>used the <hi>Booke,</hi> the <hi>Confutation</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I haue vndertaken, cannot but with horrour perceaue therein a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and often iterated exprobation made to the whole <hi>Army of the liuing God.</hi> For he chargeth as subiect to vniuersall damnable Errours not only the present Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, and that of some later tymes before; but also the most prime and Primitiue
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pag. 292. nu. 91.</note> Ages of the 5.4.3.2. by Name, <hi>yea the Church Apostolicall,</hi> the
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pag. 144. n. 31.</note>
      <hi>Blessed Apostles themselues, euen after they had receaued the Holy Ghost.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="2">2. Against this Defyer, and Challenger of the Church of God, as I did hartily wish, so did I hopeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expect, that of the famous <hi>Vniuersity,</hi> in the sight and hearing wherof this hatefull exprobation was made, an <hi>Vniuersity</hi> stored with so many well experienced warriours and redoubted Champions, some one would haue appeared in field with the complete Armour of Christian inuincible learning. My desire was groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on feare, least otherwayes in the iudgment of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity the most vnpartiall Arbiter of former demerits, this <hi>Nursery of sciences</hi> in ancient tymes so renowned for Christian piety and learning, might be thought to haue
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>wanted, in this occasion, either <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>Theology</hi> to discerne, or <hi>Maturity</hi> of <hi>Iudgment</hi> to consider, or <hi>Zeale</hi> of <hi>Christianity</hi> to detest, or <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>Elocution</hi> to confute such vnchristian Principles.</p>
   <p n="3">3. What may haue been the cause of this their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, I will not passe my Iudgment. Whatsoeuer it were, I am confident of their <hi>Christianity,</hi> that they will approue, fauour, and applaud <hi>Christianity maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> and say with <hi>S. Paul,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip. 1.18.</note> so that Christ be preached any manner of way, I ioy therein, and will ioy.</hi> Which Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise if they haue read ouer &amp; perused, I dare say, they haue found therin a little <hi>Dauid,</hi> short and solid, pious and pithy, learned and religious, armed with <hi>smooth stones</hi> of cleere Truth, gathered from the <hi>current</hi> of Christian Tradition, deliuered by the <hi>Pastorall slinge</hi> of the Churches Authority. On the other side, a mighty Giant destitute of all the signes and markes of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian souldier, armed neither with the authority of the present Christian Church, nor perpetuall <hi>Traditions,</hi> nor <hi>Councells,</hi> nor <hi>Consent of Fathers,</hi> nor with their sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle sentences, which he reiects as Bul-rushes of no strength.</p>
   <p n="4">4. He layeth claime to the <hi>Armour of light,</hi> the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bible: but this is only to daunt his Aduersary with words, not to vse the same in deeds: For neuer Writer appeared in matter of Controuersy more bare then he is of this kind of proofe. He hath cited twice or thrice some texts of Scripture, so few, and so short, that I dare say, al the words of Scripture vrged in his Booke against vs may be cōprized in ten lynes. He cōfideth only in the <hi>launce</hi> of his <hi>Dialectical Discourse,</hi>
      <note n="(d)" place="margin">Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of Logicke <hi>Preface n. 12.</hi>
      </note> which he presumeth he can deliuer so assuredly by the stronge Arme of his Human <hi>Reason,</hi> and dexterity of naturall <hi>Wit,</hi> as euer
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>infallibly
<note n="(e)" place="margin">By discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se no man can possibly be lead into Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. <hi>ibid.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>to hit the marke of reuealed Truth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="5">5. That short Treatise as I said, of <hi>Christianity main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned,</hi> hath foyled this daring challenger by a stroke <hi>on the forehead,</hi> by laying open his <hi>Principles,</hi> how they <hi>destroy Christianity;</hi> wherby he cannot but fall to the ground in the Iudgment of all Christian Churches. The spoyles of his victory, he leaueth <hi>to his Armiger</hi> to gather, that he may also haue part of the honour, and in the glorious victory, which is, as
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Epist. 84.</note>
      <hi>S. Hierome</hi> sayth, <hi>cum Dauide extorquere gladium de aduersarij manibus, &amp; su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbissimi Goliae caput proprio mucrone truncare,</hi> to confute and make away with the heads of his erroneous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, by the force of his owne sword, his words, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and principles.</p>
   <p n="6">6. To take this course for the Confutation of his Booke I was vrged by <hi>Necessity,</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi> Necessity, against an Aduersary who denyeth all the Principles of Christian fayth. He often repeates with much pride, but still without proofe:
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
         <hi>Pag.</hi> 376. <hi>lin.</hi> 6. <hi>pag. 131. lin. 27.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>I see plainly and with my owne eyes, that there are Popes against Popes, Councells against Councels, some Fathers against others, the same Fathers against themselues, a consent of Fathers in one age against a consent of Fathers in another age, the Church of one age against the Church of another Age.</hi> Scripture remaynes, which he doth (though not so openly and professedly, yet) cleerely and manifestly discard, as a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious witnes. For he teacheth, <hi>that in respect of making a thing incredible, or of no credit, it is all one
<note n="(h)" place="margin">
            <hi>Pag. 215. lin.</hi> 16.</note> whether the Contradictions be reall, or only seeming:</hi> So that a writing full of seeming contradictions can be of no more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with vs, then if the contradictions were reall. Now he professeth, <hi>that
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pag. 136. n. 9. lin. 15.</note> in all Controuersies betwixt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants one with another, which are innumerable, there is still a
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>seeming conflict of Scripture with Scripture; that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may with so great probabilities be alleaged on both sides, that we
<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pag. 41. l. 7.</note> may expect an Elias to reconcile the repugnances.</hi> If then the Scripture be to our seeming, full of conflicts and irreconciliable repugnances, as well as Popes, Councells, Fathers; how can it be of more authority &amp; credit?</p>
   <p n="7">7. Who doth not see, that there is no way to deale with this man, but to hamper him in the knots of his owne speach, from the Authority wherof he will not disclayme. He is not
<note n="(l)" place="margin">
         <hi>Pag. 152. l.</hi> 15.</note>
      <hi>an Idolatour of S. Austen,</hi> but of himselfe: <hi>D Field
<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pag. 84. n. 86.</note> is not infallible,</hi> but he is: <hi>Optatus
<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pag. 298. n. 97.</note> his sayings be not fit to determine controuersies of Fayth,</hi> but his are. <hi>S. Cyprians
<note n="(o)" place="margin">
            <hi>Pag.</hi> 268. <hi>n.</hi> 44.</note> sentences be not a rule of faith,</hi> but his be. The Scripture is full of seeming cōflicts, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, and irreconciliable Repugnances;</hi> but he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer confesse so much of his owne Booke. There be <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Ages against Christian Ages;</hi> but he will thinke we do him wronge, if we say, that in his writings <hi>Pages</hi> are repugnant to <hi>Pages,</hi> yea many tymes sentences of the same Page are at deadly food the one with the other. This then is the way to confute, and confound him; to shew that being lead by passion one way, and by the euidence of truth another, he hath spokē seelily &amp; vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely against the Authority of the Church, solidly and iudiciously for it.</p>
   <p n="8">8. This is the style still held by the Almighty to vanquish and ouerthrow the Enemyes of his Church <hi>by sending the
<note n="(p)" place="margin">Isa. 19 14.</note> spirit of giddines vpon them.</hi> A victory which may seeme not vnlike that which <hi>Gedeon</hi>
      <note n="(q)" place="margin">Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic, 7.</note> got against the <hi>Madianites,</hi> who lay like <hi>a multitude of locusts wasting and destroying the land of Israel.</hi> Three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred souldiers by Gods appointement, hauing empty
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>pitchers in their hands, and in ech of the pitchers a light hidden, breaking the pitchers one against the other, the <hi>Madianites</hi> were confounded with the sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain noise and light; so as they fell to
<note n="(r)" place="margin">Jm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misit Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus gladium in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stri &amp; mu ua se caed: tru <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</note> quarell with ech other, and mutually destroy themselues. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceytes of this man may be termed <hi>a multitude of locusts</hi> which wast and consume <hi>the whole land of Israel,</hi> all the <hi>grounds</hi> and principles of Christian fayth In his Booke there be Pages (those aparted which cōteyne the Text of <hi>Charity mantayned)</hi> about three hūdred, which empty of proofe for his owne Religion, haue hidden in them the light of Catholike Truth. These Pages being in this Reply, by violent encounter of his direct Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, beaten and broken the one against the other, <hi>sound out by the noyse of the cracke,</hi> the emptinesse of his vayne Religion, and togeather shew forth the clee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e light of Catholike doctrin. Hence his wasting and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structiue Principles come to fight togeather, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy ech other, and so leaue the holy Church, and the <hi>Gedeon</hi> therof, <hi>conquerant ouer humane Wit.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="9">9. <hi>Charity</hi> also hath set me on this Course of ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wering, by the discouery of his Contradictions, as iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the same more efficacious then any other, for the reclayming of him, and the like Wanderers who are lead into contempt of the Churches Authority, by the ouer-valuing of their owne wits. When he shall find himselfe, and others see him lost in a labyrinth of inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable perplexities, enclosed on euery side with the contrarieties of his owne sayings, they will happily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect, how weake, blynd, miserable humane Reason is, and vnfit to be the guide of Christians in their <hi>walking by fayth</hi> towards eternall life. For this cause, haue I sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this Treatise, <hi>The Church conquerant ouer humane Wit,</hi>
      <pb n="8" facs="5"/>to signify that he needs not be more ashamed of being conquered by the Church, then of being of the number of men. My drift is not to insult ouer him fallen so low into folly, but to condescend to help him vp againe, by confessing my selfe subiect to the like imbecillity of wit. My mind is not to blast or blemish the good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that some may haue conceaued of his sharpe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding; nor do I charge him with any want of common Iudgmēt, besides that which is caused throgh want <hi>of speciall Grace.</hi> It was want of <hi>Grace</hi> that he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke the vngracious Attempt of opposing the whole Church of God, no want of <hi>Wit</hi> not to haue performed what no wit can effect. No man will haue better successe that shall go about so bad an enterprize.</p>
   <p n="10">10. Giuing thankes vnto God, I may confesse, that Catholike Education hath instilled into my soule such reuerence towards the whole Church of Christ, as I know not what way I should go about to oppose her Iudgment: that were there no other way to saluation, then that which this man teacheth, and runneth, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying on my owne wit and discourse, against <hi>the whole Church, Generall Councells, Consent of Fathers;</hi> I should ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily thinke saluation for me impossible. Neuerthelesse should I be tempted, and such a phrensy of Pride take hold of my soule, I belieue I should fall into the like Contradictions against my selfe, as now I admire how this man being of so good a wit, could possibly fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. What he telleth vs out of <hi>Gusman de Alfarache,
<note n="(t)" place="margin">
            <hi>Pag. 12 n.</hi> 50.</note> that the Hospitall of fooles is of a large extent,</hi> I do verily admit to be most true. And therfore being as all men are, sick &amp; subiect to ignorāce about diuine matters, should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to be vnder the CVRE of the Catholike Church, I am persuaded, I should be no sooner out of the Hospi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>of <hi>Sancto Spirito</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> then in <hi>Goosmans Hospitall,</hi> in the number of those who, as <hi>S. Paul</hi>
      <note n="(u)" place="margin">
         <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes se sapientes stulti fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti sunt.</hi> Rom. 1.21.</note> sayth, <hi>Presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming themselues to be wise, prooue to be fooles,</hi> by contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions against themselues.</p>
   <p n="11">11. King Alexander by selfe flattery, and the flattery of others, thought himselfe to be the <hi>Sonne of Iupiter,</hi> but wounded in battaile, he became docible and apt to learne the lesson, which bloud running about his eares, told and taught him, <hi>that he was mortall.</hi> But <hi>M. Chilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> being entred into the lists of single Combat with the <hi>Maintayner of Charity,</hi> though he be beaten, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, disgraced at euery bout, forced to contradict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, to say and vnsay, to recall his words, to deny his grantes; yet high conceyte of his owne worth, makes him so insensible of these his wounds, as he doth boast and bragge, that in answering the <hi>Maintayners</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>he hath not byn any way perplexed.</hi> I therfore in this Confutation open againe the woundes which selfe-Ignorance had closed vp from his sight, that by these ouertures that holesome lesson of Christian Humility may find entrance into his head and heart, <hi>That no wit of man, is a fit match to encounter with the whole Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="12">12. Wherein if I put him to some payne, he will I hope remember, that it is
<note n="(x)" place="margin">
         <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liora sunt vulnera diligentis quam frandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenta os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culae o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientis.</hi> Prou. 27.6.</note> better to be recalled to life out of a sound, by the blowes of a friend, then to be betrayed, and stifled vnto death by the kisses of a foe He hath drunke ouer much of the sweet milke of selfe pleasing Conceyte, which by flattery of some other may be increased in him, that he seemes lulled into a dead sleep as
<note n="(y)" place="margin">Iud. 4.</note>
      <hi>Sisara</hi> was, I can do him no greater cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity, then to pinch him with his own Contradictions so hard, and hould him so fast, that he may in the depth
<pb n="10" facs="6"/>of his soule feele the smart of his folly, and awake to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent before
<note n="(z)" place="margin">Sopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem morti conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecit &amp; mortuns est.</note>
      <hi>Iahel,</hi> or rather Hell strike the nayle of obdurate obstinacy into his head, and so ioyne his sleep with death, his death with euerlasting damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
   <p n="13">13. Togeather with the discouery of Contradictions, I still lay open &amp; demonstrate in them, and by them, the Infallible Authority of the Church assisted not to erre by Gods infinite wisdome; that if pinched by his Contradictions he awake and open his eyes, he may presently behould <hi>the beauty and glory of this vnspotted spouse of the lambe, the Virgin-Mother of Christians,</hi> and so be moued to <hi>lay downe his
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
            <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. in cap 39. Iob. Jn sinum virginis omni fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posita ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. <hi>In capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem redigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectum in obse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium Christi.</hi>
         </note> head, and the Vnicornes horne</hi> of his singular Wit, <hi>in the lappe</hi> of her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; choosing to be rather taken captiue by <hi>voluntary subiection to her Truth,</hi> then shewed a thrall of errour, in the chaines of insoluble Contradictions against him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe.</p>
   <p n="14">14. In citing his testimonies I haue been exact &amp; pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual euen to a <hi>line;</hi> and to set downe <hi>formally,</hi> fully and largely <hi>his wordes, and whole discourses;</hi> more perhaps then some may thinke necessary or fitting: but I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be found faulty for <hi>excesse</hi> in sincerity, then for <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> Yea the wordes that were vpon some occasion ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before, I haue, when in other occasiōs I make vse of the same, repeated them againe at large, for the Readers greater ease, not to bind him to seeke for them in the place of the former citation. I haue quoted not the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> but the <hi>Chapter, Number,</hi> &amp; <hi>line</hi> of the number, that so the quotations may be common both to the first, &amp; second Edition which agree in <hi>Chapters, Numbers</hi> and <hi>lines,</hi> but not in <hi>Pages.</hi> Yet sometimes when the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are long, I haue quoted the page and the line of the
<pb n="11" facs="6"/>first Edition in the text; of the second in the margin. The Chapters of the booke be these following.</p>
   <list>
      <item>1. That Christian fayth is not resolued finally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to natural wit and Reason, but into the Authority of the Church.</item>
      <item>2. That Christian fayth is absolutely certaine and infallible.</item>
      <item>3. That the current of Christian Tradition is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt, both in the fountaine, and in the streame.</item>
      <item>4. That the Scripture is not the only Rule.</item>
      <item>5. That the Church is infallible in all her Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salls of fayth.</item>
      <item>6. That all Protesters against the Church of Rome, are Schismatiques.</item>
      <item>7. That they are also Heretiques.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>