<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102475_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13982</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24295</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102475</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A trvmpet to call sovldiers on to noble actions : By the rare and new examples of two Christian kings and a prince, personally meeting in the open field of warre. Viz. Gustanus [sic] the now-present King of Sweden, against Sigismond King of Poland, and the Prince his sonne, in remouing of the siege of Meve, a towne in Poland, which was formerly gotten by the Sweden King, from the Poland. With many memorable stratagems and military occurrences attending on so honourable a designe. Sent out of Sweden, from a great man in the state, and written with his owne hand Translated out of the Latine copie</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bourne, Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 <publisher>Archer, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="1" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O see Kings and Princes sweat in Battailes in these dayes, is so rare and vnusuall, that this warlike En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter of <hi>Gustanus</hi> the King of Sweden, with the King of Poland and his sonne, is for the remarkabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of it, worthy to be engrauen in Tables of brasse.</p>
   <p>The Prize for which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended was the Towne of Meve in Poland. The honour of the Aduenturer (the King of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den) the more to be exalted, in that hee went out of his owne Court and Country (where hee liued in fulnesse of all content) to trample on the fields and faces of his enemies, to beat at the Gates of the Polacke Cities, hunting after glory in a foraigne Kingdome, in despight of all the horrors which warre <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>seth to bring along with it: not regarding the petty Townes which he fought for, and did rescue, but for the victory which shall crowne his fame to all eternitie.</p>
   <p>Here you shall see a braue young Gentleman, lay by all kingly regards of his owne life, and with eight thousand Swedens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant and fight with thirty thousand Poles, and their adherents. The Polander hauing the aduantage of a hill, vpon which hee lay encamped and entrenched, and the Sweve spreading his handfull of an army beneath another hill.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="2" facs="3"/>
Here you may see this young King of Sweden, to fetch off à common Souldier, in his owne person, and to kill with his owne hands, that Polacke, who had set vpon the other.</p>
   <p>By which example of the Kings valour, the subiects vnder him, ran out like Lyons to the Battaile, and came off with a most glorious conquest: Glorious to their King, to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to themselues, and their posteritie, and a dishonour to the Enemy, being so many, to be driuen out of their owne fields by so few: some reporting that of the Poles and Cossackes were slaine in this Battaile 5000 at least.</p>
   <p>And albeit the truth of this great Action challengeth all Rites, Praises, and Acclamations to be giuen as due rewards to the Sweden (a stranger to vs) yet let not this story (when it is read in after-times) be so spitefull as to bury the Name and Memory of the English Nation, honoured in the Darings and high deeds of Colonell <hi>Muschampe</hi> (our Country-man) who behaued himselfe nobly, manfully, and as a true-worthy Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier in all this seruice.</p>
   <p>Neyther must wee smother the high courage of that braue Bohemian <hi>Torne,</hi> whose warlike acts in this Enterprise, are his speaking Chronicles: hee being after the King of Swedens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture home, left Generall in his stead.</p>
   <p>So Noble Souldiers, wishing you all no worse fortune in your Battailes, nor no lesse fame, than here the Sweves haue atchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I leaue you to reade that which may serue as a patterne and president for all heroicall spirits to follow.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>So Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>