<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONOVR OF ALMIGHTIE GOD.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102324_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08779</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19069</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102324</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONOVR OF ALMIGHTIE GOD.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christs confession and complaint : concering his kingdom and seruants; conuincing Iewes of obstinacie, Romish Catholickes of conspiracie, seducers of sedition, Arminians of apostacie, and diuers others of coldnes, schisme, treachery &amp; hypocrisie. By I.P</title>
                 <author>J. P.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 95, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE HONOVR OF ALMIGHTIE GOD.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>TERNALL and incomprehensible Lord God, who hast</hi> giuen <hi>to thine only begotten Sonne</hi> Iesus Christ, dominion and a Kingdome, that all people, Nations and languages <hi>should</hi> serue and obey him; <hi>and who hauing first sent this</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>to the</hi> Iewes, <hi>who reiected it, and since to diuers other Nations that haue fallen a way frō it, and follo wed Antichrist, hast of they great goodnesse, vouchsafed among other places, to haue thy</hi> Kingdome <hi>now these many yeeres in this</hi> Iland: <hi>yet haue not we O Lord, in humilitie and thankefulnesse, in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith and saluation, subiected our selues to the same; but</hi> the Corner stone <hi>hath beene in sundrie points, of diuers</hi> Builders refused: <hi>who haue brought in new and contrarie doctrines against</hi> the word of they Grace <hi>and Kingdome; and many, O Lord, haue followed</hi> their pernicious wayes. We haue sinned and done wickedly, and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled by departing from thy Precepts; <hi>and thereby haue deserued,</hi> that thy Kingdome should also be taken frō <hi>vs,</hi> and giuen to a Nation bringing forth the fruits thereof:</p>
   <p>
      <hi>But, O Lord God, if</hi> the foundations be destroyed, <hi>yet</hi> what hath the Righteous done? <hi>What hath they holy Sōne</hi> Iesus <hi>done, that he should lose his Kingdome, &amp; so many people here, and in other Nations? or if he lose none that</hi> thou hast giuen him, <hi>yet that he should not haue them to serue him with more freedome? He is worthy to be serued of all,</hi> without feare of <hi>Enemies,</hi> vvho redeemed vs to thee by his
<pb facs="4"/>blood, out of euery kindred and tongue, and people and Nation. <hi>It hath beene said,</hi> The Kingdomes of this world are become the Kingdomes of our Lord, and of his Christ, and he shall raigne for euer. <hi>Wee know O Lord, that thou wilt make good they</hi> Word; and if we beleeue not, yet thou abidest faithfull. <hi>Neuerthelesse,</hi> the Kings of the earth haue set themselues, and the <hi>Rulers</hi> take counsell together against <hi>thee,</hi> and thy Christ: <hi>In many Kingdomes and Prouinces, where the Gospell hath beene lately preached, they seeme to haue preuailed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced people to Antichristian slauery: but thou, O Lord, hast promised to</hi> speake vnto them in thy wrath, <hi>and by</hi> thy Word to ouercome <hi>them. Vp, Lord, therefore, and</hi> let not man haue the vpper hand: Awake, awake, &amp; put on strength, O Arme of the Lord, awake as in the ancient dayes, <hi>when</hi> thou didst deuide the Sea; and brakest the heads of <hi>the Egyptian</hi> Dragons in the waters: take vnto thee <hi>againe, O Lord,</hi> they great power, and raigne <hi>ouer all Nations, Iewes, and Gentiles: though they and we haue deserued no such King, but rather the most contrary; yet in the multitude of they mercies, burie the multitude of all our trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions: suffer not them nor vs</hi> to walke in darkenesse; <hi>but for thine</hi> owne Names sake, send out thy light and thy Truth, <hi>and</hi> let them leade vs, and bring <hi>vs to the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing knowledge and obedience of thee and thy Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Giue <hi>a blessing, O Lord, to all good meanes conducing to the same, &amp; namely to these few proofes &amp; obseruations, gathered, by thy assistance, from the</hi> Confession and Complaint <hi>of thy deare Sonne. In them, O God, defend what is thine owne: And</hi> let not those, O Lord God of hosts, that put their trust in thee, de ashamed <hi>of the Truth</hi> because of me, <hi>for who am I, dust and ashes, one of the lowest ranke of thy Seruants, that when many great and learned dare not, or doe not, I should aduenture to shew the wrongs done to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="4"/>of my Sauiour, that am not able of my selfe to thinke a good thought? Thou knowest, O Lord, that most men</hi> haue the faith of our Lord Iesus Christ, with respect of persons, <hi>looking more who writeth, then what is written; though they confesse, that it oft pleaseth thee,</hi> out of the mouthes of Babes and sucklings, to ordaine strength, because of thine enemies; <hi>for</hi> their <hi>greater shame and confusion,</hi> that <hi>so</hi> thou mightest still the enemie and auenger; <hi>when they shall see, that if they could get all the wise, and learned, and mightie men in the world, to be on their side, yet thou canst</hi> choose <hi>and enable</hi> the foolish things of this world to confound the wise, and the things that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e not, to bring to nought the things that are. <hi>Thou, O Lord God, art to such weakeones, the best Patron, the surest</hi> Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eld and Buckler: Shew <hi>therefore</hi> thy marueilous louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, O thou that sauest them that trust in thee, from those that resist thy right hand. <hi>Thou that canst mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest thy might in weakenesse,</hi> Bow the heauens, O Lord, and come downe, and make thy Name knowne to thine aduersaries, that the Nations may tremble at thy presence: Cast downe the strong holds and high <hi>conceits of proud Heretickes,</hi> exalted against the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thee the only true God, <hi>and thy Sonne</hi> Iesus Christ whom thou hast sent: <hi>Bring</hi> into captiuitie euery thought, to the obedience of thy Christ: for thine, O Lord, is the Kingdome, <hi>that then thou shouldest</hi> rule <hi>all, thine</hi> the power and the glorie, <hi>of giuing and effecting all good things: to thee, O Father, together with thy Sonne our Sauiour, and thy holy Spirit, three Persons, one true and euerliuing God, be giuen, as due is, all obedience, honour, praise, and glorie, now and for euer, Amen.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>