<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Sir THOMAS HOPE of Craig∣hall Knight Baronet, Advocat ge∣nerall to his Majestie of great Bri∣taine, in his Kingdome of Scotland, Wisheth all health and happinesse, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>M., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102714_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06682</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17139</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102714</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Sir THOMAS HOPE of Craig∣hall Knight Baronet, Advocat ge∣nerall to his Majestie of great Bri∣taine, in his Kingdome of Scotland, Wisheth all health and happinesse, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>M., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The generall practise of medecine : Comprehending the most remarkable maxims appertaining to the diagnosis, where, by everie disease is knowne, the prognosis, whereby the issue is foreshowne, and therapie, which poynteth out the methodick, proceeding in the cure. Collected out of the most famous, both ancient and moderne wryters, for the use of such as be ignorant of the Greeke and Latine tongues. By Philiatreus</title>
                 <author>Philiatreus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wreittoun (Scribonius), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Sir THOMAS HOPE of Craig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall Knight Baronet, Advocat ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to his Majestie of great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, in his Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> Wisheth all health and happinesse, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is reported of <hi>Caesar (Right Honourable</hi>) that oft times he praised his Souldiours good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, although they wanted skill: And <hi>Cicero</hi> aswell commended stamme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Lentulus</hi> for his painful industry, as learned <hi>Laelius</hi> for his passing elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: Which considered (although wisedome did will mee not to straine further than my sleive would stretch) I thought good to present this small Treatise to your H. protection, hoping
<pb facs="3"/>
your H. will out of your accustomed clemencie, accept it, and take my well meaning for an excuse of my boldnesse, in that my poore will is not in the wane, whatsoever this imperfect worke doth want. The Emperour <hi>Trajan</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver without suters, because so courteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee would heare everie complaint. The Lapidaries continually frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Court of <hi>Adobrandinus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was his chiefe study to search out the nature of stones. All that courted <hi>Atlanta</hi> were hunters, and none sued to <hi>Sapho</hi> but Poëts: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever <hi>Mecaenas</hi> lodgeth, thither no doubt will Schollers flocke. And your H. beeing a worthie favourer and fosterer of learning, hath forced many through your exquisit vertue, to offer the first fruits of their study at the shrine of your Courtesie. But though they have waded farre and found mynes, and I gadded abroad to get nothing but mytes: yet this I assure my selfe,
<pb facs="3"/>
that they never presented you their treasure with a more willing mind, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hen I doe this simple trash, which I hope your H. will so accept. Resting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>herefore upon your wonted clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie, I commit you to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>