<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102388_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20628</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7031</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102388</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Deaths duell, or, A consolation to the soule, against the dying life, and liuing death of the body : Deliuered in a sermon at White Hall, before the Kings Maiesty, in the beginning of Lent, 1630. By that late learned and reuerend diuine, Iohn Donne, Dr. in Diuinity, &amp; Deane of S. Pauls, London. Being his last sermon, and called by his Maiesties houshold the doctors owne funerall sermon</title>
                 <author>Donne, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Fisher, Benjamin</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Redmer, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 47, 1 page, portraits (metal cut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Sermon was, by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
Authoritie, stiled the
Authors owne funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.
Most fitly: whether
wee respect the time, or the
matter. It was preached not many dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
his death; as if, hauing done this, there
remained nothing for him to doe, but to die:
And the matter is, of Death; the occasion and
subiect of all funerall Sermons. It hath beene
obserued of this Reuerend Man, That his
Faculty in Preaching continually encreased:
and, That as hee exceeded others at first; so,
at last hee exceeded himselfe. This is his last
Sermon; I will not say, it is therefore his best;
because, all his were excellent. Yet thus much:
A dying Mans words, if they concerne our
<pb facs="4"/>
selues; doe vsually make the deepest impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
as being spoken most feelingly, and with
least affectation. Now, whom doth it not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
to learn, both the danger, and benefit of
death? Death is euery mans enemy, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
hurt to all; though to many, hee be occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
of greatest goods. This enemy we must
all combate dying; whom hee liuing did almost
conquer; hauing discouered the vtmost of his
power, the vtmost of his crueltie. May wee
make such vse of this and other the like prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiues,
That neither death, whensoeuer it
shall come, may seeme terrible; nor life te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious;
how long soeuer it shall last.</p>
   <signed>R.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>