<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>What cause first mooved the Author to write this A∣rithmeticke,
and with what order it is here taught, which
order the contents of the chapters therof hereafter follow∣ing
doe plainly shew.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102547_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16221</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3146</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102547</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>What cause first mooved the Author to write this A∣rithmeticke,
and with what order it is here taught, which
order the contents of the chapters therof hereafter follow∣ing
doe plainly shew.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>M. Blundevile his exercises : containing sixe treatises, the titles wherof are set down in the next printed page: which treatises are verie necessarie to be read and learned of all yoong gentlemen that haue not bene exercised in such disciplines, and yet are desirous to hau knowledge as well in cosmographie, astronomie, and geographie, as also in the arte of navigation, in which arte it is impossible to profite without the helpe of these, or such like instructions. To the furtherance of which arte of navigation, the said M. Blundevile speciallie wrote the said treatises and of meere good will doth dedicate the same to all the young gentlemen of this realme</title>
                 <author>Blundeville, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 350 leaves, 3 folded plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction_to_treatise_of_arithmetic">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>What cause first mooved the Author to write this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmeticke,
and with what order it is here taught, which
order the contents of the chapters therof hereafter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
doe plainly shew.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Began this Arithmeticke more than seuen
yeares since for a vertuous Gentlewoman,
and my verie deare frend M. <hi>Elizabeth
Bacon,</hi> the daughter of Sir <hi>Nicholas Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi>
Knight, a man of most excellent wit,
and of most deepe iudgment, and sometime
Lord Keeper of the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi>
and latelie (as shee hath bene manie yeares past) the most loving
and faithfull wife of my worshipfull friend M. Iustice <hi>Wynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
not long since deceased, who for his integritie of life, and
for his wisedome and iustice daylie shewed in gouernement, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
for his good hospitalitie deserued great commendation. And
though at her request I had made this Arithmeticke so plaine
and easie as was possible (to my seeming) yet her continuall sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
would not suffer her to exercise her selfe therein. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
that diuerse having seene it, and liking my plaine order of
teaching therein, were desirous to haue copies thereof, I thought
good therefore to print the same, and to augment it with many ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie
rules meet for those that are desirous to studie any part of
Cosmographie, Astronomie, or Geographie, and speciallie the
Arte of Navigation, in which without Arithmeticke, as I haue
said before, they shall hardly profit. But nowe to returne to my
<pb facs="5"/>
matter, the contents of this Arithmeticke are these here follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
First, hauing defined what Arithmeticke is, and what nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration
or numbring is, and of what parts it consisteth, and how
to number any great summe written in many figures, I deale
with the foure speciall kindes of Arithmeticke, that is, Addition,
Subtraction, multiplication, and division. Then I shewe the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of working in whole numbers, called in Latine <hi>Integra,</hi> by
the rule of proportion, otherwise called the golden rule, or the rule
of three. Then I treat of broken numbers called Fractions, setting
downe seuen necessarie rules belonging thereunto, by the helpe
whereof you shall be the better able to adde, subtract, to multiplie
and divide the same. That done, I shew how to vse the rule of three
aswell in dealing with sole fractions as with fractions annexed to
integrums, which rule of three is threefold, that is, the common
rule, the rule reverse, and the double rule, the order of all which
three kindes I doe plainlie teach by examples, shewing wherein,
how, and when, they are to be vsed. Next to that I set downe the
rule of fellowship, a necessarie rule for those that haue to traffique
in anie trade of merchandize, giving divers examples thereof.
Next to that I treat of Arithmeticall, and Geometricall progres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
and also of proportion, and of the three kindes thereof, that
is, of proportion Arithmeticall, Geometricall, and musicall.
Then I shew how to finde out the square roote of anie number,
and also the vse thereof in setting of Battels, and also how to finde
out the cubique roote of any number. And last of all I treat of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stronomicall
fractions, shewing how to adde, to subtract, to mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply
and divide the same. And also to take the square root there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
without the knowledge of which fractions, you can neuer cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate
any thing trulie out of the Astronomicall Tables.</p>
   <p>Some perhaps do look here that I should speak somewhat of the
rules of <hi>Algebra,</hi> whereby all subtill and intricate questions of
Arithmeticke are to be vnfolded, wherewith I leaue indeede
<pb facs="5"/>
deale, partlie, for that I haue not of long time exercised my selfe
therein, and partlie because I knowe that one hath begun to write
thereof, whose booke being once ended, I doubt not but that hee
will shortlie after print the same to the great profite and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rāce
of al those that delight in such good exercises. But in the mean
time I haue thought good to adde (as I haue saide before) vnto
this Arithmeticke a plaine description, together with the vse of
the Tables of Sines, of lines tangent and secant, which Tables
will pleasure many that would gladlie know how and wherein to
vse them, and specially such seamen as haue some taste of Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticke,
without the which no good almost is to bee done in anie
science.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>