<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reverend Author on his severall workes.</title>
           <author>Beesley, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102116_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00814</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10935</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102116</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reverend Author on his severall workes.</title>
                 <author>Beesley, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blessed birth-day : celebrated in some pious meditations, on the angels anthem. Luke 2. 14. Also holy raptures in contemplating of the most obserueable adjuncts about our Saviours nativitie. By Charles Fitz-Geffry</title>
                 <author>Fitz-Geffry, Charles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Forrest, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 55, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reverend Author on his severall workes.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>SIR, I not praise your witt, for that (all know)</l>
      <l>Praises it selfe: each line that thence doth flow</l>
      <l>Like to some pearle, or ray, or streame, well showes</l>
      <l>The Mine, Sunne, Fountaine, whence it first arose.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But that which ravishes iust praise from me,</l>
      <l>Is the choice method of your Poetrie;</l>
      <l>And that you could with such due equipage</l>
      <l>Sute seuerall poems to your severall age:</l>
      <l>So that in this your exemplary art</l>
      <l>Acts both the Poets, and the Preachers part.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Your younger wit, (as taking a delight</l>
      <l>In bold endeavours) ventur'd to recite</l>
      <l>The deeds of valiant Drake who by your skill,</l>
      <l>And strong descriptions, goes that voiage still</l>
      <l>Which once he did, and with full blasts of fame</l>
      <l>Yet sailes, (securely) round the earth againe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then, as experience taught you to survay</l>
      <l>The Worlds conditions, your free Muse would play</l>
      <l>In various Epigramms, where both for tongue,</l>
      <l>Conceit, and choise of verse, you seeme to runne</l>
      <l>With foremost Martiall, and so thriue therein;</l>
      <l>That you come nearest to the Goale next him.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But having now retreated from the fome</l>
      <l>Of surging youth, and safe at length come home</l>
      <l>To quiet age, diviner thoughts inspire</l>
      <l>Your pregnant fancy, and with holier fire</l>
      <l>In flame you to the sweet discovery</l>
      <l>Of Heavenly mysteries: where the most high</l>
      <l>Must exercise your soaring braine, to tell</l>
      <l>The Natalls of our Saviour, which so well</l>
      <l>You haue perform'd with each nice circumstance</l>
      <l>Of time, and place, and persons, to advance</l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>Such lofty wonders, that you make to vs</l>
      <l>Those miracles seeme more miraculous.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This is your praise: but will you heare me noise</l>
      <l>The shame of others that grow old in toies,</l>
      <l>Write plaies with spectacles, and spend an age</l>
      <l>Past threescore yeares on sonnets, and the stage:</l>
      <l>That chafe their palsied fancies, and molest</l>
      <l>With a forc't flame those embers that would rest:</l>
      <l>That bald, and dry, and sere, and wither'd, yet</l>
      <l>Yeild blossoms still, and chilblaines of their wit:</l>
      <l>As if (like Hesiod's infants) they still were</l>
      <l>But children at their almost hundreth yeare:</l>
      <l>That thinke their wild inventions too much pent</l>
      <l>In sacred taskes, and not their element</l>
      <l>To be in heavenly things, as if such stuff</l>
      <l>Were not conceited, rich, and fine enough</l>
      <l>For their loose numbers, or could not yeeld straines</l>
      <l>Of matter high enough to fill their veines</l>
      <l>With raptures; but o! how is this made vaine</l>
      <l>By noble Bartas! whose Heroicke braine</l>
      <l>Adorn'd Gods works, and like another light,</l>
      <l>Pictur'd the whole creation to our sight.</l>
      <l>Nay how is this made lye by those Saint-men,</l>
      <l>(Those spheares of witt) Tertullian, Nazianzen,</l>
      <l>Nissen, Lactantius, and more of that crue,</l>
      <l>That could be Fathers, and yet Poets too;</l>
      <l>And when they could not their rude enemies pierce</l>
      <l>With gentle prose, they batter'd them with verse,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But let them passe, and sucke the empty shout</l>
      <l>Of lewd applauses, which will shortly out</l>
      <l>In stench, and rottennesse, and then commit</l>
      <l>Their Authors to the <hi>Iudgement</hi> of their wit.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But surely who would dye (as they should doe)</l>
      <l>Good Poets, must first learne to be like you.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>HEN. BEESLEY A.A.A.M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>