<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧To the Right Honourable and most Noble Lord, WILLIAM Lord Compton, Baron of Compton, Nestors yeeres, with the felicitie of both Worldes.</title>
           <author>Folkingham, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102453_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01017</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11123</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102453</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧To the Right Honourable and most Noble Lord, WILLIAM Lord Compton, Baron of Compton, Nestors yeeres, with the felicitie of both Worldes.</title>
                 <author>Folkingham, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Feudigraphia : The synopsis or epitome of surueying methodized. Anatomizing the whole corps of the facultie; viz. The materiall, mathematicall, mechanicall and legall parts, intimating all the incidents to fees and possessions, and whatsoeuer may be comprized vnder their matter, forme, proprietie, and valuation. Very pertinent to be perused of all those, whom the right, reuenewe, estimation, farming, occupation, manurance, subduing, preparing and imploying of arable, medow, pasture, and all other plots doe concerne. And no lesse remarkable for all vnder-takers in the plantation of Ireland or Virginia, ... Composed in a compendious digest by W. Folkingham. G</title>
                 <author>Folkingham, W. (William)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Moore (More), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 88 pages, folded table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧To the Right Honourable and most <hi>Noble Lord,</hi> WILLIAM <hi>Lord</hi> Compton, Baron of Compton, <hi>Nestors</hi> yeeres, with the felicitie of both Worldes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O deriue my inducements (Right Honourable) of Dedicating these shallow Deseignes vnto a Mecae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas of such Supereminence, from Presidents of worthy witts and particular Obligees to eminent Patrons, my Fortunes haue not so auspiciously en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared me their happy Fauourite. But the Vniuersall concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of good Hearts with hearty zeale (from the Verge of a vaste extent) in the <hi>Center</hi> of true affectionated praise of your worth, and prayers for your weale, hath hasted &amp; haled-on the whole Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of my affections to runne with the Generall Concurse of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained welwillers, to congratulate your Lordships hopefull and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie Consolidations: For such and so manifold are those worthy Attributes of accomplished Amplitude and magnified Merits dimayning from the sacred <hi>Source</hi> of true Nobility, that they haue euen winged my feruent Desires, (more animated with self-approument of deuote sinceritie then amazed with myrrors of Magnificence) to the consecrating of these my prest Deseignemēts to your Honourable Patrocinie. But if such Motiues bee incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to giue due Colour of excuse to Intrusions so exorbitant, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech
<pb facs="3"/>
your Lordship giue me leaue to flee to the prostrate Plea of praying your gracious Indulgence for my rude <hi>Presume</hi> in daring from the remote <hi>Nadir</hi> of obscurity, to eleuate the flaggie Wing of so weake a Pineon towards the <hi>Zenith</hi> of Perfection, the mark and Pitch for Skie-towring Faulcons, whose Quills imped with strong Sarcells of the Grace of Greatnes, are inlisened and inhabled to transcende and climbe-aboue the mistie Vapours that cloude and Eclipse all Flights which peirce not to the <hi>Welkin</hi> of the <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies.</hi> For who sees not that <hi>Heroes</hi> (Gods Vice-gerents) can dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie euen the inglorious Groome, &amp; giue such Glosse, and Tincture to home-made <hi>Statuaes,</hi> as shal attract the Eye of wonder to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the potent Artists for refining &amp; remoulding their (now) new creatures, as well as with the Touch-stone of refined knowledge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trud &amp; banish all Deseignes, disfurnisht of true &amp; due self-worth, from the Confines of high Repute? But least in labouring, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulgar Ingredients, to palate an ill seasoned Seruice, I should by te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and vnrelished Tearmes, impart a worse distaste, I will screw-vp this Key with the prostrate sacring of my selfe and my poore Endeauours at the Shrine of your gracious Clemencie. And so euer wishing vnto your Honour the happie fruition of vnconfined Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity. I rest, now and euer,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>London at the White Hart in Cheape-side,</hi>
         <date>Iunij. <hi>6. 1610.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lordships humbly deuoted.</hi> W. Folkingham.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>