<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>ERRATA.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102095_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00746</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10874</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102095</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>ERRATA.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The calling of the Ievves : A present to Iudah and the children of Israel that ioyned with him, and to Ioseph (the valiant tribe of Ephraim) and all the house of Israel that ioyned with him. The Lord giue them grace, that they may returne and seeke Iehovah their God, and Dauid their King, in these latter dayes. There is prefixed an epistle vnto them, written for their sake in the Hebrue tongue, and translated into English. Published by William Gouge, B. of D. and preacher of Gods word in Blackefryers. London</title>
                 <author>Finch, Henry, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Bladen, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 234, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="119"/>
   <head>ERRATA.</head>
   <p>Faults escaped which it may please the Reader to amend with his Pen before he read, r<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>signifieth, read.</p>
   <p>FOlio 2. line 3. for <hi>(high)</hi> read, <hi>large,</hi> line 9. for <hi>into</hi> r. <hi>vnto,</hi> fol. 9. l. 9. for <hi>moane,</hi> read <hi>meane,</hi> fol. 10. l. 7. put out fig. 1. and put it after, obseru, fol. 13. Deut. 32. &amp;c. at the margent put it out there &amp; put it after line 24. f. 14. l. 25. r. <hi>spurre put,</hi> line 34. put out, often. l. 37. in stead of, <hi>particularly,</hi> r. <hi>particuler,</hi> fol. 15. l. 1. &amp; 2. put out amongst damosels, &amp;c. and put it line 3. after Instruments, fol. 18. l. 12. put out, <hi>first,</hi> l. 19. for <hi>third</hi> r. <hi>teach,</hi> fol. 33. line. 30. for <hi>if</hi> r. <hi>of,</hi> fol. 37. line 29. for <hi>insufferable</hi> r. <hi>vnsufferable,</hi> fol. 38. line 14. for <hi>opposition</hi> r. <hi>exposition,</hi> l. 26. r. <hi>was in,</hi> l. 28. for <hi>godlie</hi> r. <hi>goodly,</hi> line 34. in stead of 2. <hi>By.</hi> r. 8. <hi>An.</hi> fol. 50. line 2. for <hi>excellently</hi> r. <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi> fol. 52. line 24. for <hi>or</hi> r. <hi>are.</hi> fol. 60. line 18. for 11. r. 14. fol. 63. line <hi>vlt.</hi> for <hi>Joel</hi> 3. 12. r. <hi>Ioel</hi> 3. 8. fol. 70. line 33. for <hi>my</hi> r. <hi>the,</hi> fol. 78. line 2. &amp; 3. put out 9. 10. line 10. before verse 7. put Chapter 20. fol. 79. line 3. after <hi>but,</hi> put <hi>there,</hi> fol. 80. line 3. r. verse 9. 10. fol. 90. line 12. for <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> read <hi>ending,</hi> fol. 99. line 4. for <hi>Hartesbi</hi> r. <hi>Hartsebi,</hi> fol. 108. l. 27. for <hi>moment</hi> r. <hi>monument,</hi> fol. 133. line 24 <hi>after readie,</hi> adde, <hi>to say,</hi> fol. 153. line 3. for <hi>sixt</hi> r. <hi>second,</hi> line 5. for 67. r. 63. line 7. put out <hi>seauenth,</hi> line 11. for 21. r. 25. in stead of <hi>sixt</hi> read <hi>second,</hi> line 27. for <hi>Dan.</hi> 1. 11. read <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. 1. fol. 154. line 1. for <hi>let</hi> r. <hi>left,</hi> fol. 155. line 35. after <hi>is</hi> adde <hi>it,</hi> fol. 160. line 5. for <hi>wrought</hi> r. <hi>wrote,</hi> line 23. for <hi>seauenth</hi> r. <hi>seauentieth,</hi> fol. 161. line 14. after Angel, <hi>say to a messiah gouernor shàll be seauen seauens, and sixtie two seauens</hi> fol. 161. line 26. for <hi>any</hi> r. <hi>an.</hi> fol. 162 line 24. for <hi>while</hi> r. <hi>whole,</hi> fol. 163. line 33. for <hi>those</hi> r. <hi>these,</hi> fol. 164 line 5. r. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 29. 18. line 22. for <hi>gaue</hi> r <hi>giue,</hi> fol. 165. put out line r. and a peece of the second fol. 167. line 23. put out namely 26. fol. 168. line 25. r. <hi>his death,</hi> fol. 172 line 12. r. <hi>was in doing,</hi> fol. 175. line 31. for <hi>their</hi> read <hi>there,</hi> line 23. put out, 480. <hi>yeares from the Passeouer to the Temple,</hi> line 35. for <hi>Iudge</hi> r. <hi>Iudges ruled,</hi> line 37. r. <hi>Gedeon</hi> 40. fol. 176. line 1. read <hi>Elon</hi> 10. l. 8. r. <hi>Ammon</hi> 18. fol. 177. line 4. after <hi>anew</hi> adde 52. fol. 179. line 17. for 25. r. 15 line 35. for <hi>he</hi> read <hi>God,</hi> fol 182. line <hi>vlt.</hi> for <hi>certaine</hi> r. <hi>retaine,</hi> fol. 186. line 24. for <hi>Ier.</hi> 37. &amp;c. read <hi>Ier.</hi> 3. 7. &amp;c. fol. 188. line 30. for <hi>hath</hi> r. <hi>had,</hi> fol. 189. line 6. for <hi>diated</hi> read <hi>doated,</hi> fol 191. line 6. for <hi>into</hi> read <hi>vnto.</hi> fol. 192. line 21. for 2. r. 11. fol. 198. in the margent for <hi>Shidds</hi> say <hi>Shields,</hi> line 28 for <hi>into</hi> r. <hi>vnto,</hi> fol. 199. line 10. for <hi>into</hi> r. <hi>vnto.</hi> fol. 206. line 10. for <hi>(as)</hi> r. <hi>all.</hi> fol. 220. line 10. for <hi>tuned</hi> r. <hi>tamed,</hi> fol. 222. line 21. for <hi>thirdly</hi> read <hi>fourthly,</hi> fol. 227. l. 34. for <hi>fall</hi> r. <hi>kall.</hi> fol. 230. line 12. for <hi>puttedst</hi> r. <hi>didst put.</hi> fol. 231. line 27. read <hi>grow: notably expressing.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="120"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="120"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>