<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE CON∣TEINING FIVE SVNDRIE ABVSES or corruptions of holy Scriptures, common to all Heretikes, and agreeing specially to these of our time▪ with many other necessarie aduertisements to the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102715_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01309</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11430.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102715</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE CON∣TEINING FIVE SVNDRIE ABVSES or corruptions of holy Scriptures, common to all Heretikes, and agreeing specially to these of our time▪ with many other necessarie aduertisements to the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defense of the sincere and true translations of the holie Scriptures into the English tong : against the manifolde cauils, friuolous quarels, and impudent slaunders of Gregorie Martin, one of the readers of popish diuinitie in the trayterous Seminarie of Rhemes. By William Fulke D. in Diuinitie, and M. of Pembroke haule in Cambridge. Wherevnto is added a briefe confutation of all such quarrels &amp; cauils, as haue bene of late vttered by diuerse papistes in their English pamphlets, against the writings of the saide William Fulke</title>
                 <author>Fulke, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 95, 1, 144, 147-514, 517-532, 4, 71, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="response_to_preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEINING FIVE SVNDRIE ABVSES or corruptions of holy Scriptures, common to all Heretikes, and agreeing specially to these of our time▪ with many other necessarie aduertisements to the reader.</head>
   <div type="Martins_comments">
      <head>MARTIN.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>AS it hath bene alwaies the fashion of Heretikes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend</hi>
         <note place="margin">Heretikes fiue vvaies specially abuse the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note>
         <hi>Scriptures, for shew of their cause: so hath it bene also their custome and propertie to abuse the saide Scriptures many waies, in fauour of their errours.</hi>
      </p>
      <div type="Fulkes_response">
         <head>FVLKE.</head>
         <p>
            <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HETHER these fiue abuses haue bene common to all heretikes, &amp; whether it hath bene the fashion of all here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes to pretende Scriptures for shewe of their cause: though I will spare nowe to enquire of, as a thing wherin learned men at the first sight may espie the great skil that <hi>Martin</hi> pretendeth to haue in discerning of heretikes and heresies; yet will I shew (by the grace of God) that none
<pb n="4" facs="5"/>
of these fiue abuses are committed by vs, or our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like translations, &amp; that the popish heretikes are in some sort, or other guiltie of them all.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="1" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 1.</hi> One way is, to denie whole bookes thereof or<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Denying cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine bookes or parts of bookes.</note> partes of bookes, when they are euidently against them. So did (for example) Ebion all S. Paules epistles▪ Manicheus the Actes of the Apostles, Alogiani S. Iohns Gospell, Marcion ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny peeces of S. Lukes Gospell, and so did both these and other he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes in other bookes, denying and allowing what they liste, as is euident by S. Irenaeus, S. Epiphanius, S. Augustine, and all antiquitie.</p>
      <div n="1" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 1. First we denie no one booke of the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall scripture that hath bene so receaued of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like church, for the space of 300. yeares, &amp; more, as it hath bene often proued out of Eusebius, S. Ierome, and other ancient authorities: but the Papists in aduauncing Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphall bookes to be of equall credite with the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Scriptures, do in effect deny thē all. Besides that to adde vnto the word of God, is as great a fault as to take away from it, the one being forbidden vnder as heauie a curse, as the other. Those blasphemies of Pighius &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius, the one calling the holy Scripture a nose of waxe and a dumbe iudge, the other terming the Gospel writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, to be a blacke Gospell, and an ynkie Diuinitie, and that of Hosius acknowleging none other expresse word of God, but onely this one worde <hi>Ama,</hi> or <hi>dilige,</hi> loue thou: what other thing do they import, but a shamelesse deniall of all bookes of the holy Scripture in deede, how soeuer in worde they will seeme to admitte them.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 2.</hi> An other way is, to call into question at the<note place="margin">2 Doubting of their authoritie, and calling thē into question.</note> least and make some doubt of the authoritie of certaine bookes of holy scriptures, therby to diminish their credite, so did Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus affirme of the whole new Testamēt, that it was not writtē by the Apostles: and peculiarly of S. Matthewes Gospell, that it was some other mās vnder his name: &amp; therfore not of such cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, but that it might in some part be refused. So did Marcion &amp; the Ariās deny the epistle to the Hebrues to be S. Paules. Epiph.
<pb n="5" facs="5"/>
li. 2. haer. 69. Euseb. li. 4. hist. c. 27▪ &amp; Alogiani the Apocalypse to be S. Iohns the Euāgelist. Epiph. &amp; August in haer. Alogianorii.</p>
      <div n="2" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 2. We neither doubt of the authoritie of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie certaine booke of the holy Scriptures, neither cal we any of them into question, but with due reuerence do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thē all, &amp; euery one to be of equall credit &amp; authority, as being al inspired of god▪ giuē to the church for the building vp thereof in truth, and for the auoiding of fables, &amp; heresies: But the Papists arrogating to their Pope, authoritie to allowe or refuse, any booke of holy Scripture, &amp; affirming that no Scripture hath authoritie, but as it is approued by their church, do bring al bookes of the holy Scripture into doubting, &amp; vncertaintie, with such as wil depend vpō their Pope, &amp; popish churches au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: which they affirme to be aboue the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, saying they might as wel receaue the gospel of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus as of S. Marke, &amp; by the same authoritie reiect the Gospell of S. Matthew, as they haue done the Gospel of S. Bartholomew. These blasphemous assertions al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though some of them would couler, or mitigate with gentle interpretations: yet their is no reasonable man but seeth, into what discredite and vncertaintie they must needes bring the authoritie of the Canonicall bookes of holy Scripture with the simple and ignorant.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 3.</hi> An other way is, to expound the Scriptures<note place="margin">2 Voluntarie expositions ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones fansie or heresie.</note> after their owne priuate conceite and phantasie, not according to the approued sense of the holy auncient fathers and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, so did Theodorus Mopsuestites (Act. Synod. 5.) affirme of all the bookes of the Prophets, and of the Psalmes, that they spake not euidently of Christ, but that the auncient fathers did voluntarily draw those sayings vnto Christ which were spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of other matters, so did all heretikes, that would seeme to ground their heresies vpon Scriptures, and to auouch them by Scriptures expounded according to their owne sense and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
      <div n="3" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 3. We expound not the Scriptures after our owne priuate conceite, and fantasie: but as neere as God
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>
giueth vs grace, according to the plaine and natural sense of the same, agreable vnto the rule or proportiō of faith, which bene approued by the auncient fathers, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike church of Christ, in al matters necessarie to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall saluation. Not bringing a newe and straunge sense which is without the Scriptures, to seeke confirmation thereof in the Scriptures (as the manner of heretikes is rightly noted by <hi>Clemens)</hi> but out of the Scriptures thē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues seeke we the exposition of such obscure places as we find in them, being perswaded with <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> that nothing in a manner is founde out of those obscure and darke places, which may not be found to be most plaine ly spoken in other places. And as for the approued sense of the holy auncient Fathers, and Catholike Church of the eldest and purest times, if the Papists durst stand vnto it, for the deciding of many of the most waightie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies, that are betweene vs, there is no doubte, but▪ they should soone and easily be determined, as hath bene shewed in diuerse and many treatises, written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them. In which if any thing bee brought, so plainely expounding the Scripture against their popish heresies, as nothing can be more expresse nor cleare, then they are driuen to seeke newe and monstrous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of those Fathers interpretations: or else they answere, they are but those Fathers priuate expositions, appealing to the Catholike churches interpretation, which is nothing else but their owne priuate conceipte and fansie, hauing no recorde to proue that Catholike Churches interpretation, but the present hereticall opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, of this late degenerated Antichristian congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And whē they haue discoursed neuer so much of the Catholike churches interpretation, they reduce and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte all mens iudgements to the determinatiō of their Councels, &amp; the decrees of the Councels to the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of their Pope, which as he is oftentimes a wicked man of life: so is he ignorant and vnlearned in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to whose most priuate cēsure, the holy Scriptures
<pb n="7" facs="6"/>
themselues, and al sense and exposition of them is made subiect, vnder colour that Christ praying for Peter, that his faith should not fayle in temptation, gaue all Popes suche a prerogatiue, that they could not erre in faith▪ though they were wicked of life, voyde of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ignorant in the Scriptures, destitute of the spirite of God, as is proued moste inuincibly by example of diuerse Popes, that haue bene heretikes, and maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of such errours, as are not now in controuersie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs (least they should say we begge the principle) but of the secte of the Arrians, Monothelites, Eutychi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Saduces, and such other.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="4" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 4.</hi> An other way is, to alter the very originall<note place="margin">4. Changing some vvordes or sentences of the very origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall text. Tertul. cont. Marae cio. li. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. in princ. Tertul. lib. 5.</note> text of the holy Scripture, by adding, taking away, or changing it here and there for their purpose. So did the Arians in sundry places, and the Nestorians in the first epistle of S. Iohn, and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially Marcion, who was therefore called, <hi>Mus Ponticus,</hi> the mouse of Pontus, because he had gnawen (as it were) certaine places with his corruptions, whereof some are sayd to remaine in the Greeke text vntill this day.</p>
      <div n="4" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 4. The originall text of the holie Scripture we alter not, either by adding, taking away, or changing of any letter, or syllable, for any priuate purpose, which were not only a thing most wicked and sacrilegious, but also vaine, and impossible. For, seeing not only so many auncient coppies of the original text are extant in diuers places of the worlde, which we can not, if we woulde, corrupt, and that the same are multiplied by printing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to so many thousande examples, wee shoulde bee rather madde than foolishe, if we did but once attempt such a matter, for maintenaunce of any of our opinions. As also it is incredible, that Marcion the mouse of Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, coulde corrupt all the Greeke coppies in the world, as Lindanus, of whome you borrowed that conceite, imagineth, in those places in which he is charged by Tertullian. For Marcions heresie was not so general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued by the Greeke Churche, that all men would
<pb n="8" facs="7"/>
yeeld vnto him, neither was Tertullian so soūd of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Latine Church, that whatsoeuer he iudged to be a corruption in Marcion▪ must of necessity be so ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. But if adding, and detracting from the Scripture, be proper notes of heretikes, who can purge Stephen Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner, &amp; Gregorie Martine? The one for adding vnto a the verse of the Psalme, this pronowne <hi>se,</hi> him selfe, to proue the carnall presens, citing it thus. <hi>Escam se dedit ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentibus eum.</hi> He gaue himselfe to be meate▪ to them that feare him, whereas the words of the Prophet, according to the Hebrue, Greeke, and Latine are no more but▪ <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scam dedit.</hi> He hath giuen meat, &amp;c. The other in his fond booke of schisme, citing this text out of 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. as many Papistes doe against the certaintie of Faith. <hi>Qui stat, videat ne cadat.</hi> He that standeth let him take heede he fall not. Whereas not only the truth of the Greeke: but euen the vulgar Latin translation hath. <hi>Qui se existi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat stare,</hi> He that thinketh or supposeth that he standeth, let him take heede that he fall not. But of such additions and detractions, vsed by the Romishe rattes, farre worse than the myse of Pontus, we shall haue more occasion to speake hereafter.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="5" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 5.</hi> Another way is, to make false translations of the Scriptures for the maintenaunce of errour and heresie: so<note place="margin">False and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical trāslation.</note> did the Arians (as S. Hierome noteth in 26. Esa.) reade and translate Prouerb. 8. <hi>Dominus creauit me in intio viarum suarum,</hi> that is, <hi>The Lord created mein the beginning of his waies,</hi> so to make Christ the wisedom of God a mere crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, possedi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> S. Augustin also lib 5. cont. Iulian. c. 2. noteth it as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of some Pelagian. Gen. 3. <hi>Fecerunt sibi vesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta▪</hi> for, <hi>perizómata,</hi> or <hi>campestria,</hi> that is, <hi>They made them selues garments.</hi> Whereas the word of the Scripture is, b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eeches or aprons proper and peculiar to couer the secretparts. Againe, the selfe same heretikes did read falsely Rom. 5. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnauit mors ab Adam vsque ad Moysen etiam in eos qui<note place="margin">Aug. ep. 89. &amp; lib. 1. de pec. mer. cap. 11.</note> peccauerunt in similitudinem praeuaricationis</hi> Adae▪ that is. <hi>Death reigned from Adam to Moyses, euen on them</hi>
         <pb n="9" facs="7"/>
         <hi>that sinned after the similitude of the preuaricatiō of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> to maintaine their heresie against originall sinne, that none were infected therewith, or subiect to death &amp; damnation, but by sinning actually as Adam did. Thus did the old heretiks.</p>
      <div n="5" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 5. As touching false and hereticall transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which is the chiefe argument of this booke, I doubt not, but by the grace of god to cleare our english translators from any wilfull corruptions, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of any errour, or heresie: such as were those of the Arrians &amp; Pelagians, which Gregorie Martin, as though he vttered some great peece of skill, doth so diligently expresse. I shall haue occasion also to shew, that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes them selues of our times, maintaining their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt vulgar translation, against the truth of the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall textes of Greeke, and Hebrew, are most guiltie of such corruption, and falsification, whereof although they be not the first authors, yet by obstinate defending of such errors, they may proue worse than they which did first commit them. For the authors of that vulgar tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation, might be deceiued, either for lacke of exact knowledge of the tongues, or by some corrupt, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true copies which they followed, or else perhaps that which they had rightly translated, by fault of the writers, &amp; negligence of the times might be peruerted: but these men frowardly iustifying all errours of that translation, howsoeuer they haue bene brought in, do giue plaine te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony, that they are not led with any cōsciēce of Gods truth, but wilfully carried with purpose of maintaining their owne errours: least if they did acknowledge the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the Romish church in that one point they should not bee able to defende any one iote of their heresie, whose chiefe colour is the credit and authoritie of that particular and false church, rather than any reason or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument out of the holy Scriptures, or testimonie of the most auncient Christian and Catholike church.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="6" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 6.</hi> What these of our daies? is it credible that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so wel warned by the condēnation &amp; detestation of thē, they
<pb n="10" facs="8"/>
also would be as mad and as impious as those? Heretikes (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader) be alwayes like Heretikes, and howsoeuer they differ in opinions or names, yet in this point they agree, to abuse the Scriptures for their purpose by all meanes possibly. I will but touch foure points of the fiue before mentioned, because my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose is to stay vpon the last onely, and to discipher their corrupt translations. But if I would stand vpon the other also, were it not<note place="margin">That the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants &amp; Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinists vse the foresaid fiue meanes of defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> easie to shew the maner of their proceeding against the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to haue bene thus: to deny some whole bookes and partes of bookes, to call other some into question, to expound the rest at their pleasure, to picke quarrels to the very originall and Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall text, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o fester and infect the whole bodie of the Bible with cancred translations?</p>
      <div n="6" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 6. It is very true, that so many Heretikes as pretend the authoritie of the holy Scriptures, abuse the same to their owne destruction: and no Heretikes worse than the Antichristians, or Papistes. As partly hath bene seene already in euery one of your fiue markes, &amp; more may appeare in those foure pointes which you will han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in the Preface, because the argument of your whole booke is the fift: so that in the ende you shal be proued no wiser with your fiue pointes, than he that came forth with his fiue egges, &amp; neuer a good of them all. But you aske, if it were not easie for you to shew (if you would stand vpon them) that the Protestants vse all the said siue meanes of defacing the Scripture? I answer no, and that shal you see when demonstratiō is made, how vainly you haue laboured in the last point: which howsoeuer you would haue it appeare to be a sudden writing, of small trauail, by interlacing a few lines here &amp; there, against M. Whitaker, against me, &amp; some other: yet it is euident both by Bristowes threatning, and Campions promise, that it hath bene a work of some yeares vnto you: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in beside that you are beholding much to Lindanus, for diuers quarrels against Caluin, and to sir Thomas More, for many cauillations against W. Tyndals translation: there is litle worthy of so long study, and large promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
<pb n="11" facs="8"/>
as haue gone before this diligent discouerie: so that if you will make the like triall in the rest, you shall finde them as hard to proue as this last.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="7" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 7.</hi> Did not Luther deny S. Iames epistle &amp; so contemne it that he called it an epistle of strawe, and not worthy of an Apostolicall spirit? must I proue this to M. Whitakers, who would neuer haue denied it so vehemently in the superla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue<note n="*" place="margin">Cont. rat. Edm. Camp. pag. 18. Retent pag. 32. dist. <hi>of the Rock</hi> pag. 307. Luther in no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>o Test. Germa. in Prefat. Iacobi.</note> degree for shame, if he had not thought it more shame to graunt it? I neede not goe farre for the matter: Aske M. Fulke, and he will flatly confesse it was so. Aske Caluin <hi>in arg. ep. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi.</hi> Aske Flaccus Illyricus, <hi>in argum. ep. Iacobi,</hi> and you shall perceiue it is very true. I will not send you to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Germans and others, both of his owne time and after, that wrote against him in the question of iustification: among whome not one omitteth this, being a thing so famous and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous to the confusion of that Arch heretike.</p>
      <div n="7" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 7. I know not whether euer Luther denied S. Iames epistle as vnworthy of an Apostolical spirit, but I beleue you may take a twelue monethes daye more to proue it, as also that he did so contemne it, that he called it an epistle of straw. But M. Whitaker which denied it so vehemently▪ must aske of me, who moste slatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse (sayth M. Martin) that it was so. I pray you sir, vrge me not to confesse more than I know, or euer knew. But you haue confessed it already in two printed bookes, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. pag.</hi> 32. <hi>Disc</hi> of the Rock, <hi>pag</hi> 307. In the place first ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ther are these words But to proceed: LVTHER DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIETH THE EPISTLE OF S. IAMES, BECAVSE IT IS AGAINST HIS HERESIE OF IVSTIFI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CATION BY FAITH ONELY. <hi>We allow not Luther, neither did he allow him selfe therein, for he retracteth it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> First those wordes of Luthers denyall being prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a diuerse letter, may testifie sufficiently to euery reasonable man, that they are the obiection of Bristow, and not the confession of Fulke, who not simplye ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth them as true, but by concession, proueth that if they were true, yet Luthers opinion, against which he
<pb n="12" facs="9"/>
him selfe hath written, ought not to preiudice him, and much lesse all other men, that neuer held that opinion. In the later cited place, are these wordes. <hi>And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the epistle of S. Iames, it is a shamelesse slaunder of him to say that the Protestants reiect it, but we must heare his reason. First Luther calleth it a strawen epistle. So Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther called the Pope supreame head of the Church, and the masse a sacrifice propitiatorie. If Protestants be charged to holde whatsoeuer Luther sometime helde, and after repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> &amp;c. Who seeth not in these words, that I rehearse the obiection of Saunder, which is common to him with many other Papistes, which not discussing whether it be true or no, but supposing it were as Saunder and the rest of the Papistes doe affirme. I shewe that it is no good consequence, to charge all Protestants with Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers priuate opinion, which perhaps he helde some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and after retracted, more than to charge vs with all opinions of Papistrie, which de did hold, before God opened his eyes to see the absurditie of them. And yet if he had helde that opinion, and neuer retracted the same, he were not in worse case than Eusebius, who in playne wordes affirmeth, that the same epistle is a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfet or bastard epistle, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. Doe you not see nowe how flatly Maister Fulke confesseth that it was so? Such confessions as these, are nowe &amp; than extorted out of the auncient fathers writings, which are not liuing to expounde their meanings. But I had thought Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Martin could haue discerned betwene a suppose or concession, and an absolute assertion, or a flat confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, especially of one whose writing is plaine enough, and beside is aliue to interprete himselfe, if any ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitie were therein. But be it that Maister Martin ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would not, or could not see in my writing any thing else but a flat confession of Luthers denying of S. Iames epistle, and calling it an epistle of strawe, of what fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head proceedeth it, that he willeth Maister Whitaker to aske Caluin <hi>in argum. Epist. Iacobi,</hi> whether Luther so
<pb n="13" facs="9"/>
speake of that epistle? in which argument Luther is not once named by Caluin, so farre is it, that he doth testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie any such thing against Luther. Onely he sayth, that some there are in these dayes, which thinke that epistle not worthy of authoritie, which could not be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood of Luther, who long before Caluin wrote that argument, had forsaken that opinion, if euer he helde any such, as all those Dutche Bibles and Testaments of Luthers translation, in which those wordes so muche bayted at, and so much sought for are omitted, doe giue sufficient testimonie. What <hi>Flaccus Illyricus</hi> reporteth▪ who perhaps helde that opinion him selfe, and woulde father it vppon Luther, I haue neither opportunitie to seeke, nor care to knowe. But howe great a matter it is, that all the Popish Germans, and other, who haue written against Luther, doe so spitefully gnawe vpon, I haue learned at length by relation of Maister Whitaker. whome you send to aske of me: who after long search and many editions turned ouer, at the length lighted vpon a Dutch Testament, by likehood one of the first that Luther did sette forth in the German tongue, in which he findeth neither deniall of S. Iames epistle to be Canonicall, nor affirmation that it is vnworthy of an Apostolicall spirit, no nor that whereof there hath bene so much babling of all the Papistes, that he calleth it an epistle of strawe simply, and in contempt, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in comparison of the epistles of Paule and Peter, and other bookes of the newe Testament, the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of which one aboue an other, after he hath shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in sundry degrees, at last he sayth, the epistle of Iames in comparison of these, is strawye, or like straw. Which he sayth not in respect of the credit or authority thereof, but in regarde of the argument or matter handled therein, which all wise and godly men will confesse to bee not so excellent and necessary, as the matter of the holye Gospels and Epistles of some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Apostles, namely of Paule, Peter, and Iohn.
<pb n="14" facs="10"/>
Our Sauiour Christ himself, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 12▪ calleth the doctrine of regeneration, in such plaine maner as he vttered it, to Nicodemus, earthly things in comparison of other grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mysteries, which he coulde haue expressed in more heauenly &amp; spirituall sort. If I haue spoken to you (sayth he) of earthly things, and you haue not beleued, how if I shoulde speake to you of heauenly things, will you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue? Were not he an honest and a wise man, that vpon these words of Christ spoken in comparison, would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude by his authoritie, that regeneration were a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible matter, a thing not spirituall, not heauenly, but simply and altogither earthly. And yet with, as good reason, for ought I see or can learne of Luthers wordes concerning this matter, he might so inferre, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists doe inforce, the like against Luther. Wherefore it is nothing else but a famous and infamous cauillation, to the confusion of all the Papistes which write against Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that no one of them omitteth vpon so false and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous a ground, to sclaunder him so haynously, and to charge all Protestantes with his assertion so enuiously: which if it were his, should not be so euill as other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike writers haue affirmed of that Epistle, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not sufficient to charge him, and much lesse others with heresie: but being not his simple affirmation, yet because it hath bene offensiuely taken, he him selfe hath put it out, and giuen it ouer. O what a sturre would they keepe, if they had any weightie matter of truth to bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then him withall?</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="8" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 8.</hi> To let this passe: Tobie, Ecclesiasticus, and the Machabees are they not most certainly reiected? And yet<note place="margin">Conc. Cart. 3. can. 47.</note> they were allowed and receiued for Canonicall, by the same au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie that S. Iames Epistle was. This Epistle the Caluinists are content to admit, because so it pleased Caluine: those<note n="*" place="margin">Argu. in epist. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</note> bookes they reiect, because so also it pleased him. And why did it so please Caluine? Vnder pretence forsooth, that they were once doubted of, and not taken for Canonicall. But is that the true cause in deede? Howe doe they then receiue S. Iames<note n="*" place="margin">Whitak. p. 10.</note>
         <pb n="15" facs="10"/>
Epistle as Canonicall, hauing before doubted of also, yea (as they say) reiected?<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note>
      </p>
      <div n="8" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 8. You may well let it passe, for it is not worth the time you spend in writing of it, and if you had bene wise, you would vtterly haue omitted it. But what say you of Tobie, Ecclesiasticus, and the Machabees most certainly by vs reiected? <hi>They were allowed</hi> (you say) <hi>for Canonicall by the same authoritie that S. Iames Epistle was.</hi> And thinke you that S. Iames Epistle was neuer allowed for Canonicall before the third Councell of Carthage? For, of the other it is certaine they were neuer receiued by the Church of the Israelits before Christ his cōming, nor of the Apostolike and primitiue Church for more than 300. yeres after, as both Eusebius out of Origines, and the Councell of Laodicea <hi>Can.</hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>9. confirmed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde by the sixt generall Councell of Constantinople sheweth for the Greeke Church, and S. Ierome <hi>in prologo</hi>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note>
            <hi>Galeato</hi> for the Latine Church. As for the prouinciall Councell of Carthage holden by 44. Bishops of Africa, if we were bound to receiue it for these bookes, we must also acknowledge fiue bookes of Salomon, which in the same Councell are authorised, whereas the Church neuer knew but of three. And although the booke of wisedom should be ascribed to Salomō, there could be but foure. Againe, how they vnderstand the word Canonical, it may be gathered both out of the wordes of the same Canon, where they giue none other reason of the approbatiō of all those books of Scripture, but that they haue receiued them of their fathers to be read in the Church: and also out of S. Augustine, who was one present at the same<note place="margin">
               <hi>De doct. Christ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> Coūcell: which after he hath declared how a man should discerne the Canonicall Scriptures from other writings, by following the authoritie of the Catholike Churches, especially those that haue deserued to haue Apostolike sees, and to receiue their Epistles, he addeth further. <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebit igitur hunc modum in scripturis canonicis, vt eas quae ab omnibus accipiuntur Ecclesijs Catholicis, praeponat eis quas</hi>
            <pb n="16" facs="11"/>
            <hi>quaedā non accipiunt. In eis vero quae non accipiuntur ab om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, praeponat eas, quas plures grauiorès{que} accipiunt eis quas pauciores minoris{que} authoritatis Ecclesiae tenent. Si autem alias inuenerit à pluribus, alias à grauioribus haberi, quanquam hoc inuenire non possit, aequalis tamē auctoritatis eas habēdas puto. Totus autem canon scripturarum in quo istam considerationem versandam dicimus, his libris continetur.</hi> He shall hold ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this meane in the canonical Scriptures, that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre those which are receiued of all catholike churches, before those Scriptures which some Churches do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. But in those which are not receiued of all, let him preferre those Scriptures which the greater number and grauer churches do receiue, before those which churches fewer in number &amp; of lesse authority do hold. But if he shal find some Scriptures to be had of fewer churches &amp; other some of grauer churches, althogh you can not find this thing, yet I thinke they are to be accōpted of equall authority. Now the whole canō of scriptures in which we say this consideration must be occupied is contained in these books. Fiue books of Moises, that is Genesis, Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, &amp;c. By this saying of Augustine, it is manifest, that he calleth canonicall Scriptures, not only those bookes that ought of necessity to be receiued of al churches: but also such as were receiued of some, &amp; of some were not, in which nūber were these bookes of Tobie, Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, &amp; the Machabees, which by his owne rule, were not to be receiued as of absolut &amp; soueraigne authority, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Apostolike churches of Asia &amp; Europa, &amp; those of grauest authoritie, among which was the church of Rome in that time, did not receiue thē, as witnesseth not only S. Hierome a Priest of Rome, but also Ruffinus of <hi>Aquileia, in symbolo,</hi> who both declare what bookes were receiued in their churches as canonical, &amp; of irrefragable authority to build principles of faith vpon them, &amp; what books were admitted only to be read for instruction of maners. And therfore according to the rule of Augustin &amp; testimony of the anciēt fathers, &amp; because it cōsenteth
<pb n="17" facs="11"/>
with the rest of the scriptures, &amp; not for Caluins pleasure we receiue the Epistle of S. Iames, though it hath not bene alwaies, and of all Churches receiued. Concerning the name of Caluinists, as of all other nicke names, that it pleaseth you of your charity to bestow vpon vs, it shall suffice to protest once for all, that we acknowledge none other name of our profession, but Christians, &amp; Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes: and that we haue neither receiued that Epistle, nor reiected the other, bicause it pleased Caluin so. This may serue for a cleare demonstration, that in the first English Bibles that were printed vnder the name of Thomas<note place="margin">
               <hi>Anno.</hi> 1532. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1537.</note> Mathew, before Caluine wrote any word of the reiectiō of those bookes, or of receiuing of the other, they are called Apocrypha, &amp; printed with other of that marke, by thēselues, &amp; the Epistle of S. Iames without any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion acknowledged to be one of the canonical Epistles, wheras Caluines Institution was first printed An. 1536. &amp; his argument vpon S. Iames Epistle 1551. You may see what honest dealing the Papistes vse, to bring the truth into discredit, &amp; the professors thereof into hatred with the simple &amp; vnlearned people, bearing thē in hand, that we haue no cause to receiue or refuse bookes of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but Caluines pleasure. But the God of truth wil one day reward these impudēt liars &amp; shameles slaunderers.</p>
         <p>Well let vs now see vnder what pretēce, it pleased Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine to reiect these bookes. <hi>Vnder pretence forsooth</hi> (sayth Martin) <hi>that they were once doubted of, and not taken for Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical.</hi> I pray you sir, where doth Caluine pretend that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cause? In his <hi>Instit. li.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5 <hi>sect.</hi> 8. He alleageth diuerse other causes touching the bookes of <hi>Machabees,</hi> as euery mā that wil may read. Shame you nothing to forge such manifest vntruths, &amp; that in such matters as you may be conuinced in them by ten thousand witnesses? What cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit shal be giuen to you in matters that cōsist vpon your owne bare testimonie when you force not to faine of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, that wherin euery man may reproue you? And as for the only pretence you speake of, Caluine doth so
<pb n="18" facs="12"/>
litle esteeme it, that notwithstanding the same, he doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not to receiue the Epistle of S. Iames because it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable to the whole body of the canonical Scripture as if you had read his argumēt vpon that Epistle you might easily haue perceiued.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="9" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 9.</hi> Marke gētle reader for thy soules sake, &amp; thou<note place="margin">Ibid. pag. 17. M. VVhitaker by these vvords condemneth their ovvne Seruice booke, vvhich appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth these bookes of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticus, to be read for holy Scripture, as the other. Doe they read in their Churches Apocryphall &amp; superstitious bookes for holy Scripture, or is he a Puritane, that thus disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth their order of daily Seruice.</note> shalt find, that heresie &amp; only heresie is the cause of their deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing these books: so farre, that against the orders &amp; Hierarchies &amp; particular patronages of Angels, one of them writeth thus in the name of the rest. <hi>We passe not for that Raphael of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie neither do we acknowledge those seuē Angels which he speaketh of, al this is farre from Canonical Scriptures, that the same Raphael recordeth, &amp; sauoureth I wote not what superstition.</hi> Against free will thus: <hi>I litle care for the place of Ecclesiasticus, neither will I beleeue free will, though he affirme an hundred times, That before men is life &amp; death.</hi> And against praier for the dead, &amp; intercession of Saincts thus: <hi>As for the booke of the Machabees, I do care lesse for it thā for the other. Iudas dreame cōcerning Omas I let passe as a dreame.</hi> This is their reuerence of the scriptures which haue uniuersally bin reuerenced for canonical in the church of God aboue 1100 yeres. Con. Cart. 3. &amp; parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly of many fathers long before. Aug. de doct. Christ. l 2. c. 8.</p>
      <div n="9" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 9. The mouth that lieth killeth the soule. The reader may thinke you haue small care of his soules health, when by such impudēt lying you declare that you haue so smal regard of your own. But what shal he mark? <hi>That heresy, &amp;c.</hi> You were best say that Eusebius, Hierom, Ruffine &amp; al the churches in their times were heretiks, &amp; that only heresie was the cause of their deniall of these bookes. For such reasons as moued thē moue vs, &amp; some thing also their authority. But how proue you that only heresie moueth vs to reiect thē? Because M. Whit. against the orders, &amp; Hierarchies, &amp; particular patronages of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels writeth in the name of the rest. That <hi>we passe not, &amp;c.</hi> Take heede least vpon your bare surmise you belie him where you say he writeth in the name of the reste, as in the next sectiō following you say, he writeth in the name
<pb n="19" facs="12"/>
of both the vniuersities, for which I am sure he had no cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missiō frō either of thē, althogh he did write that which may well be aduouched by both the vniuersities, yet I knowe his modestie is such, as he will not presume to be aduocate for both the vniuersities, and much lesse for the whole church, except he were lawfully called therto. This is a cōmon practise of you Papists, to beare the world in hand that whatsoeuer is writtē by any of vs in defense of the truth is set forth in the name of al the rest, as though none of vs could say more in any matter, than any one of vs hath writtē, or that if any one of vs chaūce to slip in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny smal matter, though it be but a wrong quotatiō▪ you might open your wide sclaunderous mouths against the whole church for one mans particular offense. Now tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching any thing that M. Whit. hath written, you shal find him sufficient to maintaine it against a strōger aduersary thā you are, &amp; therfore I wil medle the lesse in his causes. And for the orders &amp; patronage or protection of Angels by Gods appointment, we haue sufficient testimonie in the Canonical Scriptures, that we neede not the vncertain report of Tobies booke to instruct vs what to thinke of thē. But as for the Hierarchies, &amp; patronage of Angels, that many of you Papistes haue imagined &amp; written of, neither the canonical Scriptures, nor yet the Apocryphal bookes now in controuersie, are sufficient to giue you warrātise. The like I say of freewil, praier for the dead, &amp; intercession of Saincts. But it grieueth you that those A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryphal scriptures, which haue bin vniuersally receiued for canonicall in the church of God aboue 1100. yeares should find no more reuerēce amōg vs. Stil your mouth rūneth ouer. For in the time of the Canon of the coūcel of Carthage. 3. which you quote, these bookes were not vniuersally reuerenced as canonical. And Augustine him selfe speaking of the booke of Machabees, <q>
               <hi>Cont.</hi> 2. <hi>G and. Ep. c.</hi> 23. cōfesseth that the Iewes accoūt it not as the law, &amp; the Prophetes, &amp; the Psalmes, to which our Lord gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth testimonie as to his witnesses, saying. It behoueth
<pb n="20" facs="13"/>
that all things should be fulfilled which are writtē in the Law, &amp; in the Prophets, &amp; in the Psalmes cōcerning me: but it is receiued of the Church, not vnprofitably, if it be soberly read or heard.</q> This writeth S. Augustine, whē he was pressed with the authority of that booke by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natists, which defended that it was lawful for them to kil themselues, by exāple of Razis, who is by the author of that booke commēded for that fact. <q>He saith it is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not vnprofitably, &amp; immediatly after. Especially for those Machabees that suffred paciently horrible persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for testimony of Gods religiō, to encourage Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians by their example.</q> Finally, he addeth a condition of the receiuing it, if it be soberly read or heard. These spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches declare, that it was not receiued without all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie, as the authenticall word of God: for then should it be receiued necessarily, &amp; because it is Gods word e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially, &amp; how soeuer it be read or heard it is receiued of the Church, not only necessarily, but also profitably. Beside this, euen the decree of Gelasius, which was neare 100. yeares after that councel of Carthage, alloweth but one booke of the Maccabees. Wherfore the vniuersal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence that is bosted of, can not be iustified.</p>
         <p>But M. Whitaker is charged in the margent, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the seruice booke, which appointeth these books of Toby &amp; Ecclesiasticus to be read for holy Scripture, as the other. And where finde you that in the seruice booke M. Martin? Can you speake nothing but vntruths? If they be appointed to be read, are they appointed to be read for holy Scripture, and for suche Scripture as the other canonicall bookes are? The seruice booke appointeth the Letanie, diuerse exhortations and praiers, yea home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to be read: are they therefore to be read for holy &amp; canonicall Scriptures? But you aske. <hi>Do they read in their Churches Apocryphall and Superstitious bookes for holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi> No verily. But of the name Apocryphall I must distinguish, which somtimes is taken for all bookes read of the Church, which are not canonicall: sometime for
<pb n="21" facs="13"/>
such bookes onely, as are by no meanes to be suffered, but are to be hid or abolished. These bookes therefore in controuersie, with other of the same sort, are some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times called <hi>Hagiographa,</hi> holy writings, as of <hi>S. Hierom praefat. in lib. Tobiae:</hi> sometime <hi>Ecclesiastica,</hi> Ecclesiastical writings, and so are they called of Ruffinus. Because<note place="margin">In expositione Symbol<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</note> (sayth he) they were appointed by our Elders to be read in the Churches, but not to be brought forth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme authoritie of faith: but other Scriptures they na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Apocryphall, which they would not haue to be read in the Churches. So sayth <hi>S. Hierom in praefat. in Prouerb.</hi>
            <q>Euen as the Church readeth in deede the bookes of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith, Tobias,</hi> and the Machabees: but yet receaueth them not among the Canonical Scriptures: so let it read these two bookes (of Ecclesiasticus and wisedom) for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the people, not for the confirmation of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Ecclesiastical doctrines.</q> These auncient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters shal answer for our seruice booke, that although it appoint these writings to be read: yet it doth not appoint them to be read for Canonicall Scriptures. Albeit they are but sparingly read, by order of our seruice booke, which for the Lordes day, &amp; other festiuall daies, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly appointeth the first lesson out of the Canonicall Scriptures. And as for superstition, although M. Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker say, that some one thing sauoreth of I know not what superstition, he doth not by and by condemne the whole booke for superstitious, and altogither vnworthy to be read, neither can he thereby be proued a Puritane, or a disgracer of the order of dayly seruice.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="10" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 10.</hi> As for partes of bookes, doe they not reiect certaine peeces of Daniel and of Hester, because they are not in the Hebrew, which reason S. Augustine reiecteth: or because they were once doubted of by certaine of the fathers? by which reason some part of S. Marke and S. Lukes Gospell might nowe also be called in controuersie, specially if it be true which M. Whitakers by a figuratiue speech more than insinuateth, <hi>That<note place="margin">pag. 10.</note> he can not see by what right that which once was not in
<pb n="22" facs="14"/>
credit, should by time winne authoritie.</hi> Forgetting him selfe by &amp; by, &amp; in the very next lines admitting S. Iames epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle (though before doubted of for Canonicall Scriptures, vnles<note place="margin">M. VVhitakers booke.</note> they receiue it but of their curtesie, &amp; so may refuse it when it shall please them, which must needes be gathered of his wordes, as also many other notorious absurdities, contradictions, and dumbe blanckes▪ Which onely to note, were to confute M. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers by him selfe, being the answerer for both Vniuersities.</p>
      <div n="10" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 10. As for peeces of Daniel, &amp; of Hester, we reiect none, but only we discerne that which was written by Daniel in deede, from that which is added by Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotion the false Iew, &amp; that which was written by the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God of Esther, from that which is vainly added by some Greekish counterfecter. But the reason why we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect those patches (you say) is because they are not in the Hebrew, which reason <hi>S. Augustine</hi> reiecteth. Here you cite <hi>S. Augustine</hi> at large, without quotation, in a matter of controuersie. But if we may trust you that <hi>S. Augustine</hi> reiecteth this reason yet we may be bold vpon <hi>S. Hieroms</hi> authoritie, to reiect whatsoeuer is not found in the canō of the Iewes, written in Hebrew, or Chaldee. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer was such, <hi>S. Hierom</hi> did thrust through with a spit or obeliske, as not worthy to be receyued. Witnes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>S. Augustine</hi> him selfe, <hi>Epist. ad Hier.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. in which he disswaded him from translating the Scriptures of the olde Testament out of the Hebrew tongue, after the 70. Interpreters, whose reasons as they were but friuolous, so they are derided by <hi>S. Hierom,</hi> who being learned in the Hebrew &amp; Chaldee tongues, refused to be taught by <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi> that was ignorant in them, what was to be done in translations out of them. Also <hi>Hieronym</hi> him selfe testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth that <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Hebrew, hath neither the story of <hi>Susanna,</hi> nor the hymne of the 3. children, nor the fable of Bel &amp; the Dragon: which we (saith he) because they are dispersed throughout the whole world haue added, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a spit before them, which thrusteth them through, lest we should seeme among the ignorant to haue cut of a great part of the booke. The like he writeth of the
<pb n="23" facs="14"/>
vaine additions that were in the vulgar edition vnto the booke of Esther, both in the Preface, &amp; after the ende of that which he translated out of the Hebrew. There are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reasons also beside the authoritie of <hi>S. Hierom,</hi> that moue vs not to receiue them. As that in the storie of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanna,</hi> Magistrats &amp; iudgement of life &amp; death are attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Iewes being in captiuitie of <hi>Babylon,</hi> which hath no similitude of truth. Beside out of the first chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the true <hi>Daniel,</hi> it is manifest, that <hi>Daniel</hi> being a young man was caried captiue into <hi>Babylon,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Nebucadnezer,</hi> but in this counterfect storie, <hi>Daniel</hi> is made a young child in the time of <hi>Astyages,</hi> which reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned immediatly before <hi>Cyrus</hi> of <hi>Persia.</hi> Likewise in the storie of Bel and the Dragon, <hi>Daniel</hi> is said to haue liued with the same king <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and after when he was cast into the lyons denne, the Prophet <hi>Habacuck</hi> was sent to him out of <hi>Iurie,</hi> who prophecied before the first comming of the Chaldees, and therefore could not be aliue in the daies of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> which was more than 70 yeares after. The additions vnto the booke of <hi>Esther</hi> in many places, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray the spirite of man, as that they are contrary to the truth of the story, containing vaine repetitions, &amp; ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of that which is contained in the true historie, &amp; that which most manifestly conuinceth the sorgerie, that in the epistle of <hi>Artaxerxes, cap.</hi> 16. <hi>Haman</hi> is called a Macedonian, which in the true storie is termed an Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gite that is an Amalekite, whereas the Macedonians had nothing to doe with the Persians many yeares after the death of <hi>Esther &amp; Haman.</hi> I omit that in the <hi>ca.</hi> 15. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. the author maketh <hi>Esther</hi> to lie vnto the king in saying that his countenance was ful of all grace, or else he lyeth him selfe, <hi>v.</hi> 17. where he saith, the king beheld her in the vehemēcy of his anger, &amp; that he was exceding terrible.</p>
         <p>As for other reasons, which you suppose vs to follow, because these parcels were once doubted of by certaine of the fathers, it is a reason of your owne making, and therefore you may confute it at your pleasure. <hi>But if that be true which Maister Whitaker by a figuratiue speech doth</hi>
            <pb n="24" facs="15"/>
            <hi>more than insinuate, parte of S. Markes and S. Lukes Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell, may also be called in controuersie.</hi> Why? what saith M. VVhitaker? Marie, <hi>that he can not see by what right that which once was not in credit, should by tyme winne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</hi> But when I pray you was any part of S. Marke or S. Luke out of credit? if any part were of some person doubted of, doth it follow that it was not at al in credit? you reason profoundly, and gather very necessarily. As likewise <hi>that he forgetteth him selfe in the very next lines, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting S. Iames epistle (though before doubted of) for Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall.</hi> VVill ye say that S. Iames epistle was once not in credit, or not worthy of credit, (for that is his plaine meaning) because it was doubted of, yea reiected of some? yea, you saye it must needes be gathered of his wordes, that we receiue it but of curtesie, and so may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse it when it pleaseah vs. Demonstrate this in a syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gisme out of his words if you can, or all the whole rable of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> if you be able. For my part I can but maruaile at your bold assertions, and abhorre your impudent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcements. As for other contradictions, notorious ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdities, dumbe blanks, &amp; I know not what other mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters you feine vnto him, without all proofe or perticular declaration, all wise men see howe easie a matter it is to raile &amp; slaunder in generals, &amp; whē you dare come to particulars, I doubt not but the world shal see your va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie so detected by M. Whitaker him selfe, that you shal haue litle ioy thus insolently to deface his godly &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned writings. It had bene more than time that his booke had bene confuted, which hath bene abroad a yeare and a halfe almost, if you can with such facilitie by onely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting such matters, shewe that he confuteth him selfe. But somwhat you must say afarre of, to saue your credit with your Disciples, to keepe them playe for the time, while with long studie, and great trauaile, you are crowding out great trifles.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="11" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 11.</hi> For the second point, which is not the grosse de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of bookes, but yet calling of them in question, mouing
<pb n="25" facs="15"/>
scruples about them, and diminishing their authoritie and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, I will goe no further than to S. Paules epistle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,<note place="margin">In the argument Bib. an. 1579.</note> which I will not aske why they doubt of, or rather thinke it not to be S. Paules, for they will tell me, because it was once in doubte (not considering that it was in like maner doubted whether it were Canonicall, &amp; yet they will not now denie but it is Canonicall) but I must aske them and request them to make a reasonable answere, why in their English Bible of the yeare 1579. and 1580. they presume to leaue out S. Paules name out of the very title of the saide epistle, which name is in the<note n="*" place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> Greeke, and in Bezaes Latine translation, both which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse to folow. See the title of the new Test. an. 1580. Doth not the title tell them that it is S. Paules? why seeke they further: or why do they change the title, striking out S. Paules name, if they meant to deale simply and sincerely? and what an hereticall pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uishnes is this, because Beza telleth them of one obscure Greeke copie that hath not Paules name, and onely one: that they will rather folow it, than all other copies both Greeke and Latin? I report me to all indifferent men of common sense, whether they do it not to diminish the credite of the epistle.</p>
      <div n="11" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 11. Nowe concerning the seconde pointe, which is calling of some bookes into controuersie or mouing scruples about them, to diminish their credite, or auctoritie, whether you be guiltie of that crime ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than we, I haue somewhat noted before. But with what euidence you are able to charge vs, it cōmeth now to be cōsidered: you will go no further than the epistle to the Hebrewes. You may be ashamed to haue gone so far. For of al bookes of the new Testament, their is none that we might worse spare to confounde your blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous heresies, than that epistle, which is the very mall to beate into pouder the abominable Idoll of your Masse, and your sacrilegious priesthood seruing to the same. Wherefore it is without all colour that you charge vs, to seeke to diminish the credite of that epistle. But you will not aske why we doubt of, or rather thinke it not to be S. Paules, because we will tell you, that it was once
<pb n="26" facs="16"/>
in doubt. If you acknowledge that the auctor of this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle was once in questiō, you cleare vs of mouing scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples about it, or calling it in question, which was your first charge. Let Eusebius, Hierome, and other auncient<note place="margin">
               <hi>Euseb. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Hieronim. ad▪ <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. Tom.</hi> 3.</note> writers, beare that blame, if it be blame worthie, to tell what other mens opinions haue bene in such a matter. Some holding that it was written by S. Luke, some by S. Barnabas, some by S. Clemens. But you must wit if you wil, that they which at this day doubt of the writer ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or else thinke it not of S. Paules penning, haue other reasons to lead them, than onely because it was doubted of. For beside those reasons which they had, which of old time doubted of the writer therof, as the diuersitie of the stile, and inscription thereof, and manner of reasoning, they haue also obserued something out of the epistle it self, which seemeth to argue, that it was not writtē by S. Paule: as that in the beginning of the 2. chapter he saith, <hi>The doctrine of saluation was confirmed to vs by thē that heard it, after it was first spoken by the Lord him self,</hi> which seemeth to agree with the profession of S. Luke in the beginning of his gospell. Wheras S. Paule denieth <hi>that he learned his gospel os men, but only by reuelation of Iesus Christ. Gal.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 12. But of all thē that doubt, or thinke it not to be S. Paules epistle, there is not one that doubteth of the auctoritie thereof, but that it is equall with the epistle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, or the gospell of S. Iohn. Although in the Latine<note place="margin">
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>in Euāg Math. <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 26.</note> church as S. Hierom testifieth, it hath bene doubted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were Canonicall. The cause seemeth to be the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie of the Nouatians, which abused a text out of the 6. chapt. against remissiō of sinnes cōmitted after grace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, which we shew was no sufficiēt cause to refuse so diuine an epistle, seing the Apostle speaketh not of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular faults, which are cōmon to the faithful oftētimes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day, but of an vtter apostasie, &amp; falling cleane away frō the truth of the gospel once knowen &amp; professed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an horrible contempt &amp; persecuting of the same. But <hi>we must make you a reasonable answere, why in the English Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi>
            <pb n="27" facs="16"/>
            <hi>printed</hi> 1579. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1580. <hi>we presume to leaue out S. Paules name, out of the very title of the said epistle? which name is in the Greeke &amp; Bezaes Latine translatiō, which we professe to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</hi> I answere without any presumptiō, that that which is vncertaine we spare to affirme. Exāple we haue not only that ancient Greeke copie whereof Beza speaketh, which leaueth out the name of Paulé, but also diuerse printed bokes in which that name is left out. Beside it is certain, that title was not of ancient time vniuersally added. For S. Hier. <hi>in Catalogo scriptorū ecclesiast.</hi> after he hath recited al the epistles of S. Paule, at lēgth he cōmeth to this epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, <hi>Epistola autē quae fertur ad Hebraeos, &amp;c.</hi> But the epistle which is called vnto the Hebrewes, is not thought to be his, for the differēce of the stile &amp; speach, but either writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tē by Barnabas, as Tertullian holdeth, or by Luke the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelist, as some men thinke, or by Clemens, that after was B. of the Romane church, whom they say to haue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered &amp; adorned the sentēces of Paul in his own speach, or els truly, bicause Paule did write vnto the Hebrews, &amp; because of the enuie of his name amōg thē he cut of the title in the beginning of the salutation. These things cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, what neede those tragical exclamations in so tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling a matter? <hi>Doth not the title tell it is S. Paules? why strike they out S. Paules name? what an hereticall peeuishnesse is this?</hi> For lacke of good matter, you are driuen to lowde cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors against vs, but I will euen conclude in your owne wordes, I reporte me to all indifferent men of common sense, whether we do it to deminish the credite of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle, which of al S. Paules epistles we might least misse, when we come to dispute against your Popish sacrifice, &amp; sacrificing priesthood: or whether you do not craftily moue a scruple in the mindes of simple persons, to make thē doubt of the auctoritie of that epistle (whose double cannon shot you are not able to beare, whē it is thūdred out against you) vnder colour that it is not of sound cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit among our selues, that vse it against you. Which of al the lies that euer Satan inuented, &amp; taught you to vtter, is one of the most abhominable.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="12" type="Martins_comments">
      <pb n="28" facs="17"/>
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 12.</hi> I know very well that the authoritie of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall Scripture standeth not vpon the certaintie of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, but yet to be Paules or not Paules, Apostolicall or not A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicall, maketh great difference of credite and estimation. For what made S. Iames epistle doubted of sometime, or the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of S. Peter, and the rest, but that they were not thought to be the epistles of those Apostles? This Luther sawe very well, when he denied S. Iames epistle to be Iames the Apostles wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. If titles of bookes be of no importāce, then leaue out Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Marke, Luke, and Iohn, leaue out Paule in his other epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles also, and you shall much pleasure the Manichees and other old Heretikes: &amp; if the titles make no difference, vrge no more the title of the Apocalypse, <hi>S. Iohn the Diuines,</hi> as though it were not S. Iohns the Euangelistes, and you shall much displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure some Heretikes now a daies. Briefly, most certaine it is, and they know it best by their owne vsual doings, that it is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall way to the discredite of any booke, to denie it to be that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, vnder whose name it hath bene receiued.</p>
      <div n="12" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 12. If you know so well that the auctoritie of the Canonical scripture, standeth not vpō the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the auctor: as in deede it doth not. For the bookes of Iudges, of Ruth, of Samuel the later▪ of the Kings, &amp;c. who can certainly affirme by whom they were written? with what forehead do you charge vs to doubte of the auctoritie of this epistle, because we reporte out of the auncient writers, the vncertaintie of the auctor? or leaue out that title whiche is not certainely true? <hi>But yet</hi> (you say) <hi>to be Paules or not Paules, apostolicall or not apostolicall, maketh great difference of credite and esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi> If by apostolicall you meane of apostolicall spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite or auctoritie, I agree to that you say of apostolical, or not apostolicall. If you meane apostolicall that only which was writtē by some Apostle, you will make great difference of credite &amp; estimatiō betweene the Gospell of Marke, Luke, and the Actes of the Apostles, from the gospels of Mathew and Iohn. But which of vs I pray you that thinketh that this epistle was not writtē by S. Paul,
<pb n="29" facs="17"/>
once doubteth whether it be not of Apostolicall spirite and auctoritie? Which is manifest by this, that both in preaching and writing wee cite it thus, <hi>the Apostle to the Hebrewes.</hi> And if it were written by S. Luke, or by S. Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which both were Apostolike men, seing it is out of controuersie that it was written by the spirite of God, it is doubtlesse Apostolicall and differeth not in credite and estimation from those writings that are knowen cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to haue bene writtē by the Apostles. But I maruel greatly why you write, that to be Paules or not Paules, maketh great difference of credite &amp; estimation. Those epistles that are Peters and Iohns are not Paules, &amp; yet I thinke their is no great difference of credite &amp; estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betweene them &amp; Paules. What you thinke I know not, but you write very suspitiously. You aske what made S. Iames epistle, or the second of Peter and the rest, to be sometimes doubted of, but that they were not thought to be the epistles of those Apostles? Yes, something else, or else they doubted vainely of them, and without iuste cause, as I thinke they did. But when their were two A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles called Iames, he that doubteth whether the epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle was written by Iames the brother of Iohn, &amp; is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suaded it was written rather by Iames the sonne of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaeus,</hi> doubteth nothing of the credit, auctoritie, &amp; esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the epistle. No more doe wee, which doubt whether the epistle to the Hebrewes were written by S. Paule, seeing we are perswaded it was written either by S. Barnabas, or by S. Luke, or by S. Clement, as the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient writers thought, or by some other of the Apostles or Euangelists, we make no question but that it is Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicall, and of equall auctoritie with the rest of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly scriptures. But Eusebius denied the epistle of S. Iames, because he was perswaded that it was written by no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle or Apostolike man, and therefore saith plainly that it is a bastard or counterset: and so belike was Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deceiued▪ if euer he denied it, as you say he did. <hi>But if titles of bookes be of no importance</hi> (say you) <hi>then leaue out</hi>
            <pb n="30" facs="18"/>
            <hi>Matthew, Marke, Iohn, and Paule in his other Epistles.</hi> What nede that I pray you? Is there no difference betwene lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing out a title whereof there hath bene great vncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and diuersitie in Gods church, and which in some Greeke copies both written and printed is left out: and in leauing out those titles that neuer were omitted, nor neuer any question, or controuersie moued of them by any of the auncient catholike fathers? But you will vs to vrge no more the title of the Apocalypse of S. Iohn the Diuine, as though it were not S. Iohn the Euangelistes, &amp; we shall please I know not what heretikes of our time except it be the Papistes whom it would most concerne, that the reuelation of S. Iohn in which their Antichrist of Rome is so plainly described were brought out of credit. But if you had read Bezaes preface before the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalypse, you should finde that euen by that title, he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth a probable argument, that it was written by Iohn the Euangelist, because it is not like that this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent name THE DIVINE coulde agree to any Iohn in the Apostles time so aptly, as to Sainct Iohn the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelist, beside the consent of al antiquitie, ascribing that Reuelation to Sainct Iohn the Euangelist and Apostle. <hi>Last of all</hi> (you say) <hi>it is most certaine and we knowe best by our vsuall doings, that it is a principall way to discredit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny booke, to deny it to be the authors vnder whose name it hath bene receyued.</hi> Howe certaine it is with you, whereof no man else but you can see any light of reason or necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of conclusion, I knowe not, but wee are not so voyde of witte, if we lacked honestie, that we would discredite Paules Epistle, by saying it was Peters, or Augustines sermon, by saying it was Ambrose, or Chrysostomes worke by saying it was Basils. But if wee would bring any booke out of credite by denying the auctor whose title it hath borne: wee would rather intitle it to some other writer of lesse credite, or later tyme, or by some other argumentes proue it vnworthie of credite, not by onely denying it to be the auctors, vnder whose name
<pb n="31" facs="18"/>
it hath hene receyued.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="13" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 13.</hi> But I come to the thirde point of volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie expositions of the Scripture, that is when euery man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth according to his errour and Heresie. This needeth no proofe, for we see it with our eyes. Looke vpon the Caluinistes and Puritanes at home, the Lutherans, Zuinglians, and Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists abrode: reade their bookes written vehemently, one secte against an other: are not their expositions of one and the same Scripture as diuerse and contrarie, as their opinions differ one from an other? Let the example at home be, their controuersie about the distinction of Ecclesiasticall degrees, Arch-bishop, Bishop, and minister: the example abroade, their diuerse ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations and phantasies▪ vpon these most sacred wordes, <hi>Hoc est corpus meum.</hi>
      </p>
      <div n="13" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 13. That euery one of vs expoūdeth the scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture voluntarily according to his errour or heresie, you say it needeth no proofe, for you see it with your eyes. You haue very cleere sight to see a mote in other mens eies, but can not see a beame in your owne. You make your demonstration by the Caluinists and Puritans at home, &amp; the Lutherans, Zuinglians, &amp; Caluinists abroad▪ the one for the distinctiō of Ecclesiastical degrees, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop, Bishop, &amp; Minister: the other for their diuerse i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations &amp; phantasies of these wordes▪ <hi>Hoc est corpus meum.</hi> But I beseech you sir, touching the domestical dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentiō, what is the text, or what be the texts of Scripture? vpon which these voluntarie expositions▪ are made▪ for the distinction or confusion of Ecclesiastical degrees? If they had bene as ready as <hi>Hoc est corpus meum,</hi> they should haue bene set downe, as well as that. But I suppose they are yet to seeke for that controuersie, as I take it standeth rather in collections than interpretations, and in questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whether the political gouernment of the Church be distinctly expressed in the scripture, or no. As for the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention abroad, I confesse to stand a great part in exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that text, wherin although the one part doth erre, is that a sufficient cause to condēne thē both. The church
<pb n="32" facs="19"/>
of Africa, and the Church of Rome, and the two princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall lights of them both Cyprian and Cornelius, dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about rebaptizing them that were baptized of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes. The Aphricans not in one text onely, but in the<note place="margin">Cyprianus, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Concilio A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phricano.</note> exposition of many, differed from the Romanes, &amp; from the truth, yet it were hard to condemne them both for Heretikes, &amp; least of all them that held the truth. S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine and S. Hierom dissented about a text of S. Paule to the Galathians, of Peters dissembling, as their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary epistles doe testifie. The truth was of S. Augustines side, yet was not the other an heretike, following a wrōg interpretation. And to come nearer home vnto you, the Dominicans &amp; Franciscans Friers were at daggers draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as we say) yea at most sharpe and bitter contention betwene themselues, and all the Popish Church was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided about their brawling, concerning the conception of the virgin Marie, whether she were conceaued in sinne, or no, where many texts of Scripture must needes receiue voluntarie expositions, if not of both partes, yet at the least of one parte: which of those will you say were heretikes? If you say neither of both, then must you haue stronger reasons to proue vs all heretikes, than voluntarie expositions, where parties be in diuerse opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, especially in matter not ouerthrowing the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Christian religion. And when you haue gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the most voluntarie expositions you can finde, yet shall you finde none so grosse, so absurde, so imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, as you Papistes haue coyned, for maintenaunce of your errours and heresies, of which you your selfe are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed, though otherwise you haue iron foreheads and brasen faces. A few examples among a great many shall suffice. God made man according to his owne image, that is to say, we must haue images in the Church. No man lighteth a candell and putteth it vnder a bushell, the meaning is, that images must be set vpon the altar. God made two great lightes, the Sunne and the Moone, that is, the Pope to be aboue the Emperour. Beholde here
<pb n="33" facs="19"/>
are two swordes: that is, the Pope hath power of both the swordes. Put on the whole armour of God, that is, the Priest must put on all his vestiments, before he saye Masse. I am become as sownding brasse, or as a tinckling Cymbal, that is, the bels in the steeple signifie preaching of Gods word. I might fill many leaues, yea a whole booke of such popish expositions, as the Papistes in our dayes dare not for shame abide by.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="14" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 14.</hi> And if you will yet haue a further demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration, this one may suffice for all. They reiect Councels, &amp; Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the Catholike Churches interpretation, vnlesse it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Gods word, and whether it be agreeable or no, that Luther shall iudge for the Lutherans, Caluin for the Caluinists, Cartwright for the Puritans, and an other for the Brethren of loue: briefly them selues will be iudges both of Councels and<note n="*" place="margin">Whitak. pag. 17. &amp; 120.</note> Fathers, whether they expound the Scriptures well or no, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery youth among them vpon confidence of his spirit and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge wil saucily controule not onely one, but all the fathers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting togither, if it be against that which they imagine to be the truth.</p>
      <div n="14" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 14. We had neede of a better demonstrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than the former, by which you your selues are proued Heretikes, rather than we. But let vs see how handsomly you begin. <hi>They reiect</hi> (say you) <hi>Councels and Fathers, and the Catholike Churches interpretation, vnlesse it be agreeable to Gods word.</hi> Thus farre you say wel. We doe reiect not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly those that you name, but euen an Angel from heauen, except his message be agreeable to Gods word. But all the rest that you assume to the ende of this section, is a starke staring lye, except that you saye of H. N. for the brethren of loue, which are more like to you than to vs. For neither Luther, nor Caluin, nor Cartwright is iudge among vs, whether any thing be agreeable to the worde of God, but whatsoeuer any of them doe saye, it is exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and tryed by the Scriptures. And the Scriptures them selues, where they are so obscure, that neither by cōmon sense, knowledge of the original tongue, Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
<pb n="34" facs="20"/>
Rhetorike, Logike, storye, nor any other humane knowledge, nor iudgement of any writers, olde, or new, the certaine vnderstanding can be found out, they are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expounded by conference of other plainer textes of Scripture, according to the analogie of faith: or els they remaine stil in obscuritie, vntill it shall please God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile a more cleere knowledge of thē. But none so like the familie of loue as you Papists are, which reiect coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, fathers interpretation of the most auncient Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, yea &amp; manifest Scripture it self, except it be agreable to the iudgement of your P. M. <hi>Pontifex Max.</hi> the Pope, as those familiar diuels, submit all things to the sentence, &amp; authoritie of their H. N. Shame you nothing therefore to quote Whitaker <hi>pag.</hi> 17. &amp; 120. as though he affirmed, that we our selues will be iudges, both of Councels, &amp; Fathers, whether they expound the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures well or no? because he writeth (percase) that we ought to examine al mens writings by the word of god. Doth the Apostle make euery man iudge of all thinges, when he willeth euery man to examine all things▪ and to hold that which is good? If any youth vpon confidence of his wit, or knowledge, presume too much in diuine matters, we count it rashnesse. But that any youth among vs, vpon confidence of his spirit, will saucily controwle all the fathers cōsenting togither against his fantasie, except it be some Schismatike or Heretike, that is cast out from amongest vs, I doe vtterly denye, neither are you able to proue it of any that is allowed among vs.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="15" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 15.</hi> Wherevpon it riseth that one of them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth this as very wel said of Luther, <hi>That he esteemed not<note place="margin">Ibid. pag. 101.</note> the worth of a rushe a thousande Augustines, Cyprians, Churches, against him selfe.</hi> And an other very finely &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiuely, (as he thought) against the holy Doctor &amp; Martyr S. Cyprian, affirming <hi>that the Church of Rome can not erre<note place="margin">Praef. ad 6. theses Oxon pag. 25.</note> in faith,</hi> saith thus: <hi>Pardon me Cyprian, I woulde gladly beleue thee▪ but that beleeuing thee, I should not beleeue the Gospell.</hi> This is that which S. Augustine saith of the like
<pb n="35" facs="20"/>
men, <hi>dulcissimè vanos esse, non peritos, sed perituros, nec<note place="margin">Lib. Confess. 1. cap. 14. lib. 7. c. 20.</note> tam disertos in errore, quàm desertos à veritate.</hi> And I thinke verily, that not onely we, but the wiser men among them selues, smile at such eloquence, or pitie it, saying this, or the like most truly, <hi>Prodierunt oratores noui, stulti adolescentuli.</hi>
         <note place="margin">Cicer. de Senect.</note>
      </p>
      <div n="15" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 15. Why shoulde you not at your pleasure vpon your false assumption generall, inferre one or two slaunders particular. M. Whitaker defendeth that it was well said of Luther. <hi>That he esteemed not the worth of a rush a thousand Augustines, Cyprians, Churches, against himselfe.</hi> Woulde God that euery Papist would reade his owne words in the place by you quoted, that he might see your impudent forgerie. For I hope there is no Christian, that will imagine, that either Luther would so speake, or any man of honestie, defend him so speaking. For Luther was not so senselesse, to oppose his owne person, but the truth of his cause, grounded vpon the holy Scriptures, not only against one thousand of men, holding the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, but euen against tenne thousand of Angels, if they should oppose them selues against the truth of God. But I am too blame to deale so much in M. Whitakers cause, who ere it be long, will displaye the falshoode of Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie Martin, in a Latine writing, to his great ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</p>
         <p>The next cauil is vpon M. Rainoldes words, in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to his sixe positions, disputed vpon at Oxford, where against Cyprian, affirming that the Church of Rome can not erre in faith, he sayth: <q>Pardon me Cyprian, I would gladly beleeue thee, but that in beleeuing thee, I shoulde not beleeue the Gospel.</q> These wordes you confesse that he spake figuratiuely, and finely, as he thought: but that he vsed the figures of Ironve and concession, you will not acknowledge, but all other men may easily see. For first he no where graunteth, that S. Cyprian affirmeth, that the Churche of Rome can not erie in fayth. But immediatly before the wordes by you translated, after he had proued out of the eleuēth to the Romans, that
<pb n="36" facs="21"/>
the particular Church of Rome may be cut of, as well as the Church of the Israelites, which were the naturall braunches, he asketh the question <hi>Quid? &amp; Cypriano se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus est visum?</hi> What? And did it seeme otherwise to <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian?</hi> Pardon me <hi>Cyprian, &amp;c.</hi> His meaning is plaine, that Cyprian thought not otherwise than S. Paule hath written, or if he did, it was lawfull to dissent from Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian. As a litle after he sayth: <hi>Quare si Romanam Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am errare non posse, &amp;c.</hi> Wherefore if Cyprian thought that the Church of Rome could not erre in that point, by the sentence of the Papistes, he him selfe is to be condemned of errour: for diuerse Papistes whome he nameth, confesse that euery particular Church may erre, and Verratus, one of them, affirmeth that the Church of Rome is a particular Church, which the rest can not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. And in deede that which Cyprian writeth, is about certaine runneagate Heretikes, that flying out of the Church of Carthage, sought to be receiued of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church of Rome. All this while here is no graunt that Cyprian affirmeth, that the Church of Rome cannot erre in faith. And if Cyprian had so affirmed contrary to the scripture, it might haue bene iustly replied vnto him, which S. Augustine saith when he was pressed with his authoritie. <hi>Contra Crescon. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 31. <hi>Nos nullam Cypriano facimus iniuriam.</hi> We do <hi>Cyprian</hi> no wrong, when we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish any writings of his from the Canonical autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the diuine Scriptures. And in truth the wordes which <hi>M. Rainolds</hi> before cited out of <hi>S. Cyprian, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ep</hi> 3. <hi>ad Cornel.</hi> are spoken of no matter of faith, but in a matter of discipline. Neither doth Cyprian say, that the Church of Rome can not erre in faith, but that those Heretikes which brought letters from schismatikes &amp; profane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, did not consider, that they are Romans, whose faith is praised by the cōmendation, or preaching of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, to whom <hi>perfidia,</hi> falshood, or false dealing can haue none accesse. Meaning that the Romans so long as they cōtinue in that faith which was praised by the Apostle, cā
<pb n="37" facs="21"/>
not ioyne with Heretikes and Schismatikes, that are cast out of other Catholike Churches. For that he could not meane that the Pope or Church of Rome cannot erre in faith (as the Papistes affirme) it is manifest, for that in a question of religion▪ he dissented both from the Bishop and Church of Rome, as all learned men knowe he did, which he would neuer haue done, if he had beleeued they could not erre. <q>And that his meaning was not that the Bishop of Rome could not erre in matters of disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, it is manifest in the next epistle, where he complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that Basilides a wicked man, after his crimes were detected, and his cōscience made bare by his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, went to Rome, and deceyued our fellow Bishop Stephanus, dwelling farre of, and being ignorant of the case, so that he sought ambitiously to be vniustly resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the Bishoprike from whence he was iustly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed. These things proue, that S. Cyprian thought it no impossible thing, for the Bishops and Church of Rome to erre in faith or gouernment.</q> Wherefore that you cite out of Augustine agreeth best vnto your selfe, and such as you are, who imploy al your eloquence and vtterance, to set foorth lies and slaunders. Laste of all, when you haue nothing else to disgrace those graue and learned writers, you woulde make them by abusing a peece of Tullie, cōtemptible for their youth, among such as know them not, who if they wanted half a score yeares a peece, of that ripe and well seasoned age they haue, yet with those giftes of godlinesse and learning, which God hath in great measure bestowed vpon them, they were wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be reuerenced. So that Venemous traytor, which writeth of the persecution of the Papistes, maketh me a very yong man, and therefore contemned of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers at Wisbiche, and yet I can easily proue, that I was of lawfull age, if more than twise one and twentie yeares will serue, before euer I sawe Wisbiche castle.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="16" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 16.</hi> The 4. point is, of picking quarels to the very originall text: for alter and change it I hope they shall not
<pb n="38" facs="22"/>
be able in this watchfull world of most vigilant Catholikes. But what they would do, if all Bibles were only in their handes and at their commaundement, ghesse by this: that Beza against the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence<note place="margin">Beza the mouse of Geneua, gnavveth the text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> of all copies both Greeke and Latine, (In his Annot. vpon the newe Testam. set forth in the yeare 1556.) thinketh <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, is more than should be in the text Mat. 10: and <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Luc. 22. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Act. 7: the first, against Peters supremacie: the seconde, against the real presence of Christs bloud in the B. Sacrament: the third, against the making of what soeuer images, whether they be adored or no. Thus you see how the mouse of Geneua (as I told you before of Marcion the mouse of Pontus) knibbleth and gnaweth about it, though he can not bite it of altogither.</p>
      <div n="16" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 16. In this point you do nothing but picke quarrels, seeing you confesse that neither they haue, nor can alter, or chaunge any thing of the originall text. If Beza expresse his coniecture vpon some grounde or si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of reason, that <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> in Mathew 10. <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> Luc. 22. and <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> Act 7. might perhaps be added to the texte out of the margent or otherwise, and yet dothe not precisely affirme it, but leaue it to iudgement and triall of auncient copies, if any shall be found to fauour his coniecture, what hath he like to the mouse of Pōtus Marcion, which altered &amp; corrupted the text? you say he knibbleth &amp; gnaweth about it, though he can not bite it of altogither. And for what aduātage? forsooth, because the first worde maketh for Peters su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie, a poore supremacie that Peter can gaine in that he is named the first in the Cataloge of the Apostles, which is but a primacie of order, not of honour, or as Ambrose saith, a primacie of confession, not of honour,<note place="margin">
               <hi>De ineam. dom. cap.</hi> 4.</note> of faith, not of degree. The secōd word you say is against the real presence of Christes bloud in the B. Sacrament. You are a perilous catte that can spie a mouse gnawing at the real presence, which none of the auncient Fathers, or late writers before these dayes could finde in those wordes. And as for making of Images who doth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidde,
<pb n="39" facs="22"/>
except it be in any vse of religion, whiche God doth forbidde in the second commaundement of the first table. And where you will haue men to ghesse what we would do if all Bibles were only in our hands, by this example of Bezaes coniectures. I wishe men rather to consider what the Romish rattes were like to do in that case, which in their translation of the ten commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes for the peoples instruction, haue cleane gnawen out the second commaundement, and because they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bite it cleane out of the Bible, they seeke all shiftes to hide it vnder the first commaundement. Finally whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lindanus and you do picke quarrels against all the euidence of all Greeke copies, I referre me to your 4. section, where out of Lindanus you falsely affirme that certaine of Marcions corruptions remayne in the Greke text vntill this day.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="17" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 17.</hi> He doth the like in sundrie places which you may see in his Annotat. Act. 7. v. 16. Where he is saucie against al copies Greeke and Latin to pronounce corruption, corruption, auouching &amp; endeuouring to proue that it must be so, and that with these words, <hi>To what purpose should the holy Ghost, or Luke, adde this?</hi> Act. 8. v. 26. But because those places cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne no cōtrouersie, I say no more but that he biteth at the text, and would change it according to his imagination, if he might: which is too proud an enterprise for Beza, &amp; small reuerence of the holy scriptures, so to call the very text into controuersie, that whatsoeuer pleaseth not him, crepte out of the margent into the text, which is his common and almost his only coniecture.</p>
      <div n="17" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 17. Where Beza noteth corruption in places that concerne no controuersie, it appeareth that without parcialitie he desireth to restore the texte to sinceritie. And yet he is charged of you with pride and saucinesse. Why more I pray you, than Lindanus, of whom you lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to pratle so much of the mouse of Pontus? Which <hi>lib.</hi> 2 <hi>de optim. gen. interpret. scripturas,</hi> hath diuerse chapters of the defect of the Greeke text, of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundance, and of the corruption thereof. If Lindanus
<pb n="40" facs="23"/>
might doe this with modestie, and desire to finde out the truth (as I thinke he did) why may not an indifferent reader, iudge the like of Beza, in his doings? As for cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out of the margent into the texte, which you say is his common and almost onely coniecture, why may it not come to passe in writing out of the bookes of the Scripture, as it hath in other writings of other auctors. And that eyther by that meanes, or by some other meanes, corruption hath hapned to al copies that at this day are extant, both Greeke &amp; Latine, in naming Hiere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie for Zacharie, Math. 27, Who is so blinde that he wil not see? yet the ordinarie Glose cōfesseth, that there were diuerse copies in times past, in which the name of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie was not, but the worde Prophete generally. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in the vulgar Latine texte, in the beginning of S. Markes Gospell, Esay is cited for that which is written in Malachie▪ and some Greeke copies haue the same, frō whence it is like the Latine translation receaued that er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. But the more part of best Greeke copies, leaue out the name of Esay. Howe these corruptions should come into the text, except it be out of the margent, if you can finde a better coniecture, we shall be content with more patience to heare you, than you can abide to heare Beza.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="18" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 18.</hi> He biteth sore at the word <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Luc. 1. v. 7<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. and will not translate that, but the Hebrue word of the old<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> Testament, but at <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> (Act. 2. v. 24.) much more, and at <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> (Act. 7. v. 14.) exceedingly: but yet after he hath said all that he could against it, he concludeth, that <hi>he<note place="margin">No. Test. an. 1556. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Beza reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Greeke <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of the nevv Testamēt vvith the Hebrevve text of the old, by putting out of the Greeke text so much as pleaseth him.</note> durst not, and that he had a conscience, vpon coniecture to change any thing.</hi> And therefore all this is gnawing only. But in the 3. of Luke he maketh no conscience at all, to leaue out these wordes vers. 36. <hi>Qui fuit Cainan,</hi> not onely in his owne translation, but in the vulgar Latine which is ioyned therewith, saying in his Annot. <hi>Non dubitauimus expungere,</hi> that is, <hi>We doubted not to put it out:</hi> and why? <hi>by the authoritie of Moyses Gen. 11.</hi> Whereby he signifieth, that it is not in the Hebrue Gen. 11. where this posteritie of S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m is
<pb n="41" facs="23"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eckened: and so to maintaine the Hebrue veritie (as they call it) in the old Testament he careth not what become of the Greeke in the newe Testament, which yet at other times, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the vulgar Latine text, they call the Greeke veritie, and the pure fountaine, and that text whereby all translations must be tried.</p>
      <div n="18" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 18. His biting (as you call it) at the worde <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. and <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, <hi>Ast.</hi> 2. and <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, <hi>Act.</hi> 9. Seeing they concerne no controuersie, might haue bene contained in the section next before, especially se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you confesse he sayth he durst not, and that he had a conscience vpon coniecture to chaunge any thing. But in the 3. of <hi>Luk. vers.</hi> 36. He maketh no conscience at all to leaue out the words, <hi>Qui fuit Cainan,</hi> saying in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations, that he doubted not to put it out by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Moyses, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. A sore charge to diminish any part of the holy Scripture. But if he haue only corrected an errour of the scribe, which by all likelihoode tooke vpō him to adde vnto S. Luke out of the Greeke text of the 70▪ that which is not in the Hebrue, verily, I see not what offense he hath committed. For first he can meane no fraude in cōcealing those words, wherof he doth admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the reader, and of the cause of his leauing them out. Secondly▪ he winneth no aduantage against his aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or to his own cause, by omitting to say, that Sala was the sonne of Cainan, whom Moyses affirmeth to be the sonne of Arphaxad. And seeing Moyses <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. hath no such Cainan the sonne of Arphaxad, it is not like that S. Luke, who borrowed that parte of his genealogie out of Moises, woulde adde any thing which Moises had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. But you say that Beza to maintaine the Hebrue verity of the old Testament, eareth not what become of the Greke in the new Testament. You should haue made your antitheton more ful (wherein it seemeth you plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed your selfe not a litle) if you had sayed that Beza to maintaine the Hebrue veritie of the olde Testament, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not what becommeth of the Greeke corruption in
<pb n="42" facs="24"/>
the newe Testament: and so you shoulde haue spoken both more eloquently, and more truly. But at other times (you say) against the vulgar Latine text, they call the Greeke, text the Greeke veritie, and the pure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and that whereby all translations must be tried. We say in deede that by the Greeke text of the newe Testament, all translations of the newe Testament must be tried, but we meane not by euerie corruption that is in any Greeke coppie of the newe Testament, and muche lesse that the Hebrue text of the olde Testament, should be reformed after the Greeke of the newe, where it is vncorrupted: and least of all where any copie is guiltie of a manifest errour as in this place nowe in question.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="19" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 19.</hi> But if he haue no other way to reconcile both Testaments, but by striking out in the Greeke of the new, all that agreeth not with the Hebrue of the old Testament, then let him alter and chaunge so many wordes of our Sauiour him selfe, of the Euangelistes, and of the Apostles, as are cited out of the olde Testament, and are not in Hebrue. Which places they know are verie many, and when neede is, they shall be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to their handes. Let him strike out (Mat. 13. v. 14. 15. &amp; Act. 28. v. 26. 27.) the wordes of our Sauiour and S. Paule, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of Esay, because they are farre otherwise in the Hebrue.<note place="margin">Est. 6. 9. 10. Gal. 3. 13. <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note> Strike out of the Epistle to the Galathians these wordes, <hi>vpon a tree:</hi> because in the Hebrue it is only thus. <hi>Cursed is he that is hanged.</hi> Deut. 21. in finc. Yea strike out of Dauids Psalmes that which concerneth our redemption vpon the crosse<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> much neerer, <hi>They haue pearced my handes and my feete,</hi> Psal. 21. because in the Hebrue there is no suche thing. Let thē controule the Apostle, Eph. 4. for saying, dedit, <hi>he gaue gifts:</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> because it is both in the Hebrue and Greeke, (Psal. 67.) <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepisti,<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note> thou tookest giftes.</hi> and (Hebr. 10.) for, <hi>corpus aptasti,</hi> let them put, <hi>aures perforasti,</hi> because it is so in the Hebrue, Psalm. 40. To be short, if all must be reformed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Hebrue, why doth he not in S. Steuens sermon cut off the number of siue soules from seuentie fiue, because it is not in the Hebrue?</p>
      <div n="19" type="Fulkes_response">
         <pb n="43" facs="24"/>
         <p>FVLK. 19. If you had read Beza his workes as dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to learne the truth out of them, as you haue pried here &amp; there busily howe to espie some fault or errour in them, you shoulde easily haue founde, that he hath other waies to reconcile both the Testaments, &amp; the difference that seemeth to be in the allegatiōs, than by striking out of the Greeke in the newe, all that agreeth not with the Hebrue of the olde Testament. And therefore vainly you bid him alter so many words as are cited in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament out of the old, which are not in the Hebrue, and strike out of <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. <hi>v</hi> 14. 15. and <hi>Act.</hi> 28. <hi>v.</hi> 26. 27. the words of our Sauiour▪ and S. Paule, cited out of Esay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are otherwise in the Hebrue. Beza knoweth that Christ and his Apostles alwaies kepe the sense of the Hebrue verity, although they do not alwaies rehearse the verie wordes. But whereas you bid him out of <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 13. strike out these words (<hi>vpon a tree</hi>) because in the Hebrue it is only thus: <hi>Cursed is he that is hanged.</hi> You shew either grosse ignoraunce or intolerable frowardnesse▪ for these words (<hi>vpon a tree</hi>) are in that verse, &amp; in the next before. For thus the Hebrue text is. 22. <hi>When there shalbe in any</hi>
            <note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note>
            <hi>person a sinne to be adiudged to death, &amp; he shalbe deliuered to death, if thou shalt hang him vpō a tree:</hi> 23. <hi>Let not his carcase tarie all night vpon that tree, but in any case thou shalt burie him the same day, for accursed to God is he that is hanged.</hi> The word (<hi>tree</hi>) being twise named before, who would be so madde to say, that S. Paule hath added it beside the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue text. Likewise where you bidde vs strike out of the Hebrue. <hi>Psal.</hi> 21. that which concerneth our redemption on the crosse. <hi>They haue pearced my handes and my feete,</hi> because in the Hebrue there is no suche thing: you say most vntruely, for there is nothing else in the Hebrue, no not in the common readings, as Iohannes Isaake a Popishe Iewe will teache you, who hath confuted the cauils of Lindanus against the Hebrue texte, of whom you borrowed this exam le, where if you had not beene blinde with mallice, you mighte haue seene
<pb n="44" facs="25"/>
that Sainct Hierome did reade without controuersie, <hi>Fix<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>runt,</hi> they haue pearced, as also that the most aunciēt copie of the Hebrue Psalmes, supposed to haue pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Sainct Augustine of Cāterburie, hath <hi>Charu</hi> they<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note> haue pearced, though you had bene ignoraunt what is written concerning this word in the Masoreth and what Isaac also writeth of that word, as it is commonly redde, that it can not signifie, as you fantasie <hi>sicut leo:</hi> like a lion. And therefore the Chalde, paraphrast turneth it, As a lion, they pearced my handes and my feete. But of this matter more hereafter, as occasion shall be giuen. As for the Apostle, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4. saying that Christ gaue giftes, whereas of Dauid it is sayd, he receiued giftes, speaketh nothing contrarie to the Hebrue: but sheweth wherefore Christ hath receiued gifts: namely to bestow vpon his church. Except you will say that Christ gaue of his owne and receiued none: and so the Apostle doth shewe the excellencie of the trueth, aboue the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure: Christ aboue Dauid. Likewise, where the Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist sayeth in the Hebrue: Thou hast opened mine eares, the Apostle doth rightly collect, that Christ had a bodie, which in his obedience was to be offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the father. Last of all you would haue fiue soules cut from 75. in Sainct Stephens Sermon, because it is not in the Hebrue: but you are deceiued. For Sainct Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen gathereth the whole number of them that are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the fortie sixt chapter of Genesis. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the two sonnes of Iuda, that were deade, and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobes foure wiues, to shewe howe greate his familie was at the vttermost, before he went downe into Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, and howe greatly God did multiplie him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde. What is there in any of these examples like to <hi>Qui fuit Cainan,</hi> about whiche you make so muche a doe?</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="20" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 20.</hi> Must such difficulties &amp; diuersities be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued by chopping and changing, hacking and hewing the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred text of holy Scripture? Sec into what perplexities wilfull
<pb n="45" facs="25"/>
heresie and arrogancie hath driuen them. To discredit the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Latine translation of the Bible, and the fathers expositions according to the same (for that is the originall cause of this) and besides, that they may haue alwaies this euasion, <hi>It is not so in the Hebrue, it is otherwise in the Greeke,</hi> and so seeme iolly fellowes and great clerkes vnto the ignorant people, what do they? they admit onely the Hebrue in the old Test. and the Greeke in the newe, to be the true and authenticall texte of the Scripture. Wherevpon this foloweth, that they reiect, and must needes reiect the Greeke of the old Test. (called the Septuagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta)<note place="margin">Their perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in defending both the hebrue text of the olde Testament, and Greeke texte of the nevv.</note> as false, because it differeth from the Hebrue. Which being reiected, therevpon it foloweth againe, that wheresoeuer those places so disagreeing from the Hebrue are cited by Christ or the Euangelists and Apostles, there also they must be reiected, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they disagree from the Hebrue, and so yet againe it folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the Greeke text of the new Testament is not true, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is not according to the Hebrue veritie: &amp; consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the wordes of our Sauiour, and writings of his Apostles must be reformed (to say the least) because they speake according to the Septuaginta, and not according to the Hebrue.</p>
      <div n="20" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 20. Who alloweth, or who can abide chop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and changing, or hacking and hewing the sacred text of holy Scriptures? As for the perplexities where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto you faine that wilfull heresie and arrogancie hath driuen vs, is of your weauing, for God be praised we can wel inough with good conscience &amp; sound knowledge, that may abide the iudgement of all the learned in the world, defend both the Hebrew text of the olde Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Greeke text of the new. Not of purpose to discredit the vulgar Latine translation, and the expositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the fathers: but to fetch the truth, vpon which the hope of our saluation is grounded, out of the first foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and springs, rather than out of any streames that are deriued from them. And this we doe agreeable to the auncient fathers iudgements. For who knoweth not what fruitfull paines <hi>S. Hierom</hi> tooke in translating the Scripture out of the originall tongue, neither would he
<pb n="46" facs="26"/>
be disswaded by S. Augustine, who although he misliked that enterprise, at the first, yet afterward he highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the necessitie of the Greeke &amp; Hebrue tongues for Latine men, to find out the certaine truth of the text in the infinite varietie of the Latine interpretations: <q>for thus he writetth, <hi>De doct. Christ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>Contra ignota signa propria magnum remedium est linguarum cognitio. E<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> latinae &amp;c.</hi> Against vnknowen proper signes, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of tongues is a great remedie. And truly men of the Latine tongue, whom we haue now taken in hand to instruct, haue neede also of two other tongues vnto the knowledge of the diuine Scriptures, namely the Hebrue, &amp; the Greeke, that recourse may be had vnto the former copies, if the infinite varietie of the Latine interpreters shal bring any doubt, although we find oftētimes in the bookes, Hebrue words not interpreted, as <hi>Amen, Alleluia, Racha, Osanna, &amp;c.</hi> and a litle after <hi>Sed nō propter haec pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca &amp;c.</hi> But not for these few wordes which to marke and inquire of, it is a very easie thing, but for the diuersities (as it is said) of the interpreters, the knowledge of those tongues is necessarie. For they that haue interpreted the scriptures out of the Hebrue tōgue into the Greke tong, may be nūbred, but the Latine interpreters by no means can be numbred. For in the first times of the faith, as a Greeke booke came into euery mans hand, &amp; he seemed to haue some skill in both the tongues, he was bold to interpret it. Which thing truly hath more helped the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, than hindred, if the readers be not negligēt: for the looking vpon many bookes, hath often times made manifest sundry obscure or darke sentences.</q> This is S. Augustines sound iudgement, of the knowledge of tongues, and diuersitie of interpretations, for the better vnderstanding of the Scriptures. But let vs see what be the absurdities, that you gather of our defending the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall texts of both the tongues. First, we must needes reiect the Greeke of the olde Testament, called <hi>septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginta,</hi> as false, because it differeth frō the Hebrew. Where
<pb n="47" facs="26"/>
it is not onely different in wordes, but also contrary in sense, Why should we not? but if it reteine the sense and substance, although it expresse not the same wordes, we neede not reiect it. S. Hierom, who was required by Paula, and Eustochium, to expounde the Prophetes, not onely according to the truth of the Hebrew, but also af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the translation of the Septuaginta, whereof he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse tymes complayneth: vppon the first of Nahum, sayth expresly, that it was against his conscience alwaies, to follow the same. <q>
               <hi>Ignoscite prolixitati, &amp;c.</hi> Pardon me that I am so long. For I can not, following both the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and the tropologie or doctrine of maners, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend both briefly: most of all, seeing that I am so great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye tormented, or troubled with the varietie of the translation, and against my conscience sometimes I am compelled to frame a consequence of the vulgar edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which was the Septuaginta. This was Sainct Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roms opinion of the Septuagintaes translation.</q> But vpon reiection of that translation (say you) it followeth that wheresoeuer those places, so disagreeing from the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue are cited by Christ, or the Euangelistes and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, there also they must be reiected, because they disagree from the Hebrue, and so the Greeke text of the newe Testament is not true, and consequentlye the wordes of our Sauiour, and writinges of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles speaking according to the Septuaginta, must at leaste bee reformed. It is an olde saying, and a true, that one inconuenience being graunted, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye doe followe, and so you may heape vp an hundred after this manner. But for aunswere I say, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Sauiour, nor his Apostles, citing any place out of the olde Testament, doe bring any thing disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing in sense, and substance of matter (the purpose for which they alleage it considered) from the truth of the Hebrue text. Therefore there is no neede that the 70. in those places should be reiected. Althogh our Sauiour Christ speaking in the Syrian tōgue, is not to be thoght
<pb n="48" facs="27"/>
euer to haue cited the text of the 70. which is in Greeke. And his Apostles and Euangelists vsing that text, regard the substance of the sentence, &amp; not the forme of words. For many times they cite not the very wordes of the Greeke 70. neither: &amp; S. Hierom <hi>in Catalogo script: Eccles.</hi> which is set as a Preface to S. Mathewes Gospell, telleth you expresly, that in the Hebrew example of S. Mathew which he had, wheresoeuer the Euangelist S. Mathew ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his owne person, or in the person of our Lorde and Sauiour, vseth the testimonies of the olde Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he followeth not the authoritie of the 70. transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, but the Hebrew: of which these are two places: Out of Egypt haue I called my sonne. And he shall be called a Nazarite. See you not what a perilous perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie we are are in by defending both the Hebrue text of the olde Testament, and the Geeke of the Newe, when neither are contrarie to the other?</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="21" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 21.</hi> All which must needes followe, if this be a good cōsequence, <hi>I find it not in Moises, nor in the Hebrue, therefore I strooke it out,</hi> as Beza doth and saith concerning the foresaid words. <hi>Qui fuit Cainan.</hi> This consequence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs see how they will iustifie: and withall let them tell vs, whether they will discredit the newe Testament, because of the Septuaginta, or credit the Septuaginta, because of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, or how they can credit one, and discredit the other, where both agree and consent togither: or, whether they will discredit both, for credit of the Hebrue: or rather, whether there be not some other way to reconcile both Hebrue &amp; Greeke, better than Bezaes impudent presumption. Which if they will not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, let them flatly cōfesse that he did wickedly, &amp; not (as they doe) defend euery word and deede of their maisters, be it neuer so hainous, or salue it at the least.</p>
      <div n="21" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 21. No whit of that doth followe by stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out <hi>qui fuit Cainan.</hi> Because it is not foūd in Moises, &amp; therfore we haue nothing to do to iustifie your vaine consequence grounded vpon an absurdity of your owne deuising. But we must tell you whether we will discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite
<pb n="49" facs="27"/>
the new Testament, because of the Septuaginta? no not for a thousand millions of Septuagintaes, nor for all the worlde will we credite the Septuaginta, against the truth of the old Testament. But what soeuer is cited out of the 70. in the new, is not contrarie to the Hebrew in the old, and therefore the way of reconciliation is easily found, without discrediting both, or either of both in those places. And in this place, which is a meere corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, borrowed out of the corruption of the Septuagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taes, or a Iudaical additiō <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. I think there is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way of reconciling than to strike it cleane out, as Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za hath done, whiche generation neither is in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew veritie, nor in your owne vulgar Latin translation, either <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. or 1. <hi>Par.</hi> 1. Beside that it maketh a foule errour in the computation of time, adding no lesse than 230. yeares betweene <hi>Arphaxad</hi> and <hi>Sala,</hi> more than the Hebrew veritie, or the vulgar Latin agreeing therewith, doth number. And therefore he was more presumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that out of the corrupt and false text of the Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginta, added the same vnto the Genealogie in S. Luke, than Beza, which by the authoritie of Moses remoued the same. If you will still persist to defende the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Septuaginta, against the Hebrew veritie, which like an Atheist you deride, at leastwise defende your owne vulgar Latine translation of the old Testament, and deliuer your selfe out of that perplexitie, in which you would place vs, betweene the Hebrew of the old, and the Greeke of the new Testament. Seing no lesse doubts intangleth you betweene the Latine of the new, and the Latine of the olde, differing altogither a like, as the Greeke and the Hebrew do.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="22" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 22.</hi> Alas how farre are these men from the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie<note place="margin">Hovv the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers reconcile the said Hebrue and Greeke. Li. 18. de Ciui<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. c. 43. 2. Lib. de Doct. Chr. c. 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</note> of the auncient fathers, and from the humble spirite of obedient Catholikes, who seeke all other meanes to resolue diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, rather than to do violence to the sacred Scripture, and when they finde no way, they leaue it to God. S. Augustine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the difference of the Hebrue &amp; the Greeke, saith often
<pb n="50" facs="28"/>
to this effect, that it pleased the holy Ghost to vtter by the one, that which he would not vtter by the other. And S. Ambrose thus, <hi>Wee haue founde many thinges not idly added of<note place="margin">Hexam. li. 3. ca. 6.</note> the 70. Greeke interpreters.</hi> S. Hierom, though an earnest patrone of the Hebrue (not without cause, beyng at that time<note place="margin">In Prooem. li. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralip.</note> perhaps the Hebrue veritie in deede) yet giueth many reasons for the differences of the Septuaginta, and concerning the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saide places of S. Luke, he doth giue a reason thereof, both for<note place="margin">Comment. in 28. Esa. and in quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion. Hebrai.</note> the 70, and for the Euangelist that folowed them, neither doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the truth thereof, nor controlling them <hi>by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Moyses</hi> (as Beza speaketh) that is, by the Hebrue. Others say concerning Cainan, that Moyses might leaue him out in the Genealogie of Sem, by the instinct of the same Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, that S. Matthew left out three kings in the genealogie of<note place="margin">Mat. c. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</note> our Sauiour. Where if a man would controll the Euangelist by the Hebrue of the old Testament that is read in the bookes of the kings, he should be as wise and as honest a man as Beza. Lastly, Venerable Bede thinketh it sufficient in this very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie<note place="margin">Praef. in Act. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>post.</note> of Cainan, to maruell at it reuerently, vather than to search it dangerously. And thus farre of picking quarels to the originall text, and their good will to alter and change it as they list, if they might be suffered.</p>
      <div n="22" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 22. Here of pittie you will shewe vnto vs a peece of learning, how the Fathers reconcile the sayde Hebrue and Greeke, without violence to the text, as they do alwayes, or else leaue the matter to God.</p>
         <p>First S. Augustine <hi>De ciuitate, lib.</hi> 18. <hi>cap.</hi> 43. <hi>de doctr. chr. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. of their agreement, notwithstanding they<note place="margin">8<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</note> were separated into seuerall celles, gathereth, that those Septuaginta were inspired with the same prophetical spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of interpreting, that the Prophetes were in fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shewing. But this doth S. Hierome vtterly denie, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rideth<note place="margin">Pr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fat. in Pent<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> teuch.</note> the ground of this imagination, those 72. celles at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> as a fable and a lie. That S. Ambrose saith, we haue found that many thinges are not idely added of the 70. Greeke interpreters: We confesse as much, where<note place="margin">
               <hi>Hexam. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> their addition serueth for explication of that whiche is
<pb n="51" facs="28"/>
contavned in the Hebrue, and so meaneth Ambrose: not that they had auctoritie to adde any thing, which Moses had omitted. And we acknowledge with S. Hierome, that their may be many reasons giuen for the difference of the one, frō the other: But concerning this place of S. Luke now in question, you say he giueth a reason therof, both for the 70. &amp; for the Euangelist that followed thē, neither doubting of the truth thereof, nor controlling them by the auctoritie of Moses. And for this you quote <hi>Comment. in</hi> 28. <hi>Esa.</hi> and <hi>in question. Hebrai.</hi> in neither of which places is any mention of this place, much lesse any reason giuen to reconcile it, or the Septuaginta with the Hebrue. It seemeth you redde not the bookes your selfe, but trusted to much some mans collectiō, which you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstoode not. In the Preface to the Hebrue questions, Hieronime excuseth him selfe against enuious persons, that barked against him as though he did nothing but reproue the errors of the 70. saying. <q>That he thinketh not his labour to be a reprehension of thē, seing they would not expresse vnto Ptolomaeus king of Alexādria, certain mysticall thinges in the Scriptures, and especially those things which promised the comming of Christ, least the Iewes might haue bene thought to worship an other God, whom that follower of Plato therefore did greatly esteeme, because they were said to worship but one god. But the Euangelistes also, and our Lorde and Sauiour, and S. Paule the Apostle, bring foorth many thinges, as it were out of the old Testament, which are not had in in our bookes, of whiche in their due places wee will more fully discusse. Whereof it is cleare, that those are the more true examples, which agree with the auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the newe Testament.</q> Thus much Hierom in that place: but neither in his questions vppon Genesis, nor 1. <hi>Paralip.</hi> the proper places for this texte, is their any mention of this place of Luke, <hi>Qui fuit Cainan.</hi> In the place cited by you vpon the 28. of Esay, hee sayth, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimus in Apostolo, &amp;c.</hi> We reade in the Apostle. In other
<pb n="52" facs="29"/>
            <q>tongues and lippes will I speake to this people, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther so shall they heare me, sayth the Lorde. Which see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me to be taken out of this present chapter, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Hebrew. And this we haue obserued in the old Testament, except a few testimonies which only Luke vseth otherwise, whiche had knowledge of the Greeke tongue rather, wheresoeuer any thing is said out of the old Testamēt, that they set it not according to the 70. but according to the Hebrue, folowing the translatiō of no mā, but turning the sense of the Hebrue into their owne speach.</q> You see that Hierome saith nothing parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, &amp; that which he sayth generally, concerneth this place nothing at all. And very like it is, that this corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption was not crept into S. Lukes text in his tyme, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially seeing neyther S. Ambrose in his commentarie vpon S. Luke, once toucheth this controuersie, as hee doth all other questions about that Genealogie. Where you say S. Hierome was a great patrone of the Hebrue, not without cause, being at that time perhaps the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue veritie in deede. It is without perhaps, or perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture, that not one iote, or pricke of the lawe of God can perishe, by the testimonie of our Sauiour Christe, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. And if you will beleeue <hi>Arias Montanus,</hi> an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent learned Papiste, he will tell you as much, out of the same text doubtles, in his Preface vnto the great Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by him set out, with diligent obseruation of all the Accents &amp; Hebrue points, which Christ (sayth he) will neuer suffer to perish. And if the Hebrue veritie were in Hieronyms time (as doubtlesse it was) whether he had a perfect copie therof, or no, the same <hi>Arias Montanus</hi> testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, if you dare credite him, being one of your sect, for opinion, though in sinceritie of minde, and loue of the truth, which I pray to God to reueale vnto him, I thinke him far better than a number of you: he (I say) affirmeth in the same Preface, against the obiection that is made of the Iewes corruption of the Hebrue bookes: <q>
               <hi>Etenim apud nonnull.</hi> for we reade in some auctors that through
<pb n="53" facs="29"/>
the fraude and impulsion of the spirit of errour, some of the nation of the Iewes in times past were brought to that point of insolencie, or madnesse, that in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Christian church, they changed some words, which might altogither breake of that their contention of oppugning the Christian veritie: But those places so defiled by them, were very fewe, and in the bookes of our writers, and also in the copies, both printed &amp; writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the Iewes them selues, are all for the most partno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and shewed out. For although either by the fraude of those men, or by the ignorance of the booke writers, or by iniurie of the times, some change hath bene made in the Hebrew bookes, which we vse, yet is there not one word, nor one letter, nor point that is mentioned to haue bene of olde time, which is not found to haue bene safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept, in that moste riche treasurie, which they call the Mazzoreth. For in that, as in an holy and faithfull custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, appointed with vttermost diligence, and great study, the remnants, monuments, tokens, steppes, and examples of the auncient reading, are all conteined, and the way how to compare the olde and new reading is shewed: of which truely, being compared togither, a very certaine way is extant, to the prescript rule whereof, the holy my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries may be shewed forth, examples whereof some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in this worke, in due place, and else where also, with Gods helpe, we will set forth.</q> Thus farre Arias Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, whose iudgement if you say you are not bound to follow, yet I suppose you can yeelde no sufficient reason, why you should not credit his testimonie, concerning the certaintie of the Hebrew veritie, remaining to this daye, and which shall remaine to the worldes ende, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all the smatterers among you, would brast for spite against it. Concerning the opinion of them, which thinke that Moses might leaue out <hi>Cainan,</hi> in the genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of <hi>Sem,</hi> by the same spirit that Mathew left out three kings in the genealogie of our Sauiour. I answer, if it be lawfull so to imagine, we may without studie answer all
<pb n="54" facs="30"/>
controuersies, although the same reason is not of Moses compiling a certaine account of the time, from the floud to the calling of Abraham, and of Mathew, shewing by the legall discent, which euery man might take out of the bookes of Kinges and Chronicles, that Christ was the sonne of Dauid, and therefore he was not bound to the number of successors, seeing for memorie, it was his purpose to recite but thrise foureteene generations. That Beda maruaileth at the doubt, which he could not dissolue, his modestie is to be commended, rather than his knowledge. Neuerthelesse, the same Beda, in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face vnto his retractation vpon the Acts of the Apostles, speaking of such difference, as he founde in the Greeke text of the Actes, from the Latine, he saith: <q>
               <hi>Quae vtrum negligentia interpretis omissa, &amp;c.</hi> Which things, whether they were omitted through negligence of the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or otherwise vttered, or for lack of regard of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters depraued, or otherwise left, as yet we coulde not know. For I dare not so much as suspect, that the Greeke copie was falsified: wherefore I admonish the Reader, that wheresoeuer we haue done these things, he reade thē for his learning: yet that he interlace them not in his booke, as places corrected except perhaps he shal find the same in some Latine booke of a peculiar edition, to haue bene of olde so interpreted.</q> This place sheweth that in Bedes time, there were more Latine translatiōs than one, &amp; that the vulgar Latine was not of such authoritie, but that it might be corrected by the Greeke, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of other auncient Latine translations. Likewise vpon the text in question, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>in Luc. cap.</hi> 3. he confesseth that the name &amp; generation of Cainan, according to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew verity, is found neither in Genesis, nor in the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles: saying that S. Luke tooke this generation from the edition of the Septuaginta. But whether is the truer, or whether both can be true, he leaueth it to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God. Noting that whereas according to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew verity, from the floud to the birth of Abrahā, there
<pb n="55" facs="30"/>
were but 292. yeares, the 70. make 1077. so that the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is no lesse than of 785. yeares. But to fauour this fact of Beza, in putting out the name of Cainan, there is an auncient copie of the Gospels &amp; Actes in Greeke and Latine, of as great antiquitie by all likelihood, as any copie this day extant in Christendome, sent vnto the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuersitie of Cambridge this laste yeare, by Beza him selfe, there to be kept in the cōmon librarie, in which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, this generation of Cainan, both in the Greeke, &amp; in the Latine, is cleane left out, euen as Beza hath done in his translation. So that he hath not onely the authoritie of Moses, which of it selfe is sufficient, but also the testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of this most aūcient booke, both for the Greeke &amp; for the Latine, to approue his facte in putting out <hi>Qui fuit Cainan.</hi> What your vulgar latine translation hath left out in the later ende of the Lordes prayer in S. Mathew, and in the beginning and middest in S. Luke, whereby that heauenly prayer is made vnperfect, not comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all things that a Christian man ought to pray for, beside many other like omissions, whether of purpose, or of negligence, and iniurie of time, yet still by you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, I spare to speake of in this place.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="23" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 23.</hi> Which also may be proued by all their false<note place="margin">The 5. abuse of Scriptures, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt translation. vvhich is the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of this booke.</note> translations (being the principall point I meane to speake of) most euidently. For as now they translate falsly to their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, because they can not alter the text: so would they, if it were possible, haue the text agreeable to their translation. For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he that translateth, <hi>ordinances,</hi> when it is in the originall Greeke text, <hi>iustifications,</hi> and, <hi>traditions,</hi> he would rather that it were, <hi>ordinances,</hi> also in the Greeke: but because he can not bring that about, he doth at the least what he can, to make the ignorant beleeue it is so, by so translating it.</p>
      <div n="23" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 23. You shall neuer be able to proue by any trāslatiō of ours (though perhaps in some we may erre,) that we haue any purpose, either to falsifie the truth, or to change the text though it were possible for vs. In tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slating we haue dealt with a good conscience, albeit
<pb n="56" facs="31"/>
not alwaies peraduenture, we haue attained to the full truth, which in translating out of one tongue into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is a very hard point throughly to obserue. Your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of ordinances translated, for that which in the Greeke is iustifications and tradition, when you shewe where, and by whome it is so translated, you shall receiue an answer. In the meane time, (I say) a translator that hath regard to interprete for the ignorant peoples instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may sometimes depart from the etymology, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon signification or precise turning of worde for word, and that for diuerse causes. You your selues translate not <hi>Ecclesia,</hi> alwayes the Church, but sometimes the assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, nor <hi>Seniores,</hi> Elders, but Seniors, or auncients. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would you translate <hi>Presbyter,</hi> alwaies a priest, if you translated the olde Testament. In the storie of Susanna, you would not call them Priestes, that layd waite for her honestie and life: yet in your vulgar Latine, they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Priestes. So are they called <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> in Greeke, in the new Testament, which you turne sometimes Priests, sometimes auncients, and sometimes Seniors.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="24" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 24.</hi> And this of all other is the most fine and subtill treacherie against the Scriptures, to deceiue the ignorant readers withall, (which S. Paule calleth <hi>the secret thinges of<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> dishonestie, and adulterating of the word of God,</hi> as it were mingling water with wine like false vinteners) when they giue them for Gods word, &amp; vnder the name of Gods word, their owne words, and not Gods, forged and framed, altered and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, according to differences of times, and varietie of new opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and diuersitie of humors and spirits, diuersly and different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">The Heretikes dissention about their translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Dial cont. Melan. Lind. dubit pag. 84. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>6. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>8. c See Zuing resp <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess. Tigurinorum.</note> one Heretike not onely correcting his fellow euery day, but one egerly refuting and refelling an other. Bucer, and the Osian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drians and c Sacramentaries against Luther for false translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Luther against Munster, Beza against Castaleo, Casta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leo against Beza, Caluin against Seruetus, Illyricus both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Caluin and Beza: The Puritanes controule the grosser Caluinists of our country, yea the later translations of the selfe same Heretikes, controule the former exceedingly, not onely
<pb n="57" facs="31"/>
of ouersights, but of wilfull falsifications, as it is notorious in the<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. pag. 83. 97.</note> later editions of Luther and Beza, and in our Englishe Bibles set forth in diuerse yeares, from Tindall their first translatour vntill this day: yea (which is more) the Englishe translatours<note place="margin">The nevv Test of the yeare 1580.</note> of Bezaes newe Testament, controule him and his translation which they protest to followe, <note n="*" place="margin">Luc. 3. 36.</note> being afraide sometime and ashamed to expresse in Englishe his false translations in the Latin.</p>
      <div n="24" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 24. By false translations wilfully and of purpose to falsifie the truth of Gods word is as grosse &amp; as abhominable treacherie, as to corrupt the verie text, although I thinke S. Paule speaking of the couertures, or cloakes of dishonestie, and adultering of the worde of God 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. meaneth a further cūning, than false trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. That those whom you call heretikes finde fault with one an others translations, they do none otherwise, than you Popish heretikes. Do not you Gregorie Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, in the 7. chapter and 33. section of this booke finde fault with all the Catholikes as you terme them, that translate <hi>Sheol, Sepulchrum,</hi> a sepulchre, and not alwayes<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note> hell? If Bucer, or Zwinglius do iustly obserue any errour in Luther, or Luther in Munster, or Beza in Castalio the Anabaptist, or Caluine in Seruetus the horrible here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, yea and if froward &amp; schismaticall Illyricus can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer any errour committed by Caluine, and Beza: the truth leeseth nothing, when the errours of men are found out by what meanes soeuer. That you speake of the Puritanes, controuling the grosser Caluinistes of our countrie, I knowe not what you meane, neither doe I thinke you can iustifie your words, for translation of the Scriptures. Where you say, the later translations of the selfe same heretikes controule the former exceedingly, not only of ouersightes, but of wilfull falsifications, it is a wilfull and impudent sclaunder: yet you blushe not to say, it is notorious. Howe I pray you? You aunswere in the later editions of Luther and Beza, and in our Englishe Bibles set forth in diuerse yeares, from Tyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall
<pb n="58" facs="32"/>
their first translatour. That Luther, Beza, and the later translatours of the Englishe Bibles haue corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted some small faultes that haue escaped in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer editions, it may be graunted. But doe Luther, and Beza therefore accuse them selues, or the later Englishe translatours the former, of wilfull falsifications? I thinke those brute beastes, to whome Ambrose ascribeth the<note place="margin">
               <hi>Hexam. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> arte of making syllogismes (if they could speake) would not conclude thus brutishly. Certaine it is that Balaams asse did reason substantially. But muche more you saye the Englishe translatours of Bezaes newe Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doe controule him and his translation, being somtimes afraid and ashamed to expresse his false trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. If it be so, they are more modest than you, which seeme to bee afrayed, or ashamed of nothing so much, as least you might seeme to faile in vnshamefast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. But to the purpose. If they thinke Beza (as all men may erre) hath somewhat troden awrye, is it a faulte to auoyde his steppe, or a prowde controuling or accusing him of falsification? Neuerthelesse where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in soeuer Luther, Beza, or the Englishe translatours,<note place="margin">
               <hi>De doct. Christ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p.</hi> 11.</note> haue reformed any of their former ouersightes, the matter is not so great, that it can make an heresie. Yea, if you were of Sainct Augustines iudgement you would acknowledge that the multitude and diuersitie of trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, is for the benefite of them that be ignoraunt in the tongues, yea &amp; of them also, that be learned in them oftentimes, that of diuerse mens translations, they may iudge which is the aptest.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="25" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 25.</hi> But in this Catalogue of dissentions falsifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and disagreeing translatours, I will not greatly rippe vp old<note place="margin">Act. 1. 14. &amp; 2: 23. Act. 3. 21. The German, French, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish corruptions of the nevv Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament.</note> faultes, neyther abroad, nor at home. I leaue Luthers false tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slations into the Germaine tongue, to the credite of Staphylus, <hi>Apolog. part. 2.</hi> and Emserus, praef. <hi>Annot. in no. Test. Luth.</hi> and other Germaine writers of his owne time, that saw them &amp; read them, and reckoned the number of them in the new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only, about <note n="*" place="margin">See Lind. Dubit. p. 84. 85. &amp;c.</note> 1400. hereticall corruptions: I leaue Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines
<pb n="59" facs="32"/>
and Bezas french corruptions, to so many worthie men as <note n="*" place="margin">Vigor and the rest.</note> haue noted them in their french bookes against the said here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes: Tindals and his companions corruptions in their first En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Bible, to our learned countreymen of that age, and namely to the right reuerend Father and Confessor Bishop Tonstal, who in a sermon openly protested, that he had foūd in the new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment onely, no lesse than two thousand. If wee know it not, or wil not beleeue it, <note n="*" place="margin">Lind. Dub. p. 98.</note> strangers in their Latine writings testifie it to the world.</p>
      <div n="25" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 25. We are muche beholding to you, that you will not rippe vp olde faultes abroad, nor at home: and leaue Luthers Dutch translation with a 1400. here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall corruptions in the new Testament only, with Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uins &amp; Bezaes French corruptions noted by Vigor, and the rest. Also Tyndals &amp; his companions corruptions in their first English Bible, in whose translation of the new Testament Bishop Tonstal professed openly in a sermon that he found no lesse than 2000. corruptions. This you know he protested with the same tongue, with which he forsware the Pope, &amp; sware to the kings supremacie, and with which he preached a solēne sermō, which is in print before the King, against the Popes vsurped tirāny, pride, false doctrine, couetousnesse, crueltie, treason, peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Scriptures, as in the same Sermon more at large it appeareth: and therefor we neede not Lindanus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to testifie of his credit. But thankes be to God that when you haue scraped all that vnto you seemed to haue any shewe of corruption, you can not finde 200. faultes in the translation of the whole Bible, nor in three se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall translations of the same, which pointes you are faine to dilate, with such vaine tautologies, and repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that all learned men are ashamed of your tedious writing and yet to make your booke to be of some tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable lēgth, you had no better shift, than to note a sort of Bezaes corruptions in his Latine Testament. Who if you woulde write against him in Latine, any thing worth the noting, woulde thanke you for your paynes.
<pb n="60" facs="33"/>
and reforme his errours, but if you brought nothing but cauils, woulde so shake you vppe, as you shoulde haue small ioy of your insolent inuectiue: but you prouided well for that, by writing against a French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, in Englishe. And as for the number of errours, or coruptions that you woulde haue the ignoraunt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue to bee in our Englishe translations, you thinke is so greate, as must needes make the simple abhorre it. But looke homewarde a litle vnto your authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall vulgar Latine translation, howe manye faultes bee in that, which your Tridentine Councell hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorised. And here I will not charge it with the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries thereof, as you doe ours; but with great friendes of it, and your doctrine. Lindanus Bishoppe of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonde, and Isidorus Clarius Monke of Casine, and Bishoppe Fulginatensis, of whiche the former wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a whole booke, discussing howe he woulde haue<note place="margin">
               <hi>De opt. Gen. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpr. lib.</hi> 3.</note> the errours, vices, corruptions, additions, detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, mutations, vncertaynties, obscurities, pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, barbarismes, and soelecismes of the vulgar Latine translation corrected and reformed: bringing manye examples of euerie kinde, in seuerall chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and sections. The other Isidorus Clarius giuing<note place="margin">In his Epistle to the reader prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Venice <hi>apud Iuntas.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>557.</note> a reason of his purpose in castigation of the sayed vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Latine translation, confesseth that it was full of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, almost innumerable, which if he shoulde haue reformed all according to the Hebrue veritie, he could not haue set forth the vulgar edition, as his purpose was. Therefore in many places he retayneth the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed tanslation, but in his annotations admonisheth the reader, howe it is in the Hebrue. And notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this moderation, he acknowledgeth that about 8000. places are by him so noted &amp; corrected. This Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle the Deputies of the Councell of Trent could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide, and therefore in the later edition of this Bible, set forth with obseruation of their censure 1569. it is cleane left out, as also a godly collection of the same Isidorus,
<pb n="61" facs="33"/>
of places of Scripture, exhorting to the studie of holy Scripture, and a like sound confession of those thinges which the Scriptures teach, &amp;c.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="26" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 26.</hi> But I omit these as vnknowen to our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,<note place="margin">The authors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in this booke.</note> or to this age, and will deale principally with the English translations of our time, which are in euery mans handes within our country, the corruptions whereof, as they are partly touched here and there in the annotations vpon the late newe English Testament Catholikely translated and printed at Rhemes so by occasion thereof, I will by Gods helpe, to the better commoditie of the Reader, and euidence of the thing, lay them closer togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and more largely display them, not counting the number, because it were hard, but esteeming the weight and importance of so many as I thought good to note, specially in the new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Where I haue to aduertise the Reader of certaine speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things, which he must obserue.</p>
      <div n="26" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 26. You should rather omit them as vntrue, for albeit it can not be denied, but some faults may es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the most faithfull and diligent translator, yet so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heretical corruptions, either in the Dutch, or English are incredible, and turne rather to the discredit of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuser in all wise mens iudgement, than to the parties so charged. In like maner as Surius noteth no lesse than 11000. lyes in Sleidan, more to his owne reproche, than to the defacing of Sleidans credit. You professe wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therefore, not to count the number, but to esteeme the weight and importaunce of suche faultes as you thought good to note: if there were as great faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in your performance, as there is wisedom in your profession. But now to your nine aduertisements to the Reader.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="27" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 27.</hi> First, that in this booke he may not looke for<note place="margin">Certaine aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisements to the Reader.</note> the proofe or explication and deciding of controuersies, Which is done in the Annotations vpon the new Testament, but onely therefuting or controlling of their false translations concerning the said controuersies, which is the peculiar argument of this <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>reatise.</p>
      <div n="27" type="Fulkes_response">
         <pb n="62" facs="34"/>
         <p>FVLK. 27. I thinke their is no wise reader woulde loke for the deciding of so many cōtrouersies in so smal a booke, &amp; he that shal seeke them in your Annotations, shall find euen as litle to the purpose, except he will take your determinatiō without proofe for a sufficiēt decisiō. As for the doctors you quote without iudgment, fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, falsly, truncately, and otherwise abusiuely, haue all or the most bene answered long agoe. And if neede shal be, with litle labour may be answered againe.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="28" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 28.</hi> Secondly, that we refu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e sometime one of their translations, sometime an other, and euery one as their fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood giueth occasio. Neither is it a good defense for the falshood of one, that it is truely translated in an other: the reader being deceyued by any one, because commonly he readeth but one. Yea one of them is a condemnation of the other.</p>
      <div n="28" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 28. That sheweth your malice, rather than either wisedome or honestie. For if we our selues in our later translations, haue corrected some small and few er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, that haue ouerslipped vs in our former trāslatiōs, we haue shewed our sinceritie and care of setting out the truth by al meanes. And where you say, it is no good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, the reader being deceiued by any one, because cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mōly he readeth but one. I answere you, first there is not in the worst translation any fault escaped, that may of it selfe lead him into a damnable errour. Secondly, he hath the word of God expounded, by catechizing, sermons, &amp; lectures, in which he may learne the substance of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian religion. Thirdly, he hath at hand euery where lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Diuines, vnto whose counsell he may resort, if he be offended with any thing that he readeth in his Bible, soū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding contrarie to the publikely receiued doctrine of the Church. In that you say the one of our translations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth the other, it had bene sufficient to haue said, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth: which is only, where there is a manifest error in the one: for otherwise the diuersities of trāslations (as S. Augustin teacheth you) may much profit the simple rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: &amp; they that be diligent studēts of the Scriptures in
<pb n="63" facs="34"/>
the English tongue, will not satisfie them selues with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery translation, but wil seeke for the best approued.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="29" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 29.</hi> Thirdly, that we speake indifferently against Protestants, Caluinists, Bezites, and Puritans, without any cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious distinction of them, being all among themselues brethren and pewfellowes, &amp; sometime the one sort of them, sometime the other, more or lesse corrupting the holy Scriptures.</p>
      <div n="29" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 29. A wise aduertisement. But this is to be noted, that now you acknowledge them to be all bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren among them selues, and pewfellowes. But when you list, they shall be at deadly feude one against an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and no communitie or fellowship betwene them.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="30" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 30.</hi> Fourthly, that we giue but a taste of their corruptions, not seeing so farre, nor marking all so narrowly and skilfully, as them selues know their owne subtilties &amp; meanings, who will smile at the places which we haue not espied.</p>
      <div n="30" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 30. He that considereth your quarrels pickt to words of one signification, as Church &amp; Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, iustice and righteousnes, Elder and Priest, Image and Idol, workes and deedes, and such like, will not thinke that you haue past ouer any great matters worth the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of: but that you would set a vaine bragge of the case, as though there were much worse matter, than you haue witte to conceiue. Yet you say confidently, that we as guiltie of our owne subtilties and meanings, will smile at the places which you haue not espied. You are like to those southsayers mentioned in Tullie, of whom one sayd, that he maruailed, if when they mette togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one of them did not smile vppon another, because they deluded the cittie, &amp; got themselues much honour with such vaine superstitions. So you beyng newly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, subtill and partial translaters, thinke other men to be like your selfes. But euen as the head of your Church once iested with his Cardinall, how great wealth &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that fable of Christ (so the beast called the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian religion) had brought them: euen so you his lewde limmes, make sporte among your selfe of the
<pb n="64" facs="35"/>
holy worde of God, which you haue corrupted, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what with your blinde translatiōs, but much more with your hereticall Annotations. So said your great friend Campion, in open audience, that he could make as good sport vpon the incarnation of Christ. According to your owne affection therefore you iudge of vs, and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the truth, as the day will trie, when the secretes of all hartes shall be made manifest.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="31" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 31.</hi> Fifthly, that the very vse and affectation of certaine termes, and auoiding other some, though it be no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration against them, but that they may seeme to defend it for true translation, yet was it necessarie to be noted, because it is and hath bene alwayes a token of hereticall meaning.</p>
      <div n="31" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 31. When our translation is true, I doubt not but we shall defende the vse of some termes, and the auoiding of other some, by as good reason, as you shall defende the like in your translations, especially where you affect new termes vnused, or not vnderstoode, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide common and vsuall termes of the same significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as Euangelizing for preaching the Gospel, aduēt of Christ, for the cōming of Christ, scandalizing, for offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, scandale, for offense, &amp;c. Which if it be, as you say, alwayes a token of hereticall meaning, first plucke your selfe by the nose, and then see if we can not defend our doings.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="32" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 32.</hi> Sixtly, that in explicating these things, we haue endeuoured to auoide (as much as was possible) the tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse of Greeke and Hebrue wordes, which are only for the learned in these tongues, and which made some litle doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this matter (which of necessity must be examined by them) were to be written in Englishe or no. But being perswaded by those (who them selues haue no skill in the sayd tongues) that euerie reader might reape commoditie thereby, to the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing and detesting of such false &amp; Hereticall translations, it was thought good to make it vulgar and common to all our deere countrie men, as the newe Testament it selfe is common, whereof this Discouerie is as it were a handmaide, attending
<pb n="65" facs="35"/>
therevpon for the larger explication and proofe of corruptions there brie<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ly touched, and for supply of other some not there mentioned.</p>
      <div n="32" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 32. He that seeth your margent painted with Greeke and Hebrewe wordes, in so many places, may guesse whether it were possible for you to haue auoided the tediousnesse of them, when in diuerse places the Greeke and Hebrew wordes are set without all neede of them, and sometimes where there is no controuersie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them: as in the 5. section of this Preface, where you shew the corruptions of the Arrians and Pelagians, and in the 19 section, where you would shew the difference of the new Testament from the olde, in citing of testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. But the Hebrewe word in the Psalme 21. or 22. which you falsly say, signifieth no such thing, as pearcing, you set not downe, lest your falshood by them that haue skill, might be conuinced. And if you had cared as much to finde out the truth as to shewe your skill in both the tongues, you would haue written in Latine, especially against Beza, which neuer wrote in English. And vaine it is that you pretend to make the matter common to your deare countrimen, that be vnlearned, for the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muste reste in them that haue knowledge in the tongues, albeit you had written in Latine. It is all one therefore to the vnlearned, as if you had onely said, there are many faults or corruptions, which in a Latine booke shall be discouered to the iudgement of the learned▪ see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ignorant can not vnderstand your demōstratiōs.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="33" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 33.</hi> Seuenthly, that all the English corruptions here noted, and refuted, are either in all or some of their English Bibles printed in these yeares, 1562. 1577. 1579. And if the corruption be in one Bible, not in an other, commonly the sayd Bible or Bibles are noted in the margent: if not, yet sure it is, that it is in one of them, and so the Reader shall find it if he find it not alwaies in his owne Bible. And in this case the Reader must be very wise and circumspect, that he thinke not by and by we charge them falsly, because they can shew him some later edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="66" facs="36"/>
that hath it not so as we say. For it is their common and knowen fashion, not onely in their translations of the Bible, but in their other bookes and writings, to alter and change, adde &amp; put out, in their later editions, according as either them selues are ashamed of the former, or their scholers that print them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, dissent and disagree from their Maisters. So hath Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Caluins, and Bezaes writings and translations bene chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged both by them selues, and their scholers, in many places, so that Catholike men when they confute that which they find eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent faults in this or that edition, feare nothing more than that the Reader hath some other edition, where they are corrected for very shame, and so may conceiue that there is no such thing, but that they are accused wrongfully. For example. Call to minde the late pretended conference in the Tower, where that matter<note place="margin">Touching S. Iames Epistle.</note> was denied and faced out for Luthers credit, by some one booke or edition of his, which them selues, and all the world knoweth, was most truly layd to his charge.</p>
      <div n="33" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 33. First this is vntrue, for some you haue noted in the new Testament, printed 1580. Secondly, it is vncertaine, for two of these translations might be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in one yeare, and so I thinke they were. Therefore I know not well which you meane, but I guesse that the Bible 1562. is that which was of Doctor Couerdales tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation, most vsed in the Church seruice in King Edwards time. The Bible 1577. I take to be that, which being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised by diuerse Bishops, was first printed in the large volume, and authorized for the Churches, about tenne or twelue yeares agoe. That of 1579. I knowe not what translation it be, except it be the same that was first prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Geneua, in the beginning of the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Raigne. And this coniecture as the fittest I can make, I must followe, seeing your note of distinction, is as good, as that fond fellowes, that would know his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters horse by the bridle.</p>
         <p>But it is a common and knowen fashion, you say, vsed of vs, that not onely in translations, but in other bookes and writings of ours, we alter and change, adde, and put
<pb n="67" facs="36"/>
to in our later editions. And who vseth not so to doe, if by later cogitations, that often are wiser, he finde any thing meete to be changed? Doe not you Papistes vse the same? Is Bristowes chapter of obedience in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, nothing altered from the high treason contained in the first edition? Is nothing added, taken away, or changed in your Iesus Psalter, in any of your editions, or are you your selues ashamed of the former? Or haue your schollers presumed to alter their maisters writings? If you may haue an euasion in these cases, I trust we are not so pente in, but we may change our owne writings without shame of the former, or corruption in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. As for the example of S. Iames Epistle, denyed (as you saye) and faced out for Luthers credit, will serue you for no proofe. For so farre off is it, that we, or the world doe knowe, that is was moste truly layed to his charge: that nowe we knowe of a certaintie, that it was a very slaunder, as false, as it was common: seeing Luthers wordes of that Epistle, are not absolute, but in comparison, as is confessed by you, and founde by some of vs to be none otherwise in deede, who haue not stoode vpon one onely booke or edition, but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as many as they could come by, both in the Latine, and in the Dutch tongue.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="34" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 34.</hi> Eightly, in citing Beza, I meane alwaies (vnlesse I note otherwise) his Latine translation of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, with his annotations adioyned thereunto, printed in the yeare 1556.</p>
      <div n="34" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 34. You were afraide, lest they that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoode not Latine, for whose sake you wrote in English this treatise, might take hurt by Bezaes translations, and annotations in Latine. And if he him selfe haue espied, and corrected any thing of his first edition, that was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">In his later edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō 156<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. he hath <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fuit Caina<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> both in the Greek &amp; in the vulgar Latine.</note> faultie or offensiue, in his two later editions, with great equitie, as though you were the onely man that had discouered his errours, you muste let all the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned in Englande knowe, what shamefull corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="68" facs="37"/>
you haue obserued in Bezaes translation, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="35" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 35.</hi> Lastly and principally is to be noted, that<note place="margin">VVe charge them not vvith forsaking the olde approued Latine text, though it be an ill signe, and to their euident confusion.</note> we will not charge them with falsifying that which in deede is the true and authenticall Scripture, I meane the vulgar Latine Bible, which so many yeares hath bene of so great authoritie in the Church of God, and with all the auncient fathers of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Church, as is declared in the Preface of the newe Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: though it is much to be noted, that as Luther, onely in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of his heresies, did wilfully forsake it, so the rest followed, and doe follow him at this daye, for no other cause in the world, but that it is against them. And therefore they inueigh against it, and against the holye Councell of Trent, for confirming the<note place="margin">Kemnitius. Caluin.</note> authoritie thereof, both in their speciall treatises thereof, and in all their writings, where they can take any occasion.</p>
      <div n="35" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 35. In the margent, <hi>You will not charge vs with forsaking the old approued Latine text, though it be an ill signe, and to our euident confusion.</hi> S. Augustine, though a meere Latine man, whome you your selfe doe after confesse to haue vnderstoode but one tongue well, and that was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his mother tongue, learned (as he confesseth) of his nurses, is not so addicted to the Latine translation, but that he would haue men to seeke to the Hebrew, and Greeke fountaines, which you like a blasphemous hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite deny to be the true, and authenticall Scriptures in deede: allowing onely the vulgar Latine translation, as though neither the Churches of Greece, Syria, Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Aethiopia, nor any other in the world, which haue not the vulgar Latine, had not the true and authenticall Scriptures. And though your vulgar Latine hath for many yeares bene of great authoritie in the Latine Church, from the time when the knowledge of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew and Greeke tongues haue decayed: yet is it vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly false, that you say that it hath bene of great authoritie with all the fathers of the Latine Church: whereas there is not one that liued within 400. yeares after Christ, that knew it, but almost euery one followed a seueral transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="69" facs="37"/>
And S. Augustine in the place before cited, telleth you, that there were innumerable translations out of the Greeke into the Latine. Againe that your vulgar Latin, is full of many errours, and corruptions, I haue shewed by the confession of Isidorus Clarius, and Lindanus two of your owne profession: of which the one tooke paines by the Hebrue and Greeke to correct it, the other shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed meanes how it should be corrected. And where you say that Luther and his followers forsooke it for none other cause in the world, but that it is against them, it is vtterly vntrue. For beside that they haue made cleare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration of many palpable errours therein, (which they that haue any forehead amongst you cānot denie.) they haue and do dayly conuince you of horrible here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, euen out of your owne corrupt vulgar translation. Finally whosoeuer shall reade what Caluine and Kem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius hane written against the Councell of Trent, for auctorizing that translation, shall plainely see, that they had something else to alledge against it, which nothing at all concerneth their opinions, that be contrarie to the Popish heresie.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="36" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 36.</hi> And concerning their wilfull and hereticall auoyding thereof in their newe translations, what greater argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can there be than this, that Luther, who before alwaies had reade with the Cath. Church and with all antiquitie, these wordes of S. Paul, <hi>Haue not we power to leade about A<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9. Mulierem soro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. 2. Pet. 1.</note> WOMAN A SISTER, as also the rest of the Apostles?</hi> and in S. Peter, these wordes, <hi>Labour that BY GOOD WORKES you may make sure your vocation and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> sodenly, after he had contrarie to his profession taken a <hi>wife</hi> (as he called her) and preached that all other votaries might do the same, and that faith only iustified, <hi>good workes</hi> were not necessarie to saluation: sodenly (I say) after he fell to these heresies, he began to reade and translate the former Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures accordingly, thus: <hi>Haue not we power to lead about a SISTER A WIFE, as the rest of the Apostles? and, Labour that you may make sure your vocation and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection:</hi>
         <pb n="70" facs="38"/>
leauing out the other wordes, <hi>by good workes.</hi> And so do both the Caluinists abroade, and our English Protestants at home reade and translate at this day, because they holde the selfe same heresies.</p>
      <div n="36" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 36. If their be no greater argument, as you confesse there can be none, that their auoyding of this vulgar Latine is wilfull and hereticall, than this, that Luther defended his mariage beyng a votarie, by that texte of 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 9. wherein the Apostle challengeth power to leade aboute with him a sister to wife, whiche your texte hath <hi>Mulierem sororem</hi> a woman a sister. And that to proue that faith only iustifieth and good workes are not necessarie to saluation, he lefte out of the text of S. Peter good workes, by which the Apostle exhorteth vs to make sure vnto our selues our vocatiō, &amp; election: there is none argument at all of wilful, needlesse, or he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>oyding. For although the mariage of ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall ministers generally is proued by that Scripture: yet the mariage of votaries specially, is nothing confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And for the mariage of Bishops, Priestes and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, your owne translation of 1. Tim. 3. and Tit. 1. both Latine and English will warrant them to be the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes of one wife, so that euery childe may see, that he needed not for that purpose, to corrupt the texte, 1. Cor. 9. And as for the other texts, 2. Pet. 1. although this worde, (by good workes,) is not expressed in the moste Greeke copies, yet the whole circumstance of the place giueth it necessarily to be vnderstoode, and yet it maketh nothing agaynst iustification by fayth only. For our election which is most certaine &amp; immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in Gods determinatiō, is made certainly knowen vnto vs by good workes, the fruites of iustifying faith, euen as the effectes doe necessarily proue the cause gone before. And so dothe Thomas Mathewes Bible note: likewise the Bishops Bible, and the Geneua Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for so I had rather call them, than by the yeares in whiche they were once printed, whiche haue bene often
<pb n="71" facs="38"/>
printed, and perhaps all in some one yeare. Couer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dales Bible also addeth these wordes by good workes, whiche is redde in some Greeke copies. So true it is that you say, wee leaue it out, because wee holde the selfe same heresie: As likewise that you slaunder vs to hold, that good workes are not necessarie to saluation, whereas we beleeue that good workes are as necessarie to saluation, as fayth, in all them that are iustified by faith onely. But because you are not able to withstand the truth which we beleeue, you faine odious Monsters, as Dragons, Centaures, Hydraes to fight withall before the people, that you might gette the prayse of glorious conquerours: like S. George on horsebacke, that in a pageant vanquisheth an hideous dragon made of paper or painted clothes.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="37" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 37.</hi> So do they in infinite places alter the olde text, which pleased them well before they were Heretikes, and they do it with brasen faces, and playne protestation, hauing no shame nor remorse at all, in fleeing from that which all anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie with one consent allowed and embraced vntill their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie daies. Which though it be an euident condemnation of their nouelties in the sight of any reasonable man that hath any grace: yet as I began to admonish thee (gentle Reader) we will not charge them for altering the auncient approued Latin tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation, because they pretend to folowe the Hebrue and Greeke, and our purpose is not here, to proue that they should not folowe the Hebrue and Greeke that now is, before the auncient appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Latine text, which is done briefly already in the preface to the new Testament.</p>
      <div n="37" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 37. You were afrayde belike to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matched in rayling, and therefore you thought to beare vs downe at once, with a whole floud of reprochfull slaunders, and that you vtter euen with the same face, with which you affirme, that al antiquitie with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sente allowed and embraced your vulgar Latine texte: for what else you shoulde meane I cannot coniecture, seing you say afterwarde you will not charge vs for alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="72" facs="39"/>
the auncient approued Latine translation. What say you <hi>Martin?</hi> doth all antiquitie with one consent allowe and imbrace your vulgar Latine translation? What is the cause then that the most of all antiquitie of the Latine Church vsed not your vulgar Latine text? or dare you ioyne issue with me, that all the Latine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors for 400 yeares after Christe, vsed none other La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine translation but that? or that they all knewe your vulgar Latine translation: you are neuer able to proue it. The 70. translation in deede was greatly esteemed, and almost generally receyued in the Greeke and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Churches, and out of it were innumerable Latine versions, as S. Augustine affirmeth. But your vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine followeth it not in many places, as it were easie to shewe, if time and occasion serued, and I suppose you will not denie. As for the reasons you bring in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the newe Testament, to proue that we should not followe the Hebrue and Greeke that now is, before that auncient approued text, when they come to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered it shall appeare how vayne and friuolous they are. But as for the Hebrue and Greeke that now is, may easilie be proued to be the same that alwaies hath bene, neither is their any diuersitie in sentence, how soeuer some copies eyther through negligence of the writer, or by any other occasion do varie from that which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly and most generally receyued in some letters, syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables, or wordes.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="38" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 38.</hi> Neither will we burden them, for not fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing<note place="margin">VVe charge them not vvith forsaking the Greeke copies that agree vvith the auncient ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued Latine text, though this be a signe of their incredible partialitie.</note> the vulgar Latine texte, when the same agreeth with most auncient Greeke copies: which notwithstanding is great partialitie in them, &amp; must needes be of an heretical wilful hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, that among the Greeke copies themselues, they reiect that which moste agreeth with the vulgar Latine text, in places of controuersies: Yet will wee not I say, neither in this case, lay falsehood and corruption to their charge, because they pretend to translate the common Greeke text of the newe Testament, that is, one certaine copie. But here at the least lette them
<pb n="73" facs="39"/>
shewe their fidelitie, and that they be true and exact transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. For here onely shall they be examined and called to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
      <div n="38" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 38. In translation we follow the common vsuall and printed coppies, as you doe in your transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and yet you know there be as many, yea ten times as many diuerse readings in the Latine, as are in the Greeke: witnesse hereof the Bible printed at Antwerpe, by Christopher Plantine 1567. of Hentenius castigation: where the margents almost of euerie leafe be full of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse readings obeliskes, asterisks, stigmates, signifying the variety that is in many copies, by adding, detracting, chaunging.</p>
         <p>The same is confessed by Arias Montanus.<note place="margin">
               <hi>In apparat. Bibl. De opt. Gen. inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret. sc. lib.</hi> 3.</note>
         </p>
         <p>Lindanus likewise acknowledgeth as much.</p>
         <p>Of that which you say we reiect that which best a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth with the vulgar Latine in places of controuersie, you bring none example. But that among your diuerse readings, you reiect that which agreeth best with the Hebrue and with the Greeke in places of controuersie. I will giue you an example. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3 <hi>v.</hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>5. where the Hebrue truth teacheth, that the seede of the woman shall breake the serpentes heade, and the Greeke translateth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noune in the masculine gender (<hi>he</hi>) meaning Christ: and some auncient copies of your vulgar Latine haue <hi>(ipse)</hi> you neuerthelesse followe that blasphemous cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, that in these later times hath bene receiued in your vulgar Latine Bibles, and reade still in your texte <hi>ipsa,</hi> she, which though you would wrest blasphemous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the virgin Marie, which is proper to Christ, can not by the circumstance of the place be aptly referred to any but to Eue.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="39" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 39.</hi> And if they followe sincerely their Greeke<note place="margin">VVe charge thē for forsaking &amp; false translating their ovvne He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue &amp; Greeke text.</note> and Hebrue text, which they professe to followe, and which they esteeme the onely authenticall texte, so farre we accuse them not of hereticall corruption. But if it shall be euidently proued, that they shrinke from the same also, and translate an
<pb n="74" facs="40"/>
other thing, and that wilfully, and of full intention to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce their false religion and wicked opinions, making the Scriptures to speake as they list: then we trust, the indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent reader for his owne soules sake, will easily see and conclude, that they haue no feare of God, no reuerence of the Scriptures, no conscience to deceiue their readers: he will perceiue that the Scriptures make against them, which they so peruert and corrupt for their purpose: that neither the Hebrue nor Greeke text is for them, which they dare not translate truly and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely: that their cause is naught, which needeth suche f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ule shiftes: that they must needes knowe all this, and therefore doe wilfully against their conscience, and consequently are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinate heretikes.</p>
      <div n="39" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 39. We craue no pardon, if it can be proued that wee haue wilfully translated an other thing than is contained in the Hebrue and Greeke, to maintaine any false religion or wicked opinion. Prouided alwayes, that if any translatour, or all the translatours, haue igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly erred in misunderstanding any worde or phrase of the Hebrue or Greeke text, that if it may be plainly she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vnto them, they acknowledging the fault, they may not be charged with hereticall corruption, from which it is certaine, their intention was most free.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="40" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 40.</hi> And the more to vnderstand their miserie and wretchednesse, before we enter to examine their transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, marke and gather of all that which I haue sayed in this Preface, their manifolde flightes and iumpes, from one shift to an other, and howe Catholike writers haue pursued and chased them, and followed them, &amp; driuen them euen to this extreame refuge &amp; seely couert of false translation, where also they must of necessitie yeeld, or deuise some new euasion, which we can not yet imagine.</p>
      <div n="40" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 40. Hitherto I hope the indifferent reader will confesse, that you haue driuen vs to no iumpes, nor shiftes, but onely vttered your owne malicious and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned quarrels. And howe Popishe writers haue pursued and chased vs to extreame refuge, and seely
<pb n="75" facs="40"/>
couert of false translation, let it appeare by the learned answeres of M. Iewell, M. Horne, M. Nowell, M. Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, M. Calfhill, and others, that I speake nothing of mine owne simple labours, who being one of the meanest, hauing confuted tenne or twelue of your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pishe treatises, can receiue no replye of any man, but onely of poore Bristowe: to whome in this respecte, I confesse my selfe more beholding, than to all the Papistes beside, sauing that I haue reioyned to him almost two yeares agoe, and yet I heare not of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="41" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 41.</hi> First we are wont to make this offer (as we<note place="margin">The diuerse shifts and flights that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants are driuen vnto by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, as it vvere the iumps and turnings of an hare before the hounds.</note> thinke) most reasonable and indifferent: that forasmuch as the Scriptures are diuersely expounded of vs &amp; of them, they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be tied to our interpretation, nor we to theirs, but to put it to the arbitrement &amp; iudgement of the auncient fathers, of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councels, of vniuersall custome of times and places in the Catholike Church, No, say they, we will be our owne iudges and interpreters, or follow Luther, if we be Lutherans: Caluin, if we be Caluinists: and so forth.</p>
      <div n="41" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 41. For expounding of the Scriptures, we will not refuse the arbitrement and iudgement of the auncient fathers, of generall Councels, of vniuersall cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of times, and places in the Catholike church, for this you say is your offer, which was neuer refused of vs, though you most falsely affirme, that we say we will be our owne iudges, and interpretours, or followe Luther, if we be Lutherans: Caluine, if we be Caluinistes, &amp;c. Who euer sayed so, you shamelesse sclau<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>derer? What haue you differing from vs? Wherein you haue the iudgement of the auncient fathers, of generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, of vniuersall custome, of times and places in the Catholike church? Vnlesse perhappes you meane some wretched sophistrie, by disioyning these that you here seeme to ioyne togither. And if you so doe, we must first aske you, whether you your selues in all exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Scriptures, will stand to the arbitrement of
<pb n="76" facs="41"/>
euerie auncient father, or of euerie generall Councell, or of any custome in any time or place. I knowe and you can not deny it, that you will stande to nothing, that is not allowed by your Pope, though fathers, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, custome, time or place, or all the world be against it, yea the manifest Scripture, which is so plaine that it needeth no exposition: as the commaundement against images in religion. Theodoret, Gelasius, Vigilius, Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome, against transubstantiation, Epiphanius against images, the sixt councell of Constantinople for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the Pope of heresie, the councels of Constance and Basil for deposing the Popes, and decreeing, that the councell is aboue the Pope &amp; many other like mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters beside, in which you goe clearely from the consent of all antiquitie for 600. yeares, as the Bishoppe of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum hath made plaine demonstration, and you are not able to replie.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="42" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 42.</hi> This being of it selfe a shamelesse shift, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse it be better coloured, the next is to say, that the Scriptures are easie and plaine and sufficient of them selues to determine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie matter, and therefore they will be tried by the Scriptures onely. We are content, because they will needes haue it so, and we alleage vnto them the bookes of Tobie, Ecclesiasticus, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees. No, say they: we admit none of these for Scripture. Why so? are they not approued Canonicall by the same authoritie of the Church, of auncient Councels and fathers, that the other bookes are? No matter, say they, Luther admitteth them not, Caluine doth not allow them.</p>
      <div n="42" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 42. That the Scriptures are plaine and easie to be vnderstoode of them that vse the ordinary meanes to come to it, for all doctrine necessarie to be knowen, and sufficient to determine euerie matter, the holie Ghost him selfe doth testifie, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and some of the auncient fathers also doe beare witnesse, as Augustine <hi>de doct. Christ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Chrysost. in Gen. hom.</hi> 13. <hi>de verb. Esai. Vidi d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>minum, &amp;c. hom.</hi> 2.</p>
         <p>If therefore you had the spirite of the auncient
<pb n="77" facs="41"/>
fathers, you would be content to be tryed by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for reuerence you ought to Gods most holye and perfect writings, and not because we will haue it so, who are content in many controuersies to be tryed by the iudgement of the auncient fathers, or general Councels, or vniuersall custom of times and places: and in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies, wherein all the auncient fathers, all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and vniuersall custom of all times and places doe consent▪ if any think such things can be brought against vs, as it is falsly and sophistically bragged. But whereas we refuse the bokes of Tobie, Ecclesiasticus, Machabees, for Canonicall Scripture, it is not (as you say ridiculou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly) because Luther and Caluine admitteth them not, but because they are contrary to the Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and were ne<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>er receiued of the Church of Israel for Canonicall, nor of the Catholike Church of Christ, for more than 400. yeares after Christ, as I haue shewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="43" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 43.</hi> Well, let vs goe forwarde in their owne daunce. You allowe at the least the Iewes Canonicall bookes of the olde Testament, that is, all that are extant in the Hebrewe Bible: and all of the newe Testament without exception. Yea, that we doe. In these bookes then, will you be tried by the vulgar auncient Latine Bible, onely vsed in all the West Church aboue a thousandyeares? No. Will you be tried by the Greeke Bible of the Septuaginta interpreters, so renowmed and authorised, in our Sauiours owne speaches, in the Euangelistes and Apostles writings, in the whole Greeke Church euermore? No, How then will you be tried? They answere, Only by the Hebrue Bible that now is, and as now it is pointed with vowels. Will you so? and do you thinke that only, the true authenticall Hebrue which the holy Ghost did first put into the pennes of those sacred writers? We do thinke it (say they) and esteeme it the only authenticall and true Scripture of the old Testament.</p>
      <div n="43" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 43. Where so many of your owne Popish writers do accuse your vulgar Latine text of innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble corruptions, what reason is there, that we should fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="78" facs="42"/>
that translation onely, especially seeing God hath giuen vs knowledge of the tongues, that we may resort to the fountaines them selues, as S. Augustine exhorteth. As for the Greeke translation of the Septuaginta, from which your owne vulgar Latine varieth, (although we reuerence it for the antiquitie, and vse it for interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of some obscure places in the Hebrew) why should you require vs to be tried thereby, which will not be tried by it your selues? If I were as captious as you are with Iohn Keltrige, about the Greeke Bible of the Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaginta Interpreters, I might make sporte with you, as you doe with him: but I acknowledge your <hi>Syn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cdoche,</hi> that you meane the olde Testament onely, whereas the word Bible, is commonly taken for both. But to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, we acknowledge the text of the olde Testament, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>n Hebrew and Chaldee, for in the Chaldee tongue were some partes of it written, as it is now printed with vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, to be the onely fountaine, out of which we muste draw the pure truth of the Scriptures for the olde Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, adioyning herewith, the testimonie of the Mazzo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, where any diuersitie of pointes, letters, or wordes, is noted to haue bene in sundry auncient copies, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne that which is proper to the whole context, from that which by errour of the writers, or printers, hath bene brought into any copie, olde or newe.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="44" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MATT. 44.</hi> We aske them againe, what say you then to<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note> that place of the Psalme, where in the Hebrue it is thus, <hi>As a lion my handes and my feete:</hi> for that which in truth should be thus, <hi>They digged</hi> or <hi>pearced my hands and my feete:</hi> being an euident prophecie of Christes nailing to the crosse. There in deede (say they) we followe not the Hebrue, but the Greeke text. Sometime then you follow the Greeke and not the Hebrue onely. And what if the same Greeke text make for the Catholikes, as in these places for example, <hi>I haue inclined my hart to keepe thy iustifications for reward:</hi> and, <hi>Redeeme thy sins with almes:</hi> might we not obtaine here the like fauour at your handes for the Greeke texte, specially when the Hebrue
<pb n="79" facs="42"/>
doth not disagree? No, say they, nor in no other place where the Greeke is neuer so plaine, if the Hebrue worde at the least may be any otherwise interpreted, &amp; drawen to an other significatiō.</p>
      <div n="44" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 44. We say to you first, that you haue falsely pointed the Hebrue word in the margēt for all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bookes that euer I haue seene, as Bomberge both in <hi>folio,</hi> and <hi>quarto,</hi> Stephanus, Basil, Plantine, Arias Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus, Cōplutensis, al place <hi>Camets</hi> vnder <hi>Caph,</hi> where you make <hi>Patach.</hi> But perhaps your Hebrue is most out of Mūsters Dictionarie, where it is pointed as you make it. But for answere to your question, we say, that their is a double testimonie of the Mazzorites to proue, that in the most auncient and best corrected copies, the Hebrue was <hi>Caru,</hi> they haue digged or pearced: this is testified not onely by our translators, but also by Ioannes Isaac your owne Rabbin, against Lindanus a prelate of yours. And this the auctors of the Complutense edition, doe acknowledge, for thus they haue pointed it <hi>Caru,</hi> where<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note> is nothing but the redundans of <hi>Aleph</hi> (whiche is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood in euery <hi>Camets</hi>) differing from the vsuall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and declining of the Verbe <hi>Carah,</hi> that signifieth<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note> to pearce or digge. Againe, where it is redde other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, if it be rightly pointed, as it is in Arias Montanus <hi>Caari,</hi> it cannot signifie <hi>Sicut leo,</hi> as a lion, as both the<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note> Mazzorites do teach, and Iohannes Isaac a Grammarian out of thē by the points, &amp; the note ouer <hi>iod</hi> doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonstrate. For what should <hi>shure<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h</hi> sound in <hi>iod?</hi> or if you would contend it should be <hi>Daghes,</hi> to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose should it be in <hi>iod,</hi> if the worde should signifie as a lion? Therefore howsoeuer this varietie of copies came either by negligence of some writers, or by corruption of the Iewes, wee haue sufficient warrant for the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and true reading, whiche the Greeke translator did followe, whiche also was in S. Hieromes copie, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise hee woulde not haue translated out of the Hebrue <hi>Fixerunt:</hi> they haue pearced. Therefore Rabbi Ioseph, which made the Chalde<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Paraphrase vpon the Psalter,
<pb n="80" facs="43"/>
laboured to expresse both the copies, as well that which hath plainely (they haue pearced,) as that whiche hath it corruptly, as though it spake of a Lion, and yet can not rightly be so translated, because the points are imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect euen for that reading. Therefore he hath saide <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kethin</hi>
            <note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note>
            <hi>Heich Cheariah,</hi> They haue indented and pearced like a lion my handes and my feete▪ as it is in the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice print of Daniel Bomberg, although <hi>Arias Montanus</hi> in his Bible, haue no more but <hi>Nachethin,</hi> which he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slateth,<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note> biting my handes and my feete. I haue played the foole to vtter these matters in the mother tongue to ignorant men, that can make no triall of them, but you haue not only giuen me example, but also enforced me with your vnsoluble question (as you thought) by one word somewhat out of frame, to ouerthrow the whole Hebrue text. But you are to be pardoned, for that you follow your M. Lindanus herein, who hath nothing else in effect to quarrel against the Hebrue text, but this: &amp; therfore he repeteth it in many places, to make greater shew of it as you doe. In other, places where the Hebrue worde hath diuerse significations, who shall forbid vs to chuse that which is most agreeable to the circumstance of the text, and to the analogie or rule of faith?</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="45" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 45.</hi> We replie againe and say vnto them, why, Is not the credit of those Septuaginta interpreters, who them selues were Iewes, and best learned in their owne tongue, and (as S. Augustine often, and other auncient fathers say) were inspired with the holy Ghost, in translating the Hebrue Bible into Greeke: Is not their credit (I say) in determining and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining the signification of the Hebrue worde, farre greater than yours? No. Is not the authoritie of all the auncient fathers both Greeke and Latine, that followed them, equiualent in this case to your iudgement? No, say they, but because we finde some ambiguitie in the Hebrue, we will take the aduantage, and we will determine and limit it to our purpose.</p>
      <div n="45" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 45. S. Hieronym aboundantly aunswereth this cauill, denying that supposed inspiration, and de<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="81" facs="43"/>
the fable of their 70. celles, which yet pleased Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine greately, yea calling in question, whether anye more were translated by them, than the fiue bookes of<note place="margin">Praefat. in pent.</note> Moses: because Aristaeus, a writer in Ptolomees time, and after him, Iosephus, make mention of no more. The same cause therfore that moued S. Hierome to translate out of the Hebrewe, mooueth vs: whose translation, if we had it sounde ande perfect, might much further vs for the same purpose. Althoughe for the signification of the Hebrewe wordes, we require no more credite, than that which al they that be learned in the Hebrewe tongue, must be forced to yeelde vnto vs. And seeing your vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare Latine departeth from the Septuagintaes interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, euen in the bookes of Moses, whiche (if anie bee theirs) may most rightly be accounted theirs, because it is certaine they translated them, although it be not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine whether they translated the rest: with what equity do you require vs to credite them, which your owne vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare translation, affirmeth to haue translated amisse? as I haue shewed before in the example of Canans genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. An other example you haue in the 4 of Genesis, <hi>Nonne si bene egeris recipies, &amp;c.</hi> If thou shalt do wel shalt thou not receiue? but if thou shalt doe euill, straighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy sinnes shall be present in the doores. The greke texte, hath <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not if thou haste rightly offered: but thou hast not rightly diuided: hast thou sinned? be stil. Where your translation commeth muche nearer to the Hebrue, as might be shewed in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie many examples. As for the auncient fathers credit of the greeke Church, and the Latine that folowed them, if our iudgement alone be not aequiualent vnto them, yet let these auncient fathers, Origene, and Hierome, that thought them not sufficient to be followed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gathered or framed other interpretations, let theyr iudgement, I say, ioining with ours, discharge vs of this fonde and enuious accusation.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="46" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 46.</hi> Againe, we condiscend to their wilfulnes, and
<pb n="82" facs="44"/>
say: what if the Hebrewe be not ambiguous, but so plaine and<note place="margin">Psalm. 15.</note> certaine to signifie one thing, that it can not bee plainer? As,<note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </note>
         <hi>Thou shalt not leaue my soule in Hel,</hi> whiche prooueth for vs, that Christ in soule descended into Hell. Is not the one He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewe worde as proper for soule, as <hi>anima</hi> in Latine, the other, as proper and vsual for hel, as <hi>infernus</hi> in Latine. Heere then at the least wil you yeeld? No, say they, not here neither. for Beza telleth vs, that the word, which commonly and vsually signifieth, <hi>soule,</hi> yet for a purpose, if a man wil straine, it may signifie, not onely <hi>bodie,</hi> but also, <hi>carcase.</hi> and so he translateth it. But Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za (say we) being admonished by his friendes, corrected it in his later edition. Yea, say they, he was content to change his tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation, but not his opinion concerning the Hebrewe worde, as himselfe protesteth.</p>
      <div n="46" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 46. You haue chosen a text for example, wherein is least colour (except it bee with the vnlearned) of an hundred. For, whereas you aske, whether <hi>Nephesh,</hi> be no not as proper for soule, as <hi>anima,</hi> in Latin, &amp; <hi>Sheol</hi> for Hel, as <hi>infernus</hi> in Latine? I vtterly deny both the one and the other. For <hi>nephesh</hi> is properly the life, and <hi>Sheol,</hi> the graue or pit, though it may sometimes be taken for Hel, which is a consequent of the death of the vngodly, as <hi>nephesh</hi> is taken for person, or ones selfe, or as it is sometimes, for a dead carcase. Yea, there be that hold, that it is neuer taken for the reasonable immortall soule of a man, as <hi>anima</hi> is, specially of Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call writers. That Beza translated the Greeke of the newe Testament after the signification of the Hebrewe wordes, althoughe it was true in sense, yet in mine opinion, it was not proper in wordes: and therefore he himselfe hath corrected it in his latter editions, as you confesse, hee hathe not chaunged hys opinion concerning the Hebrewe: the reason is, because it is grounded vppon manifest textes of Scripture, whiche hee citeth, Leuit. 19. verse. 27. &amp; cap. 21. verse. 1. and 11. Num. 5. verse 2. and 9. verse 10. In the firste place your owne vulgare Latine translation, for <hi>la nephesh</hi> turneth
<pb n="83" facs="44"/>
            <hi>mortuo.</hi> you shall not cut your flesh for one that is dead. In the second place, your vulgare Latine hathe, <hi>Ne non contaminetur sacerdos in mortibus.</hi> and, <hi>Ad omnem mortuum non ingredietur omnino.</hi> Lette not the Priest bee defiled with the deathes of his countreymen. and, The highe Priest shall not enter into any dead bodie at all: where the Hebrue is <hi>lenephesh.</hi> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note> In the thirde place your vulgare Latine readeth <hi>pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius{que} est super mortuo.</hi> they shall caste out him that is pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted by touching a dead carcase, where the Hebrewe is <hi>lanephesh</hi> In the first place, your vulgare Latine hathe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dede, <hi>anima,</hi> but in the same sense, that it had before <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuo</hi> for the text is of him that is vncleane, by touching a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dead bodie, which in Hebrue is <hi>nephesh.</hi> How say you nowe, is the Hebrewe worde as proper for soule, as <hi>ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> in Latine? except you wil say, the Latine worde <hi>ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> dothe properly signifie, a dead bodie: hathe not Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za good reason to retaine his opinion concerning the Hebrewe worde, when hee hathe the authoritie of youre owne vulgare translation? You that note such iumps, and shiftes in vs, whether wil you leape to saue your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie? will you saye, the Hebrewe texte is corrupted since your translation was drawen out of it. The seauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie interpretours then will crie out againste you: for they with one mouth in all these places, for the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewe worde <hi>nephesh,</hi> render the vsuall signification <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, adding in the 21. of Leuit. v. 11. <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, which either you muste translate, a deade bodie, or you shall call it absurdly, a dead soule. Woulde any man think to haue founde in you, eyther suche grosse ignoraunce, or shamefull negligence, or intollerable malice against the trueth, that Beza sending you to the places, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you woulde not, or you coulde not examine them, or, if you dydde examine them, that you woulde notwythstanding thus malitiouslye agaynste youre owne knowledge and conscience, raile against him? you make vs to saye, if a manne will straine
<pb n="84" facs="45"/>
the worde, it may signifie not onely bodie, but also car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>case. What saye you? did Moses straine the worde to that signification? You saide beefore, that wee were at the iumps and turnings of an hare beefore the houndes, suche mightie hunters you are, and wee suche fearefull hares before you. I am not skilful in the termes of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but in plaine Englishe I wil speake it, that if al the traiterous wolues and foxes, that bee in the kennell at Rhemes, woulde doe their beste, to saue your credit in this section, nay in this whole preface, they shall neuer be able to maintaine their owne, with anye indifferent reader.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="47" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 47.</hi> Wel then doth it like you to reade thus, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Bezaes translation, <hi>Thou shalt not leaue my car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casse in the graue?</hi> No, we are content to alter the word carcas, (which is not a seemely word for our sauiors bodie) and yet wee are loath to say soule, but if we might, we would say rather, <hi>life, person,</hi> as appeareth in the margent of our Bibles. but as for the Hebrue word that signifieth Hel, though the Greke &amp; Latin Bible throughout, the Greke and Latin fathers in al theyr wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, as occasion serueth, doe so reade it and vnderstande it, yet wil we neuer so translate it: but for <hi>Hel,</hi> we wil say <hi>graue,</hi> in al such places of scripture, as might infer <hi>Limbus patrum,</hi> if we shoulde translate, <hi>Hel.</hi> These are their shifies, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and windings, in the olde Testament.</p>
      <div n="47" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 47. I haue shewed you before, that in the newe Testament, we like better to translate according to the proper and vsual signification of the Greke word. But the Hebrewe worde in the olde Testament may bee translated according to the circumstaunce of the place, life, person, selfe, yea, or dead bodie, and in some place perhaps carcase. You folow vs very neare▪ to seeke aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the English worde carcase, which commonly is taken in contempt, &amp; therfore we would not vse it, spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the bodie of our Sauiour Christe, when it was dead. But you hunt your selfe out of breath, when you woulde bring the same contempt to the Latine worde
<pb n="85" facs="45"/>
            <hi>Cadauer,</hi> which Beza vsed. For <hi>Cadauer</hi> signifieth general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a dead bodie of man or beast, and by your vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine translator, is vsed for the dead bodies of sacrifices, of<note place="margin">Cadauer.</note> Saincts, and holy men, as indifferently, as for carion of beastes, or carcases of euill men. Namely in Iob. 39. v 33.<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note> wheresoeuer the dead body is, thether will the Eagle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort, which similitude our Sauiour Christe applieth to him selfe, Math. 24. v. 28. wheresoeuer the dead bodie is, thether wil the Eagles be gathered, where he compareth him selfe to the dead body, and the faithfull to the Egles.</p>
         <p>Now concerning the other Hebrue worde, which you say signifieth hell, because the Greeke, and vulgar Latine interpretor do so translate it. When iust occasion shal be giuen afterwarde <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. I will shew that it properly sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a graue, pit, or place for dead bodies, and that in this place of the 16. Psalme, it muste needes so signifie, not onely the later part of the verse, expressing in other wordes that which was saide in the former: but also the Apostles prouing out of it the resurrection of Christe, doe sufficiently declare. If you haue no place therefore in the Scriptures, to proue your <hi>Limbus patrum,</hi> but where the holy Ghost speaketh of the death and buriall of the fathers, no maruaile though you must straine the Hebrue worde, which properly signifieth graue, and the Greeke worde, which properly signifieth a darke place, and especially the Latine, whiche signifieth generally a lowe place: none of all the three wordes signifying hel, as wee commonly vnderstande the worde hell, properly and onely, but by a figure where mention is made of the death of the vngodly, whose rewarde is in hell. These be the poore shiftes, turninges and windings that you haue to wreath in those fables of <hi>Limbus patrum,</hi> &amp; Purgatorie, which the Church of God, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the worlde vnto the comming of Christ, neuer heard of, nor many hundreth yeares after Christe, vntill the Mōtanists, or such like hethenish heretikes brought in those fantasies.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="48" type="Martins_comments">
      <pb n="86" facs="46"/>
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 48.</hi> In the newe Testament, wee aske them will you be tried by the auncient Latine translation, which is the texte of the fathers and the whole Churche? No, but wee appeale to the Greeke. What Greeke, say wee, for there bee sundrie copies, and the beste of them (as Beza confesseth) agree with the saide auncient Latine. For example in Saint Peters wordes, <hi>Labour that by good workes you may<note place="margin">2. Pet. ca. 1.</note> make sure your vocation and election.</hi> Duth this Greeke copie please you? No, say they: wee appeale to tha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Greeke copie, which hath not those wordes, <hi>by good workes,</hi> for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise wee shoulde graunt the merite and efficacie of good workes towarde saluation. And generally to tell you at once, by what Greeke we will be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ried, we like best the vulgar Greeke texte of the new Testament, which is most common and in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans handes.</p>
      <div n="48" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 48. Wee neede not appeale to the Greeke; for any thing you bring out of the vulgar Latine against vs. As for that text, 2. Pet. 1. Labour that by good works, &amp;c. I haue answeared before in the 36. <hi>Section.</hi> Wee like well the Latine, or that Greeke copie which hath those wordes by good workes, for we must needes vnderstand them, where they are not expressed: and therefore you do impudētly beelie vs to say they do not please vs. <q>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin vpon that text saith, <hi>Nonnulli codices habent bonis ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, sed hoc de sensu nihil mutat, quia subaudiendum est e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiā si non exprimatur.</hi> Some bookes haue By good works, but this chaungeth nothing of the sense, for that must be vnderstoode although it be not expressed.</q> The same thing in effect saith Beza: that our election, and voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion must be confirmed by the effects of faith, that is by the fruites of iustice, &amp;c. therefore in some copies wee finde it added by good workes. So farre of is it, that Beza misliketh those wordes, that hee citeth them to proue the perpetuall connection of Election, Vocation, Iustification, and Sanctification. This is therefore as wicked a slaunder of vs, as it is an vntrue affirmation of the vulgar Latine, that it is the texte of the fathers, and
<pb n="87" facs="46"/>
the whole Churche: whereby you shewe your selfe to be a Donatiste, to acknowledge no Churche, but where the Latine texte is occupied. So that in Greece, Syria, Armenia, Aethiopia, and other partes of the worlde, where the Latine texte is not knowen, or vnderstood, there Christ hath no Churche by your vnaduised asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That we like best the most common Greeke text, I am sure that we doe it, by as good reason, if not by bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than you in so great diuersities of the Latine texte, who like best of that which is most common, and in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans handes.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="49" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 49.</hi> Well, say we, if you will needes haue it so, take your pleasure in choosing your text. And if you will stande to it, graunt vs that Peter was chiefe among the Apostles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause your owne Greeke text saith, <hi>The first, Peter.</hi> No, saith<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> Beza: we will graunt you no such thing, for these wordes were added to the Greeke text by one that fauoured Peters primacie. Is it so? then you will not stande to this Greeke texte neither. Not in this place, saith Beza.</p>
      <div n="49" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 49. In graunting Peter to be the firste, wee neede not graunt him to be the chiefe, and if we graunt him to be the chiefe, it followeth not that he is chiefe in auctoritie. But if that were graunted, it is not necessarie that he was head of the Church. And albeit that were also graunted, the Bishop of Rome could gaine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by it. But what saith Beza, where the texte saith, the firste Peter? If wee muste beleeue you, hee saith, <hi>No, wee will graunt you no suche thing, for these wordes were added to the Greeke texte by one that fauoured Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters primacie.</hi> I praye you Martin where hath Beza those wordes? will you neuer leaue this shamefull for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie? Beza in the tenth of Mathew doth only aske the question. <hi>Quid si hoc vocabulum, &amp;c.</hi> what if this worde were added, by some that would establish the Primacie of Peter? for nothing followeth that may agree with it. This asketh Beza but as an obiectiō, which immediatly after he answeareth, &amp; concludeth that it is no addition,
<pb n="88" facs="47"/>
but a naturall word of the text, found in all copies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed by Theophylact an enimie of the Popes primacie, and defendeth it in the third of Marke, where it is not in the common Greeke copies nor in the vulgar Latine, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Erasmus, who finding it in some Greeke copies, thought it was vntruely added out of Mathew. But Beza saith: <hi>Ego verò non dubito quin haec sit germana lectio.</hi> But I doubte not but this is the true and right reading of the texte: and therefore hee translateth <hi>Prim<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> the firste Simon, out of the fewe copies Erasmus speaketh of. Therefore it is an abhominable slaunder to charge him with following the common receyued texte where it seemeth to make against you when hee contendeth for the truth against the common text, yea and against your owne vulgar Latine, to giue you that which you make so great accompte of, that Peter in the Cataloge of the Apostles was firste. So greatly hee feareth to acknowledge that Peter was called first. And so true it is that you charge him to say. <hi>No, wee will graunt you no such thing, for these wordes were added to the Greeke texte by one that fauoured Peters primacie.</hi> I hope your favourers seeing your forgerie thus manifestly discouered, will giue you lesse credite in other your shamelesse slaunders, at the leastwise this in equitie. I trust all Papistes will graunt, not to beeleue your report against any mans writing, except they reade it thōselues. Now <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>at this worde, (the first) argueth no primacie, or superioritie, beside those places quoted by Beza, Act. 26. 20. Rom. 1, 8. &amp; 3, 2. You may read 1. <hi>Par. v▪</hi> 23 <hi>&amp;</hi> 24. where the posteritie of Leui and Aaron are rehearsed as they were appointed by Dauid in their orders, or courses. <hi>Subuel primus, Rohobia primus, sors prima Ioiarib, &amp;c.</hi> where least you should thinke of any headship, or principalitie, because the Hebrue is somtime <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, &amp; the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, you may see, that <hi>Subuel is</hi> called <hi>primus</hi> of the sonnes of Gerson, when there is no more mentioned, &amp; more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly, <hi>Rohobia</hi> is called <hi>primus</hi> of the sonnes, of Eleazer,
<pb n="89" facs="47"/>
of whome it is sayd, that he had no more sonnes, &amp; that <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> signifieth here, the first in order, it appeareth by those generations, where the second, third, or fourth, is named, as in the sonnes of Hebron, and of Oziel. Also in the sonnes of Semei, where Iehoth is counted the first, Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za the second: Iaus and Beria, becaused they increase not in sonnes, were accounted for one familie. In all which, there is no other primacy, than in the first lot of Ioiarib, where the Hebrew worde <hi>is harishuon,</hi> and so follow the<note place="margin">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </note> rest<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>n order, vnto foure and twenty courses. Therefore there is no cause why we should not stand to the Greeke text, in that place, neither did Beza euer deny to stande to it.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="50" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 50.</hi> Let vs see an other place. You must graunt vs (saywe) by this Greeke text, that Christes very bloud which was shed for vs, is really in the chalice, because S. Luke sayth so in the Greeke text. No, sayth Beza, those Greeke wordes came out of the margem into the text, and therefore I translate not according to them, but according to that which I thinke the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Greeke text, although I finde it in no copies in the world, and this his doing <note n="*" place="margin">See chap. 1. num 37. chap. 17. num. 11.</note> is maintained &amp; iustified by our English Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, in their writings of late.</p>
      <div n="50" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 50. Still Beza speaketh, as you inspire into him, while he speaketh through your throte, or quil. The truth is, Beza sayth, that either there is a manifest Soloe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophanes, that is an appearance of incongruitie, or els those wordes (which is shed for you) seeme to be added out of S. Mathew, or els it is an errour of the writers, placing that in the nominatiue case, which should be in the datiue. For in the datiue case did Basil read them in his morals, 21. definition.</p>
         <p>Neuertheles, all our olde bookes (sayth Beza) had it so written, as it is commonly printed in the nominatiue case. Here are three seuerall disiunctions, yet can you finde none, but one proposition that you set downe, as though it were purely and absolutely affirmed by Beza. Likewise, where you speake of no copies in the world,
<pb n="90" facs="48"/>
you say more than Beza, who speaketh but of such co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies as he had, who, if he were of no better conscience, than you would haue him seeme to be, might faine some copie in his owne handes, to salue the matter. But the truth is, that since he wrote this, he found one more auncient copie, both in Greeke, and Latine, which nowe is at Cambridge, where this whole verse is wanting. But of this matter, which somewhat concerneth my selfe particularly, I shall haue better occasion to write in the places by you quoted, cap. 1. num. 37. and cap. 17. num. 11. where I will so iustifie that which I haue written before, touching this place, as I trust all learned and indifferent Readers, shall see how vainely you insult against me, where you bewray grosser ignorance in Greeke phrases, than euer I woulde haue suspected in you, being accounted the principall Linguist of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie at Rhemes.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="51" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 51.</hi> Well yet, sayewe, there are places in the same Greeke text, as plaine for vs as these now cited, where you can not say, it came out of the margent, or, it was added falsely to the text. A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, <hi>Stand and hold fast the traditions, &amp;c.</hi> by this<note place="margin">2. Thess. 2.</note> text we require that you graunt vs traditions deliuered by word of mouth, as wel as the written word, that is, the Scriptures. No, say they, we know the Greeke word signifieth tradition, as plaine as possibly, but here and in the like places, we rather translate it, <hi>ordinances, instructions,</hi> and what els soeuer. Nay Sirs, say we, you can not so answer the matter, for in other places, you translate it duely, and truely, <hi>tradition:</hi> and why more in one place, than in another? They are ashamed to tell why, but they must tell, and shame both thom selues, and the deuill, if euer they thinke it good to answer this treatise, as also why they chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>congregation,</hi> which was alwaies in their first translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, into <hi>Church,</hi> in their later translations, and did not change likewise <hi>ordinances,</hi> into <hi>traditions, Elder<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> into <hi>Priestes.</hi>
      </p>
      <div n="51" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 51. That the Thessalonians had some parte of Christian doctrine, deliuered by word of mouth, that is, by the Apostles preaching, at such time as he did write
<pb n="91" facs="48"/>
vnto them, and some part by his Epistles, the text enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth vs to graunt, and we neuer purposed to denye: But that the Church at this daye, or euer since the newe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament was written, had any tradition by worde of mouth, of any matter necessary to saluation, which was not contayned in the olde or newe Testament, we will neuer graunt, neither shall you euer be able out of this text, or any text in the Bible to proue. Make your Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logismes, when you dare, and you shall be aunswered. But we knowe (you saye) that the Greeke word signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, tradition, as plaine as possibly, but here, and in like places, we rather translate it, ordinances, instructions, and what else soeuer. We knowe that it signifieth tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, constitution, instruction, precept, also mancipation, treatise, treason.</p>
         <p>For al these the Greeke Dictionaries do teach, that it signifieth. Therefore if in any place we haue translated it ordinaunces, or instructions, or institutions, we haue not gone from the true signification of the worde, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can you euer proue, that the worde signifieth such a doctrine onely, as is taught by worde of mouth, and is not, or may not be put in writing. But in other places you can tell vs, that we translate it duely and truly, tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and you will know, why more in one place, than in another, affirming that we are shamed to tell why. For my part, I was neuer of counsaile with any that transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Scriptures into English, and therefore it is pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, I can not sufficiently expresse what reason moued the translators so to varie in the exposition of one and the same worde. Yet can I yeelde sufficient reason, that might leade them so to doe, which I thinke they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. The Papistes doe commonly so abuse the name of tradition, which signifieth properly a deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, or a thinge deliuered, for such a matter as is deliuered onely by worde of mouth, and so recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from hande to hande, that it is neuer put in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but hath his credite without the holye Scriptures
<pb n="92" facs="49"/>
of God, as the Iewe had their Cabala, and the Scribes &amp; Pharisees had their traditions beside the lawe of God,<note place="margin">
               <hi>Irenaeus, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> and the Valentinian Heretikes accused the Scriptures, as insufficient of authoritie, and ambiguously written, and that the truth could not be found in them by those that knewe not the tradition, which was not deliuered by writing, but by worde of mouth, iumpe as the Papists doe. This abusing of the word, tradition, might be a sufficient cause for the translators, to render the Greeke worde, where it is taken for such doctrine as is beside the commaundement of God, by the name of traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the worde is commonly taken. But where the Greeke worde is taken in the good parte, for that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which is agreeable with the holy Scriptures, they might with good reason auoide it, as you your selfe doe not alwayes translate <hi>tradere,</hi> to betray, but sometimes to deliuer. So did the translators giue these words, ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, instructions, institutions, or doctrine deliuered, which doe generally signifie the same that tradition, but haue not the preiudice of that partiall signification, in which the Papistes vse it, who wheresoeuer they find tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, straight way imagine they haue found a sufficient argument, against the perfection and sufficiencie of the holy Scripture, and to bring in all riffe raffe, and trishe trashe, of mans doctrine, not onely beside, but also con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye to the manifest worde of God, conteined in his most holy and perfect Scriptures. To the shame of the deuill therefore, and of all popish maintainers of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions vncommaunded by God, this reason may be yelded.</p>
         <p>Nowe to aunswer you why <hi>Ecclesia</hi> was first transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted congregation, and afterward Church: the reason that moued the firste translators (I thinke) was this: the worde Churche of the common people, at that tyme, was vsed ambiguously, both for the assemblie of the faythfull, and for the place in which they as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled: for auoyding of which ambiguitie, they
<pb n="93" facs="49"/>
translated <hi>Ecclesia</hi> the congregation, and yet in their Creede, and in the notes of their Bibles, in preaching, &amp; writing they vsed the word Church for the same, the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter translators seing the people better instructed, &amp; able to discerne when they read in the Scriptures, the people, from the place of their meeting, vsed the worde Church in their translations, as they did in their preaching. These are weightie matters that wee muste giue accompt of them▪ Why we chaunge not ordinances into traditions, and Elders into Priests, wee will answere when we come to the proper places of them. In the meane season wee thinke there is as good cause for vs in translating, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to auoide the termes of traditions and prieste, as for you to auoid the names of Elders calling them aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, and the wise men sages, as though you had rather speake French, than English as we do. Like as you tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate <hi>Conside.</hi> haue a good hart after the french phrase, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than you would say as we do, be of good comforte.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="52" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 52.</hi> The cause is, that the name of Church was at the first odious vnto thē, because of the Catholike Church which stoode against them: but afterward this name▪ grewe into more favour with them, because of their English Church, so at length called and termed. But their hatred of Priests and traditions continueth still, as it first began, and therefore their translation also remaineth as before, suppressing the names both of the one and of the other. But of all these their dealings, they shal be told in their seuerall chapiters and places.</p>
      <div n="52" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 52. I pray you, who translated first the creed into the English tongue, and taught it to the people▪ &amp; for that cause were accounted heretikes of the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Romish rable? If the name of Churche were odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto them, why didde they not suppresse that name in the creede, whyche they taught to yong and olde, and in steede of Catholike Church, call it the vniuersal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation or assembly? Wel Dauus, these things be not aptely diuided according to their times. The firste tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation of the Bible that was printed in the english tong,
<pb n="94" facs="50"/>
in very many places of the notes, vseth the name Church, &amp; most notoriously in the song of Salomon, where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery other verse almost it telleth which is the voice of the Church to Christ her spous<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>▪ which no reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man would thinke the translators would haue done, if the name of the Church had bene odious vnto them, or that they thought the Catholike church stood against thē. Looke Thomas Mathewes Bible, in the Canticles of Salomon, &amp; vpon the 16. of S. Mathewes Gospell, the 18. verse, the wordes of Christ to Peter. Therfore your sense<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les imaginations, shewe no hatred of the Catholike Church in our translators, but cancred malice, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent follie in your selues.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div n="53" type="Martins_comments">
      <p>
         <hi>MART. 53.</hi> To conclude, as I began, concerning their shiftes, and iumpes, and windings, and turnings euery way, from one thing to an other, till they are driuen to the extreme refuge of palpable corruptions, and false translations: consider with me in this one case onely of traditions, as may be likewise considered in all other controuersies, that the auncient fathers, councels, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, vniuersalitie, and custom of the whole Church allowe traditions: the Canonicall Scriptures haue them, the Latine text hath them, the Greeke text hath them: onely their transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue them not. Likewise in the olde Testament, the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Latine text hath such and such speeches, that make for vs, the renowmed Greeke text hath it, the Hebrewe text hath it: onely their translations haue it not.</p>
      <p>These are the translations which we call heretical and wilful, and which shal be examined and discussed in this Booke.</p>
      <div n="53" type="Fulkes_response">
         <p>FVLK. 53. By what windings and turnings I pray you are we driuen to that miserable refuge of palpable cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and false translations? for hitherto you haue shewed none, but such as shewe your owne ignoraunce, or malice. Neither (I hope) you shal be able to shewe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, though you sweat neuer so sore at your work. Yes, I weene, this one case only of traditions, for so you seeme to say, if it be considered, wil discouer no lesse. It is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, if for your sake, al the Greeke Dictionaries in the
<pb n="95" facs="50"/>
world must not be corrected, &amp; taught to say, that <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> cā signifie nothing but a tradition, that is not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. But yet you rolle in your accustomed rhetorike, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the antiēt fathers, coūcels, antiquitie, vniuersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, &amp; custome of the whole Church allow traditiōs, &amp; so do we, so many as be good &amp; agreeable to the holie scripturs, but that there be traditiōs of matter necessarie to saluatiō▪ not contained in the holie scripturs, whē you bring your fathers, Councels, &amp;c. you shal receiue an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere to them. That the canonical scripture alloweth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny traditions contrary to the doctrine therof, or to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply any want or imperfection therof, as though al things required to make the man of God perfecte, prepared to all good workes, were not conteyned in the Scriptures, you shall neuer be able to proue, although for spite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the perfection of the Canonicall Scripture, you should braste a sunder, as Iudas did, which betrayed the auctor of the Scripture. Finally, what so euer you say out of the old Testament, without proofe or shew of proofe, it is as easily denied by vs, as it is affirmed by you. When you bring but only a shadow of reason, it shall sone be chased away, with the light of truth.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>