<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102863_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08119</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18480</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102863</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Norfolkes furies, or a view of Ketts campe : necessary for the malecontents of our time, for their instruction, or terror; and profitable for euery good subiect, to incourage him vpon the vndoubted hope of the victorie, to stand faithfully to maintayne his prince and countrey, his wife and children, goods, and inheritance. With a table of the maiors and sheriffes of this worshipfull city of Norwich, euer since the first grant by Henry the fourth: together with the bishops of that see, and other accidents here. Set forth first in Latin by Alexander Nevil. Translated into English, for the vse of the common people, by R.W. minister at Frettenham in Norfolke, and a citizen borne, who beheld part of these things with his yong eyes</title>
                 <author>Neville, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, hauing read ouer this Treatise with great pleasure, and not a little profit: both in regard of the matter, and elegancie of the stile (in respect whereof, in my simple iudgement, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath deserued great commendation) I wished with many other, that some man would take the paines to translate the same into our Mother Tongue: that the thing which concerned so many, might be knowne of all. But seeing hitherto no man hath vndertaken the Worke: especially being now<note place="margin">This was transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeeres since.</note> twentie yeares olde, since the first setting it forth in Latine by the Author: fearing also le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t the matter might be buried vnder ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ion in the ages to come, I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e ventured vpon the labour my selfe, and by the goodnesse of God haue finished the same for thy benefit. Wherein I haue omitted nothing (to my remembrance) but deliuered truly as I receiued it from the Author, neyther haue I, in my simple iudgement, altered the sence, though through the daintinesse of the Phrase, not fitting our English Tongue: I haue sometime (and that very seldome) altered his wordes, as the Learned can beare me record. Wherfore I beseech thee (cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader) accept of my poore labour: and let not Dame Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, nor Idle Enuie, offer me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that discourtisie, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arpe at my trauaile, while I meane well to all, and meddle but with the refuse of other men. The Worke is worthie the looking vpon, and especially in these dayes, when the like is wished of many, and looked for of some. For who can be ignorant of the malice of the enemies of the grace of God against vs, hauing knowne their se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erall attempts for our destruction in the dayes of our late Soueraigne of blessed Memory, and seene, and heard of the continuance therof, (no lesse cruell) since his Maiesties comming to the Crowne? wherof their Powder Plot (a thing m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st immane, and barbarous with manie practices besides) is sufficient witnesse, and testifieth their malice to be implacable (as
<pb facs="4"/>
those that had sworne against <hi>Paul,</hi> neuer to eate nor drinke, till they<note place="margin">Act. 23. 12.</note> had s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aine him) whose hope lieth not so much in their owne prouision, as in the intertainment, and helpe they looke for amongst vs: which was the cause that sometime they attempted so farre vpon our Coasts, as was made knowne vnto vs by Proclamation, in the dayes of our late Queene, and the like by his Maiestie (that now swayeth the Scepter) since. To the which end, a number of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esuites at that time were dispatched into the Land, and at this day, vnder his Maiestie haue beene, and are still creeping, and croking in corners like the Frogges of Egypt: that perswading his Maiesties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to defend their Catholike Religion, they may be readie to stirre vp Ciu ill Dissention at home, or else prepare themselues to ioyne with Forraine Forces, if at any time (which God forbid) they shall in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ade the Land. Both which are most dangerous, and bring (as our Sauiour Christ saith) ruine, and destruction to Kingdomes or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Moreouer it is a thing against Nature: for Dogges of the same Kennell seldome fight together, except at meate: seruants of the same Family commonly make a side. <hi>Abraham</hi> vsed it for a great reason to <hi>Lot, Let there be no strife I pray thee, betweene<note place="margin">Gen. 13. 8. Exod. 2. 13 Act. 7. 23.</note> thee, and mee; neyther betweene thy Heardsmen, and mine: for we are brethren.</hi> And <hi>Moses</hi> would haue pacified the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter betweene the two Hebrewes contending together, because they were brethren: that is, both Iewes, and Countriemen▪ Wherefore you my brethren of the Ministerie, let vs not weaken our selues, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our selues, while we bitterly contend about matters of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstance, but let the rule of the Apostle take place among vs. <hi>Let not him that eateth, despise him that eateth not, and let not him<note place="margin">Rom. 14. 3.</note> which eateth not, iudge him that eateth; for the Kingdome of God standeth not in these things.</hi> If any man thinke otherwise, God shall reucale it vnto him: but let vs ioyne together in loue. <hi>Vis vnita fortior.</hi> And let the earnest suit of the Apostle be heard, and preuaile with vs, that <hi>nothing bee done of contention or of<note place="margin">Phil. 2. 2.</note> vaine glotie: but follow the truth in loue. If any man list to be contentious, we haue no such custome, neyther the Churches<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>.</note> of God.</hi> Let not the vniust challenge of the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pists be found true among vs, at the last: that we agree not among our selues (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though of all men they might w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rst haue said it, that haue so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sects among them) for how shall wee draw the people to vnitie,
<pb facs="4"/>
while our selues or at oddes, and one brother smiteth another?</p>
   <p>Againe, you my Countrymen, and naturall borne English Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, be not deceiued by the subtiltie of Popish Iesuites, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>r Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ourites, which make it no matter of Conscience to set at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie naturall Subiects from true obedience to their Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ge Princes, and to take vp Armes against them: Yea▪ perswade it meritorious, to lay violent hands, and take away the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es of the Lords Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: that they may not bee vnlike themselues: a Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>udie Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whose Kingdome standeth only by bloud. But lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thou vpon tho courtesie of Papists where they preuaile, and learne to loue thine owne Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rey, and naturall Gouernment: for truly was it said of <hi>Augustus Caesar,</hi> of one who had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>led from <hi>Anthonie,</hi> and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>sted much of his great Facts for <hi>Caesar,</hi> at the Table, <hi>Proditionem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo▪ Proditores non item.</hi> I loue Treason, but I commend not Traytors. And let this bee a caueat vnto thee: And suffer not a conceit of thy Religion, and of Rome to carrie thee against the Commandement of God: for God hath not allowed at any time the breach of his Royall Law, neyther hath hee giuen any one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement▪ to tolerate the breach of another, as the Pope would perswade. To ioyne with thy naturall Princes enemie is monstrous, and against his Commandement, yea though they were euil. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore feare him that hath power to cast thy bodie and soule into hell, and feare not the Bugge, of Rome, whose Buls are but Lead, and his Thund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lts feathered at the wrong end: which returneth vpon the Discharger: whose cursings are turned into blessings, as this Land witnesseth: and her Maiestie, which neuer prospered better, then since he beganne to curse. And make vse of this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie, where thou shalt see the end of such as take vp Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their Prince, and Countrey.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, you that are faithfull Subiects to his Maiestie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage you your hearts, and strengthen your hands, and furnish your selues willingly: for the confidence of a good cause is great, as hauing God not an idle Beholder, but an effectuall worker, which teacheth our hands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o warre, and our fingers to figh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>: which giueth Victorie to Kings, and helpeth his Anoi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ted: vnto whom it is all one (if we respect himselfe) to obtaine Victorie with few or no power. And feare not rayling <hi>Rabshake,</hi> nor so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tish <hi>Sennacharib:</hi> for there are more with vs, then are with them: with them is an arme
<pb facs="5"/>
of flesh, but with vs is the Lord of Hosts to fight our Battailes.</p>
   <p>Wherefore be valiant, my good Countriemen, and fight with your God▪ for his worship, for your Countrey your King, your selues▪ your Wiues, Children, and inheritances, and make vse of this Booke, where you shall see the truth preuaile, and Rebels receiue their iust hire. And now you Male-contents, which desire a change, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbance of States, and watch for such oportunities, that you might be ryfling, and inuert all order, thinking thereby to become Lords, and to make the Noble, and Honourable vile, and care not what come, or who come, so you might bee scuffling: settle your selues in some honest calling, that you may liue by the sweat of your owne browes, being blessed of God. For you that now promise your selues golden hils, shall (as you may perceiue in this Historie) find that you are but in a golden dreame, drenched in all filthinesse. And you that couet to flie so high with <hi>Icarus,</hi> shall fall shamefully by an Hempen String: and take heed, lest (as you may finde beere by experience) being carried with an idle hope, and the vaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of some, you bind not your selues aforehand, or enter too far: for you cannot get out when you would. They that are in Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, are to be admonished (as they doe) to looke vnto the beginnings.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>—Sero medicina paratur,</l>
      <l>Dum mala per longas inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>luere horas.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Thus Gentle Reader, lest I should increase the Volume too much, I commend thee to God, and the guiding of his Grace, to establish thy heart in true obedience: first, towardes his Maiestie, next, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes our Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Iames</hi> in all bodily dutie. And if you receiue any fruit of my labour, my paines is recompensed. Let God haue the whole prayse, and helpe me with thy Prayers: Who of his infinite mercie conuert, or soone confound his Maiesties ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, establish his Scepter in his hand, and the Crowne vpon his head, that he may triumph ouer all his and our Enemies in this life, and may after life remaine, and raigne in the Kingdome of his Saints, for euer,</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>Farewell, Gentle Reader, thy poore brother in Christ, <hi>R. W.</hi> Minister at Frettenham, in Norfolke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>