<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Readers generally a gene∣rall aduertisement of the Authour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102875_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01514</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11636</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102875</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Readers generally a gene∣rall aduertisement of the Authour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The posies of George Gascoigne Esquire</title>
                 <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Smith (Smyth), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, clviij, 2, 4, 36, 45-76 pages, 77-86, 85-106 leaves, 107-173, 3, 175-290, 10 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>To the Readers generally a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>aduertisement of the</hi> Authour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll that is written is written for our instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the holy Apostle witnesseth to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in his .xv. Chapter. And in his ninth Chapter of his first Epistle to the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, hee glorieth that hee coulde (as it were) transforme himself into all professions, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to winne all kinde of men to God: saying that with the Iewes he became a Iew: with them that were vnder the law, he seemed also vnder the lawe: with the feeble, he shewed himselfe feeble. And to conclude, he became all things to all men, to the ende that hee might thereby winne some to saluation. My Schoolemaster which taught me Grammer, woulde alwayes say that some schollers he woonne to studie by strypes, some other by fayre meanes, some by promises, some other by prayses, some by vainglorie, and some by verie shame. But I neuer hard him repent him that euer he had persuaded any scholler to become studious, in what sort soeuer it were that hee woonne him. For whether the braue Gennet be broken with the bitte, or with the snaffle, whither he be brought in awe with a Spurre, or with a wand, all is one if he proue readie and well mouthed.</p>
   <p>Thus much I write (gentle Reader) to the ende that myne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent may appeare in publishing of these Posies. VVherein as there are many things morall, so are there also some verses more sauced with wantonnesse than with wisedome. And as there are some dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which may please and delight the godly and grauer sort, so are there some which may allure the yonger sort vnto fond attempts. But what for that? Hath <hi>Terence</hi> bene forbidden to be read, bicause his Comedies are rehearsals of many madde prankes played by wanton youthes? No surely.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Paracelsus,</hi> and sundrie other Phisitions and Philosophers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that in euerie thing naturall there is to be founde Salt, Oyle,
<pb facs="10"/> and Brimstone. And I am of opinion, that in euery thing which is written (the holy scriptures excepted) there are to be founde wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, follie, emulation, and detraction. For as I neuer yet saw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing so clerkly handled, but that therein might be found some imperfections: So coulde I neuer yet reade fable so ridiculous but that therein some morallitie might be gathered. And as the good writer shall be sure of some to bee maliced: so the bad shall neuer escape the byting tongues of slaunderers.</p>
   <p>But to returne to my purpose: If in the hardest flint there may be found sparkes of liuely fire, and the most knottie peece of Box, may be wrought to a fayre Doogen hafte: let these fewe suffice to persuade thee, that I haue not procured the publication heereof to any ende, so much as that the youthful sort might therein take ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and the aged recreation.</p>
   <p>Nowe if any (misgouerning their owne wittes) doe fortune to vse that for a Spurre, which I had heere appoynted for a Brydle, I can none otherwise lamēt it, but to say that I am not the first which hath bene misiudged. Truely (gentle Reader) I protest that I haue not ment heerein to displease any man, but my desire hath rather bene to cōtent most men: I meane the diuine with godly Hymnes and Psalmes, the sober minde with morall discourses, and the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest will with sufficient warning. The which if it so fall out, then shall I thinke my selfe right happie. And if it fall out otherwise, I shall yet neuer bee ashamed to become one of their corporation which reape floutes and reprehension for their trauayles.</p>
   <p>But bicause these Posies growe to a great bundell, and thereof also the number of louing lynes exceedeth in the Superlatiue, I thought good to aduertise thee, that the most part of them were written for other men. And out of all doubt, if euer I wrote lyne for my selfe in causes of loue, I haue written tenne for other men in layes of lust. For I counte greater difference betweene loue and lust, than there is diuersitie betweene witte and wisedome: and yet witte and I did (in youth) make such a fray, that I feare his cosen wisedome will neuer become freendes with me in my age. VVell, though my folly bee greater than my fortune, yet ouergreat were mine vnconstancie, if (in mine owne behalfe) I shoulde compyle so
<pb facs="10"/> many sundrie Songs or Sonets. I haue heard of an honest plaine meaning Citizen, who (being ouercharged with many matters in the lawe, and hearing of a common solicitor of causes in the Citie) came home to comfort his wife, and tolde hir that he had heard of one which dwelt at Billingsgate, that coulde helpe all men. Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n so (good Reader) I was a great while the man which dwelt at Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingsgate. For in wanton delightes I helped all men, though in sad earnest I neuer furthered my selfe any kinde of way. And by that it proceedeth, that I haue so often chaunged my Posie or worde. For when I did compile any thing at the request of other men, if I had subscribed the same with mine owne vsuall mot or deuise, it might haue bewrayed the same to haue beene of my doing. And I was euer curious in that behalfe, as one that was lothe to bewray the follies of other men. And yet (as you see) I am not verie daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to lay my selfe wide open in view of the worlde. I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so sundrie tymes chaunged mine owne worde or deuise. And no meruaile: For he that wandereth much in those wildernesses, shall seldome continue long in one minde.</p>
   <p>VVell, it were follie to bewayle things which are vnpossible to be recouered, sithence Had I wist doth seldome serue as a blasone of good vnderstanding. And therefore I will spende no more wordes in this Preface, but I pray thee to smell vnto these Posies, as <hi>Floures to comfort, Herbes to cure,</hi> and <hi>VVeedes to be auoyded.</hi> So haue I ment them, and so I beseech thee Reader to accept them.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>