<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102282_Fr5_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11041</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102282</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The diamond of deuotion : cut and squared into sixe seuerall points: namelie, 1 The footpath to felicitie. 1 2 A guide to godlines. 81 3 The schoole of skill. 181 4 A swarme of bees. 209 5 A plant of pleasure. 245 6 A groue of graces. 283 Full of manie fruitfull lessons, auaileable to the leading of a godlie and reformed life: by Abraham Fleming</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William, Assignee(s) of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 320, 4 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="109"/>
   <pb n="211" facs="109"/>
   <head>The Preface to the <hi>Christian Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E see that Bees being a sociable creature, that is, apt for companie, flee together in swarmes, and assembled vnder one hiue, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the dutie wherevnto they are ordeined, namelie, to make Honie. The benefite of this labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and diligent creature is so ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie, that such as haue knowne and tasted by due proofe and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience the fruite of their trauell, and the sweetenesse of their worke, will be hardlie persuaded to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the fostering of them, for feare of losing so singular commodities as they do yeeld.</p>
   <p>Euen so this swarme of Bees, which I, not by the sound of a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen, but by the painefulnesse of my pen, haue gathered together out of
<pb facs="110"/>
the pleasant garden of Gods most holie word, where I found them scattered heere and there among the fragrant flowres, and sweete beds of wholesome hearbes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king most comfortable Honie, and offering thee a tast thereof, are not lightlie to be esteemed, considering that the issue and euent of their trauell, well ordered and vsed, is so beneficiall, as nothing more, if anie thing like.</p>
   <p>For their Honie hath this vertue, that to such as eate it, and digest it throughlie, it giueth a regenerated mind, a sanctified soule, a circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed hart, a mortified bodie, and all good things that man can imagine or deuise: of which spirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who so hath once possession, his conscience will tell him what it is to taste, to sucke, to eate, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughlie to digest Honie made by such a swarme of Bees. These Bees followe one another orderlie and decentlie, without desire of first or highest place: out of one garden
<pb facs="110"/>
they gathered it, in one hiue they made it, and for all godlie disposed peoples feeding heere they leaue it in their Honicombes.</p>
   <p>There is none that hauing wit, will finde fault with water of the cleerest fountaine, with floure of the finest wheate, with a garment of the costliest silke, with a ring of the purest golde, with a iewell of the highest price. For it is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man to couet the verie best things, yea, and to obteine them, if they may be gotten for anie monie. Heere thou hast a swarme of Bees, making most excellent Honie, sweete, pleasant, and whoalsome. It differeth from ordinarie Honie, because the Bees that made it, are extraordinarie, and the flowers whereout they suckt it, grew in no common garden: it is offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee gratis, no gaine looked for, but onelie thy good will in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it, and thy diligence in vsing it. Make much therefore of these Bees, and open thy mouth wide,
<pb facs="111"/>
that thy throte swallowing their sweete Honie, may distribute the same to all thine inward partes, and that the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and inward man may be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Abraham Fleming.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>