<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE THRICE Honoured Sr. IOHN WYNNE, Knight and Baronet, to his Right Worshipfull Sonne, Sir RICHARD WYNNE, attendant in Ordinary vpon the Prince his Grace, and one of the Gentle∣men of his Priuie Chamber, and to his two Sonnes in Law, those worthy Knights, Sir Roger Mostynne, and Sir Iohn Bodvell, grace be vnto you, and peace, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Williams, Gr.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102808_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15445</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25716</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE THRICE Honoured Sr. IOHN WYNNE, Knight and Baronet, to his Right Worshipfull Sonne, Sir RICHARD WYNNE, attendant in Ordinary vpon the Prince his Grace, and one of the Gentle∣men of his Priuie Chamber, and to his two Sonnes in Law, those worthy Knights, Sir Roger Mostynne, and Sir Iohn Bodvell, grace be vnto you, and peace, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Williams, Gr.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The delights of the saints : A most comfortable treatise, of grace and peace, and many other excellent points. Whereby men may liue like saints on earth, and become true saints in heauen. First deliuered in a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the second day of December, being the second Sunday of the Parliament. And in other sermons within the Cathedrall Church of Saint Paul, London. By Gryffith Williams, Doctor of Diuinity, and Parson of Lhan-Lhechyd. The contents are set downe after the epistle to the reader</title>
                 <author>Williams, Gryffith</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Butter, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 448 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE THRICE Honoured S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. IOHN WYNNE, Knight and Baronet, to his Right Worshipfull Sonne, Sir RICHARD WYNNE,</hi> attendant in Ordinary vpon <hi>the Prince his Grace, and one of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of his Priuie Chamber, and to his two Sonnes <hi>in Law, those worthy Knights, Sir</hi> Roger Mostynne, <hi>and Sir</hi> Iohn Bodvell, <hi>grace be vnto you, and peace, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>HONOVRED SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hose <hi>many, great, dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fauours</hi> of your Worship vnto me, euer since I came from my <hi>Honourable Lord &amp; Master, the Earle of Montgomeries</hi> seruice, vnto your parts (which I professe haue beene my chiefest incouragement of continuing like <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi> at <hi>Ahabs</hi> gate) and the <hi>pious practise</hi> of your Worship in all your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; such <hi>daily, priuate,</hi> and <hi>publique praiers</hi> in your house, that meales are not more frequent then praiers, such
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>care,</hi> not only to prouide <hi>spirituall food,</hi> the preaching of Gods word, to those hungry and thirsting Christians (that doe gape and long for the same, as <hi>the drie ground doth for raine in the time of drought)</hi> in your Parish Church, and Market towne of <hi>Lhan Rwste,</hi> euery se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond market day, but also by your owne continuall example, of comming, and neuer missing to come, <hi>your selfe,</hi> (while your health permits you) and <hi>calling others,</hi> to hearken vnto that <hi>diuine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise,</hi> for the furtherance of the same. And then such kinde and <hi>louing enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment</hi> of vs <hi>Prophets</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets children</hi> at your table, where we haue <hi>conuiuium theologicum:</hi> and are most commonly able to make a <hi>Iurie of Ministers</hi> vpon any controuersiall point of Diuinity, so as I am sure in Wales <hi>none,</hi> in England I thinke <hi>few</hi> haue the like: and such a <hi>desire</hi> to haue all the poore ignorant people of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey <hi>instructed in the Catechisme and principles of Christian religion,</hi> and many more such like <hi>fruits of grace.</hi> And likewise the worthie <hi>seruice</hi> vnto your King, and the great good that you
<pb facs="5"/> doe vnto your <hi>countrey,</hi> by the <hi>recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling</hi> of many variances, the <hi>punishing</hi> of lewd offendors, <hi>maintaining</hi> the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique peace and tranquillity of all, and especially the <hi>releeuing</hi> of so many <hi>poore</hi> as you doe, both at your <hi>doores,</hi> and by <hi>your purse,</hi> for which you haue so many praiers and intercessors: <hi>&amp; impossibile est multorum preces non exaudiri</hi> (as S. <hi>Chrysostome</hi> speaketh.)</p>
   <p>I say <hi>these things,</hi> and many like <hi>fruits of grace and peace,</hi> that I might iustly speake of, would proue me to be <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull,</hi> and vnworthy of your loue, and indeed <hi>vnmindfull of my dutie</hi> to God and his Church, if I did not <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge</hi> those many kindnesses, that I haue receiued from your Worship, and likewise <hi>set downe</hi> some of those <hi>fruits of piety,</hi> and good workes, that you doe both in Church and Commonwealth, to be a <hi>patterne vnto your brethren,</hi> to be imitated herein, and especially to those <hi>three worthy Knights,</hi> your sonne and sonnes in law, <hi>and all the rest</hi> of your children and posteritie, which God hath blessed, <hi>and blessed them all</hi> (I doubt not but for your sake, and your
<pb facs="6"/> most milde and vertuous <hi>Lady,</hi> who brought a <hi>blessing</hi> vnto your house) equall in grace, in vertue, and in all faire carriage, to the best mans children that I doe know; that when they <hi>see not you,</hi> when you doe see <hi>the face of God in glorie,</hi> they may euer see the <hi>true records</hi> of your <hi>pietie</hi> and practise, for their <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>patterne</hi> for imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for howsoeuer I, <hi>dust and ashes,</hi> am nothing, of none account, and shall <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to nothing,</hi> yet I hope I may say of this my poore labours of veritie, as the Poet said of his labors of vanity, that<hi>—nec Iouis ira, nec ignis, Nec poterit ferrum, nec edax abolere vetustas.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And therefore I presumed <hi>out of my vnfained loue,</hi> to insert your honoured name in the frontispice of this tract. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it as the token of <hi>a thankfull heart;</hi> for though you may haue <hi>many greater friends,</hi> yet will I euer rest in the number <hi>of your truest</hi> and faithfullest friends,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>At your seruice, wholly to be commanded, GR. WILLIAMS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>