<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Iudicious vnderstanding gentle∣man, and my much approued and esteemed good freind, Maister ROBERT BRANTHVVAITE, Gentleman Taylor of the Kings Maiesties Tower of London. Iohn Taylor Dedicates this his Poeticall Weatherworke, with his best wishes, for your hearts contentment.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102629_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13446</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23752</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102629</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Iudicious vnderstanding gentle∣man, and my much approued and esteemed good freind, Maister ROBERT BRANTHVVAITE, Gentleman Taylor of the Kings Maiesties Tower of London. Iohn Taylor Dedicates this his Poeticall Weatherworke, with his best wishes, for your hearts contentment.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Faire and fowle vveather: or a sea and land storme : betweene two calmes. With an apologie in defense of the painefull life, and needfull vse of sailors. By Iohn Tailor</title>
                 <author>Taylor, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Blower (Blore), Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Butler, William 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Iudicious vnderstanding gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and my much approued and esteemed good <hi>freind, Maister</hi> ROBERT BRANTHVVAITE, Gentleman Taylor of the Kings Maiesties Tower of London. <hi>Iohn Taylor</hi> Dedicates this his Poeticall Weatherworke, with his best wishes, for your hearts contentment.</head>
   <l>KInde Sir, my loue to you's ingag'd so deepe,</l>
   <l>That were I Idle, I were much ingratefull:</l>
   <l>Or should my thankes, forgetfull, euer sleepe</l>
   <l>In me, 'twere base, vnmannerly and hatefull.</l>
   <l>Then though I cannot pay you halfe my score,</l>
   <l>Vouchsafe to take this trifle as a part,</l>
   <l>As time enables me you shall haue more,</l>
   <l>And therefore now accept my willing heart.</l>
   <l>I know, you well doe vnderstand and know</l>
   <l>The weake defects of my defectiue Muse,</l>
   <l>Yet doe I hope you will this fauour showe</l>
   <l>That loue may her vnwilling faults excuse.</l>
   <l>And so to your protection I commend</l>
   <l>This Pamphlet, as vnto my deerest freind.</l>
   <byline>
      <hi>Yours in my best imployments to be commended.</hi> IOHN TAYLOR.</byline>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>