<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS PRE∣face to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102777_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16282</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3198.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102777</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS PRE∣face to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The manners, lavves, and customes of all nations : Collected out of the best vvriters by Ioannes Boemus Aubanus, a Dutch-man. With many other things of the same argument, gathered out of the historie of Nicholas Damascen. The like also out of the history of America, or Brasill, written by Iohn Lerius. The faith, religion and manners of the Aethiopians, and the deploration of the people of Lappia, compiled by Damianus à Goes. With a short discourse of the Aethiopians, taken out of Ioseph Scaliger his seuenth booke de Emendatione temporum. Written in Latin, and now newly translated into English. By Ed. Aston</title>
                 <author>Boemus, Johannes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Burton, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 408, 449-589, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE most famous and memorable lawes, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes, and manners of all nations, and the situation of each seueral Countrie, which <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodotus</hi> the father of Histories, <hi>Diodorus Sicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Berosus, Strabo, Solinus, Trogus Pompeius Ptolomy, Pliny, Cornelius Tacitus, Dionysiuss Afer, Pomponius Mela, Caesar, Iosephus,</hi> and of later Writers, <hi>Ʋincentius, Aeneas Syluius,</hi> (who was afterward Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the second) <hi>Antonius Sabellicus, Iohannes Nauclerus, Ambrosius Calepinus, Nicholas Perottus</hi> in his books intituled, <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nucopiae,</hi> and many other famous Historiographers, haue confused<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and (as it were) by parts commended vnto vs in their Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries: I haue (good diligent Reader) as my leysure would serue, collected, abridged, digested, and compacted together in this <note place="margin">The cause why he writ this booke.</note> short and compendious Breuiary: wherein you may easily finde what euer you haue occasion to looke for; which I haue effected, not in expectance of gaine, nor affecting popular prayse, but free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and without other recompence, then the pleasure and profite the thing it selfe bringeth with it. And herein I haue expressed as well the customes of auncient time, as those which be in vse at this day; as well the good as the bad, in differently: that both lying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen before thine eyes, by their examples thou mayst follow and imitate in the course of thy life, those which be honest, holy, and commendable, and auoyd those which be dishonest and shameful. And hereby thou shalt perceiue (good Reader) in what perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and happinesse we now liue at this day, and how fimply, rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and vnciuilly our forefathers liued, from the Creation of the world to the generall Floud, and for many ages after. When as
<pb facs="6"/>
they, vsing no money, no merchandize, but equalling one bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit with another, had nothing proper to themselues, but sea and land as common to all, as the aire and firmament. No man then ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped after honor and riches, but euery one contented with a little, liued a rurall, secure, and idle life, free from toyle or trauell, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with one or more wiues and their sweet children, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no other house than the heauens, the shadow of a tree, or some homely cabbin: their meate was then the fruite of trees, and milke of beasts; their drinke water, and their clothing, first, the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most rinde or broade leaues of trees, and afterwards the skinnes of beasts vnhandsomly stitched together. They were not then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed in and immured in walles, nor defended with ditches, but wandring abroad at their willes, with their cattell, not then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed in inclosures, reposed their bodies where euer night tooke them, sleeping ioyfully and securely without feare of theeues or robbers, wherof that age was ignorant.</p>
   <p>All which things afterwards crept in and insued of mens varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble willes, emulation and dissonant desires, when fruites gotten without labour beeing insufficient to sustaine such multitudes, and other things growing defectiue, and for the repelling and repres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the often incursions and fierce assaults of beasts and forraine <note place="margin">The cause why people inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted neere toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> people, they were constrained to gather themselues into multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, to ioyne their forces together, and to apportion themselues certaine limits and territories wherein to liue; where (ioyning and vniting their houses for neighbourhood) they beganne to liue a more ciuill and popular kind of life, to fence and fortifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues with wals and trenches, and to ordaine lawes, and elect ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates for the maintenance of peace and tranquilitie amongst them: And then they began to prouide for their maintenance, not onely by husbanding their grounds, or following their flockes, but by sundry other exercises, and new inuented arts, to passe by sea with their nauies into forren nations: first, for transporting of companies to inhabit new-found countries, and then for trafficke and trading one with another: to traine vp horses for the cart, of copper to make coyne, to cloth themselues more curiously: to feed more daintily, to haue more humanity in their speech: more ciuili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in their conuersation, more state in their buildings, and in all
<pb facs="6"/>
points to be more mild, more wise, and better qualified: and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aside all grosse barbarisme, and beastly cruelty, abstayning from mutuall slaughter: from deuouring of humane flesh, from ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine and robberie, from open and incestuous coupling of children with their parents, before indifferently vsed: and from many more such enormities, applyed their reason and strength to recouer the <note place="margin">The earth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered from hir first rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and barren nesse, and made fertile.</note> earth, which (beeing then either ouergrown with thicke woods, ouerrunne with wild beasts, or ouerflowed with standing waters) lay rude, barren, desert, vnfrequented, and inconuenient for mans dwelling, and (with their industrie and labour) playning and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it from heapes of stones, rootes of trees, and superfluous wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, made it fertill and very delightsome to behold. And allowing the plaines and champion grounds for tilling, and the lesser hilles for vineyards, did so manure &amp; dresse the earth, (with instruments made for the purpose) as it brought foorth both corne and wine in aboundance, which before yeelded nothing but acornes and wild apples, and those also sparingly produced.</p>
   <p>The valleys they beautified and adorned with most delectable gardens, and well watered medowes, leauing onely the toppes of mountaines for woods, and assigning so much soyle for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of fruite, as they scarce left sufficient for fuell and fodder. Then they began to people all places more plentifully, to erect new buildings, of ferme houses to make hamlets, of boroughes great citties, to build temples in valleys, towers on mountaine tops, to encompasse their fountains with hewed marble stones, &amp; inuironing them with plants on all sides for shadow, deriued their running waters thence into their cities, through pipes &amp; conduits: to search deepe in the ground for water, where naturally it was wanting: to hold in and restraine the streames and violent riuers, with dams and bankes of earth, which before would often flow at large, to the great destruction of the Inhabitants, and (that they might bee passable, and no hidderance or impediment to mens businesse) to build ouer them strong and stately bridges, vppon bending Arches or Pyles fastened and firmely rampered in the ground, to cast downe Rockes in the sea, which whilome were woont to bee daungerous for saylers, to make hauens, inroades, and harboroughes both in Ilands, and on the Continent.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
To digge Dockes and Rodes, wherein shippes might rest in secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, free from danger of wind or weather. And so diligently to decke and garnish all things both by land and sea, that the earth (as now it is) compared to his former filthinesse and deformitie, may be thought to be an other earth, different from that it was before, and not much vnlike that most delectable garden, out of which our vnfortunate first founders <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> were eiected <note place="margin">The earth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise.</note> for transgressing the diuine commandement.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, many most noble Disciplines, and liberall Arts, were by men found out, which (that they might remaine to all poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie) were by diuers Characters, and new-inuented notes of letters, committed to bookes and tables, and did so farre exempt and aduance them beyond all humane condition, as they might haue beene thought rather to leade the most blessed liues of dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied men, then men indeed.</p>
   <p>Had not Satan the Prince of the world, and enemie of mankind, (by sowing his most pestilent Cockles amongst the good corne) confounded their most intire and happie estate. For he seeing the multitude of people increase, and the pleasure of the world held in better estimation, stirred vp with enuie, first found them guiltie to themselues for committing damnable sins, and afterwards made them with curiositie to affect the knowledge of future and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things, from the obscure answers of Oracles: And to the end he might abolish all knowledge, of one true and onely God, and <note place="margin">The true God forgotten.</note> trouble all mankind with some notable euill: he taught them the prophane worship of false gods and goddesses, causing them to commit idolatrie, and do reuerence vnto them, making the Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phian Temples in one place, the Euboian in another; in another the Nasamonian, and the Dodoman okes (by his diuellish inspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to vtter foorth Oracles. By which means he procured that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine honors were attributed to <hi>Saturn</hi> in Italy, to <hi>Iupiter</hi> in Creet to <hi>Iuno</hi> in Samos, to <hi>Bacchus</hi> in Thebes and India, to the Sun and Moone, (vnder the names of <hi>Isis</hi> &amp; <hi>Osyris)</hi> in Aegypt: to <hi>Vesta</hi> in <note place="margin">Plurality of gods, &amp; which god was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped in each seueral country</note> Troy: in Affricke to <hi>Pallas</hi> and <hi>Triton:</hi> to <hi>Mercury</hi> (vnder the name of <hi>Teutas)</hi> in Fraunce and Germany: to <hi>Mynerua</hi> in Himet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tū &amp; Athens: to <hi>Apollo</hi> in Boeotia, Rhodes, Chius, Patura in Lycia,
<pb facs="7"/>
the lesser Phrigia and Thimbra. To <hi>Diana</hi> in Delos and Scythia; To <hi>Venus</hi> in Cyprus, Paphos, Gnydos, and Cythera: to <hi>Mars</hi> in Thrace, to <hi>Ʋulcan</hi> in Lipara and Lemnos, to <hi>Priapus</hi> in Lampsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus neere Hellispont, and to others in many other places, whose names (for their rare inuentions and great benefits bestowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their people) were then most fresh in memory.</p>
   <p>Moreouer also, after Christ Iesus, the true Sonne of the liuing <note place="margin">Jesus Christ reduced the world from error.</note> God, appearing in flesh, and pointing out to the erring multitude the perfect path-way of saluation, by his word and example, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting to newnesse of life, to the glory of his heauenly father, and sending his Disciples forth into all the world, by their whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some doctrine and preaching, had confounded their damnable idolatry, and spread abroad a new religion, and new institutions of life, yea and preuailed so much, as being receiued of all nations in the world, there could nothing more be desired for the obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of true felicity: when Satan returning into his former ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and going about to circumuent, and get againe his habitation in mens curious hearts, which before (by the comming of Christ) hee was forced to forsake, reduced some into their former errors, and so corrupted and blinded others with new hereticall opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as it had beene better for them, neuer to haue tasted the truth, then so sodainely and maliciously to forsake the knowne way of saluation. For now at this day all the people of Asia the lesse, Armenia, Arabia, Persis, Siria, Assiria and Media, and in Affrick, the <note place="margin">The large Countries of the Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans.</note> Aegiptians, Numidians, Libians and Muritanians. In Europe, all those of Greece, Misia and Thrace, vtterly abiecting Christ, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue and with all honor and deuotion adore, that most accursed and Epileptical <hi>Makomet</hi> and his damnable doctrine. The Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians (which at this day bee called Tartars) a very large and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous nation, dee, some of them worship the Idols of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Cham:</hi> some the stars, and some others the true and onely GOD, at the preaching of Saint <hi>Paul:</hi> the people of India and Aethiopia, which bee vnder the gouernment of <hi>Prestor Iohn,</hi> hold the faith of Christ, but in a manner that is far different from ours. But the sincere and right beliefe of our Sauiour Christ, wherewith (by his speciall grace) the whole world was once illumined, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained onely in Germany, Italy, France, Spaine, England, Scotland,
<pb facs="8"/>
Ireland, Dacia, Liuonia, Prussia, Polonia, Hungaria, and of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Isles of Rhodes, Scicilia, Corsica, Sardinia and of some few besides. So far hath that most cruel enemy of mankinde preuailed, by bringing in such diuersity of manners, such hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and damnable superstitious abuses in ceremonies and sacred things, that whilest euery nation contendeth by strongest ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to prooue that the GOD which they worship and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore is the true and great GOD, and that they onely goe the <note place="margin">The diuersitie of worshipinge is the seminarie of distention.</note> way of eternall happinesse, and all others the by-path that lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to perdition.</p>
   <p>Whilest also euery sect indeauoureth to aduance and set forth themselues, it insueth that (each one persecuting other with mortall enmity and deadly hatred) it is not onely daungerous to trauell into forraine nations, but in a manner vtterly bard and prohibited, which I perswade my selfe is the cause, that the names of bordering nations beeing scarce knowne to their neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest neighbors, whatsoeuer is either written or reported of them, is now accounted fabulous and vntrue: the knowledge whereof <note place="margin">The Greeke Philosophers first glory.</note> notwithstanding hath euer beene reputed so pleasant, so profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and so praise-worthy, as it is most manifest, that for the loue and desire thereof onely, without other cause at all, very many forsaking father and mother, wife and children, countrie and kin (and that which is more) neglecting their owne health, haue aduentured through great difficulties and daungers, care and troubles, long and tedious iourneies into forraine nations, onely to furnish themselues with experience. So as it is vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true that not in these daies onely, but almost from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world, All those haue bin generally esteemed men of greatest authority, wisdome and learning, and by open con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent haue beene elected and chosen Maisters and Gouernours, Councellors and Iudges, Captaines and Controllers, who hauing <note place="margin">The law-giuers first authority.</note> sometimes trauelled strang countries, haue knowne the manners of many people and cities, for euer as those auncient Philosophers of Greece and Italy, which were first founders of sundry sects wherin they instructed their Disciples &amp; Schollers, as namely <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> of the Socratick sect, <hi>Plato,</hi> of the Academicke, <hi>Aristotle,</hi> of the Peripatick, <hi>Antisthines</hi> of the Cynick, <hi>Aristyppus,</hi> of the Cyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naicke,
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>Zeno</hi> of the Stoicke, and <hi>Pithagoras</hi> of the Pithagoricke. As also those old law-giuers <hi>Minos</hi> and <hi>Rhodomanthus</hi> to the men of Creete, <hi>Orpheus</hi> to those of Thrace, <hi>Draco &amp; Solon</hi> to the Athenians, <hi>Licurgus</hi> to the Lacedemonians, <hi>Moses</hi> to the Iewes, <hi>Zamolxis</hi> to the Scythians, and many others which wee see haue set down to their people diuers prescript ceremonies &amp; ciuil dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplines: inuented not of those seueral sects, disciplines and lawes, within their city walles, but learned and brought them from the Caldeans themselues (beeing the most wise men of the world) from the Indian Philosophers, the Brackmans &amp; Gymnosophists, <note place="margin">The Caldeanes the wisest men in the world.</note> and from the Aegiptian Priests, with whom sometimes they were conuersant. To conclude, wee plainely perceiue that those most renowned worthies, <hi>Iupiter</hi> of Creete (who was reported to haue measured the world fiue times ouer) and his two sonnes of like disire and successe, <hi>Dionysius,</hi> surnamed <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and valiant <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi> and <hi>Theseus</hi> his imitator, <hi>Iason</hi> with the rest of the Greekes which went with him for the golden Fleece, wether-beaten <hi>Vlisses</hi> and <hi>Aencas</hi> the outcast of Troy, <hi>Cyrus, Darius, Xerxes, Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the Great, <hi>Hanibal</hi> the Carthaginiā, <hi>Mithrydate</hi> king of Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus (expert in the language of fifty nations) the great <hi>Antiochus</hi> and innumerable other Romane Princes and Gouernors, the <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pios,</hi> the <hi>Marii,</hi> the <hi>Lentuli, Pompey</hi> the Great, <hi>Iulius Caesar, Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uian Augustus,</hi> the <hi>Constantines, Charles, Othones, Conrades, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and <hi>Frederickes,</hi> haue by their warlike expeditions into for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine nations, purchased vnto themselues an euerlasting fame and immortal memory. Wherefore seeing there is so great pleasure and profit in the knowledge of countries, and of their manners, and also seeing it is not in euery mans power, nor yet lawfull for many causes, for euery one to trauel and behold lands far remote: thou maist (good gentle reader) as wel by reading comprehend &amp; vnderstand, the most renowned customes of al nations, and the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueral sytuation of each country, expressed in this booke, and that as readily, &amp; with as much pleasure, as if, taking thee by the hand, I shold lead thee through euery nation one after an other, &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully relate vnto thee, in what place, and vnder what kind of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, each nation haue liued heretofore and now doe liue.</p>
   <p>Nor would I haue thee distasted or carried away, for that by some too seuere reformer, it may bee obiected and laide in
<pb facs="9"/>
my teeth, that I haue produced for new and for mine owne, a matter written long agoe, and heretofore handled of no lesse then a thousand Authors, and that I haue vsed only their words without alteration: But if thou diligently marke my purpose, thou shalt find that (in imitation of that liberal houshoulder, to whom Christ in the Gospell compared euery learned scribe) I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented thee (my kinde guest) with some things, as well out of mine owne braine, as wholy extracted from the hidden treasure of my bookes, and not onely with borowed and vnknowne stuffe, but with sundry new dainties of mine owne deuising.</p>
   <p>Farewel, and what euer thou findest herein accept in good part.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>