<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE LADIE BENNET.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102573_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09644</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19909</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102573</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE LADIE BENNET.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vertues anatomie. Or A compendious description of that late right honorable, memorable, and renowned Bedfordshire lady, the Lady Cheany, of Tuddington. By Charles Pierse</title>
                 <author>Pierse, Charles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>TO THE LADIE BENNET.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam, the seruice I doe owe to all</l>
   <l>Your sisters, and your house in generall,</l>
   <l>Would ask a volume, if y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I could write it,</l>
   <l>Or had but wit sufficient to indite it.</l>
   <l>Yet, Madam, since I haue no worldly store,</l>
   <l>I giue you that, I neuer gaue before:</l>
   <l>And wanting one, yet may you take the other,</l>
   <l>The fruits, my weake inuention could discouer.</l>
   <l>Heere in this little volume may be read,</l>
   <l>Some of her noble vertues, being dead;</l>
   <l>Where you may striue in imitation,</l>
   <l>To make more glorious by your application.</l>
   <l>Some can gleane vertue from the smallest things,</l>
   <l>And hony sucke from meanest flowers that springs:</l>
   <l>Then how much more from her, whose honor true,</l>
   <l>Such store of vertues doth afford to you.</l>
   <l>Where, Madam, your faire intellectiue minde,</l>
   <l>May more then I can, or haue vttered, finde.</l>
   <l>Reade o're her life, and in your iudgement view her,</l>
   <l>Who hath not much admir'd, that euer knew her?</l>
   <l>Where eyes, eares, hearts, are vanished with the same,</l>
   <l>Of her long happie, and time-honored name.</l>
   <l>Then, Madam, since my meannesse is too great,</l>
   <l>Of such a waightie subiect to intreat:</l>
   <l>Some fauour lend, to grace this worke the better,</l>
   <l>For which acceptance, I will die your debter.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>