<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Steuen Bysshop of wynchester to the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1546</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102856_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01463</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11589</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102856</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Steuen Bysshop of wynchester to the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration of suche true articles as George Ioye hath gone about to confute as false</title>
                 <author>Gardiner, Stephen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1546</date>
                 <publisher>Herford (Hereford, Hertford), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Toy (Toeus), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>clxxx leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Steuen Bysshop of wynchester to the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD geue the (gentle reader) iudgement to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne truth frome vntruth. Bitwene whiche two, in the personnes of me and Ioye, thou shalt se contenciō. Wherin I haue not suche regarde to the man, to dispute with hym (whom by saynt Poules counsayll, after so many admonitions, I shoulde exchue) but onelye to treate the matter, which nedeth true explication. As I haue contemned the ioyly hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and other ianglers, wiselye in my frendes opinions: so shoulde I do Ioye, for any thyng he hath sayde of me. And agaynst Ioye I stryue not, who ouerturneth him self, but am enforced to talke with
<pb n="ii" facs="2"/>
hym, as a medler in the thynge, which I can not pretermitte, and suffre vndeclared. I cā not frame my writinges meet for all mens capacities, eyther learnynge fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, or the matter wyll not suffre, good wyll wanteth not, whiche I wold wysshe, were through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye persuaded vnto the, with this also, that albeit, thar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our beleef, with knoweledge sufficient, for direction of our lyuynge, to gods pleasure, may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended of rude and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wittes: yet the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussion of the scriptures, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth goddes further giftes of erudicion and learnynge. Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>