<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the curteous Reader.</title>
           <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102691_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B13659</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11415a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102691</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the curteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of the Parallele, or conference of the ciuill law, the canon law, and the common law of this realme of England : Wherein the agreement and disagreement of these three lawes touching diuers matters not before conferred, is at large debated and discussed. Whereunto is annexed a table contayning the principall Questions, matters, and pointes of the Dialogues ensuing. Handled in seauen dialogues, by William Fulbecke</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wight, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 74, 8 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="92"/>
   <pb facs="92"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="93"/>
   <pb facs="93"/>
   <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vrteous Reader, when <hi>Sulpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> returning out of <hi>As<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a,</hi> sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from <hi>Aegina</hi> to <hi>Megara,</hi> he began to cast his eye, and bend his contemplation to the regions round about him: behind him was <hi>Aegina,</hi> before him <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gara,</hi> on the right hand <hi>Piraeus,</hi> on the left hand <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> which had bene in ancient time verie flourishing Cities, but were now ruinated, prostrated, and buried in dust: that wise Romane whose eye did alwaies ayme at some conuenient marke, and whose mind made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vse of her selected obiect, when he saw these car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kasses of townes, considered his owne estate, which was far more brittle. I likewise wandring in my thoughts through the paradise of learning, amongst many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull apparitions espied foure excellent lawes: the first was the canon-law, to which for the grauity I bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: the second the Ciuil, which for the wisedom I admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: the third the Common law, to which I did my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: the fourth the law of Nations, which I submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siuely reuerenced, yet the hew and state of her seemed to bee much chaunged, and the iniquitie of crabbed times had set the print of her metamorphosis vppon
<pb facs="94"/> her: Her other three sisters did condole with her, and deplore the iniurie of the times which did cause her crasines. I perceiuing this, waied mine owne frailtie, which in one and this very spring tide haue in my selfe knowne the force of seasons, and to the glorie of God acknowledged it: I had no meanes of comfort where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to refresh this drooping Ladie, but onely with a plaine English mantle to attire her, and recommend her vnto thee. She will report many things vnto thee of the renowmed <hi>Assyrians,</hi> the valiant <hi>Persians,</hi> the spirit-guided <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> the prudent <hi>Grecians,</hi> the admirable <hi>Romanes,</hi> the noble harted <hi>Carthagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the victorious <hi>Macedonians,</hi> the deliberatiue <hi>Turkes,</hi> the politike <hi>Italians,</hi> the chiualrous <hi>French,</hi> the most puissant <hi>&amp; inuictis Romano Marte Britan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Tibul. 4. Elegi. 1.</note> she will manifest vnto thee their iudgements, their censures, their aduises, and practises:</p>
   <q>
      <l>Et quae mox imitere scias: nec desinet vnquam</l>
      <l>Tecum Graia loqui, tecum Romana vetustas:</l>
      <l>Antiquos audito duces: assuesse futurae</l>
      <l>Militiae: Latium retrò te confer in aeuum. <note n="b" place="margin">Claudi. de quart. Consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. Honor.</note>.</l>
   </q>
   <p>I commit this booke gentle reader to thy curtesie: it is the first to my knowledge that hath bin written of this matter: if my paines be not correspondent to the dignitie of the subiect, the pardon lyeth in the benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of thy curtesie: Euerie one cannot be a <hi>Scipio,</hi> or a <hi>Laelius,</hi> to ouertake euerie thing which they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take: euerie one cannot say as one of them said: <hi>Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entis non est dicere, non putaram. Appelles</hi> could but only describe the head and face of <hi>Venus: Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi>
      <pb facs="94"/> killed many Troianes, could not surprise their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and <hi>Virgill</hi> before he commeth to the death and tombe of <hi>Aeneas,</hi> fayleth, and slippeth into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of the death and tombe of a Gnat. Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is a rare birde, which flieth from many, that with sweating and breathing follow it. Yet some handle that, which they can not gripe, and their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour is not disliked. Some make a bolde attempt, and fayle of the victorie, whose audacitie is accompted a vertue: Some in not despairing of that they purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, haue been thanked for their hope. For mine owne part I craue no thankes, but good woordes, and good will, and thy fauourable acceptance (friendly Reader) which being an effectuall benefite may perfit all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections. Farewell in the Lord.</p>
   <closer>
      <date>March 30. Anno Domini 1602.</date>
      <signed>Thine in all kind respect WILLIAM FVLBECK.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>