<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his assured Friend, H C. at his Lodging neere Bishops-Gate in London.</title>
           <author>Barlow, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102769_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16303</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3215</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102769</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his assured Friend, H C. at his Lodging neere Bishops-Gate in London.</title>
                 <author>Barlow, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo letters or embassies : The one sent by the states of Bohemia, to the Elector of Saxony: the other from the Popes Holines to the Emperour, concerning the troubles of Germany</title>
                 <author>Bohemia (Země), Sněm</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Jones, William 3.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>44 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To his assured Friend, <hi>H C.</hi> at his Lodging neere Bishops-Gate in London.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>Sr.</hi> If I should send you ouer the Relations both in <hi>Latin, Dutch,</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> which come to this Towne concerning the variety of Newes about the troubles of <hi>Europe,</hi> I should weary you with the multiplicity of Bookes, and my selfe with the cunning of transportation: Besides, I am sure to bee preuented in sending you Newes, because it will bee stale ere it come to your handes by my meanes: Therefore I desist from either troubling you or my selfe in that kinde, and yet haue I chanced on something, which I am sure none can helpe you to, but by my meanes: So it is then, that there, came to my hands two seuerall Coppies of seuerall Letters, one from <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> as the summe of an Embacy from the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Bohemia</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Desertion of the King in these tumultuous times: another from Mr. <hi>Fodringham</hi> in <hi>Vienna,</hi> written by the <hi>Pope</hi> to the <hi>Emperour,</hi> concerning the pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Troubles, and admission of a Peace (if the motiue might bee correspondent to his Honour) rather then aduenture to bee terrified with so much effusion of Blood, or hazard the Dignity of the <hi>Empire,</hi> by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Warres goe forward. And these as you see I haue Printed heere in <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> and they are so pleasing to the Inhabitants heere, that I presume, they will bee as
<pb facs="3"/>
acceptable there to all the welwillers of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Affaires: and so wishing your Contentment in the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reading, bee bolde that whensoeuer any thing comes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of you, you shall not fayle of it. For I am still your Friend:</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>WILLIAM BARLOW.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>