<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Thomas Gale Chi∣rurgian, vnto the frendlye Readers, Salutations.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102805_Fr5_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11529</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102805</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Thomas Gale Chi∣rurgian, vnto the frendlye Readers, Salutations.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine vvorkes of chirurgerie, nevvly compiled and published by Thomas Gale, maister in chirurgerie</title>
                 <author>Gale, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gale, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hall, Rowland</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 53, 7, 5, 58, 1, 3, 19, 2, 4, 90, 8 leaves, 5 folded tables, illustrations, portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="170"/>
   <head>Thomas Gale <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgian, vnto the frendlye</hi> Readers, Salutations.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen as I hadde finished my Institutions, Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridion, and Treatise of woundes made wyth Gonne shotte (louynge Reader) I dyd ryghte well perceyue that the preceptes of the arte in them conteyned, shoulde not so farre extend and serue so well thy vse, excepte I did set oute suche medicinal instruments, as bothe are mencioned in the same bookes, and of necessitie are required in the arte of Chirurgerie: as vnguen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, oyles, Baulmes, lotions, wounde drynkes, Emplasters, Cerotes, Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plasmes, Trochisce, Pouders, &amp; &amp; such lyke. For although I haue set out di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers approued medicines in other my workes, yet they be but as an hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in comparission to this Antido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, and put forthe there onely for
<pb facs="171"/> example sake. Wherefore I haue dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen oute of the moste approued Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours olde and newe, suche medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes as bee both easely prepared, and of moste effecte and vertue: addynge hereto what I haue founde profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and necessarie by longe experience and practise. And althoughe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce at the fyrst it may seeme som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what obscure and harde (because I put the receptes and compositions in the Latyne tongue) yet yf you doe accustomablye vse to reade them, and conferre either wyth the Apothecarie where as you doe not perfectly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande the same, or elles vse the helpe of a Dictionarie, they wyll bee vnto you bothe familier and playne. And thynke not that I haue done thys (louynge Reader) because I woulde make it moore hearde and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: But I dyd it chiefelye for that the Latyne names are vniuersallye vsed, &amp; that there are an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of simples which want Englyshe names, &amp; those (for the more part) that
<pb facs="171"/> may be Englyshed, are not vniuersal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowen through England by that same name: because of the diuersitie that is vsed in callinge of simples, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the countrey. And yet I doe not omit to set out in the English tongue as well the methode and way of composition of suche medicines, as I haue placed in this Antidotarie: as also faithfully declared their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and vse, for what causes they are inuented, and for what infirmities they serue. And although it seeme harde, obscure, and difficulte at the first face, yet folow thou styll the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of the wyse Poet who sayeth:
<q>Assiduo illisu durum cauat vndula saxum.</q>
   </p>
   <p>Whiche Verses maye bee englished with vs in this maner.</p>
   <q>
      <l>The watrie droppes so moyst and softe,</l>
      <l>Doth perse hard stones with dropping oft.</l>
   </q>
   <p>So in like case (dere reader) the hard names of medicines by oft reding will be persed, I meane they wyll be as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile &amp; easy vnto you as possible may be.
<pb facs="172"/> Nowe there resteth no more but that thou wylte with the same good wyll and mynde receyue these my trauai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and expences, that I frely do offer them vnto thee. So doynge I wyll not here staye God wyllyng, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate other of my labours with thee. Fare moste heartely well in Christ oure Sauiour. At my house in London, the first day of August. 1563.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>