<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102531_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01075</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11188</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102531</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A comparatiue discourse of the bodies natural and politique : VVherein out of the principles of nature, is set forth the true forme of a commonweale, with the dutie of subiects, and the right of the soueraigne: together with many good points of politicall learning, mentioned in a briefe after the preface. By Edvvard Forset</title>
                 <author>Forset, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bill, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 100 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Commonweale with all her parts,<note place="margin">The aptest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblances of a Commonweale.</note> orders, qualities, and requisites what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, is (for better apprehension &amp; illustration) set forth by sundry fit resemblances, as by the architecture of an house, by the swarming and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting of Bees in an hiue, by a ship floating on the sea, and such like; but by none more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than eyther by the vniuersall masse of the whole world, (consisting of all the seuerall subsistances in that great frame by the high wisdome and might of God compact and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) or else by the body of man, being the lesser world,<note place="margin">The greater and lesser world.</note> euen the diminitiue and modell of that wide extending vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall. And (by the way) it were a paynes well bestowed, to obserue the good correspondence betweene euery the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular parts or faculties in man, and the other distinct parts, powers, and operations of that bigger bulke: which seemeth to haue beene both sweetly and soundly conceaued by that thrice renowmed Philosopher <hi>Trismegistus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Trismegistus his great Giant.</note> when he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined an huge and mightie Gyant, whose head was aboue


<pb facs="3"/>
the firmament, his necke, shoulders, and vpper parts in the heauens, his armes and hands reaching to East and West, his belly in the whole spaciousnesse vnder the Moone, his legges and feet within the earth. But for that the discourse or discouery of this secret, with the agreeable references to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise therof, falleth not within the line wherwith I haue listed and bounded this Treatise; I wil only from this obseruation of Gods owne imitating of himselfe in the likenesse of the lesse with the greater,<note place="margin">Gods imitating of himselfe, a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for our imitating of him</note> gather and infer that which giueth groundworke vnto my purpose: That the incōprehensible wisdome of God, in the composing &amp; ordering of his works in nature, hath so dignified them with all perfection, as that they be left vnto vs as eminent and exemplary patterns, as well for the consolidating, as for the beautifying of that wee worke by arte or policie; as well for conioyning of all discordances into firmenesse, as also for the applyablenesse of particulars in their many seruices, for the vse and beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the whole. It is beyond the compasse of any contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, that in the morall vertues Christes actions are our instructions; and no lesse may the like rule hold, that in the contriuing of a prudent gouernment, the impressions and footsteps of Gods wisdome (which in things naturall wee contemplate by study) be in the poynt of regiment, our dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories for imitation. Wherefore seeing that the vttermost extent of mans vnderstanding, can shape no better forme of ordering the affayres of a State, than by marking and matching of the workes of the finger of God, eyther in the larger volume of the vniuersall, or in the abridgement thereof, the body of man: I account these two to be the two great lights for enquiry and meditation concerning this businesse, and doe worthily omit all other worthlesse pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidents, as inferiour starrelights, which oftentimes seduceth


<pb facs="3"/>
by their dimnesse, and at their best are but deriuatiue and subalterne vnto these. And of these two also (as not daring to gaze too much vpon the Sunne,<note place="margin">Man the fittest patterne to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of a ciuill state.</note> and vnable in mine own weakenesse to run the round of such a large cōpasse) I haue made my choyce to pursue only those applyances, which from the so skilfull workemanship of God in man, may bee well apted to the ciuill gouernment of the assemblies of men: which being of more facilitie to bee vnderstood (as deduced from a more familiar example) and equalling the other both in dignitie (hauing the same authour) and in certayntie (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specting the fitnesse of their relation) may also sort both agreeably with other mens likings (as bred in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somes) and with mine intentions, which seeketh wholy a demonstratiue plainenesse.</p>
   <p>This similitude was both fitly and fortunatly enforced by <hi>Menenius Agrippa,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Agrippa his tale of the parts of the body. Liuius lib. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> who being imployed in the appeasing and persuading of the seditious reuoulting commons of Rome, did by a very tale of this proportionable respectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the parts in mans body, and the mutualitie of kindnes and ayd afforded from each to other, so sensibly shew them their errour, that surseasing their malignant enuy where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were inraged against their rulers (whom they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as the idle belly that swallowed the labors of their hands) they discerned at the last, that their repining against, and their pining of that belly, whence was distributed vnto them their bloud and nourishment, necessarily tended to their owne destruction; and were thereuppon forthwith reclaymed into their bounds of obedience. The like compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison is most diuinely enlarged by a much better Orator,<note place="margin">The like compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons vsed in the scriptures. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>12.</hi>
      </note> and in a much more important poynt of the vnseparable vnion of the members of Christ with their head, and of the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary communion of their distinct gifts and works amongst


<pb facs="4"/>
themselues; yea, it hath pleased God himselfe for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestation in some measure of his vnmeasurable infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, &amp; the incomprehensible nature of his dietie, to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe vnto vs as it were some glimse thereof, by this selfe same well agreeing semblance, drawne and borrowed from our weak, mortall, and sinfull bodies. His omni-science is set forth by an all-seeing eye, his omnipotencie by a mightie and outstretched arme, his mercy by the cheerefulnesse of a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing countenance, his bountie by the opening of his hand, and filling of all things with his blessings: by which so apt tipes he openeth for our more easie vnderstanding, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundnesse of his attributes, and (as I may say) the mysteries of his essence.</p>
   <p>I need not spend any speech in the praise of such familiar and well pleasing illustrations:<note place="margin">In praise of such comparisons.</note> looke but vpon that exsupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and not attainable by humane powers wisdome of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> is not the brightest apparance thereof in compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue parables? but behold a greater than <hi>Salomon,</hi> who without parables spake nothing to them; as if both the depth and delicacie of wits inuention for either prouing or persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, consisted chiefely in such equipolling and Parabolicall applications. It remayneth that before I proceed to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing or presenting vpon the Stage of State the simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes themselues, to be scanned and considered of, (which I wish may proue themselues right paralele) I do for aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage enterline first a Caution, then a Limitation: My Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is,<note place="margin">A Caution against cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing with dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>similitudes.</note> That no man in streyning too hard, do force the bloud, where he is offered milke. It is easie for a curious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iector, euen in the fittest comparisons to make disseuerance by inferring different respects and inequallitie. The dissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes of things be infinite, and rometh with errour in the circumference, where the well apted likenesse setleth in


<pb facs="4"/>
the center of truth, and is compacted closely in one onely point of good congruitie, from the which it may neither be drawne awry without wrongfull wresting, nor enlarged too far without extreame torturing. It is the greatest miracle of Gods powerfull wisdome, in the innumerable formes of things, to make so infinite variation; Then it must needs be a great worke of the wit of man, in such multiplicitie of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to find out the well agreeing semblances, To knit and match together sundry things by an aptnesse of applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the proper effect of vnion; but to disioyne the well coupled from their louely analogie of each to other, is a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent diuorce and distraction: Therefore let such makebates (if any be) abate their humor of crossing with dissimilitudes, &amp; content their conceits with that which they shall discerne to be matched with a right mirror, and representingly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by the shew of a good concordance.</p>
   <p>My Limitation is,<note place="margin">A limitation not to striue too far.</note> That it be not exacted or expected of me, so mincingly to manage this matter, as that vnto euery particuler part or facultie of our humane nature, I must needs find out in the States bodie some seuerall members or braunches entirely matchable to the same; like a picture to be newly drawne by a former patterne, conforming therewith in euery line, shape, or shadow. We vse to say that one man is like an other, if but the faces, yea the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours or figures, yea the frownes or smyles, yea the casting of the eyes, or any other shewes in their visages doe seeme to agree, though in other respects or parts there be betwixt them rather apparant repugnances, than any right resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances; Then let no man think that I will so be put to my shifts, or that I will impose my selfe so hard a taske, as (by descending to each singuler or indiuiduall) to find for it an euen yoak-fellow, or well matching companion, that may


<pb facs="5"/>
serue as a relatiue or representatiue vnto it, by the aptnesse of propriety: The which labour as it would be endlesse in toile, so would it be no lesse needlesse in vse; and I hope it will suffice, so to compare or make parity betweene the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Naturall and Politique, that each part may be brought in rather easilie entreated, than streiningly intruded; and rather agreeing naturally, than forced violently. Therefore omitting all industrious curiousity, and friuolous affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of following too far (where yet I must needs fall short;) I onely desire, that where I shall shew a reciprocall likenesse of habitude, affection, or disposition; there the similitude may passe approued, and induce assent: and that where these may not readily be had, there I may find such curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous construction, as that I may neither be charged with partiality of concealing (where it is meet I should be mute) nor be suspected of vnsufficiencie for not pursuing where I can find no footing.</p>
   <p>It is vnfallable what I propound for my first principle, That in euery particular person, there is both the seed and similitude of a State incorporat, yet to imagine or seeke for in each seuered or subdeuided parts, such affinitie and fitnesse betwixt them, as may mutually illustrate each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; were not to tune but to crack the strings, and to make <hi>quidlibet ex quodlibet,</hi> or, <hi>ex quouis ligno Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium.</hi> Modestie and discretion bindeth vs to a stint, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the which if we shall stretch or streine,<note place="margin">Of enforcing a similitude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ablenesse.</note> we may iustly be said to haue borrowed of the wyer-drawers: we must not compell our applications there to shake hands and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, where discrepance of nature hath estranged and set apart. Were it not ridiculous for absurditie, and blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for impietie, if in that serious similitude of Christs comming to Iudgement like a theefe in the night, we should


<pb facs="5"/>
(beyond the ge<gap reason="illegible: scratched out" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>inall agreeablenesse of their vnlooked for stealing vpon vs) in other most vngodly sences linke in Christ in likenesse with a theefe? Or if that other notable parable of the vniust Steward, were (from the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his prouident preuention) racked with other refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, to make his deceiptfulnesse also praise-worthy; who would not conuince such vnfit and lefthanded handling, both of wildnesse in wit, and wickednesse of hart? To conclude, I will knit vp this point thus, That in the knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and according of things diuers into one point of agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (making by such their enterchangeable lendings of like reason and respect, a lightsomnesse of proofe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding) we must auoid their diuersities as sands and rocks, and keep the right channell of an allowed likenesse; which will conduct vs both safely and delightsomly in this course of comparing.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>