<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The Author his Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Teelinck, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102633_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13570</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23861</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102633</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The Author his Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Teelinck, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pauls complaint against his naturall corruption : With the meanes how to bee delivered from the power of the same. Set forth in two sermons vpon the 24 verse of the 7. chapter of his epistle to the Romanes. By me William Teelinck, preacher of the word of God at Middleburgh</title>
                 <author>Teellinck, Willem</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Bellamy, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 66, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶ The Author his Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough in all the holy Scripture (the word of truth) it be found to be most true, that in the world there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more hatefull and fearefull then sinne, yet daily experience tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that there are very few which are grieued, and troubled therewith: there are to bee found in this cursed world, multitudes of them that mourne for their temporall losses, and crosses the fruit of sinne; one, complaineth pittifully of his pouertie, of the losse, and damage he hath susteined; another of his sicknesse, of the griefe, and paine that he hath suffered; a third of the shame, contempt, disgrace, or iniurie which this, or that man hath offered vnto him; but few consider that sinne is the mother of all this mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe: yea, when they are free from the foresaid incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences, though they lie plunged, and smoothered in sinne, they are neuer touched therewith, but passe away their time carelesly, and securely; Let them care, that care will: onely some few, whose eyes God hath opened for to see the mysteries of his kingdome, doe make their sinnes their greatest trouble, and griefe; and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good cause; for it is most certaine, and true that he
<pb facs="5"/>shall neuer see God with ioy, hereafter in heauen; which commeth not to see his sinnes with a holy, and godly sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row here vpon earth: In this sense, those that <hi>mourne</hi> are called <hi>blessed</hi> of our Sauiour himselfe. Therefore for to moue men unto this godly sorrow for their sins, and to stirre them vp vnto an holy zeale against all sinnes, I haue published these Sermons following, wherein I haue shewed how we may be deliuered both from the condemning, and commanding power of sinne unto our eternall comfort: whereby if any man reape benefit, I shall highly reioyce in my labour herein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed. Farewell in the Lord.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Middleburgh</hi>
         <date> the <hi>21. of Iuly. 1620.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, WILLIAM TEELINCK.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>