<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1559</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102987_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11915</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22227a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102987</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sixt tragedie of the most graue and prudent author Lucius, Anneus, Seneca, entituled Troas : with diuers and sundrye addicions to the same. Newly set forth in Englishe by Jasper Heywood studient in Oxenforde. Anno domini. 1559. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum</title>
                 <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Tottell (Tathyll, Tothill, Tottyl), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1559</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>86 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶To the readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough (gentle Reader) thou mayst perhaps thinke me arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, for that I onely among so many fine wittes, and towardly youth, (with which England this day florisheth) haue enterprised to set forth in englishe, thys present piece, of the flowre of all writers Seneca, as who saye not fearing what grauer heddes might iudge of me, in attēpting so harde a thyng, yet vpon me pondering what next ensueth, I trust both thy selfe shalt clere thyne owne suspicion, and thy chaunged opinion, shal iudge of me more right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full sentence. For neyther haue I taken thys worke first in hand, as once entēding it shoulde come to light (of well doing whereof I vtterly dispayred) and being done but for mine owne priuate excercyse. I am in mine opinion herein blameles, thoughe I haue (to proue my selfe) pryuatly taken &amp; part which pleased me best. of so excellent an aucthor, for better is time spēt in the best then other, and at first to attempt the hardest writers, shal make a man more prompt, to translate the easyer with more facilitie. But now sins by request, and frendshyp of those, to whom I coulde deny nothing, this woorke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst my will, extorted is out of my handes, I nedes must craue thy pacience in reading, and facilitie of iudgement: when thou shalt aparāt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly see, my wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>les lacke of learning, praying the to consyder. how harde a thyng it is for me, to touche at full in all poyntes, the aucthoures
<pb facs="4"/>
minde, (being in many places very harde and doubtfull and the worke muche corrupt by the defaute of euill printed bookes) and also how farre aboue my powre, to keepe that grace, and maiestye of style, that Seneca doth, when both so excellent a writer, hath past the reache of all imitacion, and also thys our englishe toong (as many thinke and I here fynde) is farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, to compare with the latten, but thou (good reader) if I in any place, haue swerued from the trew sence. or not kept the royaltie of speach, meete for a tragedy, impute the tone to my youth: and lack of iugement, the other to my lacke of eloquence. Now as concerning sondry places augmented and some altered in thys my translacion. Fyrst forasmuch as thys worke se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto me, in some places vnpersyite (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left so of the authour or part of it lost as tyme deuoureth all thynges I wotte not) I haue (where I thought good,) wyth addicyon of mine owne pen, supplied the want of some thynges, as the fyrst Chorus, after the fyrst act beginning thus. O ye to whom &amp;c. Also in the second acte. I haue added the speche of Achilles spright, rysing from hell to require the sacrifice of Polixena beginning in this wise. Forsaking now &amp;c. Againe the three last sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of the Chorus after the same acte, and as for the third Chorus which in Seneca begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thus, Que <hi>vocat sedesi</hi> for as much, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is therin but a heaped noumbre of farre &amp; strange countreies, consydering with my selfe, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <pb facs="5"/>
the names of so many vnknowne countreyes mountaines. desertes, and woodes should haue no grace in the englishe tonge, but be a straunge and vnpleasaunt thing to the readers, (exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e I should expounde the histories of eche one, which would be farre to tedious) I haue in the place therof, made a nother beginning in thys maner. O Ioue that leadst &amp;c. whych al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teracyon may be borne withall, seeing that the Corus is no part of the substance of the matter. In the rest I haue for my sclender learning, endeuored to kepe touche with the Latten, not woorde for woorde or verse for verse as to ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pounde it, but neglecting the placing of the wordes obserued their sence. Take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>entle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this in good worth, wyth all hys fautes fauour my first beginninges, and amende ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with good will, such thynges as herein are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mis, then to depraue or discommende my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and paynes, for the fautes, seing that I haue herein, but onely made way to other that can farre better do thys or like, desyring them that as they can, so they woulde. Fare well gētle reader, &amp; accept my good will.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>