<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL CHRISTIAN Parents, and Gouernours of Families; Grace &amp; Peace be multiplied.</title>
           <author>M., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102271_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07477</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17861</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102271</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL CHRISTIAN Parents, and Gouernours of Families; Grace &amp; Peace be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>M., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Spirituall food, and physick : vis. Milke for the younger. Meat for the stronger. The substance of diuinitie. A pill to purge out poperie</title>
                 <author>Mico, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fisher, Benjamin</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 165, 9 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO ALL CHRISTIAN Parents, and Gouernours of Families; Grace &amp; Peace be multiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is (as yee know, welbeloued) the Commandement of God, that Parents should teach and instruct their children in the true Religion and worship of God, as it is to be seene in these places following, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.9.6.6.11.18, 19. <hi>Prouerbs</hi> 22.6. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6.4. Examples also there are of many that did it, as, <hi>Abraham, Dauid, &amp;c. Gen.</hi> 18.19. 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.9 <hi>Prouerbs</hi> 4.3, 4. <hi>Timothy</hi> knew the Scriptures from a child, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. &amp; that (no doubt) by the instruction of his mother, and his grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, who are commended for their faith by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. Secondly, the benefit that
<pb facs="3"/>followeth heereof, is great, <hi>Prouerbs.</hi> 22.6. And the want heereof is the cause of much euill to your children, and (many times) of great griefe to your selues. Be diligent therefore and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to performe this duty. Parents generally teach their children to say the Lords prayer, the Creede, and the ten Commandements: and it is a good and commendable thing for them so to doe. But they are not there to stay, (as if it were sufficient to say these things without booke) but to goe further, and to teach them the meaning thereof. Many aged persons there be, that can say the words, but vnderstand little or nothing thereof: nay know not so much as what the Creed is, but vse it for a prayer. The reason heerof is, they were not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nstructed in their youth. That all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (euen the simplest) may be able to teach their children the meaning of the things afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, I haue heer framed, first of all, a very short Catechisme for little ones; from the age of foure, to 6 or 7 yeeres. In which time I think there is scarce any of so weak capacitie, but may be able to learne it. Secondly, I haue framed another, fit for such as are of six or seuen, till they come to ten or twelue yeeres of age, and may in that time be easily learned: and the rather, because the first is comprehended in it.
<pb facs="3"/>Then thirdly, I haue more particularly &amp; large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly set downe the meaning of each Article of the Creede, of the Sacraments, of euery Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and of euery petition of the Lords prayer: with diuers other points necessary to be knowne of all Christians, and that before they come to bee partakers of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. And this also may the more easily be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, because the second Catechisme is included in it. And in all three I haue laboured for three things, namely, order, breuitie and plainness. For this I finde by (almost 30. yeeres) experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, (in the Ministerie) that things orderly, briefly, and plainely handled, are best remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and soonest learned: and though the Answeres bee many, yet if they bee short and plaine, both children and others will learne them with ease and delight. Concerning the method and order heere obserued, it is this:</p>
   <p>First, briefly it sheweth the benefit of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing, what it is, and what be the parts of it, <hi>Quest.</hi> 1. to <hi>Q.</hi> 8.</p>
   <p>Secondly, it sheweth what God is, and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe his workes of Creation, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, and namely, mans creation. All which are comprehended in the first Article of the Creed, <hi>Quest.</hi> 8. to 30.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, it discouereth our misery by reason
<pb facs="4"/>of sinne, <hi>Quest.</hi> 30. to 44.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, it declareth how we are redeemed from our misery, namely, by Christ, where is shewed what Christ is concerning his person, <hi>Quest.</hi> 44. to 57. Then what hee did to worke our redemption, and to make it perfect, the which is set downe in the 4.5. and 6. Articles, <hi>Quest.</hi> 57. to 74. And what is the last worke that Christ shall performe on earth, <hi>Quest.</hi> 74, 75, 76.</p>
   <p>Fiftly, it maketh knowne, how all that which Christ hath done, is made profitable to vs, <hi>Quest.</hi> 77. to 81.</p>
   <p>Sixtly, it sheweth who they are which are sanctified and ioyned to Christ, namely, the Church, and what benefits belong to the Church, <hi>Quest.</hi> 81. to 98.</p>
   <p>Seuenthly, it sheweth what is required on our behalfe, that we may be partakers of Christ and his benefits, namely, a true faith, what this faith is, how it is wrought in vs, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee are said to bee saued by faith onely, <hi>Quest.</hi> 98. to 104.</p>
   <p>Now because the Sacraments are ordained of God for the helpe of our faith, it sheweth next what these Sacraments are, what things are thereby signified and sealed to vs, and what is required to the right vse of them,
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Quest.</hi> 104. to 144. And forasmuch as that faith whereby we are iustified, is not a dead, but a liuely faith, it sheweth what this faith doth bring forth in vs, namely, repentance, and repentance good workes: what these good workes are, namely, such as God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>Quest.</hi> 144. to 159. And then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in order the meaning of the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, <hi>Quest.</hi> 159. to 247. Then after that follow certaine points concerning the Law, as whether wee can bee iustified by the workes of the Law? If not, then to what end the Law doth serue, and wherefore wee are to doe good workes, how they are to bee done, and whether they shall be rewarded of God or no? <hi>Quest.</hi> 247. to 258.</p>
   <p>Lastly, it sheweth that wee of our selues can doe no good work, but onely by the grade of God, and that the grace of God is to be obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of vs by prayer: and then followeth the meaning of the Lords prayer and what shall become of all after this life, <hi>Quest.</hi> 258. to the end.</p>
   <p>All which things are briefly, familiarly and plainely set downe by Questions and Answers that euen the simplest may easily (if they will vse the meanes) both learne and vnderstand the same. And because that in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb facs="5"/>nothing is to bee receiued, but what is plainely proued by the Scriptures, I haue at the end of almost euery Answere, quoted the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scriptures, for the proofe of the same. And the places (for the most part) are plaine and easie, as you shall finde if you turne to them. And that you may see that whatsoeuer is necessary to be knowne, beleeued and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of vs to saluation, is conteined in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I haue also set downe in order the very substance of Diuinity in Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
   <p>Lastly, to the end that all may the more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Popery, I haue added a Dialogue betweene a weake Christian, and a Minister, shewing that Popery is contrary to the very grounds of the Catholike Religion, and that therefore Papists cannot be good Catholikes. And this I haue done, not in hatred of their persons, (for I wish vnfainedly their conuersion in this world, and their saluation in the world to come) but in hatred of their false doctrine, and that the simple may not be seduced with the title and colour of Catholikes and Catholike Church. Although many sound and learned diuines haue of late yeeres fully laid open all points of Popery, and throughly confuted the same: yet the vulgar sort, eyther for want of
<pb facs="5"/>money to buy their bookes, or leysure to reade them (being for the most part verie large) or else for want of knowledge to iudge of them (being learnedly written) know not so much as what Popery is: but thinke (yea and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times speake it) that the Papists differ not much from vs, and that wee might bee easily recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled.</p>
   <p>For the good therefore of the simple and vnlearned, I haue briefly, plainely and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly set downe such speciall points, as they doe hold contrary to the very grounds of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: that so, such as yet stand, may be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the weake ones kept from embracing Popery, and such as are of late falne from vs, may (if Gods will bee such) bee reclaimed.</p>
   <p>By Papists I vnderstand such as cleaue to the Pope in religion, and are obedient vnto him. And I thinke they will not be offended with the name, no more then wee are with the name of Protestants. And in setting downe their opinions, I deale not with them, as they deale with vs, namely, charging vs with such things as wee teach not, but rather vtterly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime.</p>
   <p>As for example: There was not long since (in a certaine Citie of this kingdome) appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended a Iesuite: and among other things
<pb facs="6"/>found about him, hee had a certaine paper, wherein were 44 positions, set downe as doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines maintained by Protestants: and of these 44. almost 20 of them were grosse lies. As for example:</p>
   <p>First, that wee hold and teach, that children are saued onely by the faith of their parents without baptisme.</p>
   <p>Secondly, that one must not baptize but at a Sermon.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, that God doth not onely permit, but doth cause sinne.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, that there is no Cup of consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
   <p>Fiftly, that one may preach without being sent, with such like things; which are most notorious lies: for Protestants teach no such things, but rather the contrary. If any haue broached such doctrine, if they bee knowne, they are punished by our Church.</p>
   <p>And this hath bin their practice from time to time, in charging vs with such points of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, as were neuer allow'd of, but condemned by vs. In setting downe therefore of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, I alleadge eyther their very words, or the summe therof, and quote the places where the same are to bee found. And I doe not set downe the words of some priuate man, or of
<pb facs="6"/>such as are of no account in the Church of Rome, but of their Councell of Trent; the <hi>Rhemists, Bellarmine,</hi> and such as whose words and writings are approued and allowed of by the Church of Rome.</p>
   <p>And then at the end of euery particular point of Popery, I quote also diuers of our owne late Writers, where the points are hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led more at large: so that if any be disposed to see what they hold, and how they are confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, hee may turne to the Authors, and finde the same. And because the Papists stand so much vpon antiquitie, I haue also set downe the time when the most substantiall points of Popery came first into the Church. (See Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Abbot,</hi> in defence of the reformed Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, <hi>page</hi> 109. to 121.)</p>
   <p>There is one thing, which (it may be) some will not like of, and that is, the vsing of some homely comparisons, and pleasant conceites: but I would haue such to know, that a Pill is a very bitter thing, and therefore men (many times) before they come to swallow it, will roll it in hony, or some other sweet thing, that it may goe down the more pleasantly: and therefore I haue done the like with this my Pill, that so it may be taken with the more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. And heerein I haue done but as <hi>Elias</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>did with <hi>Baals</hi> Priests, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 18.27. and no more then <hi>Esay</hi> did with idolaters in his time, <hi>Esay</hi> 44.16.</p>
   <p>My request then to you is, that you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept these foure small mites, and employ them for your owne direction, and the good of your families. Teach your little ones the first, and then as they growe in yeeres, let them learne the rest. And heerein you are to haue a respect to the nature and condition of your children. If they be but of weake capacitie, and haue but weake memories, you are to require the lesse of them. If that you would allow them some small time in euery weeke to learne the same, and euery Lords day (after the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like exercises in the Church) you would spend but one hour, or halfe, in examining them, you shall finde, that in a few yeeres they would euen learn them all. And further, this you shal finde, that by teaching your families, you shall much profit your selues, so that when you shall heare the Catechisme expounded in the Church (as Ministers are now cōmanded to do it) you shall by this meanes vnderstand the better what is taught, and profit a great deale the more by it.</p>
   <p>You shall doe well also to reade ouer often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Texts of Scriptures (as they are set downe in order) and so you shall see how euery
<pb facs="7"/>point of doctrine (deliuerd by the Minister in Catechizing) is confirmed. And concerning the Catechisme for Catholikes, you shall doe well also sometimes to reade it, or cause your children to doe it, that so you may see what Poperie is, and accordingly take heede of it. These things if you be carefull to performe, I doubt not, but (in a short time) you shall finde great good to come heereof to your children, much comfort to your selues, and God hereby shall be glorified: to whose most blessed and holy direction, I commend you now and for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to his vttermost, <hi>I. M.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>