<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102198_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15509</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25775</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102198</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Christianity maintained. Or a discouery of sundry doctrines tending to the ouerthrovve of Christian religion: contayned in the answere to a booke entituled, mercy and truth, or charity maintayned by Catholiques</title>
                 <author>Knott, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 3-80 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ONDER not <hi>(Christian Reader)</hi> That I entitle this Little Treatise, <hi>Christianity Maintained.</hi> I giue it that Name, because that is the thing which I endeauour heer to make good, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst one who ouerthrows <hi>Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> not by remote Principles, or strained Inferences, but by direct assertions, &amp; cleere deductiōs, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally flowing from diuers of his doctrines: which if it be made appeare, I cannot but hope, that all who take comfort in the glorious, and most happy name of <hi>Christian,</hi> will giue me <hi>the right hands of fellowship</hi> in this Common Cause. Ancient Pacianus sayes<note n="(a)" place="margin">Epist. ad Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prou.</note> of euery orthodoxe belieuer, that <hi>Christian is his name, Catholicke his Surname. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke</hi> cannot be conceiued without <hi>Christian.</hi> But Christianity so long as it is maintained, wil afford some com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Principles of beliefe, which may direct men to find, that one <hi>Catholicke</hi> Church of Christians, by meanes whereof our <hi>Lord</hi> hath decreed to giue <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glory.</hi> Let ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither preiudice auert, nor priuat respects diuert the good Readers vnderstanding from weighing in an equal ballance that which is herce layd before it. God forbid any
<pb n="4" facs="6"/>Christian should exceed the desper are folly of the Iewes, who would not depose their priuat quarells, euen while they were circled with a hostile army of <hi>Romans:</hi> or be losse aduised then the Romans, who tooke occasion to make peace at home, by the pronocations of the Enemy abroad, indging it wife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be swayed with feare of greater euill, especially when they could do it, vnder the honourable title of a <hi>Common</hi>
      <note n="(c)" place="margin">Liu. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>good.</hi> In which respect, I lay asde, and as it were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get at this present, the Surname of <hi>Catholicke,</hi> while my scope is to maintaine <hi>Christianity.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> But I must notwithstanding by the way desire thee, by example of this Man whose errours I vndertake to disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that thou wilt be pleased, to reflect vpon the misery into which they do bring themselues, who forsaking in truth that glorious <hi>Surname,</hi> content themselues with the only name of <hi>Christians.</hi> For consequently hauing lost the <hi>Guift,</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> of supernaturall and infused <hi>Fayth,</hi> which in their <hi>Christendome</hi> they receaued, they lye so open to all manner of deceites, that though they be warned of them, they runne vnawares into them: because not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or not esteeming and weighing the necessity and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of a <hi>Guide,</hi> they follow the <hi>Eye</hi> of their owne <hi>Reason</hi> only, which is too short-sighted to preserue them from falling into the manifold pitfalls, which lye on all sides of Christian Fayth, as we learne by all those, who in all ages haue swarued from it.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> This Man, as the world knowes, had warning abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, in a little Treatise called, <hi>The Direction,</hi> that he <hi>should not goe a destructiue way tending to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of all Religion,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Direct. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a. 4. per totū.</note>
      <hi>no lesse then of Catholicke Doctrine.</hi> How little he hath obserued it, will appeare by the ensuing discourse, penned to the like intent, and to no
<pb n="5" facs="6"/>other, then, I dare say, the <hi>Direction</hi> was, to wit, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, or rather now, to discouer <hi>Socinianisme</hi> couertly cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping into this Kingdome vnder the shrowde of <hi>Naturall Reason.</hi> The vanome of which Sect being still, as it seemes, growing, or as I may say, compounding, it is no wonder if the enemy of mankind doth vse all his art to make that Treatise more and more odious, by which it began to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <note place="margin">The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection falsified.</note>
      <hi>3.</hi> For to what other purpose doth this man in his preface say, against all Truth, and against the word of the letter, that the Author of the <hi>Direction, fastens the</hi>
      <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. n. 7.</note>
      <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Atheisme and Irreligion vpon all wise and gallant men that are not of our owne Religion:</hi> and this in a different letter, as the very words of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectour,</hi> who yet hath neither any such words or sense. And againe, that<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. n. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>as the Samaritans saw in the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples coūtenances, that they meant to goe to Hierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, so you pretend it is euen legible in the forheads of those men, that they (that is some Protestants of worth, and learning and auctority too) are euen go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nay making hast to Rome:</hi> words set downe in a different letter, and in the same context with the other words of the <hi>Direction,</hi> which yet hath not any one such word, or syllable. And the Author was farre from presuming to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the intentions of those persons, with whom this man would make him odious.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> He neither commended, nor discommended, nor so much as considered their <hi>vicinity</hi> to vs. His purpose was to shew that for want of some <hi>publicke infallible Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> they could not possibly auoyd frequent variations, by which whether they fell to come neerer to vs, or to go fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from vs, was not materiall to his purpose. Let altars be
<pb n="4" facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="5" facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb n="6" facs="8"/>demolished to morrow, let pictures be defaced, let all that is done be vndone; These last alterations will prooue his intent as strongly as the others can, wherein they happen to agree with vs. For his scope being to discouer the impietyes of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and to preuent the hurt of soules by forewarning them of the danger; to this end he declared some of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons for which this Sect disperseth it selfe, and is able to do it, by working vpon the minds of diuers Protestants. The chiefest he affirmed to be the want of a publicke infallible Iudge of Controuersyes, without which they are left to their owne <hi>priuate</hi> spirît, or wit, and discourse, which must of necessity bring forth a multitude of differences, alterca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and alterations, and end in <hi>Socinianisme,</hi> the quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tessence whereof is to resolue <hi>Fayth into Opinion,</hi> or into euery mans owne <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Persuasion.</hi> Now to shew that for want of some liuing <hi>Guide,</hi> alterations in matters of <hi>Fayth</hi> and Religion must needes be frequent, he alle ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged such instances, as lay open to the knowledge, and euen to the eye of euery man, and might afford a more sensible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration of what he intended to euince: Yet so, that (as I said before) his Argument receaued strength, not from their comming neere to vs, but from their altering from themselues. From thence to inferre, that they must intend Popery, because they happen to agree with vs in some things or rather seeme to agree, but indeed differ; is iust as if one should say: The first Protestants in England, intended to persist in Papistry, euen when they purposed the contrary, yea euen when they did actually depart from vs: Because (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooth) they were not so furious against euery particular do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Catholicks, as some others were. And I wonder how these men dare belieue the B. Trinity, and other princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall mysteries of Christian Fayth, since they must by this
<pb n="7" facs="8"/>meanes agree with Papists, and so may feare least them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues be in a way to Popery.</p>
   <p n="5">
      <hi>5.</hi> Others are apt to belieue on the contrarie side, that the <hi>Directour</hi> was so farre from hoping that Protestants would become Catholicks by these degrees, as that he rather feared it might be a cause of some temptation to Catholicks, and a setling of Protestancy more effectually then could haue been performed either by the feruour of Zelots, or feare of Death, or any other meanes. And therfore I make bold to say, that although we Catholicks, his Maiesties most humble and loyall subiects, should be most vnworthy and vngratefull creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, if we did not with deepest thankefulnes acknowledge our infinite obligation to the tender Clemency of our dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne: Yet I may truly say (if such a Truth may be spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken without offence) that by many degrees They are more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable, and vnthankefull, who are vnquiet, because the most moderate, that is, the most powerfull meanes which can be thought of, are put in execution, for establishing that which they pretend to desire, I meane the Protestant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; vnlesse indeed they desire Protestancy should perish, if it do not in all respects perfectly and punctually sute with their humours. For it is a true saying; Moderate things may last, but no Violence can long endure.</p>
   <p n="6">
      <hi>6.</hi> This then was the <hi>Directours</hi> intention, free from all malignity, and directed only to matters of Religion, and good of soules in the manner declared aboue. Which to be true, I haue heard him affirme most seriously by all that can be feared, or hoped for in the next life, for all eternity; and therefore he could not but be sorry, that any writing of his was interpreted to an other meaning, of which if he had but once imagined his words to haue been capable, himselfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out so much as hearing any plea of defense, would haue been
<pb n="8" facs="9"/>the first to haue sentenced them to be destroyed, and all me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of them to be forgotten. And he hopes that upon this sincere declaration it will be belieued, that if he erred, it was against his owne intention, and not, <hi>a more erroris, sed er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore amoris</hi> (as Blessed <hi>S. Austine</hi> speakes) <hi>not by any loue to errour,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>22.</hi> Cinit. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>but by an errour of loue,</hi> to the eternall good of soules, by preuenting the daunger of their falling into precipices of <hi>Socinian</hi> doctrines.</p>
   <p n="7">
      <hi>7.</hi> But the foule Imputation wherewith, euen in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle Dedicatory to the Kings most Excel. Maiesty, this man is bold to calumniate the whole Order of Iesuites, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent doubtlesse to make the <hi>Directour,</hi> and his endeauours hatefull, (tearming it, <hi>that Order which enuenomes poison it selfe, and makes the Roman Religion more malignant and turbulent then otherwise it would be: whose very Rule and Doctrine obliges them to make all men, as much as lyes in them, subiects vnto Kings, &amp; seruants vnto Christ no further then it shall please the Pope</hi>) is a most virulent slaunder, and most vniust vntruth. For the cleering whereof, though we might content our selues either with his ignorance of our <hi>Order, Rule,</hi> and <hi>Doctrine;</hi> or with the guiltinesse of his owne Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, in regard, that probably he cannot choose but know, that the intent of them, and our proceedings, are nothing such as he proclaymes them: yet I thought fit here to touch briefly some grounds, whereby his Maiesty chiefly, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may receaue satisfaction, that there is no such thing in our <hi>Order, Rule,</hi> and <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as this man is pleased to cast vpon it.</p>
   <p n="8">
      <hi>8.</hi> And first (in regard, by what he sayth in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, of the <hi>fourth Vow</hi> which the Iesuits make <hi>of spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall obedience to the Pope, proper to their Order,</hi> it
<pb n="9" facs="9"/>seemes, that which he doth vent in his Epistle Dedicatory, hath relation to that <hi>VOW</hi>) it is to be vnderstood, that, that <hi>Fourth VOW</hi> is wholy <hi>circa Missiones, concerning Missions,</hi> in order to the help of soules,<note place="margin">Constit. part. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi> L. C.</note> as the words of that <hi>Vow</hi> expressely speake, and their <hi>Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions</hi> declare thus: <hi>Tota intentio huius Voti Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diendi Summo Pontifici fuit, &amp; est circa Missiones, &amp; sic intelligi oportet liter as Apostolicas, vbide hae Obedientia loquūtur, in omnibus quae iufferit Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Pontifex, &amp; quocunq miferit &amp;c. The whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of this Vow to obey the Pope, was, &amp; is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Missions, and so the Apostolicall Letters are to be vnderstood, where they speake of this Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, in all things which the Pope shall commaund, and whithersoeuer he shall send &amp;c.</hi> As for their <hi>Rules</hi> in generall, they are confirmed by the same Authority, which confirmed the Rules of all Religions Orders, and there is nothing in them which is not most holy, and which hath not been accounted such, euen by our Enemies: or if there be any thing to be found in them otherwise, let this man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it if be can. They are not so hard to come by, but that S. Paules Churchyard may of times afford them. <hi>Doctrine</hi> their Order approoues none but what is taught by other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Diuines, as hath been often demonstrated against such as this man is. And therefore we hold our selues bound in all duety to be, and to professe our selues to be, as loyall subiects to the soueraigne <hi>Maiesty of our King,</hi> as louing and tender towards his <hi>Sacred Person,</hi> as respectfull and dutifull to his <hi>Commaunds,</hi> as any other of his subiects of what profession soeuer; and to be bound also to teach all other subiects, that the same subiection is due, not only <hi>for feare,</hi> but <hi>for Conscience</hi> also, by the law of <hi>God,</hi> of <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
      <pb n="10" facs="10"/>and <hi>of Nations.</hi> This we shall be ready to make good at all times; as also to giue his <hi>Maiesty</hi> full satisfaction, by what meanes his <hi>Maiesty</hi> shall be pleased to appoint, in any particular point of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> or <hi>Practise,</hi> which is, or may be imputed to our <hi>Rule,</hi> or <hi>Order.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="9">
      <hi>9.</hi> It were ouer great boldnesse to appeale in this to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing testimony of him, who in his experience abroad hath beene acquainted with more <hi>Communities</hi> of our <hi>Order,</hi> then this man hath beene with <hi>Persons</hi> in his late chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges when he professed himselfe a <hi>Roman Catholicke,</hi> and conuersed with diuers of vs: And by the equall hand which he carryeth towards all sorts of persons, obligeth all without preiudice to any. His Maiesty may be pleased to vse what meanes in his Royall wisedome he shall thinke best. And if he should thinke it fit to pitch vpon such a Testimony, we should esteeme our selues happy in the choyce; notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that <hi>M. Chillingworth</hi> may conceaue otherwise, in regard that he wilneeds haue it, that <hi>Signor Con</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited the Directour from writing bookes any more,<note place="margin">Pref. n. <hi>25.</hi>
      </note> or at least, <hi>hath reason to do it.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="10">
      <hi>10.</hi> But he must know, that we are of a different disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and therefore though that Person were not of that eminent Integrity, Piety, wisedome, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty, and all kind of worth as he is, who by so many wayes hath obliged many great Persons to our nation, and howerly receiues a most gracious regard from those whose iudgment and example all should dread, we esteeme it a great happinesse to be subiect to all lawfull Auctorities. And whatsoeuer our skill be in Logicke, yet by Gods grace we will alwayes in hart, word, and deed maintaine these to be good and lawfull Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments: A Person of so eminent wisedome as he is whom this man names, <hi>aduises</hi> me not to write; Therefore it is <hi>fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test</hi>
      <pb n="11" facs="10"/>for me not to write. And this other: A Person endued with Authority, <hi>commandes</hi> me not to write: Therefore it is not only <hi>fit,</hi> but <hi>necessary</hi> for me not to write. But this Logicke is no Philosophy with <hi>Socinians,</hi> who will haue no Maisters' but themselues, euen in matters concerning the eternall saluation of their soules, and will one day find to their cost, that Holy <hi>S Bernard</hi> vttered a most important Truth when he said: <hi>Qui se sibi Magistrum constituit, stul to se Discipulum subdit. He who will be his owne Maister, shall be scholler to a foole.</hi> But it is time for me to take vp &amp; conclude this Preface with this caueat, that I would not haue the Reader cōceiue that in this litle volume I haue touched all this mans Doctrines which tend to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of <hi>Christianity,</hi> but only such as were most obuious. Nor is it my purpose at this time, exactly to cōfute his groūds or answere his obiections, which may be done hereafter. My maine busines is to demonstrate, that vnder the Name of <hi>Christians,</hi> he vndermines <hi>Christianity,</hi> and setles <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianisme.</hi> Which is the cause that mooued me to set forth this short Treatise for a present Antidote, till a larger ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were can be published. For who will aduenture vpon food if be know it is mixed, and euen incorporated with deadly poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son? This is the scope of this Treatise, whereto I hope all Christians will concurre. <hi>Socinians</hi> are but an aggregate of <hi>Iewes, Manicheans, Arians,</hi> and other condemned sects, which all good <hi>Christians</hi> ought to detest. I hartily with their Conuersion: yet if they will obstinately resist, in despite of their inuentions the words of the Apostle will be verified, <hi>Iesus Christ yesterday, and to day,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>the same also for euer.</hi> And they shall giue a fearefull account for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of al Churches, and errours against <hi>Christian Fayth,</hi> when repentance will nothing auaile: Euen at that day, when
<pb n="12" facs="11"/>as <hi>S. Ambrose</hi> grauely sayth:<note place="margin">Lib. 5. de fide c. 7.</note>
      <hi>The Iew shall perforce ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge whom he crucified; when the Manichean shall adore whom he belieued not to haue come in flesh; when the Arian shall confesse him to be omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent whom he denied.</hi> And I may adde; when all good <hi>Christians</hi> shall ioyfully behold him, whose <hi>Fayth</hi> they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to <hi>Maintaine.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>