<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE OF THE AVTHOR TO MASTER IOHN RIDER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102272_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00919</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11025</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102272</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE OF THE AVTHOR TO MASTER IOHN RIDER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Catholike confutation of M. Iohn Riders clayme of antiquitie : and a caulming comfort against his caueat. In which is demonstrated, by assurances, euen of protestants, that al antiquitie, for al pointes of religion in controuersie, is repugnant to protestancie. Secondly that protestancie is repugnant particularlie to al articles of beleefe. Thirdly, that puritan plots are pernitious to religion, and state. And lastly, a replye to M. Riders Rescript; with a discouerie of puritan partialitie in his behalfe. By Henry Fitzimon of Dublin in Irland, of the Societie of Iesus, priest</title>
                 <author>Fitzsimon, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Auroi (Ouroy), Pierre.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>34, 394, 28, 2, 118 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE OF THE AVTHOR TO MASTER IOHN RIDER.</head>
   <p>WOrshipful M. <hi>Rider.</hi> You haue this Aunswer, yf later then expected, yet I assure my selfe sooner then affected: So that as an vngratefull guest, it preuenteth all wellcome. You might haue had it long befor, but that your inuitation therof was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the new requesting frends to meales; with many capps, and verbal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>urtesie, but without intertaynment, charitie, or hospitalitie. For you prouoked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e to labour it, but debarred me to publish it. And noe merueile: for you knew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t to be that it is; to wit, a hand wryting to <hi>Balthazar; Mane, Thechel, Phares; Daniel</hi> to a licentiouse Iudge, conuerting his iniquitie vpon his owne head; And (that I may not be a tedious reherser of what you feele better then I can expresse) a <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Goliath,</hi> by his owne swoord beheading him, and destroying tenn thowsand of his compagnions. Not that I impute any woorth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or weight, to my cooperation therin: but that the cause it defendeth is so inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnable, as lyke a firme rock, it crusheth them that fall on it, and oppresseth them on whom it falleth. You might haue bene thought wyse yf you had houlden your peace. For men of your sorte, hauing a negatiue religion, are commonly satisfyed to carpe at our sayings, without care to iustifie their owne, and but by extremitie, to specifie any positiue doctrin, that they may haue libertie to change at will. But you would be a more venturouse Caualiero then the residue: let all the world iudge, whether it was for any extraordinarie wys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or sufficiēcie, if you, who among thowsands were most vnfit, haue professed playne decretal positions, repugnant not only to all christianitie, but (which ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily by you is more esteemed) to all your owne confraternie; or rather (because you continualy iarr) to your confederated diuersitie. So that many of your most iudicious surmisers mistrust, that by some promised promotion of papists, you had praeiudiced, and in a maner betrayed your profession to infamie, and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, &amp; of sett purpose, by so discouering many defectiue articles, and enorme absurdities therof, which to our owne contryes can not choose but cause à dislyke, yf not a loathsomnes, and surfet, and being notifyed to other contryes, (which had bene done, yf I had not altered my purpose only for better concealing for what friuolous futilities the Catholick fayth in Christ Iesus is exchanged, by wryting in our vulgar toung, what I first intended to haue written in latin)
<pb facs="14"/>
would produce in them ether a disdayne toward vs, or deploration against our estate, that so many good dispositions, and otherwyse deepe capacities, are so mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serably miscaryed by so base, and deceitfull delusions, palpablie perceauable euen to winking eyes. I assure you no mans death I know, had bene vnto me more vnwished before this my awnswer published, least it had bene suspected, or excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that I had imposed your owne printed assertions, vpon your profession. But my synceritie will appeare perspicuously, by inserting your booke intirely, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordantly to your <hi>Dublinian</hi> edition; which can not be imagined to haue bene a deede of any other then your selfe. You haue great and sundrie causes to be thankfull for this my awnswer. First, because it displayeth seueral dangerouse errours, by which you would haue eternally perished, and now by reclayming them, yf you please, you may escape. Secondly, that by it the sharper reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and refutation of others who would and might more disdaynfully reproue you, is perhapp anticipated, and hindred. Thirdly, that for sparing fauor toward you, many slips are indulgently dissembled, and such as are detected, in the most milde style that might possiblie belong to maters of lyke qualitie, are prosecuted. I cowld calculate others, yf I attended deserued gratitude in one of your disposition, or education. Howsoeuer you will interpret kinde and beneficious offices, I will incessantly implore Gods infinit mercie toward you, and your complices, that he would open your obstinat eyes, and mollifie your hardned harts, and mitigat his incensed wrath against you: wherby you may vnderstand your errours, abandon your heresies, cease to diuide the Churche and scattre Christs Catholick flock, being by so pretious redemption formerly vnited; And finaly, that being myndfull whence you are fallen, you repent, and returne to your first workes, least your candlestyke be remoued, and for want of true light, fall into that infidelitie of all Christian religion, which in <hi>Africk, Grece,</hi> and other places, immediatly succeded opinions begon, and stifflye retrayned, against the Apostolick, Romain, and Catholick beleefe. God graunt. Fare yee well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>