<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST GRATIOVS AND Reuerende Father in God, Iohn by the prouidence of God, Lord Archbishop of Canterburie, Primate and Metropolitane of all England, and one of the Lords of her Ma∣iesties most honourable priuie Counsell.</title>
           <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102692_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01291</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11414</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102692</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST GRATIOVS AND Reuerende Father in God, Iohn by the prouidence of God, Lord Archbishop of Canterburie, Primate and Metropolitane of all England, and one of the Lords of her Ma∣iesties most honourable priuie Counsell.</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pandectes of the law of nations : contayning seuerall discourses of the questions, points, and matters of law, wherein the nations of the world doe consent and accord. Giuing great light to the vnderstanding and opening of the principall obiects, questions, rules, and cases of the ciuill law, and common law of this realme of England. Compiled by William Fulbecke</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wight, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 90 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="129"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST GRATIOVS AND Reuerende Father in God, Iohn by the prouidence of God, Lord Archbishop of Canterburie, Primate and Metropolitane of all England, and one of the Lords of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties most honourable priuie Counsell.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight reuerend, and right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, it is now a twelue-month past sithence I presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to your Grace a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue discourse of the lawes: A subiect deseruing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious search of some di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing braine, by mee superficially handled, and as it were left to others to be complementally perfected: but sithence by good successe and the fauour of the Almightie it hath gained the approbation of men skilfull and learned, who haue perswaded and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged mee to make further progresse in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse, least I might seeme coy in weighing lightly
<pb facs="130"/> their frendly speeches, &amp; careles in refusing so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant a taske, though to me importable, as being the club of <hi>Hercules</hi> laid vpon the sholders of <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi> I haue again aduentured vpon this cumber some prouince, and drawne other furrowes in this stony soile: and as I haue continued the worke, so haue I continued the dedication thereof in all constant ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruance to your Lordship, whose regardfull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance toward me hath merited more at my hands then such worthlesse paines, rather by the trauaile of my pen, and the practicke of my contemplation, to publish and notifie to the worlde my dutifull thankfull and zealefull affection toward your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces person, then by the vnfeatured lumpe and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportioned bearewhelpe of my misconceyuing, &amp; miscarying endeuour, to platforme a consummate and exemplarie Parallele or Trinomion, which is an obiect to be aymed at, and a pray to be pursued; not of the Stonegall, the Muskette, and the Merlin, but of the Eagle, the Goshauke, and other birdes of an higher wing, and more surmounting flight: and for the accomplishment thereof it were to be wished, that God would vouchsafe our Innes of Court with some second <hi>Budaeus,</hi> that is a third <hi>Varro,</hi> whose skill in the lawes might bee exquisite, whose paines extreme, whose reward excellent: for mine owne parte though I bee rather a rash then a voluntarie soldier in this campe, yet I am bound by conscience not to eate the bread of idlenes, to do for my country what I can, and to labour in my calling as I may.
<pb facs="130"/> And whatsoeuer this Booke is, or whatsoeuer my selfe am, or whatsoeuer my prayer may preuaile with Almightie God, all these, if these be anie thing, doe with the knee of submissiue reuerence professe vassallage to your Lordship. And if the Heauens would sympathize with my hart, and my hart should not by pleasing my selfe, and others, displease your Grace, the verie Heauens should be long without you, that this land may be long the better for your Lordship. The God of heauen graunt this, if it be his will, for Learninges sake, <hi>Quae duplices tendens ad sydera palmas,</hi> prayeth for the same: <hi>Vertue</hi> prayeth for the same: Straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers pray for the same: <hi>Beneficence</hi> to the riche: <hi>Munificence</hi> to the poore, craue the same: The Church with sacred vowes: The Common weale with more then common wishes implore the same. What period can be better then prayer? Therefore here I cast anchor, and bind vp these spreading lines.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to commaund: WILLIAM FVLBECKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>