<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the frindly Reader Vlpian Fullwell wisheth health.</title>
           <author>Fulwell, Ulpian</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102758_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01354</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11475</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102758</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the frindly Reader Vlpian Fullwell wisheth health.</title>
                 <author>Fulwell, Ulpian</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The flovver of fame : Containing the bright renowne, &amp; moste fortunate raigne of King Henry the viii. Wherein is mentioned of matters, by the rest of our cronographers ouerpassed. Compyled by Vlpian Fulwell. Hereunto is annexed (by the aucthor) a short treatice of iii. noble and vertuous queenes. And a discourse of the worthie seruice that was done at Hadington in Scotlande, the seconde yere of the raigne of king Edward the sixt</title>
                 <author>Fulwell, Ulpian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 <publisher>Bamford, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hoskins, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 59, 1 leave, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the frindly Reader Vlpian Fullwell wisheth health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE wyse &amp; sage Philosopher <hi>Solon,</hi> noting the insolencie of <hi>Cressus,</hi> who esteemed him self the happiest man ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, because of his abundant welth, tolde him, that no man is to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted happie during his lyfe tyme, because he kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not whether it shall ende with renowne or infamie. Concluding hereby, that a goodly lyfe, &amp; a godly death maketh a perfect happie man.</p>
   <p>Nowe, seing our late soueraigne Lorde Kynge <hi>Henrye</hi> the eyghth, hath hit the marke of trewe felicitie, and wonne the game of ioyfull immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: what ruthe were it, that so singuler an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample shoulde not be recorded in the golden booke of perpetuall Fame. His noble lyfe, his Godly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedinges, his inuicted raygne, his fortunate suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, his whole race of lyfe, and ende of the same, deserueth to be engraued in letters of pure Golde. If <hi>Alexander</hi> (the myghtie Monarche of <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don)</hi> was offended with a Schoolemaster in whose Schoole he founde not the fame of <hi>Vlisses</hi> (written by <hi>Homer)</hi> howe much more maye wee deeme he woulde checke and reproue all Englyshe Gentlemen, that laye not before their faces the
<pb facs="5"/>
booke of King <hi>Henryes</hi> lyfe, if he were nowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs. But happely it will be sayd vnto mee, Sir, if you weare as good an Englyshe Poet as <hi>Homer</hi> was in Greeke: or if the worthinesse of your style were comparable to the matter, wee would the better esteeme of your woorke. If that bee thy obiection (gentle Reader) I cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse my selfe. For I confesse I haue not the gifte of flowing eloquence, neyther can I enterlace my phrase with Italian termes, nor powder my style with frenche Englishe or Inkhorne Rhethoricke, neyther cowche my matter vnder a cloake of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inuentions, to feede the daintie eares of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate yonkers. And as I cannot: So if I could, I woulde not. For I see that manye men are so affected with these premisses, that manye good matters are obscured, the Aucthors encombred, the woorkes but meanely commended, and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der deceaued. For while he coueteth to come to the purpose, he is lead amasked in the wylde Desert of circumstance and digression, seeking farre and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding little, feeding his humor on pleasant woordes of slender wayght, guyded (or rather giddyed) with plaucible eloquence.</p>
   <p>I do not herein condempne, neither discomende the noble Science of Rhethorike, nor the eloquent Rhethoritian, but rather wishe that excellent skill to be employed onlye on such matters as may both commende the speaker, and the thing spoken, or the writer and the thing written: hauing alwayes
<pb facs="5"/>
the cheefe respect to tyme &amp; place. For as it would sounde verye absurde to the eares of the skilfull Musitian to heare a gallyard, or any other daunce playde on the solemne Organs: So no lesse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie is it, to daunce after an Hymn or other cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning voluntarie. Thus (gentle Reader) I desyre at thy handes, that thou accept the matter, &amp; beare w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> my crabbed meeter. Considering well that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes is founde good graffes vppon a Crab tree stocke. Take then the fruite, and accepte my good will. And if thou list bestowe anye fyling vpon the roughnes of my phrase, I shall bee beholding vnto thee. If not, yet shall my desyre be satisfied with thy good worde.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Vlpianus Fulwell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>