<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER TREATING OF THESE THREE POINTS: OF THE TRANS∣LATION OF HOLY SCRIPTVRES INTO THE vulgar tongues, and namely into English: of the causes vvhy this nevv Testament is translated ac∣cording to the auncient vulgar Latin text: &amp; of the maner of translating the same.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102491_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16049</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2884</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102491</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER TREATING OF THESE THREE POINTS: OF THE TRANS∣LATION OF HOLY SCRIPTVRES INTO THE vulgar tongues, and namely into English: of the causes vvhy this nevv Testament is translated ac∣cording to the auncient vulgar Latin text: &amp; of the maner of translating the same.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Nevv Testament of Iesus Christ, translated faithfully into English, out of the authentical Latin : according to the best corrected copies of the same, diligently conferred vvith the Greeke and other editions in diuers languages; vvith arguments of bookes and chapters, annotations, and other necessarie helpes, for the better vnderstanding of the text, and specially for the discouerie of the corruptions of diuers late translations, and for cleering the controversies in religion, of these daies: in the English College of Rhemes</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Foigny, Jean de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Reims</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 745, 27 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER TREATING OF THESE THREE POINTS: OF THE TRANS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATION OF HOLY SCRIPTVRES INTO THE vulgar tongues, and namely into English: of the causes vvhy this nevv Testament is translated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the auncient vulgar Latin text: &amp; of the maner of translating the same.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE holy Bible long since translated by vs into English, and the old Testament lying by vs for lacke of good meanes to publish the vvhole in such sort as a vvorke of so great charge and importance requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: vve haue yet through Gods goodnes at length fully finished for thee (most Christian reader) all the NEVV TESTAMENT, vvhich is the principal, most profitable &amp; comfortable peece of holy vvritte: and, as vvel for all other institution of life and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, as specially for deciding the doubtes of these daies, more propre and pregnant then the other part not yet printed.</p>
   <p>Vvhich translation vve doe not for all that publish,<note place="margin">Translation of the Scriptures into the vulgar tōgues, not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie or profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the time.</note> vpon erroneous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of necessitie, that the holy Scriptures should alvvaies be in our mother tonge, or that they ought, or vvere ordained by God, to be read indifferently of all, could be easily vnderstood of euery one that readeth or heareth them in a knovven language: or that they vvere not often through mans malice or infirmitie, pernicious and much hurtful to many: or that vve generally and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely deemed it more conuenient in it self, &amp; more agreable to Gods word and honour or edification of the faithful, to haue them turned into vulgar tonges, then to be kept &amp; studied only in the Ecclesiastical learned languages: Not for these nor any such like causes doe vve translate this sacred booke, but vpon special consideration of the present time, state, and condition of our countrie, vnto vvhich, diuers thinges are either necessarie, or profitable and medicinable novv, that othervvise in the peace of the Church vvere neither much requisite, nor perchance vvholy tolerable.</p>
   <p>In this matter,<note place="margin">The Churches vvisedom and moderatiō con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cering vulgar translation.</note> to marke onely the vvisedom &amp; moderatiō of holy Church and the gouernours thereof on the one side, and the indiscerete zeale of the
<pb facs="3"/> popular, and their factious leaders, on the other, is a high point of prudence, These later, partly of simplicitie, partly of curiositie, and specially of pride and disobedience, haue made claime in this case for the common people, vvith plausible pretences many, but good reasons none at all. The other,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 24, 45, 1 Cor. 4, 1.</note> to vvhom Christ hath giuen charge of our soules, tho dispensing of Gods mysteries and treasures (among vvhich holy Scripture is no smale store) and the feeding his familie in season vvith foode fit for euery sort, haue neither of old nor of late, euer vvholy condemned all vulgar versions of Scripture, nor haue at any time generally forbidden the faithful to reade the same: yet they haue not by pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike authoritie prescribed, commaunded, or authentically euer recommended any such interpretation to be indifferently vsed of all men.</p>
   <p>The Armenians say they haue the Psalter and some other peeces translated by S. Chrysostom into their language,<note place="margin">The Scriptures in the vulgar languages of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers nations.</note> vvhen he vvas banished among them:<note place="margin">Bib. Sāct. li. 4.</note> and George the Patriarch,<note place="margin">Hiero, ep. 134.</note> in vvriting his life, signifieth no lesse. The Saluo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians affirme they haue the Scriptures in their vulgar tongue, turned by S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom, and some vvould gather so much by his ovvne vvordes in his epistle to Sophronius,<note place="margin">Bib. Sāct. lib. 4.</note> but the place in deede proueth in not. Vulpilas surely gaue the Scriptures to the Gothes in their ovvne tonge, and that before he vvas an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian.<note place="margin">Aūcient Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like translations of the Bible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Italian, Frenche, &amp; En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish tongue.</note> It is almost three hundred yeres, since Iames Archbishop of Genua, is said to haue translated the Bible into Italian. More then tvvo hundred yeres agoe, in the daies of Charles the fifth, the Frenche king, vvas it put forth faithfully in Frenche, the sooner to shake out of the deceiued peoples hādes, the false he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical translations of a secte called <hi>Vvaldenses.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Li. 1 hist. Angl. c. 1.</note> In our ovvne countrie, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the Latin tonge vvas euer (to vse Venerable Bedes vvordes) common to all the prouinces of the same for meditation or studie of Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and no vulgar translation commonly vsed or occupied of the multitude, yet they vvere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>xtant in English euen before the troubles that Vvicleffe and his folovvers raised in our Church, as appeareth, as well by some peeces yet remaining,<note place="margin">An aunciēt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincial cōstitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in England concerning En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>See Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvod li. 5 tit. de Magistris.</hi>
      </note> as by a prouincial Constitution of Thomas Arundel Archbishop of Canturburie, in a Councel holden at Oxford. vvhere straite prouision vvas made, that no heretical version set forth by Vvicleffe, or his adherentes, should be suffered, nor any other in or after his time be published or permitted to be readde, being not approued and allovved by the Diócesan before: alleaging S. Hierom for the difficultie and danger of interpreting the holy Scripture out of one tonge into an other, though by learned and Catholike men. So also it is there insinuated, that neither the Translations set forth before that Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes time, nor other aftervvard being approued by the lavvful Ordinaries, were euer in our countrie wholy forbidden, though they were not (to say the truth) in quiet and better times (much lesse when the people vvere prone to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teratiō, heresie, or noueltie) either hastily admitted, or ordinarily readde of the vulgar, but vsed onely, or specially, of some deuout religious and contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues persons, in reuerence, secrecie, and silence, for their spiritual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte.</p>
   <p>Now since Luthers reuolt also,<note place="margin">The like Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and vulgar translations in many coūtries, since Luthers time.</note> diuers learned Catholikes, for the more speedy abolishing of a number of false and impious translations put forth by sundry sectes, and for the better preseruation or reclaime of many good soules endangered thereby, haue published the Bible in the seueral languages of almost all the principal prouinces of the Latin Church: no other bookes in the world being so pernicious as hereticall translations of the Scriptures, poiso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the people vnder colour of diuine authoritie, &amp; not many other remedies
<pb facs="3"/> being more soueraine against the same (if it be vsed in order, discretion, and humilitie) then the true, faithful, and sincere interpretation opposed therevnto.</p>
   <p>Vvhich causeth the holy Church not to forbid vtterly any Catholike trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,<note place="margin">The Churches order &amp; deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatiō concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like translatiōs of the Bible in vulgar tōgues.</note> though she allow not the publishing or reading of any absolutely and without exception, or limitation: knowing by her diuine and most sincere wisedom, how, where, when, and to whom these her Maisters and Spouses giftes are to be bestowed to the most good of the faithful: and therfore neither generally permitteth that which must needes doe hurt to the vnworthy, nor absolutely condemneth that which may doe much good to the worthie. Vvherevpon, the order which many a wise man wished for before, was taken by the Deputies of the late famous Councel of Trent in this behalfe,<note place="margin">Ind. lib. prohibit. regula 4.</note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by supreme authoritie, that the holy Scriptures, though truely and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikely translated into vulgar tonges, yet may not be indifferētly readde of all men, nor of any other then such as haue expresse licence therevnto of their lawful Ordinaries, with good testimonie from their Curates or Confessors, that they be humble, discrete and deuout persons, and like to take much good, and no harme thereby. Vvhich prescript, though in these daies of ours it can not be so precisely obserued, as in other times &amp; places, where there is more due respecte of the Churches authoritie, rule, and discipline: yet, we trust all wise and godly persons will vse the matter in the meane while, with such modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, meekenes, and subiection of hart, as the handling of so sacred a booke, the sincere senses of Gods truth therein, &amp; the holy Canons, Councels, reason, and religion do require.</p>
   <p>Vvherein, though for due preseruation of this diuine worke from abuse and prophanation, and for the better bridling of the intolerable insolencie of proude, curious, &amp; contentious wittes, the gouernours of the Church guided by Gods Spirit,<note place="margin">The holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures neuer read of al persons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently, at their pleasure.</note> as euer before, so also vpon more experience of the maladie of this time the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> before, haue taken more exacte order both for the readers and translatours in these later ages, then of old: yet we must not imagin that in the primitiue Church, either euery one that vnderstoode the learned tonges wherein the Scriptures were written, or other languages into which they were translated, might without reprehension, reade, reason, dispute, turne and tosse the Scriptures: or that our forefathers suffered euery schole-maister, scholer, or Grammarian that had a litle Greeke or Latin, straight to take in hand the holy Testament: or that the translated Bibles into the vulgar tonges, were in the handes of euery husbandman, artificer, prentice, boies, girles, mistresse, maide, man: that they were sung, plaies, alleaged, of euery tinker, tauerner, rimer, minstrel: that they were for table talke, for alebenches, for boates and barges, and for euery prophane person and companie. No, in those better times men were neither so ill, nor so curious of them selues, so to abuse the blessed booke of Christ: neither was there any such easy meanes before printing was inuented, to disperse the copies into the handes of euery man, as now there is.</p>
   <p>They were then in Libraries,<note place="margin">Vvhere and in vvhose handes the Scriptures vvere in the primitiue Church.</note> Monasteries, Colleges, Churches, in Bishops, Priests, and some other deuout principal L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y mens houses and handes: who vsed them with seare and reuerence, and specially such partes as perteined to good life and maners, not medling, but in pulpit and schooles (and that mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately to) with the hard and high mysteries and places of greater difficultie. The poore ploughman, could then in labouring the ground, sing the hymnes
<pb facs="4"/> and psalmes either in knowen or vnknowen languages,<note place="margin">Hovv the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> of those daies did read them, vvith what hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of life and maners.</note> as they heard them in the holy Church, though they could neither reade nor know the sense, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and mysteries of the same. Such holy persons of both sexes, to whom S. Hierom in diuers Epistles to them, commendeth the reading and meditation of holy Scriptures, were diligent to searche all the godly histories &amp; imitable examples of chastitie, humilitie, obedience, clemencie, pouertie, penance, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noūcing the world▪ they noted specially the places that did breede the hatred of sinne, feare of Gods iudgement, delight in spiritual cogitations: they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred them selues in all hard places, to the iudgement of the auncient fathers and their maisters in religion, neuer presuming to contend, controule, teach or talke of their owne sense and phantasie, in deepe questions of diuinitie. Then the Virgins, did meditate vpon the places and examples of chastitie, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie and demurenesse: the maried, on coniugal faith and continencie: the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, how to bring vp their children in faith and seare of God: the Prince, how to rule: the subiect, how to obey: the Priest, how to teach: the people, how to learne.</p>
   <p>Then the scholer taught not his maister,<note place="margin">The fathers sharply repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend as an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>use, that al indifferenly should reade, expound, and talke of the Scriptures.</note> the sheepe controuled not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor, the yong student set not the Doctor to schoole, not reproued their fathers of error &amp; ignorance. Or if any were in those better daies (as in al times of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie such must needes be) that had itching eares, tikling tonges and wittes, curious and contentious disputers, hearers, and talkers rather then doers of Gods word: such the Fathers did euer sharply reprehend, counting them vnworthy and vnprofitable readers of the holy Scriptures. S. Hierom in his Epistle to Paulinus, after declaration that no handy craft is so base, nor liberall science so easy, that can be had without a maister (which S. Augustine also affirmeth,<note place="margin">Hiero. ep. 103<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 6.</note>
      <hi>De vtilitate cred. cap. 7.)</hi> nor that men presume in any occupation to teach that they neuer learned, <hi>Only</hi> (saith he) <hi>the art of Scripture is that vvhich euery man chalengeth: this the chatting old vvife, this the doting old man, this the brabling sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, this on euery hand, men presume to teach before they learne it.</hi> Againe, <hi>Some vvith poise of lofty vvordes deuise of scripture matters among vvomen: othersome (phy vpon it) learne of vvomen, vvhat to teach men, and lest that be not ynough, by facilitie of tong, or rather audacitie, teach that to others, vvhich they vnderstand neuer a vvhit them selues. to say nothing of such as be of my facultie: vvho stepping from secular learning to holy scriptures, and able to tickle the eares of the multitude vvith a smothe tale, thinke all they speake, to be the Law of God.</hi> This he wrote then, when this maladie of arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie and presumption in diuine matters, vvas nothing so outragious as now it is.</p>
   <p>S. Gregorie Nazianzene made an oration of the moderation that vvas to be vsed in these matters:<note place="margin">In orat. de moderatio. in disputa. seruanda.</note> where he saith, that some in his time thought them selues to haue all the wisedom in the world, when they could once repeat tvvo or three wordes, and them ill couched together, out of Scriptures, but he there diuinely discourseth of the orders and differences of degrees: how in Christes mysticall body, some are ordeined to learne, some to teach: that all are not Apostles, all Doctors, all interpreters, all of tonges and knovvledge, not all learned in Scriptures &amp; diuinitie: that the people went not vp to talke with God in the mountaine, but Moyses, Aaron, &amp; Eleazar: nor they neither, but by the difference of their callings: that they that rebell against this ordinance, are guilty of the conspiracie of Corè &amp; his cōplices: that in Scripture there is both milke for babes, and meate for men, to be dispensed, not according to euery ones
<pb facs="4"/> greedines of appetit or vvilfulnes,<note place="margin">The Scriptures must be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure and discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to eche mans neede and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie.</note> but as is most meete for eche ones necessitie and capacitie: that as it is a shame for a Bishop or Priest to be vnlearned in Gods mysteries, so for the common people it is often times profitable to sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, not to be curious, but to folovv their Pastors in sinceritie &amp; simplicitie: vvhereof excellently saith S. Augustine,<note place="margin">De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>gone Christ. c. 33.</note>
      <hi>Fidei simplicitate &amp; sinceritate lactati, nutriamur in Christo: &amp; cum parui sumus, maiorum cibos non appetamus.</hi> that is, <hi>Being fed vvith the simplicitie and sinceritie of faith, as it vvere vvith milke, so let vs be nourished in Christ:</hi>
      <note place="margin">De bono perseuer. c. 16.</note>
      <hi>and vvhen vve are litle ones, let vs not couet the meates of the elder sort.</hi> Vvho * in an other place testifieth, that the vvord of God can not be preached nor certaine mysteries vttered to all men alike, but are to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered according to the capacitie of the hearers:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.</note> as he proueth both * by S. Paules example, vvho gaue not to euery sort strong meate, but milke to many, as being not spiritual,<note place="margin">Io. 16.</note> but carnal and not capable: and * by our lordes also, vvhho spake to some plainely, and to others in parables, &amp; affirmed that he had many things to vtter vvhich the hearers vvere not able to beare.</p>
   <p>Hovv much more may vve gather, that all thinges that be vvritten, are not for the capacitie and diet of euery of the simple readers, but that very many mysteries of holy vvritte, be very far aboue their reach, &amp; may and ought to be (by as great reason) deliuered them in measure &amp; meane most meete for them? vvhich in deede can hardly be done,<note place="margin">Ia orat. de modera. in disp. serua. in fine. Hiero. in prooem. cō. mentar. in Ezachi.</note> vvhen the vvhole booke of the Bible lieth before euery man in his mother tonge,<note place="margin">The Ievves lavv for not reading certaine boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of holy Scripture vntil a time.</note> to make choise of vvhat he list. For vvhich cause the said Gregorie Nazianzen vvisheth the Christians had as good a lavv as the Hebrues of old had: vvho (as S. Hierom also vvitnesseth) tooke order among them selues that none should read the <hi>Cantica Canticorum</hi> nor certaine other pieces of hardest Scriptures, till they vvere thirtie yeres of age.</p>
   <p>And truely there is no cause vvhy men should be more loth to be ordered and moderated in this point by Gods Church and their Pastors, then they are in the vse of holy Sacraments: for vvhich as Christ hath appointed Priestes and ministers, at vvhose handes vve must receiue them, and not be our owne car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers:<note place="margin">Eph. 4.</note> so hath he giuen * vs doctors, prophetes, expoūders, interpreters, teachers and preachers, to take the lavv and our faith at their mouthes: because our faith and religion commeth not to vs properly or principally by reading of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">Ro. 10, 17.</note> but (as the Apostle saith) by hearing of the preachers lavvfully sent: though reading in order and humilitie, much confirmeth and aduanceth the same. Therfore this holy booke of the Scriptures, is called of S. Ambrose, <hi>Liber sacerdotalis, the booke of priestes,</hi> at vvhose handes and disposition vve must take and vse it. <hi>Li. 2. ad Grat.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The vvise vvil not here regard vvhat some vvilful people do mutter,<note place="margin">The popular obiections of vvithholding the Scriptures from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ansvvered.</note> that the Scriptures are made for all men, and that it is of enuie that the Priestes do keepe the holy booke from them. Vvhich suggestion commeth of the same serpent * that seduced our first parents,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> vvho persuaded them, that God had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden them that tree of knovvledge, lest they should be as cunning as him self,<note place="margin">Vvhy the Church permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not euery one at their pleasure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ade the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> and like vnto the Highest. No, no, the church doth it to keepe them from blind ignorant presumption, and from that vvhich the Apostle calleth <hi>falsi no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis scientiam knovvledge falsely so called:</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6, 20.</note> and not to embarre them from the true knovvledge,<note place="margin">Ro. 12, 3.</note> of Christ. She vvould haue all vvise, but <hi>vsque ad sobrietatem, vnto sobrietie,</hi> as the Apostle speaketh: she knovveth the Scriptures be ordained for euery state, as meates, elements, fire, vvater, candle, kniues, svvord, &amp; the like:
<pb facs="5"/> vvhich are as needful (most of them) for children as old folkes, for the simple as the vvise: but yet vvould marre all, if they vvere at the guiding of other then wise men, or vvere in the handes of euery one, for whose preseruation they be profitable. She forbiddeth not the reading of them in any language, enuieth no mans commoditie, but giueth order hovv to doe it to edification, and not destruction:<note place="margin">The holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to carnal men &amp; Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, are as pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les to svvine.</note> hovv to doe it without casting <hi>the holy to dogges,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 7, 6.</note> or <hi>pearles to hogges:</hi> (See S. Chrysost. <hi>ho. 24 in Matth,</hi> declaring these hogges &amp; dogges to be carnal men &amp; Heretikes, that take no good of the holy mysteries, but thereby do both hurt them selues &amp; others:) how to doe it agreably to the soueraine sinceritie, maiestie, &amp; depth of Mysterie conteined in the same. She vvould haue the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous Heretike, notvvithstanding he alleage them neuer so fast, flying as it vvere through the whole Bible, and coting the Psalmes, Prophets, Gospels Epistles, neuer so readily for his purpose, as Vincentius Lirinensis saith such mens fashion is:<note place="margin">Li. de pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> yet she vvould according to Tertullians rule, haue such mere vsurpers quite discharged of all occupying and possession of the holy Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is her old and onely right and inheritance, and belongeth not to Heretikes at all,<note place="margin">Orig. in 2 ad Ro.</note> vvhom Origen calleth <hi>Scripturarū fures, theeues of the Scriptures.</hi> She would haue the vnvvorthy repelled, the curious repressed, the simple mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured, the learned himbled, and all sortes so to vse them or absteine from them, as is most conuenient for euery ones saluation: with this general admonition, that none can vnderstand the meaning of God in the Scriptures<note n="*" place="margin">Luca 24.</note> except Christ open their sense, and make them partakers of his holy Spirit in the vnitie of his mystical bodie: and for the rest, she committeth it to the Pastor of euery pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince and people, according to the difference of time, place, and persons, how and in vvhat sort the reading of the Scriptures is more or lesse to be procured or permitted.</p>
   <p>Vvherein,<note place="margin">S. Chrysostoms exhortations to the reading of holy Scriptures, and vvhen the people is so to be exhorted.</note> the varietie of circūstances causeth them to deale diuersly: as we see by S. Chrysostoms people of Constantinople, vvho vvere so delicate, dull, vvorldly,<note place="margin">In vita Athanasij.</note> and so much giuen to dice, cardes, specially stage-plaies or theaters (as S. Gregorie Nazianzene witnesseth) that the Scriptures &amp; all holy lections of diuine things were lothsome vnto them: whereby their holy Bishop was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<note n="*" place="margin">Ho. 2 in Mat. &amp; ho. 3 de Lazaro. et ho. 3 in 2 ad Thess. &amp; alibi sapè.</note>in many of his sermons to crie out against their extreme negligence and contempt of Gods vvord, declaring, that not onely Eremites and Religious (as they alleaged for their excuse) but secular men of all sortes might reade the Scriptures, and often haue more neede thereof in respect of them selues, then the other that liue in more puritie and contemplation: further insinuating, that though diuers thinges be high and hard therein, yet many godly histories, liues, examples, &amp; precepts of life and doctrine be plaine: and finally, that when the Gentiles vvere so cunning and diligent to impugne their faith, it were not good for Christians to be to simple or negligent in the defense thereof. as (in truth) it is more requisite for a Catholike man in these daies vvhen our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries be industrious to empeache our beleefe, to be skilful in Scriptures, then at other times vvhen the Church had no such enemies.</p>
   <p>To this sense said S, Chrysostom diuers thinges,<note place="margin">S. Chrysostom maketh nothing for the popular and licentious reading of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures vsed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants novv a daies.</note> not as a teacher in schole, making exact and general rules to be obserued in all places &amp; times, but as a pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit man, agreably to that audiēce &amp; his peoples default: nor making it therfore (as some peruersely gather of his wordes) a thing absolutely needful for euery poore artificer to reade of studie Scriptures, nor any vvhit fauouring the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous, curious, and contentious iangling and searching of Gods secretes, reproued by the foresaid fathers, much lesse approuing the excessiue pride and
<pb facs="5"/> madnes of these daies,<note place="margin">Euery simple artificer among them readeth much more the deepest &amp; har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest question̄s of holy Scripture, then the moral partes.</note> vvhen euery man and vvoman is become not only a reader, but a teacher, controuler, and iudge of Doctors, Church, Scriptures and all: such as either contemne or easily passe ouer all the moral partes, good examples, and precepts of life (by vvhich as vvell the simple as learned might be much edified) &amp; only in a maner, occupie them selues in dogmatical, mystical, high, and hidden secretes of Gods counsels, as of Predestination, reprobation, election, prescience, forsaking of the Ievves, vocation of the gentiles, &amp; other incomprehensible mysteries,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.</note>
      <hi>Languishing about questions</hi> of onely saith, fiduce, nevv phrases and figures,<note place="margin">2 Tim. c. 3</note>
      <hi>euer learning,</hi> but <hi>neuer comming to knovvledge,</hi> reading and tossing in pride of vvitte, conceit of their ovvne cunning, and vpon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption of I can tell vvhat spirit,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.</note> such bookes specially and Epistles, as S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter foretold that the vnlearned and instable vvould depraue to their ovvne damnation.</p>
   <p>They delight in none more then in the Epistle to the Romans,<note place="margin">They presup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose no difficul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, which al the learned fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers felt to be in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> the <hi>Cantica canticorum,</hi> the Apocalypse, which haue in them as many mysteries as wordes. they find no difficultie in the sacred booke<note n="*" place="margin">Apoc. 5, 1.</note> clasped vvith seuē seales. they aske for no expositor<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 8. Confess. lib. 12. cap. 14.</note> vvith the holy Eunuch. they feele no such depth of Gods science in the scriptures, as S. Augustine did, vvhen he cried our, <hi>Mira profunditas eloquiorum tuorum, mira profunditas (Deus meus) mira profunditas: horror est intendere in eam, horror honoris, &amp; tremor amoris.</hi> that is, <hi>O vvonderful profoundnes of thy vvordes: vvonderful profoundnes, my God, vvonderful profoundnes: it maketh a man quake to looke on it: to quake for reuerence, and to tremble for the loue thereof.</hi> they regard not that vvhich the same Doctor affirmeth,<note place="margin">See ep. 3. Aug.</note> that the depth and profunditie of vvise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, not only in the vvordes of holy Scripture, but also in the matter &amp; sense, is so vvonderful, that, liue a man neuer so long, be he of neuer so high a vvitte, neuer so studious, neuer so seruēt to attaine the knovvledge thereof, yet vvhen he endeth,<note place="margin">Hiero, ep. 13. c. 4.</note> he shall confesse he doth but begin. they feele not vvith S. Hierom, that the text hath a hard shel to be broken before vve come to the kirnel. they vvill not stay them selues in only reading the sacred Scriptures thirtene yeres together,<note place="margin">Ruff. Ec. hist. li. 2. c. 9.</note> vvith S. Basil &amp; S. Gergorie Nazianzene, before they expound them, nor take the care (as they did) neuer othervvise to interpret them, then by the vniforme consent of their forefathers and tradition Apostolike.</p>
   <p>If our nevv Ministers had had this congitation and care that these and all other vvise men haue,<note place="margin">Maners and life nothing amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but much worse, since this licentious tossing of holy Scriptures.</note> and euer had, our countrie had neuer fallen to this mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable state in religion, &amp; that vnder pretence, colour, and coūtenance of Gods vvord: neither should vertue and good life haue bene so pitifully corrupted in time of such reading, toiling, tumbling and translating the booke of our life and saluation: vvhereof the more pretious the right and reuerent vse is, the more pernicious is the abuse and prophanation of the same: vvhich euery man of experience by these fevv yeres proofe, and by comparing the former daies and maners to these of ours, may easily trie.</p>
   <p>Looke vvhether your men be more vertuous, your vvomen more chast, your childrē more obedient, your seruants more trustie, your maides more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest, your frendes more faithful, your laitie more iust in dealing, your Cleargy more deuout in praying: vvhether there be more religion, feare of God, faith and conscience in all states novv, then of old, vvhen there vvas not so much reading, chatting, and iangling of Gods vvord, but much more sincere dealing, doing, and keeping the same. Looke vvhether through this disorder, vvomen teach not their husbands, children their parents, yong fooles their old and vvise fathers, the scholers their maisters, the sheepe their pastor, and the People
<pb facs="6"/> the Priest.<note place="margin">Scriptures as profanely cited as heathen poë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> Looke vvhether the most chast and sacred sentences of Gods holy vvord, be not turned of many, into mirth, mockerie, amorous ballets &amp; detes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table letters of loue and leudnes: their delicate rimes, tunes, and translations much encreasing the same.</p>
   <p>This fall of good life &amp; prophaning the diuine mysteries, euery body seeth: but the great corruption &amp; decay of faith hereby,<note place="margin">Scriptures er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>neously ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to euery vvicked mans priuate fansie.</note> none see but vvise men, who onely knovv, that, vvere the Scriptures neuer so truely translated, yet Heretikes and ill men that follovv their ovvne spirit and knovv nothing, but their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uàte fantasie, and not the sense of the holy Church and Doctors, must needes abuse them to their damnation:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2,</note>and that the curious simple and * sensual men vvhich haue no tast of the things that be of the Spirit of God, may of infinite places take occasion of pernicious errors. for though the letter or text haue no error, yet (saith S. Ambrose) the Arrian, or (as vve may novv speake) the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinian interpretation hath errors. <hi>lib. 2 ad Gratianum ca.</hi> 1. and Tertullian saith, <hi>The sense adulserated is as perilous as the style corrupted. De Praescript.</hi> S. Hilarie also speaketh thus: <hi>Heresie riseth about the vnderstanding, not about the vvriting: the fault is in the sense, not in the vvord. lib. 2 de Trinit. in principio.</hi> and S. Augustine saith, that many hold the scriptures as they doe the Sacraments, <hi>ad speciem, &amp; non ad salutem: to the outvvard shevv, and not to saluation. de Baptis. cont. Donat. lib. 3 ca.</hi> 19. Finally all Sect-maisters and rauening vvolues,<note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> yea * the diuels them selues pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Scriptures,<note place="margin">Al Heretikes pretend Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> alleage Scriptures, and vvholy shroud them selues in Scriptures, as in the wooll and fleese of the simple sheepe. Vvhereby the vulgar, in these daies of generall disputes, can not but be in extreme danger of error, though their bookes vvere truely translated, and vvere truely in them selues Gods ovvne vvord in deede.</p>
   <p>But the case novv is more lamentable:<note place="margin">The Scriptures haue been false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally translated into the vulgar tongues, and sundrie other vvaies sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giously abused, and so giuen to the people to reade.</note> for the Protestants and such as S. Paul calleth <hi>ambulantes in astutia,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.</note>
      <hi>vvalking in deceitfulnes,</hi> haue so abused the people and many other in the vvorld, not vnvvise, that by their false translations they haue in steede of Gods Lavv and Testament, &amp; for Christes vvritten vvill and vvord, giuen them their ovvne vvicked vvriting and phantasies, most shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in all their versions Latin, English, and other tonges, corrupting both the letter and sense by false translation, adding, detracting, altering, transposing, pointing, and all other guileful meanes: specially vvhere it serueth for the aduantage of their priuate opinions, for vvhich, they are bold also, partly to disauthorise quite, partly to make doubtful, diuers vvhole bookes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovved for Canonical Scripture by the vniuersal Church of God this thousand yeres and vpward: to alter al the authentical and Ecclesiastical vvordes vsed sithence our Christianitie, into nevv prophane nouelties of speaches agreable to their doctrine: to change the titles of vvorkes, to put out the names of the authors,<note n="*" place="margin">Bezaan not. in c. 1. Lu. v. 78.</note> to charge the very Euangelist vvith follovving vntrue translation, to adde whole sentences proper to their sect, into their psalmes in meter,<note n="*" place="margin">See the tenth arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of their Creede in meter.</note> euen into the very Creede in rime.<note place="margin">Al this their dealing is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as occasion serueth) in the Annotations vpon this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiment: and more at large in a booke la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely made pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely of that matter, called, <hi>A</hi> DISCOVERIE <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
      </note> al vvhich the poore deceiued people say and sing as though they vvere Gods ovvne vvord, being in deede through such sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious treacherie, made the Diuels vvord.</p>
   <p>To say nothing of their intolerable liberty and licence to change the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed callings of God, Angel, men, places, &amp; things vsed by the Apostles and all antiquitie, in Greeke, Latin, and all other languages of Christian Nations, into nevv names, sometimes falsely, and alvvaies ridiculously and for ostenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion taken of the Hebrues: to frame and fine the phrases of holy Scriptures after the forme of prophane writers, sticking not, for the same to supply, adde, alter or diminish as freely as if they translated Liuie, Virgil, or Terence. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="6"/> no religious respect to keepe either the maiestie or sincere simplicity of that venerable style of Christes spirit, as S. Augustine speaketh, vvhich kind the holy Ghost did choose of infinite vvisedom to haue the diuine mysteries ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vttered in, then any other more delicate, much lesse in that meretricious maner of vvriting that sundrie of these new translators doe vse: of vvhich sort Caluin him selfe and his pue-fellovves so much complaine,<note place="margin">Caluin cōplai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of the new delicat trā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slators, namely Castalion: him self &amp; Beza be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as bad or vvorse.</note> that they professe, Satan to haue gained more by these nevv interpreters (their number,<note place="margin">Pref. in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uū Testa. Gal. 1567.</note> leuitie of spirit, and audacitie encreasing daily) then he did before by keeping the word from the people. And for a paterne of this mischeefe, they giue Castalion, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuring all their churches and scholars to bevvare of his translation, as one that hath made a very sport and mockery of Gods holy vvord. so they charge him: them selues (and the Zuinglians of Zuricke,<note place="margin">Iost<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Sim lerus in vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geri.</note> vvhose translations Luther ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore abhorred) handling the matter vvith no more fidelitie, grauitie, or sinceritie, then the other: but rather vvith much more falsification, or (to vse the Apostles vvordes) <hi>cauponation</hi> and <hi>adulteration</hi> of Gods vvord, then they, besides many vvicked gloses,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 17.</note> prayers, confession of faith, conteining both blasphemous errors<note n="*" place="margin">See the 4 arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of their Creede in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vvhere they professe that Christ descēded to deliuer the fathers, &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in their cōfessiō of their faith, they deny <hi>Limbus patrum.</hi>
      </note> and plaine contradictions to them selues and among them selues, all priuileged and authorised to be ioyned to the Bible, and to be said and sung of the poore people, and to be beleeued as articles of faith and vvholy consonant to Gods vvord.</p>
   <p>Vve therfore hauing compassion to see our beloued countrie men, vvith extreme danger of their soules, to vse onely such prophane translations, and erroneous mens mere phantasies, for the pure and blessed vvord of truth, much also moued therevnto by the desires of many deuout persons: haue set forth, for you (benigne readers) the nevv Testament to begin vvithal,<note place="margin">The purpose &amp; commoditie of setting forth this Catholike edition.</note> trusting that it may giue occasion to you, after diligent perusing thereof, to lay avvay at lest such their impure versions as hitherto you haue ben forced to occupie. Hovv vvell vve haue done it, vve must not be iudges, but referre all to Gods Church and our superiors in the same. to them vve submit our selues, and this, and all other our labours, to be in part or in the vvhole, reformed, corrected, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, or quite abolished: most humbly desiring pardon if through our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, temeritie, or other humane infirmitie, vve haue any vvhere mistaken the sense of the holy Ghost. further promising, that if hereafter we espie any of our ovvne errors, or if any other, either frende of good vvil, or aduersarie for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of reprehension, shal open vnto vs the same: vve vvil not (as Protestants doe) for defense of our estimation, or of pride and contention, by vvrangling vvordes vvilfully persist in them, but be most glad to heare of them, and in the next edition or othervvise to correct them: for it is truth that vve seeke for, and Gods honour: which being had either by good intention, or by occasion, al is vvel.<note place="margin">The religious care &amp; sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie obserued in this translatiō.</note> This vve professe onely, that vve haue done our endeuour vvith praier, much feare and trembling, lest vve should dangerously erre in so sacred, high, and diuine a vvorke: that vve haue done it vvith all faith, diligence, and sinceritie: that vve haue vsed no partialitie for the disaduantage of our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, nor no more licence then is sufferable in translating of holy Scriptures: continually keeping our selues as neere as is possible, to our text &amp; to the very vvordes and phrases vvhich by long vse are made venerable,<note place="margin">See S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust. li. 3. confes. c. 5.</note> though to some propsiane or delicate cares they may seeme more hard to barbarous, * as the whole style of Scripture doth lightly to such at the begining: acknowledging with S. Hierom, that in other writings it is ynough to giue in trāslation, sense for sense, but that in Scriptures, lest vve misse the sense, vve must keepe the very
<pb facs="7"/> vvordes. <hi>Ad Pammach. epistola 101. ca. 2 in princip.</hi> Vve must, saith S. Augustine, speake according to a set rule, lest licence of wordes breede some vvicked opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion concerning the thinges conteined vnder the vvordes. <hi>De ciuitate lib. 10. cap,</hi> 12.<note place="margin">The auncient fathers kept re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiously the very barbaris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Latin text.</note> Vvhereof our holy forefathers and auncient Doctors had such a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious care, that they vvould not change the very barbarismes of incongruities of speach vvhich by long vse had preuailed in the old readings or recitings of scriptures▪ as,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.</note>
      <hi>Neque uubent neque nubentur,</hi> in Tertullian li. 4. in Marcion. in S. Hilarie in c. 22 Mat.<note place="margin">Mar. 8.</note> and in al the fathers. <hi>Qui me confusus fuerit, confundar &amp; ego eum,</hi> in S. Cyprian ep. 63 nu. 7. <hi>Talis enim nobis decebat sacerdos</hi> (vvhich vvas an elder translation then the vulgar Latin that novv is) in S. Ambrose c. 3 <hi>de fugaseculi.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hebr. 7.</note> and S. Hierom him self, vvho othervvise corrected the Latin trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation that vvas vsed before his time, yet keepeth religiously (as him self pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth <hi>Praefat.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 10. 22.</note>
      <hi>in 4 Euang. ad Damasum)</hi> these and the like speaches, <hi>Nonne vos magis pluris estis illis?</hi> and, <hi>filius hominis non venit ministrari, sed ministrare:</hi> and, <hi>Neque nubent, neque nubentur:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 13.</note> in his commentaries vpon these places. and, <hi>Non capit Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetam perire extra Hierusalem,</hi> in his commentaries <hi>in c. 2. Ioël. sub finem.</hi> And S. Augustine, vvho is most religious in al these phrases, counteth it a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial pride and infirmitie in those that haue a litle learning in tonges, &amp; none in thinges, that they easily take offense of the simple speaches or solecismes in the scriptures. <hi>de doctrina Christ. li. 2. cap,</hi> 13. See also the same holy father <hi>li. 3 de doct. Christ. c.</hi> 3. and <hi>tract. 2 in Euang. Ioan.</hi> But of the maner of our translation more anon.</p>
   <p>Now, though the text thus truely translated, might sufficiently, in the sight of the learned and al indifferent men,<note place="margin">Of the ANNO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TATIONS, vvhy they vvere made, &amp; vvhat matter they cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine.</note> both controule the aduersaries corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and proue that the holy Scripture vvhereof they haue made so great vauntes, make nothing for their nevv opinions, but vvholy for the Catholike Churches beleefe and doctrine, in all the pointes of difference betvvixt vs: yet knovving that the good and simple may easily be seduced by some fevv obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate persons of perdition (vvhom vve see giuen ouer into a reprobat sense, to whom the Gospel,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.</note> vvhich in it self is the odour of life to saluation, is made the odour of death to damnation, ouer vvhose eies for sinne &amp; disobedience God suffereth a veile or couer to lie, whiles they read the nevv Testamēt, euen as the Apostle saite the Ievves haue til this day,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.</note> in reading of the old, that as the one sort can not finde Christ in the Scriptures, reade they neuer so much, so the other can not finde the Catholike Church nor her doctrine there neither) and finding by experience this saying of S. Augustine to be most true,<note place="margin">De doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Christ. lib. 3. cap. 10.</note>
      <hi>If the preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of any erreneous persuasion preoccupate the mind, vvhatsoeuer the Scripture hath to the contrarie, men take it for a figuratiue speach:</hi> for these causes, and somevvhat to help the faithful reader in the difficulties of diuers places, vve haue also set forth reasonable large ANNOTATIONS, thereby to shevv the studious reader in most places perteining to the controuersies of this time, both the heretical cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and false deductions, &amp; also the Apostolike tradition, the expositions of the holy fathers, the decrees of the Catholike Church and most auncient Coūcels: which meanes vvhosoeuer trusteth not, for the sense of holy Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, but had rather folow his priuate iudgemēt or the arrogat spirit of these Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries, he shal vvorthily through his owne wilfulnes be deceiued. beseeching all men to looke vvith diligence, sinceritie, and indifferencie, into the case that concerneth no lesse then euery ones eternal saluation or damnation.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Vvhich if he doe, vve doubt not but he shal to his great contentment, find the holy Scriptures most clerely and inuincibly to proue the articles of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="7"/> doctrine against our aduersaries, vvhich perhaps he had thought before this diligent search, either not to be consonant to Gods vvord, or at least not conteined in the same,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Heresies make Catholikes more diligent to search and finde the senses of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for refel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the same.</note>
      <hi>and finally he shal proue this saying of S. Augustine to be most true.</hi>
      <note place="margin">In Psal. 67. propè finem.</note> Multi sensus &amp;c. Many senses of holy Scriptures lie hidden, and are know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to some fevv of greater vnderstanding: neither are they at any time auouched more commodiously and acceptably then at such times, vvhen the care to ansvver heretikes doth force men there vnto. For then, euen they that be negligent in matters of studie and learning, shaking of sluggishnes, are stirred vp to diligent hearing, that the Aduersaries may be refelled. Againe, hovv many senses of holy Scriptures, cōcerning Christes Godhead, haue been auouched against Photinus: hovv many, of his Manhod, against Manichaeus: hovv many, of the Trinitie, against Sabellius: hovv many, of the vnitie in Trinitie, against the Arrians, Eunomias, Macedonians: hovv many, of the Catholike Church dispersed through out the vvhole vvorld, and of the mixture of good and bad in the same vntil the end of the vvorld, against the Donatistes and Luciferians and other of the like errour: hovv many against al other heretikes, vvhich it vvere to long to rehearse? Of vvhich senses and expositions of holy Scripture the approued authors and auouchers, should othervvise either not be knovven as al, or not so vvel knovven, as the contradictions of proud heretikes haue made them.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thus he saith of such thinges as not seeming to be in holy Scriptures to the ignorant or heretikes, yet in deede be there. But in other pointes doubted of, that in deede are not decîded by Scripture, he giueth vs this goodly rule to be folovved in all, as he exemplifieth in one.</hi> Then doe vve hold <hi>(saith he)</hi> the veritie of the Scriptures, vvhen vve doe that vvhich novv hath seemed good to the Vniuersal Church, vvhich the authoritie of the Scriptures them selues doth cōmend: so that, forasmuch as the holy Scripture can not deceiue, vvhosoeuer is afraid to be deceiued vvith the obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of questions, let him therein aske counsel of the same <hi>CHVRCH,</hi> vvhich the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture most certainely and euidently shevveth and pointeth vnto.<note place="margin">Many cause<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> vvhy this nevv Testament is trāslated accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin text.</note>
      <hi>Aug. li. 1. Cont. Cres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. c.</hi> 13.</p>
   <p>NOVV TO GIVE thee also intelligence in particular, most gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, of such thinges as it behoueth thee specially to knovv concerning our Translation: Vve translate the old vulgar Latin text, not the common Greeke text, for these causes.</p>
   <p>1. It is so auncient,<note place="margin">It is most aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</note> that it vvas vsed in the Church of God aboue 1300 yeres agoe, as appeareth by the fathers of those times.</p>
   <p>2. It is that (by the common receiued opinion and by al probabilitie) vvhich S. Hierom aftervvard corrected according to the Greeke,<note place="margin">Corrected by S. Hierom.</note> by the appointment of Damasus then Pope, as he maketh mention in his preface before the foure Euangelistes, vnto the said Damasus: and <hi>in Catalogo in fine,</hi> and <hi>ep.</hi> 102.</p>
   <p>3. Consequently it is the same vvhich S. Augustine so commendeth and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovveth in an Epistle to S. Hierom.<note place="margin">Ep. 10.</note>
      <note place="margin">Commēded by S. Augustine.</note>
   </p>
   <p>4. It is that,<note place="margin">Vsed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the fathers.</note> vvhich for the most part euer since hath been vsed in the Churches seruice, expounded in sermons, alleaged and interpreted in the Commentaries and vvritings of the auncient fathers of the Latin Church.</p>
   <p>5. The holy Councel of Trent,<note place="margin">Only authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, by the holy Councel of Trent.</note> for these and many other important consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations,<note place="margin">Sess. 4.</note> hath declared and defined this onely of al other latin translations, to be authentical, and so onely to be vsed and taken in publike lessons, disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, preachings, and expositions, and that no man presume vpon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to reiect or refuse the same.</p>
   <p>6. It is the grauest,<note place="margin">Most graue, least partial.</note> sincerest, of greatest maiestie, least partialitie, as being vvithout al respect of controuersies and contentions, specially these of our
<pb facs="8"/> time, as appeareth by those places vvhich Erasmus and others at this day tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate much more to the aduantage of the Catholike cause.</p>
   <p>7. It is so exact and precise according to the Greeke,<note place="margin">Precise in fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovving the Greeke.</note> both the phrase and the word, that delicate Heretikes therfore reprehend it of rudene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. And that it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovveth the Greeke far more exactly then the Protestants translations, beside infinite other places, we appeale to these. Tit. 3. 14. <hi>Curent bonis operibus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>esse.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. Engl. bib. 1577, <hi>to mainteine good vvorkes.</hi> and Hebr. 10, 20. <hi>Viam nobis initiatut,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. English Bib. <hi>he prepared.</hi> So in these vvordes, <hi>Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficationes, Traditiones, Idola &amp;c.</hi> In al vvhich they come not neere the Greeke, but auoid it of purpose.</p>
   <p>8. The Aduersaries them selues,<note place="margin">Preferred by Beza him self.</note> namely Beza, preferre it before al the rest. <hi>Inpraefat. no. Test an.</hi> 1556. And againe he saith, that the old Interpreter transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted very religiously. <hi>Annot. in 1. Luc. v.</hi> 1.</p>
   <p>9. In the rest, there is such diuersitie and dissension, and no end of reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one an other,<note place="margin">Al the rest mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked of the Sectaries them selues, eche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending an other.</note> and translating euery man according to his fantasie, that
<note n="*" place="margin">Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hla. c. 11 de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. Script. authorit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note>Luther said, If the vvorld should stand any long time, vve must receiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine (which he thought absurd) the Decrees of Councels, for preseruing the vnitie of faith, because of so diuers interpretations of the Scripture. And Beza (in the place aboue mentioned) noteth the itching ambition of his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv-translators, that had much rather disagree and dissent from the best, then seeme them selues to haue said or vvritten nothing. And Bezas translation it self, being so esteemed in our countrie, that the Geneua<note n="*" place="margin">The nevv Test. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thē ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re 1580. in the title.</note> English Testaments be translated according to the same, yet sometime goeth so vvide from the Greeke, and from the meaning of the holy Ghost, that them selues which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test to trāslate it, dare not folow it. For example, <hi>Luc.</hi> 3, 36. They haue put these wordes, <hi>The sonne of Cainan,</hi> which he wittingly and wilfully left out: and <hi>Act. 1,</hi> 14. they say, <hi>Vvith the vvomen,</hi> agreably to the vulgar Latin: where he saith, <hi>Cum vxoribus, vvith their vviues.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>10. It is not onely better then al other Latin trāslations,<note place="margin">It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> then the vulgar Greeke text it self.</note> but then the Greeke text it self, in those places where they disagree.</p>
   <p>The proofe hereof is euident, because most of the auncient Heretikes were Grecians, &amp; therfore the Scriptures in Greeke were more corrupted by them, as the auncient fathers often complaine. Tertullian noteth the Greeke text which is at this day (1 Cor. 19. 47) to be an old corruption of Marcion the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The auncient fathers for proofe therof, and the Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries them selues.</note> and the truth to be as in our vulgar latin,<note place="margin">Li. 5 cont. Marcionō.</note>
      <hi>Secundus</hi> homo de coelo coelestis, The second man from heauen heauenly. So reade other<note n="*" place="margin">Ambrose. Hierom.</note> auncient fathers, and Eras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus thinketh it must needes be so, and Caluin him self folovveth it <hi>Instit. li. 2. c. 13. parag.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Li. 1, cont. louin. c. 7.</note> Againe S. Hierom noteth that the Greeke text <hi>(1 Cor. 7, 33)</hi> which is at this day, is not the <hi>Apostolical veritie</hi> or the true text of the Apostle: but that which is in the vulgar Latin, <hi>Qui cum vxore est, solicitus est quae sunt mundi, quomodo placeat vxori, &amp; diuisus est. He that is vvith a vvife, is careful of vvorldly things, hovv he may please his vvife, and is deuided or distracted.</hi> The Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastical historie called the Tripartite,<note place="margin">Li. 12 c. 4.</note> noteth the Greeke text that now is <hi>(1 Io. 4, 3)</hi> to be an old corruption of the auncient Greeke copies, by the Nestorian Heretikes, &amp; the true reading to be as in our vulgar Latin, <hi>Omnis spiritus qui soluit</hi> IESVM, <hi>ex Deo non est. Euery spirit that dissolueth</hi> IESVS, <hi>is not of God:</hi> and Beza confesseth that Socrates in his Ecclesiastical historie readeth so in the Greeke,<note place="margin">Li. 7. c. 32.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> &amp;c.</p>
   <p>But the proofe is more pregnant out of the Aduersaries them selues. They forsake the Greeke text as corrupted, and translate according to the vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,
<pb facs="8"/> namely Beza and his scholers the English translatours of the Bible,<note place="margin">The Caluinistes them selues oftē forsake the Greeke as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late according to the aūcient vulgar latin text.</note> in these places. Hebr. chap. 9, vers. 1. saying, <hi>The first couenant,</hi> for that vvhich is in the Greeke.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>The first tabernacle.</hi> vvhere they put, <hi>couenant,</hi> not as of the text, but in an other letter, as to be vnderstood, according to the vulgar Latin, vvhich most sincerely leaueth it out altogether, saying, <hi>Habuit quidem &amp;prius instificatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp;c. The former also in deede had iustifications &amp;c.</hi> Againe, <hi>Ro. 11, vers.</hi> 21. They translate not according to the Greeke text,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>Temporiseruientes, seruing the time,</hi> vvhich Beza saith must needes be a corruption: but according to the vulgar Latin, <hi>Domino seruientes, seruing our Lord.</hi> Againe, <hi>Apoc. 11, vers.</hi> 2. they translate not the Greeke text, <hi>Atrium quod intra templum est, the court vvhich is vvithin the teme:</hi> but cleane contrarie, according to the vulgar Latin, vvhich Beza saith is the true reading, <hi>Atrium quod est foris templum, the court vvhich is vvithout the temple.</hi> Onely in this last place, one English Bible of the yere 1562, folovveth the errour of the Greeke. Againe, 2 <hi>Tim. 2. vers.</hi> 14. they adde, <hi>but,</hi> more then is in the Greeke, to make the sense more cōmodious and easie, according as it is in the vulgar Latin.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> Again, <hi>Ia.</hi> 5, 12. they leaue the Greeke, and folovv the vulgar Latin, saying, <hi>lest you fall into condemnation. I doubt</hi> not (saith Beza) <hi>but this is the true and sincere reading, and I suspect the corruption in the Greeke came thus &amp;c.</hi> It vvere infinite to set dovvne al such places, vvhere the Aduersaries (specially Beza) folovv the old vulgar Latin and the Greeke copie agreable therevnto, condemning the Greeke text that novv is, of corruption.</p>
   <p>Againe, Erasmus the best translatour of al the later,<note place="margin">Superfluities in the Greeke▪ vvhich Erasmus calleth trifling and rash addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> by Bezas iudgement, saith, that the Greeke sometime hath superfluities corruptly added to the text of holy Scripture. as <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. to the end of the <hi>Pater noster,</hi> these vvordes, <hi>Because thine is the kingdom, the povver, and the glorie, for euer-more.</hi> Vvhich he calleth, <hi>nugas,</hi> trifles rashly added to our Lords praier, and reprehendeth Valla for blaming the old vulgar Latin because it hath it not, likevvise <hi>Ro.</hi> 11, 6. these vvordes in the Greeke, and not in the vulgar latin: <hi>But if of vvorkes, it is not novv grace: othervvise the vvorke is no more a vvorke.</hi> and <hi>Mar.</hi> 10, 29. these vvordes, <hi>or vvife,</hi> and such like.<note place="margin">See No. Test. Graec. Rob. Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phani in folio, <hi>and</hi> Cris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ins.</note> Yea the Greeke text in these superfluities condemneth it self, and iustifieth the vulgar Latin excedingly: as being marked through out in a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of places, that such and such vvordes or sentences are superfluous, in al which places out vulgar Latin hath no such thing, but is agreable to the Greeke vvhich remaineth after the superfluities be taken avvay. For example, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned in the end of the <hi>Pater noster,</hi> hath a marke of superfluitie in the Greeke text thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>▪ and <hi>Marc.</hi> 6, 11 these vvordes, <hi>Amen I say to you, it shal be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrhe in the day of iudgement, then for that citie.</hi> and <hi>Mat.</hi> 20, 22. these vvordes, <hi>And be baptized vvith the baptisme that I am baptized vvith?</hi> Vvhich is also superfluously repeated againe vers. 23. and such like places exceding many: which being noted superfluous in the Greeke, and being not in the vulgar Latin, proue the Latin in those places to be better, truer and more sincere then the Greeke.</p>
   <p>Vvherevpon vve conclude of these premisses, that it is no derogation to the vulgar Latin text, which we translate, to disagree from the Greeke text, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it may notwithstanding be not onely as good,<note place="margin">The vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin translation agreeth vvith the best Greeke copies, by Bezas ovvne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> but also better,<note place="margin">Beza pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. No. Test. 1556 See him also Anno. in 13. Act. <hi>v.</hi> 20.</note> and this the Aduersarie him self, their greatest and latest translatour of the Greeke, doth auouch against Erasmus in behalfe of the old vulgar Latin trāslation, in these notorious vvordes. <hi>Hovv vnvvorthely and vvithout cause</hi> (saith he) <hi>doth Erasmus blame the old Interpreter as dissenting from the Greeke? he dissented, I graunt, from those Greeke copies vvhich he had gotten: but vve haue found, not in one place, that the same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation
<pb facs="9"/> vvhich be blameth, is grounded vpon the authoritie of other Greeke copies, &amp; those most a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ncient. Yea in some number of places vve haue obserued, that the reading or the Latin text of the old Interpreter, though it agree not sometime vvith our Greeke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies yet it is much more conuenient, for that it seemeth be folovved some better and truer copie.</hi> Thus far Beza. In vvhich vvordes he vnwittingly, but most truely, iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth and defendeth the old vulgar Translation against him self and al other ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillers, that accuse the same, because it is not alwaies agreable to the Greeke text: Vvhereas it vvas translated out of other Greeke copies (partly extant, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not extant at this day) either as good and as auncient,<note place="margin">Vvhen the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers say, that the Latin text must yeld to the Greeke, &amp; be corrected by it, they meane the true and vncorrupted Greeke text.</note> or better and more aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, such as S. Augustine speaketh of, calling them <hi>doctiores &amp; diligentiores, the more learned and diligent Greeke copies,</hi> vvhervnto the latin translations that faile in any place, must needes yeld. <hi>Li. 2. de doct. Christ. c.</hi> 15.</p>
   <p>And if it were not to long to exemplifie and proue this, which would require a treatise by it self, we could shew by many and most cleere examples through out the new Testament, these sundrie meanes of iustifying the old translation.</p>
   <p>1 First, if it agree with the Greeke text (as commonly it doth, and in the greatest places cōcerning the controuersies of our time, it doth most certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) so far the Aduersaries haue not to complaine:<note place="margin">The vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Translatiō, is many waies iustified by most auncient Greeke copies, &amp; the Fathers.</note> vnles they wil complaine of the Greeke also, as they doe <hi>Ia. 4. v▪</hi> 2. and 1 <hi>Pet. 3. v.</hi> 21. where the vulgar Latin foloweth exactly the Greeke text, saying, <hi>Occiditis:</hi> and▪ <hi>Quod vos similis formae,</hi> &amp;c. But Beza in both places correcteth the Greeke text also as false.</p>
   <p>2 If it disagree here and there from the Greeke text, it agreeth with an other Greeke copie set in the margent, whereof see examples in the foresaid Greeke Testaments of Robert Steuens and Crispin through out▪ namely 2 <hi>Pet. 1, 10. Satague vt per bona opera certam vestram vocationem faciatis.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. and Marc. 8. v. 7. <hi>Et ipsos benedixit,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>3 If these marginal Greeke copies be thought lesse authentical then the Greeke text, the Aduersaries them selues tel vs the cōtrarie, vvho in their trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations often folow the marginal copies, and forsake the Greeke text: as in the examples aboue mentioned <hi>Ro. 11. Apoc. 11. 2 Tim. 2. Iac.</hi> 5. &amp;c. it is euident.</p>
   <p>4 If al Erasmus Greeke copies haue not that which is in the vulgar Latin, Beza had copies which haue it, and those most auncient (as he saith) &amp; better. And if al Bezas copies faile in this point and wil not helpe vs, Gagneie the Frenche kings preacher, and he that might commaund in al the kings libraries, he found Greeke copies that haue iust according to the vulgar Latin: &amp; that in such place as would seeme otherwise lesse probable▪ as <hi>Iac. 3. vers. 5. Ecce quantus ignis quam magnam silum incendit! Behold hovv much fire vvhat a great vvood it kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth!</hi> A man would thinke it must be rather as in the Greeke text,<note place="margin">Codex ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronensis. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>A litle fire vvhat a great vvood it kindleth!</hi> But an approued auncient Greeke copie alleaged by Gagneie, hath as it is in the vulgar Latin. And if Gagneis copies also faile some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, there Beza and Crispin supply Greeke copies fully agreable to the vulgar Latin. as <hi>ep. Iudae vers.</hi> 5. Scientes semel <hi>omnia,</hi> quoniam IESVS &amp;c. and <hi>vers</hi> 19. Segregant <hi>semetipsos.</hi> likewise 2 Ephes 2. <hi>Quòd elegerit vos primitias:</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> in some Greeke copies. Gagn. &amp; 2 <hi>Cor. 9. Vestra amulatio,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. so hath one Greeke copie. Beza.</p>
   <p>5 If al their copies be not sufficient, the auncient Greeke fathers had copies and expounded them, agreable to our vulgar Latin as 1 <hi>Tim. 6, 20. Prophanat vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum nouitates.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> So readeth S. Chrysostom and expoundeth it against Heretical &amp; erroneous nouelties. Yet now we know no Greeke copie that readeth so.
<pb facs="9"/> Likewise <hi>Io. 10, 29. Pater meus quod mihi dedit maius omnibus est.</hi>
      <note place="margin">The Greeke fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> so readeth S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril and expoundeth it <hi>li.</hi> 7 in <hi>Io. c.</hi> 10. likewise 1 <hi>Io. 4, 3. Omnie spiritus qui soluit</hi> IESVM, <hi>ex Deo non est.</hi> so readeth S. Irenaeus li. 3. c. 18. S. Augustine <hi>tract. 6. in Io.</hi> S. Leo <hi>epist.</hi> 10. c. 5. beside Socrates in his Ecclesiastical historie, <hi>li.</hi> 7. c. 22. and the Tripartite <hi>li. 12. c.</hi> 4. vvho say plainely, that this was the old and the true reading of this place in the Greeke. And in what Greeke copie extant at this day is there this text Io. 5, 2. <hi>Est autē Hierosolymis probatica piscina?</hi> and yet S. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostom, S. Cyril, and Theophylacte read so in the Greeke, and Beza saith it is the better reading▪ and so is the Latin text of the Romane Masse booke iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and eight other Latin copies, that reade so▪ for our vulgar Latin here, is according to the Greeke text, <hi>Super probatica.</hi> &amp; Ro. 5. v. 17. <hi>Donationis &amp; iustitiae.</hi> so readeth Theodorete in Greeke.<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> &amp; <hi>Lu. 2. v.</hi> 14. Origen &amp; S. Chrysostom reade, <hi>Hominibus bonae voluntatis,</hi> and Beza liketh it better then the Greeke text that novv is.</p>
   <p>6. Vvhere there is no such signe or token of any auncient Greeke copie in the fathers, yet these later Interpreters tel vs, that the old Interpreter did fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv some other Greeke copie. as Marc. 7, 3. <hi>Nisi crebro lauerint.</hi> Erasmus thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that he did read in the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>often:</hi> and Beza and others commend his coniecture, yea and the English Bibles are so translated. vvhereas novv it is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> vvhich signifieth the length of the arme vp to the elbovv. And vvho vvould not thinke that the Euangelist should say, The Pharisees vvash often, because othervvise they eate not, rather then thus, <hi>Vnles they vvash vp to the elbovv, they eate not?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>7. If al such coniectures,<note place="margin">The Latin fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> and al the Greeke fathers help vs not, yet the Latin fathers vvith great consent vvil easily iustifie the old vulgar trāslation, vvhich for the most part they folovv and expound.<note place="margin">See An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan. in No. Test. <hi>and</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. Luca Brugensis in biblia.</note> as, Io. 7, 39. <hi>Nondum erat spiritus datus.</hi> so readeth S. Augustine <hi>li. 4 de Trinit. c.</hi> 20. and li. 83. <hi>Quaest. q.</hi> 62. and <hi>tract. 52 in Ioan.</hi> Leo <hi>ser. 2 de Pentecoste.</hi> Vvhose authoritie vvere sufficient, but in deede Didymus also a Greeke Doctor readeth so <hi>li. 2 de Sp. sancto,</hi> translated by S. Hierom, and a Greeke copie in the Vaticane, and the Syriake nevv Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Likevvise Io. 21, 22. <hi>Sic eum volo manere.</hi> so reade S. Ambrose, <hi>in Psal.</hi> 45. &amp; <hi>Psal. 118. octonario Resh.</hi> s. Augustine and Ven. Bede vpon S. Iohns Gospel.</p>
   <p>8. And lastly, if some other Latin fathers of auncient time, reade othervvise, either here or in other places, not al agreing vvith the text of our vulgar Latin, the cause is, the great diuersitie and multitude that vvas then of Latin copies, (vvhereof S. Hierom complaineth) til this one vulgar Latin grevv onely into vse.<note place="margin">Praefat. in 4. Euang. ad Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum.</note> Neither doth their diuers reading make more for the Greeke, then for the vulgar Latin, differing oftentimes from both. as vvhen S. Hierom in this last place readeth, <hi>Si sic eum volomanere, li. 1. adu. Iouin.</hi> it is according to no Greeke copie novv extant. And if yet there be some doubt, that the readings of some Greeke or Latin fathers, differing from the vulgar Latin, be a checke or condemnation to the same: let Beza, that is, let the Aduersarie him self, tel vs his opinion in this case also.<note place="margin">Praefat. citata.</note>
      <hi>Vvhosoeuer,</hi> saith he, <hi>shal take vpon him to correct these things</hi> (speaking of the vulgar Latin translation) <hi>out of the auncient fathers vvritings, either Greeke or Latin, vnles he doe it very circumspectly and aduisedly, he shal surely corrupt al rather then amend it, because it is not to be thought, that as often as they cited any place, they did alvvaies looke into the booke, or number euery vvord.</hi> As if he should say, Vve may not by and by thinke that the vulgar Latin is faultie and to be corrected, vvhen vve read othervvise in the fathers either Greeke or La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, because they did not alvvaies exactly cite the vvordes, but folovved some
<pb facs="10"/> commodious and godly sense thereof.</p>
   <p>Thus then vve see that by al meanes the old vulgar Latin translation is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued good,<note place="margin">The fevv and final faultes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligently crept into the vulgar Latin transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and better then the Greeke text it self, and that there is no cause vvhy it should giue place to any other text, copies, or readings. Marie if there be any faultes euidently crept in by those that heretofore wrote or copied out the Scriptures (as there be some) them vve graunt no lesse, then vve vvould graunt faultes novv a daies committed by the Printer, and they are exactly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Catholike vvriters, namely in al Plantins Bibles set forth by the Diuines of Louan:<note place="margin">Sess. 4.</note> and the holy Councel of Trent vvilleth that the vulgar Latin text be in such pointes throughly mended, &amp; so to be most authentical. Such faultes are these, <hi>Inside,</hi> for <hi>in fine: Praescientiam,</hi> for, <hi>praesentiam: Suscipiens,</hi> for, <hi>Suspiciens:</hi> and such like very rare. vvhich are euident corruptions made by the copistes, or grovven by the similitude of vvordes. These being taken avvay, vvhich are no part of those corruptions and differences before talked of, vve translate that text vvhich is most sincere, and in our opinion and as vve haue proued, incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt. The Aduersaries contrarie, translate that text, vvhich them selues confesse both by their vvritings and doings, to be corrupt in a number of places, &amp; more corrupt then our vulgar Latin, as is before declared.</p>
   <p>And if vve vvould here stand to recite the places in the Greeke vvhich Beza pronounceth to be corrupted,<note place="margin">The Caluinists confessing the Greeke to be most corrupt, yet translate that only, and hold that only for authentical Scripture.</note> vve should make the Reader to vvonder, hovv they can either so plead othervvise for the Greeke text, as though there vvere no other truth of the nevv Testament but that: or hovv they translate onely that (to deface, as they thinke, the old vulgar Latin) vvhich them selues so shamfully disgrace, more then the vulgar Latin, inuenting corruptions vvhere none are, nor can be, in such vniuersal consent of al both Greeke and Latin copies. For example, Mat. 10. <hi>The first Simon, Vvho is called Peter.</hi> I thinke (saith Beza) this vvord <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">In An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. No. Test. an. 1556.</note>
      <hi>first,</hi> hath been added to the text of some that vvould establish Peters Primacie. Againe <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. The Chalice, <hi>that is shed for you.</hi> It is most likely (saith he) that these vvordes being sometime but a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal note, came by corruption out of the margent into the text. Againe <hi>Act.</hi> 7. Figures vvhich they made, <hi>to adore them.</hi> It may be suspected (saith he) that these vvordes, as many other, haue crept by corruption into the text out of the margent. And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. He thinketh the Apostle said not <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>victorie,</hi> as it is in al Greeke copies, but <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>contention.</hi> And <hi>Act.</hi> 13. he calleth it a manifest errour, that in the Greeke it is, 400 <hi>yeres,</hi> for, 300. And <hi>Act. 7. v.</hi> 16. he recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vp a vvhole catalogue of corruptions. namely <hi>Marc. 12. v.</hi> 42. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Vvhich is a farthing:</hi> and <hi>Act. 8. v.</hi> 26. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>This is desert.</hi> and <hi>Act. 7. v.</hi> 16 the name of Abraham, &amp; such like. Al vvhich he thinketh to haue been added or altered into the Greeke text by corruption.</p>
   <p>But among other places, he laboureth excedingly to proue a great corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Act. 7. v.</hi> 14. vvhere it is said (according to the <hi>Septuaginta,</hi> that is, the Greeke text of the old Testament) that Iacob vvent dovvne into Aegypt vvith 75 soules. And <hi>Luc. 3. v.</hi> 36. he thinketh these vvordes <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Vvhich vvas of Cainan,</hi>
      <note place="margin">They standing precisely vpon the Hebrue of the old, and Greeke text of the nevv Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, must of force denie the one of them.</note> to be so false, that he leaueth them cleane out in<note n="*" place="margin">An. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 1556 and 1565.</note> both his editions of the nevv Testament: saying, that he is bold so to doe, by the authoritie of Moyses. Vvhereby he vvil signifie, that it is not in the Hebrue text of Moyses or of the old Testament, and therfore it is selfe in the Greeke of the nevv Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Vvhich consequence of theirs (for it is common among them and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth al Scriptures) if it vvere true, al places of the Greeke text of the nevv Testament, cited out of the old according to the Septuaginta, and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="10"/> to the Hebrue (vvhich they knovv are very many) should be false, and so by tying them selues onely to the Hebrue in the old Testamēt, they are forced to forsake the Greeke of the nevv: or if they vvil mainteine the Greeke of the nevv, they must forsake sometime the Hebrue in the old. but this argument shal be forced against them els vvhere.</p>
   <p>By this litle, the Reader may see vvhat gay patrones they are of the Greeke text,<note place="margin">They say the Greeke is more corrupt then vve vvil graunt them.</note> and how litle cause they haue in their owne iudgements to translate it, or vaunt of it, as in derogation of the vulgar Latin translation, &amp; how easily we might answer them in a word, why we translate, not the Greeke: forsooth because it is so infinitely corrupted, But the truth is, we do by no meanes graūt it so corrupted as they say, though in comparison we know it lesse sincere &amp; incorrupt then the vulgar Latin, and for that cause and others before alleaged we preferre the said Latin, and haue translated it.</p>
   <p>If yet there remaine one thing which perhaps they wil say, when they can not answer our reasons aforesaid: to wit, that we preferre the vulgar Latin before the Greeke text,<note place="margin">We preferre not the vulgar Latin text, as making more for vs.</note> because the Greeke maketh more against vs: we protest that as for other causes we preferre the Latin, so in this respect of making for vs or against vs, we allow the Greeke as much as the Latin, yea in sundrie pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces more then the Latin, being assured that they haue not one, and that we haue many aduantages in the Greeke more then in the Latin, as by the Annotations of this new Testament shal euidently appeare:<note place="margin">The Greeke text maketh for vs more then the vulgar Latin.</note> namely in al such places where they dare not translate the Greeke, because it is for vs &amp; against them. as when they translate, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>ordinances,</hi> and not, <hi>iustification,</hi> and that of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose as Beza confesseth <hi>Luc.</hi> 1, 6. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>ordinances,</hi> or <hi>instructions,</hi> and not <hi>traditions,</hi> in the better part. 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 2, 15. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Elders,</hi> and not <hi>Priests:</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>images</hi> rather then <hi>idols.</hi> and especially when S. Luke in the Greeke so maketh for vs (the vulgar Latin being indifferent for them and vs) that Beza saith it is a corruption crept out of the margent into the text.<note place="margin">Luc. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>0.</note> Vvhat neede these absurd diuises and false dealings with the Greeke text,<note place="margin">For the real presence.</note> if it made for them more then for vs, yea if it made not for vs against them? But that the Greeke maketh more for vs,<note place="margin">For fasting.</note> see 1 Cor. 7. In the Latin, <hi>Defraude not one another, but for a time, that you giue your selues to prayer.</hi> in the Greeke, <hi>to fasting and prayer. Act. 10,</hi> 30. in the Latin Cornelius saith, <hi>from the fourth day past vntil this houre I vvas praying in my house, and behold a man &amp;c.</hi> in the Greeke, <hi>I vvas fasting, and praying.</hi> 1 Io. 5, 18, in the Latin,<note place="margin">For free vvil.</note>
      <hi>Vve knovv that euery one vvhich is borne of God, sinneth not. but the generation of God preserueth him &amp;c.</hi> in the Greeke, <hi>but he that is borne of God preserueth him self. Apoc.</hi> 22, 14. in the Latin, <hi>Blessed are they that vvash their garmēts in the bloud of the lambe</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Against only faith.</note> in the Greeke, <hi>Blessed are they that doe his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Rom. 8, 38. Certus sum &amp;c.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Against only faith.</note>
      <hi>I am sure that neither death nor life, nor other creature is able to separate vs from the charitie of God.</hi> as though he vvere assured, or we might and should assure our selues of our predestination,<note place="margin">Against special assurance of saluation.</note> in the Greeke, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>I am probably persuaded that neither death nor life</hi> &amp;c. In the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists about the Sacrifice and B. Sacrament, in the Latin thus: <hi>This is my bloud that shal be shed for you:</hi> and in S. Paul, <hi>This is my body vvhich shal be betraied or deliuered for you:</hi> both being referred to the time to come and to the sacrifice on the crosse.<note place="margin">For the sacrifice of Christs body and bloud.</note> in the Greeke, <hi>This is my bloud vvhich is shed for you:</hi> and, <hi>my body vvhich is broken for you:</hi> both being referred to that present time when Christ gaue his body and bloud at his supper, then sheading the one and breaking the other; that is, sacrificing it sacramentally and mystically. Loe these and the like our aduantages in the Greeke, more then in the Latin.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/> But is the vulgar translation for al this Papistical,<note place="margin">The Protātats condemning the old vulgar translation as making for vs, cōdemns them selues</note> &amp; therfore do we folow it? (for so some of them call it, and say it is <note n="*" place="margin">Against D. Sand. Rocke pag. 147. See Kemnis. in exam. Cōc. Trid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 4.</note> the worst of al other.) If it be, the Greeke (as you see) is more, and so both Greeke and Latin and consequently the holy Scripture of the new Testament is Papistical. Againe if the vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin be Papistical, Papistrie is very auncient, and the Church of God for so many hundred yeres wherein it hath vsed and allowed this translation, hath been Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistical. But wherein it is Papistical? forsooth in these phrases and speaches,<note place="margin">Mat. 3. &amp; 11. Eph. 5. Luc. 1. Heb. 13.</note>
      <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiam agite. Sacramentum hoc magnum est.</hi> AVE GRATIA PLENA. <hi>Talibus hostiis promeretur Deus.</hi> and such like. First, doth not the Greeke say the same? see the Annotations vpon these places. Secondly, could he translate these things Papistically or partially, or rather prophetically, so long before they were in controuersie? thirdly, doth he not say for <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>nitentiam agite,</hi> in an other place, <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>nitemini:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mar. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. Luc. 16. v. 20.</note> and doth he not translate other mysteries, by the vvord, <hi>Sacramentum,</hi> as <hi>Apoc. 17, Sacramentum mulieris:</hi> and as he translateth one vvord, <hi>Gratia plena,</hi> so doth he not translate the very like vvord, <hi>plenus vlceribus,</hi> vvhich them selues do folow also? is this also Papistrie? Vvhen he said Heb. 10, 29. <hi>Quanto deteriora merebitus supplicia</hi> &amp;c. and they like it vvel ynough:<note place="margin">It is void of al partialitie.</note> might he not haue said according to the same Greeke word, <hi>Vigilate vt mereamini fugere ista omnia &amp; stare ante filium hominis.</hi> Luc. 21, 36. and, <hi>Qui merebuntur saculum illud &amp; resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem exmortuis &amp;c.</hi> Luc. 10, 35. and, <hi>Tribulationes quas sustinetis, vt mereamini regnum, Dei, pro quo et patimini.</hi> 2. Thess. 1. 5. Might he not (we say) if he had partially affecteted the word merite, haue vsed it in al these places, according to his and <note n="*" place="margin">Na. Test. 1580.</note> your owne translation of the same Greeke word Hebr. 10, 29? Vvhich he doth not, but in al these places saith simply, <hi>Vt digni habeamini,</hi> and, <hi>Qui digni habeb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>tur.</hi> and how can it be iudged Papistical or partial, when he saith,<note place="margin">in ep. ad Hebr.</note>
      <hi>Talibus hostiis promer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tur Deus, Heb. 13?</hi> Vvas Primasius also S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines scholer, a Papist, for vsing this text, and al the rest, that haue done the like? Vvas S. Cyprian a Papist,<note place="margin">Ep. 14 &amp; 18.</note> for vsing so often this speach, <hi>promereri Dominum iustis operibus, po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nitentia, &amp;c.?</hi> or is there any difference, but that S. Cyptian vseth it as a deponent more latinly, the other as a passiue lesse finely? Vvas it Papistrie, to say <hi>Senior</hi> for <hi>Presbyter, Ministrantibus</hi> for <hi>sacrificantibus</hi> or <hi>liturgiam celebran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, simulacbris</hi> for <hi>idolis, fides tuaete saluum fecit</hi> sometime for <hi>sanum fecit?</hi> Or shal we thinke he was a Caluinist for translating thus, as they thinke he was a Papist,<note place="margin">The Papistrie thereof (as they terme it) is in the very sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of the Holy Ghost, more, then in the translatiō.</note> when any word soundeth for vs?</p>
   <p>Againe, was he a Papist in these kinde of wordes onely, and was he not in whole sentences? as,<note place="margin">Mat. 16. 10. 20.</note>
      <hi>Tibi dabo claues, &amp;c. Quicquid solueris in terrae, erit solutum &amp; in coelis.</hi> and, <hi>Quorum remiseritis peccata, remittuntur eis.</hi> and, <hi>Tunc red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det vnicuique secundum operasua.</hi> and,<note place="margin">Mat. 16. la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 2.</note>
      <hi>Nunquid poterit sides saluare eum? Ex operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus iustificatur homo &amp; non ex fide tantùm.</hi> and,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.</note>
      <hi>Nubere volunt, damnationem habentes, quia primam fidem irritam fecerunt.</hi> and,<note place="margin">1 Io. 5.</note>
      <hi>Mandata eius grauia non sunt.</hi> and, <hi>Aspexit in remunerationem.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> Are al these and such like, Papistical translations, because they are most plaine for the Catholike faith which they call Papistrie? Are they not word for word as in the Greeke, and the very wordes of the holy Ghost? And if in these there be no accusatiō of Papistical partiality, vvhy in the other? Lastly, are the auncient fathers, General Councels, the Churches of al the west part, that vse al these speaches &amp; phrases now so many hundred yeres, are they al Papistical? Be it so, and let vs in the name of God folow them, speake as they spake, translate as they translated, interprete as they interpreted, because we beleeue as they beleeued. And thus far for defense of the old vulgar Latin translation, and why we translated it before al others: Now of the maner of translating the same.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/> IN THIS OVR TRANSLATION,<note place="margin">The maner of this translation, and vvhat hath been obserued therein.</note> because we wish it to be most sincere, as becōmeth a Catholike translation, and haue endeuoured so to make it: we are very precise &amp; religious in folowing our copie, the old vulgar approued Latin: not onely in sense, which we hope we alwaies doe, but sometime in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wordes also and phrases, which may seeme to the vulgar Reader &amp; to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon English cares not yet acquainted therewith, rudenesse or ignorance but to the discrete Reader that deepely weigheth and considereth the importance of sacred wordes and speaches, and how easily the voluntarie Translatour may misse true sense of the Holy Ghost, we doubt not but our considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and doing therein, shal seeme reasonable and necessarie: yea and that al sortes of Catholike Readers wil in short time thinke that familiar, which at the first may seeme strange, &amp; wil esteeme it more, when they shal<note n="*" place="margin">See the last Table a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> the end of the booke.</note> otherwise be taught to vnderstand it, then if it were the common knowen English.</p>
   <p>For example,<note place="margin">Certaine vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des not English nor as yet fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar in the English ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue.</note> vve translate often thus, <hi>Amen amen,</hi> I <hi>say vnto you.</hi> Vvhich as yet seemeth strange. but after a while it wil be as familiar, as <hi>Amen,</hi> in the end of al praiers and Psalmes. and euen as when we end with, <hi>Amen,</hi> it soundeth far better then, <hi>So be it:</hi> so in the beginning, <hi>Amen, Amen,</hi> must needes by vse and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom sound far better, then, <hi>Verily verily.</hi> Vvhich in deede doth not expresse the asseueration and assurance signified in this Hebrue word, besides that it is the solemne and vsual word of our Sauiour <note n="*" place="margin">See annot.</note> to expresse a vehement asseueration, and therfore is not changed, neither in the Syriake nor Greeke,<note place="margin">Amen.</note> nor vulgar La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin▪ Testament,<note place="margin">Io. c. 8. v. 34. &amp; Apoc. c. 19. v. 4.</note> but is preserued and vsed of the Euangelistes and Apostles them selues, euen as Christ spake it, <hi>propter sanctiorem authoritatem▪</hi> as S. Augustine saith of this and of <hi>Allelu-ia</hi>
      <note place="margin">Alleluia.</note>
      <hi>for the more holy and sacred authoritie thereof, li. 2. Doct. Christ. c.</hi> 11. And therfore do we keepe the word <hi>Allelu-ia,</hi> Apoc. 19, as it is both in Greeke and Latin yea and in al the English translations, though in their bookes of common praier they translate it, <hi>Praise ye the Lord.</hi> Againe, if <hi>Hosanna, Raca, Belial,</hi> and such like be yet vntranslated in the English Bibles, why may not we say,<note place="margin">No, Test. an. 1580. Bib. an. 1577.</note>
      <hi>Corbana,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Parasceue.</note> and <hi>Parasceue:</hi> specially when they Englishing this later thus, <hi>the preparation of the Sabboth,</hi> put three wordes more into the text, then the Greek word doth signifie, <hi>Mat,</hi> 27, 62. And others saying thus, After the day <hi>of preparing,</hi> make a cold translation and short of the sense: as if they should trāslate, Sabboth, <hi>the resling.</hi> for, <note n="*" place="margin">Mar. 14. v. 42.</note>
      <hi>Parasceue</hi> is as solemne a word for the Sabboth eue, as <hi>Sabboth</hi> is for the Iewes seuenth day. and now among Christians much more solemner, taken for Good-friday onely. These wordes then we thought it far better to keepe in the text, and to tel their signification in the margent or in a table for that purpose, then to disgrace bothe the text &amp; them with translating them.<note place="margin">Pasche.</note> Such are also these wordes, <hi>The Pasche. The feast of Azymes.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Bib. 1577.</note>
      <hi>The bread of Proposition.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 17.</note> Vvhich they translate <hi>The Passeouer,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Azymes.</note>
      <hi>The feast of svvete bread, The shevv bread.</hi> But if <hi>Pentecost</hi> Act. 2 be yet vntrāslated in their bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and seemeth not strange: why should not <hi>Pasche</hi> and <hi>Azymes</hi> so remaine also, being solemne feastes, as Pentecost was? or why should they English one rather then the other? specially whereas <hi>Passeouer</hi> at the first was as strange, as <hi>Pasche</hi> may seeme now, and perhaps as many now vnderstand <hi>Pasche,</hi> as <hi>Passe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> and as for <hi>Azymes,</hi> when they English it, <hi>the feast of svveete bread,</hi> it is a false interpretatiō of the word, &amp; nothing expresseth that which belongeth to the feast, concerning vnleauened bread. And as for their terme of <hi>shevv bread,</hi> it is very strange and ridiculous, Againe, if <hi>Proselyte</hi> be a receiued word in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish bibles <hi>Mat. 23. Act. 2:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Neophyte.</note> why may not we be bold to say, <hi>Neophyte.</hi> 1 Tim. 3? specially when they translating it into English, do falsely expresse the signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb facs="12"/> of the word thus, <hi>a yong scholer.</hi> Vvhereas it is a peculiar word to sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie them that were lately baptized, as <hi>Catechumenus,</hi> signifieth the newely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed in faith not yet baptized, who is also yong scholer rather then the other▪ and many that haue been old scholers, may be <hi>Neophytes</hi> by differring baptisme. And if <hi>Phylacteries</hi> be allowed for English <hi>Mat.</hi> 23, we hope that <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dragmes</hi> also, <hi>Prepuce, Paraclete,</hi> and such like, wil easily grow to be currant and familiar. And in good sooth there is in al these such necessitie, that they can not conueniently be translated.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> as when S. Paul saith, <hi>concisio, non circumcisi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>:</hi> how can we but folow his very wordes and allusion? And how is it possible to expresse <hi>Euangelizo,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Vvhy vve say, <hi>our Lord,</hi> not, <hi>the Lord</hi> (but in certaine cases) see the Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations 1 <hi>Tim. 6. pag.</hi> 585.</note> but as vve do, <hi>Euangelize?</hi> for <hi>Euangelium</hi> being the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel▪ what is, <hi>Euangelizo</hi> or <hi>to Euangelize,</hi> but to shew the glad tydings of the Gospel, of the time of grace, of al Christs benefites? Al which signification is lost, by translating as the English bibles do, <hi>I bring you good tydings.</hi> Luc. 2, 10. Therfore we say <hi>Depositum,</hi> 2 Tim. 6. and, He <hi>exinanited</hi> him self, Philip. 2. and, You haue <hi>reflorished,</hi> Philip. 4. and, <hi>to exhaust,</hi> Hebr. 9, 28, because vve can not possibly attaine to expresse these vvordes fully in English, and vve thinke much better, that the reader staying at the difficultie of them, should take an occasion to looke in the table folovving, or othervvise to aske the ful meaning of them, then by putting some vsual English vvordes that expresse them not,<note place="margin">Catholike ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes proceding from the very text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> so to deceiue the reader. Sometime also vve doe it for an other cause. as vvhen vve say, <hi>The aduent of our Lord,</hi> and, <hi>Imposing of handes,</hi> because one is a solemne time, the other a solemne action in the Catholike Church: to signifie to the people, that these and such like names come out of the very Latin text of the Scripture. So did <hi>Penance, doing penance, Chalice, Priest, Deacon, Traditions aultar, host,</hi> and the like (vvhich vve exactly keepe as Catholike termes) procede euen from the very vvordes of Scripture.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, we presume not in hard places to mollifie the speaches or phrases, but religiously keepe them vvord for vvord, and point for point, for feare of missing,<note place="margin">Certaine hard speaches and phrases.</note> or restraining the sense of the holy Ghost to our phantasie. as Eph. 6. <hi>Against the spirituals of vvickednes in the celestials.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Io. 2.</note> and, <hi>Vvhat to me and thee vvoman?</hi> whereof see the Annotation vpon this place. and 1 Pet. 2. <hi>As infants euen novv borne, reasonable, milke vvithout guile desire ye.</hi> Vve do so place, <hi>reasonable,</hi> of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, that it may be indiffēt both to infants going before, as in our Latin text: or to milke that folovveth after, as in other Latin copies and in the Greeke. <hi>Io. 3</hi> vve translate,<note place="margin">The Protestāts presumptuous boldnes and Ii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettie in trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating.</note>
      <hi>The spirit breatheth vvhere he vvil &amp;c.</hi> leauing it indifferent to signifie either the holy Ghost, or vvinde: vvhich the Protestants translating, <hi>vvinde,</hi> take avvay the other sense more common and vsual in the auncient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Vve translate Luc. 8, 23. <hi>They vvere filled,</hi> not adding of our ovvne, <hi>vvith vvater,</hi> to mollifie the sentence, as the Protestants doe. and c. 22. <hi>This is the chalice, the nevv Testament &amp;c.</hi> not, <hi>This chalice is the nevv Testament, likevvise,</hi> Mar. 13. <hi>Those daies shal be such tribulation &amp;c.</hi> not as the Aduersaries, <hi>In those daies,</hi> both our text and theirs being othervvise Iac. 4, 6. <hi>And giueth greater grace,</hi> leauing it indifferent to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> or to the <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> both going before. Vvhereas the Aduersaries to to boldly &amp; presumptuously adde, saying, <hi>The Scripture giueth,</hi> taking avvay the other sense, which is far more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable. likevvise <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12, 21 vve translate, <hi>So terrible vvas it vvhich vvas seen, Moyses said &amp;c.</hi> neither doth Greeke or Latin permit vs to adde, <hi>that,</hi> Moyses said, as the Protestants presume to doe. So vve say, <hi>Men brethren, Avvidovv vvoman, A vvoman a sister, Iames of Alphaus,</hi> and the like. Sometime also we fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of purpose the Scriptures phrase. as,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note>
      <hi>The hel of fire,</hi> according to Greeke and
<pb facs="12"/> Latin. vvhich we might say perhaps, <hi>the firy hel,</hi> by the Hebrue phrase in such speaches,<note place="margin">Gehenn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> ignis.</note> but not, <hi>hel fire,</hi> as commonly it is translated. Likevvise <hi>Luc.</hi> 4, 36. Vvhat <hi>vvord</hi> is this, that in povver and authoritie he cōmaundeth the vncleane spirits? as also, <hi>Luc</hi> 2. Let vs passe ouer, and see the <hi>vvord</hi> that is done, Vvhere we might say, <hi>thing,</hi> by the Hebrue phrase, but there is a certaine maiestie and more signification in these speaches, and therfore both Greeke &amp; Latin keepe them, although it is no more the Greeke or Latin phrase, then it is English. And vvhy should vve be squamish at nevv vvordes or phrases in the Scripture, vvhich are necessarie: vvhen vve do easily admit and folovv nevv vvordes coyned in court and in courtly or other secular vvritings?</p>
   <p>Vve adde the Greeke in the margent for diuers cause<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.<note place="margin">The Greeke added often in the margent for many causes.</note> Sometime vvhen the sense is hard, that the learned reader may consider of it and see if he can helpe him self better then by our translation. as Luc 11. <hi>Nolite extolli.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. and againe, <hi>Quod superest date eleemosynam.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. Sometime to take away the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguitie of the Latin or English, as Luc. 11. Et <hi>domus supradomum cadet.</hi> Vvhich we must needes English, <hi>and house vpon house, shal fall.</hi> by the Greeke, the sense is not, one house shal fal vpon an other. but, if one house rise vpon it self, that is, against it self, it shal perish according as he speaketh of a kingdom deuided against it self, in the wordes before. And Act. 14. <hi>Sacerdos Iouis qui erat.</hi> in the Greeke, <hi>qui,</hi> is referred to Iupiter. Sometime to satisfie the reader, that might otherwise conceiue the translation to be false as <hi>Philip. 4. v.</hi> 6. But in euery thing by praier, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, not, <hi>in al praier,</hi> as in the Latin it may seeme. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time when the Latin neither doth, nor can, reache to the signification of the Greeke word, we added the Greeke also as more significant.<note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note>
      <hi>Illi foli seruies, him only shalt thou serue,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. And <hi>Act.</hi> 6. Nicolas a <hi>stranger</hi> of Antioche, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, and, <hi>Ro. 9. The seruice,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. to <hi>perfite, instaurare omnia in Christo,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. And, <hi>Vvherein he hath gratified vs,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. &amp; Eph. 6. <hi>Put on the armour,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. and a number the like. Sometime, when the Greeke hath two senses, and the Latin but one, we adde the Greeke. 2. Cor. 1. <hi>By the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taion vvherevvith vve also are exhorted.</hi> the Greeke signifieth also <hi>consolation &amp;c.</hi> and 2 Cor. 10. <hi>But hauing hope of your faith increasing, to be &amp;c.</hi> vvhere the Greeke may also signifie, <hi>as</hi> or <hi>vvhen your faith increaseth.</hi> Sometime for aduantage of the Catholike cause, when the Greeke maketh for vs more then the Latin. as, Seniores,<note place="margin">Act. 15. 2 Thes. 2.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Vt digni habeamini.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Qui effundetur,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Praecepta,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. &amp; Io. 21. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Pasce &amp; rege.</hi> And sometime to shew the false translation of the Heretike,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> as when Beza saith, <hi>Hoc poculum in meo sanguine qui.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. &amp;, <hi>Quē oportet coelo cōtineri.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Act.</hi> 3. Thus we vse the Greeke diuers waies, &amp; esteeme of it as it is worthie, &amp; taken al cōmodities thereof for the better vnderstāding of the Latin, which being a translation, can not alwaies attaine to the ful sense of the principal tonge, as vve see in al translations.</p>
   <p>Item vve adde the Latin vvord sometime in the margent,<note place="margin">The Latin text sometime no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent.</note> vvhen either vve can not fully expresse it, (as <hi>Act.</hi> 8. They tooke order for Steuens funeral, <hi>Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerunt Stephanum.</hi> and, Al take not this vvord, <hi>Non omnes capiunt.</hi>) or vvhen the reader might thinke, it can not be as vve translate. as, <hi>Luc.</hi> 8. A storme of winde descended into the lake, and <hi>they vvere filled, &amp; complebantur.</hi> and Io. 5. vvhen Iesus knevv that he had novv a long time, <hi>quiaiam multum tempus haberet.</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in his infirmitie.</p>
   <p>This precise folovving of our Latin text, in neither adding nor dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing, is the cause why we say not in the title of bookes, in the first page, S. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thevv,
<pb facs="13"/> S. Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> because it is so neither in Greeke nor Latin.<note place="margin">In the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of bookes, Matthew, Paul &amp;c. not S. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew. S. Paul &amp;c.</note> though in the top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of the leaues folovving, where vve may be bolder, we adde, S. Matthew &amp;c. to satisfie the reader. Much vnlike to the Protestants our Aduersaries, vvhich make no scruple to leaue out the name of Paul in the title of the Epistle to the Hebrues,<note place="margin">Bib. an. 1579. 1580. an. 1577 1562.</note> though it be in euery Greeke booke vvhich they translate. And their most authorised English Bibles leaue our (Catholike) in the title of S. Iames Epistle and the rest, vvhich vvere famously knovven in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church by the name of <hi>Catholicae Epistolae.</hi> Euseb. hist. Eccl. li. 2 c. 22.</p>
   <p>Item vve giue the Reader in places of some importance,<note place="margin">An other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent.</note> an other reading in the margent, specially vvhen the Greeke is agreable to the same. as <hi>Io. 4. transiet de morte ad vitam.</hi> Other Latin copies haue, <hi>transiit,</hi> and so it is in the Greeke.</p>
   <p>Vve binde not our selues to the pointes of any one copie, print, or edition of the vulgar Latin, in places of no controuersie, but folovv the pointing most agreable to the Greeke and to the fathers commentaries.<note place="margin">The pointing sometime al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ed.</note> As Col. 1, 10. <hi>Ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantes dignè Deo, per omnia placentes. Vvalking vvorthy of God, in al things pleasing.</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1, 17. Vve point thus, <hi>Deus Domini nostri Iesu Christi, pater gloriae.</hi> as in the Greeke, and S. Chrysostom, &amp; S. Hierom both in text and commentaries. Vvhich the Catholike reader specially must marke, lest he finde fault, vvhen he seeth our translation disagree in such places from the pointing of his Latin Testament.</p>
   <p>Vve translate sometime the word that is in the Latin margent,<note place="margin">The margent reading some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time preferred before the text.</note> and not that in the text, when by the Greeke or the fathers we see it is a manifest fault of the writers heretofore, that mistooke one word for an other. As, <hi>In fine,</hi> not, <hi>in side,</hi> 1. Pet. 3. v. 8. <hi>praesentiam,</hi> not, <hi>praescientiam,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. v. 16. Heb. 13. <hi>latuerunt,</hi> not, <hi>placue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>unt.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Thus we haue endeuoured by al meanes to satisfie the indifferent reader, and to helpe his vnderstanding euery way, both in the text, and by Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and withal to deale most sincerely before God and man, in translating and expounding the most sacred text of the holy Testament. Fare wel good Reader, and if we profit the any whit by our poore paines let vs for Gods sake be partakers of thy deuout praiers, &amp; together with humble and contrite hart call vpō our Sauiour Christ to cease these troubles &amp; stormes of his derest spouse: in the meane time comforting our selues with this saying of S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine: <hi>That Heretikes, vvhen they receiue povver corporally to afflict the Church doe exercise her patience: but vvhen they oppugne her onely by their euil doctrine or opinions. then they exercise her vvisedom.</hi> De ciuit. Dei li. 18. ca. 51.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>