<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honorable, and his singuler good Lord, the Lord Robert Dudley, knight of the honorable order of the Garter, Maistie of the Worst, and one of the Queenes maiesties most honorable priuie Counsayle.</title>
           <author>Purfoote, T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102937_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10597</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20870</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102937</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honorable, and his singuler good Lord, the Lord Robert Dudley, knight of the honorable order of the Garter, Maistie of the Worst, and one of the Queenes maiesties most honorable priuie Counsayle.</title>
                 <author>Purfoote, T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Remedies for diseases in horses : Approued and allowed by diuers very auncient learned mareschalles</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Honorable, and his singuler good Lord, the Lord <hi>Robert Dudley,</hi> knight of the honorable order of the Garter, Maistie of the Worst, and one of the Queenes maiesties most honorable priuie Counsayle.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>YOur large renowme and wel deserued prayse</l>
      <l>(Most noble Lord) in prudent shal profounde,</l>
      <l>In marcial feates, whose like in these our dayes</l>
      <l>By iust accompt scarse any where is founde,</l>
      <l>Ioyned with th'zeale borne to your countrey ground,</l>
      <l>Hath prickt me forth, and much hath moued mee,</l>
      <l>My poore good wil to shewe in some degree.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And for because your Lordships office is</l>
      <l>Most worthely assigned by our Queene,</l>
      <l>To viewe and see that nothing be amisse</l>
      <l>About her horse and stable as I ween<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</l>
      <l>But that the same in time may be foreseene,</l>
      <l>Vnto your Honour humbly I present</l>
      <l>This Treatise smal, to further that intent:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Beseeching you to take this in good part,</l>
      <l>Euen as the same with single minde is ment:</l>
      <l>Way not the gift, regarde the geuers hart,</l>
      <l>My trauayle shal happely be spent,</l>
      <l>And you also resemble verament</l>
      <l>That worthy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ing, that tooke with thankful minde</l>
      <l>A draught of water of a simple hinde.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Although this volume smal do seeme in sight,</l>
      <l>No little foulte yet therein shal you finde,</l>
      <l>A Larke in worth doth farre surmomit a Kite:</l>
      <l>A grayne of golde by doome of eche mans minde,</l>
      <l>A pounde of leade to passe is aye assignde:</l>
      <l>The Diademe in value farre exceedes</l>
      <l>Great massy rockes: fine flowers large stinking weedes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>This little booke shal teache you soone to knowe</l>
      <l>Th'original cause of eche infirmitie,</l>
      <l>That in an horse by any meanes may growe,</l>
      <l>The name, the place of euery malady,</l>
      <l>And howe you shal the cure thereto apply:</l>
      <l>So as you may by remedies founde,</l>
      <l>Preserue his health, and keepe him safe and sounds.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For though you haue a comely Courser great,</l>
      <l>And <hi>Pegasus</hi> vnto his syre he haue,</l>
      <l>Though passing trim the troden wayes he beate,</l>
      <l>With loftie looke that trotteth fine and braue,</l>
      <l>With raine as round as hare can wishe or craue</l>
      <l>As trimly treade, can yarke aboue the grounde,</l>
      <l>And seemely saulte and turne both light and rounde.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Although he can the Galliarde gallope to,</l>
      <l>Passe the Carrier, the Cornettie can daunce,</l>
      <l>Can fetche the Capriol, and other trickes can do,</l>
      <l>As braue and fine as any hence to Fraunce:</l>
      <l>What doth auayle these vertues to aduaunce,</l>
      <l>By diligence thus brought to perfect frame,</l>
      <l>If afterwarde he fal diseasde or lame?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Which to preuent this little Treatise vse,</l>
      <l>That shal (I trust) in daunger him defende.</l>
      <l>As time doth serue vouchsafe it to peruse:</l>
      <l>And so most humbly here I doo intende</l>
      <l>My leaue to take, beseeching in the ende</l>
      <l>Almightie Ioue, whom you both loue and serue,</l>
      <l>Your Lordship long in honour to preserue.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your L. most humble <hi>T. Purfoote.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>