<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102112_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00793</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10911</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102112</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The answere vnto the nine points of controuersy, proposed by our late soueraygne (of famous memory) vnto M. Fisher of the Society of Iesus : And the reioynder vnto the reply of D. Francis VVhite minister. With the picture of the sayd minister, or censure of his writings prefixed</title>
                 <author>Fisher, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 <publisher>English College Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>56, 160, 400 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="3" facs="112"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Gratious, and Dread Soueraygne,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Conference about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giō between <hi>Doctor White</hi> and Me, was occasion, that your Maiesty called me to your gracious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, not disdayning to dispute with one so meane and vnworthy as my self; imitating his Benignity whose Vicegerent you are, and according to the Phrase of Holy Scripture, <hi>As</hi>
      <note n="(a)" place="margin">
         <hi>2. Reg.</hi> 14.17. Sicut Angelus Dei, sic est Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus meus Rex.</note>
      <hi>his Angell.</hi> And as it is the property of the Good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, first to strike feare and terrour into them to whome he appeares, but in the end to leaue them full of comfort; in like sort your Maiesty. For though the first salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation carryed a shew of seuerity, yet your dismissing me was benigne and gratious, not only pardoning my earnestnes in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the part of the Catholike Church, but also saying, <note n="(*)" place="margin">What the Minister doth obiect against this narration, is refuted in M. <hi>Fishers</hi> Booke, about vntruths falsely layd to his charge.</note>
      <hi>You liked me the better.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb n="4" facs="113"/>The gratefull acknowledgement, and admiration of this your Princely Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, makes me desire from the bottome of my Soule, that I could fully satisfy your Maiestie of my dutyfull and loyall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is fast tyed vnto your sacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son by a threefold <note n="(b)" place="margin">Funiculus triplex di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficilè rumpitur. <hi>Eccles.</hi> 14.14.</note> inuiolable bond. The <note n="(*)" place="margin">The Minister saith, that the Iesuits Oratory is plausible, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon enters into a cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon place, that <hi>Truth needs no Trimming,</hi> which is true, yet if needs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes Apologies &amp; Defence against Slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note> Law of nature obligeth me thereunto, as being your Maiesties borne Subiect, the transgression whereof were Vnnaturall, Barbarous, Inhumane.</p>
   <p>The Law of God requires the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, and perfect Allegiance at my hands, binding me to regard you as his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and to acknowledge your power and authority, <hi>as</hi>
      <note n="(c)" place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note>
      <hi>his Ordination</hi>: so that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the doctrine of the Catholike Church, I must not only outwardly obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, but also admit your Maiesties will and command with Reuerence, into the secret closet of my inmost <note n="(d)" place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5.</note> Cōscience &amp; Soule.</p>
   <p>The Constitutions also of the Order wherof I am an vnworthy mēber, do strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly command me the same, in seuerest man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner charging the Subiects therof no wayes to meddle in State-matters, or in Princes affaires; much lesse vnder pretence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to attempt any thing, or to consent vnto any enterprize, that may disturbe the quiet and tranquillity of Kings and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. And seeing we are so deuoted to our own Institute, that our <note n="(e)" place="margin">
         <hi>Colloquium de Secretis Iesuitarum.</hi>
      </note> Aduersaries thereupon amongst many other Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations,
<pb n="5" facs="113"/>
lay to our charge, that we more reuerētly esteeme, &amp; carefully obserue the constitutions of our Rule, then the Law of God; I shall for your Maiesties fuller satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factiō, set downe some part of our Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions in this point, in māner following.</p>
   <p>
      <note n="(f)" place="margin">
         <hi>Decret.</hi> 101. <hi>Cong. 5. General. ac Can.</hi> 12. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ius<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</hi>
      </note>
      <note n="(g)" place="margin">
         <hi>Monita Gener. §. 18.</hi> The Constitutions, out of which these are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, be tearmed <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita Generalia,</hi> Generall Admonitions, because they cōcerne generally al persons of the Order, by way of distinction from <hi>Particular,</hi> which cōcerne only some kind of persons, as Preachers, Maisters &amp;c. Which particular Admonitiōs are as publick as the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. Whereby you may see the Ministers ignorāce in Logicke to be equall vnto his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice against Iesuits, who sayth that the terme of <hi>Generall Admonitions,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding to meddle in State-matters, argueth that Iesuits haue other <hi>Secret Admonitions,</hi> that warrant such medling. As though <hi>Generall Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions</hi> were condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct agaynst <hi>secret,</hi> and <hi>particular</hi> against <hi>publik.</hi> Wheras general may be kept <hi>secret,</hi> &amp; <hi>particular</hi> be made <hi>publike.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Vt ab omni specie mali abstinea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; querelis etiam ex falsis suspicionibus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenientibus quoad fieri poterit occurratur, praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur nostris omnibus in virtute Sanctae Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae, &amp; sub poena inhabilitatis ad quaeuis officia &amp; dignitates, seu praelationes, vocis{que} etiam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuae quàm passiuae priuationis, ne quispiam pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicis &amp; saecularibus Principum negotijs, quae ad rationem Status, vt vocant, pertineant, vlla ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione se immiscere, nec etiam quantumuis requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>situs &amp; rogatus, eiusmodires politicas tractandi curam suscipere audeat, vel praesumat.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note n="(h)" place="margin">
         <hi>Decret.</hi> 57. <hi>&amp; Can.</hi> 17.</note>
      <hi>Illa autem omnia quae à spirituali In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structione diuersa sunt, negotia Status censeri debent, qualia sunt quae ad Principum inter se foedera, vel ad Regnorum iura &amp; successiones pertinēt, vel ad bella tam ciuilia quàm externa.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note n="(i)" place="margin">
         <hi>In Regulis communibus, Reg. 41.</hi>
      </note> Iubet regula 41. <hi>vt saecularia negotia, vtpote quae sunt à nostro Instituto aliena, &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementer à spiritualibus auocant, multùm auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semur.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note n="(k)" place="margin">
         <hi>In Regulis Concionatorum.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Iubentur Concionatores Societatis à re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensionibus Principum, &amp; Magnatum Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. abstinere, &amp; obedientiā erga Principes &amp; Magistratus frequenter, &amp; seriò suis in Concio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus
<pb n="6" facs="114"/>
populo commendare.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note n="(l)" place="margin">
         <hi>In Constitutionibus.</hi>
      </note> Iubent Cōstitutiones nostrae varijs in locis, <hi>vt oremus speciatim pro Principibus, eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum{que} spirituali saluti praecipuâ curâ procuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae, ac promouendae inuigilemus, ob vniuersale bonum, quod ad multos alios qui eorum authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem sequuntur, vel per eos reguntur, proue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niet.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <note n="(m)" place="margin">
         <hi>In Instructionibus.</hi>
      </note> Extat denique Instructio pro Confessarijs Principum, <hi>quâ Nostris seriò interdicitur, ne occasione huius muneris rebus Politicis, aut Reipublicae gubernationi se immis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceant. Iubentur etiam hanc Instructionē Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pibus ostendere, curare{que} vt ij planè intelligant, quid Societas ab eo postulat qui Confessarium sibi eligit, neque per Leges nostras licere nobis alijs conditionibus id oneris suscipere.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I humbly craue pardon for offering so many particulers of our Rule vnto your Maiesties perusall, which I should not haue done, but out of a most strong desire to giue your Maiestie <note n="(n)" place="margin">
         <p>The Minister sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth this argumēt into this forme: <hi>No Iesuite ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing the Rules of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der can meddle in state mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Euery Iesuit obserueth the rules of his Order.</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, <hi>No Iesuit doth meddle in State matters.</hi> And thē in answere thereof he sayth: <hi>He that belieues the</hi> Minor, <hi>must be a stranger in the world, and haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued an Anchoret, or Recluse in some Caue, who neuer heard of</hi> Campian, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, Creswell, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, Suarez, Bellarmin, &amp;c. I Answere, This doth shew the Innocē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Iesuits, seeing you can bring no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of their dealing in State-matters, but such as are eyther ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culously impertinent, or manifestly false. Was it matter of State, and not of Religion in <hi>Bellarmine</hi> to write agaynst the English abnegation of the Popes Authority? Or in <hi>Suarez,</hi> to write <hi>Contra sectam Anglicanam,</hi> the English Schisme and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy? Or in <hi>Philopater,</hi> to write for the Innocency of Catholike Priests? Or in <hi>Mariana,</hi> to giue instructions about the pious Education of a Christian Prince? In which writings if they hap to erre (as <hi>Mariana</hi> did not by way of assertion, but by way of doubt) doth this proue they dealt in state-mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? The Casuists that write about matters of Conscience, how farre Kinges may proceed without sinne and diuine offence in waging warre, exacting Tribute, and the like state-actions, do they deale in state-matters if perchance they hap to erre? What impertinency is this?</p>
         <p>Now also see your falshood. That <hi>Fa. Parsons</hi> wrote the booke called <hi>Dole-man,</hi> you cannot proue, and he with oath denyed it, naming ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther secular Gentleman, as Authour. That <hi>M. Garnet</hi> had his annoynted fingar in the Gunpowder treason, is so false, as euen your Lord <hi>Cooke</hi> did not accuse his Fingars of dealing therein, but only his Eares for hearing thereof in Confession. What Catholike in Christendome, though an Anchoret or Recluse, hath not heard of the singular Innocency &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy of <hi>F. Campian,</hi> and of your Hereticall barbarity towards him? <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bden</hi> in your Protestant History [<hi>Elizab. pag.</hi> 336.] doth acknowledge, that the Queene (which she would not haue done, had she not been well assured of his Innocency) would no wayes a long tyme consent vnto his execution. At last, seeing your Ministeriall rage agaynst him would not belieue her to be truly a Protestant in heart vnlesse she imbrued her hands in his Innocent bloud [<hi>importunis precibus euicta permisit</hi>] being ouercome by your importunity, she permitted him to your cruelty (as <hi>Pilate</hi> did Christ to the Iewes) to be butchered, with sundry other Priests, [<hi>pleros{que} tamen conscios fuisse non credidit</hi>] yet did she not (sayth he) belieue some of them to be guilty of the treasons you in your malice obiected agaynst them.</p>
         <p>And yet if some Iesuit should agaynst his Rule meddle in State-mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, is this to be imputed to the Order? Did all the Apostles, and all the Angells keep their Order? Yea, seing you hold Ministers to be worthy of Religious Adoration [<hi>pag.</hi> 224.] and therfore more holy and venerable then Angells, I pray you, do they all keep their Orders, Rules &amp; Canons? Yet euery man is to be thought to keep the Rules of his Society and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporation, vntill the contrary be cleerly proued agaynst him. And when this is proued agaynst some one, that crime is to be taken as the fault of the person, not of the Order. This is the law of common Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the contrary proceeding of Ministers agaynst Iesuits, is Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and Sauage.</p>
      </note> satisfactiō, against such wrongefull aspersions, wherewith
<pb n="7" facs="114"/>
Maleuolency, and Suspicion laboureth to disgrace vs, &amp; to make vs odious to them, whome (howsoeuer disaffected from vs) we must perpetually reuerence and obey; and of whom vnder God, our comfort, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fety, and the successe of our Labours doth
<pb n="8" facs="115"/>
principally depend. And when I consider your Maiesties gracious disposition, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent maturity, &amp; sharpnes of Iudgment to penetrate assuredly into the depth of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, togeather with our Innocency, whereof our owne Conscience is vnto vs insteed of a thousand Witnesses, and which (as we are perswaded) doth in the course of our actions, and whole procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings appeare to any that shall vnpartially and without passion looke into them▪ I cannot despayre, but the prayers which for this intent with teares and afflicted harts we daily powre forth, will at last so much preuayle with that Soueraigne Gouernour of the world, <note n="(o)" place="margin">Cor Regis in manu Domini. <hi>Prou. c.</hi> 21.1.</note>
      <hi>in whose hands are the hart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of Princes,</hi> that your Maiestie may conceiue some better opiniō of your (without cause so much calumniated) subiects, as to iudge of vs according as our Cōstitutions frame vs, and our Actions deserue; and not as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> pleaseth disaffection to paint vs forth.</p>
   <p>And as your Maiesty is a liuing Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt of that late Paragō of <hi>France, Henry</hi> the fourth, and of his wisdom and other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cely excellencyes; so why may we not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayne a far off a hopefull thought that your Maiesty may one day be better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med against so many maleuolent suggesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and see that they proceed from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther origen then our desert, as that famous <note n="(p)" place="margin">Heere also the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister formeth the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after his owne stāpe, as if the argumēt were grounded on the temporall prosperity of this King, saying: <hi>Your reuerence looketh this way: Henry the fourth a wise King was prosperous in his re-intertayning the Iesuits.</hi> Ergo, <hi>the King of great Britayne should do well to intertayne them.</hi> Did not the Minister looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>squint on Iesuites, he would not haue thus wrested the argument awry. The Argument is this: <hi>Henry</hi> a wise and prudent King, bitterly incensed against Iesuits through misinformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by exact looking into their Institute and course of life, discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that only Maleuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency voyd of truth, did vent such accusatiōs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynst them. Therefore the same may happen, and be hoped of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as wise and prudēt a Prince. Temporall Prosperity, as it doth not euer accōpany the friends of Iesus, so neither the fauourers of Iesuits, nor I thinke the friends of Ministers. The first king in the world that euer loued Minister, was <hi>Christerne</hi> king of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> a fast friend vnto <hi>Luther,</hi> of whose miseries &amp; misfortunes all historyes are full. [<hi>Tribus Regnis exutus à suis, &amp; à Successore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>inctus in Clathrata cauea &amp;c. Tursellin. hist. pag.</hi> 256.] Can they brag of the prosperity of the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> their first Prince in Germany? of <hi>Seyme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> their first Prince in <hi>England</hi>? of <hi>Iames</hi> the bastard their first in <hi>Scotland</hi>? of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> their first in the Low Countryes?</note> Prince did, thereupon restoring the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> whome sinister Information had banished
<pb n="9" facs="115"/>
whom sinister Information had banished out of his kingdome, for which fact (saith the <note n="(*)" place="margin">
         <hi>Petrus Mattheus in his History of Henry the fourth of France.</hi>
      </note> Historiographer of France) <hi>he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued thankes from all parts of the world, euen out of</hi> Peru, and Cochin, Iapon, Goa, and China with presents of some singularities of the Country. <hi>I obserued</hi> (saith the same Author) <hi>the pleasure which he tooke in spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of that action, and what content he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, when as a great Cardinall told him that by this restoring, his Maiestye had gotten two thousand learned pens for his seruice and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual fame. When as the Iesuits represented vnto him the Catalogue of Colledges, &amp; the thankes of the three Prouinces of France, he vsed these words vnto them, which should serue as an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphe vpon all their houses:</hi> Assurance fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes Confidence; <hi>I trust in you, assure your selues of me; with these papers I receiue the harts of all your company, and with the effects I will witnes mine vnto you. I haue allwaies said that they which feare and loue God well, cannot but do well,</hi> and are alwaies most faithfull to their Prince. <hi>We are now better informed, I did hold you to be otherwise then you are, and
<pb n="10" facs="116"/>
you haue found me other then you held me. I would it had beene sooner, but there is meanes to recompence what is past. Loue me, and I will loue you.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Noe labours would we spare, nor any endeauour omit, nor sticke to venture the losse of any thing deare vnto vs (except the grace of God &amp; our eternall saluation) to purchase a small portion of that fauour your Maiesties meanest subiects enioy, that we might in some sort cooperate to the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of the Christian world, which (as we are perswaded) doth on your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styes person singularly depend.</p>
   <p>For God, rich in mercy and goodnes, as he hath made your Maiesty partaker of his power &amp; authority in gouerning this inferiour world: so likewise he hath ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you with many Excellent guifts, as Wisedome, Learning, Authority with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Princes, and Common Wealthes, made you beloued of your subiects, that on you are cast the eyes of all Christiā coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes, as on the person whom the Prince of peace, hath beyond the rest enabled, to <note n="(q)" place="margin">Heere our Replicant shewes himselfe to be according to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steriall kind, by railing at the Answerer, &amp; by scorning <hi>Peace and vnity,</hi> saying contemptuously: <hi>Forsooth to ioyne togeather againe the parts of Christē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome distracted. Decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers loue to fish in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled waters.</hi> It was Luthers ioy to see the world in dissensiō. tom. 9. Germ. de Comit. Worm. fol. 8. <hi>Nihil ita mihi visu iucundum, quàm cùm tumultus &amp; dissenssio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes exoriuntur.</hi>
      </note> ioyne togeather againe the parts of Christendome distracted one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through Controuersies of Religion.</p>
   <p>If the requests of the pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers were such as the Roman Church might yield vnto them, without ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing the very foundations of the vnity of Fayth; if insteed of Catholike
<pb n="11" facs="116"/>
principles misliked by them, they did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose such other of their owne, as she might see some probability▪ or allmost possibility of assured cōtinued peace likely to follow vpon her yielding in some points; feeling-Compassion (in regard of the wound of discord bleeding in the hart of Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) would moue her to the vttermost approach towards Protestāts, that the Law of God can permit, though with some dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to her Honour.</p>
   <p>But so it is, that those that desire her reformation, be so many for number, and for opinions so deuided amongst thēselues, that it is impossible she should satisfy all. <note n="(r)" place="margin">
         <p>The Minister a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this cleere &amp; cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincing discourse of the Answerer, cōmeth forth with this syllogisme set downe in a distinct let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ech proposition in a distinct line very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestically. <hi>Whosoeuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth in errour, ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>The Roman Church abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in errour.</hi> Ergo,</p>
         <p>
            <hi>The Roman Church ought to reforme.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi>The Assumption</hi> (saith he) <hi>is manifest by the repugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes of the Roman doctrine with holy Scripture.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Is not this most ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous? Against him I op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose this Syllogisme. The Minister forced by truth, doth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that by Theology which he calls Sophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strie, <hi>we giue seeming solu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vnto their arguments out of Scripture.</hi> pag. 581. But Arguments vnto which seeming solutiōs are giuen, be not manifest. <hi>Ergo,</hi> Protestants haue no manifest argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to proue our Religion to be against Scripture, and so without ground breake the peace of Christendome.</p>
      </note> Their conditions of peace are, that she reforme herselfe, by forsaking definitions of Generall Councells, Customes, Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vniuersally receiued for many ages, tyme out of mind cōfessedly without any <hi>knowne beginning</hi> since the Apostles. Insteed of these meanes (so potent to stay stagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Consciences, and to keep the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian world in peace) they present her with the Scripture, vnderstood <note n="(s)" place="margin">The Minister heere very impudently denies that Protestants resolue by priuate illumination; whereas himselfe more then twenty times in this Reply, doth teach that ech Protestant doth lastly resolue by diuine illumination, whereby he seeth manifestly the resplendant verity of things belieued, as wil appeare afterward.</note> by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate illumination, the source of discord,
<pb n="12" facs="117"/>
from which an Ocean of strife must needs flow. These things considered your most Iudicious Maiesty cannot but see, that her yielding would not compose debates al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready begun, but rather open a wide gappe vnto innumerable new braules, &amp; bring them into Kingdomes hitherto with such dissention vntoucht.</p>
   <p>Wherfore there being no possibility that the Catholike part could gaine peace to Christendome by any yielding vnto our aduersaryes either reasonable, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable; whither should louers of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord turne themselues but vnto your Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Maiesty, that haue in your power the affections of Protestants, and therfore would be the <note n="(t)" place="margin">Heere the Minister raileth vēting new scol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Phrases, <hi>Grosse er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and the sharking ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine of the Romish Harpyes, trampling Gods truth, and Gods people vnder the foote of the inerrable, and vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollable Grand Seigneur, of the seauen-hilled-Citty, lewd Superstition, Roman tyrāny</hi>: tearming the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerer <hi>impudent, bold, franticke, guided by an euill Genius,</hi> &amp; the like, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for motioning vnto his Maiesty the meanes of the reunion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome, and for his conceauing some possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to giue satisfactiō which his maiesty him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe doth allow that we should conceaue as possible, saying; Except she reforme herselfe, or else be ABLE to giue me satisfaction.</note> fittest instrumēt for their Re-vnion with the Roman Church. The God of Charity hath put into your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties hart a desire of vnity of the Church, and into your hand an Oliue-bough. Crowne of peace, to set it on the head of Christendome, which weary of endles cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention powreth forth vnto your Maiesty her suppliant Complaint; <hi>Quem das finem (Rex Magne) laborum?</hi> And seing nothing hindreth, but that your selfe are not yet sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfyed in some Doctrines of the Romane church, particularly <hi>in the Nine points</hi> your Maiesty hath set downe in writing, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly present vnto your Maiesty these my poore labours for your satisfaction, so much desired of the Christian world.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>