<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102503_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01115</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11229</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102503</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An abridgement of the booke of acts and monumentes of the Church : vvritten by that Reuerend Father, Maister Iohn Fox: and now abridged by Timothe Bright, Doctour of Phisicke, for such as either through want of leysure, or abilitie, haue not the vse of so necessary an history</title>
                 <author>Foxe, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <publisher>Bright, Timothy.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 504, 288, 64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsidering the great vse and profite of that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie worke of <hi>Actes and Monumentes,</hi> written by Master <hi>Iohn Fox,</hi> of blessed memorie: and by reason of the largenes of the volume, and great price, how the most were bereaued of the benefite of so necessarie an Historie: J often wished, some man would take the paines to draw the same into an Abridgement: that, both those that are busied in affaires, or not able to reach to the price of so great a booke, might also haue vse of the historie with them that neither want leisure, nor hability suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient. But, seeing hetherto nothing done that way, nor hearing of any that had it in purpose, J vētured vpon the labor my self, &amp; thus haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it for thy vse: wherein, J haue omitted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to my remembrance, and as my iudgement serued me, that is materiall to the historie, so farre as the nature of an Abridgement would permitte. As for Treatises, Disputations, Epistles, and such like, J leaue them to be read all together in the large Booke: which I doe exhort thee (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)
<pb facs="3"/> the rather for my Abridgements sake, to buy, and vse. For, as the copiousnes of that notable worke, hath hid the riche treasures of the same, through charge of price, and mens affaires: So this my labour may geue thee an assay, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, to know further, whereof thou maist here take (as it were) the taste. J assure thee, in mine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, there is not a booke, vnder the Scriptures, more necessarie for a Christian to be conuersant in. There is no Burgesse of a Citie, that hath care of his corporation, but would be glad to know, how in times past, the world went with his Corporatiō, that therby he may vnderstād the better how to be haue himselfe therein, as occasion shall serue: and, not onely woulde desire to knowe the lawes of the same, but also, what examples haue any way beene geuen, touching the same. Euen so, it becommeth much more Christians, that are Citizens of the church of Christ, and haue a communitie in that bodie, to know, not onely the lawes of this Citie, (which is the word of God) but also, what hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen, either good, or bad, and euerye accident: whereupon, experience may arise by example, and wisdome thereof, to be put in vse accordingly. We may read what hath befallen the worthiest Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths in this world, and what stormes they
<pb facs="3"/> haue endured, and all sunke, vnder them. This Common-wealth of the Church standeth for euer, though the stormes that haue blowen vpon it, haue beene more boysterous than any other state hath endured. And by reason of cōtinuāce, geueth great varietie of examples: of Gods prouidence, of his mercie, of his fatherly chastizements, and correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of that holy faith, which hath ministred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible strength of constancie, &amp; patience to this heauenly state of Christes Church, in the middest of all stormes of tryall. And here mayst thou reade, not onely what hath beene suffered of the olde Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the church, who haue with their bloud pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased vnto vs this freedome of the Gospell: but of late times, what thy father, thy mother, thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her, and thy friēd haue suffered for like testimonie, wherby the sincerity of the Gospel standeth at this day. When (I say) in this Abridgement, thou maist reade these things, J mean much more in the large volume, where all such matters lie open at the full: and whereto (I pray thee) let this my labour be (as it were) an introduction. And if thy hability serue thee, or any other disposition thereto, J pray thee let not this booke withdraw thee. For, Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in all kinde of learning, haue byn vsed, for such respects as J haue before mentioned: besides,
<pb facs="4"/> the memorie embraceth them more readily: and not to hinder great volumes. Neither doo they of their own nature, work such effect. If slouth of some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons neglect them, so are they punished therfore in wanting that belongeth vnto them to know: &amp; yet through Abridgementes, haue some furniture of that profitable instruction, whereof otherwise they would be vtterly ignorant. It is said, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines</hi> Abridgement lost <hi>Trogus Pompeius: Trogus</hi> peraduenture is lost, but whether through <hi>Iustines</hi> Abridgement, that hardly can be proued: and had it not beene for <hi>Iustine,</hi> we had lost with <hi>Trogus,</hi> the history too. The case is far otherwise since printing was knowen: for, who would lose a leafe of <hi>Liuie,</hi> for any Abridgement. Before, it may be, charge of written Copies might be some cause, why the large volumes were not so vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall. And I pray thee, if the Author him self (the fittest of all men, being an History so meet, euen for the meanest Christian, especially in these times, and conteyning recordes of such things, as are els no where to be had) had takē it in hand: had it not byn thanks-woorthy? Yet so had beene greater danger in decaying the booke at large in regard of the more sufficient performance of the worke, than by this of mine. I trust the matter needeth no</p>
   <gap reason="missing" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ pages">
      <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>