<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Sparke, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102433_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12700</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23019.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102433</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Sparke, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A brotherly persvvasion to vnitie, and vniformitie in iudgement, and practise touching the receiued, and present ecclesiasticall gouernment, and the authorised rites and ceremonies of the Church of England : VVritten by Thomas Sparke Doctor in Diuinitie. And seene, allowed, and commended by publike authoritie to be printed</title>
                 <author>Sparke, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 83, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Christian <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant (welbeloued in the Lord) that I haue and doe vndergoe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready the hard censure of many for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming my selfe as I haue to the orders of our Church, and that I am like to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure harder for the writing and publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Treatise following, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade others so to doe likewise. And all this the rather, for that eyther through ignorance what my iudgement in former times hath beene of these matters now in question, or misconstruction of some of my former actions, many as it seemeth (haue conceiued) that heretofore I haue not beene the same man, that now in this my dealing I mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest my selfe to be. To satisfie therefore all men (if it may be) in this respect; first they are to vnderstand that though there be now, vpon occasion of the manner of this new vrging the rites and ordinances of our Church as they are, some diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in outward shew, betwixt my former courses, and this which I now take, that yet that prooues not (circumstances duely considered) any alteration of my minde or iudgement at all touching these things: For I alwaies before, as occasion serued me, both in Pulpit, and otherwise in priuate conference with many, manifested my selfe to be of that opinion, that I alwaies thought they were rather to be yealded vnto, being but of the nature they are, and being vrged no otherwise then
<pb facs="5"/>in deed and truth they be, by our Church, then that any mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster should for his refusing conformity therunto, suffer himself to be put from the vse of his gifts, place and ministery, for such a necessity is laid vpon vs that be in the ministery, (I alwaies knew and remembred) to preach the Gospell, that woe is to vs if we do not so: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. And with <hi>Archippus</hi> I euer vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, that <hi>Paule</hi> had said to euery one of vs, take heed to thy ministery that thou hast receiued in the Lord, that thou fulfill it. <hi>Coll.</hi> 4.17. And therfore I could neuer think (and so my vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all saying hath been alwaies to my friends and felow ministers talking with me of these things) that at the last day it would or could be taken for a sufficient excuse or reason in any of vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the great Iudge of quick &amp; dead, and the chiefe Bishop of our soules, of and for our surceasing therefrom, to say and plead we could not be suffered to continue and to go on therin vnlesse we conformed our selues in these thinges, as this our Church requireth now at our hands. And therefore also how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer otherwise weake brethren were not wilfully and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly in such things to be offended by vs, yet if after so many yeares instruction, they would be so weake still, as that they would rather wish vs to leaue our ministery, what mischiefe or inconuenience soeuer therby should grow, eyther to them, or to our selues and ours, and to the whole Church by our so doing, then to yeald to the vse of these things, I could neuer yet perswade my selfe that we were bound, to preuent the not offending of such, by suffering our selues to be run vpon these so daungerous rocks. But indeed I alwaies rather thought, that that was to redeeme the not offending of them in such things, at a farre higher and costlier rate and price, then eyther wee were bound to giue for it, or it were worth: and therefore that in this case, the onely thing that remained for vs to doe, was, holding on still our ministery, better to instruct them, and to
<pb facs="5"/>pray for them that God would make them wiser and stronger, and so to leaue them to him. And the rather haue I beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in this my opinion, because I plainly find, that Maister <hi>Cartwright</hi> himselfe (as desirous as he was otherwise, that they that are in authoritie would haue rather beene pleased to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue sundrie of thē) was yet in this case of the very same iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as any man may see he was in his secōd part of his secōd reply, chap. the last. Then secondly, though when I haue beene called by lawfull authoritie to some conference about these matters (as sometimes I haue beene; and by the same had leaue then freely to say my mind touching these things) I haue not refused in dutifull manner to lay downe my reasons, why they that were in authoritie (hauing questionlesse thereby power as well to remooue or alter such rites and ceremonies, as to continue them, as that plainely is confest they haue, both in our Common Booke it selfe, and in the booke of Articles) might well be pleased, for the better encouraging of many, both to enter into the ministerie, and the quieter to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue therein, as also thereby the sooner to breed peace, vnitie and loue amongst our selues, and to remooue offence from the weake and tender consciences of many, to vse their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authoritie, rather to remooue, or alter certaine of them, then to continue and vrge them as they were: yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen then also (as it is well knowne, as occasion was offered) I sundrie times plainely protested, that for my owne part, those reasons notwithstanding, I thought it not fitt, if authoritie would not yeelde therefore so to do, but for other reasons see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of more force thereunto, should chuse rather to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and so to vrge them still, that any man therefore eyther should shunne the ministerie, or suffer himselfe to be depriued thereof. For I neuer thought them, but waied and vnderstood as they are with vs, eyther of themselues simply vnlawfull,
<pb facs="6"/>or any way so inconuenient, that any should therefore runne vpon eyther of these rocks. Much more therefore I haue won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at those men, and greatly alwaies in my minde haue I misliked them, who for things of no other nature then these (about which our domesticall controuersies haue beene) haue yet euen therefore growne vnto such a mislike of the state of our Church, as that they both in pulpit and print, haue thought they might, not onely most bitterly seeke the disgrace both of it, and the gouernours thereof, but also make (as they haue too to many of them) a plaine and open schisme therin, yea and an vtter rent &amp; breach therfrom. And (I praise God for it) the feare thereof from the beginning, and the falling of it out so when it did, together with the serious consideration of the nature of the questions themselues, haue so alwaies kept me in loue and liking of the present gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the orders thereof, that hitherto euer peaceably and quietly, I haue liued vnder, and in the practise thereof, and neuer yet could be brought (how well soeuer I haue liked of some that haue seemed zealous &amp; forward in wishing as they counted it, reformation of and in certaine things, for their painfulnesse in their places, and fruitfulnesse of their labours otherwise in their ministery) eyther to be present at any of their meetings and consultations to that end, or to yeald them my hand at any time, to any thing concluded therein by them: yea alwaies as I haue said, I haue not onely misli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, (to the disturbance and disquiet of so famous a Church of Christ as this of ours is) all those their exceptions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it notwithstanding, that any should seeke eyther in Pulpit or Print, to deface it and disgrace it, as I sawe too many did: but also what credite soeuer at any time God hath giuen mee with any, especially of any great place, I haue vsed it to the best of my skill, and credite with them,
<pb facs="6"/>to breede and to nourish in them a good liking of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Church-gouernment, and so in time and place to bee as they might, Patrons for it, rather then any way to suffer themselues to bee drawne to ioyne with them that sought the subuersion thereof, and to bring in an other. Inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that thirdly I may with a safe and good conscience both before GOD and man proteste, that I neuer yet coulde bee brought by any thing that I haue euer heard or read to that purpose these foure and thirtie yeares that I haue beene in the Ministerie (and yet I thinke I haue read most, if not all that hath beene since written to that ende) eyther to thinke that forme and plott of Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement so much admired and magnifyed as the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and onely fit gouernement for Christes Church by a paritie of Ministers and their Presbiteries, eyther fitting for such a Monarchye as this is, or any way in deede so aunswerable or conformable to the perpetuall gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vsed by GOD for and in his Church, eyther since <hi>Moses</hi> or <hi>Christ,</hi> during the Storie, eyther of Newe Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Olde, as this by <hi>Archbishopps, Bishoppes,</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors</hi> of ours is. And heereupon it hath beene, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great part of my time Bishoppe <hi>Coopers</hi> Chaplaine, to my good liking, and contentment, I haue not onely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies euer since I was Minister, liued as an ordinarie Pastour, euer also discharging the office of such an one, in my own person, in and vnder this gouernment, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at any time once, eyther presented or conuented, for the omission or transgression of any of the orders there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; but also for sundrie yeares was I by the said Bishoppes gifte Archdeacon of <hi>Stow</hi> in <hi>Lincolnshire,</hi> and so had beene still, but that it was so farre from mee, that I found I coulde not do that good therein that otherwise I
<pb facs="7"/>might, and in conscience tooke my selfe bound to haue done. Likewise hence it hath beene, that neuer to this day was I so much as made priuie too, or acquainted with any petition or supplication exhibited to Prince, Parliament, or Conuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation tending to any alteration of this present gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And lastly, certaine it is, that I neuer ministred the Communion but I receiued it kneeling, and as for the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plesse I haue long agoe, and verie often worne it, neyther e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer refused I the wearing of it, where or when I had one to weare, and when it was eyther by my people, or by the Ordinarie of the place required at my hands, or when I my selfe saw the vse of it would open vnto me any wider doore, or procure me any more opportunitie to doe good with any: and when I least vsed it, yet euen then also I had a care, when my Text gaue mee any occasion, so to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint my people with the doctrine of Christian liberty, and to teach them the free vse of such indifferent things, that it should not any way be iustly offensiue to any of them, when at any time for order sake, vpon occasion they should see mee most formally vse them. And touching subscription if I would or should denie it, sure I am the Bishoppe of <hi>Lincolnes</hi> recordes would prooue it, that twice or thrice I haue heretofore vpon occasion subscribed, in effect euen as now it is required. Finally, I must needes say (whatsoeuer other men haue fancied of mee) though with <hi>Bucer</hi> in his opinion giuen of our Common Booke, I haue thought certayne things therein so set downe, as that <hi>Nisi candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de intelligantur,</hi> that is, vnlesse they bee fauourably vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood, they seeme to carrie some shew of contrarietie to the word of God, yet in verie deede, I neuer thought any thing therein, or within the compasse of the required sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription such, but that the same by such a charitable and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable
<pb facs="7"/>construction, and that also but well standing with the professed, and publikely established doctrine of our Church, and with the best and true meaning of the Bookes themselues whence the obiections to the contrarie did seeme to arise, might with a good conscience for the peace and good of the Church be quietly yealded vnto. And in that best sense, as I knew charitie did binde vs all to take euery thing, so I coulde neuer be perswaded, but that with a very good liking, and allowance of the state, wee freely might. And therefore that is all that euer I desired, if to them that were in authoritie, in peaceable manner by conference with or before them, when it should or did please themselues to call or admit men thereunto, it could not be perswaded, for the reasons and respects aforesaid, that it were best to alter those things, whereupon some tooke occasion to shunne the ministerie or to leaue it, that otherwise were likely to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for their gifts therein, that yet they would be pleased, (as by law alreadie established I know they might) to allow euery thing within any of the bookes whereunto that sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription reacheth, to be construed and taken of euery one, in the best sense they could, &amp; for the better and more certaine direction thereunto, to publish the same as therby allowed so to be taken. And so to conclude my iudgement alwaies hath beene and is of this present Church gouernment, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thereof, if they that be in place of gouernment therein, euery one of them would do but that good in his place, which by the lawes thereof alreadie made he both might an ought, it would be so happie and blessed euery way as none should iustly haue cause eyther to complaine of the old, or to seek to bring in a new. And before the last conference before his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> it is well knowne in the countrey where I dwell, that in a publike meeting of the ministers
<pb facs="8"/>before the commissarie and many ministers, vpon occasion there giuen mee, I made it publikely knowne that I was, and euer had beene of this iudgement that I haue said, and therefore then further I shewe (as elsewhere sundrie times before others of greater place, and namely to my owne Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesan also, before the said conference had) how vnwilling I was, eyther there, or elsewhere, to be drawne to stand in any opposition or contention with the reuerend fathers, about any of these matters: For my iudgement is that neuer that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, but dutifull ioyning with them is likely any way to be the meanes to procure the Churches good. Being therfore thus perswaded, and therefore so thinking of the lawfulnesse of my owne course, as also taking the inconueniences of the other to bee so many and great sundrie waies as I doe, (the times now also considered wherein wee liue) how can I but in Christian charitie, in this manner doe the best that I can, both thus to make my minde knowne in these things, and also by this insuing Treatise, to seeke to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade others to be like minded as I am, and for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons therein set downe to yealde to doe as I doe. The best and most fauourable construction therein, I haue giuen of the things that men vse to sticke at, and yet with all I trust I haue made it appeare that the same stands verie well with the true meaning of the books themselues whence the doubts arise, and with the publikely receiued doctrine of this our Church: This Treatise therefore being seene and allowed thus to be printed and published according to the order in that case prouided, may the rather I hope draw men to vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie and conformitie, for that euen thereby they may see, that thus both in their practise and subscription, they are by publicke and sufficient authoritie allowed, to take and construe euerie thing in the best sense that may bee.
<pb facs="8"/>And the rather that it might so doe, (because amongest bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren I thought that the likeliest way to perswade) I haue stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died to deliuer my mind in as louing &amp; brotherly a phrase and manner as I could. Wherefore hoping that all reasonable men herewith will be satisfied, and so be content and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling without any preiudice from my person, to read and consider what I haue set downe in this Treatise following, I bid thee Christian Reader hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily farewell in the Lord. 1606.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing brother vnfainedly, <hi>Thomas Sparke.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>