<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Worshipfull Sir Thomas Hiren, Knight, Maior of the Worshipful Citie of Norwich, and his brethren the Aldermen, Master Sheriffes and the whole Comminaltie, R. W. wisheth all increase of Worship, Prosperitie, and Peace, from God euen our Father, and from the Lord Iesus Christ our Sauiour.</title>
           <author>W., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102863_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08119</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18480</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102863</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Worshipfull Sir Thomas Hiren, Knight, Maior of the Worshipful Citie of Norwich, and his brethren the Aldermen, Master Sheriffes and the whole Comminaltie, R. W. wisheth all increase of Worship, Prosperitie, and Peace, from God euen our Father, and from the Lord Iesus Christ our Sauiour.</title>
                 <author>W., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Norfolkes furies, or a view of Ketts campe : necessary for the malecontents of our time, for their instruction, or terror; and profitable for euery good subiect, to incourage him vpon the vndoubted hope of the victorie, to stand faithfully to maintayne his prince and countrey, his wife and children, goods, and inheritance. With a table of the maiors and sheriffes of this worshipfull city of Norwich, euer since the first grant by Henry the fourth: together with the bishops of that see, and other accidents here. Set forth first in Latin by Alexander Nevil. Translated into English, for the vse of the common people, by R.W. minister at Frettenham in Norfolke, and a citizen borne, who beheld part of these things with his yong eyes</title>
                 <author>Neville, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Worshipfull Sir <hi>Thomas Hiren, Knight, Maior of the Worshipful Citie of Norwich,</hi> and his brethren the Aldermen, Master Sheriffes and <hi>the whole Comminaltie,</hi> R. W. <hi>wisheth all increase of</hi> Worship, Prosperitie, and Peace, from God euen our Father, and from the Lord Iesus Christ our <hi>Sauiour.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, and my beloued Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triemen<note place="margin">Now more then twenty yeeres since.</note> the Citizens of <hi>Norwich,</hi> when in the house of my friend, among other Bookes I found (vnlooked for) this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise written in Latine, by one <hi>Alexander Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil</hi> an English man: The very Title of the Booke drew mee into a farther desire of looking into the matter: the rather because lying at that time, and in that place where these Furies were committed, I beheld some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with my young eyes: and receiuing many strange things from the report of others, I desired, and was glad to see the thing in order▪ which when I entred vpon, the elegancie of the Phrase, together with the Argument, promised mee a double fruit, <hi>viz.</hi> not only to know the Storie in order, but also to reuiue, and sharpen my poore skill in that Tongue, now through disuse and tract of time declining: so as I made it from my other Studies, my recreation. In the pursuit whereof, I found (as the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> saith of the wisdome of <hi>Salomon</hi>) that the one halfe of the calamities, and miseries of this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull Citie (my Mother) was neuer sufficiently
<pb facs="3"/>
knowne vnto me: Neyther the miraculous deliuerance, sufficiently acknowledged by mee, for I finde it farre greater then I thought. Wherefore reading it ouer now once, and againe, and communing with diuers of my friends about the matters therein contained: I found a generall desire in them all to haue it in English. Whereupon, my selfe hauing found such pleasure mixt with profit in the reading heereof (if I should not bee enuious: hauing also certaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence that it was not extant by any particular Treatise) thought good to satisfie their expectation, though of many the vnfittest: That so prayse might be giuen vnto God of many. And as the benefit increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth in our eyes, so our thankesgiuing might grow, and abound. Wherefore vnto that godly order taken, alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die for the yearely remembrance of this deliuerance, and solemnitie of Thankes giuing, as the Poet sayth in the like.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Annuus assuetum Domine natalis honorem,<note place="margin">Tristibus Elegia. 6.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Exigit: ite manus ad pia Sacra meae.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Goe thou the labour of my hands, and receiue vnder your Worshipfull protection, the good meaning of a poore friend, which wisheth well, as hee hath good cause, to your Worships, and this Citie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships for life,
R. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>