<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST EX∣cellent Princesse Elizabeth, the only daughter of IAMES, King of great Brittan, and wife to the most Illustrious Prince FREDERICK the Fift, Count Palatine of Rheine, Arch-sewer of the holy Empire, first Elector, and Duke of BAVARIA.</title>
           <author>Hutton, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102613_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01194</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11309</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102613</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST EX∣cellent Princesse Elizabeth, the only daughter of IAMES, King of great Brittan, and wife to the most Illustrious Prince FREDERICK the Fift, Count Palatine of Rheine, Arch-sewer of the holy Empire, first Elector, and Duke of BAVARIA.</title>
                 <author>Hutton, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the most auspicatious marriage: betwixt, the high and mightie Prince, Frederick; Count Palatine of Rheine, chiefe sewer to the sacred Roman Empire, Prince Elector, and Duke of Bauaria, &amp;. and the most illustrious Princesse, the Ladie Elizabeth her Grace, sole daughter to the high and mightie Iames, King of great Brittaine, &amp;c : In III. bookes: composed in Latine by M. Ioannes Maria, de Franchis. And translated into English</title>
                 <author>Franchis, Joannes Maria de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Blainchard (Blanchard), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 77, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Wedding pamphlets</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Princesse <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the only daughter of IAMES, King of great <hi>Brittan,</hi> and wife to the <hi>most Illustrious Prince</hi> FREDERICK <hi>the Fift,</hi> Count Palatine <hi>of</hi> Rheine, <hi>Arch-sewer of the holy Empire, first Elector, and Duke of</hi> BAVARIA.</head>
   <l>FAire Heauen of Graces, Hauen of content,</l>
   <l>The Worlds great Hope, and greater Ornament;</l>
   <l>Grace these my labours, with your heauenly eyes,</l>
   <l>In whose milde Hauen, my Hope at anchor lies;</l>
   <l>Where (may this ship with your safe-conduct ride)</l>
   <l>She will not feare a world of foes beside:</l>
   <l>Say that some Rouer, who my lading spies,</l>
   <l>Shooting to make me his vnlawfull Prize,</l>
   <l>Call me a Pirate of anothers wit,</l>
   <l>That cannot make me stoope: Ile answere it.</l>
   <l>The Goods at first, they were bequeath'd to me,</l>
   <l>At my dispose, to change the Propertie.</l>
   <l>So that I wasted not the Principall,</l>
   <l>For that be you my Iudge imperiall:</l>
   <l>VVhere, finde me guilty, punish not my will,</l>
   <l>But rather pitty mine vnured skill.</l>
   <l>Besides (dread gracious Princesse) this I vow,</l>
   <l>By me they'd ne're been alter'd but for yow;</l>
   <l>Presuming, natiue cloaths of <hi>Brittany,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Would better please then silks of <hi>Italy;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Say they'r not good, yet haue I done my best,</l>
   <l>To please your Grace, be pleas'd, and I am blest:</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Highnesse most humbly deuoted,
SAMVEL HVTTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>