<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS LOVING and much respected Friend, Mr. THOMAS GATAKER Bacheler in Diuinitie.</title>
           <author>Featley, Daniel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102920_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01540</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11666</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102920</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS LOVING and much respected Friend, Mr. THOMAS GATAKER Bacheler in Diuinitie.</title>
                 <author>Featley, Daniel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A iust defence of certaine passages in a former treatise concerning the nature and vse of lots, against such exceptions and oppositions as have beene made thereunto to Mr. I.B : Wherein the insufficiencie of his answers giuen to the arguments brought in defence of a lusorious lot is manifested; the imbecillitie of his arguments produced against the same further discouered; and the point it selfe in controuersie more fully cleared; by Thomas Gataker B. of D. and author of the former treatise</title>
                 <author>Gataker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bird, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 270, 6 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO HIS LOVING and much respected Friend, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. THOMAS GATAKER Bacheler in Diuinitie.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p> I haue perused your <hi>Answer</hi> to <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. B.</hi> his <hi>Pamphlet</hi> against you; wherein you haue so clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the point in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie betweene you; that I much pitty your oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents hard lot to fall vpon such a subiect and <hi>tenet</hi> concerning <hi>Lots,</hi> as afforded him so small store of <hi>Obiections</hi> against your <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
that he was euen constrained, according to the manner of some old <hi>Roman▪ Orators</hi> noted by <hi>Quintilian, Caussarum vacua con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitijs implere.</hi> Neither the <hi>matter</hi> in hand, about which learned <hi>Protestants</hi> may differ in iudgement without breach of <hi>Charity,</hi> or preiudice to Christian <hi>vnity,</hi> nor your hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it <hi>dog matically</hi> and <hi>scholastically</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>gall</hi> at all, could occasion such <hi>heats.</hi> I cannot imagine therefore, what should so much moue him, but the badnesse of his <hi>cause,</hi> and the weaknesse of his owne <hi>Arguments,</hi> which he seeth by your handling them to be like <hi>wier-strings</hi> ill-nealed, which would not endure the least straining. For albeit I confesse that we are all apt to take too much hold of any point of liberty reached vnto vs out of Gods word; and in particular I cannot but deplore <hi>sortem sortis, the Lot of Lot</hi> it selfe, which hath beene and is too much by the licentious abused, and thereby in a sort defamed, especially in <hi>Carding</hi> and <hi>Dicing:</hi> yet <hi>Gods truth</hi> must not be suppressed because of <hi>mans errors;</hi> neither is it a safe way to goe about to cure an error in <hi>practise,</hi> by another error in <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
I meane, to reforme the <hi>abuse</hi> in <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorie Lots</hi> by totally condemning the <hi>vse</hi> it selfe of them. Though a <hi>Surgean</hi> meane neuer so well in letting his Patient bloud who needeth it, yet if he strike not the right veine, he had better haue spared his paines. The sinne too regnant in <hi>sports</hi> and <hi>games</hi> now a-daies is not in vsing the <hi>Lot,</hi> but in not obseruing those <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Cautions</hi> in these and other <hi>Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations,</hi> which are iudiciously and piously set downe by you in your compleat <hi>Treatise of Lots.</hi> Let those <hi>Cautions</hi> be obserued, and set aside the authoritie of some <hi>Diuines,</hi> whose <hi>persons</hi> they haue in admiration aboue others; what is there in the casuall falling of <hi>the Dye,</hi> or dealing of <hi>the Cards,</hi> more than in the fall of <hi>a Coyte,</hi> or lighting of <hi>an Arrow</hi> neerer or further, or the turning of <hi>a Boule,</hi> to ensnare the Conscience? <hi>Art</hi> more ruleth the one, and <hi>Nature</hi> the other; <hi>Gods prouidence</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence being equall in either. For to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that because <hi>some Lots</hi> haue beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrated to <hi>an holy vse</hi> sometimes, therefore <hi>all Lots</hi> are <hi>sacred,</hi> is a feeble kinde of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing. And to impose <hi>a speciall and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>worke of Gods prouidence,</hi> vpon the casuall euent of the <hi>Lot,</hi> more than vpon other naturall accidents and deliberate actions of men, is a temerarious and groundlesse assertion. And furthermore to charge all those <hi>seruants of God,</hi> who moderately vse their <hi>Christian liberty</hi> in these <hi>Games,</hi> with so hainous a sinne, as is <hi>the prophaning of a thing sacred,</hi> or <hi>taking in vaine Gods deciding Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> is an vncharitable censure. The Lord open the eyes of all that seeke to serue him in sinceritie and singlenesse of heart, that neither by enlarging their <hi>Christian liberty</hi> they open a gap to <hi>licentiousnesse,</hi> nor yet by too much restraining it lay a snare on <hi>weake Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> To deliuer you my iudgement and aduice in a word; <hi>Satis actum est:</hi> you haue sifted this point of <hi>Lots</hi> to the bran. Let me aduise you hereafter <hi>non reciprocare serram con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionis de ludis sortiarijs,</hi> but rather to imploy your able pen against the <hi>Sorcerers</hi> of <hi>Aegypt</hi> now abounding in euery place, and making aduantages of the least differences among vs, who hold the like pretious faith pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from the drosse of their superstition. This
<pb facs="4"/>
aduice, I know, you will take in good part, as proceeding from</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your true affectionate friend and fellow-labourer in the Lords haruest, DANIEL FEATLY▪</signed>
      <dateline>Croydon <date>Sept. 2. 1623.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>