<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO
THE MIGHTYE
and High renowned Prince,
HENRY, Prince of great
Brittaine, all happines.</title>
           <author>Hasset, Blener</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102660_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16207</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3130</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102660</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO
THE MIGHTYE
and High renowned Prince,
HENRY, Prince of great
Brittaine, all happines.</title>
                 <author>Hasset, Blener</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A direction for the plantation in Vlster : Contayning in it, sixe principall thinges, viz. 1. The securing of that wilde contrye to the crowne of England. 2. The withdrawing of all the charge of the garrison and men of warre. 3. The rewarding of the old seruitors to their good content. 4. The means how to increase the reuenue to the Crowne, with a yearely very great summe. 5. How to establish the puritie of religion there. 6. And how the vndertakers may with securitie be inriched</title>
                 <author>Blenerhasset, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO
THE MIGHTYE
and High renowned Prince,
HENRY, Prince of great
Brittaine, all happines.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ightie and High renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<hi>PRINCE,</hi> the fourth parte of
<hi>Ireland,</hi> depopulated <hi>VLSTER,</hi> but
now redeemed, deliuered and quite
acquitted by the Kinges Maiesties
(your most louing Fathers) wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
wisdome &amp; industrie, from the vsurping tyrannie
of Traytors, &amp; from a long &amp; a most lamentable capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie:
Dispoyled, she presents her-selfe (as it were) in a
ragged sad sabled Robe, ragged (indeed) there remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
nothing but ruynes &amp; desolatiō, with a very little
showe of any humanitie: of her selfe she aboundeth with
many the very best blessings of God: amongst the other
Prouinces belonging to great <hi>Brittaines</hi> Imperial
Crowne, not much inferiour to any. Thē regard her, for
vnto your Highnesse it belongeth chiefely to regard her.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>
Fayre <hi>England,</hi> she hath more People then she can
well sustaine: goodly <hi>Vlster</hi> for want of people vnma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nured,
her pleasant fieldes and rich groundes, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine
if not desolate, worsse.</p>
   <p>Would your Excellencie with fauourable respectes,
but countenance the Action, then the neuer-satisfied
desires of a fewe, should not quite disgrace and vtterly
ouerthrowe the good and exceeding good purposes of
many, but with an excellent Plantation it would be
Peopled plentifully, yea fortified and replenished with
such and so many goodly strong Corporations, as it
would be a wonder to beholde: Without which it is not
possible (for I say what certainely I knowe) so suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
to secure that wilde Countrie any long time. The
desire wherof hath caryed (or rather violently drawne
me to this presumption) I being a playne Country-man
and one of the Vndertakers in <hi>Farmannagh.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If my endeauours may in any respect be so auailable;
that fayre successions, long posteritie may at length be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
her with securitie in some proportion beautified,
then I shall be of many, the most happy, especiallie if
your Highnesse shall giue good acceptance to these my
desires. The Almightie GOD of Heauen blesse and
preserue your Excellencie still and euermore, with those
his super-exceding graces.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Excellencies
most humble suppliant:
<hi>Thomas Blener hasset.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>