<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102226_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15848</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26113</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102226</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The victory of patience : and benefit of affliction, with how to husband it so, that the weakest Christian (with blessing from above) may bee able to support himselfe in his most miserable exigents. Together with a counterpoyson or antipoyson against all griefe, being a tenth of the doves innocency, and the serpents subtilty. Extracted out of the choisest authors, ancient and moderne, necessary to be read of all that any way suffer tribulation. By R.Y</title>
                 <author>Younge, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Allott, Mary.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 259, 53 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Othing in this world can bee framed so perfect, but it shall have some delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quensies; to prove that more were in the Compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor: and it is almost as easie to find faults, as to make them. To spy the inconveniences of a house built, is nothing: but to lay the plot well, at first, requires the pate
<pb facs="3"/>
of a good Contriver. All Alchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists can doe well till they come to doing: But there is a further distance from nothing to the least thing in the world; then between it and the greatest.</p>
   <p>All publique actions are sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to diverse, and uncertaine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations; for a great many heads judge of them, and mens censures are as various as their palats, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. Our writings are as so many dishes; our Readers, guests. Bookes are like faces; that which one admires, another slights. Why? Some will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne what they do as little un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand as they doe themselves: Others, the better a thing is, the
<pb facs="3"/>
worse they will like it. <hi>They hate him</hi> (saith Amos) <hi>that rebuketh in the gate, and they abhor him that speaketh uprightly, Amos</hi> 5.10. You know, <hi>Herods</hi> festered conscience could not endure <hi>Iohn Baptists</hi> plaister of truth; a galled backe, loves not the curry Combe; a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed face, loathes the true glas, nothing is so hatefull to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speratly wicked, as good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell: with <hi>Balaam</hi> they grutch to be stayed in the way to death, and fly upon those that oppose their perdition. And how should they other then miscarry; who have a Pirate (the flesh) for their guide? So that if a man should observe the wind of Applause, he should
<pb facs="4"/>
never sowe; or regard the clouds of Aspersion, hee should never reape. But I had rather hazard the censure of some, then hinder the good of others: yea, I had rather misse of what I expect, then faile to do my utmost. Wherefore, I present to thee, curteous Reader, a posey of such flowers as I have gathered abroad. If they be liked (as <hi>Phidias</hi> said, concerning his first portrayture) expect more; if not, onely this.</p>
   <p>To fore-relate their variety, and severall worths, were to imitate an Italian Host, meeting you on the waies, and promising before hand, your fare and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Wherefore let it please you
<pb facs="4"/>
to see and allow your cheare. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in generall; my Booke is a feast; wherin holsomnesse strives with pleasantnesse, and variety with both. Each Chapter seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall is a severall dish, stuft full of notable sayings and examples (for that's the meate) by which a man may, not only become more elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, but more wise; not alone, able to say well, but to doe well; for quaint and elegant phrases, on a good subject, are baites, to make an ill man vertuous. Pithy sentences, curious metaphors, witty apophthegmes, sweet simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes, and rhetoricall expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions (which <hi>Aristotle</hi> would have, as it were, sprinkled in the
<pb facs="5"/>
most serious discourses) are to the minde, as musicke to the body; which (next to sleepe) is the best recreation. Or as pleasant and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable Sause, which gives a more savory tast to holsome, and profitable Divinity. And thou shalt finde but few here, which are not both sinewy, and sharpe: <hi>mucrones verborum,</hi> pointed spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; either fit to teach, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible to perswade, or sage to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise, and forewarne; or sharpe to reprove, or strong to confirme, or piercing to imprint▪</p>
   <p>But alas! most men regard not what is written, but who writes: valew not the mettall, but the Stampe which is upon it.
<pb facs="5"/>
To these, I say little, as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve little: and turne my speech to all that reserve themselves open, and prepared, to receive each profitabe instruction, and continuall amendment; to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Reader, that sucks hony from the selfe same flower which the Spider doth poyson; wishing him to come, that out of this Treatise which he did not know before; and well note what speakes to his owne sinne: And perhaps he may, in this short jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney make more true gaine, then <hi>Salomons</hi> Navy did from Ophir, or the Spanish fleete from the West Indies; for in so doing, he shall greatly increase his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb facs="6"/>
and lessen his vices. In one day he may reade it, and ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, be the better for it.</p>
   <p>But methinkes I am too like a carelesse Porter; which keepes the guests without dores, til they have lost their stomackes; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I wil detaine you no longer in the porch, but unlock the dore, and let you in.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>