<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONble.
Sr. THOMAS RICHARDSON,
Lord Chiefe Iustice of his Majesties
Common Pleas: And Sir IOHN DENHAM, one of his
Majesties Barons of the Exchequer; All
Health and Happinesse, here and
hereafter.</title>
           <author>Foster, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102538_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01090</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11202</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102538</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONble.
Sr. THOMAS RICHARDSON,
Lord Chiefe Iustice of his Majesties
Common Pleas: And Sir IOHN DENHAM, one of his
Majesties Barons of the Exchequer; All
Health and Happinesse, here and
hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Foster, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Plouto-mastix: the scourge of covetousnesse: or, An apologie for the publike good, against privacie : A sermon preached at the assises in Deuon, at the command of the Lord Byshop of Exon, anno, 1630. By Thomas Foster, Master of Arts and rector of Farway</title>
                 <author>Foster, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Slater (Slaughter), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sparke, Michael 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 26, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HON<seg rend="sup">ble</seg>.
S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. THOMAS RICHARDSON,
Lord Chiefe Iustice of his Majesties
Common Pleas: And Sir IOHN DENHAM, one of his
Majesties Barons of the Exchequer; All
Health and Happinesse, here and
hereafter.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Will not say, <hi>Importunity</hi> of
friends hath <hi>prest</hi> this <hi>Sermon</hi>
to the <hi>Presse:</hi> that's a <hi>Common
Plea;</hi> and implies a <hi>Tacit</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation
of the owne worke;
which is not so commendable;
it beeing as great <hi>Wisdome</hi> in
our <hi>sufficiency,</hi> not to know our
selves, as, in our <hi>Wants</hi> to know
our selues. But I may boldly avouch, <hi>Ambition</hi> has no
hand in the <hi>Impression.</hi> For had I beene that way affected
I have had time enough, to be a <hi>foole</hi> in print (as well as
some others) long ere now-<hi>Scribimus indocti, doctique.</hi> But
I have ever beene as desirous to <hi>Suppresse</hi> my <hi>Labours,</hi> in
this kinde, as others to <hi>Presse</hi> theirs. The truth is, the
reason, why I have ventur'd to come on the <hi>Publike
<pb facs="3"/>
stage,</hi> and to make my <hi>Meditations Legible,</hi> is, To see
whether I can finde more Charitable <hi>Readers</hi> of my
<hi>Well-meant Endeavours,</hi> then I had some <hi>Hearers;</hi> whose
unhappy <hi>Misprision</hi> (making themselves, occasionally,
guilty) would have made me guilty of that, I neyther
spake, nor meant; (of that which I hate) A personall
<hi>Invective.</hi> Whereas it may appeare (upon ingenuous
perusall) neither the <hi>Person,</hi> nor the <hi>Place,</hi> but the too-well
knowne <hi>Offence (Negligence</hi>) of some persons in
those <hi>Places,</hi> is inveighed against. I can truely say
with Saint <hi>Ierome-Nullum loesi, nullius nomen mea Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura
designatum est: Neminem specialiter meus sermo pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>savit
(ad Nepot.</hi>) And the Poet tels me (I take it) discreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,-<hi>Licuit,
semper{que} licebit.-Parcere personis, dicere de
vitijs.</hi> Whosoever takes offence at this, it is-<hi>Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum
acceptum,</hi> indeed; and I suppose, he is no <hi>Competent
Auditor.</hi> For if guilty Consciences, who are <hi>Parties</hi>
should be admitted <hi>Iudges</hi> of <hi>Divine Reprehension,</hi> the
<hi>Pulpit</hi> should bee counted a <hi>Pasquil;</hi> every <hi>admonition</hi>
thence (how discreetly-zealous soever) an invective
<hi>Defamation. Guilty Consciences</hi> are like the Elephant:
which being conscious of his owne <hi>Deformity,</hi> cannot
abide to see his <hi>Face</hi> in the cleare Springs, but seekes
for troubled and muddy Chanels, to drinke in; So
they, knowing their soules to be so filthy, that they
dare not view them in the cleare waters of <hi>Truth,</hi> and
<hi>Sincere Admonition,</hi> flee to the troubled Chanels of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villation,</hi>
and <hi>Contradiction▪ Arbitror te veritate supera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,
ad detractionem, vitae meae, et maledicta converti,</hi> saith
<hi>Ierome, (Contra Helvid.</hi>) But-<hi>Qui volens, detrahit famae
meae, nolens addit mercedi,</hi> saith <hi>August. (Cont. Petil. lib. 3.
cap.</hi> 7.) And thus,-<hi>Quandiu aegri, indignantur,</hi> whiles
<pb facs="3"/>
men are sicke of <hi>Impenitencie,</hi> they are <hi>Impatient</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe;-<hi>Sed
sanati, gratulantur,</hi> but being cur'd by
<hi>Repentance,</hi> they shake hands with the <hi>Monitor,</hi> and
thanke him, saith <hi>August. (Ad Fest. Epist.</hi> 166.) Then
they will acknowledge, <hi>'Tis better once smart, then ever
ake:</hi> And so a <hi>Galling</hi> truth shall have more thankes,
at the last, than a <hi>smoothing Supparasitation,-Hee that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buketh
a man, shall finde more favour, at the length, than hee
that flattereth with his tongue, (Prov.</hi> 28. 23.) But hee
that can, now, play with his <hi>Euphemismes</hi> and <hi>Eulogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um's,</hi>
and cry,-<hi>Pax pax, when there is no peace,</hi> makes
the best <hi>musicke</hi> in the eares of this <hi>secure Age.</hi> He that
bids the wicked AHABS,-<hi>Goe vp to Ramoth Gilead, and
prosper, (1. King.</hi> 22. 12.) is now the best <hi>Politician.</hi> Hee
that that can-<hi>Dawbe with vntempered morter,</hi> is counted
the best <hi>Architect</hi> of Soules. This they call, <hi>Good tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
Mildnesse, Discretion.</hi> This is the way, they say, to
sleepe in whole skinne, to rise to <hi>Preferment.-(Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequium
amicos, veritas odium,</hi>) Such preferment God
send them, who love the <hi>praise of Men, more than the praise
of GOD.</hi> And-<hi>whether it be right in the sight of God, to obey
men, rather than God, iudge yee.</hi> But what shall I say?</p>
   <q>Pro captu Lectoris habent sua fata Libelli.</q>
   <p>As <hi>Bookes,</hi> so <hi>Sermons</hi> have their <hi>Credit</hi> or <hi>discredit</hi>
from the fancy of their <hi>Readers</hi> or <hi>Hearers.</hi> And it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
an easier matter to <hi>Dislike,</hi> than to <hi>Doe the like.—Facilia
sic putant omnes, quae iam facta; nec de salebris co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitant
vbi via strata, (Lips.</hi>) If you come to an <hi>Inne</hi> in
<hi>Germany,</hi> and dislike your fare, dyet, lodging, the <hi>Dutch
Host</hi> tels you, in a <hi>surly</hi> tone,-<hi>Aliud tibi quaeras diverso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,
(Erasm. Dial.</hi>) Such is my resolution: who likes
not this, may reade some other thing.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
My Lords, I have not without Cause, <hi>Inscrib'd</hi> this
<hi>Sermon</hi> unto your Names. First, it was Preach'd in the
great <hi>Assembly,</hi> whereof your selves were a <hi>Principall
part.</hi> Secondly, Preach'd on that <hi>Subiect,</hi> wherein your
<hi>Places</hi> have a <hi>Principall</hi> interest; The <hi>Common Good</hi> of
Church and Common-weale. A <hi>Subiect</hi> as necessary
for those <hi>Times,</hi> as the <hi>Times</hi> are <hi>Subiect</hi> to <hi>Necessity:
Private</hi> ends having brought the <hi>Publike Good,</hi> almost,
to it's <hi>End;</hi> and <hi>Hungry Coveteousnesse,</hi> like PHARAOH's
leane kine, devour'd this fat and flourishing <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale.</hi>
To you therefore (as being-<hi>Patres Patriae,</hi> and-<hi>Ecclesiae
Patroni</hi>) this <hi>Weake,</hi> but <hi>Well-meant Labour</hi> of
mine, flees for <hi>Patrociny</hi> and <hi>protection.</hi> I shall make it
my humble <hi>Suite,</hi> that you will be pleas'd to entertaine
it, as DAVID, <hi>lame</hi> MEPHI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>OSHETH, for his Father
IONATHAN's sake. <hi>Lame</hi> it is in both feet. (<hi>Lame</hi>
in the <hi>Birth,</hi> by <hi>vnskilfull</hi> handling, <hi>lame</hi> in the <hi>Nursing,</hi>
by <hi>uncharitable scanning</hi>) yet entertaine it for it's fathers
sake, Your <hi>Country's</hi> sake, whose <hi>Love</hi> begat it. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
that <hi>Apologue</hi> in the <hi>Talmud;</hi> the grapes in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi>
sent, upon a time, to the <hi>Vine-leaves,</hi> in <hi>Iudaea</hi> desiring
them, to come and over-shadow them; otherwise the
heat would consume them, and so they should never
come to <hi>Maturity.</hi> Your Lordships may easily guesse
at the <hi>Mythology.</hi> If <hi>Learning</hi> be not sheltred by those,
who are in <hi>Eminent place,</hi> and if they cast not their
<hi>Shadow</hi> over it, it will soone perish; But where they fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
it, it prospers. If the <hi>Spring</hi> bee cold, the <hi>Plants,
Herbes,</hi> and <hi>Blossomes</hi> are nipt and wither; But where
the <hi>Influence</hi> is seasonable, there all things reviue, thrive,
flourish. So where <hi>Great Persons</hi> are averse from <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi>
the <hi>Spirits,</hi> which would otherwise, blossome, doe
<pb facs="4"/>
wither and decay. But when it is upholden by men of
<hi>Higher place,</hi> it is like a <hi>Fountaine</hi> of <hi>Living Water.</hi> For
my part I cannot praise my <hi>Present</hi> otherwise, then by
the <hi>Truth</hi> of that heart, from which it proceeds:
which shall bee <hi>Ambitious</hi> of all occasions, that may
testifie a <hi>Gratefull</hi> acknowledgement of your <hi>Lordships
undeserved</hi> favours; and wherewith, I will daily <hi>Petition</hi>
the Lord of Lords for the continuance of your <hi>Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi>
and <hi>Welfare.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most obsequious
Servant, in the Lord,
THO: FOSTER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>