<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>T. Ch. In prayse of Gascoignes Posies.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102875_Fr1_5_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01514</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11636</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102875</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>T. Ch. In prayse of Gascoignes Posies.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The posies of George Gascoigne Esquire</title>
                 <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Smith (Smyth), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36, clviij, 2, 4, 36, 45-76 pages, 77-86, 85-106 leaves, 107-173, 3, 175-290, 10 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>T. Ch. In prayse of Gascoignes Posies.</head>
   <l>THough goodnesse of the gold, needes no mans praise ye know,</l>
   <l>(And euery coyne is iudgde and found, by weight, by stamp, or show)</l>
   <l>Yet doth the prayse of men, giue gold a double grace,</l>
   <l>And makes both pearls and Iewels rich, desirde in euery place.</l>
   <l>The horse full finely formde, whose pace and traine is true,</l>
   <l>Is more esteemde for good report, than likte for shape and view.</l>
   <l>Yea sure, ech man himselfe, for all his wit and skill,</l>
   <l>(If world bestow no lawde on him) may sleepe in silence still.</l>
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <l>Fame shewes the value first, of euerie precious thing,</l>
   <l>And winnes with lyking all the brute, that doth the credit bring.</l>
   <l>And fame makes way before, to workes that are vnknowne</l>
   <l>And peoples loue is caried ther, where fame hir trump hath blown.</l>
   <l>A cunning workman fine, in Cloyster close may sit,</l>
   <l>And carue or paint a thousand things, and vse both art and wit,</l>
   <l>Yet wanting worldes renowne, may scape vnsought or seene:</l>
   <l>It is but fame that outruns all, and gets the goall I weene.</l>
   <l>The learned Doctors lawd, that heales where other harmes,</l>
   <l>By cōmon prayse of peoples voyce, brings pacients in by swarmes.</l>
   <l>A goodly stately house, hath seldome any fame,</l>
   <l>Till world behold the buildings through, and people see the same.</l>
   <l>The Flowers and Posies sweete, in better price are held,</l>
   <l>VVhen those haue praysde their vertues rare, that haue their odor smeld.</l>
   <l>So by these foresayd proofes, I haue a pardon free,</l>
   <l>To speake, to write, and make discourse, of any worke I see,</l>
   <l>That worthie is of prayse: for prayse is all we get.</l>
   <l>Present the worlde with labors great, the world is in your det,</l>
   <l>It neuer yeeldes rewarde, nor scarce iust prayse will giue:</l>
   <l>Then studie out to stand on fame, and striue by fame to liue.</l>
   <l>Our olde forefathers wise, saw long before these dayes,</l>
   <l>How sone faint world would fail deserts, and cold would wax our prayse.</l>
   <l>And knowing that disdeyne, for toyle did rather rise,</l>
   <l>Than right renowne (whose goldē buds, growes vp to starry skies)</l>
   <l>Betooke their labors long, and euery act they did,</l>
   <l>Vnto the Gods, from whose deepe sight, no secret can be hid.</l>
   <l>And these good gracious Gods, sent downe from heauens hie,</l>
   <l>(For noble minds) an endlesse fame, that throw the world doth flie.</l>
   <l>VVhich fame is due to those, that seeke by new deuice,</l>
   <l>To honor learning euery way, and Vertue bring in price.</l>
   <l>From Knowledge gardeyn gay, where science sowes hir seedes,</l>
   <l>A pretie Posie gathered is, of <hi>Flowers, Hearbes,</hi> and <hi>VVeedes.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>The Flowers by smel are found, the hearbs their goodnes showes,</l>
   <l>The VVeedes amid both hearbs &amp; flowers, in decēt order growes.</l>
   <l>The soft and tender nose, that can no weedes abide,</l>
   <l>May make his choise of holesome hearbes, whose vertues well are tride.</l>
   <pb facs="13"/>
   <l>The fine and flowing wittes, that feede on straunge delites,</l>
   <l>May tast (for seasning daintie mouthes) the bitter weede that bites.</l>
   <l>The well disposed minde, and honest meaning man,</l>
   <l>Shall finde (in floures) proude Peacoks plumes, and feathers of the Swan.</l>
   <l>The curst and crabbed Carle, that Posies flings away,</l>
   <l>By this (perhaps) may find some cause, with prettie floures to play.</l>
   <l>The kinde and louing worme, that woulde his ladie please,</l>
   <l>My light on some such medcin here, shal do them both much ease.</l>
   <l>The Lad that lykes the schoole, and will good warning take:</l>
   <l>May snatch some rules oute of this booke, that may him doctor make.</l>
   <l>The hastie trauayling head, that flies to foreyne place,</l>
   <l>May wey by this what home is woorth, and stay his rouing race.</l>
   <l>The manly courage stoute, that seeketh fame full farre,</l>
   <l>Shall find by this how sweete is peace, and see how soure is warre.</l>
   <l>This Posie is so pickt, and choysely sorted throw,</l>
   <l>There is no Flower, Herbe, nor VVeede, but serues some purpose now.</l>
   <l>Then since it freely comes, to you for little cost,</l>
   <l>Take well in worth these paynes of him, that thinkes no labor lost:</l>
   <l>To do his countrie good, as many others haue,</l>
   <l>VVho for their toyles a good report, of worlde did onely craue.</l>
   <l>Grudge not to yeeld some fame, for fruites that you receyue,</l>
   <l>Make some exchaunge for franke good will, some signe or token leaue,</l>
   <l>To shew your thankfull harts. For if you loue to take,</l>
   <l>And haue a conscience growne so great, you can no gift forsake,</l>
   <l>And cannot giue againe, that men deserue to reape,</l>
   <l>Adieu we leaue you in the hedge, and ore the stile we leape.</l>
   <l>And yet some stile or verse, we after shape in ryme,</l>
   <l>That may by arte shewe you a Glasse, to see your selues in tyme.</l>
   <l>Thus wish I men their right: and you that iudge amisse,</l>
   <l>To mend your minds, or frame your Muse, to make the like of this.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>