<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102197_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15508</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25774</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102197</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Charity mistaken, with the want whereof, Catholickes are vniustly charged : for affirming, as they do with grief, that Protestancy vnrepented destroies salvation</title>
                 <author>Knott, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard (Buree), Jeanne</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 130, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>PREFACE.</head>
   <p>HAVING obserued the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, which men are growne to take, in not holding it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary to belieue that any one Religion is precisely true; &amp; that for the excusing of themselues from blame, they thinke fit to lay the fault on others as being too strict in approuing and vpholding only one; I haue thought fit to imply some of my houres vpon examining, how much or little reason they haue, in a case of this high impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, either to bragge of their owne charity, or to impeach the opiniō of ours. And therefore I shall humbly pray all my Protestant Readers, to bring attention without passion to the perusall of this ensuing discourse; wherein I will hope they shall meet with cause, to be as good to themselues as I wish, or at least to giue
<pb facs="3"/>
ouer mistaking vs, though perhaps▪ they shall not care to mend themselues. But certainly if there be any such thing, as Heauen, and God, and Christ, and Faith, and Church, &amp; that indeed there be but one: not only shall they be misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men in the next life, vvho apply not thēselues intirely to the beliefe of that, and that alone; but they shall euen in this vvorld be vvorthily held ignorant and imprudent, vvho taxe men as vncharitable for nothing but because they approue not many. For let that, vvhich follovveth, be vvell vveighed; and they vvill see that not only Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes affirme this truth; but that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe there of is also auowed both by the practise and principles of the chief Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants themselues in their vvritings; hovvsoeuer the contrary discourse raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth too much in the minds and mouths of particular men of that profession, vvho haue many times so much of the good fellovv, that they haue too little of the good Christian. But I remit my selfe to that, vvich follovves: vvhich againe I recommend to the Reader.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>