<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY MVCH REVERENCED AND TRVELY RESPECTED Friend, Master ISAACH HORNE, Pastor and Preacher of Gods sacred Word at ELLSFIELD in Hampeshire, To him Grace and Peace be Multiplyed.</title>
           <author>Lovell, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102843_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06388</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16859</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102843</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY MVCH REVERENCED AND TRVELY RESPECTED Friend, Master ISAACH HORNE, Pastor and Preacher of Gods sacred Word at ELLSFIELD in Hampeshire, To him Grace and Peace be Multiplyed.</title>
                 <author>Lovell, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo soveraigne salves for the soules sicknesse : deliuered in certaine sermons at Hurst-church in the county of Berkes, neere Reading. By Robert Lovell, then minister and preacher of Gods word in the same parish</title>
                 <author>Lovell, Robert, curate of Allhallowes, Barking</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY MVCH REVERENCED AND TRVELY RESPECTED Friend, Master ISAACH HORNE, <hi>Pastor</hi> and <hi>Preacher</hi> of Gods sacred Word at ELLSFIELD in <hi>Hampeshire,</hi> To him Grace and Peace be Multiplyed.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>REVEREND SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S J was in the midst of this Preaching-businesse, it fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that a Letter of yours long since written vnto mee, came to my hands, wherein I perceiued your desire of see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing somewhat on this ensuing Text. And I sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed much that it came no sooner, that I might haue satisfied your desire, and shewed my duty to him to whom I owe my selfe in so great a measure as I cannot expresse: for when mine owne father
<pb facs="3"/>forsooke me, who tooke me in? When he receiued me againe to fauour, who reconciled vs? When he would haue bound me to a Trade; who dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded him? When he would not heare of my go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Vniuersitie;</hi> who preuailed with him but you? so that to speake the truth,</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Tu Herus, Tu Patronus, Tu Pater esses.</hi> Yea, without Excesse of speech, or Suspition of flattery,<note place="margin">Plutarch. de vita Alex.</note> I may truely say of you as <hi>Alexander</hi> did of <hi>Aristotle; Hic mihi Principium vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uendi dedit, Iste autem Bene viuendi ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem tradidit.</hi> For who in the Countrey gaue me either Countenance or Maintenauce in my course of Schollership, but you? I speake <hi>Truely,</hi> I blesse God <hi>Humbly,</hi> I thanke you <hi>Heartily,</hi> It was <hi>You,</hi> and none but <hi>You</hi> that did it. But <hi>Quid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribuam?</hi> Like for Like? I cannot, for your <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours</hi> are beyond my <hi>Deserts,</hi> and your <hi>Deserts</hi> are aboue the reach of my <hi>Requitall. Siluer</hi> and <hi>Gold</hi> haue I none, but such as I haue, giue I vnto you; to wit, <hi>Duty</hi> for <hi>Loue; Loue and Respect</hi> for <hi>your louing me when I was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Loued nor Respected.</hi> In token of which I send these vnpolished papers, but how? not to <hi>Direct</hi> you, but that you should <hi>Correct</hi> them.</p>
   <p>My <hi>Schoole-exercises</hi> haue beene oft cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
<pb facs="3"/>by you, and now I refuse not that my <hi>Church-seruices</hi> be censured with your <hi>Delea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> For I am of that Fathers minde, which in all his workes and writings did not onely desire <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Lectorem,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. proae. ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Lib. 3. de Trinitae.</note>
      <hi>fed etiam Liberum Correcto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> I therefore choose that I might be <hi>Blamed</hi> of you by your <hi>friendly smitings,</hi> rather then <hi>Balmed</hi> of Carping <hi>Momus,</hi> and Scourging <hi>Zoilus,</hi> with their <hi>Precious</hi> (or rather <hi>Pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi>) <hi>Balmes,</hi> which euer yet were found of the <hi>Ingenious,</hi> nay <hi>Religious,</hi> to be rather <hi>Hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> then <hi>Helpefull</hi> to their <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Hearts.</hi> And further I craue that if you meete with any, <hi>Qui vel non Intelligendo Reprehendunt,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug. contra Faustam. lib. 22. cap. 34.</note>
      <hi>vel Reprehendendo non intelligunt,</hi> that you would be as silent with such as may be: say little to them, and lesse of them, lest in your prayers, you will beg with me, <hi>That they might be either of a more sound Iudgement, or sober and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified Affection.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I confesse it to be a shrew'd aduenture to traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique with one poore talent in <hi>Publique,</hi> whilest I behold richer graces buried in <hi>Silence.</hi> But iudging it better to Husband a <hi>Little</hi> to the Common good, rather then to hoard vp <hi>Much in Sullen Niggardize,</hi> I send it into the world. It
<pb facs="4"/>is but a yong plant, yet yong plants thriue, if the Sunne warme them with it's beames. Cast then your eye of acceptance on these <hi>weake</hi> beginnings and you shall hearten mee in my proceedings. Which hoping, I commend againe to your kind ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, and your selfe with it, to the blessing of our gracious God, and doe rest with all due reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my Study at Saint</hi> Michaels <hi>in</hi> Crooked Lane, <hi>Lond.</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>25. of</hi> Nou. <hi>1620.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your poore Scholler in all Christian seruices to be commanded, <hi>ROBERT LOVELL.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>