<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument, or Epitome, of the whole Poeme.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102613_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01194</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11309</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102613</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument, or Epitome, of the whole Poeme.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the most auspicatious marriage: betwixt, the high and mightie Prince, Frederick; Count Palatine of Rheine, chiefe sewer to the sacred Roman Empire, Prince Elector, and Duke of Bauaria, &amp;. and the most illustrious Princesse, the Ladie Elizabeth her Grace, sole daughter to the high and mightie Iames, King of great Brittaine, &amp;c : In III. bookes: composed in Latine by M. Ioannes Maria, de Franchis. And translated into English</title>
                 <author>Franchis, Joannes Maria de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Blainchard (Blanchard), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 77, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Wedding pamphlets</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Argument, or Epitome, of the whole Poeme.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vpiter, by meanes of <hi>Mercury</hi> his messenger, summons a Conuocation of the Gods to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farre and dispose of things here below; at this Synod, <hi>Religion</hi> (being a power amongst the heauenly deities of no small repute) made her appearāce, being ful of afflictiō, &amp; depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of that accustomed coelestiall pompe, and diuine ornaments with which all th'other Gods then assembled in the Consistorie of the highest heauens did most gloriously shine: which moued all the Gods to maruell, and father <hi>Iupiter</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to require the cause of her griefe, whereof in her actions and habit she gaue such wofull remonstrances. To whom shee answered with teares, and sobbes, that this happened vnto her, because she was so torne and persecuted in the world, by wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and superstition, and other of <hi>Pluto's</hi> fire-brands, that she had scarce any place there safely to rest her selfe, farther intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, what barbarous &amp; horrible torments she and her followers had, for many ages past, suffered, and still did indure. Which complaint of hers, moued the Deities to compassionate her, and caused them (being inkindled with a iust wrath against the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall Furies) to begin to muster vp, and bend their coelestiall forces to succour her: But then the ruler of the Gods (hauing with his most maiestick awfull becke calmed their indignation) most louingly comforted his afflicted Daughter; telling the dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that this was not to be remedied with fury and the destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men, but with fatherly and long sufferance to bring home to his flock those strayed sheep, by good counsell and exhortation, as in his eternall decrees hee had in this case determined; and that the chiefe meanes for the effecting hereof was, the linking together of two royal families in amost profitable marriage, long since preordained by Fate, for the reformation of these corrupted times: And then he repeated the auncient oracle of the goddess <hi>Themis,</hi> now vpon the point to be performed, in the persons of the most illustrious Lady, the Princesse of great <hi>Brittany,</hi> and of the most noble Prince <hi>PALATINE,</hi> the vertues of which excellent couple, euen <hi>Ioue</hi> himselfe collanded, and foretolde the many
<pb facs="5"/>
blessings that should proceed of these royall Nuptialls: whereby <hi>Religion,</hi> and the whole Quier of Heauen, were with great hopes appeased.</p>
   <div n="2" type="book">
      <head>THE II. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>THe Gods, with their recomforted Sister, doe congratulate each other, and she returnes them thankes for their so great fauors, and they allioine, and moue <hi>Iuno,</hi> the president of marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, and <hi>Venus</hi> the mother of loue, to assume the Embassy &amp; the effectuating of this disseigne of the gods.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Iuno</hi> sends downe vpon the earth <hi>Iris</hi> her Embassadress, clad with most artificialluestiments, in which the reforming of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the occurrences of greatest consequence in the world for many yeeres past were inwoo<gap reason="illegible: faint" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>en; and with <hi>Iris, Venus</hi> ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as colleague <hi>Cupid</hi> her sonne, with a troope of other Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall personages: who being repleat with ioy, and prophecying, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogh the regions of the aire, the greatnes of this most happy vnion, arriued at <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> being the Metropolis of the <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>atinate,</hi> where they entring secretly by night, <hi>Cupid</hi> with golden dart, &amp; amorous, fire in a dream, strook &amp; inflamed the young Prince, not yet knowing the obiect of his desire till afterwards walking in his gallery, entraunced with those amorous thoughts, his eye lighted on the picture of the L. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the only daughter of the most puissant King of great <hi>Brittā,</hi> with whose portraiture, amōgst di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others of the greatest Princesses in the world, the said galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was beautified. At the first sight of that faire picture, of a more faire substance; the Prince was supprised with a new flame, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging that that was the beautifull forme which <hi>Cupid</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented vnto him, and with which he stirred him vp to loue; and hereupon the Prince causeth the picture to be taken downe, and placed in his owne chamber, and to this shrius of his Goddess, he daily offers many truly inamorated and deuoted Orisons: But his loue more &amp; more continually increasing▪ his excellency could not be satisfied with this liueless resemblance, but after many cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultations resolues to goe in person into England to see at the life, the Mistris and owner of that faire form, which had captiuated his heart; whither at length with a most auspitious successe, and a most noble retinew, he happily arriued.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="book">
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <head>THE III. BOOKE.</head>
      <p>WHere being honorably receiued of the King, &amp; his whole Court, the Prince, with the excellency of his endowments of nature and art, &amp; by the inuisible assistance of the supernall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in kindles no lesse flames of loue, in the virgin breast of the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Princesse towards him, then were in his Excellencies towards her highness: And whilst each of these two, most louing, and most louely louers, did day &amp; night seuerally meditate of this their first loue; <hi>Consus</hi> the lord of councel, in the shape of <hi>Philon,</hi> late his Maiesties tutor, appear'd in night to the sleeping king, telling his highness, that the cōming of the Prince Elector into his kingdom, was by the ordinance of heauen; to the end, that by the aliance made between them, by the Princess his daughter, the state of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion should he established by this most wished for mariage. To this heauenly Counsellor the king consented, with this <hi>prouiso,</hi> that the Prince should first (as it was fitting) request it at his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse hands, which his excellency afterward willingly performing, his Maiesty, at the first motion, graciously condescended. The es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spousalls are prolaimed, and at the report hereof the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome reuels and keeps royall festiualls, and the father of waters <hi>Oceanus,</hi> hauing by <hi>Triton</hi> his Trumpeter assembled the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine &amp; fluuiall powers, doth out of the cleer brow of heauen, and the most temperate season of the spring, prognosticate happy suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, highly praysing in this match the iudgement of the foresee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sapient King, and therwithall prouokes euery thing to reioyce.</p>
      <p>Now comes the Bridall day, in honor whereof <hi>Vulcan,</hi> the God of fire, at the intercession of <hi>Venus</hi> his wife, doth with his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement play his masters prize, in presenting strange and delightful fire-workes vpon the Thames: And <hi>Mars</hi> in competition with him, to content the Queene of loue, shewes valiant and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous feates and stratagems of warre; and the City, to shew her loue and legeance to her Soueraigne, with many sorts of stately showes disembowelleth the inmost of her heart: and the king himselfe, because there should be nothing wanting in this high solemnety, keepes an open Court full of all royall delights; In the middest whereof the marriage is consummated, and the most lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing royall paire obtaine the height of their amorous desires.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>