<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Gwalter Lynne to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102763_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06660</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17117</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102763</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Gwalter Lynne to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe and compendiouse table, in a maner of a concordaunce : openyng the waye to the principall histories of the whole Bible, and the moste co [m] mon articles grounded and comprehended in the newe Testament and olde, in maner as amply as doeth the great concordau [n] ce o the Bible. Gathered and set furth by Henry Bullynger, Leo Iude, Conrade Pellicane, and by the other ministers of the churche of Tygurie. And nowe first imprinted in Englyshe. D.M.L [sic] The third boke of the Machabees a booke of the Bible also prynted vnto this boke which was neuer before translated or prynted in any Englyshe Bible. The contentes of this booke are conteyned in the next leafe</title>
                 <author>Bullinger, Heinrich</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lynne (Lin), Walter (Gualter, Wouter van)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>292 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>Gwalter Lynne to the Reader.</head>
   <p>GEntill Reader yf that you woll take the paynes, as to reade o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Epystell dedycated to me Lady of Somersetts grace, and the Preface of the Authoures before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, there by shall you comme to the ryghte knoweledge and vse of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of thys brefe Concordaunce, God geue vs grace that we maye so reade and vse it to the honoure of hys name and to the profyte of our brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and neyghboures and oure saluaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Amen.</p>
   <p>Dearely beloued bretheren and fryen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des I praye you hartely make you well aquaynted wyth the bokes of the holy Bybell thorouwe muche readynge of them so shall you be much Eased in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge any thynge aboue named in the Prefaces. <note place="margin">ij. Timo iij.c.</note>For all scrypture geuen by inspyracyon of God is profytable to teache, to ymproue, to amende, and to in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sturct in ryghteousnes, that the man of God maye be perfect and prepared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="7"/> all good workes.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">ij. Petr. i.d.</note>For the scripture came neuer by the wyll of man: But holye men of God spake as they were moued by the holy goost.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Zachar. vij.c.</note>Whyche the Lorde of hoostes sente in hys holy spyryte by the prophetes afore tyme.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>