<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, Sir Horatio Veere Knight, Lord Veere of Tilbury, and Generall of the English Forces under the High and mighty Lords the States generall of the united Provin∣ces in the Netherlands. And to his pious Consort, the Lady Mary Veere, increase of grace, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Sibbes, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102404_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12171</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22479</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102404</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, Sir Horatio Veere Knight, Lord Veere of Tilbury, and Generall of the English Forces under the High and mighty Lords the States generall of the united Provin∣ces in the Netherlands. And to his pious Consort, the Lady Mary Veere, increase of grace, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Sibbes, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The bruised reede, and smoaking flax : Some sermons contracted out of the 12. of Matth. 20. At the desire, and for the good of weaker Christians. By R. Sibbes. D.D</title>
                 <author>Sibbes, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dawlman (Dolman), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>54, 72, 63-347, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, Sir <hi>Horatio Veere</hi> Knight, Lord <hi>Veere</hi> of <hi>Tilbury,</hi> and Generall of the English Forces under the High and mighty Lords the States generall of the united Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Netherlands. And to his pious Consort, the Lady <hi>Mary Veere,</hi> increase of grace, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ouldiers that carie their lives in their hands, had
<pb facs="3"/>
need above all others to carie grace in their hearts, that so having made peace with God, they may bee fit to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with men. And having by faith in Christ disarmed death before they dye, they may sacrifice their lives with the more courage and comfort: which to neglect being a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of eternity, is not valour but desperate madnesse, because in
<pb facs="3"/>
this businesse as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versights of war, there is no place for a second repentance, the first er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror being unrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. In evills above the strength of man to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile and his patience to endure, there God hath planted the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of feare, which might stirre us up to avoyd the danger by flying to him in Christ who being our friend it is no matter who is
<pb facs="4"/>
our enemy: wee may be killed, but cannot be hurt; so safe it is to be under his command that hath command over Death, Hell, Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and all that wee most feare. Yet such is our nature that by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with danger, wee grow by degrees insensibly to be harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against it, and to looke no further then death, as if to die were onely to give up the
<pb facs="4"/>
ghost, and then an end of all. And hereupon it is that they that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the warres are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally taken to be men not most religious. The more respect those of that profession de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, that have learned upon what tearmes to live and dye, that are sure of a better life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they leave this, that have layd up their life in Christ; Amongst whom (right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable)
<pb facs="5"/>
the world hath a long time taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of you, in whom both religion, and mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary imploymēt, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of spirit, with height of courage, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility with honor, by a rare and happy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination have met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Whereby you have much vindicated your profession from common imputation, and shewed that Piety can enter into Tents,
<pb facs="5"/>
&amp; follow after camps. and that God hath his <hi>Iosuas,</hi> &amp; his <hi>Corneliuses</hi> in all ages. But I will not use many words of your selfe to your selfe, because though you have done much that may and will bee spoken of, yet you love not to heare or speake of what you have done.</p>
   <p>I may seeme to some unbefitting to offer a discourse of a bruised
<pb facs="6"/>
reede, to such a strong and flourishing Cedar. But experience shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the strongest plants in Gods house are exposed sometimes to strong windes of temptation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon meet vvith brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings; that they may the better know by whose strength they stand, and that the greatest may learne to goe out of themselves to the same common rocke and
<pb facs="6"/>
fountaine of strength with the meanest. DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VID was a valiant man, yet upon experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his oft failings and recoveries, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came towards God as a weaned child. Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse of mind to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and greatnesse of spirit against his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies may well stand together, for the way to bee above all other things, is to submit to God first. Besides; this
<pb facs="7"/>
Text speaketh of the prevailing government of Christ in his Church and in his Children, which may bee an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to your Lordship still not only to owne the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>use of Christ in these times wherein men are asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of what they should glory in, and glory in their shame; but likewise to fight the Lords battels (whē called to it) and helpe
<pb facs="7"/>
him against the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for victory atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Christs side in the end. Though God to revenge the quarrell of his Covenant, suffers his enemies, to prevaile yet for a time, to harden them the more, yet they have undertaken a damned cause, and howsoever the Church hath justly provoked God, yet the cause shall stand impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble against all created
<pb facs="8"/>
power of Devills and men. We naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire victorie, and many desire it more then truth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> goodnesse, which onely are victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and so out of a depraved judgement they crosse their owne desires, seeking to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome in that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it were safer for them to be overcome, they then are sure to meet with shame in the conclusion in stead
<pb facs="8"/>
of victory; or else we must deny Christ to be King of his Church, and Iudge of the world. Proceed on still (honorable Lord) to stand for Christ both in Peace and Warre, and this shall be found to your Honour, when Christ shall come to bee glorious in his Saints, that he thought you worthy to honour himselfe by, when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that oppose or
<pb facs="9"/>
betray the cause of Christ for base ends, shall not dare to hold up their ha ds.</p>
   <p>I would not divide you from your Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lady, being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to both, and both being one as in other bands, so in that above nature, in love to the best things: both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary in all religious courses, both in your places likewise having been imployed in great
<pb facs="9"/>
services for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, so that not onely this, but forraign States are bound to bless <hi>God</hi> for you both. Going on in these waies you will finde God making his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise good of honoring them that honour him.</p>
   <p>I doe not so farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-value this poore worke, as to thinke it worthy of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, but thus I thought
<pb facs="10"/>
meet to witnesse my deserved respect to you both. If I bee to blame for suffring these Sermons long since preached, thus to come forth, others must di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the fault with me, who had brought it to that passe, that it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most necessary for mee to take this course. The Lord continue to bless your Honours with all your branches, and to maintaine his grace in
<pb facs="10"/>
you, untill hee hath brought forth judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto victory.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honors to command in the Lord,</hi> Richard Sibbes.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>