<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument vpon Iohn.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102561_Fr2_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16078</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2962</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102561</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument vpon Iohn.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A harmonie vpon the three Euangelists, Matthew, Mark and Luke : with the commentarie of M. Iohn Caluine: faithfullie translated out of Latine into English, by E.P. Whereunto is also added a commentarie vpon the Euangelist S. Iohn, by the same authour</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 806, 2, 8, 464, 24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary_of_gospel_of_John">
   <pb n="5" facs="440"/>
   <head>The Argument vpon Iohn.</head>
   <p>IT is well knowen what this woorde <hi>Euangelium</hi> or Gospel doth signifie amongst the
Grecians: and in the scriptures it is chiefly taken for the ioyfull and happie message of
that grace which is giuen vs in Christe: to the ende we may learne (despising the worlde
&amp; the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aile riches &amp; pleasures therof) to desire this incomparable treasure with our whole
hearte, and to imbrace the same being offered vnto vs. That is naturally engrafted in vs
all, which wee see the wicked doe, namely to reioyce inordinately in the vaine pleasures of
the worlde, and to bee touched either with none, or els with a very slender feeling of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
good thinges. Therefore to the ende that God may reforme in vs this fault, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
that message which he commandeth to be published cōcerning Christ, by this name <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelium,</hi>
or Gospel. For hee doth thereby tell vs that true and perfect ioy can be had
no where els: that without all doubt wee haue in him the blessed life, in all pointes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.
Certaine there bee who extende this woorde <hi>Gospell</hi> vnto all the free promises of
God, which are also dispearsed in the lawe and the prophetes. Neither is it to bee denied
but that God so often as he doth testifie that hee will bee mercifull vnto men, and forgiue
them their sinnes, doth also offer Christe, whose propertie it is wheresoeuer hee shineth, to
spreade abroade the beames of ioy. Therefore I confesse that the fathers and wee are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers
of one and the same gospel, as touching the faith of free saluation: yet because the
spirite doth vsually speake thus in the Scriptures, that the Gospel was published when
Christe came: let vs also retaine the same maner of speech, and let this bee the definition
of the Gospel, which I haue set down, that it is, <hi>a solemne publishing or proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
of the grace reuealed in Christe.</hi> In which respect the Gospel is called the
power of God to saluation to all that beleeue, because God doth therein make manifest his
righteousnesse. It is also called the embassage whereby he reconcileth men vnto himselfe.
Furthermore inasmuch as Christe is the pledge of Gods mercie, and of his fathers loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes
vs, therefore is he also the proper matter of the Gospel. Heereby it commeth
to passe that the histories which declare that Christe appeared in the flesh, dyed, and was
raysed vp againe from the death, and was at length receiued vp into the heauens, are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
called the Gospel. For although the new Testament be called by this name, according
to that reason which of late I alleadged, yet is it come to passè by vse and custome that
that parte which doth testifie that Christ was exhibeted vnto vs in the flesh, dyed, &amp; ros<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
againe from the death, is so called by <hi>Synecdoche.</hi> But because the bare historie were
not sufficient, yea, should profite nothing vnto saluation, the Euangelistes doe not simplie
shewe that Christe was borne, that hee died, and became the conquerour of death: but they
doe also declare, to what ende he was borne, to what ende he died, and rose againe, and what
fruite we reape thereby. Yet there is this difference amongest them that the other three
set downe more at large, the life and death of Christe: but this Euangelist of ours, stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
more vpon the doctrine, wherein both the office of Christe and the force of his death,
and resurrection is declared. They doe not conceale that Christe came to the end he might
bring saluation to the worlde, that he might make satisfaction for sinnes by the sacrifice
of his death. Finally that he might in all points fulfill the function of a mediatour (like as
<hi>Iohn</hi> doth also stande somewhat vpon the historicall narration:) but the doctrine which
sheweth vnto vs the force and fruite of Christ his comming, appeareth more plainly in this
Euangelist then in the other.</p>
   <p>And whereas it is all their drift to make Christe manifest, the former Euangelistes
bring forth (that I may so speake) his body, and <hi>Iohn</hi> bringeth foorth his soule. VVherfore
I vse commonly to call this Gospel, the key that openeth the gate vnto the vnderstanding
of the other. For whosoeuer shall perfectly vnderstande of what power and force Christe
<pb n="6" facs="441"/>
is, as it is heere in plaine wordes set downe, hee shall reade with profite those thynges which
are deliuered by the other concerning the manifestation of the <hi>Redeemer.</hi> It is thought
that Iohn was most of all mooued to write, for this cause, and to this ende, that hee might
defende the diuinitie of Christe againste the wicked blasphemies of <hi>Ebion</hi> and <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus,</hi>
and this doth <hi>Eusebius</hi> and <hi>Hyerome</hi> report according to the opinion of
the olde writers: but whatsoeuer was the occasion that caused him to write at that time,
yet it is not to bee doubted but that God did farther prouide for his Churche. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
hee did so indite to the Euangelistes that which they shoulde write, that hauing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided
the partes amongst them, hee might make one perfect body. Nowe it is our dutie
so to linke and knit together the foure, that wee suffer our selues to bee taught as it were
with one mouth of them all together. VVhereas they haue placed Iohn the fourth in
order, in this they had respect to the time wherein hee writ: but the contrary order is
more profitable in reading: that beeing afterwarde aboute to reade in Matthewe that
Christe was giuen vs of the father, we may first learne out of Iohn to what end he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>