<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Preface to the true Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102282_Fr6_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11041</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102282</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Preface to the true Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The diamond of deuotion : cut and squared into sixe seuerall points: namelie, 1 The footpath to felicitie. 1 2 A guide to godlines. 81 3 The schoole of skill. 181 4 A swarme of bees. 209 5 A plant of pleasure. 245 6 A groue of graces. 283 Full of manie fruitfull lessons, auaileable to the leading of a godlie and reformed life: by Abraham Fleming</title>
                 <author>Fleming, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William, Assignee(s) of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 320, 4 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="126"/>
   <pb n="247" facs="126"/>
   <head>A Preface to the true <hi>Christian Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a naturall incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of man, for the delighting and sola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of himselfe, after some labour or exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise, to seeke such recreations, as dooe best agree with his disposition. Herevpon, some couet this game, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thersome that: and euerie man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede what maketh most for his contentment. Which kind of recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations and refreshings, men are not forbidden in Gods word to vse, so that the feare of his diuine maiestie preuent them in all their actions: and that they abuse not those bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites of recreation to a licentious and wanton libertie.</p>
   <p>Verie necessarie it is, that consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration be had of the state of the bodie, which cannot alwaies en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure labour, but that now and then it must be refreshed, not onlie with
<pb facs="127"/>
some intermission &amp; ceassing from trauell, but also with some kind of exercise coupled with delectation and pleasure, whereby not onelie the bodie, and euerie member thereof, is comforted, but the mind also, and the faculties or powers of the same iollilie quickened.</p>
   <p>Such care taken for the bodie, which is earthlie and corruptible, should teach vs (I thinke) a point of wit, which we want, touching the regard wherewith we ought to be moued for the good estate of the mind or soule, which is heauenlie and immortall. For how much the minde is more pretious than the bodie, so much the more, wisedome would, it should be esteemed: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise we shall seeme to preferre the shell before the kernell, the barke before the pith, the shadowe before the substance, yea, most absurdlie, we shall refuse wheate for chaffe, pure gold for drosse, cleere wine for dregs, and in conclusion repent our want of grace.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="127"/>It were behoofull therefore for vs, first and principallie to see to our mind, which is chiefest part of our essence and being, that the same, after some serious studie and contemplation, desiring to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshed, be not fed with fond fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, fables, dotages, imaginations, dreames, &amp; I cannot tell what idle and vnfruitefull discourses, which kindle the affections, and set the flesh a gogge: but rather with holie exercises, and godlie meditations, such as are and may be prouided for the purpose, to reuiue the spirit, and quicken the new man, if the partie be gratiouslie affected.</p>
   <p>Thou hast heere therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented vnto thine hand (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) a plant of pleasure, bearing fourteene seuerall flowers, called by the name of holie Hymnes and spirituall Songs, to reade at thy leasure for thy recreation, and not so much for thy recreation, as for thy profit: which I haue put partlie in rythme, and partlie in prose, for
<pb facs="128"/>
the satisfaction of sundrie Readers desires, some beeing addicted to this, and some delighted in that kind of writing. I would to God it were in me to frame my wit to the will of the well disposed in all points. I haue done what I could, the Lord knoweth what I would: his name be praised for all, whose glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to seeke and set foorth, I beseech him giue vs all grace, so shall the faithfull reioice and clap their hands, but shame shall fall vpon the reprobat, &amp; force them to hang downe their heads.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Abraham Fleming.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>