<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE, OR Introduction.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102083_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09850</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20115</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102083</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE, OR Introduction.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A looking-glasse for the soule, and a definition thereof. Written by Edward Popham Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Popham, Edward, gentleman</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 48 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE, <hi>OR Introduction.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He soueraigne decree of God, enacted by the <hi>Father</hi> of
Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ratified by his <hi>Sonne,</hi> and daily repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the instinct
of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost,</hi> bindeth euery good
<pb facs="6"/> Christian to distribute accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their
measure lent, be it more or lesse, so it may any waies profit,
following that saying of <hi>Plato, Non solum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis nati sumus.</hi> For
it is a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue that alloweth of no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, but of necessity
presseth euery good mind to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of dutie. <hi>Nature</hi> by
grace is not abolished but perfected, not murthered but manured; neither are
her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions quite rased or anul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but suted to the colours of
faith and vertue.</p>
   <p>And if <hi>Natures</hi> affections be so forcible, that euen
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n Hell (where rankor and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/> spight raineth, and all feeling of Gods
goodnesse is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed in mallice) it mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the rich glutton by
expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of his owne misery, to carry a desire of admonition to his
friends; much more in the Church of God, where grace quickeneth, charity
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flameth, and <hi>Natures</hi> incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation (directed by superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
grace) prouoketh ought the dutie of piety to preuaile.</p>
   <p>And who but more merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse then damned Creatures, could
see their Christian Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, almost plunged in like perill, and not be
wounded
<pb facs="7"/> with deep remorse, of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable &amp;
imminent hazard. If in beholding a mortall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, wrung and tortured with
deadly pangs, the toughest heart softneth with some <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi> If
the most fierce mind cannot but thaw &amp; melt with pitty, when it seeth
the worst <hi>Miscreant</hi> suffer his deserued torments? how much
lesse can a Christian heart consider the number of such which daily
fall into farre more bitter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamities, and not bleed in griefe for their
vncomfortable case; nay, rather imploy all their cares, studies, and
indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to winne and reclaime them from that dangerous
<pb facs="8"/> brincke of perdition?</p>
   <p>Surely, though I challenge not the prerogatiue of the best
disposition; yet my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire is, with young <hi>Tobias,</hi> to trauell
and bring home spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall substance, and medicina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble receits to cure
such ghost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly malladie, as euidently at this day is to be seene, and did
in no former <hi>Age</hi> more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly abound. I haue with <hi>Esau</hi>
prouided Venison which may procure a blessing, and bread, with
<hi>Ioseph,</hi> for the repast of their soules, which most carelesly
they oppresse with famine in time of plenty. Let it not therfore be thought

<pb facs="9"/> any dishonor to men of more grauity, or
disparagemement to any person whatsoeuer that I, in all humility, offer
my aduise in a case so much to be pittied, and a time so dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.
One man cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in all faculties, neither is it any disgrace to
the <hi>Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smith</hi> if he be ignorant of the <hi>Millers</hi> trade. Many
are deepe Lawyers, but shallow Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, and are farre to seeke in
religious actions.</p>
   <p>If therefore I offer the fruits of my labours, and make you
apresent of my zealous indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, I hope you will cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure thereof,
rather as of the
<pb facs="7"/> part of a dutifull Christian, then of any poynt of
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption. And so I humbly refer you to the rest, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Demidium facti qui bene coepit habet.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>