<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Worshipfull Mr. EDVVARD WARRE, Esquire: And to the truly religious and right vertu∣ous ELIZABETH his Wife, At Chipley in Sommerset, my much honoured friends: Mercy and peace be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Sclater, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102973_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11605</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21846</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102973</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Worshipfull Mr. EDVVARD WARRE, Esquire: And to the truly religious and right vertu∣ous ELIZABETH his Wife, At Chipley in Sommerset, my much honoured friends: Mercy and peace be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Sclater, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three sermons preached by VVilliam Sclater Doctor of Diuinity, and minister of the word of God at Pitmister in Sommersetshire. Now published by his sonne of Kings Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Sclater, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <publisher>Crooke, Andrew 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 16, 8, 17-39, 11, 19, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>To the Worshipfull M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>EDVVARD WARRE, Esquire: And to the truly religious and right vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ELIZABETH</hi> his Wife, At <hi>Chipley</hi> in <hi>Sommerset,</hi> my much honoured <hi>friends:</hi> Mercy and peace be multiplied.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Worshipfull:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>WO things more especiall, haue occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the present ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of my seruice to you: The one is, the greatneess of that loue and plenty of curtesie, which from you the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, hath euer beene deriued, and
<pb facs="15"/> willingly conueyed to our familie, sweetly to refresh, as once the liuing, but languishing stocke, so now also all the tender branches sprouting out from it: The other is, your vndeser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued fauours towards my selfe in more particular. As for the first, we are all heires to that seruice, which our deare Father in all obseruancy towards you was euer ready to performe: for the second, as I more neerely shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my selfe to stand for euer obliged to you, so for the present doe desire that my thankefull seruice may haue acceptance at your fauourable hands, wherein if (through want of skill to expresse it) I seeme any way defectiue, he pleased to suppose out of the kindnesse of those louing hearts of yours, that, that which you see not
<pb facs="15"/> heere fully tendered by my vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned quill, is inwardly in wishing thoughts supplied: In confidence whereof, here I dedicate my selfe, and these few leaues, penned by the Author my deceased Father to your worthinesse, hoping your Worships will vaile my boldnesse in your good acceptance, and trusting (for the Authors sake) that your strong hands will support this posthume worke (wrested from me by impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of some my reuerend, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious friends) which can liue now by no other heat, then what your beames giues it. It flies to you as a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued Orphan for shelter, confident of safety from the worlds vpbraiding, if you vouchsafe to yeeld it patronage. Now the God of all mercy, that hath
<pb facs="16"/> so richly furnished you with his sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing grace, preserue and keepe you blamelesse vnto the comming of the Lord Iesus, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full respectfulnesse WILLIAM SCLATER.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my Chamber in Kings Colledge in Cambridge.</hi>
         <date>Nou. 18. 1628.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>