<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102588_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01175</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11289</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102588</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The restorer of the French estate : discouering the true causes of these vvarres in France &amp; other countries, and deliuering the right course of restoring peace and quiet to all Christendome: wherein are handled these principall questions touching religion, policie, and iustice: whether it be lawfull to sweare, and keepe promise to heretikes, to force mens consciences for religion sake, to liue with, and dwell nigh heretikes, to breake the order of succession to the Crowne bycause of religion, or no. Who be schismatikes; and of the chiefe poincts of religion. How we are to iudge of the schisme in Christendome at this day. Lastly, the conclusion conteining notable admonitions to the clergie, nobles, magistrates, people, and King of France. Translated out of French. Ecclesiæ &amp; reipub. D</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 172 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here came foorth a Discourse on the praesent state of France in the yeare last past, which surely did some good: now commeth forth another writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten (as appeareth) by the same Auctor, for restoring the state of Fraunce, which is likely to do more good. The worke being first conceiued by an high wit, &amp; after shaped by ripe experience, seemeth sithence to haue passed through some rude and vncleane hand. And yet, it is not so misshapen or defaced thereby, but that the lineaments remaining do soone descry the first workman. and thus much for the forme. For the matter, it is no counterfeict stuff, but will abide the touch of the safest maximes in policie, and the triall of the soundest principles in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And as the discrete Reader (I know) will suspend his iudgemēt, till he perceiue th'Auctors purpose: so let the saucy Censurer know, that the height thereof surmounteth the reach of his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping conceipt. Fare-well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>