<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, the Knights, Iustices, and Gentlemen, and to all the rest of my religi∣ous countri-men in the Countie of Wiltshire.</title>
           <author>Webbe, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102505_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14861</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25165</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102505</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, the Knights, Iustices, and Gentlemen, and to all the rest of my religi∣ous countri-men in the Countie of Wiltshire.</title>
                 <author>Webbe, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The practice of quietnes. Or a direction how to liue quietly at all times, in all places, vpon all occasions, and how to auoide or put off, all occasions of vnquietnesse. Deliuered in six sermons at Steeple-Ashton in Wiltshire by George Webbe preacher of the word and Pastor there</title>
                 <author>Webbe, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 196 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, the Knights, Iustices, and Gentlemen, and to <hi>all the rest of my religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> countri-men in <hi>the Countie of</hi> Wiltshire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no study next the practise of Piety, like the study of peace; The Authour of the Epistle to the Hebrewes doth lincke them both together,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note>
      <hi>Follow peace and
<pb facs="5"/>holinesse;</hi> as if there could bee no holinesse without peace and quietnes. This Quietnesse is the daughter of Piety, the sister of Humility, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of many a worthy vertue. It is the honour of a family, the ornament of a citty, the muniment of a common wealth, without which no vertue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth like it selfe, nor comfort gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth content. This Art of Quietnes so needefull a study for all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians (Right worshipfull and Welbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Countrim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n) haue I according to the measure of that poore talent which I haue receiued, taught, as here it is deliuered, in my pastorall charge within your country, in sixe seuerall lectures. That I haue heere compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted them together, &amp; brought them out of the pulpit to the presse, I neede no other Apologie then my zeale to Gods glory, the common good, and my countries quietnesse. Whereunto I was the more emboldned for the
<pb facs="5"/>stopping of the mouthes of those who enuying my peace, both priuately and publikely, spare not to censure me as an vnquiet person, and an enimy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to peace. Whither I delight to so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourne in vnquiet <hi>Mesech,</hi> or to dwel in the contentious tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 20.5</note> let this small Treatise witnes. If my hart doe not goe with my words, and my desire for mine owne practise with the counsell I giue vnto others, shall not that supreame Iudge, who <hi>sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the heart,
<note place="margin">Ier. 17.10.</note> and trieth the raines,</hi> search and trye it out? vncharitable censures of selfe-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited Critickes, I doubt not but this small Treatise shall finde as well as others which formerly I haue pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished: I expect no lesse then store of carps where curious eyes go a fishing, especially where the <hi>Torpedo</hi> of blacke enuy doth bait the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ook. They who like none but themselues, how should they approoue any thing of
<pb facs="6"/>mine? how can they spare their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure against mee, who neuer speake well of any. But to leaue these <hi>Zoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists</hi> with as slender respect of their censure, as they doe of any Treatise, my hope is (Right Worshipfull and Welbeloued) that with you these my poore labours, though not for the worth of the worke, yet for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse of the subiect vpon which it doth worke, shall finde acceptance: It sheweth the path-way vnto Quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, the proper obiect (Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull) of your office, and the daily subiect (Welbeloued) of your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise. It is the duty of the Minister to teach Quietnesse, of the Magistrate to maintaine Quietnesse, of euery one to pray for Quietnesse and to practise Quietnesse. This our Country hath store of the sonnes of <hi>Leui,</hi> who preach Peace, and perswade Quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: It hath many a worthy <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Ioshua,</hi> who make Peace and
<pb facs="6"/>preserue Quietnesse; Many a sincere <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> who seeketh Peace and followeth after Quietnesse: Yet there want not in euery Diuision, Hundred &amp; Tithing, some turbulent <hi>Korahs,</hi> some seditious <hi>Shebaes,</hi> some furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Lamechs,</hi> some churlish <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals,</hi> some oppressing <hi>Ahabs,</hi> who are enimies vnto Quietnesse. Wee praise God that our country is so quiet as it is, and doe daily wish vnto the encrease of Quietnesse. Which that it may be effected, it is required of you (Right Worshipfull) that you feare God and be men of courage, that you vse all diligence to cut off the occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of variance, and to keepe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in all holy obedience. And for the rest it is required that they learne Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, practise equity, doe iustly, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue vnity. So shall wee haue a due respected Magistracy, a firme vnited communalty, and a most flourishing country, and the God of peace shall be
<pb facs="7"/>with vs, to multiply all peace and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse vnto vs. To whose blessed protection I leaue you, and and these my poore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors to his blessing. </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Steepleashton, <date>Iune, 20. 1615.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships</hi> humbly deuoted <hi>GEORGE WEBBE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>