<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Instructions Pertaining To Psalms]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1567</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102297_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15970</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2729</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102297</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Instructions Pertaining To Psalms]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhole Psalter translated into English metre, which contayneth an hundreth and fifty Psalmes. The first quinquagene</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1567</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52, 146, 2, 147-236, 6, 235-280, 2, 281-424, 48 pages, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="instructions_pertaining_to_psalms">
   <p>THe <hi>150.</hi> beyng the last Psalme, is a serious and ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nest inuitation to the prayses of God: and so most agreably placed, as last to knit vp the ende of all that is treated in the fiue seueral bookes of Psalmes so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided by the Hebrues. In whiche fiue bookes bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sparsed abroad matter of Prophecy of Christ and hys church, of History, of Doctrine, of Instruction, of Inuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of Exhortation, of Reformation, of Insultation, of Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>solation, of Gloriation, of Inuocation, of Obsecration, of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, of Patience, and such lyke. So that all breath, voyce, and sound of worde, sunge, sayd, or thoughte, should tende wholy in the ende, to prayse the Lorde, whych is the first, the mydst, and finall worke, and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, wherunto all should be referred. Furthermore because in rhe thyrd, fourth, and fifth verses, onelye musicall instrumentes be recyted, lest they should be but bare instrumentes wythout distinction, or signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of sound, in them be added for supplement, the three appropriates ascribed to God in Trinitie, as Power and Authoritie, whereby all thynges were created and wrought Wysdome and Prouidence, wherby all thynges be iustly gouerned and ruled.</p>
   <p>Goodnes and Bountie, wherby all thinges be preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, from whence procede all graces and giftes both bodely and ghostly.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="258"/>Thus this Psalme whych is the last beyng confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to that whych is the first, which is also tracted by certayne Triades describyng the felicitye of man doth resemble, the same not onely by Triades of verse but also by thys Triade included in mystery, thoughe not expressely: So determinyng the chiefe and laste woorke, that thys blessed man so described in all the course of hys lyfe should meditate, which acte in the next lyfe he shall most perfectly do and performe.</p>
   <p>Therfore the Chaunter is not vntymely broughte in for fresher remembraunce to proclayme once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne hys ioyfull Alleluya, to ende therin to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of God in Trinitie, the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoct, to whome be all honour, glory, and praise euerlastingly, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>