<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE WILLIAM Lord KNOLLES Baron of Greyes, Treasurer of his Maiesties houshold, Master of his Maiesties Wards and Liueries, and one of the Lords of his Ma∣iesties most Honorable priuie Counsell: The supreme felicitie of both worlds heartily wished.</title>
           <author>Ferebe, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102085_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00684</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10818</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102085</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE WILLIAM Lord KNOLLES Baron of Greyes, Treasurer of his Maiesties houshold, Master of his Maiesties Wards and Liueries, and one of the Lords of his Ma∣iesties most Honorable priuie Counsell: The supreme felicitie of both worlds heartily wished.</title>
                 <author>Ferebe, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lifes farewell. Or A funerall sermon preached at Saint Iohns in the Deuises in Wilshiere, the 30. of August last 1614 : At the funerall of Iohn Drew Gentleman. By George Ferebe Master of Arts, and preacher of the Word at Bishops Cannings in Wilshire</title>
                 <author>Ferebe, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE WILLIAM Lord KNOLLES Baron of Greyes, Treasurer</hi> of his Maiesties houshold, Master of his Maiesties Wards <hi>and Liueries, and one of the Lords of his</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties most Honorable priuie Counsell: <hi>The supreme felicitie of both worlds heartily wished.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His funerall Sermon preached vpon the death of a Gentleman, my pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shioner and neighbour; being by the importunitie of some brought to the Presse (I hope) for the benefit of all; comes thus to light vnder the gratious and honorable Lyuorie of your Lordships name; as a remonstrance of that dutie and thankfull acknowledgment, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I am engaged: for those many reall and liberall encouragements, my rawer and riper studies haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from that hand of bounty, which to my selfe and
<pb facs="3"/> Brethren, (aswell during our many yeeres abode in the Vniuersitie, as also since) hath alwaies layen open; whereby as we all acknowledge the vttermost of our religious respect and obseruance, vnable to satisfie the least part of that debt due to your Lordship: So wee trust the most iust God (who leaues not a cup of cold water vnrewarded) will returne your Lordship dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and treble remuneration. What entertainment it may finde in the broad world, I regard not; If from your Lordship it obteine the least approbation, I haue my hearts desire; which shall euer spend it selfe in prayer to God, for the compleating heere, and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hereafter, of your Lordships manifold graces and vertues.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lordships most bounden and dutifull</hi> Chaplaine <hi>GEORGE FEREBE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>