<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ENGLAND, IN HER REPRESEN∣TIVE BODY. The High and Illustrious Court of Parliament,</title>
           <author>Reynolds, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102594_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01180</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11293</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102594</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ENGLAND, IN HER REPRESEN∣TIVE BODY. The High and Illustrious Court of Parliament,</title>
                 <author>Reynolds, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The apologie of the Reformed Churches of France : VVherein are expressed the reasons, why they haue ioyned their armies; to those of the King of Great Britaine. Translated according to the French coppie</title>
                 <author>Eglises réformées de France</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 55, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO ENGLAND,</hi> IN <hi>HER REPRESEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIVE BODY. The High and Illustrious Court of Parliament,</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>LORDS.</salute>
      <salute>KNIGHTS.</salute>
      <salute>BVRGESSES.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou haue here (in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie) presented to you, the sighes &amp; teares of our sister Church of <hi>France,</hi> who is at this present miserably perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the bloodie power and Malice of <hi>Antichrist</hi> and his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents; as also the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked grounds and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, why shee ioynes her Armes with those of our
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> in her lawfull Defence and preseruation; For although <hi>Rebellon</hi> be the false pretect, yet Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the true cause why the Pope by his Champion the French King, now seekes her finall raine and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. Shee now mournes both in teares and blood, and breathes forth her wounds and sorrowes to vs in a fainting; yea, almost in a dying eloquence; Shall wee therefore (who professe our selues to be the best of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> and the deerest of Gods Children) permit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phannesse to preuaile ore pietie, Idolatrie to triumph ore true Religion, and the Church of Rome, ore that of God, if our Religion be theirs, must not their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and persecutions be ours, For what Peace can we haue whiles they are oppressed with Warre, or how can our consciences be at rest and tranquilitie, whiles theirs are tovmented with all sorts of afflictions and cruelties, Can that Church of France be beaten but this of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is threatned, or the Protestants of that Kingdome be extinguished but we are Eclipsed, yea, doe not their feares presage and predict ours, and their dangers fatally denounce and portend ours: We haue already seene and suffered Gods Church in Bohemia, the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>atinate, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesia and Morauia to bee ruined, and shall we not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beleeue, if that of France goe next, that this of England must immediately follow, We see the Pope is as bloody in his malice, as boundlesse in his Ambition, and that with high wrestling, and an insulting brauerie, he proceedes in his Enuie and power, at one time to roote out the name and memorie of Gods Church and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in all places and Countries of Christendome. How powerfully hath he lately preuailed with the Emperour and the King of Spaine and Poland in this bloody qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell,
<pb facs="3"/>
who with barbarous hearts and sacrilegious hands haue played their prises in oppressing and de-pressing these Churches in their Countries, and (now by a policie as subtile, as execrable) hath likewise drawne the French King to make himselfe guiltie of the same impious and bloody crimes; to ruine the Protestants of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whose Valours and Fidelities placed the Crowne on his Fathers head; and to exterminate those Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which with so much Pietie and wisedome hee had established in the Meridian of their perfection and glorie.</p>
   <p>The which to preuent, and oppose, God hath inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the heart of our Gracious King <hi>CHARLES</hi> to reach them out the hand and Scepter of his Royall assis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and so to proue himselfe a true Defender of the Faith, as well in Fact as Title. Knowing therefore that by the Lawes of Honour and Religion we are bound to ayde and asist them, and not to suffer the Vineyard of Gods Church to be thus miserably trampled ore, and rooted vp by the Champions of Rome and Hell, it will be a pious and a Noble worke for you Illustrious Lords and Gentlemen, the Great Senators, and Elders of our Israell, to contribute the meanes, as our King hath the Will, to the preseruation and building vp of so Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and glorious a Worke; by affecting it tenderly in your selues, and by cheerishing it carefully and dearely in the hearts of all the parts and members of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; For as the Protestants of France call on our King, so doth his Maiestie on you (who are the essentiall and figuratiue body thereof) and God on you all, for the speedy and vigorous assistance of this his afflicted Spouse the Church, and hee who is the searcher of all hearts the
<pb facs="4"/>
witnesse of all soules, and the Iudge of all actions, will infallibly iudge betwixt you and him, with what true Deuotion and Zeale you performe this part of his seruice and glorie.</p>
   <p>Warres are made as well with Gold as Iron, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in assisting this our afflicted Sister the Church of France, wee must second our words with deedes; our promises with effects, and our Prayers with our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. Their Enemies are strong and powerfull, their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and dangers great, so therefore must our assis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be to them. They are neere to vs by Cituation, but farre neerer in Religion, for as their cause and quarell is ours, so should the sence and feeling of their calamities, and in this sence I may iustly affirme, that they are a great part of our selues, because we generally belong all to one Church, as that Church doth particularly and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly to God.</p>
   <p>As truth is the best eloquence to perswade vs to this assistance, so Religion is the best truth, and it would bee an act not onely of Impietie, but of shame in vs, if these our three flourishing Churches, of England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Ireland, should not now powerfully assist that afflicted one of France, which sues to them for it, with teares and prayers. But Illustrious Lords and generous Gentlemen, my Iudgement prompts mee that I should wrong yours, in seeking to perswade your affections to so charitable and religious a worke, from which I know nothing is capable to direct, or disswade you, and in that behalfe I rest hopefull, if not confident, that you will at least excuse my zeale, if not pardon my presumption for proferring vp the sighes and teares of this poore perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted French Church, to your sublime Protection and
<pb facs="4"/>
Patronage, or rather to your charitable care, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious consderacion, as esteeming it euerie way as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your pittie and compassion, as of your knowledge. May the sight of her afflictions, myseries and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, teach vs how to preuent our owne, May God of his best mercie so operate with our hearts and soules, as wee may esteeme and repute them our owne, and may Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (by the Kings royall, and your Illustricus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) stretch forth her hands, to relieue this poore French Church and people, so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iustly afflicted, and so wrongfully oppressed and persecuted for God, and his Cause.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN REYNOLDS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>