<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>EPILOGVS.</title>
           <author>Brasbridge, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102876_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01522</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11645</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102876</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>EPILOGVS.</title>
                 <author>Brasbridge, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The steele glas : A satyre co [m] piled by George Gascoigne Esquire. Togither with The complainte of Phylomene. An elegie deuised by the same author</title>
                 <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Smith (Smyth), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>136 pages, portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="epilogue">
   <pb facs="30"/>
   <head>EPILOGVS.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Las (my lord) my hast was al to hote,</l>
      <l>I shut my glasse, before you gasde your fill,</l>
      <l>And at a glimse, my seely selfe haue spied,</l>
      <l>A stranger trowpe, than any yet were sene:</l>
      <l>Beholde (my lorde) what monsters muster here,</l>
      <l>With Angels face, and harmefull helish harts,</l>
      <l>With smyling lookes, and depe deceitful thoughts,</l>
      <l>With tender skinnes, and stony cruel mindes,</l>
      <l>With stealing steppes, yet forward feete to fraude.</l>
      <l>Behold, behold, they neuer stande content,</l>
      <l>With God, with kinde, with any helpe of Arte,</l>
      <l>But curle their locks, with bodkins &amp; with braids,</l>
      <l>But dye their heare, with sundry subtill sleights,</l>
      <l>But paint and slicke, til fayrest face be foule,</l>
      <l>But bumbast, bolster, frisle, and perfume:</l>
      <l>They marre with muske, the balme which nature made,</l>
      <l>And dig for death, in dellicatest dishes.</l>
      <l>The yonger sorte, come pyping on apace,</l>
      <l>In whistles made offine enticing wood,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="31"/>
Til they haue caught, the birds for whom they birded.</l>
      <l>The elder sorte, go stately stalking on,</l>
      <l>And on their backs, they beare both land and fee,</l>
      <l>Castles and Towres, revenewes and receits,</l>
      <l>Lordships, and manours, fines, yea fermes and al.</l>
      <l>What should these be? (speake you my louely lord)</l>
      <l>They be not men: for why? they haue no beards.</l>
      <l>They be no boyes, which weare such side lōg gowns.</l>
      <l>They be no Gods, for al their gallant glosse.</l>
      <l>They be no diuels, (I trow) which seme so saintish.</l>
      <l>What be they? women? masking in mens weedes?</l>
      <l>With dutchkin dublets, and with Ierkins iaggde?</l>
      <l>With Spanish spangs, and ruffes fet out of France,</l>
      <l>With high copt hattes, and fethers flaunt a flaunt?</l>
      <l>They be so sure euen <hi>VVo</hi> to <hi>Men</hi> in dede.</l>
      <l>Nay then (my lorde) let shut the glasse apace,</l>
      <l>High time it were, for my pore Muse to winke,</l>
      <l>Since al the hands, al paper, pen, and inke,</l>
      <l>Which euer yet, this wretched world possest,</l>
      <l>Cannot describe, this Sex in colours dewe,</l>
      <l>No no (my Lorde) we gased haue inough,</l>
      <l>(And I too much, God pardon me therfore)</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="31"/>
Better loke of, than loke an ace to farre:</l>
      <l>And better mumme, than meddle ouermuch.</l>
      <l>But if my Glasse, do like my louely lorde,</l>
      <l>VVe wil espie, some sunny Sommers day,</l>
      <l>To loke againe, and see some semely sights.</l>
      <l>Meane while, my Muse, right hūbly doth besech,</l>
      <l>That my good lorde, accept this ventrous verse,</l>
      <l>Vntil my braines, may better stuffe deuise.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>
      <hi>FINIS:</hi> Tam Marti, quàm Mercurio.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>