<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The Authour his Prologue. Fiammetta speaketh.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102851_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16255</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3179</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102851</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The Authour his Prologue. Fiammetta speaketh.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Amorous Fiammetta : VVherein is sette downe a catologue [sic] of all and singuler passions of loue and iealosie, incident to an enamored yong gentlewoman, with a notable caueat for all women to eschewe deceitfull and wicked loue, by an apparant example of a Neapolitan lady, her approued &amp; long miseries, and wyth many sounde dehortations from the same. First wrytten in Italian by Master Iohn Boccace, the learned Florentine, and poet laureat. And now done into English by B. Giouano del M. Temp. With notes in the margine, and with a table in the ende of the cheefest matters contayned in it</title>
                 <author>Boccaccio, Giovanni</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Newman, Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 123, 4 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>❧ The Authour his Prologue. <hi>Fiammetta speaketh.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Iserable men, when</hi> they perceiue that others haue compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of theyr miseries, and sée them selues to be pitied of some, are wont to take a certaine kinde of delight &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in their sorrowes and gréefes. Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cause the occasion therefore, of my vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary sorrowe, by tract of long time and custome, is rather augmented then deminished in me, I thinke it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse, in telling and dicoursing my bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter chaunces to you (most noble Ladies) in whose tender hearts looue perhappes dooth dwell more happely then in mine, to attempt to fill (if possibly I may) the same with pittie and compassion. And I recke not whether my spéeches come to mens eares or no, but will rather, hide them as much as I may, from them all: because the cruell dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges of one false man, are here so inuectiuely discouered of me, that others imagining the like, I might sooner expect with their scornes and tauntes to be flowted, then to be pittied with their sorrowfull teares.</p>
   <p>I beséech you (gentle Ladies) to reade it, whom I knowe by my owne selfe naturally inclined to commiseration of my misfortunes. You shall not in reading of it, finde any <hi>Grecian</hi> fables depainted and set foorth with plausible lies, nor <hi>Troian</hi> warres foule and lothsome by deadly goare, but Amorous battailes procured and maintained by innumerable pricking desires, in the which shalbe presented beé<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eyes, the miserable teares, the ouerwhelming and burning sighes, the dolefull complaintes, and the boysterous and tempestuous thoughtes, which continuall stinges pearcing my troubled soule haue taken from me my woonted appetite, depriued me of my swéete sléepe, exiled my ioyfull times, and (O death to my remembraunce) despoyled me of my péerelesse and déerest beautie. All which thinges, if you wyll
<pb facs="5"/> euery one by her selfe, or else altogether, with that pittifull heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, which for the most part all women haue, then assuredly I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swad my selfe, that you will bath your delicate chéekes with streames of gushing teares, which are to me a material cause, and chéefe occasion (dispairing of all hope and comfort to come) of perpetuall anguish and gréefe of minde. I pray you therefore (tender harted Ladies and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen) not to withhold them, but let them issue from their forced fountaines, thinking with your selues, that if your fortunes, which are not very stedfast and sure, should chaunce (which the Gods forbid) to be semblable to mine, how déere and grateful a thing should it be to you, if in lue of your lamentations, and for your hard happes I should power forth some teares againe. But because the time, (spent more in wordes, then wailinges,) may not slide away, I will force my selfe breefely to come to the performaunce of my promisse, beginning fyrst with my happy and stedfast looue, because deducing in argument from that former felicitie, to this present state and condition of life, you may both knowe and call me the most vnfortunate woman that liues. And from thence I will (as well as I can) with a ruthfull and deploring stile, prosecute these vnluckie accidentes, which not causelesse make me so gréeuously moane aad lament. But first (if miserable soules are heard) wretched woman as I am, bathed in my owne teares, I doo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore some heauenly deitie, (if any there be,) whose holy minde (moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with pitty of my distressed fare) to helpe my dolefull memory, and to directe my trembling hand in this present worke, and being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, to adde such force and vigour to them againe, that, what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishe and bitter gréefes I haue sustained, and doo yet féele in my tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mented minde, euen such the one recording the wordes and stratagēs, and the other (more willing then able to such an office) may fullie and wholy write them downe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>