<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentle READER.</title>
           <author>Garey, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102832_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01473</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11598</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102832</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentle READER.</title>
                 <author>Garey, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ientaculum iudicum: or, A breake-fast for the bench : prepared, presented, and preached in two sacred seruices, or sermons, the morning sacrifice before the two assises: at Thetford, at Norwich: 1619. Containing monitory meditations, to execute iustice and law-businesse wit a good conscience. By Samuel Garey, preacher of Gods word at Win-farthing in Norff</title>
                 <author>Garey, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Law (Lawe), Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Causon (Casson), Edmund</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 70 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the gentle READER.</head>
   <p>ANtiquity placed <hi>Mercury</hi> in their Temples among the Graces, meaning, that as <hi>Mercury</hi> (the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed God of Eloquence) and the three graces, the Ladies of Curtesie, were placed together; so Speech is desirous of friendly Eares, and Writers wish Curteous Readers.</p>
   <p>When men reade with a minde to carpe, then their throats are so narrow that nothing will downe; this seems too round, or too flat, too blunt, or too sharpe, one way awry. Many who keepe no warmth in their owne Chimney, will finde fault with their Neighbours fire: I say with <hi>Martial,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Carpere vel noli nostra, vel ede tua.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>What I preached to the Eare, I here present to the Eye, that one way or other it might get to the heart: wherein I feare the fortune of <hi>Seiramnes</hi> the Persian, who seeing many men wonder that he spake well, but nothing which he spake, euer practised, answered, That words were in his owne power, but Successe aboue his reach: So the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions here propounded, be good, and wholesome, the Successe I referre to God, who must giue increase.</p>
   <p>In publishing of which poore paines, I hunt not after worldly praise, or profit, the two Lackies of most mens labours: praise is but a vulgar breath, or ayre, fit to feed a Cameleon, my stomack can brooke no winde: and profit, many times they finde most, who preach or print least:</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Hos ego versiculos feci, tulit alter honores:</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Drones which creepe into the Hine, sucke away most of the honey, when the labouring Bees be starued: All I can say for my selfe is, I desire to doe good; Whereof if I
<pb facs="5"/>faile, yet my intent shall content my conscience: saying with the Romane Orator,</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Malim mihi facultatem, quàm voluntatem deesse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>So crauing thy curteous Acceptance of my good will, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuously acknowledging, that frequency in the Seruice of Preaching, depriues me of leisurable times to polish any thing for the Presse, or to make (as once one said) my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to smell of the Candle: If ought be amisse, impute it to the weakenesse of men: what herein is good, for thy good, giue glory vnto God, and to the word of his Grace, which is able to build thee further, &amp;c. I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thy Christian Well-willer</hi> Sa: Garey.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>