<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right honorable, Henry Earle of Pembrooke, Lord Herbert of Cardyffe, Marmyon, and S. Quynten, Lorde Praesident of the principality of Wales, and the Marches of the same, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and Lord Liuetenant of Wales, of the Marches, and of the counties of Wy and Sommerset.</title>
           <author>Fraunce, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102621_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01231</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11344</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102621</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right honorable, Henry Earle of Pembrooke, Lord Herbert of Cardyffe, Marmyon, and S. Quynten, Lorde Praesident of the principality of Wales, and the Marches of the same, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter, and Lord Liuetenant of Wales, of the Marches, and of the counties of Wy and Sommerset.</title>
                 <author>Fraunce, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lavviers logike : exemplifying the præcepts of logike by the practise of the common lawe, by Abraham Fraunce</title>
                 <author>Fraunce, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Newman, Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 85, 2, 87-151 leaves, 1 folded leaf of plates, table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right honorable, Henry Earle of <hi>Pembrooke, Lord Herbert of Cardyffe,</hi> Marmyon, and S. Quynten, Lorde Praesident of the principality of Wales, and the Marches of <hi>the same, Knight of the most noble order of</hi> the Garter, and Lord Liuetenant of Wales, of the Marches, and of the counties of Wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> and Sommerset.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>IF Lawes by reason framed were, and grounded on the same;</l>
      <l>If Logike also reason bee, and thereof had this name;</l>
      <l>I see no reason, why that Law and Logike should not bee</l>
      <l>The nearest and the dearest freends, and therfore best agree.</l>
      <l>As for the fonde conceyt of such which neuer knew them both,</l>
      <l>Better beleeue some mens bare worde, than their suspected oth.</l>
      <l>I say no more then what I saw, I saw that which I sought,</l>
      <l>I sought for Logike in our Law, and found it as I thought.</l>
      <l>If all that I haue sought and found your Honor doe content,</l>
      <l>(Let scribes and pety penmen talke) I thinck my time well spent,</l>
      <l>And labour herein well imployd: Acceptance is my meede,</l>
      <l>I craue no more, I haue no lesse, if you vouch safe to reede.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honors</hi> most vnfainedly affectionate Abraham Fraunce.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>