<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, AND TRULY NOBLE, PHILIP Earle of Pembrooke and Montgomery, Lord Chamberlaine of His Majesties Noble Family, &amp;c. Lord high Steward of the City of BRISTOLL.</title>
           <author>Palmer, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102339_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08873</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19155</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102339</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, AND TRULY NOBLE, PHILIP Earle of Pembrooke and Montgomery, Lord Chamberlaine of His Majesties Noble Family, &amp;c. Lord high Steward of the City of BRISTOLL.</title>
                 <author>Palmer, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Bristolls military garden : A sermon preached unto the worthy company of practisers in the military garden of the well governed citie of Bristoll. By Thomas Palmer, master of arts, and vicar of St. Thomas, and St. Mary Redcliffe in the same citie</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, AND TRULY NOBLE, PHILIP Earle of Pembrooke and Montgomery, Lord <hi>Chamberlaine of His Majesties Noble Family,</hi> &amp;c. Lord high Steward of the City <hi>of</hi> BRISTOLL.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Reverend Doctor of our Church did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly dedicate his expositions of this first Booke of <hi>Samuel</hi> unto that <hi>Julium Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Dr.</hi> Willet.</note> that Mirrour of Martiall Activitie, Prince <hi>Henry.</hi> To whom then can I bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter consecrate my explication of this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph, this small parcell of the same Booke than unto your Honour? unto whom the same Prince gave the deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Prize for your unparallell'd dexterity in the feates of Armes. As my discourse
<pb facs="3"/>is Martiall: so my Dedication doth dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover one qualitie of a Souldier, bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. In daring to kisse so Honorable a hand with so poore a Present. But my Particular service, and the generall obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of our City (whereof your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour hath the gratious Protection) have given the incouragement. Though this poore Souldier is prest for your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships service, yet (without your Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable passe) like one of the forlorne hope it shall dye in despaire, and bee buried in silence. If (like the Centurion) you shall bid him goe, Hee dares enter the List of a doubtfull Censure. His Dialect is (like the language of a Souldier) plaine and blunt. His weapon is the Sword of the Spirit. His posture is (like a Churchman) upon his knees: upon which your hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Orator doth daily pray. That the daies of your Honour may bee as the daies of Heaven, and the Glory of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Period of your daies. So praieth</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your most humbly devoted Servant, and unworthy Chaplaine, <hi>THOMAS PALMER.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>