<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE ADVERTISING DYVERS THINGES TO BE NOTED IN THE TREATISE FOLLOWING.</title>
           <author>Plummer, Timothy</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102251_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00912</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11019</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102251</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE ADVERTISING DYVERS THINGES TO BE NOTED IN THE TREATISE FOLLOWING.</title>
                 <author>Plummer, Timothy</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The second part of a treatise concerning policy, and religion : Wherein the necessity, fruite, and dignity of christian religion, in common welth, is euidently showed, with the absurdity of false religions, and the danger, and dammage, that ensueth thereof to all states; and by the way somme philosophical, moral, and politicall matters are treated ... finally it is clearely proued, that the catholique Roman religion only doth make a happy common welth. Written by Thomas Fitzherbert Esquyre, and Catholique priest</title>
                 <author>Fitzherbert, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Auroi (Ouroy), Pierre</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 463, 446-654, 685-697, 19 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE ADVERTISING DYVERS THINGES TO BE NOTED IN THE TREATISE FOLLOWING.</head>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <l>Sicilides Musae paulo maiora canamus,</l>
         <l>Non omnes arbusta iuuant, humiles{que} myricae.</l>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O song the pastoral poet, when he meant to tune his pype to a heygher note, that is to say, to passe from treating rural, and cuntry con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of sheppards, sheepe, goates, shrubs, busshes, hils, and dales, to sing and celebrat the prayses of <hi>Augustus Caesar,</hi> &amp; his flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing Empire, by the occasion of the birth of <hi>Saloninus</hi> sonne to <hi>Asinius Pollio</hi> cheefe fauorit of <hi>Augustus,</hi> to whome he applyed a prophesy of <hi>Sybilla Cumana,</hi> which in truth concerned the byrth of our Sauiour <hi>IESVS Christ</hi> and his most happy empyre, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer the soules of men.</p>
   <p>Therefore I being now to flye, (as I may say) a heygher pitch, then in my former Treatise, that is, to passe from handling so meane, and weake a subiect, as is the infirmity of mans wit, and humane pollicy grounded thereon, to treate of the necessity, frute, and dignity of religion in common welth, yea of that religion, and euerlasting empyre of <hi>Christ,</hi> whereof the prophetesse <hi>Sibilla</hi> spake in the prophesie aforesayde (an argument much more incomparably excelling the former, whereof I treated before, then the imperial maiesty, and power of <hi>Augustus,</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the poore and base quality of sheppeards, sheepe, busshes, hils, and dales (yea as much as heauen surpasseth earth, or rather all things nothing) I may with much more reason say, <hi>multò maiora canamus,</hi> and in steede
<pb facs="3"/> of the <hi>Sicilian Muses</hi> (whose helpe the poet implored) inuocat that holy, and deuyne spirit, which is the true light of harts, &amp; teacher of all truth, whome therefore I humbly beseech so to illuminat my vnderstanding, and guyde my pen, that I may worthily treate of so worthy &amp; hygh a su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iect, as is the transcendent woorthines and perfection of Christian religion.</p>
   <p>For although my intent is not to vnsould all the mysteries of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian faith, neyther yet to handle any part thereof further, then the same may someway concerne common welth, yet for as much as I ame to proue in this treatise, that the perfection, and felicity of common welth consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth in Christian religion, I cannot sufficiently performe the same, except I show the perfection, and incomprehensible excellency, effects, and fruits thereof, no more then if I should vndertake to treate of the woorthines &amp; felicity of man, and omit to speake of the excellency of the soule, and of the euerlasting beatitude, whereto he is ordayned, and wherein consisteth his last, and cheefe felicity.</p>
   <p>Therefore, whereas there are ouer many at this day, who haue such a prophane conceit of common welth, and pollicy, that they think matters of spirit, altogether impertinent thereto, and expect in a politicall discourse nothing els but rules, or instructions teaching cunning practyses, sleyghts, subtiltyes, shifts (or as I may tearme them tricks of state) yea coosenages, &amp; fraudulent deuyses, rather then prudent, and sound aduises, such being now the corruption generally growne in the world, that craft, and subtilty is held of many for prudence, the deepest dissimulation for the profoundest wisdome, and (if I may speake plainly without offence of modest eares) the fynest, and best cloked knauery for the wysest, and heyghest policy, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore I say to such, that if they could frame a common welth of a company of coggers, cooseners, and connicatchers, tending euery one to his owne particuler proffit, or pleasur, or yet of a congregation all of sensuall men, litle better then a heard of cattle, or beasts (I meane though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>udued with reasonable soules, yet lead, and gouerned altogether by sence) they shuld haue more reason to exclude from it, all matters not only of spirit, but also of vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, &amp; morall honesty; but if common welth be a ciuill society of men vnited with the communion of lawes, for a publyk, and common good, I say of men, that is to say reasonable creatures, hauing reasonable soules created by almighty god to his owne ymage, and for his owne seruice, yea ordayned to a supernatural end, that is, to eternal beatitude, to be obtained by spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb facs="3"/> meanes, to wit by religion, iustice, pietye, and the practise of all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue (all which I will make most euident in the ensuing discourse) nay if I euidently proue that the cheefe end, and felicity of the common welth it selfe, ys no other then the end, and happynes of euery particuler man in this lyfe, and that the same cannot otherwayse be atchiued, but by the perfect practise of christian religion, they cannot thinke it strange, or impertinent to the subiect which I handle, if I doe now and then, intermix discourses of true christian perfection, and such things as belong thereto; For seeing no common welth can be perfect without perfect vertue, nor any perfection of vertue be had without Christian perfection, nor the same be any where found but in Christian religion, as I will make most manifest heereafter, I cannot delineat a true, ciuil, &amp; political man, that is to say a perfect member of a christian common welth, except I descrybe a perfect christian, neither yet performe that, except I also show what is christian perfection; nor that without the explication of many heygh misteries, and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ellencies of christian religion.</p>
   <p>And for as much as I cannot accomplish all this with the benefit that I wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h to my reader, except I also lay doune the meanes how to attayne to christian perfection, thereby to arriue to a perfect vnion with god (which is the proper effect of true religion, and the only true felicity of man, and common welth) therefore I meane also to enterlace many spiritual aduises, and rules tending to the true vse, &amp; practise of christian religion, lest otherwayse I may be lyke to one that should tell a sick man of a souueraigne medicin for his dissease, and conceale from him the vse of it; so that my desyre, and intention, yea my obligation being (my subiect considered) not so much to show, or describe, as to make a perfect member of christian common welth, &amp; to supply the defects of humane pollicy (whereof I trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in my fyrst part) with the perfection of christian religion (which is the subiect of this my second part) I hope no man can iustly mislike that I doe oft inculeat matters of spirit, and especially the office, and duty of a true christian man, and touch also now and then, somme poynts of the heyghest christian perfection. And whereas I shall also haue occasion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late by the way, somme admirable, miraculous, &amp; stupendious effects of gods grace in holly men, I dout not but the pious, and well disposed reader, will receiue greate edification thereby, noting, and admiring therein, not only the eminent dignity, and excellency of christian religion, but also the
<pb facs="4"/> infinit power, wisdome, and bounty of almighty god towards his seruants</p>
   <p>And as for such incredulous miscreants, as the Apostle S. <hi>Iudas</hi> tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>animales spiritum non habentes,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 1.</note>
      <hi>men altogether sensual, hauing no spirit,</hi> who therefore doe not vnderstand (saith S. <hi>Paul,) ea quae sūt spiritus Dei, those things vvhich are of the spirit of god,</hi> beleeuing no more of good woorks then they see with theyr eyes,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> or touch with their hands, or can comprehend within their weake, idle, and addle heads, such I say, I remit partly to that which I haue discoursed in my first part against <hi>Atheists,</hi> and partly to the experience of gods most admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble woorke in this kind, which I shall haue occasion to demonstrat in this my second part, drawing the same from the fountayne of the holly scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, according to the interpretation of the Catholyke church, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryuing it to these our dayes, by the examples and testimony of gods saints in all tymes, and ages.</p>
   <p>And if neuertheles they persist obstinat in their incredulity, and think with some ridiculous, and blasphemous iest, (as commonly they are wont) to elude such a sacred authority of experience both ancient, and moderne, I leaue them with sorrow, and pitty of their case, to the terrible sentence of S: <hi>Peter</hi> pronounced of such as they. <hi>Hivelut pecora irrationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia &amp;c. these being lyke to vnreasonable beasts,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>naturally ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the snare, and destruction, blaspheming in those things vvhich they knovv not, shall perish in their ovvne corruption, receiuing the revvard of iniustice &amp;c.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Furthermore for as much as the differēce of opiniōs in matters of religiō at this tyme, requyreth some discussion of the truth, that thereby it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare who they are that truely professe the christiā religion, I do therefore think good to treate of diuers poynts in controuersy betwyxt the Roman Catholyks, &amp; their aduersaries, thereby to show the preiudice that groweth to state by false religions, exemplifying the same especially in <hi>Luthera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme,</hi> and <hi>Caluinisme,</hi> because those sects eyther doe comprehend, or haue engendred all other, and are more generally embraced then any of the rest.</p>
   <p>And therefore whereas I may perhaps be censured by some as ouersharpe, and vehement sometymes in the reprehension of <hi>Lutherans,</hi> &amp; <hi>Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists,</hi> and their doctrin, (out of the abundance of my zeale to the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke saith) whereby I may also seeme to cast some aspersion of iniury (as
<pb facs="4"/> perhaps it may be interpreted) vppon my owne cuntrymen, I meane <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> I wish them to vnderstand, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I hope to vse such due moderation towards <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and <hi>Caluinists,</hi> as not to reproue, and taxe them further then they shall iustly deserue, yet I think I may be the bolder with them, as iust occasion shall be offred, because I persuade my selfe that no <hi>Protestant,</hi> nor <hi>Puritan</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> can iustly take him selfe to be iniured thereby, seeing that there is none of them (for ought I know, or can imagin) that is formally eyther a <hi>Lutheran,</hi> or a <hi>Caluinist,</hi> I meane that holdeth, and professeth the doctrin of <hi>Luther,</hi> or <hi>Caluin,</hi> otherways then with such ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itions and substractions, as euery mans priuat spirit doth suggest, and therefore whatsoeuer I shall say of <hi>Luther,</hi> or <hi>Caluin,</hi> or any of theyr progeny, I would not haue it further to be extended then I meane it, which is only to those <hi>Archsectaries</hi> and such others as are content to be held, and styled for their disciples, I meane to be called <hi>Luthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ans,</hi> or <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinists.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And as for my louing Cuntrimen who reiect some part of their doctrin, and admit the rest, I would wish them, heere by the way of aduise well to consider, what assurance they haue more for that which they take, then for that which they leaue, since they (I meane <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi>) assured themselues no lesse of the one, then of the other, pretending the warrant of holly scriptures, and the assistance of gods holly spirit equally for both; So that if they were deceiued in part, they might aswell be deceiued in the whole, especially seeing that neyther of them had any other ground of his new doctrin, but only his owne priuat sence, and vnderstanding of scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, for yf they had had the assistance of gods spirit therein they, could nether of them haue erred in any part thereof, and much lesse haue dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the one from the other, so much as they did, being so opposit, &amp; cōtrary, (euen in some of the morst important, and essential poynts of faith) that they detested, &amp; condemned one an other for damnable heretykes, as their followers doe vntill this day; whereby it is euident, that at least the one of them was mightiely deceiued, and therefore had not the spirit of god, yea &amp; that the other also buylding vpon no better ground then his companion, but vpon the selfe same (I meane his owne presumption to vnderstand the scriptures aright) had no more assurance of the holl ghosts assistance then be, and therefore might erre as dangerously, and absurdly as he.</p>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <p>And if any man grounding himselfe also vpon the same foundation, follow the one more then the other, and yet neuertheles doth approue him in part, and reproue him in the rest, he is to consider, that he may with reason feare, lest he him selfe be as much beguyled in that which he acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pteth, as his maister was in that which he reiecteth, seeing he hath no more assurance for the one part, then for the other; his owne, or his may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters priuat sence of scripture, beeing the ground of both; So that we see all is buylt heere, vpon vncertainety, &amp; that no man can, by this meanes, haue any ground or assurance of his faith, whereby we may also learne what extreame folly, and danger it is for any man, to leaue the infallible iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the church (which is the spouse of <hi>Christ,</hi> and guyded by his holly spirit) to follow his owne, or any mans priuat sence in the exposition of scripture, which can proceede of nothing els but singularity, temerity, presumption, and pryde, the mother of heresy, and as I may say, the very precipice whereby infinit numbers haue fallen headlong into the pit of eternal perdition; whereof I neede not to say more heere, because I shall touch it now, and then in the ensuing discourse.</p>
   <p>It resteth now good reader, that I aduertise thee of some alteration of my desygnement, since I wrote my first part. For, although I was then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to compact my whole conceit into two volumes, or parts, yet there hath since occurred vnto me such abundance of matter, necessary, parly for thy proffit, and partly for thy delectation, that I ame now resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to adde a thyrd part. And seeing that the subiect of the whole, beeing <hi>Pollicy, &amp; Religiō,</hi> my first part treated principally of <hi>Pollicy,</hi> I meane that this second part shall treate most of <hi>Religion,</hi> &amp; the thyrd indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently of both; wherein I also hope fully to discharge my obligation tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching some particuler poynts promised in my first part, which I shall not haue oportunity to performe in this, as also to consummat the whole sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of my first proiect, whereof there will remayne much to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished, according to this my latter desygne.</p>
   <p>So that thou seest, good reader, it falleth out with me, as it doth with buylders, who seeldome content themselues with their first plot, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly spend both longer tyme, and much more money, then at the first they determined. And although I cānot presume duly to obserue the rules, and precepts of Architecture in the fabrike of this my religious pallace (if so I may tearme a woork treating of Religion) yet I will not be careles of
<pb facs="5"/> that which most importeth, and best correspondeth to the nature of such a bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lding; &amp; therefore I will not only furnish it with implements of pious lessons, and instructions of greate edifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ation, but also erect and buyld therein an oratory, or chappel for christian contemplation; and in the very por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h or entry thereof, represent vnto thee a true pourtrait of the natural contemplation of the philosophers; And though I dout not, but thou wilt fynd therein excellent matter, and perhaps woonder to see such hygh and misti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>al doctrin in pagans and heathens, who could reach no further, then nature, and the light of reason could lead them, yet I do not recommend it vnto thee for any other purpose, then to serue for a fyle to set foorth our Christian contemplation, that is, to make thee the better see, and vnderstand the excellent perfection thereof.</p>
   <p>Yf therefore it may please thee sometymes to retyre thy selfe into this contemplatiue chappel, and there with due, and serious meditation to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templat not so much the forme of the buylding, (which by the smale skill of the Architect, may fayle in proportion) as the matter, and furniture thereof, borowed from the holly scriptures, and most comtemplatiue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I dout not but thou shalt receiue such spiritual benefit, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment thereby, that thou wilt say, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> sayd vpon the mount. <hi>Bonum est nos hic esse,</hi> or with the royal prophet.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 17. <hi>Psal.</hi> 83.</note>
      <hi>Quam dilecta ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacula tua domine virtutum, concupiscit &amp; deficit anima mea in atria Domini.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And for as much as in the buylding of a Palace, special care is to be had to make it fayre, and beautifull to the eye, and to grace it with variety of pictures, images, and pourtraicts of dyuers sorts, I will be carefull also to geeue thee some satisfaction in that behalfe; and therefore doe meane to paynt, and adorne this my religious buylding, with greate diuersity of moral, and political doctrin, and with store of histories, as well profane, as Ecclesiasticall, as also with the true and liuely pourtraits of the most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and woorthy men that haue florished in gods church since our sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours tyme, proposing to thy view theyr vertuous, and heroical acts, in the contempt and triumphant conquest of the world, and themselues, for the loue of god; to the end that framing thy lyfe after the model of theyr example, thou mayst arriue to some degree, at least, of true christian perfection.</p>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <p>Moreouer, whereas there is no palace so beautifull, or magnificent that hath not dyuers retraicts, channels, sinks, and other base, and homely pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (which though they be lothsome of theyr owne nature, yet are neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary for the whole buylding) thou shalt also fynd in this my religious pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace matters of that quality, I meane the absurd, beastly, and impious opinions, and liues of <hi>Pagans, Mahometans, Ievves, Macchiauil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, Polityks,</hi> &amp; <hi>Heretyks</hi> representing vnto thee the horrour of false religion, which may serue, not only to moue thee to the detestation thereof, but also to breede in thee a greater estimation, loue, and honour of true religion.</p>
   <p>Finally, as nothing more importeth in buylding, then to lay a sure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and to make the walles substancial, and able to resist the for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, as well of wynd, and wether, as of enemies, if neede requyre, so will I haue a special care to found all this my buylding, vpon the firme, and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueable rock of truth, and to rayse strong walls of pregnant arguments, &amp; reasons drawne from nature it selfe, fortifying the same with the euident testimonies of holly scriptures, and ancient fathers, and with many old &amp; moderne examples; And therefore seeing I haue benne content, good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for my part to be at the charges, and paynes, not only to buyld this pallace, and to make it commodious for thee, but also to present it vnto thee for thy vse and habitation, I hope thou wilt not vse it as an Inne, for a bayte, or a nights lodging, (that is, only take a superficial view of it) but make thy abode in it at least for some tyme; I meane read, and ruminat the whole woork with dilligence, and after practise that which thou shalt fynd therein fit for thy vse. For so shalt thou, of this my laboure reape the benefyte, I the comefort, and almighty God the glory, to whose grace, and holly protection I recommend thee.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thy hartie well willer.</hi> Thomas Fitzherbert.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>