<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Augustine Marlorate to the christian Reader wissheth health and peace through Iesus Christe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102682_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06990</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17410</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102682</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Augustine Marlorate to the christian Reader wissheth health and peace through Iesus Christe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of the sin against the holy ghost : made by M. Augustine Marlorate. Translated out of French to the great consolation of all such as repent them of their sinnes, and to the astonying of of [sic] those that mock and despise the gospell of our Lord Jesus Christe</title>
                 <author>Marlorat, Augustin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Harrison, Luke (Lucas)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Augustine Marlorate to</hi> the christian Reader wissheth health and peace through Iesus Christe.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Est any should think</hi> that in this small Treatise, I (like an euill Attorney) would go about to defend the cause of suche, as mocking God, do dally with the Gospel thincking to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it or leaue it as oft as they list, as if of them selues &amp; at their ovvne choise they might make atonement vvith the sonne of God, vvhom they giue ouer to opprobry: I beseeche you in the name of our Lord Iesus patiētly to reed ouer this Treatise to the end.</p>
   <p>So dooing I hope ye vvil iudge that mine intent heerby is onely to bring such again into the right vvay of sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiō, as hetherto haue not so vvel pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fited in the knovvledge of the Gospel that inestimable treasure as the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and great benefit thereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth: to th'end that all such as shall heerafter hear the sound of the voice of Iesus Christe in his Churche, may knovve that he is redy to iudge suche as resist &amp; dispise his vvord, but cheef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="3"/>those that in this great light of the Gospel<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Ephe.</hi>
4.29</note> gree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e the holy spirit of God by vvhome the faithfull are sealed for the day of their redemption.</p>
   <p>Forasmuch then as the vvord of God is directed to diuers maner of people, and is not receiued of all vvith one ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner affection, as appeereth in the simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of the seed,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.19.</note> this Treatise may serue to bothe, that the good (being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired with the holy ghost) may be assu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red of the doctrin vvhich they folow and may be strengthned more &amp; more in the Lord, and in the povver of his might,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Galla.</hi> 1.8.</note> couragiously to reiect all spirits (yea vvere it an angel of Heauen) that should teach any other doctrin for the saluation of men then that vvhiche is contained in the holy gospel: and that such other as this holy and sacred do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin hath not yet takē so deep root in, may ernestly bee moued to consider at the lēgth vvherin the suretie of their saluation cōsisteth,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.14</note> that they frō hence foorth be no more like children waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring &amp; caried about with euery winde of doctrin, by the deceit of men &amp; by craftines, whereby they lye in waite to deceiue: But vvholly may rest on
<pb facs="3"/>Christe and submit them selues to him vvhich died &amp; is risen again for them:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom</hi> 14.9.</note> and also to the end that they vvhiche through infirmitie, or for fear of men, or losse of their goods &amp; honors haue shut vp and hidden the secret of faith, may vvake out of their drousy forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes &amp; heerafter open their mouthes to confesse to saluation before all men that vvhich fait harted fear hath made them so long to hide &amp; dissemble,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10.</note> least preferring the glory of men before the glory of God, they in th'end feel the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffect &amp; executiō of this horrible threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vvhich is pronoūced on thē that tempt Iesus Christ before men Finally this treatise tendeth to this end that all excuses set apart,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.33. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30. <hi>Mal.</hi>
4.6.</note> eche mā may seek for his saluation vvith fear &amp; trembling, se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing that God hauing so lōg forborn in time of ignorāce, vvilleth novv al men in all places to repent, lest he come and strike the earth to destruction.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <bibl>Ezech. <hi>18.27.</hi>
         </bibl>
         <p>VVhen the wicked turneth away from his wickednes that he hath committed &amp; doth that which is lawfull and right hee shall saue his soule aliue.</p>
      </q>
      <q>
         <bibl>Hebru. <hi>4.16.</hi>
         </bibl>
         <p>Let vs go boldely vnto the throne of grace that we may receiue mercy and finde grace in time of need.</p>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>