<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Londinens, Joan.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102862_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07935</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18305</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102862</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Londinens, Joan.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Bishop of London his legacy. Or certaine motiues of D. King, late Bishop of London, for his change of religion, and dying in the Catholike, and Roman Church : VVith a conclusion to his bretheren, the LL. Bishops of England</title>
                 <author>Musket, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>iiij leaves, v-xvj, 24, 33-174 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="v" facs="5"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Christian Reader (whether Catholyke or Protestant) heere before my Death I bequeath to thee (as my <hi>Legacy</hi>) these few leaues (though the weake and femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyne Issue of my sicke and distempered Age) contayning (no doubt, with ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zement to thy selfe) certaine grounds of my alienation of mynd frō the Protestāts Religion. True it is, that for some years past (though I was far otherwyse affected, when I did wryte my Lectures vpon <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi>)
<pb n="vj" facs="6"/>I haue preached and taught the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant fayth, with a certaine hesitation &amp; doubtfulnes of Iudgment, in regard of some tyme more seriously spent, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in those kynd of studyes, in the which (to speake in the <hi>VVisemans</hi>
      <note n="(a)" place="margin">Eccles. cap. <hi>52.</hi>
      </note>) dialect): <hi>Modicum laboraui, sed inueni mihi magnam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiem.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Many are the Reasons warranting this my change, much trauelled in, euen by my owne paynes and disquisition (for I graunt, I scorned to looke into these weighty matters, with other mens eyes:) yet by reason of the present weake state of my languishing Body, I haue selected these few particular Motiues ensuing, hereafter in due tyme to be presented to the eye of the World. Touching which I foresee, I shall fynd different (and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps some calumnious) Censures.</p>
   <p>For I probably presage, that since it wil be interpreted iniurious to the present State, as if<note n="(b)" place="margin">Tert. lib. aduers. Gentes.</note>
      <hi>non possumus &amp; Romani esse, &amp; hostes non esse;</hi> and displeasing to his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty</hi> (whom in my soule I do affect with
<pb n="vij" facs="6"/>all true Allegeance, do acknowledge with all Gratefulnes his many Honourable &amp; vndeseruing Fauours, and for whose true Happines I do, and daily wil pray, as long as this enfeebled flesh of myne shall enioy this ayre (when it shalbe reported, that the <hi>Bishop of London</hi> dyed a <hi>Romanist</hi> in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and hath not beene ashamed, euen with his owne penne, to pull in those Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of that fayth, which himself afore had aduāced; that therefore it must be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulged, either he dyed not in that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or at least that these written <hi>Motiues</hi> are but masked vnder his Name, as being framed by some Catholike Pryest, for the greater defaming of the Protestāts Ghos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</p>
   <p>No, No. By Gods infinite grace, I am resoued (notwithstanding all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary assaults whatsoeuer) to dy a menber of the Catholyke, or (as we tearme it) Papist Church: <hi>Inueni</hi>
      <note n="(c)" place="margin">
         <hi>Cantie,</hi> 8.</note>
      <hi>quem diligit anima mea, tenui eum, nec dimittam.</hi> And as an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest giuen to this my designe, I haue heere written this small Treatise, which
<pb n="viij" facs="7"/>in my lyfe tyme is deliuered to a friend. It is myne, and penned by my self, and to me the dearest and choisest Chyld, that euer the wombe of my brayne brought forth; howsoeuer it is likely that Orphan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke it shalbe cast out, and be betram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled vpon with all ensuing serpentine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity.</p>
   <p>I haue purposely enleuened the most passages thereof, with the testimonyes of diuers Protestant Wryters and Doctours; and this for two respects. One, because my selfe being heeretofore a Protestant Doctour, and placed in that eminency of seate wherin I am, I thought it the more sutable, to produce authorityes of men of my owne former Religion, Rancke, and Profession. The other for breuity; seeing the acknowledgments of Protestants in poynts controuerted, preuent, that we need not to recurre (through a long and wearisome enquiry) to Scriptures, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or Historyes, for the determining of the said Poynts: and I remember well, that dull and tedious reading, soone tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="ix" facs="7"/>the edge of fastidious and curious Witts.</p>
   <p>The truth is heere set downe plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without Affectation of pleasing Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, or (to vse the Apostles phrase) <hi>the perswasible</hi>
      <note n="(d)" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>words of humane wisdome,</hi> for at this tyme, and vpon this subiect, I little pryze a fluent, smooth, and oyled tongue.</p>
   <p>If it be demanded, why now (and not before) I do wryte this <hi>Apology?</hi> Let such men know, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lis the feare of Hell, and losse of Heauen (the only two landing-places of the Soule, after her departure from hence, for all Eternity that hath forced me heerto. Alas, my poore langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing body euery day decaying, and assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring itself, that many moneths (for I look not for yeares) it cannot hould out, som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons me now to display the very secrets of my soule, for the sauing of my soule; and not to draw any veyle betweene me, and my most inward Thoughts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions.</p>
   <p>I haue dissembled my Religion for some few yeares (so haue Wyfe, Children,
<pb n="x" facs="8"/>&amp; wordly Honours enthralled my Soule:) sweet <hi>Iesus</hi> forgiue me. I haue persecuted the Church of Christ for many yeares. O blessed Apostle <hi>S. Paul!</hi> thou, who once wast a Persecutour, but after a planter of Gods Church, intercede for me. But, O the torment of my afflicted Consciēce I haue had my hand (would to God, both hand and arme, for the preuenting of such a mischeife, had then beene cut off) in sheeding of innocent Bloud: And is it not high tyme for me, to cast vp these accounts, and to vse an introuersion vpon my owne Actions?</p>
   <p>O happy <hi>Almond,</hi> who hee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e vpon earth didst maske thy self vnder the name of <hi>Mollineux!</hi> In thy bloud, eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> in thy bloud did I wash my hands. It was I, that did further thy death: be thou O blessed Saint, who now seest and hearest me: (<hi>Quid</hi>
      <note n="(e)" place="margin">Creg. l. <hi>4.</hi> dial.</note>
      <hi>non videt, qui videntem omnia videt?</hi>) be thou, I say, out of thy <hi>Seraphicall</hi> Charity, as propitious to pray for remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of that crying-Sinne, as I am ready to acknowledge the Sinne. And let thy
<pb n="xj" facs="8"/>bloud (guilty of no other treason, then in not being a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>raytour to <hi>Christ</hi> and his Church) not resemble the bloud of<note n="(f)" place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>es. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Abel</hi> which cryed for reuenge against his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but rather the bloud of <hi>Christ</hi> which prayed<note n="(g)" place="margin">Luc. c. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note> for pardon of his Crucifiers.</p>
   <p>Well then; the state of my former lyfe, and my present weaknes being thus; haue I not iust reason to say with the Spouse<note n="(h)" place="margin">Cant. <hi>4.</hi>
      </note>: <hi>Vadam admontem mirrhae, &amp; col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem thuris</hi> (where a man by a spirituall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibilatiō of himself, enioyeth a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect being,) That is, I will spend the short remnant of my lyfe, in Pennance, and Prayer. Let my future Aduersaries spit our their Venome neuer so much in their contumelious Scripts against me. I care not, I feare not, I am resolued, for my owne good, to breake with flesh &amp; bloud, since shortly I am to leaue all flesh and bloud. I am within the iawes of death, &amp; all that I expect, is to saue my soule. And poore <hi>Doctour King</hi> dying <hi>Catholike,</hi> is not ashamed to acknowledge the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions of <hi>Doctour King,</hi> liuing <hi>Protestant.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb n="xij" facs="9"/>Therefore O most mercifull Lord, (who a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t God of God, and Man for Man) who hast sayd to a sinnefull soule: Tu<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>fornicata es cum multis amatoribus; tamen reier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere admo, &amp; ego re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>piam te;</hi> doe not repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate this poore soule of myne, which hath committed spiritual fornication with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Preferments, and other such glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Miseryes. Thou, who in thy holy Writ, hast left recorded. <hi>Quomo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o</hi>
      <note n="(k)" place="margin">Psal. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>02.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur Pater filiorum, misertus est Dominus ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentibus s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪</hi> Be hould heer thy <hi>Prodigall son,</hi> prostrating my selfe at the feet of thee my heauenly Father, humbly crauing pardon for my mispent substance and partrimony, Finally; thou, who thus assurest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Nolo</hi>
      <note n="(l)" place="margin">Fzech. cap. <hi>18.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>mortem morientis, conuertimini &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite:</hi> Looke vpon me, who now halfe dead in body, and heeretofore wholy dead in Soule, euen loathing the vpbrayding re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of my former courses, do cast my selfe betweene thy armes, to receaue a new spiritual life.</p>
   <p>Sweet Iesus, who by my creation gaue me a Being, by my Redemption a Well-being,
<pb n="xiij" facs="9"/>who suffered Deati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to preuent death, and whose wound care our wouds (<hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>
      <note n="(m)" place="margin">Isa. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>us sanatcsimi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>) vouc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e to sanctify me with thy soule; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ate my intellectuall powers with thy bloud; and to wash away all their ordure &amp; filth, with the water of thy pierced side; that so, I poore, despicable, and miserable man, seeing all my sinnes afore drowned in the gulfe of thy inexhausted Mercy, may in the end enter into thy promised (and my hoped for) <hi>Canaan.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Ioan. Londinens.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>