<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT concerning the former Catalogue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102114_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00794</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10912</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102114</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT concerning the former Catalogue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A catalogue of diuers visible professors of the Catholike faith : Which sheweth, that the Roman Church hath byn (as the true Church must be) continually visible, in all ages since Christ. Taken out of the appendix to the Reply of A.D. vnto M. Ant. Wotton, and M. Ioh. Whit ministers</title>
                 <author>Fisher, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>15, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="notice">
   <pb facs="17"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT concerning the former Catalogue.</head>
   <p>I Would haue thee aduertised (<hi>Gentle Reader</hi>) that in this Catalogue, I haue set downe the Names of all the chiefe Pastours, as being the principall members of the visible Militant Church, with obseruation of the yeare or time, and such order of succession, as I could find in those Authors, which I had at hand.</p>
   <p>Likewise I haue set downe, the names of some few other Professours, liuing in, or neere those seuerall ages, in which I haue placed them: but in this I haue not byn so curious, either to name all which are knowne, or which my selfe know to haue bene; or to set downe any precise yeare, or orderly succession of their being; but haue contented my self to name only a few in euery age, and this without specifying the particuler yeare, in which they flourished, or obseruing any exact order, in which they succeeded one another.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, I haue set downe some princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Councells, or Assemblies of the Pastors,
<pb facs="17"/>
and Doctours of the Church, leauing out many others, which I might haue set downe. The reason why on the one side, I haue set downe these particulers, is, that it may eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare, that the Catholike Roman Church hath bene continually Visible, in euery Age, as the true Church must, and ought to be.</p>
   <p>On the other side, the reason why I haue omitted so many other particulers, is, partly that I may not be too tedious to my Reader; and partly that I may not seeme to exact vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable paynes to be taken by our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saryes, when a like Catalogue shal be required of thē, of the names of like visible Professours of their Protestāt Church &amp; beliefe through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out euery age: which whiles they do not (as indeed they cannot) I may boldly say with old <hi>Irenaeus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iren. l. 1. c. 3.</note>
   </p>
   <q>
      <p>That by only bringing forth that Tradition and Religion, which the greatest, and most ancient, and to all men manifest, I say, <hi>the Church of Rome,</hi> founded and erected by the two most glorious Apostles <hi>S. Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Paul,</hi> receiued of them, and by succession of Bishops, hath brought vnto our time; we do counfound all those, which howsoeuer, either by vaine pleasing of themselues, or vaine glory, or by blindnes and peruerse iudgment, do make erroneous decoctions.</p>
   </q>
   <p>And this I may the better vrge, because
<pb facs="18"/>
(<hi>as the same</hi> Irenaeus <hi>affirmeth</hi>)</p>
   <q>
      <p> there is in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church a more powerfull principality, by reason wherof, it is necessary for euery Church, that is, for all Christians through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole world, to haue recourse vnto it &amp;c.</p>
   </q>
   <p> If any be desyrous to see more of this matter, let him peruse the <hi>Reply</hi> it selfe (out of which this Catalogue is taken) and the <hi>Treatise of Faith,</hi> newly set forth by the same Author.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="18"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>