<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The answere of Mariamastix.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102869_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07964</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18331</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102869</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The answere of Mariamastix.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Maria triumphans : Being a discourse, wherein (by way of dialogue) the B. Virgin Mary Mother of God, is defended, and vindicated, from all such dishonours and indignities, with which the precisians of these our dayes, are accustomed vniustly to charge her</title>
                 <author>N. N.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 3-335, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="reply">
   <pb n="15" facs="8"/>
   <head>The answere of <hi>Mariamastix.</hi>
   </head>
   <head type="sub">To <hi>Mariadulus</hi> (imprisoned in Body, but more in Soule) the liberty of the Ghospell.</head>
   <p>I Haue this day <hi>(Mariadulus)</hi> receaued your daring Letter. I did much wonder to see a <hi>Babilonian</hi> to haue the forehead to challenge an <hi>Israelite</hi> to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute; I meane, a Popish supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Priest, to prouoke thereto a Minister, and Preacher of the Word of the Lord. What I haue deliuered the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> day in my ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at the <hi>Crosse,</hi> the same I am ready to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ortify against any supercilious and proud Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist, with the testimonies of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Writ; in which I hope so to supererogate (to speake in your
<pb n="16" facs="9"/>owne Brethrens <hi>Dialect</hi>) and abound, as that I will euen vye sentences of Scripture, with your poore sentences, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities drawne from your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Fathers of former tymes. And I will make it as illustrious and cleere, as the Sunne, that your superstitious deuotions &amp; Prayers exhibited to <hi>Mary,</hi> are but your spirituall <hi>Idolothyta,</hi> sacrifized to your false <hi>Goddesse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Therefore to morrow expect me infallibly at your lodging, whither I will bring certaine of the faithfull Professours to be witnesses of your ouerthrow: so assured I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> come off Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious. In the meane tyme Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours in the Lord,</hi> Mariamastix.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>