<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR THOMAS Sackeuill Knight, of the most noble order of the Garter, Baron of Buckhurst, Lord high Treasurer of England, one of her Maiesties most honorable Priuie Counsell, Chauncellour of the Vniuer∣sitie of Oxford. The Epistle Dedicatorie.</title>
           <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102772_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01289</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11412</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102772</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR THOMAS Sackeuill Knight, of the most noble order of the Garter, Baron of Buckhurst, Lord high Treasurer of England, one of her Maiesties most honorable Priuie Counsell, Chauncellour of the Vniuer∣sitie of Oxford. The Epistle Dedicatorie.</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An historicall collection of the continvall factions, tvmvlts, and massacres of the Romans and Italians : during the space of one hundred and twentie yeares next before the peaceable empire of Augustus Cæsar. Selected and deriued out of the best writers and reporters of these accidents, and reduced into the forme of one entire historie, handled in three bookes. Beginning where the historie of T. Livivs doth end, and ending where Cornelivs Tacitvs doth begin</title>
                 <author>Fulbeck, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ponsonby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 20, that is 209, 7 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR THOMAS Sackeuill Knight, of the most noble order of the Garter, Baron of Buckhurst, Lord high Treasurer <hi>of England, one of her Maiesties most honorable</hi> Priuie Counsell, Chauncellour of the <hi>Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of Oxford. The Epistle</hi> Dedicatorie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Honorable, I hope your Lordship will pardon my feare transformed into boldnesse, who hauing vowed by good right vnto your Honor excellently deseruing of the more polite learning, and milder sciences, this small history, and so much fearing or rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerencing your censure, that I did hold it better to smo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it with silence, then to endow it with light, sith your Honour hath trauersed such an infinite sea of histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, when as I do but offer certaine shallow riuelettes and slender parcels of an historie: yet now notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as if all were well accomplished, I presume to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it into your Lordships hands. Therefore, that it may appeare clearely and euidently to your Lordship, what cause did especiallie mooue me to entertaine this deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,
<pb facs="3"/>
I will by your Honours fauour, in few words, as becommeth me, explane and vnfold the secret sense of my minde. The fortunes of noblemen, a man adorned with nobilitie: the state and forme of politike affaires, some eye of a common weale: the aspiring Icarian Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, he, whose authoritie is effectuall for the depres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the Popish Phaetons, is onely fit to censure and with iudiciall stile to note. And what did perswade me to this labour, being destinated to another profession, and euen then champing vpon the vnpleasant barke of the studie of the Law, which might easilie procure a distast of more delightfull learning, I do not purpose to conceale. Plutarch in that part or region of his worke, which is entitled Lucullus (for his whole volume doth resemble the hugenesse of the world) hath reported, and imparted to posteritie, that Lucullus, Hortensius, and Sisenna be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing famous for skill in Law, did by couenant determine to write according to lot the historie of that time. To Lucullus was allotted the description of the Marsian warre, who content with this taske, did with great commendation finish it: and he being a worthie Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, did in the Greeke language display the notable conquestes of the Romanes: which thing hauing recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and digested in my minde, I found by infallible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>experience, that one studious of Law might afford some leasurable time to the diuulging of an historie. For I do not despaire to follow these Romanes, though I do not aspire to their exquisite and industrious perfection: for that were to climbe aboue the climates: but to imitate any man, is euery mans talent. But this slender gift, of paper and small accompt (I would it were worthie of your
<pb facs="3"/>
Honour, your birth, your place) yet flowing from that minde, of which it was conceiued, that is to true nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie most addicted, take (most Honorable Lord) in good worth and aboue my desert or expectation, and not onely with looking, but with liking vouchsafe it. The Lord God support your Honour with vnchaungeable safetie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors most humble to commaund. WILLIAM FVLBECKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>