<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right reuerend Father in God
Iohn, Bishoppe of London, Thomas Delone,
wisheth increase of grace, and continuall happi∣nesse,
both of body and soule.</title>
           <author>Deloney, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102953_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01567</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11693</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102953</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right reuerend Father in God
Iohn, Bishoppe of London, Thomas Delone,
wisheth increase of grace, and continuall happi∣nesse,
both of body and soule.</title>
                 <author>Deloney, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration made by the Archbishop of Collen, vpon the deede of his mariage, sent to the states of his archbishoprike : VVith the letter of Pope Gregorie the. 13 against the celebration of the same mariage, and the Bishops aunswer therevnto. According to the coppie imprinted at Collen. 1583</title>
                 <author>Gebhard, Truchsess von Waldburg, Archbishop, Elector of Cologne</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the right reuerend Father in God
Iohn, Bishoppe of London, Thomas Delone,
wisheth increase of grace, and continuall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
both of body and soule.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowne to the</hi>
learned, nor of the wise forgotten,
(right reuerend Father) in what
miserable seruitude, intollerable
tormentes, heauines of heart, and
griefe of conscience, the godlie
hath from time to time continued vnder the tyranny
of superstitious Popes and Prelates of Rome, whose
intollerable pride is of the Lord detested, and of all
christian people abhorred, through whose hipocrisie
the world hath been so long deceaued &amp; many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand
soules drawne frō the truth, to the abhominable
seruice of idolatry, forsaking the lawes and cōmaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements
of God, to followe the vanities &amp; traditions
of men. Neuerthelesse, they are not ashamed most
impudently to challenge to themselues the name and
title of Catholiques and the seruants of Christ, &amp; yet
treadeth his word vnder feete, despising his holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances
and institutions, and as it were in despite of
his glory, follow the works of their owne imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
But after the world had of long time beene
blinded, by the notable dissimulation of this decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
church▪ the Lord of his mercy and loue, sending
the light of his holy worde, for the reliefe of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
flocke plainly discouered their hipocrisie, and
their filthines to all flesh. Wherby it is come to passe
that many worthy personages, lately liuing in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
and ignorance, is now turned to the trueth, with
most earnest repentance of their former life. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
the rest, through the great mercy and grace of
<pb facs="3"/>
God, this worthy Prince, &amp; bishop of Collen, Gheb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,
whose hart being opened, and his eyes cleared,
hath most effectually showne the fruites of his vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
repentance, and hauing made declaration therof
throughout his dominions and iurisdictions, hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolished
the abhominable masse, and in steed thereof
planted the euerlasting &amp; glorious Gospel of Christ,
to the great comfort of many grieued and wounded
cōsciences. Which when the Pope perceiued, &amp; knew
with great flattery and adulation, he sought to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw
him frō this most godly &amp; christian enterprise,
charging him with the othe he made to the church
Apostolique, &amp; with his duty towards God, which he
both by scripture, but specially by their owne lawes,
counsell, &amp; decrees, doth manifestly defend, &amp; by the
fame approue, that he hath done nothing against his
othe or duty in any respect: and the rather dooth he
reproue them by their owne aucthoritie, for as much
as the same is the greatest confutation that maye be
against them. And because the same was done by a
worthy person of noble race and parentage, and a bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop
by office &amp; calling, I thought none more meete
for the patron of such a specialty, thē your Lordship,
vnto whome I owe all duty &amp; reuerence, who for the
good will borne to your Lordshippe, hath dedicated
vnto you this simple translation, faithfully &amp; iustlie
done according to the coppy. Trusting you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
the same according to the worthines therof, and
be a defence against all that shall seeme to mislike of
the matter: and in so doing, you shall binde me for
euer at your cōmaund▪ vnto whome I wish continuall
prosperity in this present life, &amp; in the world to come
ioyes euerlasting.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most humble at commaund,
Thomas Deloney.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>