<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader in commendation of this worke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102777_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16282</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3198.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102777</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader in commendation of this worke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The manners, lavves, and customes of all nations : Collected out of the best vvriters by Ioannes Boemus Aubanus, a Dutch-man. With many other things of the same argument, gathered out of the historie of Nicholas Damascen. The like also out of the history of America, or Brasill, written by Iohn Lerius. The faith, religion and manners of the Aethiopians, and the deploration of the people of Lappia, compiled by Damianus à Goes. With a short discourse of the Aethiopians, taken out of Ioseph Scaliger his seuenth booke de Emendatione temporum. Written in Latin, and now newly translated into English. By Ed. Aston</title>
                 <author>Boemus, Johannes</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Burton, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 408, 449-589, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>To the Reader in commendation of <hi>this worke.</hi>
   </head>
   <l>NOt <hi>Soline, Pliny, Trogus,</hi> nor <hi>Herodotus</hi> of worth,</l>
   <l>Not <hi>Strabo</hi> best Geographer that Cretish Isle brought forth:</l>
   <l>Not true historian <hi>Siculus,</hi> nor yet <hi>Berosus</hi> sage,</l>
   <l>Nor any other writer else within this latter age:</l>
   <l>Not <hi>Siluius</hi> (after <hi>Pius</hi> Pope) the second of that name,</l>
   <l>Nor yet <hi>Sabellicus</hi> (whose workes deserue immortal fame)</l>
   <l>In volums large doe touch so neere the state of th' viniverse</l>
   <l>As doth the Author of this booke in sewer words reherse:</l>
   <l>For here each part of Asiae soile distinctly you may find,</l>
   <l>Th' Arabians, Persians and the Meades, the Scythians &amp; the Inde,</l>
   <l>The Sirian and Assirian, and all the Parthians race,</l>
   <l>The Getes and Dacians (Europs Scythes) the people ecke of Thrace:</l>
   <l>The Sauromates, and those which in Pannonia doe remaine</l>
   <l>The Germaine, the Italian the French and those of Spaine:</l>
   <l>The Irish and the British Isles (of Islands all the best,</l>
   <l>And Affricke nations al (which first old Affrican possest)</l>
   <l>The Aethiops and the Carthage men, and those of Aegipt-land,</l>
   <l>And al the people that doe dwel, on the dry Libian sand.</l>
   <l>And many more inhabitants of diuers Isles beside,</l>
   <l>And where the sect of <hi>Mahomet</hi> most chiefly doth abide:</l>
   <l>What ample large and spatious lands doe honor Christ their head,</l>
   <l>And through what kingdomes of the world his faithfull flocke are spread.</l>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>