<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RENOWMED
Pieres and noble Lordes, the Consuls, and the
whole senate of the famous Citie of Frankford.</title>
           <author>Calvin, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102561_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16078</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2962</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102561</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RENOWMED
Pieres and noble Lordes, the Consuls, and the
whole senate of the famous Citie of Frankford.</title>
                 <author>Calvin, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A harmonie vpon the three Euangelists, Matthew, Mark and Luke : with the commentarie of M. Iohn Caluine: faithfullie translated out of Latine into English, by E.P. Whereunto is also added a commentarie vpon the Euangelist S. Iohn, by the same authour</title>
                 <author>Calvin, Jean</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 806, 2, 8, 464, 24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RENOWMED
Pieres and noble Lordes, the Consuls, and the
whole senate of the famous Citie of Frank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ford.</head>
   <opener>
      <signed>I. Caluine.</signed>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F euer it seemed expedient that the pageants of
vertues should be shewed openly to the imitation
of others (which might bee a spurre as well to the
lasie lingerers, as to the restie runners): surely the
slouthfull dealing and sluggish behauiour whiche
is vsed in these our corrupt dayes maketh it seeme
necessarie: that the greater part of men which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
start back, then willingly step forward, shold
bee constrained at the least with shame of negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
to doe their dutie. For we see euery man busilie bent to a certaine
contention who shall excell in wicked practises, and that both in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
and publike affaires: that no Monarche doth seeme to be inferiour
to the nations that border vpon him either in policie, or vigilancie, or
power, or bolde attempt, whereby he may enlarge the boundes of his
empire: that no citie or common weale doth giue place to any in crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
and all captious dealing: that no man is the second in subtletie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
the proud and ambitious: finally there is no man which hath not
conspired with his companie, and that in the way of contention, slilie to
incite the rest as it were with a becke to all vitious vanitie, and he that is
ringleader in all naughtinesse sonest stirreth vp other to his lewdnesse,
whereas in the rankest route of ribalds is scarce one found out that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth
honestie: which maketh me thinke it very profitable that such
rare vertues as sometime raigne in noble personages, should bee aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
to the loftie theater or stage of due commendation, to the intent that
they being spied a farre of might allure the greater number to like them
and liue accordingly. And this I confesse (right honorable) was the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest
cause that moued me to publish this my labour abroad, vnder the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
of your names. For although I shall persuade my selfe to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited
very wel, if any that beginne of their owne accorde to creepe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
shalbe incouraged by me to runne faster: yet did not I so muche
respect this, as that I might persuade other to ioyn hands with you, or at
the least to tread the same path that you do. Notwithstāding I haue not
purposed to recite as out of a rolle all the godly qualities wherewith
you are throughly furnished: only it shall suffice at this time to set forth
that one vertue wherewith you haue bound to your honours as with a
more holy bond, aswell mee, as diuers other faithfull seruants of Iesus
Christ. This one thing is worthie highly to be prayed that fiue yeeres
since when as an horrible feare had affrighted the mindes of all men in
euery place: whenas the ouerthrowe that our enemies had giuen vs did
threaten a miserable ruine to the churches throughout Germany, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
an vtter extinguishing of the Gospel, you euen at that time beeing
placed in the fore front of the battaile stood stoutly to the free confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of your faith, which was hated to death, and retained with all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie
<pb facs="3"/>
that sincere doctrine of pietie which before you receiued: which
is a manifest argument that when you were tossed with greuous cares
and dangerous turmoyles, you desired nothing more then to fight man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
vnder Christes banner▪ But that which followeth will surely make
your names immortall; that you doe not only set out amongest your
selues the true worship of God, and imploy your faithfull labour, to
cōteine your citizens within the sheepfold of Christ: but also gather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather
the dispersed relikes of his church, thrust out of other nations,
which are as it were, members of the same, all rent and pulled in peeces.
Doubtles, it did greatly reioice my hart (cōsidering the troublesome time)
to heare that the true worshipers of God, which fled in exile from Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
and other countries, were gently receiued and entertained among
you▪ and that you did not only releeue and ease their heauie banishment
but that you had also a due consideration of the glory of the sonne of
God, insomuch that you made his Gospel to be sounded in your citie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
by the tongues of aliants, and that in a straunge language. The like
curtesie was shewed of late by the Magistrates of Tigurine to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
citizens of Lo▪ whom they did not only receiue &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oster within
the walles of their Citie, when at home they coulde not worship God
as they woulde: but also erected a Temple for them wherein they
might celebrate Gods holy seruice: neither were they diswaded by the
diuersitie of tongues from suffering Christ to speake Italian, euen in the
middest of Tigurine: but I let them passe and come againe to that I
was about to say of you. As soone as I vnderstoode that your curtesie
stretched so farre, as to suffer my countrimen to haue a holy congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
in your citie: perceiuing my selfe bound vnto you by a priuate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit:
I thought good to testifie my thākful hart by this gift which now
I present vnto you. For as the condition of our countrie men is rightly
to be lamented, who dwelling in their natiue soyle, seeme by the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
sacriledge of the Pope to be cleane banished from Christs king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:
so on the contrary part, it is not a little to bee reioyced at, that
they haue a resting place graunted them in a straunge countrie, where
they may render due honour vnto the liuing God. And surely this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
hospitalitie which you haue vsed, not so much towardes men as to-Christ
himselfe, shall bee a meanes as I trust, to moue God to powre
his rare benefites vpon you, and still to continue his liberalitie towarde
you, which do alredie slorish in all prosperitie. Doubtlesse it constrained
mee (as I signified before) to dedicate this my booke vnto you, which is
a Commentarie vpon the Harmonie made of the three Euangelists: in
making wherof, I haue takē some paines with no lesse fidelitie thē in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry.
But as it is to smal purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e to declare how seriously I haue traue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
herein: so do I submit my self to other mens iudgmēts: for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> learned,
wise, and discreete Readers, who as they take great delight in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
vtilitie, so they be not ashamed like rude &amp; barbarous caytifes, to
learne &amp; augment their knowledge by reading and studie. But as for
peruers and ouerthwart wranglers, I little esteeme, I meane not cowled
Monkes, who for the maintenance of the Popes tyrannie fight in open
place against vs: but also those vnnaturall drones which being mingled
amōg vs, desire nothing more, then clean to extinguish al sight of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
to this intent that they may cloke and couer their own ignorance.
<pb facs="3"/>
For although like dogges they despitefully bark at me, yet wil I vse this
exception alwaies, that I neede not submitte my selfe to their censure or
iudgement, either by the law of God or of men, which are not onely to
be kept vnder like children for their blamefull and infamous vnskilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:
but also most seuerely to be punished for their malitious obstinacie,
&amp; to stubbern impudēcie. But whatsoeuer they say, I trust the better sort
wil graunt, that it is lawfull for me to acknowledge without arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,
that faithfull labour, which I haue imploied to the profit of Gods
Church. There came forth two yeeres since the gospel of Iohn, with my
interpretation, which I trust hath not beene fruitelesse. And thus like an
apparitor, I haue endeuoured to my power, to set forth Christe, ryding
princelike in his foure wheeled chariot, very gloriously: By reading of
which worke, when the gentle readers haue profited them selues, they
wil not be loath to confesse, that they haue not studied it in vaine: which
Euangelicall history being described and sette forth by foure witnesses,
appointed by God himselfe, I do not without cause compare vnto a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot:
for of this sweete and pleasaunt consent God seemeth purposelye
to haue made as it were, a triumphant chariot for his son, out of which
he might plainly appeare to be seene of al his faithful people, and by the
swiftnes whereof he might lightly passe, and as it were, raunge ouer the
whole world. Neither doth Augustine vnfitly compare the foure Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelistes
to trumpets, the noyse whereof doth sound in al coastes, that the
Churche of Christe beeing summoned out of the foure quarters of the
world, might flock and gather together from the East and the VVeste,
from the South and the North, vnto an holy consent of faith. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
their absurd curiositie is the lesse to be borne withal, who being not
content with these Gospels (which be as it were proclamations procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
from heauen) thrust out their own toyes, and corrupt imaginatiōs,
which do nothing but defile the puritie of faith, &amp; cause Christes name
to be scorned and had in derision of the vngodly. As for you, which do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
farre excel the common sort, since you detest in minde al that corrupt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
wherewith the true sinceritie of the Gospell is infected, and shewe
your selues to delight in nothing more then in maintaining and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the plaine and simple doctrine, as it is set forth by Christ himselfe: I
am not only perswaded that you wil very wel like of this my watchful
worke, which expoundeth the treasure of glad tiding: but also I haue a
good hope, that this signe or token of my good will and loue to you
ward, will be aswel acceptable, in that I haue dedicated the same vnto
you. Thus I bid you farewel, right honourable Lordes, and wishe that
Christ may direct you with his holy spirit, strengthen you with his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,
preserue you vnder his protection, and enrich your Citie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
weale with his plenteous benediction. At <hi>Geneua,</hi> the first of Aug.
The yeere of our Lordes natiuitie, 1555.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>