<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVLY NOBLE IOHN ROBERTS, Son and Heire to the Right Ho∣nourable RICHARD Lord ROBERTS of Truro: the Vnualuable Riches of sincere Grace here, and of Eter∣nall Glory hereafter.</title>
           <author>Gamon, Hannibal</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S102888_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01431</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11548</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S102888</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVLY NOBLE IOHN ROBERTS, Son and Heire to the Right Ho∣nourable RICHARD Lord ROBERTS of Truro: the Vnualuable Riches of sincere Grace here, and of Eter∣nall Glory hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Gamon, Hannibal</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The praise of a godly vvoman : A sermon preached at the solemne funerall of the right honourable Ladie, the Ladie Frances Roberts, at Lanhide-rock-Church in Cornwall, the tenth of August, 1626. By Hanniball Gamon, Minister of the word of God, at St. Maugan in the same countie</title>
                 <author>Gamon, Hannibal</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Grismand (Grismond), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 37, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVLY NOBLE IOHN ROBERTS, Son and Heire to the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable RICHARD <hi>Lord</hi> ROBERTS of <hi>Truro:</hi> the Vnualuable Riches of sincere Grace here, and of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Glory hereafter.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>HONOVRABLE SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough it bee true (which a worthy Diuine<note n="a" place="margin">M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Bolton</hi> Disc. <hi>of true</hi> Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, p. 61.</note> obserueth) that formall Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites are heartned and hardned in their lewd courses &amp; false conceits of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, when they heare more infamous Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners than themselues, gloriously and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly commended at their Deaths; yet we
<pb facs="3"/>need not feare any such bad effect by the Funerall-commendation of Gods true Saints; because the publike Testimonie of their iust Praises doth not onely make the wicked more inexcusable, and the Glory of Gods Graces shine farre brighter to Posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; but also enkindleth in the hearts of the godly a greater fire of Zeale for imitation. These are some of the Ends, why it hath euer been and is still an vnreproueable Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome in Gods Church, that the Godly should be <hi>Marked</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">
         <hi>Psalm.</hi> 37.37. <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.7, 10, 11.12. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi>
      </note> and <hi>Honoured</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.33.</note> at their Deaths, as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was by all <hi>Iudah</hi> &amp; <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem: Valentinean, Satyrus</hi> and <hi>Theodosius</hi> by Saint <hi>Ambrose</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">S. Ambr. tom. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note>: <hi>Basil, Gregory</hi> and <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonia</hi> by <hi>Nazianzen</hi>
      <note n="''" place="margin">Greg. Nazian. Orat. <hi>30.28.25.</hi>
      </note>: <hi>Nepotian, Paula</hi> and <hi>Marcella</hi> by S. <hi>Ierom</hi>
      <note n="†" place="margin">S. Ierom. Ad Heliod. Ad Eustoch. Ad Princip. Ad Ocean.</note>. Had not their Holy Liues and Happie Deaths beene published by such vnpartiall Pens, wee should haue bin ignorant now of many excellent Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of sanctified Men and Women, of many comfortable workings of the Holy Ghost in them, and should haue wanted many inflaming Motiues to follow their religious steps. Vpon this consideration I was bold to commend vnto Gods people the more
<pb facs="3"/>than Ordinary passages of your Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Mothers Holy Life and Death: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue as a Christian spoken the truth of a Christian, that is, (as Saint <hi>Ierom</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>stor le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>um cui il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>uit &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> utramq. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e ni <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>l fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ere; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i Christicanu d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap> qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>t vera pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> est, Histori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m scribere non P ne g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. S. Ier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m, Epitaph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>uloe.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testeth in a like case) made a true Narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; not a Vain-glorious Panegyrick. Let Poets and Oratours praise those women, which <hi>Poppaea</hi>-like<note n="e" place="margin">Poppa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> cun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lia fuêre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Honestum animum. Tacit. Annual. l. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </note>, are graced with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things sauing a Gracious Heart: Let them commend their Wit, Wealth, Beautie, Nobilitie, and other Gifts of Fortune (as they call them) in stead of Vertues<note n="f" place="margin">Laudauit ipse Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro apud rostra for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ius &amp; quòd diuinae formae pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens fuisset, aliaque fortunae munera pro Virtutibus. Id. Annal l. <hi>16.</hi>
      </note>. Wee the Ministers of Christ, and Stewards of the Mysteries of God, must adorne none with the Honourable Attributes of Heauenly Praise; but such as are truly beautified, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched, and ennobled with the Purity and Power of Gods Feare in their Humble Soules<note n="*" place="margin">
         <hi>Esai.</hi> 61.3.</note>. This praise the Lord will Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper<note n="g" place="margin">
         <hi>Eccles.</hi> 15 10.</note>, which is vttered in that <hi>Wisdome</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 9.10.</note>, whereof the <hi>Feare of the Lord is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> But for the Saints themselues: I dare say with Saint <hi>Augustine</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">
         <hi>Epist.</hi> 125 where S. <hi>Augustine</hi> refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth to commend vnto a wicked Husbād his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wife that was dead, not onely because she desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not his praise, saying: <hi>Laudem ab homin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>bus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>am illa non quaerit, imitationem verò t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>a tantum quaerit eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am defuncta, quantum te dilexit etiam dissimilem viua;</hi> but also because her Husband loued Her not, which he proueth thus: <hi>Nam utiq si amares, cum illa esse post mortem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>esider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e, quod profectò non eris, si qualis es, talis eris.</hi>
      </note>, that they desire more the Imitation, than the Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="4"/>of their vertues: and therefore to tell you the truth (as the same Father doth his friend) you should neuer haue heard mee commend this deceased Lady, but in hope, that Gods Graces in Her might by this meanes, suruiue in your religious Imitation, and not only in you and all them that are of Her bloud; but also in all them that haue heard or shall reade this Sermon. This is all the gaine I looke and pray for, that Gods<note n="k" place="margin">
         <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.22, 28. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.8. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.3.</note> word, which I haue faithfully alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged (not without some Illustrations (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse) borrowed from the holy Fathers<note n="l" place="margin">—Ingenuo pudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re qui ornabat aeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, quid cuius es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set, confiteri—Illud (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ebat) Tertullia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, istud Cypriani, hoc Lactantij, illud Hilarij est. Sic Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutius Foelix, ita Victorinus, in hunc modum est locutus Arnobius. S. Ierom. ad Heliodor. de Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potian.</note>, whereof I need not to be ashamed) may be constantly practised by vs all. For when all is done and said, assure your selfe (Deare Sir) it is only the Life of Grace, the Grace of the <hi>Feare of the Lord</hi> can truly Honour you, or any vpon earth, sweetly comfort you at your Death, and eternally Glorifie your Soule and Bodie in Heauen. Abandon then I beseech you in the name of Christ<note n="m" place="margin">2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 3.6. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Prou.</hi> 4.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Psalm.</hi> 26.4, 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 119.32, 36, 128. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.37.</note>, all iniquitie, and all workers of iniquitie, yea abominate the sweetest sin, to which your youthfull affections are most endeared, else you will neuer be able to encline and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large
<pb facs="4"/>them to the pursuit and practise of so excellent and Glorious a Grace as the <hi>Feare of the Lord;</hi> because this godly Feare and the impenitent Allowance of any lust, is as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible as Heauen and Hell: so that if you should hate to be diuorced from your Bosome-sin whatsoeuer it be (which God forbid) you could haue no true right and interest to the precious promises of this and of that other life<note n="n" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8</note>. Thinke on this continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and hold it your greatest Honour, the Noblest imployment of your Soule, as it is indeed, to keep your selfe (as a King<note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 18.23.</note> did before you.) from your iniquitie. <hi>Quod si tu (quod procul absit) nolueris, ego liber ero. Epistola, immo concio me haec mea, cum lecta fuerit, absoluet</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">S. Ierom. ad Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storin. Materte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram.</note>. And so I rest, being mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of your Vertues,</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Saint Maugan</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>the</hi> 19. <hi>August</hi> 1626.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours in all Christian Deuotion, and heartiest prayer to God for you, <hi>HANNIBAL GAMON.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>