<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A preface to the booke folovvinge.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103013_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13678</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23968</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103013</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A preface to the booke folovvinge.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The folovving of Christ : translated out of Latin into Englishe, newlie corrected and amended. VVherevnto also is added the golden epistle of Sainct Bernarde. And nowe lastelie the rules of a Christian lyfe, made by Iohn Picus the elder earle of mira [n] dula</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Loyselet (L’Oiselet), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 158, 10 leaves, illustrations, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <head>A preface to the booke folovvinge.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Monge manye Treatises, which haue
bene put out both in Latin and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishe,
in this perillous worlde, to
seduce the simple people, &amp; to bring
them from the vnitie of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
Churche into peruers and abhominable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,
there hath bene also in tyme past before
made by diuers learned and vertuous men many
good Treatises, which yf men woulde be so dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
to looke vpon, as they are curious to looke
on the other they shoulde not so soone fall from
the true knowledge of Christes doctrine, and the
right sense of holie Scripture, whiche euer hath
bene taught by continuall succession in his holie
Churche, of the holie ghost, the spirite of truth,
who shall euer remayne with it. And amonge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of these good Treatises, there is one called,
the Imitation or folowinge of Christe, whiche in
my iudgement is excellent: and the more it is se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouslie
<pb facs="3"/>
and aduisedlie reade and looked vpon,
the more it shall like euery Christian Reader,
who will set his minde earnestlie to folow Christ
his steppes. Let them proue by reading euery day
a chapter whē they haue best leasure; and I doubt
not, but they shall finde my sayinges true. I haue
reade it ouer very many times, and the more I
reade, the more I like it and finde profite to my
soule health. It teacheth the true mortification of
the fleshe to the spirite, accordinge to the right
sense of holie Scripture, and the doctrine of 5.
Paul. VVhich I consideringe desired the Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
highnes printer to take the paynes e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>sones
to imprint it, seeinge the other is worne awaye,
whiche was verie faultie in many places. And in
this he hath done his diligence in correction
thereof, as you shall well perceyue in conferring
them together. Thus fare you well in Christ, and
praye for them that haue taken paynes in this
behalfe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>