<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honourable Henrie, Earle of SOVTHAMPTON, Baron of TICHEFIELD, Knight of the most ho∣nourable Order of the Garter, and Gouernour of the Isle of WIGHT.</title>
           <author>Hampton, Christopher</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103819_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02611</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12740</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103819</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honourable Henrie, Earle of SOVTHAMPTON, Baron of TICHEFIELD, Knight of the most ho∣nourable Order of the Garter, and Gouernour of the Isle of WIGHT.</title>
                 <author>Hampton, Christopher</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo sermons preached before the Kings most excellent Maiesty in the church of Beauly in Hampshire : The first, the last of August. The second, the 9. of August. By Christopher Hampton Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Hampton, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hall, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 21, 1, 26 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right honourable <hi>Henrie, Earle of</hi> SOVTHAMPTON, <hi>Baron of</hi> TICHEFIELD, Knight of the most <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Order of the Garter,</hi> and Gouernour of the Isle of WIGHT.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold (right honourable) the Sermons now publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which were pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by your Lordships ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, in a very sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred presence. The grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous allowance which then they receiued from a roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all diuine, giueth me hope that they will not be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome to the Church, entertaining all meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with facilitie, that aduance Christ, her Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome, Patron, and delight. What was intended in them to this purpose, he knoweth best that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things: If any thing be attained, that shall alwaies be ascribed thankfully to his goodnesse, and submitted willingly to her censure. With this obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb facs="3"/>
I haue determined to liue, and desire to die. In the meane time, they come abroad vnder the passe also of your Lordships authoritie, as of my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Magistrate. Were they iust volumes, and of any great request, your Lordship were more than worthy of them, for that heroiacall zeale wherewith you haue adorned our little <hi>Sarepta.</hi> Now making scarse a pamphlet, they are the lesse worthy of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble patron: But I haue had true experience that your Lordship accepteth the poore indeuours of our ministerie aboue their worth. Therefore recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending them to your Lordships good fauour, and your Lordship to the riches of Gods blessing, I take my leaue with reuerence, and will rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most affectionately deuoted, <hi>CHRISTOPHER HAMPTON.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>