<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlewomen Ci∣tizens of London, Flourishing dayes with regarde of Credite.</title>
           <author>Gosson, Stephan</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103345_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01953</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12097.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103345</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlewomen Ci∣tizens of London, Flourishing dayes with regarde of Credite.</title>
                 <author>Gosson, Stephan</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The schoole of abuse : conteining a plesaunt [sic] inuectiue against poets, pipers, plaiers, iesters, and such like caterpillers of a co [m] monwelth; setting vp the flagge of defiance to their mischieuous exercise, [and] ouerthrowing their bulwarkes, by prophane writers, naturall reason, and common experience: a discourse as pleasaunt for gentlemen that fauour learning, as profitable for all that wyll follow virtue. By Stephan Gosson. Stud. Oxon</title>
                 <author>Gosson, Stephen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 37, 7 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Drama</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="41"/>
   <head>To the Gentlewomen Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of London, Flourishing dayes with regarde of Credite.</head>
   <p>THE reuerence that I owe you Gentlewomen, because you are Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens; &amp; the pitie wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I tender your case, because you are weake; hath thrust out my hād, at the breaking vp of my Schoole, to write a few lines to your sweete selues. Not that I thinke you to bee rebuked, as idle huswiues, but commended and incouraged as vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Dames. The freest horse, at the wh: ske of a wand, girdes forwarde: The swiftest Hound, when he is hallowed, strippes forth: The kindest Mastife, when he is clapped on the back, fighteth best: The stoutest Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, when the Trumpet sounds, strikes fier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cest: The gallantest Runner, when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple showte, getteth grounde: and the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctest liuers, when they are praysed, winne greatest credite.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="41"/>I haue seene many of you whiche were wont to sporte your selues at Theaters, whē you perceiued the abuse of those places, schoole your selues, &amp; of your owne accorde abhorre Playes. And sith you haue begun to withdrawe your steppes, continew so stil, if you be chary of your good name. For this is generall, that they which shew thēselues openly, desire to bee seene. It is not a softe shooe that healeth the Gowte; nor a golden Ring that driueth away the Crampe; nor a crown of Pearle that cureth the Meigrim; nor your sober countenance, that defendeth your credite; nor your friends which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany your person, that excuse your folly; nor your modestie at home, that couereth your lightnesse, if you present your selues in open Theaters. Thought is free: you can forbidd no man, that vieweth you, to noate you, and that noateth you, to iudge you, for entring to places of suspition. Wilde Coltes; when they see their kinde begin to bray; &amp; lusty bloods at the showe of faire women, giue a wanton sigh, or a wicked wishe. Blasing markes are most shot at, glistring faces cheefly marked; and what followeth? Looking eyes, haue ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="42"/>
hartes, liking harts may burne in lust. We walke in the Sun many times for pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, but our faces are tāned before we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: though you go to theaters to se sport, <hi>Cupid</hi> may catche you ere you departe. The litle God houereth aboute you, &amp; fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth you with his wings to kindle fire: when you are set as fixed whites, Desire draweth his arrow to the head, &amp; sticketh it vppe to the fethers, and Fancy bestirreth him too shed his poyson through euery vaine. If you doe but listen to the voyce of the Fouler, or ioyne lookes with an amorous Gazer, you haue already made your selues assaultable, &amp; yelded your Cities to be sacked. A wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton eye is the darte of <hi>Cephalus,</hi> where it leueleth, thereit lighteth; &amp; where it hitts, it woundeth deepe. If you giue but a glance to your beholders, you haue vayled the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net in token of obedience: for the boulte is falne ere the Ayre clap; the Bullet paste, ere the Peece crack; the colde taken, ere the body shiuer; and the match made, ere you strike handes.</p>
   <p>To auoyd this discommoditie, <hi>Cyrus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused to looke vppon Panthea, And <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>
      <pb facs="42"/>
the great on <hi>Darius</hi> wife. The sicke man that relesheth nothing, when hee seeth some about him feede apace, and commend the taste of those dishes which hee refused, blames not the meate, but his owne disease: And I feare you will say, that it is no ripe iudgement, but a rawe humor in my selfe, which makes me condemne the resorting to Playes; because there come many thyther, which in your opinion sucke no poyson, but feede hartely without hurt; therefore I doe very ill to reiect that which other like, and complaine still of mine owne maladie.</p>
   <p>In deede I must confesse there comes to Playes of all sortes, old and young; it is hard to say that all offend, yet I promise you, I wil sweare for none. For the driest flax flameth soonest; &amp; the greenest wood smoketh most; gray heads haue greene thoughts; and young slippes are olde twigges. Beware of those places, which in sorrowe cheere you, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile you in mirth. You must not cut your bodyes to your garmentes, but make your gownes fit to the proportion of your bodyes; nor fashiō your selues, to open spectacles, but tye all your sportes to the good disposition of
<pb facs="43"/>
a vertuous minde. At Diceplay, euery one wisheth to caste well; at Bowles euery one craues to kisse the maister; at running eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one starteth to win the goale; At shoting euery one striues to hit the marke; and will not you in all your pastimes and recreations seeke that which shall yeelde you most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite &amp; greatest credite? I wil not say you are made to toile, &amp; I dare not graunt that you should be idle. But if there be peace in your houses, and plentie in your Coafers, let the good precept of <hi>Xenophō</hi> be your exercise: in all your ease and prosperitie, remember God, that he may be mindeful of you, when your heartes grone, and succour you still in the time of neede. Be euer busied in godly meditations: seek not to passe ouer the gulf with a tottering plank that wil deceiue you. When we cast off our best clothes, we put on ragges; when our good desires are once laide aside, wantonwil begins to prick. Being pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue at home, if you go to Theaters to driue avvay fancies, it is as good Physike, as for the ache of your head too knocke out your brains; or when you are stung with a Wasp, to rub the sore with a Nettle. When you
<pb facs="43"/>
are greeued, passe the time with your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures in sober conference, or if you can read, let Bookes bee your comforte. Doe not imitate those foolishe Patientes, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing sought all meanes of recouery, and are neuer the neere, run vnto Witchcrafte. If your greefe be such, that you may not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>close it, and your sorrowe so great, that you loth to vtter it, looke for no salue at Playes ortheaters, lest that labouring to shun <hi>Sylla</hi> you light on <hi>Charybdis;</hi> to for sake the depe you perish in sands; to warde a light stripe, you take a deaths wound; and to leaue Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick, you flee to inchaunting. You neede not goe abroade to be tempted, you shall be inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed at your owne windowes. The best coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel that I can giue you, is to keepe home, &amp; shun all occasion of ill speech. The virgins of Vest a were shut vp fast in stone walles to the same ende. You must keepe your sweete faces from scorching in the sun, chapping in the winde, and warping with the weather, which is best perfourmed by staying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And if you perceiue your selues in any danger at your owne doores, either allured by curtesie in the day, or assaulted with Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicks
<pb facs="44"/>
in the night; Close vp your eyes, stoppe your eares, tye vp your tongues; when they speake, aunsweare not; when they hallowe, stoope not; when they sighe, laugh at them; when they sue, scorne them; Shunne their company, neuer be seene where they resort; so shall you neither set them proppes, when they seeke to clime; nor holde them the st<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop, when they profer to mount.</p>
   <p>These are harde lessons vvhich I teach you; neuerthelesse, drinke vppe the potion, though it like not your tast, and you shall be eased; resist not the Surgeon, though he strike in his knife, and you shall bee cured. The Fig tree is sower, but it yeeldeth sweete fruite; <hi>Thymus</hi> is bitter, but it giueth Honny; my Schoole is tarte, but my co<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap> is pleasant, if you imbrace it. Shortly I hope to send out the <hi>Ephemerides</hi> of <hi>P<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="5 letters">
            <desc>•••••</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> by whom if I see you accept this) I wil giue you one dish for your owne tooth. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to serue at Vertues call. Stephan <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>osson.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="44"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>