<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE, by diuine prouidence, Lord Archbishop of Can∣terburie his Grace, primate of all England, and Metropolitane, one of his Maiesties most hono∣rable priuie Councell, my verie good Lord.</title>
           <author>Westerman, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103491_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14974</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25281</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103491</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE, by diuine prouidence, Lord Archbishop of Can∣terburie his Grace, primate of all England, and Metropolitane, one of his Maiesties most hono∣rable priuie Councell, my verie good Lord.</title>
                 <author>Westerman, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iacobs vvell: or, A sermon preached before the Kings most excellent Maiestie at Saint Albans, in his summer progresse 1612. By William Westerman, Bachelar of Diuinitie, and chaplaine to the most Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Archbishop of Canterbury, his Grace</title>
                 <author>Westerman, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Law (Lawe), Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST <hi>REVEREND</hi> FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE, <hi>by diuine prouidence,</hi> Lord Archbishop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie his Grace, primate of all</hi> England, and Metropolitane, <hi>one of his Maiesties most hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> priuie Councell, my verie good Lord.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost Reuerend Eather, and my verie honourable good Lord; I will not say it was my</hi> happe, <hi>but the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of</hi> God, <hi>and my happinesse, to preach this Sermon, before my dread</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> Soueraigne, <hi>in his summer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse,</hi> at Saint Albans: <hi>where, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side, that I was an eare-witnesse of the</hi> wisdome <hi>of</hi> Salomon, <hi>and a</hi> diuine Oracle, <hi>speaking through his gracious</hi> lippes: <hi>I did also experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it to bee true of his</hi> highnesse, <hi>which was once vttered concerning a</hi> Romane Emperour: <note n="a" place="margin">Qui apud te audent dicere, magnitudinem tuam ignorant: qui nonaudent, bumanitatem. Senec. controu. lib. 7. contr. 8.</note> He that dares speake before him, knowes not his greatnesse, and hee that dares not speake before him, knowes not his goodnesse. <hi>For such is his Maiestie, in Attention, and Attention in Maiestie, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make the most Audacious Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, and the most Timerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident. What I then deliuered, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of so</hi> high <hi>a</hi> presence, <hi>so great an Audience, &amp; so ample a</hi> Church, <hi>hath left such an</hi> Eccho <hi>behind it, as hath caused many to heare the sound of it, that heard not the voyce it selfe: many to report diuersly of it,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>and some earnestly to desire Copies of the whole</hi> Sermon. <hi>To satisfie all, and to preuent my often trouble, and others miss-reporting, who either bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, or worse it in the rehearsall; I am bold at last to commit it to the Presse, &amp; to present it to your</hi> Grace, <hi>vnder the</hi> banner <hi>of whose patronage and encouragement, as of a most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie and eminent</hi> Captaine <hi>in the</hi> Israell <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>I am prest, although an vnworthie</hi> Souldier <hi>of</hi> Christ Iesus, <hi>to tender the</hi> vtmost <hi>of my</hi> seruice <hi>toward the benefit of his</hi> Church. <hi>Now as this</hi> Sermon, <hi>at the first hearing thereof, receaued a most fauourable preiudgement, and acceptance, from the</hi> deepe <hi>wisdome of</hi> highest <hi>Authoritie, for the</hi> worke <hi>sake, to the which his</hi> Maiesties <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious disposition was seltly-inclinable: so my trust is, that your</hi> Graces <hi>great Iudgement and learning, for a</hi> zeale <hi>to the same worke, will kindly accept</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>of it (how small a peece soeuer,) bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the</hi> stampe <hi>of his Maiesties ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, and let it passe for Currant vnder your Graces countenance, with more facile examination, and easie Censure. Touching the Royall</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose <hi>and</hi> promise <hi>of his</hi> Maiestie, <hi>whereby the repaire of the decated</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Saint Albans, <hi>is made possible, &amp; (I trust) feazable, least any should</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">2. Cor. 12. 6.</note> thinke or speake more then they see, or heare in me, <hi>I cannot say that I was either</hi> Author, <hi>or any principall</hi> meanes <hi>or Mouer in it, except with the</hi> flye <hi>vpon the</hi> Coach, <hi>I should crie</hi> Ecce quantum pulueris excito: <hi>behold what a dust I made, when I did nothing to the purpose. For who am I first; or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</hi> any man; <hi>that</hi> I, <hi>or</hi> they, <hi>should be able to moue the</hi> deepe thoughts <hi>of a</hi> Kings heart; <hi>which by a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scedent peculiar, is in</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Prou. 21. 1.</note> manu Dei, in the hand of God, to turne as
<pb facs="4"/> the riuers of water, and to manage as it pleaseth him? <hi>Nay further, there can be neither</hi> action, <hi>or</hi> Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will, power, <hi>or</hi> purpose <hi>in any man, that is</hi> good <hi>(how little soeuer:) but it is to be reputed as</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">
         <hi>Omne quod habemus bonum gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stue est do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron: ad Cte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sipbont.</hi>
      </note> gustus Domini, <hi>a</hi> gust of the Lords <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, a</hi> touch <hi>of his</hi> finger, <hi>whose prouidence is the first</hi> Mouer, <hi>whose</hi> Grace <hi>is the</hi> Center, <hi>and whose</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>the</hi> Circumference, <hi>betweene which the</hi> lines <hi>of our</hi> liues, <hi>and best intendments, when they goe right and streight, are leuelled. And tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the</hi> meanes <hi>or mediating of the</hi> businesse, <hi>I can claime little, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers much more, and yet none</hi> verie <hi>much: for such was the religious</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> propension <hi>of his</hi> Maiesties <hi>roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all heart, readily prepared, (as our sweete</hi> Sauiour <hi>sitting at</hi> Iacobs well) <hi>to</hi> doe good, <hi>that the</hi> humble <hi>petition of his louing subiects in</hi> St. Albans, <hi>was but the discouerie of a</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>desperate sore, to a merciful</hi> Phisitian, <hi>who was more ready to</hi> cure, <hi>then they to</hi> complaine. <hi>Indeed I confesse, that the way being made for me to preach at that time, by that</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">My Lord of <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>hf. &amp; Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent.</hi>
      </note> Right Reuerēd Father <hi>then attending his</hi> Maiestie, <hi>(being also an especiall fauorite of the motion) I did as a</hi> blunt whetstone <hi>perhaps a little sharpen the</hi> razor, <hi>which had</hi> edge <hi>enough of it selfe, and like a</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Horat: Athletaesuis incitatoribus sunt fortiorcs, &amp; tamen ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>or, vt pugnet forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or. Hieron.</note>
      <hi>weake stander by, onely yeeld an</hi> applause <hi>and</hi> acclamation <hi>to my</hi> Soueraigne, <hi>as a worthie</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Sed ne{que} ille exbortatione a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum indige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, non magus sanè quam ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerosissimi pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giles, putrorum acclamatione. Bapl Athanas.</hi>
      </note> Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>running on so good a race, with so</hi> faire <hi>a</hi> course. <hi>Since which time how cōstantly his maiesty hath proceeded, how well the whole busines was spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; prepared for the publike dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch by that worthy Knight &amp;</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Christoph. Parkins.</note> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. of the Requests, <hi>formerly acquainted with</hi> Church-building, <hi>how many</hi> honorable fauorites <hi>haue seconded the proceedings, it were ouer lōg to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse. But I cannot pretermit the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes
<pb facs="5"/> of that right honorable</hi> Earl of Northhampton <hi>(so much ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning high</hi> Nobilitie, <hi>with</hi> exquisite learning, <hi>to whom our</hi> Church <hi>and state is boūd for a</hi> Monumēt <hi>in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of</hi> eternall Memorie <hi>against all traiterous</hi> Romanists) <hi>who hath rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly approued &amp; improued his godly</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire <hi>and former promise toward the repaire of that</hi> Church, <hi>with a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will</hi> beneuolence, <hi>and first-fruit of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of double</hi> weight <hi>according to the</hi> Sycle <hi>of the</hi> sanctuarie, <hi>as a luc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie hansell and example to others, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as the best gifts are, with speede and maturitie: so much is</hi> S. Albans <hi>beholding to his</hi> honor, <hi>for a short time of his youthfull yeeres there im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied. And what worthie assistance your</hi> Grace <hi>hath afforded toward the effectuall accomplishment of his</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties <hi>pleasure, not onely in this busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, but in that Religious beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of late for</hi> Prague <hi>in</hi> Bohemia,
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>all true</hi> Christian <hi>hearts doe see and acknowledge to the</hi> glorie of God, <hi>cheerefully contributing to such seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall good workes, and blessing God for the holie desires of his</hi> Maiestie <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the</hi> Gospell <hi>at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; as also for your</hi> Grace, <hi>whose vigilancie standing</hi> Centinell <hi>upon the highest</hi> watch-tower <hi>of the</hi> Church <hi>under</hi> God <hi>and his</hi> Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stic <hi>is ready to apprehend all occasions for the Aduancement of Religion, Charitie, and Learning. Neither are the Religious</hi> purposes <hi>of his</hi> Maiestie, <hi>thus happily springing up in his</hi> royall heart, <hi>so carefully strea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med out by your</hi> Graces <hi>Expedition, but they are answerably speeded and passed along through the Land, by the most</hi> vigilant Prelates. <hi>Especially that</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">My Lord B. of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
      </note> Right Reuerend Father, <hi>our most</hi> worthie Diocesan, <note n="l" place="margin">
         <hi>Caelestis tuba. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros.</hi>
      </note> that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly trumpet, <note n="m" place="margin">Eloquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae Regia: Greg: de Basilio.</note>
      <hi>and</hi> Kingly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of diuine Eloquence, <hi>hath not</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>onely excited many our brethren to the diligent</hi> prensation <hi>of the</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities <hi>of the better sort, as a</hi> prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous winde breathing forwardnes into them <hi>(that I may use his</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors <hi>owne words) according to a trust reposed in his</hi> Lordshippe, <hi>but also doth continue a most</hi> honorable care, <hi>and cautelous</hi> respect <hi>to the faithfull employment of all</hi> Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>made for that</hi> worke <hi>of</hi> Saint Albans, <hi>so happily begun, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nierubs or interruptions, saue onely such as may serue to make the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings more</hi> circumspect <hi>and</hi> sound. <hi>Yet if this</hi> worke <hi>so well becomming the</hi> Magnificence <hi>of a</hi> Christian King, <note n="n" place="margin">Letters patents.</note>
      <hi>(as his</hi> Maiestie <hi>acknowledgeth) and commended by your</hi> Grace <hi>for a</hi> Christian, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, an holy and acceptable work, <hi>should have no</hi> opposites, <hi>it were seeing the reedifying of</hi>
      <note n="o" place="margin">Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah 4. 1.</note> the Temple <hi>had many</hi> enemies: <hi>and our</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/> age <hi>is not without manie, impugning the good successe of such-like</hi> buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. <hi>The</hi> Anabaptist <hi>cannot but distast the erecting of</hi> Churches, &amp; houses <hi>of</hi> Gods <hi>publike</hi> seruice, <hi>because he standeth upon his owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate</hi> Inspiration, <hi>and neuer aspireth higher then a</hi> conuenticle <hi>at the most. The</hi> Libertine <hi>who liues at large, cannot but esteeme the</hi> Church <hi>a</hi> Prison, <hi>the publike Ministery a</hi> Sessiōs <hi>of Enquirie, where he suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth himselfe arraigned, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and therefore the</hi> graues <hi>and</hi> Tombes <hi>are as the</hi> shadow <hi>of</hi> death, <hi>occasioning</hi> feare <hi>and</hi> horror <hi>before he comes to</hi> execution. <hi>The</hi> Popish Recusant, <hi>who had wont to make more of the</hi> Cage, <hi>then of the</hi> byrd, <hi>and more of a</hi> materiall Church, <hi>then the spirituall</hi> Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, <hi>is out of loue with our</hi> houses <hi>of</hi> prayer, <hi>because therein their</hi> Masse-Priests, <hi>and</hi> strange lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>is</hi> silenced, <hi>their</hi> Images <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, their Iewish</hi> sacrifices, <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous</hi> Inuocations, <hi>and</hi> Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>are abandoned. And aboue all these, the</hi> Couetous polititian, <hi>cannot chuse but be a</hi> Church-ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, <hi>whose</hi> Mammon <hi>is his</hi> God, <hi>whose priuate</hi> estate <hi>is his</hi> Idoll, <hi>to whom onely hee buildes his</hi> house <hi>as a</hi> Temple, <hi>and intends all his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: as</hi> Ieremie <hi>saith of such like:</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">Ierem. 22. 14.</note> he buildes himselfe a wide house and large Chambers, hee makes himselfe faire windowes, and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with Cedar, and paints it with vermilion: <hi>but if he see anie thing bestowed on</hi> Gods house, <hi>or on the</hi> Ministry, <hi>he crieth with the officious</hi> purse-bearer <hi>in the</hi> Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, <note n="q" place="margin">Mark. 14. 4.</note> Quorsum haec perditio? To what end is this wast? A lesse liuing <hi>would suffice, a lighter</hi> Cloke <hi>would serue</hi> Iupiter, <hi>and a</hi> lesse Church <hi>would serue the people to</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>assemble in. Of this sort are they, that by farre-fetched</hi> Trenches <hi>closely carried, doe seeke to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and ouerthrow all, as</hi>
      <note n="r" place="margin">
         <hi>Eusebius de vita cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant. lib. 1. c. 46.</hi>
      </note> Licinius <hi>in the dayes of</hi> Constantine, <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>afaire pretence (that the ayre with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the</hi> Citie <hi>was more wholsome then the aire within the</hi> Citie <hi>where the</hi> Churches <hi>stood) would haue drawne the people</hi> to serue God <hi>in</hi> the fields, <hi>that hee might haue</hi>
      <note n="s" place="margin">Cogitans euer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ionem Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2+ letters">
            <desc>••…</desc>
         </gap>s, ibid.</note>
      <hi>demolished the</hi> Churches <hi>in</hi> the Citie. <hi>Neither are</hi> they <hi>prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants onely, as the Romanists would haue it, that would pull downe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: but the</hi> Couetous polititian, <hi>whatsoeuer</hi> maske <hi>of</hi> Religion <hi>he putteth on, like an</hi> Atheist, <hi>and, worse then an</hi> heathen, <hi>aymeth at the</hi> spoile <hi>of his</hi> God, <hi>if it may serue for his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate</hi> Emolument. <hi>For who were they that first incroached upon</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuings, <hi>and drew away the tythes and maintenance from the secular</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>priests, and so by consequence from the Ministerie, under the name of</hi> good men, <hi>and</hi> Religious, <hi>but</hi> Monkes <hi>and</hi> Fryars? <hi>It was</hi> Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Wolsey, <hi>who by authoritie from the</hi> Pope, <hi>to satisfie his</hi> Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous <hi>or</hi> Ambitious <hi>desires, or</hi> both, <hi>did pull downe</hi> sortie Monaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>and ransacked them of their wealth. And as by credible testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, I haue heard it often related, the same</hi> Cardinall <hi>being sometimes</hi> Abbot <hi>of the</hi> Monasterie <hi>of</hi> Saint Albans, <hi>sent to the</hi> Prior <hi>and</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent <hi>there, that they should conuey up their</hi> plate <hi>to London, such as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> massiue <hi>and</hi> old, <hi>was growne out of</hi> fashion, <hi>under colour that he would take order for the new refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming &amp; refyning of that unfashiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble siluer, which being sent vp accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly in carts, did so wast in the mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting belike that</hi> vestigia nulla retror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sū, <hi>there came nothing backe againe
<pb facs="9"/> that euer was heard of. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>socuer face the</hi> Papists <hi>doe make of</hi> Church building, <hi>yet it seemes they preferre pollicy before their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, for every where, saith a late</hi> Obseruant Trauailer <hi>in the</hi> lowe Countries, <note n="t" place="margin">Mr. Ioseph Hall: dec. 1. ep. 5.</note> Churches fall, and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites Colledges rise; <hi>so that not onely the</hi> furie <hi>of</hi> warre <hi>hath ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Churches, but euen superstition for aduantage, doth that among st them, which couetousnesse would faine doe among st vs,</hi> robbe God <hi>of his</hi> houses, <hi>and seruice, of his tithes and maintenance. Wherefore the great</hi> Cardinall, <hi>who accuseth vs, to haue</hi>
      <note n="u" place="margin">Angelis &amp; hominibus cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum tenentibus omnia &amp; illis delita &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis salutaria Monumenta eripuerunt. Bellar. In pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat: de lib. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit.</note> bereaued both Saints and Angels <hi>in heauen of all</hi> Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments due to them, or heathfull to vs, may a little turne his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint vpon his <hi>owne friends and sectaries, and tell them of the spoile and dilapidations occasioned in sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred</hi> and holie <hi>things, by their owne</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <hi>couetous and ambitious pollicie. But to leaue their</hi> Ruines, <hi>and come to our present building: I finde seuerall obiections made, a little hindering the forwardnesse of wel-disposed people toward a</hi> worke so good. <note n="1" place="margin">1</note>
      <hi>Some doubt least their should be superstition in building up Churches, seeing (as they say) wee finde neither the name of</hi> Church <hi>in</hi> Scripture, <hi>nor the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Churches</hi> commanded. <note n="2" place="margin">2.</note>
      <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers finde fault that an Abby Church should be reedified.</hi>
      <note n="3" place="margin">3.</note>
      <hi>Some are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the</hi> greatnesse <hi>of it, because a lesse would serue the people.</hi>
      <note n="4" place="margin">4.</note>
      <hi>And some againe suspect the faithfull im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of the</hi> money <hi>collected. To all which, seeing I haue already excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the length of an</hi> Epistle, <hi>under your Graces Reformation, I am bold to answer.</hi>
      <note n="1" place="margin">1.</note>
      <hi>The</hi> first, <hi>who doubt</hi> superstition, <hi>and finde no</hi> Scripture <hi>for</hi> Churches, <hi>I would desire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that, euen the</hi> Name <hi>Church</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>(in our tongue signifying</hi>
      <note n="x" place="margin">Church, Ky<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rith, Dom: the Lords house Angl. Scott: Ger:</note> Gods house,) <hi>is read for the</hi>
      <note n="y" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> 1. Cor. 11. 18.</note> place of Christian Assemblies, <hi>in</hi> St. Paul to the Corinthians: <hi>and the</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement <hi>for building and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring such places of prayer is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in that generall</hi> rule: <note n="z" place="margin">1. Cor. 14 26.</note> let all things be done to edifying; <note n="a" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> 1. Cor. 14. 40.</note> let all things bee done honestly and by order: <hi>which must needes respect the comlines of the</hi> place, <hi>if possible to be obtained. And therefore when</hi> some <hi>at the first erecting of comelie and spacious</hi> houses <hi>of</hi> prayer, <hi>in the time of</hi> Constantine <hi>cauilled at their</hi> greatnesse <hi>and</hi> decencie, <hi>because in pers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cution they were more</hi> homely, <hi>the</hi> Gangren Councell <hi>made a</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non <hi>against such as should affirme, that the</hi> houses <hi>of God ought to bee</hi> bare <hi>and</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Contemptibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. Hieron: Zanch. in prec. 4.</note> contemptible; <hi>for they may be</hi> simple <hi>and bare upon occasion and necessitie, but they ought not to be so, when there is peace, opportunitie</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <hi>and authoritie to illustrate them. And whereas it is obiected, that there is no expresse and particular charge in</hi> Scripture <hi>for</hi> Churches: <hi>no more there was for</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Hospinian: de orig. Templ. ca. 4.</note> Synagogues <hi>in the law, yet they were</hi> builded, <hi>and</hi> fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, <hi>by the seruants of</hi> God, <hi>and euen by</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 4. 15. 16. Iohn. 18. 20.</note> Christ Iesus himselfe, <hi>and the</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">As 15. 21.</note> Apostles, <hi>and they were worthily commended, who did build</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 7. 5.</note> Synagogues, <hi>when the destruction of them was much lamented. But to free our selues from</hi> suspition <hi>of any Superstitious conceipt, of materiall</hi> Churches, <hi>we are not so inamored of them, as the</hi> Iewes were, <hi>or the</hi> Papists are, <hi>who suppose an inherent</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">Ps. 74. 8.</note> holinesse <hi>in their</hi> stones <hi>and</hi> orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>that the building of them is</hi> meritorious <hi>to</hi> saluation, <hi>expiating murders committed; and that</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate prayers <hi>are</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Bellarm: de cultu sactorum lib 3. cap. 9.</hi>
      </note> bettered, <hi>when they are vttered within a consecrated</hi> Circle. <hi>we know that</hi> Christ Iesus <hi>is</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
      <hi>our true and</hi>
      <note n="i" place="margin">Chrisius ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licuon Dei Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum. Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius in 2. Reg. 12. ex Tertull.</note> Catholike Temple, <hi>which sanctifieth our prayers when they are made in him onely; and that through him our</hi> bodies <hi>and</hi> soules, <hi>are made Temples of the holy Ghost, and wheresoeuer our</hi> Supplications <hi>are offered in</hi> spirit and truth, <hi>they are alike acceptable to</hi> God. <hi>For what</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">
         <hi>Quid sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis hi lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des habere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turrant. par: in dedic. Eccl.</hi>
      </note> sanctitie can there bee in stones saith Saint Bernard, <hi>much like a</hi> Protestant, <hi>but that</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">
         <hi>Sancta sunt anima propter inhabitantem spiritum Dei in nobis, sancta sunt corpora propter ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas: sacta est c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam propter Corpora do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. ibid.</hi>
      </note> the place is made holy by the bodies of Saints there assembled, the bodies are sanctified by the soules, and the soules by the holie Ghost dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in them. <hi>Neither is Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building a worke of it selfe acceptable to</hi> God, <hi>but as it is referred to</hi> his seruice, <hi>as it is used for the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of</hi> holie men to <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>Hospinian: de orig: Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plor. 6. 6.</hi>
      </note> praise God, to pray to him, to heare his word, to administer the sacraments, and to nourish faith and charitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst Gods people. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/> Saint Hierome reprooues the vanitie of great buildings, when men haue no care of other dueties and vertues; when they <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Ad Demetri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad: ad Nepoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: Ministro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nulla Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctra. ib.</hi>
      </note> adorne their Churches, and make no good choice of Ministers, <hi>nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the seruice of God how sleightly that is performed. And Saint</hi> Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostome <hi>commendeth building of churches upon this condition, that if</hi> a man doe it with other graces and vertues, it <note n="o" place="margin">
         <hi>Cum cateris bonis addita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum est be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, sine cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris bonis passio est sacularis gloria. clnys. oper. imperf. in Matt. 23.</hi>
      </note> is an addition to his other vertues and goodnesse: but if hee haue care to builde Churches without other good workes, it is but a passion ofsecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and vaine gloris. <hi>And when they are built with greatest state, if the</hi> word <hi>of</hi> God <hi>bee silenced in them, his seruice and sacraments pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, then with</hi> Saint Halirie; <hi>we affirme that the</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">
         <hi>Montes mihi &amp; lacus &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>rceres &amp; 10. ragines tutrores sunt. Hil contr. Auxent.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Church of God is not</hi> bound to faire buildings: <hi>but</hi> mountaines and lakes, prisons and
<pb facs="12"/> gulphes, <hi>are safer then they. Yet with the truth, and right seruice of God, which by his great blessing</hi> we <hi>enioy, they are</hi> excellent Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, holie <hi>to the</hi> Lord, <hi>and</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles amiable <hi>to all faithfull hearts: and with</hi> St. Austin, <hi>we say, that</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">
         <hi>Hodie malibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines qui couā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur si sieri pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit, non esseecclesias vbiillis praedicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur praecepta des, noune &amp; ipsū Christium occiderens, si in terra viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium inueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent? August. ser. 220. de tempore.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>such as would haue</hi> no Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches where the Ordinances of God should be preached, it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie they would euen kill Christ, if they found him againe vpon the earth. 2. <hi>Secondly whereas some object that the purpose is to reedifie an</hi> Abby Church, <hi>as though it were some needelesse forlorne</hi> Monument of superstition; <hi>It is farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise: for this</hi> Church <hi>was reserued from the spoile, purged from the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and purchased by the inhabitants, for a</hi> parish Church, <hi>so created and consecrated to</hi> Gods diuine seruice, <hi>in the time of Reformation, and by the Authoritie of</hi> King Edward the
<pb facs="12"/> sixt of blessed <hi>memorie, and so hath continued, with the frequent resort of many passengers, and a great people inhabiting the towne. 3. But a lesse</hi> Church <hi>(will some say) would serue the people. It is true, but thē who shold haue the parings &amp; the shreds?</hi>
      <note n="s" place="margin">
         <hi>Arbore deie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta qutuis colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git ligna.</hi>
      </note> Whē a Trce fals, cuerie one gathereth vp the stickes. <hi>Great things by that meanes come to little. When his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie was pleased to prouide for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire of this Church, hee knew well that a lesse</hi> coate would haue ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the little boy in Xenophon, <note place="margin">Xenoph. Cyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pad.</note>
      <hi>then his owne, and the</hi> greater would haue fitted the bigger; <hi>that a</hi> lesse Church <hi>would haue serued the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple perhaps for fitnesse, but yet his</hi> high wisdome <hi>deemed the preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a propertie to bee best</hi> Iustice: <hi>and would haue</hi> Suum cuique, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, <hi>his owne,</hi> were it great or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: <hi>supposing it to be</hi> et pessimi ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplinec sui saeculi, a bad example <note place="margin">Traian: apud Plinium,</note>
      <pb facs="13"/> vnbecomming his peaceable and religious gouernement, to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>the limme-poling of such ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Monuments, especially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so necessarie for the recourse of his louing subiects, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring witnesse of the first entrance of the Christian faith into this Realme, by the blood and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome of Saint</hi> Alban, <hi>being a true storie, although some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing disfigured by the fabulous</hi> Additions <hi>of the superstitious. And lastly, touching the feare and suspition of the faithfull Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the money collected, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I cannot say as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, in the time of King</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoas <hi>so peremptorilie,</hi> there neede no account bee taken of the men, to whome the money is deliuered for the workemen, because they deale faithfully: <note place="margin">2 King. 12. 15.</note>
      <hi>yet it is certaine, that hitherto, they</hi>
      <pb facs="13"/>
      <hi>haue proceeded verie carefully, prouided their materials verie fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gallie, and forwarded the worke verie industriouslie, not desiring to ingrosse the mony, further then the necessitie of the worke requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and still keeping a booke of accompts, therein ready to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite all their proceedings, to the examination and censure of those worthie Knights adioyning, or to any other well-willer to this busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, who shall request it. For the continuance of which faithfull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, considering howe strong a motiue the vigilant eye, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant caution of the</hi> Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Father, my Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoppe of London <hi>will bee to the under-takers, I dare promise all good dealing; yet if standers-by may doe any good, both I and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue vowed to bee inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue into the businesse, and (fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="14"/> anie miscarriage,) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and clamour against the faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But I rest in hope of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Office, wherein I may rather commend their doings, then finde fault. In the meane time, ceasing to bee further troublesome to your Grace, I humbly take my leaue, neuer ceasing to pray, as dutie bindeth mee, for the prosperous &amp; victorious reigne of our dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, and his royall issue, that the weakest in his house may bee like</hi> Dauid, <hi>and his house a sure house, like</hi> Dauids, <hi>euen like Gods house, and as an Angell of the Lord, before the people: And for your Grace, that after manie successe-full labours in your pasto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Charge, by ruling and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Church of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied in this life, inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with comfort of conscience, outwardlie with double honour,
<pb facs="14"/> you may receiue an incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Crowne of righteousnesse and glorie, from that great Shepheard of the Sheepe, Christ le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces most humble and dueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chaplaine William Westerman.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>