<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honorable, Woolstone Dixi, Lord MAIOR of the famous Cittie of London.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103652_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15038</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25341.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103652</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honorable, Woolstone Dixi, Lord MAIOR of the famous Cittie of London.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The enemie to vnthryftinesse : publishing, by lawes, documents and disciplines. A right rule, for reformation of pride, and other prodigall and riotous disorders, in a common wealth: for the worthines of directions, a perfect mirrour for all maiestrates: (especially) of cities. And for sound counsels, and admonitions, a carde to compasse, or euery yong gentleman, honorablie and profitably to gouerne his actions. Partely, drawne out of the sage gouernme [n] t, of the most worthie emperour, Alexander Seuerus: and (generallye) discoueringe the vnsufferable abuses now raigning in our happie English co [m] mon wealth. By George Whetstons gent</title>
                 <author>Whetstone, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 36 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honorable, Woolstone Dixi, <hi>Lord</hi> MAIOR of the famous Cittie of London.</head>
   <head type="sub">
      <hi>To the Right worshipfull, Sir</hi> Edward Osburne, <hi>knight,</hi> and other the Aldermen his Assistantes: and to their learned Counseller, <hi>M. Seriant</hi> Fleetwood, <hi>Recorder of the</hi> same CITIE: his approoued good frende and Kinsman.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT HONORABLE, AND Worthie Maiestrates: hauing compiled this Booke, in the tyme of the Right worshipfull, Sir Edward Osburns Maioraltie: I dedicated the same with my ready seruice, to the worthie Maiestrats of this famous CITIE. To whom the execution of the Diciplines, contayned therein (cheefely) belongeth: I bowldly saye, if the Booke had beene as effectually regarded as it was curiously searched a number might haue made profit of my Trauell: but as olde woundes, requier deepe searchinge, euen so cankred Vices are not to be cured, but with seuere chastisments: This Booke discouereth many and so dangerous euilles: as euery man that hath care of his posterytie, is bound to be a suter for reformation: The contents therof I humbly submit vnto your graue Censures The honor of Reformation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth vnto your wisdomes, the benefit to the publick weale: and the bare trauell (only) is due vnto me: Which as at the first, I dedicated the same, for the seruice of this CITIE euen so: in this second Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, I patronize the Booke with your honorable &amp; right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full protections: no more, but accomplishment of perfect desires, with acknowledgement of my dutie and seruice.</p>
   <p>To your Honor and Worships,</p>
   <p>George Whetstons.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>