<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103737_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02618</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12747</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103737</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A happy husband or, Directions for a maide to choose her mate : As also, a wiues behauiour towards her husband after marriage. By Patricke Hannay, Gent. To which is adioyned the Good wife, together with an exquisite discourse of epitaphs, including the choysest thereof, ancient or moderne. By R.B. Gent</title>
                 <author>Hannay, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Redmer, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Redmer, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>192 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="35"/>
   <pb facs="35"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be obiected (Reader) that small is the concurrence, lesse the coherence in the titles of these two Subiects, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santly concluding that it were pittie; Death should so soone seaze on a good-wife by the course of nature, as shee is had heere in pursuit by <hi>Deaths remaind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>r.</hi> But this obiection may be answered by a twofold solution: First, the Printers importunacie, whose desire was in regard of the breuitie of the former part, to haue it by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of some other proper Subiect enlarged; t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> whose reasonable demand I equally condescen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Secondly, the Subiects propriety, which, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sceuer by the iudgement of the Critik censurer traduced (the pitch of whose knowledge aimes rather at taxing then teaching) concurres as well with the precedent Title, as Man with mortalitie, Time with mutabilitie, Life with death. And as the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>re vertuous the neerer ofttimes their disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which no doubt proceedes from Gods mercy
<pb facs="36"/>
that they might haue of him a fuller contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; so we commonly see the best Wiues limited to the shortest times, approued by that Maxime:</p>
   <lg>
      <l>For this each daies experience seemes to show</l>
      <l>Ill wiues liue longer farre then good ones doe.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Let this suffice: if not, let the Subiect it selfe write his censure, whose singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie makes of each thing an error.</p>
   <p>MVSOPHILVS.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>