<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103558_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02405</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12534</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103558</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The great and famous battel of Lutzen : fought betweene the renowned King of Sweden, and Walstein; vvherein were left dead vpon the place between 5 and 6000. of the Swedish party, and between 10 and 12000. of the Imperialists, where the King himselfe was vnfortunatly slain, whose death counterpoyz'd all the other. Pappenheim, Merode, Isolani, and divers other great commanders were offred up like so many sacrifices on the Swedish altar, to the memory of their king. Here is also inserted an abridgment of the Kings life, and a relation of the King of Bohemia's death. Faithfully translated out of the French coppie</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bourne, Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 39, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>VVEE see that in the greater Maps things are expressed more plainly then they can be in the smaller, though they be draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en all by one skill: So Vertue in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces is more perspicuous, then in Plebeians; in the sormer shee is drawen at length with all her dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions; in the latter shee is limn'd in little, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visible, vnlesse you approach very neere her. And, indeed, this is consonant to Natures owne Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, who suffers the vitali spirits in the body to go to the least member, yea to the very fingers end; yet doth shee most plentifully bestow them where shee hath the greatest imployment for them: so on the vulgar shee conferres gifts sutable to so lowe a Calling: But in Princes and Monarchs, shee cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuples and irradiates her ornaments, because by them she speakes, and giues Lawes to Humanitie. Yet is not this Rule so generall, that it often suffers not an exception: for as Nature distinguisheth betweene the Subject and the Prince by Soveraigntie, so doth shee betweene Prince and Prince by Vertue, and Abilitie. That this is true, this our deare Tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call subject will serue for a liuely and cleare demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration, whom neither this Age, nor any of the former could paralell in the management both of the Scepter, and the Sword. In his whole Reigne, his Prudencie at home hath not deserued more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration then his Prowesse abroad: For indeede, from his Youth vpwards, <hi>Mars</hi> hath beene the Spheare wherein he hath mooved, into which vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Iustice first hall'd him, and out of which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but shee appeased, or Death could remooue him. Hee was a Generall ere a Man, and with a yet
<pb facs="3"/>vnreaped Chin mowed downe his Enemies before him. With many Kingdomes at once hee waged warre, from all which hee forced conditions ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to him and his. This was not without the amazement of all men, to see a Poynt oppose and conquer so vaste a circumference. In his warres I will onely obserue three things, His Way to Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, his behaviour in it, his Carriage after it. For the first, hee did animate his Souldiers rather by Fighting, then Exhorting; nor did hee challenge to himselfe any advantage aboue the meanest of them, but Honour and Commaund. Hee knew that it is in Empire, as in the Bodie, where the most dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous diseases flowe from the Head: Wherefore hee work'd on their manners by his owne, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly firme Ciment of a Generall and his Armie. Hee well understood that Faith and Loyaltie are not to bee expected where wee impose thraldome and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude, and therefore at times he would bee fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar as wel with the Common Souldier as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder. His Invention, and execution of all Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary stratagems were ever twinnes: for in all his Conquests hee owed as much to his Celeritie, as Valour. When his foes were in their Tents secure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly discoursing of him, as a farre off, hee like the Wolfe, broke into their fable, to their irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble astonishment. They could not withstand the force of his Fame, much lesse that of his Armes. One feather more I must adde, without which his Victories had not been fully plumed, nor could haue soared so high, and that was this: Hee never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded any man to an Enterprise, in which hee would not himselfe make one. Hee taught them as well by Hand, as Tongue. I may adde, that neither Antiquitie can, nor Posteritie ever shall produce a Prince so patient of all Military wants, as of meate,
<pb facs="3"/>drinke, warmth, sleepe, &amp;c. all which are necessary to the maintenance of life. In divers sufferings of his hee recalls to my mind the most accomplisht of the Romans, <hi>Cato,</hi> who leading his Troups through the contagious and poysonous Deserts, was ever the last of his Army that dranke, saue once, when he began to them all in water taken from a spring su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected to be envenomed.</p>
   <p>Thus much of his way to Victorie, now let vs come to his Deportment in it. After all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests, such a calme immediately ensued, that the passed storme was soone forgotten, and the Enemie appeared rather like one suddenly wakened, then frighted. There was not any of his Victories that washed not her hands of all cold and innocent blood. He was so severe a Iusticer, that he ofen revēged the violating of his mercifull Decrees euen vpon the place, &amp; sometime on men of qualitie, whom he affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. The Lawes of Retaliation hee knew so well, that hee gaue to all men punctuall satisfaction for all offences received from his partie, according to the nature of the wrong done. For this cause his Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall (like the Roman) stood euer open. All his great Atchieuements were ever attended by Devotion within, and Circumspection without. He first prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God, and then provided for man, at once having an eye on his enemies next designes, &amp; his souldiers present necessities. The greatest of his glories pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased with blood &amp; sweat, could neither change the estate of his mind, or copie of his countenance. The true greatnesse of his spirit was such, that in all his actions he placed Ostentation behind, &amp; Conscience before him, &amp; sought not the reward of a good deed from Fame, but from the deed it selfe. I conclude this poynt with this assertion, That Honestie had as strict, and great a command over him, as Necessitie
<pb facs="4"/>over mankind. He was a Prince of so great &amp; cleare a fame, that Envie her selfe blushed to oppose it, and therefore was forced to assume the maske of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, under which she might securely display her inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues. Religion, Religion, it is thou that shouldst v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, but dost estrange hearts, and makest us seeke to take away euen those liues that gaue us ours. Let a man haue in eminency all the Cardinall and Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall vertues, he of a contrary sect looks on all these through a mist raised by his malice, which makes him either not see them at all, or not as they are. O <hi>Iesus, Iesus,</hi> in thy best blessed time gather thy straied flock into one fold, &amp; let Truth and Peace kisse each other. This testimony the perfections of this Prince drew from me, who was abstemious &amp; continent in euery thing, saue in the search of Glory and Vertue.</p>
   <p>It now remaines that I say something of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Treatise, in which is contained the last and greatest Battell of this King, his deplored Death, and other weightie Circumstances. The Originall is French, written by one of the ablest Pennes of that Nation. Hee begins at the Kings comming downe into <hi>Germany,</hi> and extends his Story to his death. Of all the Moderne Histories, I dare make it the <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus;</hi> for it is written in a stile so Attick, and so judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, that it may well be called, The French <hi>Tacitus.</hi> What hath been before deliver'd in other Discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses concerning this Subject, is to this nought else but a Faile. The full and perfect Translation of this rare piece, I heere promise the Courteous Reader; and in the meane time, intreat him to weare as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, this Branch, by which hee may judge the whole body,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Dix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>