<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the ancient, religi∣ous, and learned Lady, the Lady COPPEN.</title>
           <author>Winterton, Ralph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103073_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01645</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11778</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103073</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the ancient, religi∣ous, and learned Lady, the Lady COPPEN.</title>
                 <author>Winterton, Ralph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gerards meditations : written originally in the Latine tongue by Iohn Gerard Doctour in Divinitie, and superintendant of Heidelberg. Translated and revised by Ralph Winterton fellow of Kings Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Gerhard, Johann</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Buck, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Daniel, Roger</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 323, 13, 155, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the ancient, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and learned Lady, the Lady COPPEN.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He earth is watered with drops from above, and in vapours sends them up again: The rivers come from the sea, and flow back again: The aire will cleave the rock to get up to its place again: The fire came down from heaven, and thither it tends up again. From the mixture of these elements, all bodies have their temperaments: Those have in them a character of naturall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and these should follow them. This character an illiterate man may see in creatures without sense; and he that is learned may reade to the life in creatures that have sense. Man is the Epitome of all perfections in other creatures: But without this character he is like to
<pb facs="6"/>
none of them. He hath spent his time ill at the Vniversitie that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the first principles, and he would be sent back again to learn the first elements. In the soul of man, as <hi>Galen</hi> saith, there is an art of arts, and in the bodie of man an instrument of instruments: Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is the art, and the hand is the instrument: I have both, and both are the Lady <hi>COPPENS.</hi> I have reason to acknowledge it, and an hand to subscribe to it.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Ladiships servant</hi> Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>h Winterton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>