<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, EDVVARD, Lord DEN∣NY, Baron of WAL∣tham, my bountifull, and dearely honored PATRON.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103672_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B13857</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12658.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103672</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, EDVVARD, Lord DEN∣NY, Baron of WAL∣tham, my bountifull, and dearely honored PATRON.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Contemplations vpon the historie of the old Testament. The seuenth volume. In two bookes. By Ios. Hall D.D</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 516, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="120"/>
   <pb facs="120"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, EDVVARD, <hi>Lord</hi> DEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NY, <hi>Baron of</hi> WAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham, <hi>my bountifull,</hi> and dearely honored PATRON.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>One can challenge so much right in these Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, as your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, vnder whose happy shade they receiued their first concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Vnder this Iuniper of yours,
<pb facs="121"/>haue I (not driuen by force, but drawne by pleasure) slept thus long, sweetly, safely; and haue receiued these Angelicall touches: How iustly may your Lordship claime the fruits of your owne fauours? Your carefull studies in this booke of God, are fit to bee exemplary; which haue so en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched you, that your teacher shall gaine. In this reach of diuine thoughts, you shall see <hi>Benhadads</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solence taken downe by <hi>Ahabs</hi> victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, an humble (though Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>atrous) <hi>Israelite</hi> carrying it from an insul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Pagan: You shall see in <hi>Ahab</hi> the impotent passions of greatnesse, in <hi>Naboth,</hi> bleeding honesty; in <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebel</hi> bloudy hypocrisie, cruell craft; plotting from hell, pretending from heauen: You shall see the wofull suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse of an vniust mercy; <hi>Ahab</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faiting
<pb facs="121"/>what hee gaue, killed by him, whom hee should haue killed; You shall see resolute <hi>Michaiah</hi> opposing the mercenary Synode of Prophets, a beaten victor, an imprisoned free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; You shall see <hi>Ahaziah</hi> falling through his grate; <hi>Elijah</hi> climbing vp his mount, mounting vp to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; fetching fire from heauen, fetch't by a fiery charet to heauen. <hi>Elisha</hi> the heire of his mantle, of his spirit, no lesse maruellous in his beneficences, in his reuenges. What doe I foretell all? Mee thinkes I feele my selfe now too like an <hi>Italian</hi> host, thus to meet your Lordship on the way, and to promise before-hand your fare, and intertainment: Let it please your Lordship rather to see and allow your cheere; Indeed the feast is Gods, and not mine, wherein store striues with
<pb facs="122"/>delicacie; If my cookery hurt it not, it is enough: Through your hands, I commend it to the world, as I doe your Lordship, and my honorable good Lady to the gracious protection of the Almightie; iustly vowing my selfe</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Lordships in all</hi> faithfull obseruance for euer to command, <hi>IOS: HALL.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>