<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE COVRTEOVS READER.</title>
           <author>G., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103960_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06372</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16843</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103960</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE COVRTEOVS READER.</title>
                 <author>G., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true originall edict of Nants : as it was enacted by Henry the third, and confirmed by the last French King Henry the fourth of famous memory. And reestablished by Lewis the thirteenth, for the better assurance of those of the reformed religion, as appeareth by the Kings Edict of peace, dated in the campe at Mompellier the nineteenth of October 1622. and proclaimed throughout all his dominions for a finall ending of all ciuill troubles. Cum priuilegio</title>
                 <author>France</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Garrett, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 53, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE COVRTEOVS READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He powerfull God of Armies, who onely giues true strength vnto the arme, and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vnto the heart, to fight the battels of his holy name and truth, euen in the midst of hopelesse perils, hath in all ages stood for the miraculous deliuerance of his afflicted Church, when pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posterous and maleuolent minds vrged the finall ruine and extirpation thereof. This cannot in any thing more eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare, then in the bloudie and fearefull agitations of the French Church, vnder the troublesome reignes of Henry the third and Henry the fourth, of indelible me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie: when priuate massacres and open hostilitie had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most extinguished the chiefe Nobilitie and gentrie of France, and yet in the very instant of dispaire, God with his mightie finger toucht the Kings heart the third Henry, and opened the eyes of his royall vnderstanding, which produced this happie Edict of Nants now here published, for a faire pacification of all former troubles and combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions. Yet was not this fire so cleare extinguished (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the deuastations of armes, during the reigne of the last renowned Henrie) but that the opposite spirits of these times found out some vnquenched sparkes, whereof to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a new flame of cruell warre and bloudshed, euen in the young and ambitious yeares of this present Lewis the thirteenth, the which notwithstanding after some sensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble feeling of his heauie hand and displeasure, it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="3"/>
God to moderate and qualifie, by informing his Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mind, that an externall vnion and formalitie of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, cannot supplant the seeds of thirstie and insatiable ambitions, which do but attend ciuill and intestine dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the better to propagate their haughtie and imperious designes. As proceeding from one and the selfe same cause, these instant French troubles haue bene accorded with one and the like effect, the Articles of this present Peace being drawne and extracted from the modell and frame of the former Edict of Nants in this Treatise di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulged, which being at least more large and copious, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent comparing the one with the other, the best vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings may more absolutely iudge, both of the forme and substance of the present conditions. And to this end onely (courteous Reader) I haue with some charge caused this originall Edict of Nants to be translated and published, being desirous herein to gratifie thee, as he that expects no other reward then thy acceptation and loue, and that thou wilt ioyne with me, and all those well affected to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, in heartie desire and prayer, that this happie accord may stand firme and permanent. And thus I recommend my trauell and labours to thy loue, and remaine as I will euer perseuere,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy very louing and well affected: W. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>