<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO THE REVEREND FA∣ther in God, IOHN, L. Bishop of London.</title>
           <author>Fletcher, G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103162_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09911</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20174</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103162</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO THE REVEREND FA∣ther in God, IOHN, L. Bishop of London.</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The young divines apologie for his continuance in the Vniuersitie : with certaine meditations, ritten by Nathaniel Povvnoll, late student of Christ-Church in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Pownall, Nathaniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lownes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 168 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ TO THE REVEREND FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God, IOHN, L. Bishop of London.</head>
   <p>RIght woorthie, and reuerend Father in God.</p>
   <p>Blame not your ancient Obseruer, if nowe, after he hath recouered in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, at Cambridge, that life, which he lost at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from Oxford, he ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses aniew, as it wear out of his ashes, to do his humble
<pb facs="3"/>
seruice to your Lordship: and, indeede, to whome can any fruit that comes from him, bee with more right presented thē to him, in whose garden, and vnder whose shadow it griew? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whose hand should this small booke, though wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his owne Epistle, be deliuered, but vnto that, to which it hath before giuen so many Epistles? whear can it looke for protection with more hope thē whear it hath formerly, with all fauour, founde it.</p>
   <p>If your Lordship thear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will be pleased to be the defender of this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, and to breath, as I
<pb facs="3"/>
may truely say, the breath of life againe into his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Meditations, that so beeing annimated aniew with those vnspeakeable sighs, and alike feruent zeale of spirit, whearwith they wear first, as in fierie chariots, carried vp into heau'n; I doubt not but they will seeme, beeing so quickned, to any that shall reade them (especially if, as <hi>Iob</hi> wished in a case not much vnlike, his foule wear in his foules stead) no cold, or dull, or dead lettets: and in so doing, you shall not onely followe him into his graue, but call him out of it with this so speciall a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit,
<pb facs="4"/>
binding with the dead in one knot of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse all his Friends that yet liue, and cannot but ioy to see your Lordships fauour out-liue the person, on whom it is bestowed: of whome my selfe, being the least, shal euer thinke I am most bound to be.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your L. to command in</hi> all good seruice, G. FLETCHER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>