<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103164_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10179</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20456</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103164</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certaine quæres : propounded to the bowers at the name of Iesvs and to the patrons thereof. Wherein the authorities, and reasons alleadged by Bishop Andrewes and his followers, in defence of this ceremony, are briefly examined and refuted; the mistranslation of Phil. 2.10.11 cleared, and that text, with others acquitted both from commanding or authorizing this novell ceremony, here gived to be unlawfull in sundry respects</title>
                 <author>Prynne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stam, Jan Fredericksz</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 41, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A PREFACE.</head>
   <p>FOr the better clearing of this ceremony to be no duty of this text of Phil. 2.10.11. be pleased in briefe to take notice of these foure particulars: First, what the Fathers (whom <note n="*" place="margin">Page 84.85, 86.110 unto 141. <hi>None of the Fathers tell us (writes he) that this reverence of bowing the knee is to be done at the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, neither is there ANY ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse or full autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in them Therefore all that I strive for is that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers by their exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this text do not crosse and contradict that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which our Church doth seeme to gather out of it. In a word, I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour not that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers should bee fully for me, but I hope to make good that they are not against me. I desire in this matter to have them lookers on: So he against Bp.</hi> Andrewes <hi>and others, who say all the fathers are for them, that is, not for, but against them.</hi>
      </note>Mr. <hi>Page</hi> confesseth not to bee for this ceremony) generally interpret to be the name above every name mentioned in this text. Very many of thē interpret it to be nothing else, <hi>but the very name of God, and Deity of Christ it selfe.</hi> So <hi>Tertullian</hi> de Trinitate. lib. Tom. 2. p. 261.262, <hi>Athanasius</hi> de Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Christi Contr. Apollinarium. p. 271. C. <hi>Hilary</hi> in Psa. 2. p. 196 H <hi>Ambrose, Rabanus Maurus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn Salisburie</hi> on Phil. 2.9, 10. <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysius Alexandrinus</hi> Epist. Contr. Paulum Samosatenum Bibl. Patr. Tom. 3. p. 74.75. <hi>Titus Bostrensis</hi> in cap. 1. Evang. Lucae. Ibid. Tom. 4. p. 339. E. <hi>Idacius</hi> advers. Varimadum. lib. Ibid. p. 622. a. <hi>Caesarij</hi> Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. 1. p. 650. <hi>Basilius Magnus</hi> de Spiritu Sancto ad Amphil. c. 8. Tom. 1. p. 180. <hi>Cyrillus Alexandrinus</hi> in Esayam l. 5. Tom. 1. p. 362. E.F. in Ioannis Evang. l. 11. c. 17. p. 666. c. 20. p. 669. a. c. 22. p. 670. D.E. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sauri. l. 13. Tom. 2. p. 270. E.F. <hi>Agobardus</hi> ad Ludovicum Imp. Bibl. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum. Tom. 9. pars 1. p. 556. g. h. <hi>Paschatius Ratbertus</hi> in Matth. Evan. lib. 10. Ibid. pars 2. p. 1156. b. c. lib. 11. p. 1177. b. Exposit. in Psal. 44. p. 1249. G. <hi>Ioannis Cyperis.</hi> de Inform. divini nominis. cap. 11. Ibid. Tom. 11. p. 499. E. <hi>Paulus Aquiliensis</hi> Patr. Cont. Felicem Vrgelium Epist. l. 2. <hi>Aquinas</hi> 3 <note n="*" place="margin">Apud Alchuvini Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. col. 1830.1831.</note> part. qu. 49. Art. 6. Conclusio. <hi>Alexander Alen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis</hi> Theol. Summa. pars 1. qu. 21. m. 1. Artic. 4. together with <hi>Chytraeus</hi> Postil. in Domin. Palmarum. pag. 160, <hi>Zanchius</hi> in Phil. 2.9, 10. and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moderne Expositors. Other Fathers and Writers interpret it, to be <hi>the name of the onely naturall begotten Sonne of God.</hi> Thus <hi>Hierom, Theodoret, Sedulius, Remigius, Beda, Haymo, Theophylact, Anselme,</hi> and <hi>Oecumenius</hi> on Phil. 2.10, 11. <hi>Basil</hi> de Spirit. Sancto. c. 8, Tom. 1. p. 180. <hi>Augustine</hi> Contr Maximinum, l. 2. c. 2. <hi>Sancti Procli</hi> Sermo in Transfig. Christi. Bibl. Patr. Tom. 1. pars 1. p. 536. C. <hi>Etherij &amp; Beati.</hi> l. 1. Ibid. Tom. 8. p. 342. <hi>Musculus, Aretius, Zanchius,</hi> with other late Expositors. Others interpret this name to bee nothing else, <hi>but the Glory, Fame, Lordship, Soveraignty, and universal dominion and Majesty of Christ.</hi> So <hi>Chrysostom</hi> &amp; <hi>Theodoret,</hi> in Phil, 2. <hi>Petrus Blesensis</hi> Serm. 46. Bibl. Patr. Tom. 11. pars 1. p. 210. C. and others of old. <hi>Olevian, Musculus, Gualther, Marlorat,</hi> Dr. <hi>Ayray,</hi> Bishop <hi>Babington,</hi> and the whole streame of moderne interpriters. Others refer this text
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>to his name Christ,</hi> as <hi>Paschatius Ratbertus</hi> Exposit. in Psal. 44. pag. 1246. g. <hi>Paulinus</hi> Epist. ad Augustinū, Bibl. Patr. Tom 5. pars 1. p. 210. e</p>
   <p>Secondly, What they meane by <hi>bowing the knee.</hi> Not any actuall bowing of the knee in this life, at the sound, sight, or hearing of the Name Iesus; but a <hi>Vniversall subjection of all creatures to the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lordship, judicature and supreme power of Christ, especially at the day of judgement, when this text shall be onely actually, litterally, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally fulfilled.</hi> This all the Fathers and Writers quoted in the Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix, <hi>Lame Giles,</hi> and premises, and all the Authors extant that I have seene, accord to bee the genuine, true, undoubted meaning. Bishop <hi>Andrewes,</hi> Dr. <hi>Boyes,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Page</hi> himselfe confessing it.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, To what this bowing must be given by the Fathers ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict: Not to the name Iesus, but <hi>immediately to Christ himselfe.</hi> Hence <hi>Hierom</hi> Com. l. 3. in Isayam 45. <hi>Gregory Nyssen</hi> de Anima &amp; Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect. disp. p. 104.212. <hi>Ambros.</hi> Enar. in Psal. 118. Octon. 20. <hi>Hilari</hi> de Trinitate lib. p. 64. <hi>Chrysost.</hi> Hom. 32. in 1 Cor. 12. <hi>Fulgentius</hi> Object. Arrianorum discus. pag. 204. <hi>Cyrillus Alexandrinus</hi> de Incarnatione Vnigeniti. c. 11.26. <hi>Hypolitus</hi> de Consummat. Mundi &amp; Antichristo. Orat. Bibl. Patr. Tom. 3 p. 17. b. <hi>Dionysius Alexandrinus.</hi> Contr. Paulū Samosatenum. Ib. p. 74. b. <hi>Prosper</hi> Exposit. in Ps. 102. f. 236. a. <hi>Paulinus</hi> Epist. ad Apiū. Bibl. Patr. Tom. 5. pars 2. p. 187. b. <hi>Sancti Procli</hi> Sermo in transfig. Christi, Ibid. p. 335. E. <hi>Arnobius</hi> Com. in Psa. 64. Bibl. Patr. pars 3. p. 262. a. <hi>Agobardus</hi> ad Lud. Imper. Ibi. Tom. 9. pars 1. p. 556. g. <hi>Angelomi</hi> Strom. in l. Regum. 2. c. 12. p. 740, E. <hi>Damascen</hi> Orthodoxae fidei. l. 3. c. 29. p. 433. <hi>C. Simeon Thess. Archiepiscopi</hi> de divino Templo Bibl. Patr. Tom. 12. pars 1. p. 880. C. <hi>Petrus Blesensis</hi> de Transfig. Dom Ibid. pars 2. p. 915. b. <hi>Nicholaus Cabasila</hi> de Vita in Christo. l. 6, Ibid. Tom. 14. p. 127. <hi>Papa Innocentius</hi> 5. in Circumcis. Dom. Sermo. Tom. 1. p. 95. de Contemptu Mundi. l. 2. c. 15. p. 445. with <hi>Brentius</hi> in Phil. 2. 9.10. and sundry others joyntly render and read this text; <hi>Mihi, ipsi, ei, illi,</hi> or <hi>coram illo flectotur omne genu, &amp;c.</hi> not <hi>in nomine,</hi> or <hi>ad nomen Iesu:</hi> to testifie, that this bowing of the knee in the text shall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, not to, or at the name Iesus; but to the <hi>very person of Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe.</hi> So Isay 45.23. &amp; Rom. 14.9.10, 11. expresly resolve. <hi>As I live saith the LORD, every knee shall bow to ME, and every tongue shall confesse to GOD.</hi> No colour therefore is there in this text for bowing at, or to the name IESUS, but onely to IESUS HIMSELFE, when we shall all joyntly appeare before his Tribunall. The rather, because <note n="b" place="margin">In Isal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am l. 5. ca. 55. Tom. 1. p. 362. E. In Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annis E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. l. 11. c. 17. p. 666 de Incarn Vnigeniti. c. 11. p. 114 Dialog. de Trinit. l. 3 p. 270. a.</note>
      <hi>St. Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> reads it thus. <hi>Vt in nomine Iesu Christi omne genu se flectat,</hi> coupling Christ and Iesus together, and making one as
<pb facs="3"/>
much the name in the text as the other. The <note n="c" place="margin">Surius Concil. Tom. 3, p. 274.</note>
      <hi>Councell of Franckford upon the Mane</hi> under <hi>Adrian</hi> the first, reads it thus. <hi>Cessate cum adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuum nominare, qui verus Deus. Et verus Dei filius; in cujus nomine omne genu flectitur, &amp;c.</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Bibl. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trū. Tom. 3. p. 75. b.</note>
      <hi>Dionysius Alexandrinus</hi> Epist. Contr. Paulum Samos. reads it thus. <hi>Vt in nomine ejus omne genu flectatur.</hi> Arnobius Can. in Psal. 88. thus. <hi>Ego primogenitum, ponam eum, ut in nomine ejus omne genu flectatur.</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">Bibl. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trū. Tom. 5. pars 3. p. 277. b.</note>
      <hi>Angelomus</hi> in his Strom. in l. 3. Regum c. 8. thus. <hi>Christo enimpropter gloriosae meritum passionis datum est nomen quod est super omne nomen: ut in nomine ejus omne genu flectatur, &amp;c.</hi>
      <note n="f" place="margin">Bibl. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trū. Tom. 9. pars 1. p. 770. b.</note>
      <hi>Pascha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Ratbertus</hi> in Matth l. 11. thus: <hi>Et donavit illi nomen quod est super omne nomen, ut in nomine DOMINI, omne genu flectetur, &amp;c.</hi> All which antiquities overthrow this bowing at the name Iesus.</p>
   <p>Fourthly, when and where this bowing shall be. <hi>Hypolitus</hi> de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>summat. mundi Orat.<note n="g" place="margin">Bibl. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trū. Tom. 9. pars 2. p. 1156. b.</note>
      <hi>Ephraim Syrus</hi> de Apparit. Crucis temp. Iudicij p. 230. &amp; 703. <note n="h" place="margin">Bibl. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trū. Tom. 5. pars 1. p. 924.</note>
      <hi>Gregentius Archiepisc. Tephensis</hi> Disp. cum Herba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Iudaeo. <note n="i" place="margin">Bibl. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trū. Tom. 12. pars 1. p. 880.</note>
      <hi>Simeon Thes. Arch.</hi> de divino Templo. <hi>Isiodor</hi> Hisp. Com. in Gen. c. 30. p. 301. in direct termes, to omit all others. Bp. <hi>Alley,</hi> Bp. <hi>Babington,</hi> Dr. <hi>Fulke,</hi> Dr. <hi>Willet,</hi> Dr. <hi>Boyes,</hi> Dr. <hi>Ayray,</hi> in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hereafter cited, and the whole current of <hi>Expositors,</hi> expresly conclude, <hi>That it shall bee onely in the generall Day of Iudgement, for time; before Christs tribunall, for place, when and where all things in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, earth, and under the earth shall stand before his Iudgement Seate, and there cast themselves downe joyntly before him, confessing him with one consent to be their Soveraigne Lord, and calling him their LORD.</hi> This <note n="l" place="margin">Page 73.74, 75, 80 81.</note> Mr. <hi>Page</hi> himselfe, and all our Antagonists doe and must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse to be the time and place of this genuflection, prophecied of ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than prescribed, or now commanded in this text: Since Isay 45.23. Rom. 14.9, 10, 11. Matth. 7.21, 22, 23. cap. 25.31, 32, 33, 34, 37, 41, 44, 46. Revel. 5.13, 14, 15. cap. 7.11, 12. Iohn 5.22, 23, 27, 28, 29. Acts 2.34.36. cap. 10.36. and other texts in the 1. and 7. <hi>Quaere</hi> thus determine it, past all dispute. Hence then I thus argue.</p>
   <p>If the name above every name, in which all knees must bow, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this text of <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10.11. bee not the name Iesus; the bowing of the knee, no litterall actuall present genus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but only the generall subjection of all creatures in Heaven, earth, &amp; under the earth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he very person of Christ as their LORD, not to or at his name Iesus; and that at the generall Day of Iudgement before Christs owne Tribunall, not in time of Divine Service or Sermons here on earth; then this bowing at the name Iesus, neither is nor can be <note n="m" place="margin">
         <hi>This Mr.</hi> Page <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth.</hi> p. 2.5, 73, 74, 75, &amp;c. <hi>the later part of whose booke is a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ormer in all Scholl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>rs judgement, whereupon it was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in by the Bishops, and not answered.</hi>
      </note> a duty war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted,
<pb facs="4"/>
much lesse prescribed by this text.</p>
   <p>But all this is apparant by the premised Fathers and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities.</p>
   <p>Therefore the conclusion undeniable, maugre all the late ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Pamphlets and passages to the contrary, of <hi>Widdowes, Shelford, Page, Heylyn, Wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n, Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ve, Moun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ague, Pocklington, Browne, Reede, Adams, a Coale from the Altar,</hi> Bishop <hi>White,</hi> or any other, who babble and scribble much in the Iesuits and Papists words, but prove nothing at all by Scripture or Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity for this Ceremonies use or lawfulnesse, or new duty of the text, now so much urged every where, point-blank against Iohn 5.23. <hi>That all men should honour the Sonne, even as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hey ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Father.</hi> But no men honour the Father thus in bowing at the recitall of his name. Therefore they ought not thus to honour the Sonne.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>