<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Scholasticall and Methodicall Institution of the common Places of Divinitie.</title>
           <author>Wither, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103024_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13952</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24261</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103024</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Scholasticall and Methodicall Institution of the common Places of Divinitie.</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe institution of the common places of sacred divinitie : Wherein, the truth of every place is proved, and the sophismes of Bellarmine are reprooved. Written in Latine, by Lucas Trelcatius, and Englished by Iohn Gawen, minister of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Trelcatius, Lucas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Baker, Michael.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Burton, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 595, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="12"/>
   <head>A Scholasticall and <hi>Methodicall Institution of the</hi> common Places of <hi>Divinitie.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ntending to lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in a briefe and Schoole Methode a <hi>Theologicall institutiō,</hi> we will premise two thinges, in stead of a Preface or introduction thereunto.</p>
   <p>The one of Divinitie it selfe, and of the Nature and verity thereof.</p>
   <p>The other concerning the order and Methode of our institution.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Divinitie</hi> wee meane not that first patterne, which in God is of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, nay, is God himselfe (for both God &amp; that which is in God is the selfe same in a simple Essence) wherein by
<pb n="2" facs="13"/> an indivisible and vnchangeable act, he knoweth both himselfe in himselfe, and out of himselfe all and singular thinges by himselfe, but the stampe out of that former expressed and shapened by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation and gratious communication thereof, eyther according to the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall nature in all men, or according to speciall grace &amp; measure of the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the Church.</p>
   <p>Hee that would enquire the veritie hereof, ought to consider two things, first, that it is, secondly, what it is.</p>
   <p>That there is such a stampe of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, the Nature of God, the light both of our owne Naturall conscience, and supernaturall knowledge revealed, as also the common experience of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ages doe declare.</p>
   <p>The <hi>Nature of God,</hi> for sith hee is by all meanes infinitely good, we must no way think that God wanteth a good meane to communicate good, whose property it is to bee a communicator of himselfe, or to communicate himselfe with other his creatures, according to
<pb n="3" facs="13"/> their condition<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 5.45.</note>.</p>
   <p>The light both of our <hi>Naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> by which clearely shining, all men haue this setled in their heartes, that theres is a Divination, and other kindes of divine communications<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.19 &amp; 2.24.25.</note> as also of supernatural <hi>Knowledge</hi> revealed whereby wee know that whole truth to bee fully and plainely registred in the holy scriptures, which was behoofefull for vs to know to our salvation.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Common Experience,</hi> for even the Gentiles themselues being strangers from God, had the Oracles of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell in stead of these from God rather then that they would deny that stamped Divininity, or bee saide to want the same<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 1.21.22.23.</note>, for hence it came to passe, that whereas among the Heathen, some of their Gods were thought to bee very Gods, some others to be such spirites, as they called <hi>Daemones,</hi> the heathens Divinity was held to bee of two partes, for the one treated of the Gods them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, the other of<note n="d" place="margin">Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> those spirites, which they called <hi>Daemones,</hi> that which
<pb n="4" facs="14"/> treated of their Gods,<note place="margin">August. lib. <hi>5.</hi> de Civit. Dei, cap. <hi>6.</hi>
      </note> was held of them to bee three-sold, as <hi>Augustine</hi> out of <hi>Varro</hi> teacheth, to wit, <hi>Poeticall, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall,</hi> and <hi>Civill,</hi> that which did set forth the power of those spirites, was two-fold: for whereas of those spirites, called <hi>Doemones,</hi> some were good, some evill: that which discoursed of the evill spirites who were to bee pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified and appeased, was called Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke and Inchantment: but the other which delighted the good with sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, was called Divine ministration and Expiation: therefore there is a Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
   <p>Now if you respect the true interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the word, it is defined thus, to bee a knowledge of the Oracles or speeches of God: but if the thing or matter it selfe; it is a true wisedome of divine thinges from God communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, eyther by meane Naturall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to inbred principles, or else by a meane more excellent, according to grace supernaturall.</p>
   <p>And of this <hi>Divinity</hi> wee speake in
<pb n="5" facs="14"/> this place, wee call it <hi>Wisedome</hi> by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Scripture:<note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor. 26.</note> first, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the thing, as being the most certaine declarer of principles, &amp; most noble Princesse of all sciences: secondly, for the singular meane or manner of knowing, for this wisedome is distinguished from that which in the Scripture is called earthly, sensuall, and diuellish.</p>
   <p>The subject of this Theological wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are matters divine, both for their Nature, and the manner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering: for whereas a Subiect hath two partes, the one which containeth the place of the matter, &amp; is called the thing considered: the other of the forme, and is the manner of conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it: wee obserue them both in the explication of this subiect: <hi>The thing considered</hi> is God himselfe, and all thinges disposed vnto God, that is all thinges divine, eyther of their owne nature, or by relation vnto God: <hi>The manner of considering</hi> is proportionable to Gods truth, even to the whole
<pb n="6" facs="15"/> truth, and everie part thereof alike (or equally) infused, fitted to the dignity of the deliverer to the nature of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as also to the condition of those, to whome it is delivered.</p>
   <p>And this is the nature and verity of Divinity: now wee will briefly shew the Methode of our Institution concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the same.</p>
   <p>There is a two-fold <hi>Methode</hi> of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, the one from Principles, the other vnto Principles, the one <hi>a Priori</hi> proceeding from the Cause to the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and from the first and highest to the lowest and last: the other <hi>a Posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ori,</hi> proceeding from the Effect to the Cause, or from the last and lowest to the highest and first: The vse of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is chiefest in sciences contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, of the latter, in the practicke (or actiue.)</p>
   <p>Now whereas Divinity in both these holdeth the first &amp; principal place, (by reason wherof, some haue distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished it into Contemplatiue and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue) and for that it affordeth a faculty
<pb n="7" facs="15"/> both of knowing and doing well, which is the right way of wisedome: it hath fallen out that D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>vinity hath been hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in a diverse M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>thod by diverse men, yet by all of them profitably and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
   <p>For whereas all order is taken ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the nature of thinges to bee considered. or from our better and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sier knowledge thereof, <hi>Calvin, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanthon, Ʋrsinus,</hi> haue done well, who observed an order of their better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in a method, vnfoulding by way of Analysis<note n="g" place="margin">Analyti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a.</note> in like manner, <hi>Hiperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Musculus, Hemingius, Zanchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> haue done well, observing the order of Nature<note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Synthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>a Synthesis,</hi> also is con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Analysis,</hi> beginning frō things granted to that vvhich is in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion.</note> in a Method of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing and couching thinges handsomly together. Wee in this our Institution will ioyne both these together, bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing<note n="i" place="margin">a Synthesi,</note> from the Methode of compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing the disposition, and<note n="k" place="margin">Ab Analy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si.</note> from the Methode of vnsoulding the invention of the same, that from both, the<note n="l" place="margin">Systema.</note> full constitution of this body of Divinity which we haue in hand may arise.</p>
   <pb n="8" facs="16"/>
   <p>Therefore by an order Syntheticall (as wee tearme it) wee will begin from the first Principles, that by the Means wee may come to the last: but we wil set downe a declaration, such as wee call Analyticall, of the first, middle and last thinges; first in teaching the truth by way of confirmation, then in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the falshood by way of confutatiō: that, by the helpe and benefite of the Definition of every point of Divinitie, and by the Analysis of the same, through the causes thereof: but this, by the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix (or addition) of the generall so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, which wee will lay vnder e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very place (or point) and set a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the principal arguments of our adversaries, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Bellarmines:</hi> this is our Methode.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>