<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1549</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103862_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15987</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2768</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103862</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The canticles or balades of Salomon, phraselyke declared in Englysh metres, by William Baldwin</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1549</date>
                 <publisher>Baldwin, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat thou mayste vnderstande this booke the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (Christen reader) thou shalte vnderstande that it is (as it wer) a dialoge betwene Christ and his churche, or as Origen calleth it, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> spousal song of Christ and his spouse: wherin there be fower singers. Christe the brydegrome accompanied with his frendes, good bishops and teachers: And the catholike churche his spouse accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with damoysels, yong christen soules. Betwene these is all spoken that is contayned in these balades. The whole matter as Anselme taketh it, is a prophecie, describyng the estate of the churche, and with what affecciō she desyred Christ in all tymes, bothe vnder the lawe of nature, of Moyses▪ and of the gospell. No doubt but it is an hie and misticall matter, and more darkely hyd than other partes of the scripture, by meanes of the wanton wordes: which also cause many to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it to be Gods wurde. Whose errour to redresse is the chief cause why I haue medled with the matter. And because the rediest way was to make a paraphrase, I haue attem<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pted it: &amp; that in meter, because they bee balades. And althoughe I bee not so playne in al thinges as I mought haue ben by meanes of my metres, yet I trust that suche as wyll reade them dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, shall haue great lyght in vnderstanding the texte. But this I tell the good reader, thou must reade them well, (for it is not once readyng nor twise that can make thee vnderstand them) &amp; in reading note the sentence more than the time, with the argumentes whiche go before and after the songes. And reade them orderly, so shall the proces of the matter helpe the muche. The exposicion of euery Hebrue wurd, I haue put last: which wil help the muche bothe to vnderstande the song and the texte. And to the entent thou lose not thy labour in readyng, I entend with the leaue of God shortly to set furth a boke of notes, and suche an exposicion of the Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical wurdes, as shal serue the for a cōmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary. In the meane whyle, the Lorde kepe the, &amp; augment thy knowlege. Amen.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Loue and lyue.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>