<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTI∣AN READER, BVT ESPE∣CIALLY TO E. B. HIS VERY much respected friend, Grace, and Glory</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103370_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06190</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16683</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103370</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTI∣AN READER, BVT ESPE∣CIALLY TO E. B. HIS VERY much respected friend, Grace, and Glory</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Come and see. The blisse of brightest beautie: shining out of Sion in perfect glorie : Being the summe of foure sermons preached in the Cathedrall Church of Glocester at commandment of superiours. By William Loe</title>
                 <author>Loe, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Law (Lawe), Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 57, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AN READER, BVT ESPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIALLY TO E. B. HIS VERY much respected friend, Grace, and Glory</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et God arise, and let his enemies<note place="margin">Psal. 68. 1.</note> be scattered, let them that hate him, flie before him. As the smoke vanisheth, so let them perish at thy presence (ô Lord) that haue euill will at Sion. But let them that loue and seeke the Lord, be euer ioyfull and glad in him, let them be telling his praises from day to daie. And if there be any man so brutish, that loueth not the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, let him be had in execration Maranatha.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 16. 22.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Seeing man being fallen is raised by Christ onely, man is returned to God, hauing turned awaie from all good. The Angels that fell are damned, man that sinned is pardoned. To man God hath giuen a motion neuer to<note place="margin">Picus Mirād. Hexapl.</note> ceasse vntill he rest in him, grace to guide him, goodnes to imbrace him, messengers of glad tidings to instruct him, faith to furnish him with the fulnesse of perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, sanctimony to dignifie him in this life, glorie to dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him in the other life. Seeing with Iesus Christ also is the fulnesse of ioy, whose name is saluation, whose pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion<note place="margin">Zan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h. in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chirid.</note> redemption, whose sacrifice satisfaction, whose bloud purgation, whose resurrectiō sanctification, whose ascension eternall glorification. And seeing that the
<pb facs="5"/>
Lord Iesus Christ is loue substantially, hauing nothing<note place="margin">Bern. de am. dei.</note> in him selfe but himselfe, being loue it selfe essentially, not accidentally, he is also loue causally, causing it in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as in the Elements, in the creatures, in the sweete symphonie of the whole vniuerse, and in the bitter iarres of mans corrupted nature, making men to be of one mind in an house, and of one heart in a common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. He is loue actiuely louing all things he hath made, man more particularly, his redeemed most especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, with a loue to the end, in the end, without end.</p>
   <p>Louing them in their election, when they could not loue him; louing them in their redemption when they would not loue him; louing them externally, for they haue a promise to enioy their outward blessings; louing them internally, for their hearts shall be comforted; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them eternally, for they shall euer be blessed with him in heauenly things. He is loue passiuely most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be beloued, being louing euerie daie in multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his blessings, being louing euery way in magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his mercies, louing vs first in preuenting vs merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, louing vs in continuance in guiding vs powerfully, louing vs last in perfecting vs eternally. Yea so louing that if he go to punish, he walkes a soft pace, he comes in the coole of the day: but to shew mercie he runnes; for he is gracious, righteous, yea our God is mercifull, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing three, or fowre of the generation of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse; but shewing mercy to thousands that loue him, and liue in his feare. Taste then, and see how gracious the Lord Iesus is, and how plentifull is his goodnesse, which he hath layed vp for them that feare him, and prepared
<pb facs="6"/>
for them that trust in him, euen before the sonnes of men. He being the perfection of Priesthood and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, of sacrifice and sacrament, so that now who so set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his heart vpon any thing but vpon the Lord <hi>Iesus,</hi> is liable to the extreme curse of Gods desertion. Set not then your hearts on beautie, beloued, it is but a forward blossome soone nipt; nor on pleasure, it is but a bitter pill lapt in sugar; nor on your belly, it is but the pantrie for the draft house; nor on riches, they are but guiles, and baites to insnare vs, which while they are in getting wearie vs, while they are possessed, befoole vs; and when<note place="margin">Picus Mirand. in Apolog.</note> we lose them, they crucifie vs. Set not your hearts on the fauour of Princes or Potentates, for they are but the sonnes of men; nor on ambition, it is but a feather tossed with the wind; nor on gay apparell, it is but rags; nor on goodly houses, they are but so many bonefiers against the day of doome; nor on any thing vnder the sunne: but only like, and loue them in and for the Lord <hi>Iesus</hi> sake, as they are either remedies for sin, or directions <hi>in ordine ad Deum</hi> for our vsefull necessities, and furtherances to further our future happinesse. But as for those who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spite the spirit of grace, and trample the blessed bloud of the new Testament vnder their feete, as do all sycophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing Papists, schismatizing Puritans, neutralizing Atheists, satanizing scorners of all godlinesse, truth, and honestie: I will euer pray against their wickednesse, <hi>Psal. 69. Let their table be their snare, their eies dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, their habitation voide, their backes bowed downe, let them heape vp iniquitie vpon iniquitie, and let their names be razed out of the booke of life.</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
Let them be vnto vs as paganish <hi>Ethnicks, and Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans,</hi> as vncleane leapers put out of the campe of <hi>Israel,</hi> as rotten members, cut off from the bodie of the Church, as dead branches, broken off from the true vine, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane dogges, put out of the holy Citie, and as those of the <hi>Concision,</hi> of whom we must beware, <hi>Phil. 3. 2.</hi> Yea let all that is about them be hatefull vnto vs. Let the<note place="margin">Iosu. 6. Dan 3.</note> goods of such be as the cursed things of <hi>Iericho,</hi> their houses as odious as a iakes, their possessions as direfull as <hi>Acheldama,</hi> their gaines as vile as the <hi>Pharisies Corban,</hi> their name as branded and as infamous as was <hi>Ieroboams,</hi> their posteritie as obscure as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely fruite of a woman which neuer seeth the sunne. If they be honourable, and do not honor Christ, ô Lord lay their honor in the dust. If noble, let them be accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted base, vnlesse they be ennobled in <hi>Iesus Christ.</hi> If learned, let their learning be a by-word, and a fable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the vulgar, that studie not to be students in <hi>Christs</hi> schoole. If they be a whole nation, let their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be as the men of <hi>Ashdod, 1. Sam. 5.</hi> If a king, let him be made as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> that he may know the Almightie. If a Courtier, let him be despised in the sight of the king: yea let all them be deliuered ouer that loue not the Lord Iesus but despise him, vnto Sathan by excommunication, that confession at least may be wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted from them as it was from <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> the <hi>Bariesu,</hi> who craued aide of the Church which formerly they desperatly despised; that if it be the will of the Lord, they may be saued by repentance in this day of grace, before that fatall and finall diuorce from the
<pb facs="7"/>
Lord of their soules and bodies be denounced, before the curses of separation, <hi>Depart from me;</hi> of indignation,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note>
      <hi>ye cursed;</hi> of dolor, <hi>into fire;</hi> of desperatiō, into <hi>hell fire;</hi> of confusion, <hi>prepared for the deuil and his angels,</hi> be in the last <hi>iudgement</hi> awarded against them, for their contempt of the Lord Iesus Christ. But to them that seeke the Lord Iesus, <hi>mella fluant illis,</hi> and all the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of mount Gerazim, let their eares neuer heare the horrors of the vale of the children of Hinnon, but let Sions rayes shine vpon them all their life, and let the Lord <hi>Iesus</hi> appeare vnto them in his second coming to saluation, who loue him, and looke for him from heauen,<note place="margin">Heb. 9. 28.</note> and long for him from the bottome of their hearts, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>come Lord Iesu.</hi> Let them heare ô Lord thy perfect<note place="margin">Apoc. 22.</note> blessings of association, <hi>Come;</hi> of benediction, <hi>ye bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed;</hi> of inheritance, <hi>possesse;</hi> of glory, <hi>the kingdome;</hi> of election, <hi>prepared for you, before the foundations of</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note>
      <hi>the world were layed.</hi> And <hi>God perswade Iaphet to dwell in the tents of blessed Sem.</hi> Euen so (ô Lord) be it.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>