<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the richt Noble Lady, and full of all verteus Ladye ANNE Countesse of Enyie.</title>
           <author>G., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103342_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01930</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103342</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the richt Noble Lady, and full of all verteus Ladye ANNE Countesse of Enyie.</title>
                 <author>G., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of the famous historye of Penardo and Laissa : other ways callid the warres, of love and ambitione. Wherein is described Penardo his most admirable deeds of arms, his ambition of glore his contempt of loue, with loves mighte assalts &amp; ammorus temptations: Laissas feareful inchantment hir releif hir trauells and lastly loves admirabel force, in hir releiving Penardo from ye fire, doone in heroik verse, by Patrik Gordon</title>
                 <author>Gordon, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waters (Walters), Joris (George)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Dordrecht</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>280 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>To the richt Noble Lady, and full of all verteus Ladye ANNE Countesse of <hi>Enyie.</hi>
   </head>
   <l>FE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r Madame, grac'd from hyest heau'ns aboue,</l>
   <l>With wealth of Fortune, Nature, beautye Loue,</l>
   <l>Lend not to frowning looks, thy gratious eye,</l>
   <l>For this bold pryde, and arrogance in me,</l>
   <l>That darr's breath furthe, or preis to pen thy praise</l>
   <l>Earths ornament, heaun's obiect, beauties gaize.</l>
   <l>Nor <hi>Maro</hi> great, nor <hi>Naso</hi> sweit, am I,</l>
   <l>Nor haue I <hi>Homers</hi> mightie style, wheirby</l>
   <l>I might to efter aiges e're reveiue,</l>
   <l>Thy fame; thy worthe, and mak thy glory leiue,</l>
   <l>Zit wer it but t'awake the braver witts,</l>
   <l>Whoes loftie quill's thy sweitter praises fitt's,</l>
   <l>This much I say, nor vanely vaunt I nather,</l>
   <l>Thy wit, thy beautye, and thy vertue rather</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="7"/>Celestiall is, rair, excellent, devyne,</l>
   <l>(In whom all woo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>the, all grace, al goodnes shyne)</l>
   <l>Then humane, so heaun's croun's, adorn's thy bloode</l>
   <l>With Naturs wealthe, grace ful, &amp; fortuns goode</l>
   <l>Then lett the Poëts on their Muses call,</l>
   <l>To fil their brains, their pen's, their papers all</l>
   <l>With ornament of methode, witt, and sense,</l>
   <l>That flowes from thy rair worth, rair excellence.</l>
   <l>In goldin showrs, whiche fame on her faire winges,</l>
   <l>To eurye natione, countrey, kingdome bringes,</l>
   <l>And strowes it heir, and their, in eurye pairt,</l>
   <l>To beautifye speeche, eloquence, and arte,</l>
   <l>If on poore me, some, drop's she would doune poure,</l>
   <l>I'le spend my pains, my witts, soules wasting power</l>
   <l>To pen thy praise, and thy braue Mates, whoes worthe</l>
   <l>Thow stryues to mach, as thow hes match'd his birth</l>
   <l>O wonderous stryfe, blis'd, happie, perfect, pure,</l>
   <l>Long may that warre myld, pleasant, sweet, indure</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>P.G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>