<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO
HIS VVOR∣THILY
RESPEC∣TED
FRIEND,
MASTER
BARTEN HOLYDAY
ARCH-DEACON
OF OXFORD.</title>
           <author>Gomersall, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103307_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01850</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11992</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103307</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO
HIS VVOR∣THILY
RESPEC∣TED
FRIEND,
MASTER
BARTEN HOLYDAY
ARCH-DEACON
OF OXFORD.</title>
                 <author>Gomersall, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Leuites reuenge : containing poeticall meditations vpon the 19. and 20. chapters of Iudges. By R. Gomersall</title>
                 <author>Gomersall, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 76, 4 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO
HIS VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THILY
RESPEC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TED
FRIEND,
MASTER
BARTEN HOLYDAY
ARCH-DEACON
OF OXFORD.</head>
   <p>WOrthy Sir; Whilest others are
ambitious of an honourable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication,
I am thankfull for
a friendly one, this in the
meane time being mine happy aduantage
ouer them, that they expect, but I inioy a
Patron. And yet I haue not such a scarcity
of great names, to whom I might pretend
with as good a confidence as the greatest
part of Writers, but that some of the higher
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nke (to whom for their frequent courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ies
I must confesse my selfe an vnequall
debtor) might haue expected, others almost
challenged my Dedication: to whom
<pb facs="4"/>
I know no other answer of more respect and
satisfaction then this, that I concluded
the worke to bee below their notice,
how much more their protection; and that
I would haue others to take notice more of
my Friendship, then of my Ambition: But it
may be that some will conceiue an Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
in this Friendship, when I of such an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy
in study shall boast the fauours of so
growne a vertue, and intrude vpon his fame.
If this be an offence, I must professe I glory
in it, this accusation I confesse and am proud
of: such is the ambition of him that is ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured
on vertue, of the man who would
be indeared to heauen; whose desires would
not be so good, were they not so high, and
the Angels might still haue stood, had theye
neuer knowne another Pride. But not to
insist on that (which neuerthelesse I can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
too much insist on, the remembrance of
our friendship) to whom could I more fitly
dedicate a Poem, then to him that hath
shewed such excellency? or a Diuine Poem,
then to him that hath shewed such Religion
in his composures? Of this truth <hi>Persius</hi> is
a witnesse, whom you haue taught to speake
English with such a grace, that wee can vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand
when we heare him, and find no
<pb facs="4"/>
one syllable in his Dialect offensiue either to
the Elegant, or to the Chast Eare. Of this
truth <hi>Iuvenall</hi> may bee a witnesse, whom
though we doe not yet heare in publike bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering
his expressions by your exact rendring
him, yet they that haue inioy'd the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of your neerer friendship, confidently
and vpon the hazard of their vnderstanding
affirme, that hee is farre vnworthy of such an
imprisonment, that he should bee obscured
by that hand which cleared him. But it is
Diuinity that is the subiect of these verses,
and it is Diuinity which is the exercise, and
glory of your studies, which makes you an
inhabitant of the Pulpit, nay which makes
euery place where you will vouchsafe to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course,
to be a pulpit, for such is the bounty
of your religious conuersation, that howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
the place may be changed, the Sermon is
perpetuall. Sermons that at the same time
make vs deuout and witty, which by first
winning the Preacher, haue the easier Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest
of the Auditory: who are neuer with
lesse difficulty intreated to their happinesse,
then when they see they doe not goe alone.
So that now when I consider what I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,
and to whom, I beginne to suspect the
lightnesse of my worke, and thinke I haue
<pb facs="5"/>
some reason to feare the censure of such a
Friend, to whom if I shall bee excus'd, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
some glory from others, not because the
Leuite, but because He was mine; to whom,
hauing thus farre tryed his patience, I haue
nothing more to adde but this, that I am his,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>In all the duties
of Affection,
ROBERT GOMERSALL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>