<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO The Right Worshipfull his most worthy friend and Benefactour Sir John Hanbu∣rie of Kelmersh in North∣amptonshire, Together with his Sonne and heire Edward Hanburie Esquire, &amp; Mary his daugh∣ter Lady to Sir Miles Sandys of Brimsfield in Glocestersh. and all that are de∣scended from them, Gerhards Interpreter wisheth what Tem∣porall happinesse this world can af∣ford, and Eternall happinesse in the world to come.</title>
           <author>Winterton, Ralph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103039_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01638</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11769</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103039</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO The Right Worshipfull his most worthy friend and Benefactour Sir John Hanbu∣rie of Kelmersh in North∣amptonshire, Together with his Sonne and heire Edward Hanburie Esquire, &amp; Mary his daugh∣ter Lady to Sir Miles Sandys of Brimsfield in Glocestersh. and all that are de∣scended from them, Gerhards Interpreter wisheth what Tem∣porall happinesse this world can af∣ford, and Eternall happinesse in the world to come.</title>
                 <author>Winterton, Ralph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A golden chaine of divine aphorismes written by John Gerhard Doctor of Divinitie and superintendent of Heldburg. Translated by Ralph Winterton fellow of Kings Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Gerhard, Johann</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Cambridge University—Printers.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Royston (Reston, Reyston, Roystore), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 389, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO The Right Worshipfull his most worthy friend and Benefactour <hi>Sir John Hanbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> of <hi>Kelmersh</hi> in <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amptonshire,</hi> Together with his Sonne and heire <hi>Edward Hanburie</hi> Esquire, &amp; <hi>Mary</hi> his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Lady</hi> to <hi>Sir Miles Sandys</hi> of <hi>Brimsfield</hi> in <hi>Glocestersh.</hi> and all that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended from them, <hi>Gerhards Interpreter</hi> wisheth what Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall happinesse this world can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, and Eternall happinesse in the world to come.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom me perhaps you expected <hi>Physicall Aphorismes,</hi> rules and directions for health, as
<pb facs="5"/>
from a <hi>Physician;</hi> rather then <hi>Theologicall Aphorismes,</hi> doctrines of salvation, as from a <hi>Divine.</hi> And, I confesse, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering my <hi>Profession,</hi> it had been more proper for me to have sent over such unto you. But such is the nature and condition of man, whilest he lives here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, under the clouds, that no <hi>Profession</hi> can <hi>Priviledge</hi> him from storms and tempests, and from injuries of weather: Inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that even <hi>Physicians</hi> themselves many times become <hi>Patients.</hi> The <hi>Great world</hi> is a <hi>Theatre</hi> in which are <hi>Acted</hi> nothing but <hi>Tragedies</hi> of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane miseries: Every man hath his <hi>Intrat,</hi> as soon as he is born: He <hi>Acts</hi> (if I may call it <hi>Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and not rather <hi>Suffering</hi>) all his life: He findes no <hi>Exit,</hi> till he descends into the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of death, to put off his dresse.
<pb facs="5"/>
I may truely call The <hi>Great world, The Common school of Patience;</hi> and every <hi>Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> a <hi>Private;</hi> and every <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> in each Societie being a <hi>Little world</hi> within himself, an <hi>Epitome,</hi> or <hi>Module</hi> of the <hi>Great.</hi> To <hi>School</hi> we must, to learn <hi>Patience:</hi> And where should a man learn <hi>Christian Patience</hi> but in the <hi>School</hi> of <hi>Christ?</hi> And where is that but in the <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Devotion?</hi> I for one have been so exercised in a <hi>World</hi> of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi> that it hath driven me to the <hi>School</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> to learn <hi>Patience,</hi> and according to the counsell of the <hi>Apostle,</hi> In all estates to be content, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at nothing whatsoever can happen to me from without, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering that nothing comes to passe without a divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>Apollonius,</hi> as <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stratus</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
reports, being asked if he did not tremble at the sight of the Tyrant, made this answer, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>God which hath given him a terrible Countenance, hath given also unto me an undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Heart.</hi> And it is the say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Saint <hi>Chrysostome, <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> It is not so much the nature of Things, as the weaknesse of Persons.</hi> Troubles happen alike to all: but all are not alike troubled. <hi>Fire</hi> is one and the same for <hi>Nature:</hi> but for <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> it is not alwaies the same. It consumes wood and cole: but it purifies gold and silver. The <hi>Sunne</hi> softens wax, and hardens clay. The <hi>Light</hi> is comfortable to the sound, but troublesome to
<pb facs="6"/>
the diseased. The saying of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollonius</hi> I may apply thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my self, Though God hath suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered storms and tempests to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise and to be stirred up against me, yet he hath not suffered me to be removed or cast down. <hi>Though Fortune frown upon me, yet</hi> (I thank God) having a chearfull heart <hi>I can smile upon her.</hi> And the saying of Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> I may thus apply, <hi>Though troubles have come upon me, yet</hi> (I thank God who hath given me Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) <hi>I have not been trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</hi> But amongst many crosses nothing hath more afflicted me then the death of him who true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honoured you in his life, and was truely beloved by you to his death, my deare brother <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Winterton</hi> late one of her Majesties Privie Chamber. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy man! But shall I call
<pb facs="7"/>
him unhappy in his death, who was most happy in his life? That I cannot: He that lived well, certainly could not but die well? Shall I call him unhappy, because he died in a strange Countrie? Nay rather happy in this, because he died for his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Shall I call him unhappy in this, because he is taken from me? This were to love my self more then him, and to envie his happinesse. Or shall I grieve that I my self was not with him to take care for him for things necessarie in time of life, and for his funeralls after death? He wanted neither comfort in life, nor honourable buriall after death. Ever let my tongue be tyed and my hand dried up, If I do not as a poore scholar serve him with both who was so care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for him, I mean that most <hi>Heroicall worthie,</hi> (with the
<pb facs="7"/>
splendour of whose Titles and Greatnesse I dare not presume to set a lustre on so small a work as this, but shall ever admire, and proclaim his Vertues &amp; Goodnes) who of his innate and noble di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposition loved all his followers in generall, as his fellow-souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and my brother in speciall; who to his power provided for all, as for his own familie, but made much of him in health, as a faithfull servant; took care for him before his death, as for a friend; lamented for him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> his death as for a brother; and after death, saw him honourably buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as a souldier. I will not then lament his death, who is trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to a better life: Neither will I weep for him, that is in joy: Nor put on mourning clothes for him that is clothed with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie. If it was any unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse for him to die, it is his
<pb facs="8"/>
friends not his. I wept for him when he was alive: and then he seemed to me to die when I left him on shipboard at <hi>Graves-end.</hi> The next news I heare, he lies buried at <hi>Custrin</hi> in <hi>Silesia.</hi> Whom sea and land and death hath parted, I hope blessed Eternitie shall at length bring together again. So I leave him and return to you. Sir, I hope you will pardon this <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression,</hi> or rather count it no <hi>digression</hi> at all, to speak of him whom I know you dearely loved. But I was speaking of my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: for which still I finde a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie in the Sanctuarie. For my manner is, when troubles seize upon me, presently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire my self into my studie, and take in hand some book of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So presently after I parted from my brother I took in hand <hi>Drexelius</hi> his Enchiridion of
<pb facs="8"/>
Eternitie: And since, upon a new occasion offered, I renewed my acquaintance with <hi>Doctor Gerhard.</hi> It were fit that I should present my service unto you my self in mine own person, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering my many obligations to you, and your kinde invitations of me. But being otherwise hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred I have sent <hi>Gerhard</hi> in my place, who dedicates himself and his best service to honour you and your progenie. Concerning whom I may truely say thus much, If you make him your Counsellour and Companion, you shall never be without a walking Library: So full is he of Scripture Fathers and Schoolmen. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my self I can say no more but this (for I know not how to complement) I am and ever shall be in all hearty affection</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your servant RALPH WINTERTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>