<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORTHY, VERTVOVS, AND religious Gentlewoman, Mistrisse GARTHRVDE DAVIES, W. M. wisheth all terrestriall happinesse heere on earth, and all celestiall blessednesse in Heauen.</title>
           <author>Miller, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1621</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103509_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A72904</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17923.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103509</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORTHY, VERTVOVS, AND religious Gentlewoman, Mistrisse GARTHRVDE DAVIES, W. M. wisheth all terrestriall happinesse heere on earth, and all celestiall blessednesse in Heauen.</title>
                 <author>Miller, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached at the funerall of the worshipfull, Gilbert Dauies Esquire : at Christow in Deuon. By W. Miller, minister, and preacher of Gods word at Runington. April 15. Anno Dom. 1620</title>
                 <author>Miller, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1621</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORTHY, VERTVOVS, AND religious Gentlewoman, Mistrisse GARTHRVDE DAVIES, <hi>W. M.</hi> wisheth all terrestriall happinesse heere on earth, and all <hi>celestiall blessednesse in Heauen.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orshipfull, being fully assured of the sincere loue and affection which you bare vnto him, whose memoriall these lines desire still to reuiue: I am bold to present them (though rude and vnpolished) vnto your fauourable Patronage and protection. First, because of that singular loue and liking which you haue vnto Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and religious men, especially such as are faithfull Ministers and Preachers of Gods Word: Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I thought it would be vnto you no vnacceptable ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, if I endeuoured by dead letters to preserue his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and perfections in liuing name, whom cruell death hath too soone taken from you and vs, and vntimely laid in dust: and lastly, to manifest vnto you the thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of my heart, for those many good and vndeserued fauours and encouragements in my calling heretofore, from himselfe, and since his death receiued from you. These are the reasons which haue induced me to publish this my simple Weakling, vnto euery vulgar hand and
<pb facs="3"/>
eye vnder your Worships name, nothing doubting, but that your fauourable patronizing of it, will bee a principall meanes to couer the many wants, and innumerable weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses thereof, which men of gifts will soone espy. Now the God of heauen blesse you, together with that hopefull Branch that God hath sent you, from his loynes who is now with God, as a token of Gods loue and fauour to you both; with long life beere on earth, and eternall in the heauens.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Worships in all good seruice to be commanded,</hi> W. Miller.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>