<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>P., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103147_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09026</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19314</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103147</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>P., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The grounds of diuinitie : plainely discouering the mysteries of Christian religion, propounded familiarly in diuers questions and answeres: substantially proued by scriptures; expounded faithfully, according to the writings of the best diuines, and euidently applyed by profitable vses, for the helpe and benefite of the vnlearned which desire knowledge. To the which is prefixed a very profitable treatise, containing an exhortation to the study of the word, with singular directions for the hearing and reading of the same. By Elnathan Parr minister of the word, at Palgraue in Suffolke</title>
                 <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Samuel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 304 pages, x 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶ To the courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader; Thou hast here the fruit of my sicknesse, whereby in the beginning of this Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I was made vnser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable for my publique duety. In this while, considering that Time is preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and the dayes euill, as the Apostle saith, the Lord put into my heart, to redeeme the time: Whereupon (as God enabled me to hold vp my head) I looked ouer my ragged Notes, and scattered pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. Part of which, after my rude ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner pollished, are here offered vnto thee. I am not without hope, but that (by the good hand of God) as I had experience of the profit of these things, being deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by liuely voyce: so also the charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reading of them may much auayle
<pb facs="5"/>thee. I know that euery day there are many new Bookes set forth, and of this kind not a few: yet in this method, with sound &amp; briefe Propositions of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall points of Diuinity: euident and infallible proofes: succinct and perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous Explications; and plaine and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Applications, I haue not obserued any: So that, this, and also the great igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rāce of the multitude considred, I doubt not but the Indifferent, will free these my Endeuors from the censure of super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, &amp; of writing Iliads (as they say) after <hi>Homer.</hi> I confesse ingenuously that much of my Explications is drawn frō the fountains of other men, both for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Writers, and many our owne worthy Countreymen. So that, as the little Bee, greatly industrious, flieth ouer many a garden and flower, to gather a little ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: so haue I out of many mens gardens, selected and gathered many such choice things, which I iudged might most make for thy benefit. And this can be no Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
<pb facs="5"/>to mee, in asmuch as the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned know, that (not to speake of some of the Pen-men of the holy Ghost) both aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient &amp; later Writers, haue, to the great benefit of the Church, taken this course: &amp; also because I haue made such things, which I haue receiued from others, so to serue my purpose, either by contraction, addition, exposition, or marshalling into my order: that I may in some sort iustly challenge them as mine owne.</p>
   <p>The summe of this my small Labour, (to the which is prefixed an exhortation to the study of the Word) is an Expositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Description of God, named the <hi>Grounds of Diuinitie,</hi> expounded &amp; applied, because it propoundeth, preueth, and as a key openeth, &amp; easily vnlocketh, the hidden mystery and counsell of God, concerning our saluatiō by Iesus Christ. The Questions and Answers, are fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and friendly depending. The Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, plaine, &amp; for the most part, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise, pointing at some things in a word,
<pb facs="6"/>at some in a parenthesis, which to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious Reader wil be the more aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageable: and for the Vses (which being practised, are the praise &amp; life of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) I haue not obserued euery thing, nor so pressed any thing, but that I leaue much more to be gathered and obserued, by such which are accustomed to Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. In a word, that which I iudged most profitable, I haue performed for thee.</p>
   <p>If thou beest learned, as thou needest it not, so I humbly intreate thee to know that I writ it not for thee yet I barre thee not the reading, but most willingly submit it to thy censure. If thou blamest the Phrase and Stile, that it is not fluent and round, but ragged and harsh: Truly neither can I commend it. Happily, I haue striuen, to be plaine, or at least, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no skill in finer cookery, haue drest it as I was able, after our homely and country fashion for the stomackes of the vnlearned, who rellish and like better,
<pb facs="6"/>of that which is plaine and easie, then either learned and deep treatises which they vnderstand not, or such cooked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits where the cost is greater then the nourishment. Some delight in toyes like children: I should then thinke very ill of my selfe, when I should goe about to please their humour, fitter to be purged then norished. Some (&amp; worthily) in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their great acuity &amp; iudgemēt, like nothing (for themselues) but that which transcendeth common capacities: I doe not thinke my selfe able to doe that which might giue them satisfaction. And, in asmuch as there are three fold more which haue but meane knowledge, then which abound, it shall content me, that euen as Golde is common in Rich mens pockets, but Siluer is currant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the common sort; it shall (I say) content me, if, while those of deeper iudgement bee conuersant in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the learned, my Labours may be in the hands of the meaner sort, for
<pb facs="7"/>whose sake specially I haue taken this paines.</p>
   <p>For thee therefore which arte but a beginner I haue laboured. If I may adde to thy knowledge and affection, and be a helper of thy Faith and Ioy; giue thou God the glory: I haue then attained the end of my labors: Reade once, and reade againe; it may bee the second reading wil be more sauory then the first. If thou profitest herein, according as I haue prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thee, I know thou shalt neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent thee. And thus, desiring the helpe of thy prayers, I commend thee to God, and to the word of his Grace, wishing thy farther vp-building in all sauing knowledge, godlinesse, and established comfort of conscience, through Iesus Christ.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in our Christ. E. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>