<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONOVRABLE Knight, Sir Iohn Mounson, Knight of the Bathe, Sonne and Heire to the Right Worshipfull Sir Thomas Mounson of Burton in Lincolnshire, Knight and Baronet: the Author wisheth increase of grace here, and glory hereafter.</title>
           <author>Taylor, Theophilus</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103237_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13527</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23819</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103237</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONOVRABLE Knight, Sir Iohn Mounson, Knight of the Bathe, Sonne and Heire to the Right Worshipfull Sir Thomas Mounson of Burton in Lincolnshire, Knight and Baronet: the Author wisheth increase of grace here, and glory hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Theophilus</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The mappe of Moses: or, a guide for governours : Two sermons lately preached before the iudges of assize, and magistrates of the towne of Reding, at two seuerall assemblies there held for the countie of Berk. By Theophilus Taylor, Master of Arts, and pastor of the parish of S. Laurence in Reding</title>
                 <author>Taylor, Theophilus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 50 pages, folding table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE Knight, Sir <hi>Iohn Mounson,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bathe,</hi> Sonne and Heire to the Right Worshipfull Sir <hi>Thomas Mounson</hi> of <hi>Burton</hi> in <hi>Lincolnshire,</hi> Knight and Baronet: the Author wisheth increase of grace here, and glory hereafter.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy Sir: Sithence the smallest tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates in this age passe not without their Dedicatories; I would not seem singular in denying this little Booke that ordinary priuiledge; which being but newly hatcht, doth (with the Philosophers bird, which flew into his bosome) seek shelter vnder your Worships co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerture; whose name I durst not prefixe before so weake a worke, but that I haue some encouragements: as first, the inward familiarity which once I had with you for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers yeeres together in your tender age. Againe, your loue to learning, and that affection you haue alwaies shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards them that leane that way: moreouer, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious respect which you haue alwaies testified to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of truth, one maine branch whereof is briefly laid downe in this Treatise; and lastly, those employments whereunto you are sometimes called, by reason of your place of Iustice-ship; vnto the faithfull discharge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, this little (Mappe of <hi>Moses</hi>) will afford you some
<pb facs="3"/> direction. I dare not (for feare of flattery) blaze the least part of that commendation which a worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of your acquaintance hath giuen you in his Booke dedicated vnto you,<note place="margin">M. <hi>Tho. Ganif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> I squire p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>nt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>16.</note> and intituled, <hi>The Secretaries Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>:</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et I m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y boldly affirme that that generous toward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, which he with others at that time discerned in you, was but as a dram in comparison of that weight of worth which is now found in you: which as it is no little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto your godly and worthy Parents, whose earnest desire alwaies was to giue you their <hi>Lemuel,</hi> a truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and generous education: so it hath much reioyced me to heare the relation both of your religious loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, as also of the affection of your Country to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, testified sufficiently in their late nomination and election of you for one of their Knights in the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament. Now Sir, as for this poore tractate, I humbly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat your Worship to accept<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>, as a certaine testimony of my thankefull minde, <hi>qui, si non potui maxima; parua dedi:</hi> such as I haue I present vnto you; a few blotted leaues, wherein you shall not meete with any flourishing words, or curious lines; yet with Gods truth euidently laid downe in the plainest dialect; in acceptance wherof, I shal not be wanting in my prayers, for Gods blessing vpon your selfe, and your vertuous Lady, that your house and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour may continue vnblemished.</p>
   <q>
      <l>—donec fluctus formica marinos</l>
      <l>Ebibat, &amp; totum testudo perambulet orbem;</l>
   </q>
   <p>That God may direct you in all your proceedings, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease in you his sauing graces; blesse you and all yours with long life, and much happinesse, to his glory, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good, your owne comfort here, and eternall glory hereafter; in hope and full perswasion whereof, I humbly take my leaue, and rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in all obseruance, THEOPHILVS TAYLOR.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>