<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Harris, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103817_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02723</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12855</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103817</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Harris, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvay to trve happinesse : Deliuered in XXIV. sermons vpon the Beatitvdes. By Robert Harris, B. in Diuinity, and pastor of Hanwell. Also, a treatise of the nevv covenant; set forth sermon-wise, on Ezechiel the XI. By the same avthovr</title>
                 <author>Harris, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bartlet, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Badger, Richard 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 115, 114-322, 186, 2, 8, 68, 52, 55-76, that is 79, 90-129, 140-196, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth in the first, is seldom corrected in the second &amp; third concoction. This J finde true in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of these Notes. At the first, they were raw and indigested, forged in a cold and dull heart, vttered by a weake broken man, who hath his hands full with himselfe, his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities and temptations, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a people, who neither could nor
<pb facs="3"/> would expect more from him, than na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked truths and honestie. Thus it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with them whilst they were mine. From my mouth, they fell into the hand of an able man, but his shame-fac'd (J may not say blush-full) mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty was too hard for his abilities, and by this meane they wanne nothing in this second digestion. Now how the Printer (in point of distribution, and in a third place) hath done his part, thou wilt easily find. Meane while, all that J can say about so poore a businesse is this: Jf thou finde any benefit by any thing heere, I am made (for I hold doing good the best preferment) If otherwise matters sort not to thy liking, blame not me, who promise nothing, and print (I am sure) as vnwillingly, as thou canst reade. The Lord (whose power tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs
<pb facs="3"/> in mans weaknesse, goe along with them and vs both, and keepe vs from trifling, whilest <hi>Indocti coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum rapiunt,</hi> whilest others run away with grace and glorie, as that good man once, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in CHRIST, Robert Harris.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>