<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Honorable, and most Accomoplisht Earle GEORGE Earle of ENYIE lorde Gordon, and Badyenoth &amp;c. sone &amp; heire apparent to the most Illustrius Lorde George Marquies of Huntlie.</title>
           <author>Gordon, Patrick</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103342_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01930</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103342</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Honorable, and most Accomoplisht Earle GEORGE Earle of ENYIE lorde Gordon, and Badyenoth &amp;c. sone &amp; heire apparent to the most Illustrius Lorde George Marquies of Huntlie.</title>
                 <author>Gordon, Patrick</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of the famous historye of Penardo and Laissa : other ways callid the warres, of love and ambitione. Wherein is described Penardo his most admirable deeds of arms, his ambition of glore his contempt of loue, with loves mighte assalts &amp; ammorus temptations: Laissas feareful inchantment hir releif hir trauells and lastly loves admirabel force, in hir releiving Penardo from ye fire, doone in heroik verse, by Patrik Gordon</title>
                 <author>Gordon, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waters (Walters), Joris (George)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Dordrecht</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>280 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most Honorable, and most Accomoplisht Earle GEORGE Earle of ENYIE lorde <hi>Gordon,</hi> and <hi>Badyenoth</hi> &amp;c. sone &amp; heire apparent to the most Illustrius Lorde <hi>George</hi> Marquies of Huntlie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, finding my selfe inclosed in the labourinth of your al-conquering merits, and dispair<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of al reliefe, necessitie encura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me to goe forward, till the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite riches of your worth should choak the pouerty of my neere famisht Wit with abondance, while thus I thirsted for a fatall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to my longing desires, I found your Lo. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable virtues, so seated on the throne of al perfectiō, as your insatiable auarice was onely on the Heauen-infused gifts of the minde. Wheir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of since I could produce nothing for the release of my boundage but this barren Inuention, soe many be the rare &amp; excellent Wits which exceed in that kinde, as though I was assured that your wonted courtesie wold pardon my rudenes, and accept of my pouerty: Yet wold not theis onely
<pb facs="3"/>
deime it too meane a present, for soe worthie a personage: But also such multitudes of men seim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing <hi>Babouns</hi> swarmeth euerye wheire now a daies being ignorant of any thing, and yet will needes be Wittie in jesting at eurie mans actions, so that the vprote of my confused thoughts cold not be appeased, but either by obtianing aide of the first or silence, of the last, and as the silence is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, soe is the aide dishonorable; Wherfore I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued, being imboldened by affection to offere this small streame of my Witt, to the boundlesse Ocean of your virtues, vnder the shield of whose most honorable patronage, this my firste borne shall aduenture to the view of the worlde armed with silence against the sensors of the Wise, and with patience againste all the carpinge malice or skoffing jests that theis Appish <hi>Monkies</hi> can vent from their too curious inuectiue and belabored brains. And because that all my endeuours are tied alreadye with the two-fould chaine of your L. Princely virtues and more then deserued cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tesies, to which the extension of my natural duty cannot adde anie suffitient tribut for the interest which your Lo. hath in me: therefore being still in my former d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>spaire I am forc'd (in such a worlde of bands) for euer to rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your L. vn-redeemable seruant
<hi>Patrik Gordon.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>