<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Lewis, </author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103079_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15560</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103079</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Lewis, </author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vnmasking of the masse-priest : vvith a due and diligent examination of their holy sacrifice. By C.A. Shewing how they partake with all the ancient heretiques, in their profane, impious, and idolatrous worship</title>
                 <author>Lewis, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Whitaker, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 233, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>CHristian Reader, the audacious and frequent pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of the <hi>Masse-Priests,</hi> in offering their blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> with the vnsufferable impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the <hi>Romish Laity,</hi> both in conference to iustifie, and by presence to communicate therein; (more especially in our Northerne parts, where I am <hi>Resident)</hi> hath constrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me to wade into this abstruse <hi>Mystery,</hi> not intending to make it the Worlds common obiect; (as may appeare by the stile,) but rather to furnish my selfe with <hi>Defensiue</hi> and <hi>Offensiue</hi> armour; matter of <hi>answer</hi> and <hi>opposition</hi> in case of encounter. What intention had vowed mine owne, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty of Friends, and desire of the <hi>Common good,</hi> hath made thine. If thou know the <hi>Author,</hi> censure not his youth (seeing the <hi>scantinesse</hi> of <hi>yeares</hi> is supplied by the <hi>largnesse</hi> of <hi>Industry)</hi> but if thou finde any fruite worth gathering, taste it thankfully, rendring <hi>God</hi> the <hi>glory,</hi> me thy <hi>Prayers.</hi> The solidity of the matter I hope, thou canst not impeach; the plainnesse vsed in <hi>Penning,</hi> with the Faults escaped in <hi>Printing,</hi> I hope thou wilt winke at, Iudge me</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in any Christian seruice: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>LEVVIS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>