<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Epigrame to the Reader.</title>
           <author>C., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103418_Bo1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02181</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12322</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103418</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Epigrame to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>C., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Paramythion : tvvo treatises of the comforting of an afflicted conscience, written by M. Richard Greenham, with certaine epistles of the same argument. Heereunto are added two sermons, with certaine graue and wise counsells and answeres of the same author and argument</title>
                 <author>Greenham, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradock, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Dexter, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 207, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>An Epigrame to the Reader.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>THE thirstie soule, that fainteth in the way,</l>
      <l>Or hunger-bit for heauenly foode doth long:</l>
      <l>The wearied Hart, that panteth all she way</l>
      <l>Oppressed with feares, &amp; home-bread griefs among;</l>
      <l>The blinded eye, that hunt's the shining ray,</l>
      <l>Or minde enthralde, through Satans wily wrong:</l>
      <l>Let hither fare for comfort in their neede;</l>
      <l>For smothered flames a greater fire will breede.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Here siluer streames shall quench thy boyling heat,</l>
      <l>And hony dewes thy hungrie stomacke fill,</l>
      <l>Heere sweete Repose with Comfort shall intreate</l>
      <l>Thy wounded breast to cure with busy skill,</l>
      <l>Hence fetch thy ransome howsoeuer great,</l>
      <l>A mine of treasures are in this faire hill;</l>
      <l>From whose hye top thy scaled eies may see</l>
      <l>A glorious light that shall enlighten thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The streames are bloud, the dew is bread frō heauē</l>
      <l>The Rest and Comfort are coelestiall ioyes;</l>
      <l>The ransome from the crosse was freely giuen,</l>
      <l>The light is faith, which darknes all destroyes.</l>
      <l>THrise happy man that guides his steps so euen,</l>
      <l>As his pure light no gloomy darke annoyes.</l>
      <l>His ransom'd soule aeternall ioyes shall win</l>
      <l>When timelye death shall blessed life begin.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>