<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧To the Readers,
ADVENTVRERS, FAVORERS,
and wel-willers to the Plantation
in GVIANA.</title>
           <author>H., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103834_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02626</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12754</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103834</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧To the Readers,
ADVENTVRERS, FAVORERS,
and wel-willers to the Plantation
in GVIANA.</title>
                 <author>H., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A relation of a voyage to Guiana : Describing the climat, scituation, fertilitie, prouisions and commodities of that country, containing seuen prouinces, and other signiories within that territory: together, with the manners, customes, behauiors, and dispositions of the people. Performed by Robert Harcourt, of Stanton Harcourt Esquire. The pattent for the plantation of which country, his Maiestie hath granted to the said Robert Harcourt vnder the Great Seale</title>
                 <author>Harcourt, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 71, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>❧To the Readers,
ADVENTVRERS, FAVORERS,
and wel-willers to the Plantation
in GVIANA.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the part of valiant and noble spirites to
apply their indeuours to honourable and
woorthie atchiuements: but chiefely to
frame their actions therein by the rule of
vertue, and accomplish the end for which
they were created, which is in their vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
to serue and glorifie GOD, and to doe good vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:
For the better performance of their dueties in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe,
let them examine their inclinations and dispositions
in the course of their life, and what they finde themselues
most inclined vnto, to that let them seriously bend their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;
either to cherish or suppresse it; to follow or forsake it,
according as it tendeth to vertue or vice; to honour or
disgrace.</p>
   <p>As touching the courses of life, inclining to the better
part, some men are naturally giuen to bee schollers, either in
Diuinity, Philosophy, or other learning; some are more inclined
to be Statists; some to be Souldiers, and trauellers; some desire
to bee Citizens, and Merchants; and some like best to leade
Coun<gap reason="illegible: obscured" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>trey life, and follow husbandry; and othersome are
<pb facs="5"/>
wholly inclined to the Mechannicall trades, and handy crafts.
In all which professions, as men are naturally addicted more,
or lesse, they attaine to perfection, and may thereby accomplish
the end for which they were created. But to vndertake any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession
contrary to a mans naturall inclination, is a losse of time,
a worke that yeldeth no profit, but breedeth many inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
and destroyeth nature: For the meere Scholler will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
bee good Statist, Souldier, Merchant, nor Mechanicall
tradesman, (yet learning is a singular helpe in all these profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssions)
neither will the professed Souldier euer attaine to exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site
perfection in learning, or in the other professions; so lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
of the rest. The naturall inclination of man, may bee som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
restrained, corrected, and reformed, but is rarely and
hardly altered.</p>
   <q>Naturam expellas furca licèt, vsque recurret</q>
   <p>In these and all other professions whatsoeuer, men may so
proceede in their particular societies, that each seuerall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
in his proper vocation, may bee a help, comfort, and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
vnto the rest: and they are firmely bound both by the
law of God, and Nature, to exercise and follow their professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
for the benefit of others: not coueteously seeking their owne
gaine only thereby; but charitably, respecting first the glory of
God, and then the honour of their Prince, and profit of their
Countrey, which is the end for which they were created</p>
   <p>To the end therefore that our Countreymen of all professions
in this Kingdome may bee worthily induced to performe their
duties in that kinde not only at home in their owne Countrey,
but also abroade in foraigne parts, wheresoeuer any of our
Nation shall be imployed, eyther by discouery or conquest, for
the reducing of vnknowne and barbarous people (void of all
knowledge of God, and ciuill gouernement) to Christianity and
the subiection and obedience of of our Soueraigne, and that
such others as want imployment, or competent meanes to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb facs="5"/>
their professions, and are slipt aside from vertuous exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
and honourable enterprises, to idle wantonnesse, effeminate
disorders, and other extrauagant courses of life, may bee recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
reformed, and encouraged (by better endeuours) to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
their duties to God, their Prince, and their Countrey.
I thought it conuenient to propound vnto them a worthy and
memorable enterprise: (for the prosecution and accomplishing
whereof, it hath gratiously pleased his Maiesty to grant mee
priuiledge by Pattent) namely, the discouery and plantation of
a part of the great, rich, &amp; mighty Empire of <hi>Guiana:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
they shall finde variety of imployments to spend their times
worthily in their seuerall vocations; plentifull meanes to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
all wants and necessities; and many worthy aduentures to
obtaine immortall renowne and perpetuall fame.</p>
   <p>And for as much as all mens actions are subiect to miscen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
and some (perhaps) may thinke the labour lost, which is
bestowed in this enterprise, foreiudgeing the Countrey being
rude, barbarous and heathen, to bee vnprofitable; I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
here particularly shew wherein our Countreymen of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall
professions before mentioned, may profitably labour in
this worke, and performe thereby to God a seruice most accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,
and register their fame to all posteritie.</p>
   <p>First, the Scholler in diuine learning may worthily labour
the conuersion of infinite numbers of vnbeleeuing people, who
may be reduced to a quiet, sober, and ciuill life: the scoller in
Philosophy, and other Learning, may doe much good by trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
vp of the youth in the knowledge of the litterall arts, and
by the practise of his skill in Phisicke and Chirurgery: the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist
may highly aduance his Princes seruice, and his Countries
good, by giuing ayd vnto this action, and his discreet and
prouident furtherance in managing the businesse thereof: The
Souldier and Traueller, by bearing armes in the execution of
this noble enterprise, and by memorable discoueries of strange
<pb facs="6"/>
and vnknowne Countries and Nations, may open the way to
increase and inlarge the Dominion of our Soueraigne: the
Merchant by assisting the plantation there, and by erecting
conuenient factories for that purpose, may highly increase the
trade of merchandise, by returning thence the riches and
commodities there found and gathered. The Countrey-man
that professeth busbandry and tillage of the earth, may also be
sufficiently imploied for the increase of corne and catell, and
in planting, gathering, and getting as many rare and necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
fruits and prouisions, as shall be needefull for the life of man.
And lastly, the Mechannicall tradesman, and such as exercise
the handy crafts, (in which company I include all sorts of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers)
may by this action of <hi>Guiana,</hi> highly aduance their
trades and occupations, to their owne vnspeakable profit, and
benefit of others, by their diuers and sundry workes for seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
vses, and for persons of all quallity whatsoeuer; and may
teach the people of that Countrey (being once conuerted to chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity,
and brought to the knowledge of ciuill gouernement)
such seuerall trades, as our experience shall finde necessarie for
them, and conuenient for vs.</p>
   <p>Hauing heere particularly shewed wherein our Countrey-men
of diuers professions may worthily follow their vocations,
and imploy their endeuours in this action: I leaue the matter
whereon they are to worke, to be more fully expressed in the
following discourse.</p>
   <p>And because they may the better be encouraged in this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise,
by examples of the like nature: let vs looke into the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coueries
and conquests, performed by the Spaniards, in the
East and West Indies; but chiefely in the West: where with a
small number, and as it were with a handfull of men, <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando
Cortez</hi> a Spaniard, in the yeere of our Lord 1519.
discouered and conquered that great, mighty, and rich King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
of <hi>New Spaine,</hi> and the Citie of <hi>Mexico.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
And in the yeere of our Lord 1531. <hi>Don Francisco Pizar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi>
attempted the conquest of the great Kingdome of <hi>Peru;</hi> he
vanquished <hi>Atibalipa,</hi> the King of that Countrey, conquered
and subdued many spacious and rich Prouinces; and in the end
after infinite perils and dangers by practise of the Indians
and much variety of fortune, by ciuill warres with his owne
Nation, he atchiued his enterprise. The particulars of these
discoueries and conquests, are more at large recounted by <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Martyr</hi> in his Decades, by <hi>Benzo,</hi> and diuers other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,
to which for breuities sake I referre you. The honour
these Spaniards gained by these discoueries and conquests, was
doubtlesse great: but the benefit that ensued to the Crowne of
<hi>Spaine,</hi> and all the Spanish Nation thereby, was infinite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
expectation, as amply may appeare in the Authors late
mentioned, and in the Naturall and Morrall history of the East
and West Indies, written by <hi>Iosephus Acosta.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Let vs also note the wonderfull workes of God in those Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
and his great mercy thereby shewed to the Indians, who
by their continuall conuersation with Christians, are redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
from their abhominable life and cruell manners, to the
knowledge of God and their former infidelity, and to the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the holy Ghost in Baptisme; for in all those great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces,
conquered in <hi>New Spaine,</hi> the people are generaly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted
to Christianity: for about the yeere of our Lord 1524.
there went diuers learned men into those parts, who by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the Indians languages, and their painefull diligence in
teaching and instructing youth, did so effectually proceed in
that laborious worke, that within the limits of many hundred
leagues, there are few or none vnchristened. The beginning
of that Worke was very difficult, by reason of the vnaptnesse
of the Indians, so long imbrued in cruell sacrifices of humane
blood, and abhominable Idolatry, and by the continuall malice
of the diuell, rebelling against God, and striuing to maintaine
<pb facs="7"/>
his owne kingdome: but in the end their constant and paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
indeuours so farre preuailed, that Christian religion
increased amongst them, to the establishing of many Bishopricks
in <hi>New Spaine,</hi> besides diuers Schooles of learning. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
in <hi>Peru,</hi> and diuers other Countries, conquered by the
Spaniards, the conuersions of the people haue proceeded to no
lesse admirable effects.</p>
   <p>As touching the state of common wealth, they haue all
sorts of Gouernours, and magistrates in great honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation;
houses of Nobility and Gentry flourish, and increase
amongst them; Souldiers, and trauellers are regarded highly,
and worthily rewarded; Merchants, and tradesmen pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
and gather wealth in extraordinary measure; what shall
I say more, there bee few or no professions or trades amongst vs,
in these parts of Christendome, but the same are vsed, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
and practised in great perfection, both in <hi>New Spaine,
Peru,</hi> and other parts of the Indies, where the Spaniards haue
preuailed by their Conquests.</p>
   <p>By these memorable examples may our Nation (being in
valour inferiour to none other vnder Heauen) bee moued and
stirred vp to the vndertaking of this noble action of <hi>Guiana;</hi>
which in respect of the climate, firtility of the soile, and tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
disposition of the people (whereof in the following discourse
I haue spoken more at large) doth assure vs that (with Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
and assistance) as great effects may bee wrought in
the conuersion of these Nations, and as great benefit, and
commoditie may arise to the Realme and Crowne of England,
both in generall, and particular, as euer was performed or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
by the Spanish Nation, since the first beginning of their
trauels and discoueries.</p>
   <p>For if they in <hi>New Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> haue Cuchenille,
Anir, and Cotton wooll; wee in <hi>Guiana</hi> haue also Cotton
wooll Tobacco, Suger-Canes, diuers good commodities for
<pb facs="7"/>
Dyers, and likewise in all likelihood Cuchenille; and sundry
sorts of excellent wood for ioyners worke, and other vses. If
they haue variety of Apothecary drugges, and Balsome for
Phisicke, and Chirurgery; so also haue wee, and those that
are of admirable vertue. If they haue gold, siluer, and other
mettalls; Pearles, and pretious stonnes; so doublesse wee in
time may haue the like, hauing had good testimony thereof
already; as plainely shall appeare hereafter, when time better
serueth.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, in singular aduantage wee haue before them to
further, and aduance our enterprise, by the peculiar loue and
affection of the people in those parts, towards our Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
all others. For whereas the Spaniards were constrained
by great labour, bloudy battailes, and much cruelty (for which
they lost their hearts) to subdue the Indians; wee contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
are well entertained, and friendly receiued by them, being
willing to hold commerce with vs; whereby wee haue a more
secure and ready meane, to establish a peaceable and assured
Commonwealth amongst them, for the imployment of all the
seuerall professions of men mentioned before.</p>
   <p>Finally, for your better inducement to the worthy vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking
of this high action; let vs call to remembrance one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
and materiall obseruation; that is the discouery of this
Countrey of <hi>Guiana,</hi> was heretofore attempted by <hi>S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Walter
Raleigh,</hi> who made an honourable entry thereinto by the riuer
of <hi>Orenoque;</hi> what hee then, and there discouered, and how
great and assured his hopes were, of gaining to our Countrey
inestimable riches, and subduing to the Crowne of <hi>England</hi>
a potent Empire, was effectually, and faithfully published to
the world by his owne penne; which excellent discourse I wish
you to peruse, preceeding from so wise and iudiciall an
Author; who if some knowne fortunes had not crossed his
first intendiments, for the prosecuting of that enterprise) had
<pb facs="8"/>
(in all likelihood) long before this time increased the honour
of our Nation, by the reputation of the most famous and rich
discouery and conquest that the world could afford.</p>
   <p>Let vs herewithal obserue, that before his time it was often
attempted by the Spaniards, but to small effect; for eyther by
misfortune of shipwrack, discention amongst the most eminent
persons in their Troopes, mutiny of the souldiers, mistaking
of the Commanders, or violent fury of the Indians (who beare
an inueterate and mortall hatred against them) they haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
failed of their purpose: whereof the said discourse of <hi>S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>.
Walter Raleigh</hi> maketh particular mention more at large.</p>
   <p>The continuall losse, and great misfortunes that haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
the Spaniards from time to time, in all their attempts of
this discouery and conquest, for the space almost of an hundred
yeeres; and the fortunate successe that most happily fauoured
the other in his first attempt thereof, may bee a great presumti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and may giue vs an assured hope, that the powerfull hand
of God doth worke for vs in this behalfe; and hath reserued
the execution of this action for honour of our Nation.</p>
   <p>Which forcible considerations, gaue me great encouragement
to repaire the decay of so worthy an enterprise, not with intent
to rob him of his honour, who first of all our Nation (nobly
with great iudgement and valour) gaue the onset; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to doe him more honour, by working vpon his foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and prosecuting this proiect, according to his first designes,
which doubtlesse aimed at the glory of God, his Soueraignes
seruice, and his Countries good.</p>
   <p>Hereupon I made triall of my fortune in the attempt, and
haue found the successe so prosperous and hopefull, (although
it hath been chargeable vnto mee) and my acceptance so free
and friendly amongst the Indians, that it hath giuen not only
to my selfe, but also to the rest of my associats, (who with the
loue and good liking of the people, haue liued and remained in
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>Guiana</hi> for the space of three yeares) good assurance of repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the charge past with trebble recompence; and a resolued
courage to proceed in the enterprise, to the prosecution where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
we haue deuoted both our substance and our selues.</p>
   <p>And because the life of this Action consisteth in the timely
progresse thereof, and requireth the assistance of many Aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers;
I thought it very needful to lay before you these former
examples, and materiall considerations: and therewithall doe
recommend vnto your view this following Discourse (wherein
I haue compiled the hopefull fruites of my painefull trauels)
thereby to moue you to wipe away from your eyes, the cloudie
incredulous blindnesse that possessed our forefathers in the
dayes of <hi>Henry</hi> the seuenth, when they reiected the offer made
by <hi>Batholomew Columbus,</hi> in the behalfe of his brother
<hi>Christopher Columbus,</hi> and therby lost the fruition of those
inestimable riches in the West Indies, which now we see posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
by the Spanish Nation: And also doe inuite and summon
my Country-men in generall, to rouze vp their valour, to quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
and spurre on their endevours, to be coadi<gap reason="illegible: obscured" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>utors with vs in
this action, both of honour and profit.</p>
   <p>And because it may be obiected to the discouragement of
such as may haue otherwise a desire to inhabit <hi>Guiana,</hi> that
the Spaniards inhabiting about <hi>Cumana, Margarita,</hi> and
<hi>Trinidado,</hi> may disturbour Plantation, and indanger the liues
of those that shall make the first settlement there; I thought
good to resolue all such as haue affection to make themselues
Conquerors of that goodly Countrey, that from the King of
Spaines Indies nothing can offend them; for <hi>Guiana</hi> being
seated in the head of the Brises, and to the wind-ward of al the
Spanish Indies, the current also of the Sea setting to the West,
maketh it impossible for any Shipping to turne it vp from the
forenamed places towards vs. The Spaniard therefore can no
way offend vs but by a preparation out of <hi>Spaine</hi> it selfe. And
<pb facs="9"/>
whensoeuer he shall finde himselfe at so great leisure, as to send
a Fleet out of <hi>Spaine</hi> to seeke vs out vpon the shallow coast of
<hi>Guiana,</hi> eyther we shall frustrate that attempt by raising a
Fort defensible for two or three moneths (for they must famish
if they stay longer) or else by setting our selues aboue two or
three of the ouerfalles of the Riuers, where one hundred men
will defend themselues against fiue thousand. But I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded
that the Spaniards will take great deliberation, and be
well aduised of all insuing accidents, before they giue any at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
vpon vs: for we doe not finde that they haue yet attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
any thing vpon <hi>Virginia,</hi> which lieth in their way home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
from the West Indies, albeit there haue passed many years
since the first Plantation there. And surely, if <hi>Virginia</hi> had
not a sharpe Winter, which <hi>Guiana</hi> hath not (which Countrey
of <hi>Guiana</hi> is blest with a perpetuall Summer, and a perpetuall
Spring) and that it had that store of victuals which <hi>Guiana</hi>
hath, it would in a short time grow to be a most profitable place.
But thus much I can auow truely, that from <hi>Guiana,</hi> without
any great labour, there may be returned within the yeare, good
store of Cotton Wooll, very rich Dyes, diuers sorts of Gummes,
many sorts of Fethers, all kindes of rich Woods, Balsamums,
Iasper, and Porpherie stone, Waxe, Honey, and Tobacco, and so
euery yeare may we pay the Transportation, vntill we encrease
in people to make Sugars, and discouer Mines.</p>
   <p>If the paines past bestowed in my first attempt, may taste of
your gratefull acceptance, and that I may obtaine your willing
furtherance in the future, I shall then thinke my paines well
imployed, and delight my selfe in labouring for your profit; and
we all shall gaine honour and reputation, by vndergoing the
burden of so worthy a worke; whereby our Nation shall bee
greatly enriched, the Dominion of our Soueraigne much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged,
and Gods seruice in those Countries highly aduanced.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>R. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>