<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Rogers, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103184_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10914</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21185</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103184</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Rogers, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse of Christian watchfulnesse : Preparing how to liue, how to die, and to be discharged at the day of iudgement, and so enioy life eternall. By Iohn Rogers minister to the Church of Chacombe in Northampton-shiere</title>
                 <author>Rogers, John, of Chacombe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 369, that is 357, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aruell not (Christian Reader) if in publishing this Sermon, whereas (it may be) better, and more of this Argument (though I saw none) be extant, I incurre the same fault which <hi>Cato</hi> the graue Censour reproued in a certaine Roman, who taking vpon him to write a Storie in Greeke, had rather craue pardon of his fault, then keepe himselfe cleare from committing it <note n="a" place="margin">Citatur a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> in prim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> sex thesium.</note>: for when this Sermon was preached, I intended no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing lesse then the committing of it to the Presse: yet so it was, that being requested to Preach at a Gentlewomans buriall <note n="b" place="margin">The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siō of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing this Sermon.</note> and that vpon a sudden, not hauing twelue houres, no nor scarce sixe, to chuse and peruse my Text, my warning was so short and the time busie, iust two daies before Easter; and also before a iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and more then ordinary assembly, so that I had not that libertie granted me which Bears <note n="c" place="margin">Plin. lib. 8. cap. 36. &amp; Aclia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> de hist. Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> haue to lick their new-borne foales, to bring them to their owne fashion: yet (as alwaies) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying vpon the Lords present assistance (who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="8"/>
giueth better successe to short meditations, vndertaken in his Name, then to longer studies) I went to worke, affecting more (as <hi>Augustine</hi> teacheth) <hi>documenta, quam ornamenta</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Austin. de doct. Christ. li. 4. ca. 19.</note> for profitable instructions to edifie the Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, then Rhetoricall braueries to glow and tickle Attick eares; as speaking (with <hi>C. Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius)</hi> but <hi>Tarentinis &amp; Consentinis meis,</hi> who kindly gaue me wished approbation in the whole; <note n="e" place="margin">Cicero de Orat. l. 2 &amp; de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>inib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum li. 1.</note> yet this acceptance (as after it approued) was not so generall; but some few eying (as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> said) <note n="f" place="margin">Aust. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra faust. li. 5. cap. 11.</note> the Chaffe more then the Wheate of my Corne, disliked somethings cause<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse; so that (which one said) <note n="g" place="margin">Fabius Quintil.</note> is true, that <hi>foelices essent Artes, si de illis soli artifices, judicarent:</hi> but when the fooles of the people fall a censuring aboue their slipper <note n="h" place="margin">Sutor vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra crepidā.</note>: then then they to extoll themselues, take their Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to be madde and void of common sense (if they be zealous in Gods cause) and so Christ himselfe was taken as is in <hi>Mark. 3. 21. Ioh. 10. 20.</hi> and so the Abderits <note n="i" place="margin">Iuter epist. Hypocra. &amp; citatur a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nald. orat. 13</note> did <hi>Democritus,</hi> who sent for <hi>Hypocrates</hi> to giue him Helleber to cure his madnesse <hi>(virtutis laborem in sani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am arbitrantes)</hi> who comming, and admiring his Wisedome, told them that <hi>they more nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Helleber then He:</hi> And therefore (I say with <hi>Paul)</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 13.</note>; <hi>Whether we be out of our wits or in our wits, we are to God and you:</hi> and for my part I acknowledge with <hi>Austine</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">Angust. ad Pascentium epist. 174.</note>, that <hi>facile est, vt quis{que} vincat Augustinum,
<pb facs="8"/>
sed videris, vtrum veritate an clamore:</hi> easie it is to depraue my labours, but let them see whether they doe it by vniust clamours or by truth: and with <hi>Hierome</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">Hieron. dial. 1. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. Pelag.</note> likewise: <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niter respondeo, nunquam me haereticis pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percisse; sed omni egisse studio, vt hostes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiae, mei quoque hostes fierent:</hi> I neuer spared grosse transgressors (though truth bred me much hatred, and I had the more enemies thereby) but euer plainely and openly reproued them, and therefore often want there fauourable allowance in my proceedings: and no matter; <hi>For if I yet pleased men, I should not be the Seruant of Christ</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">Gal. 1. 10</note>. The issue then was, that my name was not only made a Tenis-ball &amp; Table-talke, but withall I was complained vpon to the Ecclesiasticall Magistrate, where I was faine to answere it, and besides, was in priuate so sharpely rebuked (of such as hard me not) as vnworthy of the name of a Minister, so that I might well complaine with <hi>Hierome</hi>
      <note n="o" place="margin">Hieron al Theoph ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. Ioan. Hierosolym.</note>: <hi>Ita nomen meum frequenter assumitur, &amp; car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur, ac si de libro viuentium deletus essem.</hi> And although that be true, which one saith, <hi>Hominem ingenuum irrideri turpissimum cruciari humanum</hi>
      <note n="p" place="margin">Iu Menā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro.</note>: yet for my part, I giue them thankes, for (as <hi>Plutarch</hi>
      <note n="q" place="margin">Lib. de v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitate ad hostib. capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nda.</note> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth) it will make me more circumspect, but because that <hi>optima non vllo causa tuente pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>it;</hi> I will vse only that Apologie which <hi>Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> did <note n="r" place="margin">Cicero in C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> who being accused of dotage, only
<pb facs="9"/>
recited a Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>edy called <hi>Oedipus Coloneus,</hi> made lately by him, demanding of the Iudges, if that Comedy seemed to be made by a doter or madde man. So I, for my defence, doe set forth the Sermon <hi>verbatim</hi> as I preached it, not sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing nor altering any one clause, only (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse) that in the penning thereof (as all men vse in the like) my penne ranne somewhat swift, which made euery part of the Sermon the larger, which I take to bee no fault, for so I (as with a Commentarie) cleare what was obscure, dilate what was briefly deliuered, explain things mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, &amp; adde some things further for the Readers benefit. But <hi>Quam amanter, &amp; fideliter mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo conscientia mihi testis est; si paulo aspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi>
      <note place="margin">s Ioan. Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nold. Orat. 13.</note>
      <hi>requirunt tempora; si minus cū fructu, meliora spero; si imprudentius, incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius; volui quod debui, praestiti quod potui; laudandum vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uisse, non prestitisse ignoscen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum:</hi> gentle Reader peruse it throughly, and iudge charitably, and Gods grace be with thee, and his blessing vpon thee, that long thou maiest reade, and much maiest thou profit, to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, thy comfort, and benefit of his Church. <hi>Pax praedicantibus, gratia audientibus, &amp;</hi>
      <note place="margin">t Foxiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>gloria Iesu Christo,</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord while thou art the Lords, Iohn Rogers.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>