<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>WILLIAM KETHE TO the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1558</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103263_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01880</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12020</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103263</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>WILLIAM KETHE TO the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>How superior powers oght to be obeyd of their subiects : and wherin they may lawfully by Gods Worde be disobeyed and resisted. Wherin also is declared the cause of all this present miserie in England, and the onely way to remedy the same. By Christopher Goodman</title>
                 <author>Goodman, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Crespin (Crispin), Jean</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Switzerland--Geneva City</pubPlace>
                    <date>1558</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>234, 6 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="118"/>
   <head>WILLIAM KETHE TO the Reader.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>THe vayne harte of mā, full frayle is and blynde,</l>
      <l>vncerteynely setled, and rest can none fynde:</l>
      <l>Whose hap is in wandring, to wade the wronge way,</l>
      <l>As one apte by kinde to runne still astray.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For, what thīge so good by truethe hathe bene wr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oght,</l>
      <l>Or what so well framed hath nature forth brought,</l>
      <l>Which man is not prone by crafte to accuse,</l>
      <l>And natures good gyftes dothe not sore abuse?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Thus see we how man, contemning Gods grace,</l>
      <l>Is wholie inclyned, that ill shulde take place:</l>
      <l>Whose will (truethe reiectinge) delitth that to haue,</l>
      <l>Which nature corrupted woulde seeme still to craue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Sith man then in iudgeinge, so thwartly is bente.</l>
      <l>To satisfie fansie, and not true intente:</l>
      <l>How hardly in this case, can such iudge vpright,</l>
      <l>Whē trueth doth but peepe out, as semth to our sight.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Ful nedefull then were it, we had this respecte,</l>
      <l>Before we receaue oght, or oght do reiect:</l>
      <l>The thinge to decide so with Iudgement and skill,</l>
      <l>That trueth may be stickler, and not our one will.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Beholde here a trueth drawne forth of her graue,</l>
      <l>By power sore oppressed, and made a bonde slaue:</l>
      <l>Whose chaīs, thogh this Autor could not rēt or teare,</l>
      <l>Yet hath he forth broght hir, in to moste clere ayer.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>With whome now to reason, whoso wil assaye,</l>
      <l>Shal learne how ill Rulers we oght to obeye.</l>
      <l>Whiche kill, how they ca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e not in their cruell rage.</l>
      <l>Respectīg their will more, thē lawe, othe, or charge.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="119"/>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap> longe fostered by suffrance and awe,</l>
      <l>Haue right rule subuerted, and made will their lawe:</l>
      <l>Whose pride, how to temper, this truthe will thee tell,</l>
      <l>So as thou resiste mayste, and yet not rebell.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Rebellion is ill, to resiste is not so,</l>
      <l>When right through resisting, is donne to that foo,</l>
      <l>Who seeketh, but by ruine, agaynst right to raigne,</l>
      <l>Not passinge what perishe, so she spoyle the gayne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>A publick weale wretched, and to farre disgraste,</l>
      <l>Where the right-head is of cut, and a wronge in steed plaste,</l>
      <l>A brut beast vntamed a misbegotthen;</l>
      <l>More meete to be ruled, then raigne ouer men.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>A maruelous madnesse, if we well beholde,</l>
      <l>When sighes shall assaut mē, to see them selues solde:</l>
      <l>And yet whē frō slauery, their friēds woulde thē free,</l>
      <l>To stick to their foes so, still slaues to be.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For France spiteth Spayne, which Englend doth threat,</l>
      <l>And England proud Spanyards, with salte woulde fayne eate:</l>
      <l>Yet Englande proud Spayne aydeth with men, ships, and botes.</l>
      <l>That Spayne, (France subdued once) may cut all their throtes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>A people peruerse, repleate with disdayne,</l>
      <l>Thogh flattrie fayne hide woulde their hate, and vile trayne.</l>
      <l>Whose rage, ād hotte luste, disceate, crafte and pride,</l>
      <l>Poore Naples their bondeslaue, with great grefe hath tryed.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="119"/>
      <l>Lo, these be the byrdes which Englāde muste feede,</l>
      <l>By plantinge of whom, to roote out their seede</l>
      <l>Their owne landes ād lyues, by them firste deuourde,</l>
      <l>Their maydes then ād wyues, moste vilelie deflourde.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Is this not stronge treason, ye vnnoble bloudds?</l>
      <l>To ayde suche destroyers, both with landes ād goods?</l>
      <l>But when they thus pinche you, and ye put to flight,</l>
      <l>To what forte then flee you: or where will you light?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For Englande thus solde, for Spaniardes to dwell,</l>
      <l>Ye maye not by right, possesse that ye sell.</l>
      <l>They seinge your treason, agaynste your owne state,</l>
      <l>Wil not with theirs trust you, which they know ye hate.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To Skotlande or France, yf ye then shulde cry,</l>
      <l>Your vile deeds now present, they may well reply,</l>
      <l>And Dutchlād abhorth you: this thē doth remayne,</l>
      <l>Whē Spaniards are placed, ye muste to newe Spayne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But, oh dreadfull plague, ād signe of Gods wrothe,</l>
      <l>On such noble Gnatos, stronge foes to Gods trothe.</l>
      <l>Whom fonde feare hath framed, to prop such a staye,</l>
      <l>As countrie and people, so seekth to betraye.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Which thinge herein proued, to be with out doute,</l>
      <l>All such full well finde shall, as reade it throughout.</l>
      <l>Yf then their hartes fayle them the right to defende,</l>
      <l>Confusion remayneth for suche a meete end.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>