<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Premonition to the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103012_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01575</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11700</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103012</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Premonition to the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two sermons : One, the curse and crime of Meroz. Preached at the assises at Exon. The other, a sermon of patience. At St Maries in Oxford. By Edward Gee, Doctor in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to his Maiestie. Published since his death, by his two brethren, Iohn Gee and George Gee, ministers of Gods Word</title>
                 <author>Gee, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 62 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A Premonition to the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O yeeld any reasons for the publishing these Sermons (considering the suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie of the Author, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the Argument) were to call into question the valew of an Offering cast into the treasurie of Gods Church. If <hi>TERTVLLIAN,</hi> an ancient and learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (when the Light of the Gospel shined neerer the times of the primitiue puritie) confessed that hee did adore the fulnesse of the Scriptures: Haue wee lesse cause, in these dayes (indeed not of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but of contention and libertie) to respect the sincere Expositors of the Mysteries of GOD? espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when euerie man is almost become an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretor to himselfe. But for as much as they who are the Publishers of these exercises, can best giue resolution for their publication, (how euer extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie occasions vnexpectedly withcal'd them for the present;) yet, where a man in his life time so knowne, and so deseruing to be knowne for since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of conucrsation, generalitie of learning, graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of iudgement, and soundnesse of Doctrine (as
<pb facs="3"/>the Author was) hath left any monument of his studies; there it cannot bee but an iniurie to his memorie, and a kindt of defrauding the Store-house of Religion, to conceale that for any priuate vse, which concernes a publique benefit. A Teacher, after his death, is best commended, by the remaining fruits of his labours; those parcell-reliques of this worthie man, being then read, right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderstood, and applyed, cannot but both informe the charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Christian Reader, and confirme him.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>