<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Norice, Enw.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103140_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08319</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18646</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103140</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Norice, Enw.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise, maintaining that temporall blessings are to bee sought and asked with submission to the will of God : Wherein is confuted the presumptious way of absolute praying for temporals, in the particulars, broached, and defended by Mr. Rice Boye, in a late pamphlet, intituled The importunate beggar. As also a discovery of the late dangerous errours of Mr. Iohn Traske, and most of his strange assertions. Both necessary to be knowne of all for the avoiding of the like errours, and continuing in the truth. By Edw: Norice</title>
                 <author>Norris, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 168 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader,</hi> It is so that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 7. yeares sithence, there arose an opinion in the Westerne parts, that men are to pray for temporall things in as absolute a manner as for spirituall, and that the promises are alike: one of the chiefe broachers of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb facs="3"/>(being a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi>) comes to me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the same was publikly known, and craftily demands of me, whether we may not absolutely pray unto <hi>God</hi> for bread, &amp; depend upon his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidēce for necessaries; to which I answered, that I conceived wee might and ought: shortly after I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood that there was more in the matter, &amp;
<pb facs="3"/>that under bread and necessaries, they intē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, health, life, food, raiment, good successe in affaires, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conveniences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to our selves, or others; with this rule and position that whosoever did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve should certainly obtaine those things in the particular, and if any did not, it was because they wanted<note n="*" place="margin">He pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the faith of miracles to continu stil. And that all which dyed of the plague wā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted faith.</note>
      <hi>Faith.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p>Hereupon were the <hi>consciences</hi> of many people, that lay under some outward afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (as poverty, sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of themselves or theirs, il successe, &amp;c.) much disquietted and troubled, being char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by them with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe in their praiers (as some of them cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed) &amp; making their moan concerning the same, I was intreated to deliver some <hi>grouds</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>in publicke about the point, &amp; to lay down directions cōcerning a right maner of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for tēporal things, that they might know whereupon to settle themselves, and their practise: This upon request (there being yet no open contesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) I was willing to do; and taking a stem upon a Festival, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to that purpose <hi>the fourth Petition of the
<pb facs="5"/>Lords Prayer,</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring therin certain <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments</hi> against such kind of absolute pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>outward things,</hi> and defending the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon received <hi>doctrine</hi> of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and all other Churches.</p>
   <p>VVhereat under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing shortly after how much hee was displeased, I copyed out my <hi>Arguments,</hi> and sent them to him;
<pb facs="5"/>vvhereupon he sent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad a large <hi>discourse</hi> of the point, declaring upon vvhat Grounds they held their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and with vvhat cautions of <hi>repentance</hi> &amp; <hi>love,</hi> asvvell as <hi>faith.</hi> And not long after (as I remember) an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to my five <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> inveighing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vvhere against me, and my Sermon, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with his <hi>answere</hi> to me, sharp <hi>Invectives</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>against me, for vvhat I had done and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; vvhich letters I have by mee yet to shew, ful of reproach. Hereupon I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to extract cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of his grossest <hi>Assertions,</hi> and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to the vievv of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring <hi>Ministers,</hi> that they might see vvhat <hi>Doctrine</hi> was taught, and secretly vented a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their people:
<pb facs="6"/>vvarning him vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, not to make any publike <hi>Controversie</hi> in the Church, in regard of the law forbidding the same, &amp; admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing him further by private Letters of his errour, &amp; evill dealing with me After which he was privatly &amp; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly dealt withall, by divers learned and able <hi>Ministers,</hi> labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to convince him, but all in vaine; for
<pb facs="7"/>in stead of hearkning to their counsell, hee reproached their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons with vaunts and brags, as hee had used me before, and was so far frō reforming this opinion, that hee ran out into an other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of <hi>Separation,</hi> disclaiming utterly of the Church, or any Communion with it. I then seeing the man to be so wilfull in his wayes, medled no
<pb facs="7"/>more in this poynt, but (having satisfied many) gave it over, and so it hath rested these five yeares, or thereabouts.</p>
   <p>Now after all this time (being it seemes in love with his olde conceits) he hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seasonably printed by stealth al those former passages: the <hi>Discourse</hi> of his <hi>Opinion;</hi> my <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments</hi> with their <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers;</hi> the <hi>extract</hi> of his
<pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>Assertions,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>It was,</hi> Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erilis the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologia.</note> stiling it my <hi>Prosopopeia;</hi> and his <hi>distinction</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> into <hi>Eternall,</hi> and <hi>Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> intituling the same, <hi>The importunat Beggar;</hi> vvhich hee hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlarded with many foule slāders, unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy imputations, and bitter invectives, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring me, and other <hi>Ministers</hi> that dealt with him, to <hi>Jannes</hi> &amp; <hi>Jambres,</hi> with those <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian jugglers</hi> which
<pb facs="8"/>withstood <hi>Moses,</hi> w<seg rend="sup">th</seg> such like stuffe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is full. And this he doth under pretēce that I had again refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie as much as before; whereas it cannot be proved, neither can I possibly remēber that I have at all medled with the controversie wellneers these five yeares, but had almost forgotten it.</p>
   <p>Being thus unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily
<pb facs="9"/>dealth withall, I thought it necessarie for the vindicating of my selfe, but chiefly of the <hi>Truth</hi> from his slanders (if leave may be given) to returne some answere to his <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> &amp; to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine &amp; confirme the ancient received Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and usuall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of <hi>Christians</hi> in this behalfe; to which purpose, I conceived it best to publish the
<pb facs="9"/>Sermon it selfe, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my briefe <hi>Notes</hi>) and withall, by way of <hi>Explication,</hi> to defend the truth of my Argumēts against his Replies &amp; Answers, as they lie in order, that all may see &amp; so judge of what was then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, and is still de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by me. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in admonishing the <hi>Reader</hi> first of these few things.</p>
   <p n="1">1. That in my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,
<pb facs="10"/>I stile him not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch fully the <hi>Boy,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his name; nor yet the <hi>Beggar,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the title of his booke, as I might have done; but rather the <hi>Temporary,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his singular o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of a <hi>Temporary faith,</hi> as best suiting with the matter in hand, and the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his building.</p>
   <p n="2">2. That in my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, (vvhich I little
<pb facs="10"/>thought should haue bin made so publike) I gathered such Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento, &amp; handled all in such a manner, as the time of <hi>Preparatiō</hi> would afford, &amp; was most agreeable to the quality of the Audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; w<seg rend="sup">th</seg> course I have followed in this <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> being chiefly to deale with such, and not with any of the Learneder sort,<note place="margin">For which cause I cite those Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors as are most familiar.</note> as knowing none intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled
<pb facs="11"/>with the errour.</p>
   <p n="3">3. That in my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, I have indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured as to avoid his scurrility, a thing not imitable: so also not to trace him in all his vvandring Discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, vvhich vvere end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse: but rather to answer plainly to the poynt and matter, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the rest to vanish as a myst, the light of Trueth comming in place: vvhich I speak
<pb facs="11"/>to prevent any more slanders of his (if it may bee) that I have not answered his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, or mis-tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed his Writings, because I have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearsed every imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent speech, or idle passage in thē, which I held needlesse, but onely the substance of his Doctrine &amp; drift, as hee defendeth it in his Booke; vvherein I have not wronged
<pb facs="12"/>him (that I know) a syllable. And thus <hi>Reader,</hi> commending all to the blessing of God, and thy selfe to his grace, praying that we may all be guided by a right Spirit, I remaine</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in, and for the Lord, and his Truth. <hi>Envv. Norice.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>