<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ An aduertisement to the Godly Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103322_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25631</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103322</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ An aduertisement to the Godly Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vnfouldyng of sundry vntruths and absurde propositions : latelye propounded by one I.B. a greate fauourer of the horrible heresie of the libertimes</title>
                 <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>159, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="156" facs="79"/>
   <head>¶ An aduertisement to the <hi>Godly Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>SInce the printing of this work was attempted, certain rumors haue bin spread abrode, by this lewd Libertine, or some of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers, that he neuer held or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded many of these or such like propositions. For mine owne parte I thought good, to aduertise the (gē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reader) of the falshood of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, &amp; that not onely vpon mine owne knowledge, (though therein I might haue sayd much, as who hath bin this 9. or. 10. yeeres some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what acquainted, with these &amp; such like cursed conclusiōs of his: as that we need not to pray specially for forgiuenes of sinnes: and that if we keepe our selues in our castle Christ nothing that we can cōmit in this flesh, can be sinne vnto vs: and that
<pb n="157" facs="79"/>now sith we are maried to Christ, there are no more mē because al are become women) but vpon the assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red testimonies also, of good and sufficient witnesses, in whose hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring &amp; in mine likewise he did not many moneths since, shamelesly vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; speake, the matters and points before rehearsed. Yea if the beastly bookes that he hath penned, as one which he calleth his musicke, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which he calleth his axe, and such others might be brought to light, the world should then see, not onely these, but euen a whole sea of such like absurdities and falshoods, broched and spread abrode. So that there is no reason why the christian reader, should beleue, such flying re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes published, verie cunninglie, to the discredit eyther of this, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other thing, that may be set out against him, specially, considering that it is Satans common custome,
<pb n="158" facs="80"/>both in himself, and in his seruants, to colour their wickednes with ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thereby they might, the more mightely deceiue: and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience hath taught vs, that it hath byn the very vse of sūdrie heretikes, as in old time of the Priscilianistes, and in these dayes of the family of loue, to say and vnsaie. And therfore I wish the godlie Christian to haue an eye to this, not onely to credite this or any other erroneous person, vppon a bare deniall of his or their vntruthes, but for the better sifting of them, to require a plaine, and an open confession, of the contrarie truthes and an yeelding therto, and then no doubte it shall sufficiently appeare, whether the retracting of their errors, bee plaine and simple yea or no. Thus beseeching the Lorde, to giue those that be his, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding in all thinges, that in
<pb n="159" facs="80"/>sound knowledge they may proue, what that good, holie, and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good will of his is, and in bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed obedience, labour with care and conscience, to performe the same, I ende, for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent. At London the 27. of this May. 1581.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>