<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Harris, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103817_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02723</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12855</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103817</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Harris, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvay to trve happinesse : Deliuered in XXIV. sermons vpon the Beatitvdes. By Robert Harris, B. in Diuinity, and pastor of Hanwell. Also, a treatise of the nevv covenant; set forth sermon-wise, on Ezechiel the XI. By the same avthovr</title>
                 <author>Harris, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Bartlet, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Badger, Richard 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 115, 114-322, 186, 2, 8, 68, 52, 55-76, that is 79, 90-129, 140-196, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou wilt thinke thy time lost, and thy selfe wronged, if thou shouldst not find here what thou seekest for, I'll therefore deale plainely, and doe as I would be done by: First, if thou be a verbalist, and standest vpon compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, here's nothing for thee: First, my Auditory was partly very learned, and so aboue words; partly very plaine, and so below them: Secondly, my selfe am both vnable, and vnwilling to stand on phrases, that, because I am clogg'd with ignorance, age, busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; this, because I finde, that of those poore things of mine, the plainest haue taken best hitherto: Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="7"/> the Scribe who tooke them from my mouth in the Church,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Master</hi> Iohn Trapp.</note> hath beene, contrary to my hopes, and his owne worth, superstitiously modest, else had it been easie for him to haue cast a better coate vpon these ragged meditations, and rather enlarged then abridged them. And so much for that, if thy pulse beat that way. Now, secondly, if thou be a Questionist, spare thy paines; I neuer thought the Pulpit a fit place for brawles and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, to stirre controuersies there (yet <hi>flagrant</hi>) is but to spread them, and therefore, notwithstanding the opportunity which my Text and some mens surmises of mee,<note place="margin">Apostolicae Doctrina expositio est falsae doctrinae optima refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio. <hi>Cassand</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultat.</note> as if I were somewhat warping, gaue mee, I declined polemicalls, so farre as I could, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my selfe with positiue truths, the best confuters.</p>
   <p>Truely, (Reader) I am not priuy to any priuate opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were I, that opinion which bred in me, should be buried with me too; two studies my heart abhorres, to wit, <hi>studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um partium,</hi> and <hi>studium nouarum rerum:</hi> If I can study the truth first, and the peace next, I haue as much learning as I desire, as for credit, my highest ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is that of his, <hi>viz.</hi> that my name may be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,<note place="margin">Pacia.</note> and my surname Catholique: wanton wits may please themselues in more ayerie walkes, sure I am of two things: First, that the most wise and learned of all sorts,<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Amamā</hi> in oration de barbarie in his Antibar.</note> cry downe this luxuriancy in young wits, and call them another way: And secondly, that they who know most, say least, and the maine sticklers in most controuersies, are the men, who least vnderstand where the question <hi>inter partes</hi> sticks. Lastly, if (in the third place) thou wonderest why I would giue way to the publishing of things so ordinary, in an age so learned,
<pb facs="7"/> let this suffice, I feared <hi>Bellarmines</hi> feare,<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Bellar.</hi> de scriptor Eccles. <hi>2. Sermons of godly mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Alphon</hi> a <hi>Castro</hi> aduers. haeres. Abortire coactus sum. &amp;c.</note> being plainly told, that, if I would not publish them, others would, and I had reason to thinke so, because I am already serued so, for, whereas I had conceiued something vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Mathew 5.</hi> two of the younger brethen are taught to speake, before the elder be borne. Hence this anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation, and (as one calls it) abortion. I haue said, now vse thy liberty.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>ROBERT HARRIS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>