<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohn Daye to the Christi∣an Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1559</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103098_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01662</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11800</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103098</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohn Daye to the Christi∣an Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The treasure of Euonymus : conteyninge the vvonderfull hid secretes of nature, touchinge the most apte formes to prepare and destyl medicines, for the conseruation of helth: as quintesse [n] ce, aurum potabile, hippocras, aromatical wynes, balmes, oyles perfumes, garnishyng waters, and other manifold excellent confections. Wherunto are ioyned the formes of sondry apt fornaces, and vessels, required in this art. Translated (with great diligence, [et] laboure) out of Latin, by Peter Morvvying felow of Magdaline Colleadge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Gesner, Konrad</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1559</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 408 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Iohn Daye to the <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsideringe with my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>self (louinge Reader) many and sundrye ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, how y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> nothinge is so desired, so accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, or so necessarye in the time of daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous infirmities, and pearel of bodely helth, as to preserue those y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> are free of sicknes frō the violence of the same, and to restore the sicke, weake, and languishing paciente vnto his former estate and pristinate healthe, which thyng is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the noble and excellente knowledge of Phisicke: and again, howe that this Arte is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised, yea of famous and learned men, which with out any great profit to the pacient, or worship to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> minister, because their medicines are negligently prepared: I thought it my part, by this my trauail and expenses, somwhat to serue herein thy necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Wherfor, I haue caused this precious treasure to be translated into oure vsuall, and natiue lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, that like as all men are subiecte to sicknes: so in likewise all men may by this occasion learne the way vnto helth. And because thauthor (whose name I spare to manifest, for feare of inuious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracters) do in many places of this his work, send the Reader vnto <hi>Philippe Vlstadius</hi> &amp; <hi>Brunsvvick:</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
therfore I will with expedition (if this my labors shall be thankfullye accepted,) also publishe them, sparing neither laboure, diligence, or charges for to bringe them bothe to their perfection, and also thy necessarye vse. As touchinge the excellencye of the preparinge medicines, the vtilitie springinge therof, and the argumente of the worke, because it is exactlye sette oute by the author in the preface folowing, I wil leaue to trouble the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther herein. Fare moste hartely well in Christe. At London the .ii. of May. 1559.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>