<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Worshipfull, Master Reginald Scot, Esqure; dayly increase of wealth, Wor∣ship and wisedom, in the true feare of GOD.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103604_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02428</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12561</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103604</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Worshipfull, Master Reginald Scot, Esqure; dayly increase of wealth, Wor∣ship and wisedom, in the true feare of GOD.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English phlebotomy: or, Method and way of healing by letting of blood : Very profitable in this spring time for the preseruatiue intention, and most needful al the whole yeare beside, for the curatiue intention of phisick. Collected out of good &amp; approued authors at times of leasure from his other studies, and compiled in that order that it is: by N.G</title>
                 <author>Gyer, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Maunsell (Mansell), Andrew 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <publisher>Danter, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hoskins, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 297, 5 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Worshipfull, <hi>Master Reginald Scot, Esqure;</hi> dayly increase of wealth, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and wisedom, in the true <hi>feare of GOD.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS pleasaunt and</hi> profitable practise of blood letting (Right Worshipful Sir) hath always, and that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely been accompted and called of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and latter Phisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Vnum è maioribus remedijs,</hi> one of the greater remedies in the Arte of healing; (not as I take it) for that the same is of gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test charge to the patient his purse, a veine being commonly opened for twelue pence: but because if the same be done with skill according to Arte, it bringeth great profit to health, without any great diminishing of wealth. How this so great a remedy in both the intētions, of Phisick, Preseruatiue and Curatiue, is greatly abused by vagabūd Horse-leaches, &amp; trauailing Tinkers, who find work almost in euery village, through
<pb facs="3"/>
whose wickednes (hauing in truth neither learning, knowledge, witre, nor honesty) the sober practisioner and cunning Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian liueth basely, is despised, and accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a very abiect among the vulgar sorte. The whole world with wofull weepings too too plentifully can witnesse, and many godly and faythful Christians here and else where with pinching paines and griping griefs euen to the last gaspe, haue pitifully felt. For these kinde of men are so farre off from repayrers of mennes bodies, as they would seeme to bee that they are, rather marrers and manglers of men, women and children, without all care to men whome they ought to tender, foster and cherish, without all conscience to God, to whom they must one day render a reckoning of this their desperate and diuelish dealing.</p>
   <p>No man brought vp among Christian mē of any practise or calling, but hath long sithence learned this lesson; how frayle, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, and weake soeuer our mortal bodies are, yet it hath pleased God to call them his owne temples, his owne instruments, and his owne dwelling places: an vnspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb facs="3"/>
dignitie, farre aboue that for which <hi>Alexander Magnus</hi> so contended, when hee would needs bee called the sonne of <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Paul</hi> to the Thessalonians willing vs to keepe our vessels, <hi>viz.</hi> our bodies in holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and honour, suggesteth vnto vs these two poynts: first the fragilitie and mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our earthly bodyes, comparing them to vessels of earth, and pots of clay, which break with a blow, &amp; perish with a knock: secondly, that yet they are not our owne bodyes, to vse as wee list to sensuality like bruite beasts; but to keepe them carefully, as vessels which the Lord hath clensed and washed with his owne blood, to his owne glory in all holynes and honour.</p>
   <p>The Priests of <hi>Baal</hi> cutting and launsing their owne bodies with a vayne and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked supposal, that in so doing they pleased God, grieuously sinned (as diuers affirme) both agaynst nature and godlines; against nature, because no man euer yet hated his owne flesh, but nourisheth and cherisheth it as the Lord doth the Church: against god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, because works of pietie and religion
<pb facs="4"/>
in our selues or in others, they either quite surcease, or are greatly hindered when the bodies of men are decaied in strēgth, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in vigor, languished with sicknes, or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally destroyed by death.</p>
   <p>To let passe these things which diuers deliuer out of their pulpits, of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and dignitie of mans body: haue not the Philosophers in the schooles called the same <hi>Microcosmos, Orbiculus,</hi> a little world most beautiful in forme, &amp; fayrest in shape, excelling farre all other liuing creatures whome the creator hath made. In whose braine, as in <hi>primo mobili,</hi> is fixed that ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemable Iewel called <hi>Reason,</hi> no monster or Idole, but the mother of all Artes &amp; Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, by whome (God guiding the same) are wrought &amp; inuented marueilous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by Sea and by land, in euery matter of speculation or practise. This I haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto discoursed to this drift, that those blinde bussards, &amp; runagate Artists, might at length see and consider that they are no way willed or warāted like butchers to cut, rend and teare, the bodies of men without skil, either in letting blod or any other pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise
<pb facs="4"/>
of Chirurgi, but like brethren to cure, repayr and amend that which is amisse, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing no paine taking for their own parts, nor reiecting due consultation with men experienced, that so the noble Science of healing may be generally honored, the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eased recouered, &amp; the skilful workman worthily in fine rewarded.</p>
   <p>To met with this mischief acording to my Mediocritie, and that such as are desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of this practise either for pleasure or profite, might be somwhat fraughted with a few pithy instructions and necessary rules in the same, and so at length attaine to the most exquisite cunning &amp; deep knowledge therof: I haue thought it good not onely to publish this my rude collection, contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (if I be not deceiued) the whole han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diwork of Phlebotomy, but also to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruaile my default as rudely, (yet most hū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) to request your worships fauour for the protection thereof.</p>
   <p>But for as much as <hi>Seneca</hi> that christian Ethnicke (for so dooth <hi>Erasmus</hi> terme him, for his profound wisedome &amp; deepe indgement) willeth vs in bestowing of any
<pb facs="5"/>
gift to be careful that it be fit for the estate of the giuer, and also meete for the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the receiuer, least in stead of expected thanks disgrace may growe, and what the giuer meaneth of good will, may perhaps by the receiuer either limping in iudgmēt, or freezing in delight, be little regarded, &amp; lesse countenaunced: I am in a worde or two to shew that for my part I haue not (as I thinke) much swarued from the sound aduise of the Philosopher, in making your worship patron of my poore seely paines.</p>
   <p>First for that euen your selfe haue already in print in your booke called <hi>The discouery of VVitchcraft,</hi> openly &amp; biterly enueighed against one sort of blood thirsty men, as I doo nowe against another sorte: namely witchmongers, who are daily and hourely without iust cause conuenting before Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, and haling to the halter (if the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates dexterity in the administration of iustice did not moderate their malice in murthering) poore, plaine, seely and simple innocents, and olde women: whom by fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous euidences, incredible proofes, vayn ghesses, preiudicate presumptions, meere
<pb facs="5"/>
impossibilityes they would haue condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and executed for witches. These men, in mine opinion, should farre better please God, and much better deserue, of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian cōmon wealth, if they would speedily turne from this their heathenish Infidelity, extream folly, &amp; barbarous cruelty, &amp; seek rather by due execution of lawe &amp; iustice the blood of these bloodsuckers indeede, who for want of skil in this profitable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of blood letting, in euery corner of the countrey without controlment, either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently kyl, or at leastwise accelerate the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mature deaths of dyuers faythful Christiās to God, and good subiects to their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne. A poore man that robbeth or killeth but one man, is strayght way trussed vp at Tyborne, and these desperate dicks which range the countrey with a budget of grosse stuffe, a boxe of salue, and a case of tooles, liuing in the Sanctuary of Idlenes, skilful in palmestry, tellers of fortunes, coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeyting themselues to be Iewes or Egip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians: imitatyng doctor <hi>Tocrub,</hi> with strāge lookes, diricks, pricks, crosses, figures, and such foolish fantasies, may safely kill thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands:
<pb facs="6"/>
no moe thē come vnder theyr hands, which is as many as they can get; for who is so bolde as blind Bayard? and withal mē must giue them money for murthering, whereas if they had had their iust hire, they should haue had hanging.</p>
   <p>Secondly, I haue thought your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship a meet person to dedicate this booke vnto, not so much for that it was penned at vacant times during mine abode at <hi>Scots Hall,</hi> vnder which roofe I came by your good meanes; but rather for that, thorow you whē the same was first penned it passed the view and apportatiō of that right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull and wise man M. <hi>Doctor Coldwel,</hi> a piller in this our age of that noble profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. I assure you I thought my selfe happy to haue my little Latine examined by the direction of his iudgement to whose wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and famous faculty, the matters therein mētioned were most properly appertaining.</p>
   <p>Thirdly for that being thorowly acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with your gentlemāly conditions, I am not ignorant of that ardent affection which you haue alwaies caried vnto your friends, Gentlemen I meane of like qualitie with
<pb facs="6"/>
your selfe: for, <hi>Amicitia inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ares,</hi> Loue is among like, as sayth the Philosopher, whome as you loue earnestly in time of their felicity, and health, so you neuer loathe in their calamity or sicknes, putting in vre that work of compassion &amp; Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity commended, and commanded vs in the Gospel of visiting the sick: which work as you now execute frendly without feare, so in fine you shall not finde without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. In visiting your sick friends, for <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er peritura perituri viuimus:</hi> this booke (if you will vouchsafe to bestow some va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant time in reading of it) may stand you and them in some stead, though not by cū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the practise, yet by counsell in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise: for verily it contayneth the right Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode and way of healing, practised by the auncient fathers in Phisick, <hi>Hippocrates, Galen</hi> and <hi>Auicen.</hi> And as you like a good Christian defie al magical cures which ar but cousonages, &amp; would haue other men doo the like: so here you may spie a very ready way rightly to cure all humane dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases, compendious &amp; not costly, both for your selfe and for your frined. To let passe
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Lysimachus</hi> a worthy Captayne to <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Artemisia</hi> a noble Queene, <hi>Gentian</hi> King of <hi>Illyrica,</hi> King <hi>Salomō,</hi> &amp; Queen <hi>Saba</hi> taught by <hi>Salomon</hi> in the secrets of Phisick and Nature, to the encouragement of all learned and wise gentlemen whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they doo otherwise professe) to take now and then some Phisicall discourse in hād. I produce the example of <hi>Dioscorides,</hi> no meane gentleman, but a noble Knight of Egipt who serued <hi>Anthonius</hi> and <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patra</hi> like a worthy Souldier in the field, &amp; was so delighted euen on the midst of his martial affayres with the study of Phisicke and Surgery: that one way <hi>vz.</hi> in the noble knowledge of Oiles, he excelled all men before his time, or since.</p>
   <p>For my selfe that am the giuer, if it bee obiected that this labour is friuolous, for that other men of far greater gifts than my selfe, euen of the self same profession, haue writtē of this argumēt in the english toung long agoe, as namelie Sir <hi>Thomas Eliot, &amp; Doctor Bullein,</hi> with diuers others, men of famous memorie▪ the one writing a Castle, the other a Bulwark of health: My answere
<pb facs="7"/>
is, that hardlie discusse we that argument, whereof something before to that or the like effect hath not bin extant; &amp; this I add beside, that these men intreating of manie things in one booke, were constrained euen purposelie to pretermitte some, yea diuers needful instructions which here may bee had largely discussed.</p>
   <p>If it be said that a matter of Phisick is no fit argument for a Diuine to handle, albeit I might easily wash away this with the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant examples of diuers Diuines to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, as of old <hi>Doctor Turner, Doctor Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, &amp; Doctor Coldwel:</hi> Now with diuers others yet will I say somwhat more, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that both these the Diuine and the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition work vpō one subiect, they assemble themselues in one place, <hi>vz.</hi> the chamber of the sick, they both visite and busie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues about the sick to doe him good, he is no longer <hi>Homo</hi> but <hi>Cadauer</hi> if there bee once a separation of the soule from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. <hi>Vbi desinit-Philosophus, ibi incipit medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> where the Philosopher endeth, there beginneth the Phisition: so may it be saide likewise in some sense, <hi>Vbi desinit medicus,</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>ibi incipit Theologus:</hi> where the Phisirion fayleth for the bodies recouery, there the Diuine is required for the soules health. For mine owne parte I am fully perswaded in mine owne conscience (think or say others what they list) that I haue done more good to the Church of God and common welth of this land, in this simple translatiō or col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, call it whether you wil (for I haue but borrowed it of others &amp; brought it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the english) then diuers dogged Diuines of this age, <hi>Penry, Browne, Barrow,</hi> and the sectaries I meane, who in stead of the true bread of life that came down from heauen, euen Iesus Christ with his whole &amp; whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some doctrine, fed most daungerously the soules of men with diuilish deuises, &amp; their owne fantasies accounted thēselues terrene Gods, &amp; desirous of nothing more then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their auditors, to haue their own po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions horrible &amp; hereticall tobe admired &amp; embraced as oracles from heauen. If the end of this more then Pharisaical hipocrisie be not the disturbance of Gods peace &amp; the Queenes, the wisest men in this land haue vtterly lost their wittes, which these men
<pb facs="8"/>
with al their learning, if they haue it in such plenty as they would seeme to haue, shall neuer make me beleeue for a trueth. Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of these daies prooue, that by the meanes of these men, we are al so generally infected with Cleargie factions and Laie factions, that as we are full of fansies, so we follow nothing but factions, which I pray God speedilie redresse for his great mercies sake. Finally as Atheisme is most iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou y obiected to him that holdeth these positions. God to be the creator of al things: That God only seeth &amp; searcheth the harts and reines of men: That he onely worketh miracles: That he onelie maketh thunder, lightning, and tempest, and restraineth thē at his pleasure: That he onely sendeth life &amp; death, sicknes &amp; health, wealth &amp; woe, &amp;c. And as he is most wrongfullie &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly adiudged a Papist, who detecteth the abomination of their Idolatries, their pestilēt practises of knauerie &amp; cousonage, their absurdities in opinion and impurities of life, (al which &amp; much more then I here now speake of or can call to memorie) are extāt in print, &amp; so in the sight of the whole
<pb facs="9"/>
world if men would not be wilfully blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: so by this little labour beside the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cises of my peculiar profession, it may eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare what loue &amp; liking I haue alwaies borne to good, godlie and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble studies, and how I loath loytering; and so consequentlie lust which is an vnsepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble companion of Idlenes &amp; slouth, how I haue rather passed (as I hope) with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation from <hi>Paul</hi> his Epistles to <hi>Galen de Sanitate tuenda</hi> for publike profit, than to <hi>Ouid</hi> his <hi>de Arte Amandi</hi> with condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for my priuate pleasure.</p>
   <p>Good Sir as you haue been hitherto euē (as I may saie) zealous for my preferment, and likewise iealous ouer my credit, an as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured testimony of your true loue toward me, so I beseech you take in good worth at my hands this poore gift which I offer of pure good will, which if I once perceiue that you do, I shal think my trauail suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlie recompensed: and my selfe enforced during life to the accomplishment of your good pleasure, so far forth as my tenuitie shall be able anie waie to extend.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships vnfayned welwiller &amp; to command in what I may, <hi>Nicholas Gyer,</hi> minister of the word.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>