<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE IVDICIOVS
Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103828_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02624</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12752</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103828</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE IVDICIOVS
Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A prophesie of Cadvvallader, last king of the Britaines : containing a comparison of the English kings, with many worthy Romanes, from William Rufus, till Henry the fift. Henry the fift, his life and death. Foure battels betweene the two houses of Yorke and Lancanster [sic] . The field of Banbery. The losse of Elizabeth. The praise of King Iames. And lastly a poeme to the yong Prince</title>
                 <author>Herbert, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>70 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="33"/>
   <head>TO THE IVDICIOVS
Reader.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>I Which in bloudy warres haue sleep'd my pen,</l>
      <l>Whose Muse the passing bell of peace did wring,</l>
      <l>And how the world did loose a world of men,</l>
      <l>Now chuse to touch a more concordant string,</l>
      <l>My Prince his prayse, whose prayse Ile euer sing.</l>
      <l>Tis no mechanicke hope of hired gaine</l>
      <l>That mou'd my minde these labours to sustaine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>No, that ignoble basenesse I abiure,</l>
      <l>It was the loue I euer bare the place</l>
      <l>Where first I breathed life did me allure,</l>
      <l>In pleasant paines for to consume a space,</l>
      <l>And her to prayse, though with mine owne disgrace:</l>
      <l>With my disgrace, why? though my verse be ill,</l>
      <l>I do not doubt to please the good with will.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>To thee Iudicious Reader do I send</l>
      <l>These fruites of youth, tis thee I hope to please:</l>
      <l>If that my muse the ignorant offend,</l>
      <l>No lines of mine their fury shall appease,</l>
      <l>I set iust warre before an vniust peace,</l>
      <l>I rayle not I, though I with <hi>Plato</hi> say,</l>
      <l>To please the wise, must bee the wisest way.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="34"/>
      <l>THe lotted seruant to rhy Infant age,</l>
      <l>Thrice glorious issue of a gracious King,</l>
      <l>Least that her twelue-monthes fearefull tapynage,</l>
      <l>Ingratitude suspect to thee should bring,</l>
      <l>Me, though vnworthy, chose thy prayse to sing</l>
      <l>Her mourning garments she hath cast aside,</l>
      <l>And hopes ere long to entertaine her Bride.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The Cleargie with the Barons borrowed light,</l>
      <l>Is now obscured by thy transplendant shine:</l>
      <l>The Rochet nor the Border hath no right</l>
      <l>To rule, but that which doth from thee decline,</l>
      <l>She ioyes and glories to be onely thine:</l>
      <l>Shee deemes it honour, count it no dispraise</l>
      <l>For thee with her to spend thy yonger dayes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>No matchles <hi>Machauil,</hi> nor <hi>Arietine,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Doth her plaine meaning breast with enuy breede,</l>
      <l>Her wits do moderne seeme, and not diuine,</l>
      <l>Loyall her loue though lowly is her weede,</l>
      <l>A sympathie there is of word and deede:</l>
      <l>Such as these are, in <hi>Wales</hi> thine eyes shall see,</l>
      <l>Thousands that will both liue and dye with thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>O was she euer false, vntrue, vnkinde?</l>
      <l>Since her obedience did augment thy stile?</l>
      <l>Or since the parted Roses were combinde,</l>
      <l>Did euer rebels blood her brest defile?</l>
      <l>Or did she euer Englands hopes beguile?</l>
      <l>Witnesse the world, and those that liue therein,</l>
      <l>Her spotlesse soule did neuer taste that sin.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="34"/>
      <l>Search Truthes Records, not times illuding lines,</l>
      <l>Then shall thy Princely thoughts and eyes be fed</l>
      <l>With the strange wonders of those warlike times,</l>
      <l>When thy great Grandsyres made our channels red</l>
      <l>With blood of those that on our shoares laie dead.</l>
      <l>Teaching great <hi>Caesar</hi> how to runne away,</l>
      <l>That neuer knew to slye before that day.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Ten yeares did <hi>Rome</hi> and all the world admire,</l>
      <l>For all the world and <hi>Rome</hi> ten yeares did feare</l>
      <l>The lusture of thy Bekons set on fire,</l>
      <l>Great <hi>Odonisis</hi> King, <hi>Character,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Whose endlesse worth my worthlesse Muse shall reare</l>
      <l>To that bright Spheare where honor doth remaine,</l>
      <l>She loues thee dead, thy life her loue did gaine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>VVhat honor or what glory didst thou win</l>
      <l>VVith the earthes strength to conquer but an Ile,</l>
      <l>Maister of the worlds mistres, mightie King?</l>
      <l>Only this grac'd the greatnes of thy stile,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Claudius</hi> with blood did not his hands defile.</l>
      <l>This triumph <hi>Rome</hi> did thee as highly grace,</l>
      <l>As when by <hi>Scipio Affrique</hi> conquered was.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>How many Legions <hi>Caesar</hi> didst thou send?</l>
      <l>How many Consuls did returne of thine,</l>
      <l>VVhich sought what others marr'd, by warres to mend?</l>
      <l>How many Emperours <hi>Britaine</hi> did repine,</l>
      <l>To see thy honor rise, their praise decline.</l>
      <l>Let <hi>Tacitus</hi> vnto the world declare,</l>
      <l>No land saue <hi>Rome</hi> might with this land compare.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="35"/>
      <l>I know yong Prince, and am agreeu'd to see</l>
      <l>The leeuy'd lookes of squint-cyde <hi>Theonyn:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Who saies this sault is proper vnto mee,</l>
      <l>To iudge all others base our selues diuine,</l>
      <l>No enuious <hi>Momist</hi> tis no fault of mine:</l>
      <l>That seme are so, I must confesse tis true,</l>
      <l>All are not bad of vs, nor good of you.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The mellow fields haue tares as well as corne,</l>
      <l>And thistles grow amidst the greenest grasse:</l>
      <l>An <hi>Anacharse</hi> in <hi>Tartary</hi> was borne,</l>
      <l>Vertue and vice do meete in euery place,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Clodius</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> as well as <hi>Milo</hi> was.</l>
      <l>Both good and bad in euery land we see,</l>
      <l>And so are you, if of a land ye bee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Curbe the malignant pride of enuies rage,</l>
      <l>And checke the stubborne stomackes of disdaine,</l>
      <l>These penny Poets of our brazen stage</l>
      <l>Which alwayes wish, O let them wish in vaine,</l>
      <l>VVith <hi>Rossius</hi> gate thy gouernment to staine,</l>
      <l>Make them more milde, or be thou more austere,</l>
      <l>Tis veretue, vnto vice to be seuere.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I speake not this vnto the learned wise,</l>
      <l>For them I loue, because the truth they loue:</l>
      <l>Tis the bleard iudgement of seditious eyes,</l>
      <l>That doth my muse and my affection moue,</l>
      <l>A most vnwilling Satirist to proue:</l>
      <l>Nature hath made me milde, but these hard men</l>
      <l>Turn'd my soft quill into a brazen pen.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="35"/>
      <l>Play not the Satyr peace affecting muse,</l>
      <l>I doubt not but their conscience will prouoke</l>
      <l>These Lucilists their follies to refuse,</l>
      <l>And make them soft, though they were hard as oke,</l>
      <l>Conscience makes bad men good, so wise men spoke</l>
      <l>I leaue them to their spurres, my muse shall flye</l>
      <l>Vnto that Sphere where enuy dares not prye.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Vnto that Sphere whose circuit doth containe</l>
      <l>The neuer spotted essence of his soule,</l>
      <l>Whose sacred intellect no worldly staine</l>
      <l>Could with desires rebelling aide controule:</l>
      <l>This guilded Sphere is like a golden boule,</l>
      <l>Which many lesser mazers doth containe,</l>
      <l>So many vertues in this one do raigne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Why parriall nature stepdame to my birth,</l>
      <l>Ye mixed elements affections slaues,</l>
      <l>VVhy did ye frame this vessell but of earth?</l>
      <l>An equall matter to the dead mens graues,</l>
      <l>And ioynd thereto a spirt like the waues:</l>
      <l>Low as the earth although my <hi>Genius</hi> be,</l>
      <l>Yet doth it touch skye threatning Maiestie.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>O were my wit but equall to my will,</l>
      <l>VVere I as wise as I am ignorant,</l>
      <l>Here were a place that would deserue my skill,</l>
      <l>Had I as great experience as I want,</l>
      <l>Then would I in a booke of Adamant,</l>
      <l>And Inke compoz'd by water made of golde,</l>
      <l>VVith pens of Diamond thy prayse vnfolde.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="36"/>
      <l>Let Iustice rule the organ of thy speech,</l>
      <l>And Clemency adorne thy Princely browe:</l>
      <l>Vnto thine eares long absent patience teach,</l>
      <l>By these which good men wish, let all men knowe,</l>
      <l>None but thy selfe, thy selfe can ouerthrowe.</l>
      <l>Let pittie check the rod when we offend,</l>
      <l>That makes the good more good, the bad to mend.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I witnesse call the seuen hilled Queene,</l>
      <l>How we obey'd, when Lawes obey'd were:</l>
      <l>And shall not we be now as we have bene?</l>
      <l>Feare made vs then vnnaturall bondage beare,</l>
      <l>VVe now securely liue, and cannot feare.</l>
      <l>Doubt not thereof,<note place="margin">Cornelius Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus in the life of Agrippa.</note> but come experience haue,</l>
      <l>VVe loue to serue, but loathe the name of slaue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Our gazing expectation longes to see</l>
      <l>The true admired Image of thy Syre:</l>
      <l>Which Nature hath so rightly grau'd in thee:</l>
      <l>As Phisicke causes seem'd, they did conspire</l>
      <l>To shape the like to him whom all admire.</l>
      <l>So <hi>Sions</hi> sacred singer <hi>Dauid</hi> saies,</l>
      <l>Good trees bring forth good fruit, good fruit alwaies.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Do not sweete Sallets spring from soundest seed?</l>
      <l>And is not man like God, which man did make?</l>
      <l>Can bad effects from causes good proceed?</l>
      <l>Do we see fruite on any withered stake?</l>
      <l>Or do we see in sea a bush or brake?</l>
      <l>How canst thou then not good and perfect bee,</l>
      <l>That wert engraft on such a goodly tree?</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   <pb facs="36"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>