<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103461_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02254</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12390</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103461</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The proceedings of the Grisons, in the yeere 1618 : VVherein are truely and cleerely laid open the lawfull and vrgent causes of calling an assembly of the commons: and of their due proceeding and honourable prosecution of iustice, which they were enforced to vse against some false and perfidious patriots, in a full congregation, and with absolute power met together at Tosana. Imprinted and published by commandement of the lords the heads, the counsailours and commons of the three confederations of the renowned free states of the Grisons: in maintenance of the truth, and romoouing all manner of calumniation</title>
                 <author>Graub D.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ee that will take an exact Suruey of the known World, beginning at home, and going as farre as Trauell &amp; History can lead him, shall finde few people which are <hi>Aborigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls,</hi> and first Inhabitants of the Cities or Countries they now possesse: But by settling of Collonies, or In-roads and Inundations of Warre, haue been trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted. The <hi>Saxons</hi> hither: the <hi>Cimbrians</hi> into <hi>France:</hi> the <hi>Gaules</hi> into <hi>Italy:</hi> the <hi>Vandalls</hi> into <hi>Spaine:</hi> the <hi>Greekes</hi> into the Kingdome of <hi>Naples:</hi> the <hi>Scythians</hi> into <hi>Turky:</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> into <hi>Greece;</hi> And these <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> into this part of the <hi>Alpes,</hi> anciently called <hi>Rhetia,</hi> then <hi>Canninia;</hi> after, the vpper <hi>Slesia;</hi> and now lastly, in their own Language <hi>Growpijndter</hi> or Cōfederations.</p>
   <p>This Countrey had the name of <hi>Rhetus,</hi> who sled out of <hi>Tuscany</hi> from the fury of the <hi>Gaules,</hi> in the yeere <hi>187.</hi> before the comming of Christ, and led with him many of the Inhabitants about <hi>Florence, Pisa,</hi> and <hi>Lucca,</hi> sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in these high &amp; in-accessible Mountaines: And as a few weather-beaten <hi>Troians</hi> laid the foundation of Great <hi>Rome,</hi> and some few fugitiue Citizens of <hi>Vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za, Padoa,</hi> and other Townes in <hi>Lombardy</hi> (fleeing the rage of the barbarous <hi>Gothes,)</hi> planted themselues in the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Marishes, where they first began the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Venice:</hi> So this handfull of Tuscans here plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and settling themselues, are now growne to a warlike, strong, and populous Nation. Such a fruitfull mother of children is <hi>Necessity,</hi> begotten by old <hi>Time</hi> their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that (as the mother of <hi>Cyrus</hi> dreamed) there springs a Vine in her wombe, by which in time whole Countries are ouer-shadowed.</p>
   <p>This Countrey lyeth betweene the Degrees <hi>46.</hi> and <hi>44.</hi> in Latitude: part in <hi>Germany,</hi> and part in <hi>Italy;</hi> diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Ridge of the Mountaine <hi>Splugen:</hi> On this side they speake Dutch, on the other, Bergamasque Italian. They haue free exercise of both Religions, Reformed and Romane. Here the Riuers of the <hi>Rhein</hi> and <hi>Tesin</hi> haue their heads; that, diuiding it selfe into seuerall Branches, and disemboking into the <hi>German Ocean;</hi> this other falling into the <hi>Po,</hi> is carried by him into the <hi>Venetian Gulph.</hi> It confineth East vpon <hi>Tiroll,</hi> West vpon the <hi>Swisse</hi>-Cantons, North vpon <hi>Constance, Friburg,</hi> and some parts of the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> and South vpon the Countrey of <hi>Bergamo</hi> and State of <hi>Millan.</hi> The hither part is Mountainous, and therefore not so well able to su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staine the Inhabitants; yet are there many fruitfull Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, which, (besides their frugall and parsimonious maner of liuing) supply that want. Among these is <hi>Valtelina</hi> on the Italian side; for this is so plentifull of Corne, Cattle, Wines, &amp; other fruits, as any part of <hi>Europe.</hi> The chiefe Townes of this fruitfull Valley, are, <hi>Bormio, Sondrio,
<pb facs="3"/>
Tirano, Posclauio, Morbegno, Traona,</hi> and <hi>Telo,</hi> whereof the Valley takes the name, wherein are aboue <hi>100000.</hi> soules. The part on this side hath many Castles and Townes, whereof <hi>Coira</hi> is the chiefe. It standeth vpon the Riuer <hi>Lasgar;</hi> it embraced the Christian faith the yeere <hi>448.</hi> and in <hi>744.</hi> had many priuiledges granted by <hi>Charlemain,</hi> and the Bishop thereof made Rector of <hi>Rhetia:</hi> Among other Liberties it hath the coyning of Money, which passeth currant through the whole Country.</p>
   <p>The nature and manners of this people may bee read by the Character of the <hi>Swisses:</hi> For, lying in the same Latitude, and inhabiting the like Mountaines, herein also they are like vnto them. A people giuen to Tillage and Planting their grounds; feeding vpon Butter, Cheese, Fish, Bread, Rootes, Wine, and but small store of Flesh; vsing little Merchandize, but much manifacture, borne to Armes, and brought vp to labour; much addicted to exercise, especially the Harquebuse, hauing in diuers Townes and Villages Prizes for them which doe best. They are also much delighted with hunting in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, of wilde Goates, Bucks, Beares, Wolues, and wilde Boares: holding it a great honour to take of these Beasts, and for a Trophey to naile their heads on their gates; for which also sometime the State rewards them. They are (onely on this side the Countrey) subiect to the Swisse and Dutch fault of excessiue drinking.</p>
   <p>Their Countrey is diuided into three Cantons or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federations.
<pb facs="4"/>
The first is called, The Confederation of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dè,</hi> or <hi>Ca-di-Dio:</hi> (that is, Gods House:) the second is, <hi>Lega Grisa:</hi> and the third, <hi>Lega delle Dritture,</hi> or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdictions. <hi>Cadi Dio</hi> containes the City &amp; Territory of <hi>Coira,</hi> the Valley of vpper and lower <hi>Agnadina,</hi> with <hi>Bregaglia: Lega Grisa</hi> contains the Valley of <hi>Mesolce,</hi> and <hi>Calanca,</hi> with the Lands of <hi>Rogoret &amp; Musocco,</hi> with other Valleys besides, on this side the Ridge of the Mountaines: the <hi>Dritture</hi> containe the rest of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. The first comprehendeth <hi>21.</hi> Comminalties or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations: the second <hi>19.</hi> the third <hi>10.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These three Cantons make the Confederation Generall: for though each of them haue their peculiar Magistrates, Lawes, Customes, and Iustice ciuill and criminall, yet the highest power and last Appeale is to the Senate or Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Three Cantons together: called by them the <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bach.</hi> Whereunto the first Confederation sends <hi>23.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties or Commissioners: the second <hi>28.</hi> and the third <hi>14.</hi> Where, they propound, consult, and determine onely that, for which they haue direction and command from their seuerall Cantons. To this Senate likewise belongeth to treat and conclude Peace or Warre, to make or reuoke Alliances and Leagues, to establish or abrogate Statutes and Lawes, to determine any difference betweene either of the Cantons, or resolue any businesse concerning the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall good of the whole Countrey. The places of Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly are these; <hi>Coira</hi> in the first Confederation: <hi>Illian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
in the second: and <hi>Dauosium</hi> in the last. But if the Three Confederations are to treat a Businesse, which they would haue kept secret, there are onely admitted into Councell, the Consull of <hi>Coira,</hi> the Prouinciall Iudge of the <hi>Lega Grisa,</hi> and the Amano or chiefe Iustice of the <hi>Dritture:</hi> yet the voice to confirme all, is that of the <hi>People;</hi> if there be any Appeale. For controuersies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themselues thus: If a difference arise betweene the Three Confederations, three or foure persons out of each are deputed (with discharge of their Oath to their owne Confederation) to arbitrate and compound the businesse. If two be at difference, the third determines it. If between any of the Comminalties, the Senate of all Three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federations ioyntly depute Iudges of the businesse. If be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a priuate man &amp; the Confederations, two or three Iudges are appointed out of euery seuerall Confederation. If two Confederations haue a difference with the third, sixe of the two Confederations, and sixe of the third are chosen for Iudges: and in case these agree not, one onely Iudge is chosen by the voice of all the Commons.</p>
   <p>The first League was made betweene the Bishop of <hi>Coira,</hi> and the Prouinces about him, in the yeere <hi>1441.</hi> The next betweene the Abbot of <hi>Zizatis,</hi> the Count of <hi>Mauan,</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Bezuns,</hi> with them of <hi>Coira;</hi> this was called <hi>Lega Grisa,</hi> as that former <hi>Lega Cadè:</hi> after this, the Comminalties of <hi>Segouia</hi> made League with the two former, and was called <hi>Lega delle Drit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
And lastly, in the yeere <hi>1470.</hi> they all Colleag<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But in the yeere <hi>1471.</hi> hauing difference with their neighbours of <hi>Tiroll,</hi> they all entred League with seuen Cantons of the <hi>Swisse.</hi> And lastly, the whole thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Cantons of the <hi>Swisse,</hi> with these of the <hi>Grison</hi> Confederation, and the seuen Wards or Sokes of the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesians,</hi> ioyned all in League with <hi>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Gallo:</hi> which Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was first founded and inhabited by one <hi>Sengall</hi> a Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish-man, with other of his Countrey, and after grew to haue large Territories and Priuiledges. Thus all these Cantons <hi>Grison</hi> and <hi>Swisse,</hi> with the <hi>Valesians</hi> and them of <hi>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Gallo,</hi> being a great, Warlike, and powerfull Body, stand in the gates of <hi>Italy,</hi> as firme as the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines wherein they liue, against any forraine force what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer.</p>
   <p>A larger Relation might be made of this People and Countrey: But because a great head holds no Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry with a small Body; this little shall suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to giue light to the ensuing Declaration.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>