<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The prologe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1536</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103590_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02422</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12557</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103590</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The prologe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The co [n] futacyon of the fyrst parte of Frythes boke : with a dysputacyon before whether it be possyble for any heretike to know that hym selfe is one or not. And also an other, whether it be wors to denye directely more or lesse of the fayth, put forth by Ioh⁻n Gwynneth clerke</title>
                 <author>Gwynneth, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Herford (Hereford, Hertford), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Stevenage, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1536</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>312 pages, 8</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The prologe.</head>
   <p>MOst gentyll and good cristen readers, where it is so, that it hath chaunced me not a few tymes, to be in companyes dyuers where I haue harde, amonge all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that most notable and wylye heretyke Fryth, not a lytel praysed of some, for lernynge and myche gentylnesse / of some, for very syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulare and great pacyence / and of some not onely praysed and cōmen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, but also pytied and lamented, howbeit (as I perceyue) not for his most infortunate chaūce spyrituall but for his dew and iust punishmēt corporall / and that in such maner, as though he had ben a man vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cast away without cause: I ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore by the reason of this, compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at length, so myche to wonder, remembrynge withall, his iudges
<pb facs="2"/>
to be (as I hard) no meaner persōs then pears of the reame, and that of bothe sortes / was streken with no small desyre, yf it were possyble to se his booke / wherin I myght perfytly perceyue, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very hole cause of hys worthy deth. Not for any thynge that I douted, (as I percey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued sum dyd more then y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>) whether his iudgement were iust or not / but vtterly bycause I wolde thorowly vnderstande the mater, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which I though euer he was worthyly cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dempned. And that to the intent I myght be the more able to satysfye, such as I sholde chaunce to fynde, any thyng deceyued in hym. And to be short, his booke at length I dyd opteyne. The whiche when I dyd reade / questyonles yf the fastnesse of fayth, had ben no more, then the reddynesse of suffycyēt iudgement
<pb facs="3"/>
I myght well haue sayde (as to many may) that I had met with it to sone▪ &amp; in an euyll houre: How be it the trauth to saye, after y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fyrst tyme, without fayle the oftener I redde it, the falser I foūde it. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at length I made so large report that here and there, now and then, I fayled not of some, whiche wolde not stycke to tell me, that I sayde therin myche more then I coude proue / bycause they thought I dyd other falsely reherse hym or ellys mysunderstonde hym. wherin I was dyuers tymes to this issuy dryuen, other to show forth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> booke it selfe, which I thought not best / or to gyue place to an errour, or els to promyse the probacyon of that I sayd, in wrytyng / where frythes wordes and myne sholde bothe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther apere: and therfore bycause
<pb facs="3"/>
I wold not show the book / nor any thynge geue way in suche a mater / I had none other answere to make but alwaye with this promyse / lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell therin consyderyng then, what thynges I founde and perceyued in it afterward / whiche in especyall were twayne: one, that who so euer promyseth to proue suche a falshed and do it not in dede, without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styon doth but therin cōfyrme and vpholde it, and nothynge els. The other was / what viuacite of wyt, copy of lernynge and eloquence, is (all most of necessyte) requesyte, to conuynce the tortuouse and croked wylynesse of an heretyke. And whē I perceyued a great inconueniens of the tone syde. And agayne vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly no remedy, of the tother, That is to wyt, I saw what daunger myne owne promyse had bound me vnto
<pb facs="4"/>
yf I sholde not performe it. And of the tother parte / when I consyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, how farre I was from those thynges that I shulde aptly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme it withall / good crystē rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, it is not harde to perceyue whether my mynde were therwith asstonyed or not, beyng brought in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to suche a streyt, where apered out no passage / yet thyder conueyed (I was sure) without faute. But then my cogytacyon, as who saye, sore wered and beten herwith, ranne streygth to the very thynge it selfe, which fyrst set it this a worke: that is to wyt, the very bodyly presence of our most gloryous sauiour cryst in the holy sacrament. wherin dout<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les is very trauth. The whiche trauth, bycause it myght (as full sure it was, to show y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> only strength of it selfe somtyme it wold) be with
<pb facs="4"/>
out the excellency of wyt, the copye of lernynge, and the bewty of elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. Euen therfore dyd I set vppon the accomplyshment of my promyse, without any of them all thre / as ye shall well perceyue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: wherin I moste hartely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre you to haue me excused / not for my sake, but for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theraunce of the gloryous thynge it selfe, for the loue wherof I haue not shronke thus to show my rewdenesse &amp; lytell lernyng to all men.</p>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>