<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1565</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103755_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02636</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12762</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103755</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A confutation of a booke intituled An apologie of the Church of England, by Thomas Harding Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Harding, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Laet (Latius), Hans (Jan) de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1565</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 351, 9 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eholde Reader, here thou hast a Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apologie of the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.<note place="margin">Thinges chiefly to be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in this Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> VVhich what hath moued me to write, what hath ben myne intent therein, what ende I haue looked for, what maner of writing and what order in the whole treatise I haue vsed, all this if thou desire to knowe: thus it is.<note place="margin">VVhat moued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hauthor to write.</note> To take this enterprise vpon me, I haue ben prouoked by certaine hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine intisementes I confesse: but the same moued me litle. To saye the trouth, the zeale of God it is, that chiefly hath dryuen me to take the penne in hande, and I trust his good spirite hath directed the same. verely that so it might be, my prayer hath not wanted. VVhether this zeale hath ben according to knowledge (without which it might be myslyked) or otherwise: I offer it to be tryed by such mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes as tryall may be made.<note place="margin">Triall of skillefull zeale.</note> Let both writinges be layd in balance, first, so much as concerneth the doctrine of faith, to be weighed with the weightes of the generall and aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent custome of the people of God, which in such case by the mynde of saint Augustine is to be taken for a lawe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of the olde learned fathers, of approued councels, and spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the holy scriptures, so as the catholike church hath euer vnderstanded them,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esai.</hi> 59. Iohn. 14.</note> to whom both the worde of God and the spirite of God teacher and prompter of all truth is assuredly promysed. Next, so much as concerneth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and actes of men worthy of praise or reproufe, by the
<pb facs="8"/> Authours of the Apologie mencioned, let all be tried by the weightes of true histories. Thirdly, what thinges they alleage as out of the fathers, councels, chroniclers, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonistes, and scoole men: for triall of the truth I referre all to due examination of bookes, out of which ech thing is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged. This done, if they shall be founde to haue vsed false weightes, and appeare ouer light in the balance, as neither hauing the iust poys of the scriptures, councels, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or custome for their doctrine of faith, nor of histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for maners and actes by them spoken of, nor of their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther allegations brought for proufe of other thinges: I doubt not but in the iudgement of all godly and wise men my zeale shall seme right and iust, as not being altogether besides knowledge.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">VVhat is here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised.</note>But what if it be euidently shewed, that these men haue not only failed in proufe of thinges they tooke in hand to proue, but also haue done contrary to reason, shamefastnes, and common honestie, and haue stuffed their booke with shameles lyes in generall, with scoffes, railinges, and slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders touching both the persons of certaine speciall men, and states and degrees in common, with false doctrines, errours, and heresies touching the scriptures, with prophane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt touching the most holy sacramentes, with haynous blasphemie touching God him selfe? In this case I trust my zeale shall not only be acquited of all blame, but also shal excuse the silence of others of my calling, who at length should greuously haue ben accused, if none for loue of truth
<pb facs="8"/> had brought to light those thinges, which so much it stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth men vpon in these perrilous tymes to vnderstand. That in this confutation this much is shewed and proued to the vtter discredite of the Apologie, thy selfe wilt so iudge Reader, if thou vouchesafe aduisedly to read it ouer.</p>
   <p>Myne intent hath ben only to shewe the truth,<note place="margin">Intent.</note> and to remoue men from the manyfold and crafty deceit of lying, which is the dutie partly of euery man, so farre as the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of charitie reacheth,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Eccl.</hi> 17.</note> and so farre as by God to ech one charge of his neighbour is committed: but specially of those who haue bestowed their time in studie to thende to teach others the truth, and by laufull calling haue ben appointed therunto.</p>
   <p>The ende I looke for of all my labour is,<note place="margin">Ende.</note> that the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies being confuted, lyes detected, slaunders wyped awaye, wherwith the Apologie is farced: the catholike faith which in these dayes is so much impugned, may be defended, the truth embraced, the church duely regarded, that of our dere coūtrie men, they which through gods grace stād, by reading this confutation may be animated to kepe their standing, they which stomble and slyde, may fynde wherwith to staye them, they which be fallen, may be admonished how to rise againe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> and recouer them selues from the snares of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, of whom they are holden captiue at his will.</p>
   <p>The manner of writing which I haue here vsed,<note place="margin">Manner of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison of our aduersaries is sober, softe, and gentle, yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementer, rougher, and sharper, then for my wont and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:
<pb facs="9"/> but in respect of their heate, bitternes, and railing, as many tell me, ouer colde, swete, and mylde. How so euer it shall seme to thee Reader, herein I haue done as I thought best. VVell I am assured I haue not gone farre from the steppes of the most praised auncient fathers, of whom who haue bene commended most for the spirite of meekenes, the same, though toward other offenders haue shewed them selues like mylde Moyses, yet hauing to do with heretikes, commonly haue demeaned them selues like earnest Elias. If lyers should be entreated in like sorte as true reporters, slaunderers and backebyters, as faithfull frendes, hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, as catholikes, Apostates, as stedfast christians, bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemers, as saintes: truth should be iniured, wickednes flattered, vertue misprised. Of whom the truth was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned or resisted with malice, them litle spared either the prophetes, or the Apostles, or Christ him selfe.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Order.</note>The order that I thought good to kepe is this. First, (as thou mayst here see) I haue put the wordes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie as I found them translated, sometimes by whole para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphes, sometimes by mo, sometimes by fewer and briefe sentences, according to the dependence or weight of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Then foloweth my confutation longer or shorter, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the thing confuted. Here shalt thou finde the Apologie whole, sentence for sentence, word for word. That I might seme to deale vprightly, I would leaue out nothing. And least it should be layd to me, that I had pyked out cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine pointes to refell, and left sundry other vntouched, as
<pb facs="9"/> acknowleged, and confessed for good and true: auoiding thobiection of parciall dealing, and of approuing that which is to be condemned: making their booke no worse then it is, I haue here set forth, and after my manner confuted the whole, not so as I would ech sentence to be numbred, but rather to be weighed. In weight I trust none shalbe fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde vnrefelled, though in number some fewe for lacke of pith be either sleightly touched, or quite past ouer, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of time and labour bestowed about them.</p>
   <p>All this haue I done so briefly as I could, yet hath my booke growen to a farre more largenes, then I would. For breuities sake many pointes I haue with fewe wordes trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which fully to be discussed, would by them selues requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re large treatises. But what should I do? Verelie this Apologie is such a peece of worke, as for euery heresie, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry slaunder, euery lye, briefly euery false point and part of it to be fully and thoroughly confuted and aunswered, and the contrary truth to be declared and set forth: it would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire many great volumes, and a whole mans life, wherein for my part beside the time of printing, I haue not bestowed fully three quarters of a yere. The more thy gentlenes ought to beare with me, if euery point be not founde aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to thy expectation.</p>
   <p>The authour of the Apologie,<note place="margin">The stuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe of the Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</note> if it were made by any one, and not by many heades, as it is most likely: what so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he could finde in the bookes of those late writers, who haue diuided themselues from the obedience of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="10"/> church, either concerning doctrine or manners written against the catholike faith, which they cal Papistrie, against the churh, against the Bishops of Rome, against the whole clergy: the same hath he raked together, and thrust it into the Apologie. That there was neuer booke made, which in so litle rome conteined so great a heape of lyes, errours, heresies, tauntes, scoffes, vpbraidinges, slaunders, rancours, and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemies. Such is the booke, and for such it is estemed out of England of all wise and learned men. And fewe haue yet ben sounde, which could finde in their hartes to put the pēne to paper against it, not for that they could not, or durst not, but for that they liked not to bestowe their study in such argument, as that, which they abhorre for the multitude of shameles lyes, for the vaine and light scoffes, for the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious slaunderinges of men by name, for the vnhonest disclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of fylthy matters, which chaste eares would be loth to heare, for the horriblenes of heresies, and for such other lothsom thinges sauering altogether of the spirite of Satan.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">VVriters against the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</note>Two onely I heare of that haue written against it, the one in latin, a learned Spaniard, bishop in the kingdom of Naples, the other an Italian, in the Italian tonge. Both bookes are staied from print and setting abroade as it is thought, in regard of our countrie. VVhose honour should be ouer much touched, if the whole church of the realme were so openly charged with thapprouing of such a lying, vndiscrete, vnreasonable, slaunderous and vngodly writting. For which cause my selfe thought it more conuenient,<note place="margin">For what cause this Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was written in English rather then in Latine.</note> to
<pb facs="10"/> write this Confutation in english, then in latin, that so both falsehed might be refelled, and truth defended, and also that our domesticall faultes might be considered to amendment within the bankes of England, and not by the common tonge blowen abroade through all Christendom, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and shame of our countrie.</p>
   <p>VVhereas a certaine learned man of our owne countrie, one of good accōpt, in his answere to the epistle which Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymus Osorius of godly zeale, with due modestie, rype dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and singular eloquence wrote to the Quenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, referreth that famous man for proufe and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Religion of our countrie, and for the whole real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes vniforme agreeing in the same, to the Apologie set forth (as he saith) by the church of England openly to the eyes of all the world, as a common and an assured pledge of our Religion, and there eggingly requireth him to refell it, if he be able, affirming very preiudicially that neither he, nor any other of his syde is able, (wherby he excludeth all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like men be they neuer so well learned): I feare me to wise men that will seme rather of courage a stout shewe, then of truth a substantiall proufe. Neither in my iudgement the same becommeth his person and his sundry vertues, how so euer it becommeth so feeble a cause to be set forth with a lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty brauarie of wordes. As for all others besides Osorius, whether any be able to refell it or no, let tyme trye. But how so euer that famous Bishop be either yet able, or shall at any time be willing, thou hast here gentle Reader, in the
<pb facs="11"/> meane time a confutation of that booke, and the thing done, which hath bene so stoutly affirmed, no man of Osorius side, that is to say, none that is Catholike, is able to do, and that not by a Portugall of which countrie Osorius is, but by one of thyne owne countrie. Of my ablenes what shall I saye? Therof my selfe holding silence, the thing speaketh. Truly I acknowledge it to be very small. And for that I do so ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, I thanke God nolesse, then for the measure the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof it selfe, which he hath geuen to me, I haue not geuen to my selfe.<note place="margin">The good will of thau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</note> And all this hast thou with so good a wil Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to raise thee vp that art fallen, to staie thee that art wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, to moue thee to be stedfast, that standest, briefly to comfort thee, and by all meanes to do thee good, what case, mynde, or affection so euer thou findest thy selfe in: as cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to my neighbour, loue to my countrie, dutie to God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation.</note>VVhiles thou readest this treatise, remember thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest a Confutation, which is not an vtterrance made by the prime deuise of the mynde for declaration and proufe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, wherein witte hath libertie to discourse: but an answere refelling what an other hath before affirmed. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein inuention is straighted, and true reasons be not by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of such writing so much propounded for confirmation of the truth, as false reasons dissolued for defence of the truth, and for discomfeiture of falshed, wherein the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary is answered, not opposed, controlled, not prouoked, resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, not inuaded, and as it were, his blowes broken, his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb facs="11"/> not first assaulted. VVherefore maruell lesse, if thou finde not so ample and large discourses in proufe of some pointes, in which thou longest to be resolued. I thought best to folowe the order of writing that a confutation requireth. And although I write against them, who call their booke a defence, (for so the greke word signifieth) and I therfore name them defenders: yet in respect of my purpose, which is to defend the truth, I take my selfe in dede for the defendāt, them for the chalengers. Neither for all this, if thou marke well what is here said, shalt thou finde onely falsehed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sproued, but also in most pointes of faith the truth suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently (and so farre as the nature of a confutation bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth) declared and proued.</p>
   <p>If thou desire throughly to vnderstand the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, before thou reade my wordes,<note place="margin">Instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of this Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> pervse the wordes of the Apologie, as they are placed in order. Then mayest thou iudge better of both, and see whereabout I go. Els thou mayest happen to want in me order, iudgement, coherence, disposition, comelines, and other graces requisite to an order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly talke. If thou fall vpon any one thing often times repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and therfor feele the same lothsom: blame not me, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding fault therwith no lesse then thy selfe, but him that pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Apologie, who dryueth me thervnto, and forceth me, as it were, with one cloth oftentimes to wype a mattering sore, specially hauing taken vpō me to refele euery part of it.</p>
   <p>The whole treatise I haue diuided into six partes,<note place="margin">Diuision of the whole treatise in to six partes.</note> as by diligent vewe I perceiued their booke to treate six principall
<pb facs="12"/> pointes. They are longer or shorter, equalitie of propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not curiously obserued, after the rate of the Apologie. And because distinction geueth light to the matter treated, and diminisheth the tediousnes of the reader: euery parte is diuided into chapters.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin" type="runSum">The ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of euery part brie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.</note>
      <note place="margin" type="runSum">1</note>In the first parte, I confute their rhetoricall insinuation conteining a common place, that truth is and hath ben al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes persecuted, wherby they endeuour to procure credite to their writing. <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note>In the second parte, I shewe the vntruth of their belefe, and proue the Catholike faith by them impugned. <note place="margin" type="runSum">3</note>In the third parte, I proue great controuersies and dissensions in matters of weight to be among the Gospellers, which they denye. And those disagreeinges or rather diuersities, which they be not ashamed to laye to the Catholikes, I declare either to be none at all, or such as be of no force or importance in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of faith. <note place="margin" type="runSum">4</note>In the fourth parte, I confute their shameles lyes, and falsifyinges of histories, and slaunderinges of men by name, defending truth and honestie. <note place="margin" type="runSum">5</note>In the fifth parte, I refell what they can bring for that the church may erre, and what they alleage out of sundry doctours, councels, and late writers against the catholike church. <note place="margin" type="runSum">6</note>In the sixth part, I defend the generall councels, and specially that of late hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at Trent, and shewe how they belye the fathers there as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, as well for many other thinges, as for denying, that them selues and their fellow gospellers could haue any liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or be permitted to come thither, and to treate among them about matters of faith, where the abbridgement of the safe
<pb facs="12"/> conductes for the same purpose graunted forth and cōfirmed, is recorded. Lastly, for commoditie as well of my vtterance, as of thy vnderstanding, where neither he that penned the booke, who doubtles is the chiefe authour of it, who so euer he be, nor they that haue holpe him with their notes, coūsels, and deuises, haue put to their names, the title being an Apologie, which is a greke word and signifieth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in english: through this whole confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, hauing cause sundry times to name them, I haue thought good to call the one Defender, the others, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>