<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Summe of all, in one Syllogisme.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103198_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12801</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23109</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103198</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Summe of all, in one Syllogisme.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Propositions, tending to proove the necessarie vse of the Christian Sabbaoth : or Lords day; and that it is commavnded vnto us in Gods word. VVherevnto is added the practice of that sacred day, framed after the rules of the same word. By Iohn Sprint, an unvvorthie minister of the Gospell of Iesus Christ, at Thornebery in Gloucester shire</title>
                 <author>Sprint, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 62 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Summe of all, in one Syllogisme.</head>
   <p>That the Lords daie, or Christian Sabbaoth, is <note place="margin">The Lords Day</note> necessarily to bee obserued by all Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to the end of the World.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hatsoeuer dayes obseruation was in the Newe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sanctified by</note>
      <hi>sanctified, and set apart to an holy vse:</hi>
      <note n="1" place="margin">Christs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection.</note> First, by Christ his triumphant resurrectiō. <note n="2" place="margin">Christs first ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parition.</note> Then, by his first appearing to his gathered Apostles &amp; Disciples, fiue times on that same day. <note n="3" place="margin">Christs second apparition.</note> Next, hy his second appearing to his gathered A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles. <note n="4" place="margin">Holy Ghost apparition.</note> Fourthly, by his sending of the Holy-Ghost to his Apostles gathered againe, and blessing of their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine by conuersion of soules. <note n="5" place="margin">Command ordinance of postles.</note> Fiftly, by Apostolicall Commaund, &amp; Constitution, to be obserued by Christian Churches. <note n="6" place="margin">Christs com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandement.</note> Sixtly, by Christs Commaund, not to be profaned of anie faithfull Christian. <note n="7" place="margin">Practice of postles.</note> Seuenthly, by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles solemne practice of preaching, ministring the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments in the Christian Congregation, and meditation of the Scripture. <note n="8" place="margin">Title giuen the Holy-Ghost</note> Eightly, by the holy-Ghosts induing it with a notable &amp; peculiar title of the Lords day. <note n="9" place="margin">Practice of and the most p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Churches.</note> By Apostolicall, primitiue, and all later reformed Churches general and continual practice, from thence vnto our times. <note n="10" place="margin">Iudgeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> the most so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> all &amp; godly l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned.</note> By the iudgement of the spirituall &amp; most godly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Teachers and Writers of the former and later ages. <note n="11" place="margin">Effectes Gods blessin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪</note> By the witnesse of Gods generall and continuall bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the practice therof, with peace of conscience, ioy of the Holy-Ghost, and sensible increase of knowledge and
<pb facs="4"/> grace in all sincere Christians, that with soundnesse prefesse the Gospell euery where. <note n="12" place="margin">Dislike and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>anation by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e wicked and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>sound.</note> And last of all, by the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and opposition of the onely most wicked of life, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of mind, or otherwise vnsound in iudgement and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.] <hi>The Obseruation of that Day is most necessary, and doth tie the Conscience to the end of the World.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>But such is the Obseruation of the Lords day, or first day of the weeke; and so confirmed in euery point. Therefore,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>The holy Obseruation of the Lords day or first day of the week, is most necessarie, and doth tye the conscience to the end of the World.</hi>
   </p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>The Proposition confirmed.</head>
      <p>For the first member: Look Section, 56, 55. For the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, third, fourth, seuenth, and ninth: Look Sect: 61. For the fift and sixt: Looke Sect, 58, 59. For the eight: Looke Sect. 55, 54, 59, 60, 64. For the tenth, eleuenth and twelfth: Looke, Sect, 65.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Proofes of the Assumption in the seuerall members.</head>
      <p>The 1. There is no question of this point: but that Christ rose on the first day of the weeke.</p>
      <p>The 2. That Christ appeared 5 times on that first day of the weeke; which was the day of his resurrection, and of the Christian Sabbaoth: first, to <hi>Mary Magdalen. Mark.</hi> 16 9. <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. Secondly, to the woman: <hi>Mat.</hi> 28, 9, 10, 11. Thirdly, to the two Disciples: <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. 18. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 13. Fourthly, to <hi>Peter: Luk.</hi> 24 33. 34. with 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, 5. Fiftly, to the eleuen: <hi>Mark.</hi> 16. 14 Excepting <hi>Thomas: Io.</hi> 20. 24. Wherein our Sauiour dooth comfort, instruct, authorise, and ordaine the Ministers of the Newe Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and giues them power to preach and administer the Sacraments &amp; Discipline. <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 22. 23. with <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. 15. 16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. This was performed in the night: partly by Christs appointment: <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 16. Partly for feare of the Iewes, not daring to assemble by day. <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 19. The day notwithstanding sanctified by Christs fiue fold appearing; and the Disciples holy meditation &amp; conference of and with Christ.</p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <p>The 3. That CHRIST appeared the second time on that day seuen-night (Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>ing, comforting, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structing, reproouing) appeareth; <hi>Io.</hi> 20. 26, 27, 28, 29. Where it is sayd, after eight dayes (including and counting the day of Christs resurrection for one of the eight, which is that day seuen-night:) as if he should say the eight day after: by an Hebraisme. The like speech in <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. 21. &amp; 1. 59. <hi>Leu.</hi> 12. 3. Thus <hi>Caluin, Beza, Piscator, Rollock,</hi> take it: and so do the very Papists, <hi>Ferus, Iansenius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel Sa.</hi> vpon these places.</p>
      <p>The 4. That the Apostles met vpon this very day (the first day of the weeke, on the morning; <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 15) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, because they met on the day of <hi>Pentecost. Act.</hi> 2. 1. with <hi>Leu.</hi> 23. 15. 16, called the feast of weekes. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 22. Which was the morrow after the Sabbaoth. <hi>Leu.</hi> 23. 16. 15. This also, the computation of Weekes betweene the feast of <hi>Easter,</hi> and <hi>Whitsontide</hi> dooth prooue: For it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>: as if one should say, the fiftieth day. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 1. because fiftie full dayes, or seauen weekes are to passe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the feast of <hi>Easter</hi> or Passeouer (the day after which, Christ rose) and the feast of <hi>Whitsontide</hi> or of weeks: <hi>Leuit.</hi> 23. 15. 16. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. 22. on which day the Apostles now met. For this truth, look the iudgement of <hi>Augustine, de tempore ser.</hi> 251. <hi>Nazianzen apud Baroniū: Leo Ep.</hi> 81. <hi>&amp; Concil. Constantinopol.</hi> 6 <hi>Caluine, Beza, Piscator:</hi> with the Papists. <hi>Bellarmine de cultu sanctorū: lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. See <hi>Emma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel Sa. annot. in Act.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>Baronius Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>ex Nazianzen.</hi>
      </p>
      <l>The 5. Look for the confirmation thereof. Sect. 58. 59.</l>
      <l>The 6. Look for this, Sect▪ 64.</l>
      <l>The 7. Look for this also: Sect. 60. 61.</l>
      <l>The 8. Look for this, Sect. 59. 55. 54. 60. 64.</l>
      <l>The 9. For this look Sect. 15. 20. 63. 62.</l>
      <l>The 10. Is prooued Sect. 15. 20. 34. 52.</l>
      <p>The 11. and 12. Is confirmed by palpable experience: and apprehended by him that eyther hath an eye, or win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not: Look for these, Sect. 65. and the fowre last Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons also.</p>
      <pb facs="5"/>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>