<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103059_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01600</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11728</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103059</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The life and death of Mr. Edmund Geninges priest, crowned with martyrdome at London, the 10. day of Nouember, in the yeare M.D.XCI</title>
                 <author>Geninges, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Boscard, Charles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>102, 2, 103-110 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="7" facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ACRAMENTVM REGIS caelare bonum est:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iob.</hi> 12</note>
      <hi>opera autem Dei reuelare, &amp; cōfiteri hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rificū est.</hi> It is a good thing (saith the holy Scripture) to cōceale the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of a King: but it is most honourable to reueale and cōfesse the workes of God. Like as this sētence (Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader) is verifyed, touching all the diuine works of Almighty God himselfe in generall: so the truth of it is most apparent, concerning his admirable workes in iust men and Saynts in particuler. The reason of this is manifest, because the relation of such wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes doth not only tend highly to the honour of God, who by this meanes is shewed to be admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and prayse-worthy in his Saints;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 67</note> but also to the glory of the Saintes themselues, and of Gods militant Church on earth, of which, whiles they liued, they were liuely members.</p>
   <p>Hence it hath bene euer a laudable custome of liuing Christians to report and make knowne to the world, the noble actes of Gods Saints departed cut
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>
of this vale of miseryes. But is this the onely good, that ariseth of such endeavours? No, for the historyes of the Liues of Saints doe confirme our fayth, stirre vs vp to imitate them, and haue sundry other most profitable effects. And although these motiues may suffice to perswade any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian to penne, and publish the famous actes of holy Martyrs: yet not onely these, but others also mooue me to vndertake this labour, touching the life and death of <hi>Edmund Geninges</hi> Priest, who amongst many others, in defence of Christs Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Apostolique Church, not many yeares since hath in this our Iland most gloriously shed his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud, and lost his temporall life, to gayne eternall.</p>
   <p>Of which motiues, one is my owne exact knowledg of many particulers,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Motiues that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to wryte this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course.</hi>
      </note> concerning this Blessed man, wherof others, better able to performe this matter then my selfe, perhaps are ignorant: which parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culers being memorable, would peraduenture therby be buryed in perpetual obliuion, if I should not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them thus in writing to posterity. Another motiue is, my particuler loue, and deserued affection to the party of whom I am to treat. The third is, the perswasion and intreaty of some speciall friends,
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>
whose requests in such a matter I cannot well ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglect or withstand. Finally some secret mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues haue often assaulted my mind, and inuited me to this enterprize, which in mature consideration seeme to me to haue proceeded from God himselfe, who would not haue the memory of his Saints so long obscured &amp; forgotten.</p>
   <p>These reasons as they vrged me forward, so o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers also contrariwise hitherto kept me backe,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Why this Booke was not publis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this day.</hi>
      </note> &amp; disswaded me from such proceedinges. First a feare or suspition of being accounted ouer partiall, by reason I haue bene so much linked vnto him in friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe and fauour, for which cause my Relation perhaps vnto some, might seeme in part faygned through affection, and consequently of doubtful truth. Secondly my owne insufficiency and want of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in penning such a worthy discourse as this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth. These two conceits haue hitherto kept me backe from publishing of this intention. But now the former motiues are demeed by me more forcible, and weygh downe these opposit obiections, especially seing that both these letts &amp; obstacles in the sight of an indifferent Reader, may after a sort be eyther much weakened, or altogeather remooued. The one by a protestation of truth and sincerity. The other
<pb n="10" facs="6"/>
by another meane of like quality.</p>
   <p>First therfore the censure of <hi>Salomon</hi> is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to me, who auoweth, that, <hi>Hee who spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth lyes shall not escape vnpunished, but shall perish.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 19 <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Sap.</hi> 1</note> That, <hi>God hates a lying tongue.</hi> &amp;, <hi>That a mouth which lyeth killeth the soule.</hi> Vnto whose sentence that of the Psalmist is confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable, telling vs, that our Lord <hi>will destroy all those that speake lyes.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psalm.</hi> 5 <hi>Ioan.</hi> 8.</note> Nay our Sauiour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe affirmeth, the Diuell to be a lyer, and the father of lyes. These thinges (I say) I knowe. VVhat then will it profit me to seeke to honour a Martyr, by faygning and forging a lye? Doth the glory of Gods Saints need any such foule and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honest helpes? No surely. But I will say, as holy Iob sayd:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iob.</hi> 12.</note>
      <hi>Numquid Deus indiget nostro menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio, vt pro illo loquamur dolos</hi>?</p>
   <p>Therfore to cleare my selfe from this suspition, I protest, that I will make mention of no one thing, which I haue not eyther knowne to be true my selfe, or heard from his mouth whose life and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome I write, or haue not receyued as true, by relation from very honest, vertuous, and sufficient persons, whose tender and Catholike consciences (as may iustly be thought) could not beare the burthen
<pb n="11" facs="6"/>
of vttering such vntruthes.</p>
   <p>Now touching mine owne insufficiency, I hope that the best minded Readers, whom principally I desire to profit and pleasure, will not so much exact, or expect at my handes (discoursing of such a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) Eloquence and Rhetoricall figures, as truth and the playne deliuery of thinges, tending to Gods glory, and theyr owne edification. And thus hauing deliuered vnto thee (gentle Reader) the motiues of my writing, and the drift of mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, humbly beseeching God to assist me with the ayde and direction of his holy spirit, cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing both thy patience and pardon for such faults as shall escape me eyther in wordes or style, I will enter vpon my forsayd intended Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>