<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Harding, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1564</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103740_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02630</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12758</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103740</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Harding, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to Maister Iuelles chalenge, by Doctor Harding</title>
                 <author>Harding, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bogard (Bogardus), Jean</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Louvain</pubPlace>
                    <date>1564</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 176, 179-193, 5 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Vhere as Horace sayeth, they that runne ouer the sea, chaunge the ayer, not the mynde: it is so reader, that I passing ouer the sea out of England in to Brabant, haue in some parte chaunged also my mynde. For whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re as being there, I mynded to send this treatise but to one frend, who required it for his priuate instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and neuer to set any thing abroade: now being arriued here in Louaine, I haue thought good, by putting it in printe, to make it common to many. Yet to saye the trowth, hereto I haue ben prickte more by zelouse persuasions of others, then indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by myne owne lyking. For though dutie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, be it with shame, or be it with fame,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.</note> to employe all endeuour to the defence of the Catholike faith, in these most perilouse times much impugned: yet partely by a certaine cowardly iudgement, and specially by naturall inclination, I haue euer lyked more that olde counsell vttered by the Grekes in two wordes,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> which aduiseth a man so to lyue secret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as it be not knowen, he hath lyued. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as this labour in that respecte deserueth lesse thanke, so for my parte it ought lesse to be blamed. If ought be fownde amysse, the blame thereof rightly diuided betwen my frendes and me, the greater por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion shall redownde to them, the lesser to me, as on whom the spotte of vnskille only shall cleaue, but the note of vndiscretion shall remaine to them. For as the defectes be myne and none others, so ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight of setting forth that, which was of lesse suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie,
<pb facs="3"/> is to be imputed to them, not to me. How so euer it be, the meaning of vs bothe is only this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten reader, hereby to minister vnto thee, matter of comforte in these sorowful, of staye in these waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, of vnderstanding the truth, in these erroneouse times: withall, to call him backe, who in denying these articles, hath ouerrunne him selfe. Wherein I am not all together voyde of hope. Oure lord graunt, the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of heresie, pride, stoutenes of hart in gainesaying, estimation of him selfe, and regarde of this world, stoppe not from him the holy ghostes working. Would god he maye weigh this my dooing so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently, as my meaning towardes him is right, holesom, and frendly. But in case that deepe woonde may not be cured with such salue, yet my trust is, it shall doo thee good, reader, who art either yet hole, or not so desperatly woonded which if it doo, I shall thinke my labour well requitted, and my selfe to haue acheued that reward, which I sought.</p>
   <p>Now this much I haue thought good here to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the of, that where as at the first, I appointed this to my priuate frend only, and not to all in common, (though in sundry places I folow the maner of such as mynde to publish their writinges) I haue so both or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the matter and tempered the style, as I iudge it might haue ben liked of my frend at home, and doubte whether it may beare the light abroade. I see mennes stomakes of oure time to be very delicate and diuerse. Some require swete iunkettes, some sower and sharpe sawces, some esteme the curiositie of coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerye, more then the holesomnes of viandes, some
<pb facs="3"/> can like no dishe, be it neuer so well dighte. In this diuersitie no man can please all. Who so euer seeketh it, shal fynde him selfe deceiued. I wene the best waye is, if a man herein mynde to doo ought, to make his prouision of the thinges only, wich be holesome. So shal he displease many, hurte none, and please al the good. Who so euer in doing this directeth his who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le purpose and endeuour to this ende, that he may profite and helpe all: in my iudgement, he doth the dutie of an honest and a good man. Verely in this treatise this hath ben myne onely purpose, and the meane to bring the same to effecte, hath ben such, as whereby I studied to profite holesomely, not to please delicately. How much good I haue performed, I know not, my conscience (which is ynough) beareth me witnes of good will. What the Apostles haue plā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in this great barraynesse and drowth of faith, I haue desyred againe to water. God geue encreace.</p>
   <p>If the multitude of allegations brought for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of some these Articles, shal seme tediouse, no merueile. I shuld mislike the same in an other my selfe. I graunt herein I haue not alwayes kepte due com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes. For symply to saye, what I thinke (hauing leaue to retourne to my former metaphore) soothly in some courses, I haue ouer charged the borde with disshes. Merueile not, I haue done that, I discōmend my selfe, to auoyde a more reproufe in greater respecte, I haue wittingly done a thing, in some degree reprouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Neither thinke I greatly to offende, if in this time of spirituall famine, I folow the woont of some feaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers. who of their neighbours twited with nyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardnes,
<pb facs="4"/> to shewe their largesse and bountie, feaste thē with lauishe. The aduersarie, as here thou mayst see▪ hath not spared to irke vs with reproche of penurie, of scarcitie, of lacked meane of proufes for maintenance of some good parte of oure religion. In this case to me it semed a parte of iust defence, to vtter some good store. And the nyggardes feaste by olde prouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be is well commended, thou knowest pardie. Neither yet haue we empted all our spence, as hereafter it shal appeare, if nede require.</p>
   <p>If some doo not alowe this consideration, who so euer the same shall blame, him here cōcluding, shortly I answere with Alexander king of Macedons. who to Leonidas one of his Mynnions fynding faute with spending much frankencense in sacrifices, wrote thus in fewe. Frankencense and myrre to the we haue sent plentie, that now to the Goddes thou be no more a nyggard. Fare well, at Louaine: 14. of Iune: 1563.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thom. Harding.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>