<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103614_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02479</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12608</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103614</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An oration conteyning an expostulation : as well with the Queenes Highnesse faithfull subiects for their want of due consideration of Gods blessings enioyed by meanes of her Maiestie: as also with the vnnaturall english for their disloyaltie and vnkindnesse towards the sam their soueraygne. At the first pronounced vpon the Queenes Maiesties birthday in the Guyldhall of the burrowe of Newe Windsore, by Edward Hake of Grayes Inne Gent. then Mayer of the same burrowe: and now newly imprinted this xvij. day of Nouember, in the xxx. yeere of the Queenes Highnesse most happie raigne</title>
                 <author>Hake, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Aggas, Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>VT quam minima aut quam dulcissima.</hi> Either the fewest or the sweetest words thou canst vse. It was the saying of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sope</hi> to <hi>Solon</hi> wherewith hee enfourmed <hi>Solon</hi> how hee should frame and order his speech to King <hi>Croesus.</hi> I assure thee (gentle Reader) the consideration of this speech of <hi>Aesope</hi> somewhat for a while withdrewe me from the printing of this my Oration, as knowing how much I had therein swarued from the sayd two prescripts of <hi>Aesope,</hi> namely of shortnesse and sweetnesse. But being agayne perswaded that inasmuch as the same my Oration (not being made vnto a Prince but of a Prince) had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued allowance amongst the hearers in speaking, it could not but receiue some allowance also in reading, I was cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to yeeld it to the presse, and the rather to satisfie therein the earnest solicitations of such my good friends, whom I knewe to be well affected both to the person and the cause. I knowe there is a people amongst vs, whom in no wise the matter of this my Oration will content, as whom neither the admyrable blessings of God towards vs, our Prince and Countrey can moue, nor the excelling mercies of our gracious Soueraigne allure: but of these I seeke no allowance at all, but rather content my self to be seene herein an vtter enemie to their disloyall and vndu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull dealings. And touching their auouchment of such vnnaturall Treasons and Conspyracies as haue bene here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore intended agaynst this our well prospering gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="4"/>
and State, whereof this little booke discourseth: If I should speake (as taking vpon me to aunswer them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in fewe) I would say with the <hi>Athenian Cleon: If these men haue had cause to conspire or rebell agaynst vs as they haue done,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Thucid. lib. 3. cap. 6▪</note>
      <hi>then must it be confessed that we haue ruled vniustly.</hi> And agayne, if when they haue conspyred, they shall yet thinke that mercie belongeth vnto them: I say with the same <hi>Cleon,</hi> that <hi>mercie should be vsed to them that doe the like, and not to them that haue it not, but rather haue brought themselues into necessitie to be our perpetuall enemies.</hi> But for these, I leaue them as I found them, and to our selues I wish as much in thankfulnesse and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of life, as we haue receiued in benefites at the hande of the almightie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>