<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE FRIENDLY READER concerning the profite of this booke.</title>
           <author>Stockwood, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103473_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12988</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23280</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103473</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE FRIENDLY READER concerning the profite of this booke.</title>
                 <author>Stockwood, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A plaine and easie laying open of the meaning and vnderstanding of the rules of construction in the English accidence : appointed by authoritie to be taught in all schooles of hir Maiesties dominions, for the great vse and benefite of yoong beginners: by Iohn Stockwood sometime schoolmaster of Tunbridge</title>
                 <author>Stockwood, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flower, Francis, Assignees of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Watkins, Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Linguistics and philology</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE FRIENDLY READER concerning the profite of this booke.</head>
   <p>
      <note place="margin" type="runSum">Why this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor hath been taken in the English rules.</note>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OT being altogither ignorant (right gentle Reader) of the slender capacitie of many yoong beginners in the Grammar schooles, hauing my selfe by the space of twenty yeeres exercised the office of a poore Schoolemaster, during the which time I haue had the triall of many wits, and finding by experience, that one and the selfesame thing being often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in teaching, and as it were by small drops instilled into the tender eares of the little Punies and Petites: yet by reason of the weaknes of their wits in those yoong yeeres, it hath quickly passed away without any great profit, I haue wished many times, that some good body would take pains for to lay open the rules of construction in our English Accidence, in such a plaine and ready maner, as that the little ones, might as it were by themselues easily conceiue of the meaning of the same, by the apt applying of euery ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample vnto his seuerall rule. For this being well performed, a ready way is opened to the more easie passing through the examining and parsing of such lectures, as their teachers afterwards shall thinke good to read vnto them. Which labour, bicause none hitherto hath entred vpon, I my selfe in the vacation time of the twel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aies (as they call it) haue taken vpon me, and with God his help <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nished the same. And I haue the rather made choise to deale with the English rules, bicause it is the first thing that the Accidentiaries do enter into, after they haue learned their eight parts of speech, and as it were the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all the rest of the Grammar building, the which being well laid, they shall be the better able to proceed to the vnderstanding of Latin Authors. And for as much as there lieth a great weight in the maner of teaching the yoong beginners the vnderstanding of these rules, which is chiefly to be attained by letting them familiarly and plainly see, how euery example agreeth with his rule, I hope that I haue in such sort performed this point, as that the childe of meanest conceit, if he diligently read and marke this booke, may almost without any helpe of his master, be able of himselfe, by the example, to shew the
<pb facs="4"/> meaning of euery rule, to euery one that shall demand the meaning of the same. So that the long time, the which the master was woont to spend before, about the beating into their heads of the vnderstanding of their rules, may now be spent about other matters tending to their profit, and they themselues, when as their masters words oftentimes were no sooner in at the one eare, but that they were as quickly out againe at the other to his great griefe, and many times to their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter smart, when they were well whipped for their dulnes, may by the helpe of this booke opened and laid before them, haue such a master as will at all times most gently and plainly teach them, if they will but vouchsafe to repaire and resort vnto him.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin" type="runSum">Paines spared to the school<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master.</note>The Schoolemaster then shall by this booke be eased of much paines, that he was forced to vse before to little purpose, bicause that the sound of his words striking their eares for the time, was streight waies forgotten: <note place="margin" type="runSum">Ease to the scholler.</note> and the scholler that carying away many a stripe for his dulnes and forgetfulnes was much discouraged, and not daring for feare to aske his master againe the thing which he told him twentie times before, may resort hither, and without any blowes heare againe and againe the same thing euen so often as he list, the which neither time nor tediousnes will suffer his master to repeate vnto him.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin" type="runSum">Euery father regarding the profit of his child.</note>Yea euery louing and carefull father for the profit of his sonne, the which hath somtimes in his youth been a smatterer in Grammar, and now through continuance of time, and other busines almost cleane forgotten the same, by vsing this booke, and questioning at spare times with his childe, when he commeth from the Grammar schoole, may partly increase his forlorne knowledge, and partly helpe forward by his riper wit, the tender vnderstanding of his little childe, and perceiue how he profiteth, so far foorth as concerneth the conceiuing of the meaning of euery rule, by applying euery example vnto the same, to which purpose I dare boldly pronounce, that nothing is omitted, that any way cōcerneth the fitting of euery example to euery rule through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole rules of construction, hauing framed my selfe to be as it were dunstically plaine, for the better vnderstanding of the yoong ones, vnto whom nothing can be made too plaine, in which respect the learneder sort will vouchsafe me their pardon, knowing that these paines were purposedly taken for the profit of the small ones: yet it may be that same things are heere set downe, the which being well marked, may saue my master schollers of the higher forms now and then a scowring, and also make a way for them by themselues to do
<pb facs="4"/> the like to their great profit, in the applieng the examples of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Syntaxis, vnto the rules of the same, the which will be the easier for them by the helpe of this booke, wherein they may behold the like to be performed in all the English rules, in which respect they will also be the willinger to haue the English Accidence bound with this, to aide them in the same.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin" type="runSum">This booke will further the sale of the English Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidence.</note> And by this meanes my friends the Printers of the English Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidence shall stand not a little beholding vnto me, in as much as this Booke will be so far off from hindring the sale thereof, as that it will cause the same to sell much faster, euerie one minding to buie this, being desirous also to haue that, to ioine with it, that they may the better confer the one with the other, and see in the Accidence the rule naked by it selfe seeming to be hard, heere made plaine by the example, to appeere most cleere and easie for the capacitie of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie meanest, besides that, for the marking of the order obserued both in the one and the other, it shall be verie behoouefull to haue them both bound togither.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin" type="runSum">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar allowed by authoritie.</note> Now if any curiously conceited, and giuen vnto nouelties, liking better of the later, though darker deuises of others, then being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to vse the more ancient and plainer Grammar of our owne, will demand of me, wherefore I did not rather bestow these paines vpon the making familiar the Grammar precepts of some stranger, then in opening the rules of our owne Countriman: mine answer shall be, that concerning my selfe (vnder the correction of others be it spoken) I know none in this argument (all circumstances considered) to whom our Grammar allowed by publike authoritie, ought to yeeld one foote of ground, in regard of plainnes and easines, if it be rightly vnderstood, and taught accordingly. And for the profitablenes of the same, if there were nothing else to be alleaged, but the great number of most excellent learned men, shining as notable lightes, both in the church, and also the commonwealth, yet might this in the iudgement of all wise men, seeme for to plead for the same sufficiently. So that I would wish our owne auctorized Grammar so long to be publikely propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in schooles vnto youth, vntill these admirers of new things, can auouch so much profit to haue cōmen by their new deuises, as we know by experience to haue proceeded alreadie of this our old Grammar, wherein so many profitable instruments in the ciuill and church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment haue hitherto been trained.</p>
   <p>Wherefore as I iudge our owne Grammar to be, if not more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,
<pb facs="5"/> yet in euery point as profitable as any others whatsoeuer, so haue I been heereby mooued to labor in it before in any other, <note place="margin" type="runSum">What is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in this booke.</note> and in this part of it especially, the which most concerneth the yoong beginners, for whose sake I haue not onely applied al the examples of al the rules of construction in the English Accidence, to expresse the meaning of euery seuerall rule, but haue also Englished all the examples, which hitherto haue gone onely in Latin, whereby the little ones may be much furthered.</p>
   <p>And moreouer for their greater profit, I haue borrowed from the Latin Grammar so many rules, as I haue thought most conuenient and necessarie, and haue set them downe heere also in English in their seuerall places, as may well appeere vnto so manie as binding the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish accidence with this shall take pains to compare the rules of the one with the other. As many as shall reape commoditie heereby (as I hope all those youthes especially shall, the which with diligence shall be occupied in the same) let them giue vnto God alone all the glorie, and in consideration of my paines afoord me their earnest and faithfull praiers, that whilest I liue, I may alwaies carrie a minde continuallie to do good in his church and common-wealth, to his praise, and benefit of my countrie. From my studie at Tunbridge the <hi>14.</hi> of Ian. <hi>1588.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy poore brother in Christ, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feinedlie tendring thy good, wherein he may: IOHN STOCKWOOD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>