<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In Commendation of that vertuous Gentleman Mr. Henry Welby.</title>
           <author>T., J.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103493_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68870</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25226.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103493</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In Commendation of that vertuous Gentleman Mr. Henry Welby.</title>
                 <author>T., J.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The phoenix of these late times: or the life of Mr. Henry Welby, Esq : who lived at his house in Grub-street forty foure yeares, and in that space, was never seene by any, aged 84. Shewing the first occasion, and the reasons thereof. Whose portracture, you may behold, as it was taken at his death. With epitaphs and elegies of the late deceased gentleman, who lyeth buried in S. Giles Church neere Criple gate, London</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Clutterbuck (Clotterbuck), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, portraits (metal cut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="24"/>
   <head>In Commendation of that vertuous Gentleman M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Henry Welby.</hi>
   </head>
   <l>
      <hi>WEll be</hi> the blessed <hi>Subject</hi> of these lines,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Well be</hi> the Star that now in glory shines,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Well be</hi> thou, <hi>well be</hi> all that live to dye,</l>
   <l>And dye in grace to live immortally.</l>
   <l>Thou that did'st from the world thy selfe exclude,</l>
   <l>And (by abstaining <hi>flesh</hi>) the flesh subdu'd;</l>
   <l>And with the <hi>Sword,</hi> (Gods Word) warr'd with the devil,</l>
   <l>Still striving to shunne all occasions evill:</l>
   <l>For knowing mans best workes to be impure,</l>
   <l>From sight of man thou didst thy selfe immure:</l>
   <l>Where reading good things, sin was mortifi'd,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Hope</hi> was confirm'd, and <hi>Faith</hi> was fortifi'd.</l>
   <l>Thy <hi>Charity</hi> did worke, (not one day idle)</l>
   <l>True <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Fasting</hi> did thy frailty bridle,</l>
   <l>And (like <hi>Cornelius</hi>) up to <hi>Heaven</hi> ascended</l>
   <l>Thy Almes and Orisons, and there attended,</l>
   <l>Vntill thy soule shooke off earth transitory,</l>
   <l>To be enshrin'd, and crown'd with endlesse glory.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>J. T.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>