<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103587_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02414</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12543</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103587</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pieties pillar: or, A sermon preached at the funerall of mistresse Elizabeth Gouge, late wife of Mr. William Gouge, of Black-friers, London : With a true narration of her life and death. By Nicholas Guy, pastor of the church at Edge-ware in Middlesex</title>
                 <author>Guy, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 52 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Good Reader:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T fell out with the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, at whose Funerall this Sermon was preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as it did with <hi>Iaakobs</hi> beloued <hi>Rachel.</hi> In a <note n="*" place="margin">Mistresse GOVGE brought forth her last Childe into this world, and went her selfe out of this world, in the Country house of Master <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and Mistresse <hi>Anne Gee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi>: who inhabiting the greatest part of the yeere in <hi>Black friers Londo,</hi> were desirous to shew to their Pastor there, such respect as the <hi>Sunemite</hi> and her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band did to <hi>Elisha,</hi> &amp; <hi>Onesiphorus</hi> to <hi>Paul.</hi>
      </note> strange place they both fell in trauell, and in the time of their child-bed they both departed this life. Answerably as <hi>Iaakob</hi> would not haue his <hi>Rachels</hi> memory perish with her corps, but for better preseruation thereof, erected a Pillar vpon her graue, so to the same end it is desired, that this <hi>Funerall Sermon</hi> may be published. <hi>Rachel</hi> could not be more deare to her <hi>Iaakob,</hi> then this <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was to her <hi>William.</hi> In her life time she carried her selfe worthy of all honour: and at her Funerall she was honoured with all the honour that on such a sudden the Country where she de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
<pb facs="5"/>
could afford. Her sweet soule left her body about one of the clocke in the afternoone of the <hi>26.</hi> of October, <hi>1625.</hi> being Wednesday, whereupon her Corps being infected with the Dropsie, and all the Pores of it open, by reason of her late trauell and weakenesse in Child-bed, could not bee long kept, but on the Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following, which was <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Iudes</hi> day, was buried vnder the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Table in the Church, at <hi>Edge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware,</hi> in the County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accompanied with a great multitude of sundry sorts of persons, Honourable, Worshipfull, and others. For besides that, two whole Parishes there met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, Knights, Ladies, Iustices of Peace, Ministers and other good Christians round about that place, came farre and neere to the solemnization of that Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. That the due honour done to her may be more then the honour of one day, this Pillar of Pietie is now erected for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to others in their life time to walke worthy of honour.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>