<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY LORD the Chancellor.</title>
           <author>Balzac</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103517_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02324</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12455</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103517</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY LORD the Chancellor.</title>
                 <author>Balzac</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A collection of some modern epistles of Monsieur de Balzac. Carefully translated out of French. Being the fourth and last volume</title>
                 <author>Balzac, Jean-Louis Guez, seigneur de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Bowman, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Crooke, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sergier, Richard 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 249, 9 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>TO MY LORD the Chancellor.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I Have understood of your deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, for the publishing of a <hi>Libell,</hi> lately fram'd against me. And though (perhaps) the harme that I should have received thereby, would have been but small, yet my obligation unto you, never ceaseth to be great; and this argueth a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care in you of my tranquillity, not to suffer that any, the least noise should disquiet it. I know not (<hi>my Lord</hi>) if this be not to handle with too much nicenesse and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, a man that makes profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of <hi>Philosophy</hi>; it were enough
<pb facs="12"/>
that publike <hi>Authority</hi> should shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me from the <hi>tempest,</hi> without exempting me from the <hi>wind</hi> and <hi>dust,</hi> and that it would guard my <hi>Retrait</hi> from <hi>savage</hi> beasts, without frighting away the <hi>flies</hi> also, and such importunate <hi>Insects.</hi> But (<hi>my Lord</hi>) the goodnesse which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve for me, extends farther then to ordinary justice. You take not only care for my <hi>repose</hi> amidst the <hi>hurry</hi> and tumult of <hi>Europe,</hi> but you would have the world also shew a <hi>respect</hi> unto my retirednesse, and that being <hi>sequestred</hi> from men. J should be also placed beyond the levell and reach of <hi>Detraction.</hi> Yet this Fiend did pursue S. <hi>Hierome</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto the Grotts of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and to the foot of our <hi>Saviours</hi> cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, there <hi>she</hi> found him (as he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates himselfe) although he had
<pb facs="12"/>
thought to <hi>hide</hi> himselfe. If this insolent <hi>Thing</hi> had no regard of an admirable <hi>sanctity,</hi> and a place <hi>guarded</hi> with <hi>Angels,</hi> me thinks a vulgar <hi>innocence,</hi> retired within an ill fortified village, must not expect any favourable treaty. But to passe from common conditions to the learned <hi>Tribe</hi>; If in all ages, there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rose seditious spirits, that rebelled against the <hi>Chieftaines</hi> of <hi>Arts</hi> and discipline, and if in the memory of our <hi>fathers,</hi> it was spoken openly at <hi>Paris,</hi> that <hi>Aristotle</hi> was a simple <hi>Sophister,</hi> J think they deale cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teously with me in this Country, if they be contented to call me a simple <hi>writer.</hi> That great blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of the name of <hi>Aristotle (my Lord)</hi> was D. <hi>Ramus,</hi> who afterward, though he was a <hi>Catholique,</hi> was taken for a <hi>Huguenot,</hi> at the massa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre;
<pb facs="13"/>
And indeed, some did believe that God permitted this to come to passe by a just judgement; and that the <hi>Tutelar</hi> Angell of good <hi>Letters,</hi> took the pretext of <hi>Religion,</hi> for to revenge the injuries that were done to <hi>Reason.</hi> There is one this day alive in <hi>Germany,</hi> a petty Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in Grammer, an enimy of common and generall verities, and an accuser of <hi>Cicero</hi>; who (not long since) hath put forth some obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, where he preferres a bill against his own Judge, and questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the precedency ever allowed unto that <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Latine</hi> Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. So that (<hi>my Lord</hi>) the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall consent of all the world, strengthned by a prescription of 18. centuries of years, is not a suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient title for to warrant the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of that <hi>Roman,</hi> against
<pb facs="13"/>
the prevaricating quirkes of this <hi>Barbarian.</hi> Indeed, this is a busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of no good example, but yet since it is so, and that it doth litle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile <hi>Virtue,</hi> to be consecrated by time, and to be crowned by the people, for to make it inviolable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the practises of some private Humors. There is no reason that I should complaine before so many <hi>Worthies,</hi> that have bin so ill intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themselves, and that I should be had in any consideration, where <hi>Aristotle</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> are not in safety; an ordinary man should not make moan, for suffering the same desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which extraordinary Persona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges have undergone; and I cannot with modesty, desire or expect from you, that you should reforme the world for the love of me; nay, J know (<hi>my Lord</hi>) that this litle
<pb facs="14"/>
disorder, is of some good use in a common-wealth; and it were to be wished, that malice would busy it selfe thus, about things of small importance, that it might not think of businesses of higher conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. Those that have hitherto bestowed their pains, in depraving the sence of my words, and in falsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying my works, had (perhaps) ere this time, forged mens <hi>Testaments,</hi> and minted false coines; And he that now desires from you a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, would have stood in need of a <hi>Pardon,</hi> it may be, if it had not been for me. It is better by farre, that injustice should exercise it selfe upon my books, than that it should vexe and <hi>implead</hi> against all that is good and sacred in a civill society; that unjust men should rather tosse and transpose words, invert and
<pb facs="14"/>
pervert periods of speeches, than remove the bounds of lands, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molish their <hi>Neighbours</hi> houses; To say the truth, this is the most inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent way that <hi>vice</hi> can imploy it selfe in, and I believe I have not a litle deserv'd from the common-wealth, for keeping at worke these ten years, such an infinite number of idle companions, who (certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) would have been dangerous Commonwealths-men, if they had not chosen rather to have been ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous <hi>Censors.</hi> It is well, that the heat of their braines, is <hi>exhaled</hi> out this way, and that their intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance takes this course; and that to prevent their fury, men give some scope and liberty to their folly. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them therefore this exercise (<hi>my Lord</hi>) they cannot choose but make use of their time, which they will
<pb facs="15"/>
imploy farre worse, if you doe not permit them to imploy it thus. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <hi>giddy</hi> Youth to spend their heat and fury upon a senselesse subject, and a dead letter, which is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peable either of joy or sorrow. As long as these <hi>Pen-fencers</hi> only beg the <hi>Seale</hi> of your <hi>Authority,</hi> be no niggard of the <hi>Prince</hi> his grace and favour, and abate something of your wonted severity and rigour. If it were anew &amp; unusuall thing, it may be, I should be contented to have the first <hi>Libell,</hi> which branded me with injuries be suppressed, but since there is now a pretty <hi>Library</hi> of them, I am in a manner well pleased it should swell and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, and I take a delight to build me a <hi>moniment</hi> with those stones, which <hi>Envy</hi> hath hurl'd at me, without doing me harme. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="15"/>
it no disgrace to be censur'd by some men, because I account it no credit to be favour'd by them: I intend not to canvasse for voices, nor labour a mysterious secret, whereby I may gaine the generall applause of the world. I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained what I desired, (<hi>my Lord</hi>) if I have obtained your approbation, as being derived from an un-erring <hi>principle,</hi> and from an <hi>Jntelligence</hi> most perfectly <hi>illuminated.</hi> God hath bestowed on you, a <hi>soveraigne</hi> judgement, before the <hi>King</hi> had committed to your hands, his <hi>sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne</hi> Justice. And you were most powerfull in Reason, before you were so in <hi>Authority.</hi> J need not have recourse to <hi>this,</hi> knowing that the <hi>other</hi> is no way against me, and I estime it more glory to me, to have pleased you, than I would
<pb facs="16"/>
think it satisfaction to have my enimies proscribed by you. Your speeches of me upon every occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on so full of respect, your own <hi>pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture</hi> that you bestowed upon me a yeare agoe, for a pledge of your Affection, your imparting to me the riches of your writings, I mean those writings, that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated with the <hi>spirit</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> and were full of the <hi>greatnesse</hi> of your <hi>Master,</hi> which seemed to me so farre to transcend the strength and vigor of this age, and so nearly resembling the <hi>Roman Majesty.</hi> In a word (<hi>my Lord</hi>) each moment of that happy afternoone, which I had the honour to passe away within your closet, are <hi>priviledges,</hi> which I doe value above that which you denied a <hi>Fantasme,</hi> or the Successor of <hi>Philarchus.</hi> I dare not rehearse
<pb facs="16"/>
my other obligations, by which I stand bound unto you. You have herein injoyned me silence, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that your favours would loose something of their purity, if my thanks should still attend them. Neverthelesse you must not stifle in me the intentions of an honest man, or smother the conceptions of gratefull thoughts; you have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred me from divulging my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements, but you shall not debarre me from acquitting that secret part of duty, and from being, (at least in my soule) and that while I live</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>My Lord</salute>
      <signed>Your most humble, most obliged and most thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full servant <hi>BALZAC.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>From <hi>Balzac</hi> the
<date>1 of Iuly 1637.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>