<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To euerye freendly and Courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>G., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103342_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01930</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103342</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To euerye freendly and Courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>G., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of the famous historye of Penardo and Laissa : other ways callid the warres, of love and ambitione. Wherein is described Penardo his most admirable deeds of arms, his ambition of glore his contempt of loue, with loves mighte assalts &amp; ammorus temptations: Laissas feareful inchantment hir releif hir trauells and lastly loves admirabel force, in hir releiving Penardo from ye fire, doone in heroik verse, by Patrik Gordon</title>
                 <author>Gordon, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waters (Walters), Joris (George)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Dordrecht</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>280 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To euerye freendly and Courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE,</hi> and courteous Reader, I doubt not but some their are, that wil not gentlye, but rashlie censure those my labours, Nether am I ignorant, how hard a thing it is to please euery one, Some their be that are courious, whom as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> is impossible to pleas, so haue I geuē ouer impessibilites, as one, whoes judgement could neuer reatch to the meanest of possible things: Some their be that are invyous, &amp; those as I care lytle for their feid, so hunt I not muche for their fauor: Some also wil be rashe, in geueing their judgement before they haue duely considdered, to whoes temerarious, opinione, as I geue lytle heed, so will I suffer them, to be whipt withe their owne folyes: But you that ar judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieus disereit, &amp; courteous, eune you it is, whom I wold please▪ I confes I writ not of profound, and deip maters, fitting your judgements, bot according to the shallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of my braine, as their is not much good to be reapt, so shall you not find much evill: Wheirfore, my willingnes I hope, will satisfie a great parte of your contents, &amp; sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie my defects. Looking alwayes (that altho I can not in the greatest measure satisfie your ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ectation) yit ye wil accept freindlie, of my goodwil; In respect, that vnto your charitable hands only, I cousmit the censure of these my paepers, as the vndoubted touche stone, wheron my trauels must be tryed: And how many so euer my e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rors be, which I doubt not, but the thrie afore named wil mak to many, yit to you I hope it shall suffice that I acknowledge my owne weaknes. But fearing to deceaue my self, with too muche presuming on your courtesye, I haue left of in the
<pb facs="4"/>
mids of my labours, for that I was loath to paine my self with to muche trauell, till I wer better certefied, of your fauourable acceptance, (which while I heir of, I haue thought goode to stand at a point, and breath a whyle) as the only rewaird, I craue for al my trauells yit my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel is, before yow geue judgement, that ze enter, and walk throw all my fielde, look on euery shade, searche throw euery corner, wheir amongst the pople, and tair, yow may find some pure grane, And amongst the thornes and breirs, some roses, that may perhaps haue a pleasant smell: Vpon al aduentures, hoping that suche will be your censur, as my meaning is towards yow, I bid yow fairwel</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, as you merit. P. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>