<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR THOMAS COVENTRY, Knight, Lord COVENTRY, Baron of Alesbo∣rough, Lord Keeper of the Great Seale of ENGLAND.</title>
           <author>Gouge, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103284_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01974</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12116</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103284</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR THOMAS COVENTRY, Knight, Lord COVENTRY, Baron of Alesbo∣rough, Lord Keeper of the Great Seale of ENGLAND.</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods three arrovves : plague, famine, svvord, in three treatises. I. A plaister for the plague. II. Dearths death. III. The Churches conquest over the sword. By William Gouge Doctor in Divinity, and preacher of Gods Word in Black-Friers, London</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Brewster (Bruster), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 128, 8, 129-176, 16, 177-436, 12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR THOMAS COVENTRY, Knight, Lord COVENTRY, Baron of <hi>Alesbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, Lord Keeper</hi> of the <hi>Great Seale</hi> of ENGLAND.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven he that joyned his <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Vox honorem exhibentis, &amp; omnia bono pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantis.</note>
      <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brek</hi> his joyfull applause with the joyfull acclamations of many when your Lordship <note place="margin">Gen 41. 43.</note> was first advanced to your honourable place, doth now see further cause to adde this <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Vox congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantis &amp; collan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantis Deum. <hi>Rev. 19. 6. &amp; in psal. saepissimè.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Halelu-jah,</hi> his <hi>congratulation,</hi> praising God for your conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, as in your place, so in your approved <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity,</hi> which hath beene found, (as the Apostle saith of the faith of Christians) <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">c 1 Pet. 1. 7.</note>,
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>unto your praise, and honour, and glory,</hi> like good gold, which from the furnace appeares more solid and resplendent. For, your kind of judicature, according to the nature of your place, and your owne purpose, is not onely (to use <note n="d" place="margin">Aug. ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. Epist. 158.</note> Saint <hi>Augustines</hi> phrase) <hi>Iudicis mollire sententiam, &amp; mitiùs vindicare quàm leges,</hi> but it is like that which a <note n="e" place="margin">Zac 8. 16.</note> Prophet calls <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Iudgement of peace:</hi> which <note n="f" place="margin">Hier. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lib. 2. in Zac. cap. 8.</note> Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> thus expounds, <hi>Hoc est judicium pacis ut propositum Iudex habeat pacificare discordes.</hi> This is no small difficulty, since according to the same <note n="g" place="margin">Hier. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. lib. 1. in Esa. cap. 1.</note>
      <hi>Hierom, Non est omnium rectè judicare, sed eorum qui pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes sunt:</hi> who are made wise from above. Therefore <note n="h" place="margin">Salomon in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sione per somni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um hoc à Deo postulavit, ut ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta sapientia justè populum judicaret. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Salomon</hi> in a dreame asked this of God. And shall not the praise thereof by him that receiveth it, by them that partake of the benefit of it, be retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to him from whom descendeth <note n="i" place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap> Sie distinguo, ut denationem ab ipso dono. <hi>Beza.</hi>
      </note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>; But, my good Lord, least telling the truth of your selfe may seeme flattery to others, and flattery neither sorts with your disposition, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes my profession, give mee leave in mine high esteeme of your <hi>Honour,</hi> and humble expression of mine affection, to publish my poore paines under your honourable name: wishing I were able,
<pb facs="3"/>
besides my observance to your Lordship, in my zeale to Gods Church, <hi>Gemmas offerre.</hi> But with <hi>Origen, Quia haec supra me sunt, pilas caprarum habere merear,</hi> &amp;c. For, whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever my weakenesses bee, are not these times seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable (I would they were not) for such a Subject as is here handled, <hi>Treatises</hi> of <hi>Plague</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> yea and of <hi>Warre</hi> too? For, though by the Prudence &amp; Providence of our royall <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> Sonne and Heire of the great <hi>Peace-maker,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> warre be kept out of our land: yet in other parts of Christendome, it, and the restrage like over-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flouds, to the ruine of many States and of true Religion. <hi>The Lion hath roared, who will not feare? The Lord God hath spoken, who can but prophesie?</hi> Yet are these <hi>Treatises</hi> neither to terrifie for what is past, nor to prophesie of what is yet to come; but rather to heale the wounds that have beene made by the fore-intimated arrowes, and to direct us how to keepe the Lord from fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shooting out the like. It is the part of us <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of Gods Word,</hi> out of his Word to declare what he intendeth and expecteth when he smileth, or frowneth on his people. <hi>Magistrates</hi> (who by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of their places, are in <hi>Canaans</hi> language
<pb facs="4"/>
stiled <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Gods and children of the</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 82. 6.</note>
      <hi>most high)</hi> have the power to cause divine directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to bee put in execution. Thus therefore doth an ancient Father paraphrase on that text, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in God himselfe thus speaking to Magistrates, <hi>I have given you mine own honour, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <note place="margin">
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>. Iustin. Mart. Quest. &amp; Resp. ad Orthodox. q 142.</note> and title, Therefore judge the people as if I my selfe judged it.</hi> To whom now may those seasonable <hi>Treatises</hi> which do (as it were with the finger) point at Gods particular dealing with us, be more fitly presented, then to him, who under his most excellent Majesty, hath so great a place and part, with others, to settle orders for suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couring poore people, wounded as aforesaid, and for sheltring them from those arrowes. Of the <hi>Treatises</hi> thus commended to your honourable Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, gracious acceptance is in all humility cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by him that professeth himselfe to be.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>At your Honours command, WILLIAM GOVGE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>