<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO OVR GRA∣TIOVS
AND BLES∣sed
Mother, the Church of
ENGLAND.
THE MEANEST OF HER
Children Dedicates this her Apology,
and wisheth all Peace and Happines.</title>
           <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103653_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02522</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12649</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103653</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO OVR GRA∣TIOVS
AND BLES∣sed
Mother, the Church of
ENGLAND.
THE MEANEST OF HER
Children Dedicates this her Apology,
and wisheth all Peace and Happines.</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A common apologie of the Church of England : against the vniust challenges of the ouer-iust sect, commonly called Brownists. Wherein the grounds and defences, of the separation are largely discussed: occasioned, by a late pamphlet published vnder the name, of an answer to a censorious epistle, which the reader shall finde in the margent. By I.H</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Macham, Samuel 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Edgar, Eleazar.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 145, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO OVR GRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIOVS
AND BLES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
Mother, the Church of
ENGLAND.
THE MEANEST OF HER
Children Dedicates this her Apology,
and wisheth all Peace and Happines.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O lesse then a yeare
and a halfe is past
(Reuerend, Deare,
and holy Mother)
since I wrote a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
monitory letter
to two of thine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy
Sons; which
(I heard) were fled from thee in person, in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
and somewhat in opinion: Supposing
them yet thine in the maine substance, though in
<pb facs="3"/>
some circumstances their owne. Since which, one
of them hath wash't of thy Font-water as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean,
and hath written desperately both against
thee, and his owne fellowes: From the other, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
(not two moneths since) a stomakful Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet;
besides the priuate iniuries to the monitor,
casting vpon thine honourable name blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos
imputations of Apostasie, Antichristianisme,
Whoordome, Rebellion: Mine owne wronges I
could haue contemned in silence,<note place="margin">Meam iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am patiētertuli impietatem contra Spōsam Christi ferre non potui. Hier ad Vigilant.</note> but, For Sions
sake, I cannot hold my peace: If I remember not
thee, O Ierusalem, let my tongue cleaue to the
roofe of my mouth. It were a shame, and sinne
for me, that myzeale should be lesse hote for thine
innocency, then theirs to thy false disgrace. How
haue I hastened therefore to let the world see thy
sincere truth, and their peruerse slanders. Vnto
thy sacred name then (whereto I haue in all piety
deuoted my selfe) I humbly present this my spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
and dutifull labour: whereby I hope thy weak
Sonnes may be confirmed, the strong encouraged,
the rebellious shamed: And if any shall still ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinately
accurse thee, I referre their reuenge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
thy Glorious Head, who hath espoused thee to
himselfe, in trueth and righteousnesse: Let him
whose thou art, right thee: In the meane time,
<pb facs="3"/>
we thy true sonnes, shall not onely defend, but
magnifie thee: Thou maiest be blacke, but thou
art comely: the Daughters haue seene thee, and
counted thee blessed; euen the Queene, and the
Concubines, and they haue praised thee: thou art
thy Welbelouedst, and his desire is towards thee:
So let it be, and so let thine be towards him
for euer; and mine towards you
both, who am the least of
all thy little ones,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOS. HALL.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>