<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The prologue of the famous Syr Anthonie of Gueuara, Byshoppe of Mondonnedo, preacher, chronicler, &amp; counsellour to the Emperour Charles the fifth, vpon the life of tenne Emperours of Rome. (∴) The Author proponeth.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103534_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02294</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12426</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103534</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The prologue of the famous Syr Anthonie of Gueuara, Byshoppe of Mondonnedo, preacher, chronicler, &amp; counsellour to the Emperour Charles the fifth, vpon the life of tenne Emperours of Rome. (∴) The Author proponeth.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A chronicle, conteyning the liues of tenne emperours of Rome : Wherin are discouered, their beginnings, procéedings, and endings, worthie to be read, marked, and remembred. Wherein are also conteyned lawes of speciall profite and policie. ... Compiled by the most famous Syr Anthonie of Gueuara, Bishop of Mondonnedo, preacher, chronicler, and counsellour to the Emperour Charles the fift: and translated out of Spanish into English, by Edward Hellowes, Groome of her Maiesties Leashe. Hereunto is also annexed a table, recapitulating such particularities, as are in this booke mentioned</title>
                 <author>Guevara, Antonio de, bp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 <publisher>Middleton, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 484, 10 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb n="1" facs="5"/>
   <head>¶<hi>The prologue of the famous Syr</hi> Anthonie of Gueuara, Byshoppe of <hi>Mondonnedo, preacher, chronicler, &amp;</hi> counsellour to the Emperour Charles the fifth, vpon the life of tenne Emperours of Rome. (∴) The Author proponeth.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>ARIVS GEMINVS, a man verie glorious, and Consul among the Romains, saide vnto Iulius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar: O Caesar and great Augustus, such as dare presume to speake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, knowe not thy greatnesse: and those that are abashed to appeare in thy presence, comprehend not thy noblenesse: wordes in deede right worthie of such a person. Conformable to that which Varius Geminus saide, wee do saye: <hi>It appertaineth to the greatnesse of Princes, that their persons be much authorised, and on the other parte, that they endeuour to communicate with their common wealthes, for that with their mightinesse they may giue terrour, and with their plaine mildnesse remoue all feare.</hi> Sucro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius saith of Octauius the emperour, that euer any am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadours came in his presence, which at the first sight were not touched with feare: and after in communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting did not adore him: because, great was the maiestie wherewith he did receiue them, and after, verie sweete were the woordes wherewith he did dispatch them. Of the great Cato Censorine, Plutarche saith: that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the man of moste honestie, and greatest grauitie that liued amongest the Romaines: he did neuer shewe to any man, a sadde, but cheerefull countenance, or giue
<pb n="2" facs="6"/>
euill aunswere, nor shut the doore against any person, either denyed any thing that was iust, neither shamed or disgraced any man. <hi>Not onely happie, but also most hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie is the Prince, that for rectitude of iustice is feared, and for his good condition beloued.</hi> Much weakenesse of Princes, and great Lordes is couered, and vices dissimuled, when with their owne they be of good condition, and with straungers of gratefull conuersation. Of the famous tyrant Dionysius the Siracusan, Plutarche saith: that the immortal hatred which the Sicylians did beare him, was not so much for the tyrannies that he did execute, as for the incomporcable condition which he vsed: for that verie seldome he did permitt him selfe to be seene: and verie oft was heard laughing. The contrarie wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is read of king Antigonus, the father of the greate Demetrius: whoe was proude, couetous, ambitious, cruell, and effeminate: and with all these conditions the people of his kingdomes did both suffer and serue him: onely for that they founde the dores of his house al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes open, and in his mouth an amorous aunswere. The ende of all this which we haue saide is, humblie to praye all princes, and giue warning vnto all such as be about them, alwayes to persuade and counsell them to be so humaine, that all may endure their conuersation: and yet so graue, that none presume to make small ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of them: for that it maketh much to the matter of good gouernement, to be indued with good nature and disposition. No lesse inconuenience doth followe the common wealth, for the Prince to be holden in small estimation, then to be vntractable, ouer haughtie, or straunge: for, if he be inconuersible, they abhorre him: and if not esteemed, they disobey him.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="3" facs="6"/>Sardanapalus, the last King of the Assyrians, was with all men so humaine, that women made him spinne: and of Phalaris the tyrant, it is read, that he was so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuersible, that his owne daughters durst not speake vnto him. <hi>To the ende that Princes be not abhorred in their common wealthes, they haue to consider, and also beware to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of extremities: which is to witt, in vsing too great familiaritie with some, and no lesse straungenesse with others: because muche straungenesse ingendreth hatred: and too much familiaritie leadeth to contempt.</hi> The rule that in this case wee dare giue vnto Princes, mightie and noble men, is: that they be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther so affable with their priuate and fauoured seruants, whereby to giue them hardinesse to craue any thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iust: either so straunge with them that be not priuate, as to giue them feare to demaund iustice. It is not remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from Princes, to giue their kingdomes vnto their children, to committ their secretes vnto such as be ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable, to vse their liberalitie with their priuate and fauoured seruauntes, to take their pastimes with their friendes, vpon such condition, that their conuersation be somewhat generall: for asmuche as the liberalitie of Princes extendeth not to satisfie euery suite: they sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply much more with their amorous aunswers that they giue, then with the rewardes which they bestowe. Not vnworthily was it ordeined of the moste auncient Greekes, that the vse of Princes shoulde not be to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce in their letters patents, and commaundementes: <hi>I commaund this, I will this, I forbidde this:</hi> but that they should saye: <hi>We commaund this, We will this, and ordeine this:</hi> for their better remembrance, that by speaking in the name of all, they should in time be conuersant with all, be familiar with all, and diuide rewardes amongest all, and that they are of all, and not of them selues.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="4" facs="7"/>He that hath to holde the least parte of the prince, ought to be the prince him selfe: for that, great regarde is to be had of all men, as concerning the seruice of his person: and he ought to be vigilant in all things that are profitable to the common wealth. <hi>Howe much the more the Prince regardeth him selfe: so muche the more he neglecteth him selfe. And howe muche the lesse he careth for him selfe: so muche the more shall he attaine to him selfe: for that the harmonie of the common wealth consisteth in nothing more, then all men to liue of the liberalitie and bountie of the prince: and that the Prince liue in the loue of all men.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>¶The Authour prosecuteth his intent.</p>
   <p>It is also necessarie counsell vnto the prince, that he haue a sound minde and disposition, and his intents ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie well aduertised: for that if in his affaires he make no accompt to be certeine, he shall hardly cease to erre: and if he be not attentiue to the affaires of the common wealth, he shall neuer vnderstand them.</p>
   <p>The prince ought grauely to regarde the thing he doth, before it be done: for the errour of any other whatsoeuer, the offence is onely felt in his own house: but the errour of the prince, redoundeth to the whole common wealth. The princes that be wilfull in the thinges which they will: and headstrong wherein they commaund: besides that they go laden with thoughts, holding their persons in perill, escandalize their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, accused to be ouer amarous of their owne proper iudgement, and moste great enimies of others counsell. The prince also ought very particularly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the things of the common wealth, if he wil vse good gouernement thereof. And this he hath to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertised, not of suche as goe to murmur, but of such as make iust report, and also giue counsel therein: for that
<pb n="5" facs="7"/>
      <hi>twixt the Prince and the common wealth, there shall neuer be peace, if to lyars and murmurers he giue audience.</hi> Euen as Princes desire not in their subiectes, but to be serued: euen so their subiects desire not of their princes, but to be beloued, &amp; most truely, the one is annexed vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other, and depēdeth each of other: for if in the Prince there be no loue, there is none that wil serue him with affection. Princes and great lordes, ought to holde in great estimation, that their subiectes do obey them: but much more haue the subiectes to make accompt, when their lordes do loue them: because, without comparison, his bountie is much greater that bindeth vs to loue, then the trauaile of him that offereth to serue.
<q>As loue is not repayed but with loue, so Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are not to be satisfied with only giuing such as do serue and followe them, offices, castels, customes, houses and money: but also they ought to shewe them loue in their palaces, and fauour in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: because, with their liberalitie, they recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence their seruice past: but with their loue they bind them to serue in time to come.</q>
   </p>
   <p>Princes and men of power, ought in their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to be amorous, in their speach milde, in their behauiours muche ordered: for that generous hartes, and blusshing and shamefast faces, that followe courtes, and go in Princes houses, do muche more feele the disfauour whiche they shewe them, then the rewardes that they denye them. <hi>To the ende that Princes be deliuered of displeasures: and their kingdomes better gouerned: it shalbe moste sound counsell for them to be affable with all, to giue vnto all, to deale for all, &amp; to loue all: but if they determine to holde some more priuate, they ought much to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whome they admitt to their speciall fauour: because for one to be priuate in Court, it is not sufficient that the king doe choose him: but that also he be of merite and deseruing.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb n="6" facs="8"/>In giuing rewardes, princes may not alwayes escape errour, but in commending their heartes, they ought to be most certaine: for that, <hi>In this whole world there is not the like torment, as a man to haue his loue euill imployed.</hi> If Princes and great Lordes will particularly take into their fauour any of their seruaunts, they ought to be of particular deseruing: bycause, loue shall neuer be fixed: when in him that is loued, there wanteth me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. Not without cause we sayde, that it were neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie in a Prince to be indued with a good mynd and disposition, and with sound meaning and intention: bicause if the Prince be taken with imperfect and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull affection, Alas of him, and also of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that by him is gouerned, It is euill that the Prince haue no rule in feeding, in play, in drinking, in speaking, and also in spending: but it is much worse if he vse it not in his loue and affection: for it is a rule
infallible: <q>that euerie disordinate loue, bringeth with it some notable vice. It is a loue disordinate to bee carefull to gather riches, and not to haue a mynde to spend them: bicause vnto the greatnesse of Princes it appertaineth, to seeke what to spend: and not to learne to keepe audit. It is a loue disordinate, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prince to folow the direction of his owne proper will: bicause it is impossible but he should fayle to perfourme that which hee ought, that alwayes executeth his owne wilfull minde. Loue is disordinate, when the Prince imployeth his loue in fewe, being Lord of many: by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Princes in such wise ought to loue, and be boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifull vnto their priuate and fauoured seruaunts, that they disgrace not the nobles of their kingdome. Loue is disordinate, when Princes in vanities, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles do consume their times: bycause the curious go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour
<pb n="7" facs="8"/>
in such wise diuideth time betwixt him and the common wealth: that he neither wanteth for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, or hath too much to imploy in vices. Loue is disordinate, when the Prince is orgulous, quarellous, ambitious, and proude: for notwithstanding, that as a Prince they ought all to serue him: it followeth not that as a God, they shoulde adore him. Loue is disordinate, to hazarde the giuing and diuiding of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, not as euerie man deserueth, but according to the wil of him that gouerneth: for there is no equal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie vnto the prince, as it is to chastice vice, &amp; not to remunerate seruice. Loue is disordinate, when of will he taketh away frō another, that of right apperteineth not vnto him self: bicause to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> greatnes &amp; sinceritie of princes, it is iust &amp; conuenient, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in their rewardes &amp; gifts, they shew their franke liberalitie: &amp; in receiuing, they stande with all men in iustice. The case standeth thus: y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the Prince which is indued with these loues &amp; affections, may not escape many trauels, and also ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny souden assaults and perils: for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euerie disordinate affection, she her self, with her self, bringeth griefe and displeasure.</q>
Plutarche in his bookes of cōmon welth, persuadeth the Emperour Traiane, that hee hath his will at libertie, and his loue subiect to no man: for that according as hee sayeth: It little profiteth that a Prince be Lord of many kingdomes: if on the other part, he become bondman to many vices. The diuine Plato saide, that for a prince to be good, hee ought to giue his heart vnto the common wealth, his rewardes vnto such as serue him, his desires vnto the Gods, and his loue vnto his friendes, his secretes to his priuie counsell: and the time to affaires. Oh how happy were that prince, that according to this Platonicall
<pb n="8" facs="9"/>
sentence should diuide and repart his person: bicause he being diuided for all: the whole should be ioyned together, with, and for him.</p>
   <q>¶The authour applyeth all that which is sayd, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end wherfore he did speake the same.</q>
   <p>All that which we haue aboue sayde by writing, (most souereigne Prince) wee will vtter and declare by example: for according to the saying of Eschines the Philosopher, Words well spoken, do awake and reuiue the iudgements: but great and manifest exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples persuade the heart. For to leade or intice a man to be vertuous, and to do vertuous woorkes, it maketh muche to the matter, to persuade with discrete rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, &amp; sweete words: but in conclusiō, for much cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite which we giue to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which he sayth: much more is giuē to that which he doth. The Poet Homer said:
<q>that it is, a thing verie easie to write acts of great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wesse, and verie difficil to performe them. For whiche cause it is necessarie, for such as deale with princes, to shewe them by example, all which they persuade thē by writing: to the end they see most cleare, that the great and mightie deedes done by other Princes in the worldes: they want not force to performe them: but a minde to vndertake them. No Prince hath to holde of him selfe so small estimation, that he doubt to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that which another Prince hath done in time past: for after this manner, Theodosius should be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide, by the remembraunce of Seuerus: Seuerus, of Marcus Aurelius: Marcus Aurelius, of Antoninus Pius: Antoninus Pius, of Traiane: Traiane, of good Titus: Titus, of Caesar Augustus: Caesar Augustus, of Iulius Caesar: Iulius Caesar, of Scipio: Scipio, of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Marcellus: Marcus Marcellus, of Quintus Fabius:
<pb n="9" facs="9"/>
Quintus Fabius, of Alexander Magnus: and Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Magnus, of Achilles the Greeke.</q>
The heartes of these so high Princes, did not reade and inquire of the deeds of their forefathers, to feare them, but to imitate them: &amp; surely they had great reason: bicause <hi>None a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the mortal hath done any deed so glorious, that by another man may not be beautified and made better.</hi> Princes be boūd to do such and so high deedes and enterprises, that of them selues be worthy praise, and very honourable for others to folow: for the same it is not more neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie, to haue a noble minde to giue the enterprise: thē after wards to haue the aduenture, to finish the same. Plutarche saieth, that Agesilaus the Greeke said, that <hi>Fortune did neuer shew her selfe noble, but vnto a minde that was generous and noble:</hi> and surely he said most truth, bicause <hi>men lose many things, not bicause they may not attaine them, but for that, they dare not attempt them.</hi> The Prince ought to straine and enforce him self to be good, and to imitate the vertuous: since <hi>with lesse cost, mē be vertuous thē vitious, milde then ouerthwart, valiant then cowards, patient thē furious, and sober then gluttons:</hi> for the theefe doth need as despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate a minde to scale an house, as a noble minde is due to a captein that foloweth the wars. Dionysius the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, Gorgius the tyrant, Bias the tyrant, Macrino the tyrant, &amp; Catiline the tyrant: if we might commend them, and they of thē selues giue reason: they would sweare and affirme that they passed more trauell, and found thē selues in more perill in defending their ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies, then Scipio and Cato in conseruing their cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthes. Oh, what great reason, and how much occasion haue Princes to be good, and to fauour the good: since they haue authoritie to commaunde, and riches to giue: whereof if they haue skyll
<pb n="10" facs="10"/>
to take the aduauntage, with their potencie they frame them selues to be serued, and with their giftes they bring to passe to be loued. Ioyntly with this, I admonishe and also aduise Princes and great lordes, to be magnificent in their giftes, and verie attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue in their commaundements. For, notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<q>a Prince may do what he list: it is not conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient he do what he may. Although the authoritie of the prince be free, absolute, and without measure: to him it is conuenient in all thinges to vse measure and moderation: for that euery gouernement that is absolute, hath a taste or relishe of tyrannie.</q>
Many Princes haue lost thē selues by their vices which they vsed: and many more haue beene cast away by exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting their will and power: for princes in perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming all that they can, and all which they will: it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that their affection maketh them stumble: &amp; passion, their eyes to dazell. But (moste souereigne Prince) speaking more particularly, by the imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Plutarche, and Suetonius Tranquillus, I thought good to translate, compile, and to refourme the storie of the liues of tenne Romaine princes, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie moste surely to be knowen, and verie pleasant to be read. The purpose wherefore (moste mightie Prince) I haue taken so exceeding trauaile to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde this worke, is: vnto the ende my penne may aduertise, wherein my tongue with shame dismaieth to speake: for as Bias the philosopher saide: The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of princes is so greate, that of more thinges they haue to giue them to vnderstand, then to dare or presume to speake. The king Artaxerxes trauai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on a certeine daye, a man of the countrie presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him with a little water in the palme of his hand:
<pb n="11" facs="10"/>
the which water, the king receiued and dranke: and when some did murmur of that deede, and also de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract him: the king made aunswere: <hi>It is no lesse no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenesse vnto the Prince to receiue little, then to giue greate and bountifull rewardes.</hi> The philosopher Lycurgus, that was lawe giuer vnto the Lacedaemonians, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded those of his common wealthe, that they shoulde offer vnto their Gods fewe thinges in number, and not riche of value: whereof, when he was noted and also accused, made aunswere: I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund not to offer vnto the Gods fewe thinges, for that I thinke them not to deserue muche, but because all men should haue wherewith to offer: since of all men they will be serued: for in the time of Apollo, they saide vnto mee: that they had rather haue little of manie, then much of fewe. In the lawe whiche God gaue vnto the Hebrues, he was so limitted in the thinges he demaunded, and so humaine in that he commaunded: that in the order of the sacrifices which they should offer, he did ordeine and cōmaund that the poore man whiche could not offer a goate, should offer no more but of the hayre therof. In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering that Lycurgus offered vnto his Gods, iewels of small price: and that king Artaxerxes receiued of a poore man an handfull of water: and that vnto the true and liuing God, they durst offer no more but of the hayres of a Goate, giueth mee hardinesse to present this work vnto your Maiestie. (∴)</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>