<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>A., C.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103536_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12476</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103536</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>A., C.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The staffe of Christian faith : profitable to all Christians, for to arme themselues agaynst the enimies of the Gospell: and also for to knowe the antiquitie of our holy fayth, and of the true Church. Gathered out of the vvorks of the ancient doctors of the church, and of the councels, and many other doctors, vvhose names you shall see here follovving. Translated out of Frenche into English, by Iohn Brooke of Ashe next Sandvviche. With a table to finde out all that which is contayned in the booke</title>
                 <author>Brès, Guy de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 382, 10 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OVV EASIE A THING it is (gentle reader) rashly to discō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, eche one is vnto himselfe a witnesse: but how hard a thing right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to commend, few, yet the wyser, can testifie. Therefore to make any great or tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous relation of that, which of it selfe is worthy, I thinke a thing vayne and superstuous: or to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend that which in the very shew is commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, should be to bereeue thee of thy iudgement. Notwithstanding, least I should be accused and condemned of negligence, which I haue sought to shunne and auoyde, I determined priuatly, to set thy sight openly, that this booke hath bene out of the Doctors and Counselles collected carefully, composed by the authour pithilye, and by the same alledged fitly and aptlye: and not onely out of the Doctors, but out of the Popes owne Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons culled gratiously, whereby he hath not brought a Doctor agaynst a Pope, but a Pope with a Pope conferred learnedlye. This being rightly wayed and considered. I thinke there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left for the more enuious (being the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on godly, the matter their owne, the order fitte and conuenient) as an obiect to worke on theyr insatiable minde, and desire of reprehension, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they wyll seeke and runne to the manners of the author (common practises now a dayes) to search and prye ouer curiouslye, something to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimaduert and oppugne, and sore agreeued that he hath beaten them with their owne rodde, say with
<pb facs="13"/> Zeuxis contending with Parrhasius, when he had seene all, now vncouer thy sheete Parrhasius, that we may see thy worke. Yet least there shoulde growe in their mindes some vndeserued suspition, being the authour vnknowen, I will endeauour not onely to remoue, but to roote it cleane out of their entendement: and playnely affirme that which is credibly and sincerely referred to me, that he was of manners modest, of life laborious, of countenance sober, and of witte quicke, and willing to profite euery one to his power and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. Therefore as I iudge and esteeme, there is no cause for any one, nor yet for the aduersaryes to bee greeued, seeing to the one it redoundeth to his vtilitie, and the other may not complayne, that in disclosing the veritie, he paynted foorthe that which he hath worthelye deserued. Next to this is the cause of the translatour, whome thou shalte thanke, that for thy further benifite, he hath with good zeale learned the authour to talke in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue, and shewing that which before was well spoken to a fewe, to be better spoken to a great many, rendered it, copied out of the French, into thy Englishe, vulgare and natiue speache. Lastly I admonishe the to view and reade diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the cataloge of the doctors and counselles, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the authour, which I haue layde downe, to the ende thou mightest see for thy emolument what euery one hath bene, and what he hath suffred and written, and the time he florished, wishing thee to ponder the same, and loke if they haue thought any otherwyse, then truth, or fallen into any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extricable error, not redily to condemne them,
<pb facs="13"/> as the enuious doe: but to ascribe it to mans fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilitie, as christians ought: and to marke and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print the same in thy minde, not to fall into the like, nor to stay on mans sayinges, seeing as it is vsually sayde:
<q>nihil omni parte bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>um.</q> Nothing (meaning mortall thinges) is blessed or happy on euery side but to boulster and trust who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Gods mercyes, who is onely the truthe, and the phisition for euery sore. Thus much I thought good to aduertise thee (gentle re-der) of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent booke, being, as it may be sayde, in sight fayre, in matter good, in effect fructuous and godly, wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and willing thee to accepte gratefullye that which for thy pleasure hath bene penned paynefully. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Concussus, surgo. C. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>