<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Gunter, P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103564_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02395</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12526</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103564</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Gunter, P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon preached in the countie of Suffolke : before the clergie and laytie, for the discouerie and confutation of certaine strange, pernicious, and hereticall positions, publikely deliuered, held, and maintayned, touching iustification, by a certaine factious preacher o Wickam Market, in the said countie, by which, diuers, especially of the vulgar, farre and neare, were greatly seduced. With a plaine and manifest resolution of the said point, as also an answere vnto the obiections vsed and produced, to maintayne the said dangerous position. And lastly, a three-fold reflection of the text, according to the present occasion. By P. Gunter, preacher of the Word of God, in the countie of Suffolke. Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Gunter, Peter, preacher of the Word of God</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riendly Reader, (for to thee onely I bend my course, as for <hi>Zoilus</hi> I esteeme him not, <hi>Scilleos canes obdurata aure transibo,</hi> as <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> speakes, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ieron.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>I will passe by the Scillean dogges and stoppe my eares</hi>) to thee that art friendly and indifferent I bend my speech, willing to giue thee satisfaction. Thou mayest heere behold a discouery and confutation of certaine dangerous and pernicious Positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the resolution of the points, and the manifestation of the great impietie of the contrarie doctrine. But haply whilest thou beholdest this, thou wilt be distasted and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in conscience to see such opposition in the Church of God, and thou mayest begin to faint in the path of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but rouse vp thy selfe againe, let not this hinder thee, remember it is the continuall practise of the <hi>Enuious man to sow Tares in the fie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d of God: offences must needs come</hi> (saith Christ) <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.7.</note>
      <hi>but woe be to them by whom they doe come: There must</hi> (saith <hi>Paul</hi>) <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19.</note>
      <hi>be heresies euen among you, that they which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued among you may be knowne.</hi> There was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any time of the Church so happie, wherein there were
<pb facs="5"/> not some impugners of the truth, and disturbers of the peace therof, which alway ariseth principally frō these two grounds, <hi>Ignorance of the Scriptures, and arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of nature. Ignorance of the Scriptures,</hi> when wee doe not rightly vnderstand or apply the termes and phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the Scripture, therefore <hi>Pareus</hi> makes this his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Pareus sup. Ro.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Haereses ex ignoratione scripturarum nas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur,</hi> Heresies doe arise and take their being from the ignorance of the Scriptures. Againe, <hi>from arrogancie of nature,</hi> the which, as one speakes, is <hi>concordiae pestis,</hi> the very bane of peace, and ground-worke of errors and heresies, which is as <hi>Pareus</hi> speakes, when wee doe, <hi>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis apud nosmet ipsos sapere,</hi> when we haue too good an opinion of our selues, when wee are wise in our owne conceits; such a one is apt for any error, and most hard to be reclaimed: therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> sayes, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 26.12.</note> there <hi>is more hope of a foole, then of one that is wise in his owne conceit,</hi> and God by his Prophet doth denounce a woe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst these, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Isa.</hi> 5.21.</note>
      <hi>Woe vnto them that are wise in their owne eyes, and prudent in their owne sight.</hi> And what shall I now say? shall I say that both these are seated in the Author of these pernicious Positions? oh would there were no cause so to conclude! oh that large experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence did not make it too clearely manifest! for how often was he dealt withall in priuate in all louing manner againe and againe by his most intimate friends? how oft was it expressed vnto him, how dangerous and blasphemous his Positions were? how oft was it shewed vnto him, how he ought to hold them? what distinctions he was necessarily to admit, how he was to vnderstand the Scriptures in that behalfe, what great inconuenience would arise of the
<pb facs="5"/> contrary. But what was all this? alas to no purpose, no means could preuaile. For what was the vsuall reply? Tush, <hi>they had no faith,</hi> they were <hi>traitors to the blood of Christ that held the contrarie,</hi> plainly auouching this speciall doctrine was <hi>reuealed to him by prayer.</hi> What then should here be done? heere was a great extremitie, either God must be greatly dishonoured, mens soules de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, and a wider gate opened vnto hell, or else some strict course must be taken to beat downe these iniquities, to cure these disasters, and so to become a taint for euill and inflamed tongues. For as the Comedian speakes, <note place="margin">Comedian.</note>
      <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequium amicos, veritas odium parit,</hi> flatterie gets friends, truth gets nothing but hatred, a course yet vsed by some, who had rather speake against their owne conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then clearely deliuer the truth, who had rather (to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinuate the fauour of some weake vulgar) vse priuate bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and lay dispersions by allegorizing, of <hi>Sauls</hi> thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand, and <hi>Dauids</hi> ten thousand, to infame the innocent, then truely and sincerely to lay open the nocent. But it is much that grauitie should so dissemble: of these let me say with old <hi>Iacob, Into their secret let not my soule en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> for as one speakes, <hi>amicus</hi> Plato, <hi>amicus</hi> Aristoteles, <hi>sed magis amica veritas, Plato</hi> may be a friend, <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle</hi> may be a friend, but the truth must be our chiefest friend, that must be nearest vnto vs. But what I say was to bee done in the extremitie, the holy Ghost will tell vs, plainely witnessing, that <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 4.19.</note>
      <hi>wee are rather to obey God then men:</hi> but God saies <hi>he will not giue his glory to another,</hi> how much lesse then will he like to haue it beaten downe and abolished? whether is it fitte then to obey God, and so preserue his glory, or by neglect thereof to
<pb facs="6"/> please the fancies, or purchase the fauour of carnall men? alas, who so ignorant, that is not easily able to iudge of this? our Sauiour tels vs that <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.37.</note>
      <hi>he that loueth father, mother, sonne or daughter more then him, is not worthy of him:</hi> thereby intimating, that nothing ought to bee so deare to vs as the loue of God: but how doe I loue him, if I can be content to see his <hi>Honor</hi> and his <hi>Glory,</hi> yea his very <hi>Essence</hi> surprised, and yet rest silent? oh this cannot stand with a religious heart. But indeed it is much to bee deplored, that hee that hath made shew of better things, should make his mouth the organe of such impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, should giue such an offence to the church, such occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of scandall vnto the wicked, such preiudice to religion: oh that hee did see this, or that hee would humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to God for this! but if yet this will not bee, yet let me say with <hi>Ieremie, My soule shall mourne for him in secret,</hi> yea my soule shall mourne for this, that men shall preferre their owne glorie before the glory of God, a vulgar applause before Gods sacred truth: alas the vulgar are soone miscaried. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Maximus Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Foolish</hi> Psapho <hi>desirous to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonized a god, taught priuately little birds to sing,</hi> Psapho is a great god, <hi>and when he had taught them priuately to sing it, he let them flie into the woods and hills adioyning, where sounding out this note, other birds learned to sing it also, so that the hilles, woods and hedges rung no other thing but,</hi> Psapho is a great god, <hi>which when the vulgar heard, they concluded hee was a god indeed.</hi> But fie vpon these Heathenish delusions. And friendly Reader let me intreat thee to turne thy eyes from men, for they are <hi>changable, lighter then vanitie it selfe.</hi> Euen <hi>Peter</hi> may erre, and
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>Paul</hi> may be forced to <hi>reproue</hi> him, but turne thine eyes to Gods holy truth, the pure fountaine of liuing water, that is alwayes one and vnchangeable, this is that <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ierem.</hi> 6.16.</note>
      <hi>Good way, walke in it,</hi> and thou shalt be sure to finde <hi>rest vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy soule.</hi> Say to the weake offended Christian, Be not discouraged, though men be imperfect, false and <hi>erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> yet the Law of the Lord is <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 19.7.</note>
      <hi>perfect, able to conuert the soule, a sure testimony, able to giue wisedome vnto the simple,</hi> a conduct to the ioy of spirit and peace of conscience in this life, and eternall glory in the life to come. Say also to the <hi>Libertine</hi> that makes vse of this, to ingrosse sinne, and drinke in transgression, Say vnto him, that the Lord wil <hi>wound the head of his enemies,</hi> euen the hairie scalpe of them that run on in their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 11.21.</note>
      <hi>that though hand do ioyne in hand,</hi> though they thinke they may neuer so freely commit sin, yet that they <hi>shall not be vnpunished,</hi> but that God <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 11.6.</note>
      <hi>will raine vpon them snares, fire, brimstone, and stormie tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest, that this shall be their portion to drinke.</hi> So shalt thou discharge thy dutie, promote Gods truth, aduance his Glorie, beate downe sinne, take away offence, and comfort the soules of others. Which godly care the heauenly Father for his Iesus sake, deepely imprint within thee. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus, P. GVNTER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>