<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE EDWARD LORD VISCOVNT CONA∣WAY, AND ILVLTA, BARON OF RADGLEY MARSHALL OF IRELAND, AND ONE OF HIS Majesties Most Honourable Privie Councell of .</title>
           <author>Gilbert, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103154_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01750</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11882</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103154</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE EDWARD LORD VISCOVNT CONA∣WAY, AND ILVLTA, BARON OF RADGLEY MARSHALL OF IRELAND, AND ONE OF HIS Majesties Most Honourable Privie Councell of .</title>
                 <author>Gilbert, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Architectonice consolationis: or, The art of building comfort : occasioned by the death of that religious gentlewoman, Iane Gilbert; to be studied: and with all a platforme of comfort to be raised up by her husband William Gilbert Doctor in Divinity</title>
                 <author>Gilbert, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Latham (Lathum, Lautham), George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat, John 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 48, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE EDWARD LORD VISCOVNT <hi>CONA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WAY,</hi> AND <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ILVLTA,</hi> BARON OF <hi>RADGLEY</hi> MARSHALL OF <hi>IRELAND,</hi> AND ONE OF HIS Majesties Most Honourable Privie Councell of <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>May it please your Honour,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O admit this Act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordation, that 'tis full Fourteene yeares since the happy Aspect of your gracious Favour did reflect upon me, for my good both by Sea, and Land:
<pb facs="3"/>
which left in me such an Impression of the Character of your Noble and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Disposition, that to this very Day edgeth a fresh desire to take this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious (though in another respect, a sad) Opportunity to testifie my dutifull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to your Honour. It may be, this Art of Building Comfort is not so arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially, and laboriously composed, as you have heard, and was pleased to countenance some Vniversitie-Pieces of mine: there might be more oyle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed on them, to varnish the Face of their style; but this Treatise is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more Wine to comfort the Heart of the Reader. This induced me to present to your gracious Acceptation, this Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest of that Debt of Thankfulnesse, wherein both your Favours, and Deserts <hi>(tàm Arte, quàm Marte)</hi> have bound me to you: a small Earnest is sufficient to binde the greatest Contract 'twi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t a bountifull hand, and a thankfull Heart. Let this be such of my Gratitude, and not onely a Pledge of Mine, but a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Hers, (I meane my dead
<pb facs="3"/>
Wife) whose Living Thankfulnesse to God for your Favours to me, you had, though not made knowne unto you. And if your more then ordinary Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments will permit you to read over, either Her deserved Commendation: or Her Epitaph which is much too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for her worth, (both are in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning <hi>Pages)</hi> then I hope your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship will have no cause to repent the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of this Treatise. In the meane time my Experimentall knowledge, that in you the Nobilitie of Descent and Minde concurre: the Eminencie of Parts in your selfe, and Affabilitie of Dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition to others do mutually reflect each on the other: which Harmonie may well challenge this my voluntary Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as a necessary Obligation, that for ever tyes me to fixe my Devotions on Heaven, and heartily to pray for your temporall, spirituall, and eternall Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours to dispose of William Gilbert.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>