<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vpon the Life and Death of Master Henry Welby.</title>
           <author>Marmion, Shackerley</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103493_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68870</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25226.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103493</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Vpon the Life and Death of Master Henry Welby.</title>
                 <author>Marmion, Shackerley</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The phoenix of these late times: or the life of Mr. Henry Welby, Esq : who lived at his house in Grub-street forty foure yeares, and in that space, was never seene by any, aged 84. Shewing the first occasion, and the reasons thereof. Whose portracture, you may behold, as it was taken at his death. With epitaphs and elegies of the late deceased gentleman, who lyeth buried in S. Giles Church neere Criple gate, London</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Clutterbuck (Clotterbuck), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, portraits (metal cut), 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>Vpon the Life and Death of Master Henry Welby.</head>
   <l>WHat age is this we live in, that does see,</l>
   <l>And produce wonders above Antiquity?</l>
   <l>Some Nature taxe, as if our life and growth</l>
   <l>Were unto former times inferior both.</l>
   <l>Yet we saw one of late, that when he stood,</l>
   <l>He look't as he were borne before the Flood.</l>
   <l>A second, numbring dayes, as they should have</l>
   <l>No end, or did defie Death, and the Grave.</l>
   <l>A third, as if that Nature would amend,</l>
   <l>And contract what she did before extend,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="6"/>Is like a Pigmy in his height decreas'd,</l>
   <l>Who now will say that Miracles are ceas'd?</l>
   <l>Looke farther in Mens manners, you will finde</l>
   <l>As great a disproportion in the minde:</l>
   <l>We have a <hi>Welby,</hi> can himselfe immure</l>
   <l>Within his Chamber, and there live secure</l>
   <l>Forty odd yeares, and rather more, than lesse,</l>
   <l>Than <hi>Israel</hi> once did in the Wildernesse.</l>
   <l>He eate no <hi>Manna,</hi> nor no fare so good,</l>
   <l>And yet he never murmur'd at his food.</l>
   <l>Flesh he abhorr'd, and wine; he drank smal beere,</l>
   <l>Cowes Milke and water-gruell was his cheere:</l>
   <l>It was not avarice, nor hope of gaine,</l>
   <l>Nor love towards his heire, made him abstaine:</l>
   <l>He was no Sectary, no <hi>Anchorite,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Nor yet of that engagement, to invite</l>
   <l>To such a strictnesse, vaine applause to winne;</l>
   <l>Nor was it any pennance for his sin:</l>
   <l>But once upon distaste, he took an Oath,</l>
   <l>And since all mens society did loath,</l>
   <l>Which made him live inclos'd thus; yet his purse</l>
   <l>VVas open, and the poore far'd ne're the worse.</l>
   <l>He read all Bookes, and for his recreation,</l>
   <l>He used frequent Prayer, and Contemplation.</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="7"/>O who can found the thoughts that doe arise</l>
   <l>From minds so rap't, and fill'd with extasies?</l>
   <l>Thus <hi>Welby</hi> liv'd according to his vow:</l>
   <l>Whose Life to us was but a Death, and now,</l>
   <l>That he his wonted solitute may have,</l>
   <l>He is retir'd to a more silent Grave.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Shackerly Marmion.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>