<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader, grace and peace.</title>
           <author>R., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103457_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10687</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20961</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103457</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader, grace and peace.</title>
                 <author>R., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The countrie mans comfort. Or Religious recreations : fitte for all well disposed persons. Which was printed in the yeere of our Lord 1588. And since corrected, amended, and enlarged by the same author. I.R</title>
                 <author>Rhodes, John, minister of Enborne</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Boler, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Mary.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hill, Anthony</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>90 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader, <hi>grace and peace.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, in the yeere of our Lord 1588. when the Divell, Pope, and Spaniard did rage against our late Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (never to be forgotten) and this kingdome to haue both killed vs: and to possesse the land▪ and when God had so miraculously delivered vs from that invincible Navie (as they termed it) I wrote this Booke, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in it many good Songs, Ditties &amp; Carrols, for the comfort and solace of all those that are well disposed, after so miraculous deliverance from our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the Pope and Spaniards. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it happen to light into hands that are wise and learned: know this that I doe not count it so fit a booke for thee as for the Schollers of pettie Schooles the poore Coutrieman and his familie, who wil aske these vain questions, som times saying: what shall we doe in the
<pb facs="3"/>
long winter nights: how shall we passe away the time on Sundayes, what wold you haue vs doe in the Christmas Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydayes: For such haue I made this booke, wherein I shall no doubt please their merrie minds a little, for that they are naturally given to sing, if happily I may winne them to sing good things and forsake euill.</p>
   <p>And when the gun-powder Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son was found out and bewrayed: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to looke over this little booke: and finding as great cause to mooue vnto thankefulnesse now as then: I did as my leasure serued me correct &amp; amend my former labors, and added and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented them more then was in the former booke: and now haue finished the same, I offer it to the view of all well minded persons, and as for others that cannot take plaine labors in good part: I leaue them to themselues, and the rest vnto God.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The Lords poore and humble seruant,
I. R.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>