<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103998_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06737</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17182</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103998</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Italian prophecier. That is, A prognostication made for the yeere of our Lord God 1622. Practised by Antonio Magino, Professour of the Mathematickes, in the towne of Bononia, written fiue yeeres past: declaring many wonders and fearefull proceedings, wherewith the world is threatned to happen therein by warre this present yeere. With notable complaints made by diuers nations, touching the present estate of their countrey. Faithfully translated out of Italian into Dutch, and now into English</title>
                 <author>Magini, Giovanni Antonio</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 21, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>IT is well knowne to all men of great account, and Mathematicians, what the great learning and vnderstanding of the famous Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matician <hi>Anthony Magino,</hi> Professour of the Mathematickes, in <hi>Bononia</hi> in <hi>Lombardie,</hi> as also that hee hath particularly and generally made many Prophesies by the aspects of the Planets, or course of the Heauens, and also shewed vnto mee many things, which now at this day I finde to be true, in respect of these reasons, and many others the like. I was moued to set forth some of his Kalenders, which by his sonne <hi>Fabians</hi> meanes came to my hands, with other things, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter these shall come to light. This learned Astronomer, by reason of the disease of the Stone, was very sickly, and many times as he was in his passion, he was desired by some Cardinall, Duke, or Earle, that visited him to set forth a Kalender or Prophesie, which sometimes was very painefull vnto him, for these causes: he determined as soone as he was somewhat eased of his paine, to effect the same, and made a Kalender beginning at <hi>anno 1617.</hi> and continuing to <hi>anno 1630.</hi> which now foure yeares one after another hath beene Printed, and for the most part found to be true: for these causes I thought good to Translate the same out of Italian, and to Print it in Dutch, and now into English.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>