<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST REVE∣rend Father in God, the Lord Arch-Bishop of
Canterbury his Grace, and to the rest of the Reuerend Lords Spirituall, and
the right honourable the Lords Temporal, as also to the most Worthy and
Religious Knights and Burgesses of the house of Com∣mons, all now
assembled in this happy Parlia∣ment; I. G. an vnworthy Minister of the
Church, presu∣meth to dedicate this euidence of his repentance, and
declaration of his best endeuours for the Church of England.</title>
           <author>Gee, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103001_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01576</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11701</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103001</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST REVE∣rend Father in God, the Lord Arch-Bishop of
Canterbury his Grace, and to the rest of the Reuerend Lords Spirituall, and
the right honourable the Lords Temporal, as also to the most Worthy and
Religious Knights and Burgesses of the house of Com∣mons, all now
assembled in this happy Parlia∣ment; I. G. an vnworthy Minister of the
Church, presu∣meth to dedicate this euidence of his repentance, and
declaration of his best endeuours for the Church of England.</title>
                 <author>Gee, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The foot out of the snare : with a detection of sundry late practices and impostures of the priests and Iesuits in England. VVhereunto is added a catalogue of such bookes as in this authors knowledge haue been vented within two yeeres last past in London, by the priests and their agents. By Iohn Gee, Master of Arts, of Exon-Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Gee, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 99, 9 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, the Lord Arch-Bishop of
Canterbury his Grace, and to the rest of the Reuerend Lords Spirituall, and
the right honourable the Lords Temporal, as also to the most Worthy and
Religious Knights and Burgesses of the house of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, all now
assembled in this happy Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I. G. an vnworthy Minister of the
Church, presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to dedicate this euidence of his repentance, and
declaration of his best endeuours for the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the safetie of a <hi>Ship,</hi> to haue good
<hi>Pilots;</hi> the <hi>strength</hi> of a <hi>Palace,</hi> to haue sure
<hi>Pillars;</hi> the <hi>securitie</hi> of the <hi>bodie,</hi> to haue
<hi>cleare eyes;</hi> and safe-guard of <hi>sheepe,</hi> to haue vigilant
<hi>Shepheards:</hi> So it is the<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>safety</hi> of a
<hi>Countrey,</hi> and <hi>safegard</hi> of a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> to haue many
wise and watchfull <hi>Counsellors.</hi> Wee neuer had greater reason to
blesse GOD, then in contemplation of the present time, in the perfect
vision of so many principall <hi>Planets</hi> now met together in happy
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction:</hi> such a <hi>King,</hi> such a <hi>Prince,</hi> such
<hi>Honourable Senators,</hi> such <hi>Assistants.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pro.</note>
      <hi>The eare that heareth you,
blesseth you: and the eye that seeth you, giues witnesse to you. The
blessing of Her that was ready to perish, is come vpon you.</hi> Vnder your
shadow wee are much refreshed. The God of blessing dispose of your
Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saile. <hi>Wee waite for you, as for the raine: and our mouthes are
opened wide, as for the latter raine.</hi> Ita quisque vt audit, mouetur.</p>
   <p>I need not, neither were it lesse then boldnesse and
presumption in me (Right honourable) to suggest vnto you, of what weight
and consequence those af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires are, which his Maiesty hath been
graciously pleased to referre to your ioynt consideration and aduice:
neither need I repeat, how deeply you are all interessed<pb facs="3"/>herein:
you reuerend <hi>Bishops,</hi> by your sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred profession; you the Noble
<hi>Baronage</hi> of this Realme, by your military honour, alwaies prest and
ready for the defence of Religion and of this Kingdom, against open Inuaders,
or secret vnderminers; and you the Representatiue <hi>Body of the
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> in regard of the libertie of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect; but most of all,
the free course of the Gospel without impeachment: by whom is not onely
represented, but also actua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; the desire and zeale of the body of this
kingdom, being a people true-harted, and feruent toward God in the puritie of
his worship; towards our <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> in the stedfastnesse of
obedience; and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Lawes,</hi> in wishes and hopes that they
shall stream forth <hi>motu naturali,</hi> in their owne course, without
diuersion or obstruction.</p>
   <p>But you being at this time imployed about so weighty affaires,
how may I, the meanest of the <hi>sonnes of my Mother,</hi> presume to
interrupt you? Are there not <hi>the Chariots of Israel, and the horsemen
of the same?</hi> Doe the Lords <hi>battailes</hi> want<pb facs="4"/>supply?
whence should it be expected but from them? But I may say, with
<hi>Epicte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus: Your hand euer holdeth an equall ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and your Sun
shineth alike on the poore and rich.</hi> It may be, <hi>one Scout</hi> may
vpon occasion heare &amp; know what an whole Army hath no present notice
of.</p>
   <p>True it is, (and why should I now be ashamed to manifest it
to such an Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly?) <hi>An euill and scandalous report is gone forth
of mee,</hi> in regard I was the man that was present at the Iesuite
<hi>Drury</hi> his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at the <hi>Black-Fryers.</hi> I was the same day
in the fore-noone at the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at <hi>Pauls-Crosse:</hi> and lighting
vpon some Popish company at dinner, they were much magnifying the said
<hi>Drury,</hi> who was to preach to them in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone. The ample report
which they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded him, preferring him far beyond any of the Preachers of our
Church, and depressing and vilifying the Sermons at
<hi>Pauls-Crosse,</hi> in regard of him, whetted my desire to heare his
said Sermon: to which I was conducted by one <hi>Medcalfe</hi> a
<hi>Priest.</hi> This being heard of by my Lord<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Arch-bishop
of Canterbury</hi> his <hi>Grace,</hi> hee sent for mee within few daies
after; and being before him, found mee inclining to their side. I layd open
my selfe vnto him and confessed I had some scruples in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.
Wherupon it pleased his <hi>Grace</hi> to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford me his holy counsell and
monition: which had that good effect, that albeit my foot was stept into the
<hi>Babylonian</hi> pit, yet I often meditated of his Fatherly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions.
Som other speeches I receiued from his Domestique Chaplains, D.
<hi>Goad</hi> and D. <hi>Featly:</hi> for which I shall be bound euer to pray
for them: their words left <hi>aculeos et stimulos; Vade et nè pecca
amplius, &amp;c.</hi> piercing me the more, being recorded in a publicke
narration: which, my check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conscience did iustly take for an
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement to conuict me, &amp; a Trumpet to reduce me. <hi>Like the
Prodigall, I now returne home with a Peccaui</hi> in my heart, mouth and pen,
to God and our blessed Mother the Church of <hi>England:</hi> to both I
say, <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caui contra coelum et te.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The reason why I presumed to present these lines to your
view, and offer them<pb facs="5"/>to your hands, seemeth to me iust,
because sincere; and excusable, because in some sort necessary,
in that the vastnesse of my fault requireth, forasmuch as from my
acquaintance on the left side, I can expect little lesse then indignation
and machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations against mee by them; whom, partly by my relinquishment of
them, but much more by disclosing some of their proceedings, I am like to
prouoke in a high degree: it behoueth me therefore to chuse such Refuge, as
may protect mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their malice. I haue touched (in a manner) nothing
else but the behauiour of the Priests; whereto, I might haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
somewhat of my owne knowledge, concerning the insinuations &amp;
incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vsed by those of that stamp, who professe physick:
Who, whatsoeuer they doe vnto the bodies, infuse into the mindes of many
the Kings Subiects, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter distempers; whereby those pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents tongues
distaste the wholsome food of our Church, and their hearts are
stric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with <hi>antipathy</hi> against our present State. But these
things I thought fitter for<pb facs="5"/>your Wisdomes to cure, then for my
weaknesse to declare; my intent in this Treatise, hauing beene to act the
part of vnmasking the vailed fraud of the Iesuits &amp; Priests: wherin if
you somtimes dislike the stile, condemn not me for a botcher: for, their
Stories I alter not a stitch, but giue you thē lapt vp in their own
clouts.</p>
   <p>If the forme and phrase I vse in other places bee
distastfull, as either too sharp, or too light and Ironicall for one of
my profession; let my matter bee my Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, that draweth mee thereunto;
trus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that I may be excused, if I sometime light my candle at the
Torch of <hi>Elias,</hi> when he sindged and smoaked out <hi>Baals
Priests</hi> from the nest of the Sanctuary. I iest but at their
iesting, that haue made a iest of God, and of his blessed Saints in
heauen, by casting vpon their most pure and glorious faces, the cloud, nay,
the dirt and dung of vgly, vnsauory, ridiculous Fables: whereat the sounder
Christians are scandalized, wherewith the weaker are deluded &amp;
captiuated in superstition, and the very <hi>Iewes &amp; Heathen</hi> are
driuen<pb facs="6"/>further off from listning vnto the true &amp; sacred
Mysteries of Christian Religion. For surely, no small mischiefe or
danger is it vnto Truth, to haue her precious gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eeked out with patches
of false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and, vpon pretence of imbellish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to bee dawbed ouer
with the cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-embrodery of cogging Impostures.</p>
   <p>In regard of my own particular; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I hope, I shall regaine
that good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I haue lost, and no longer bee censured by my
friends and others, as at all wauering, inclining and warping to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their
side: yet withall, you haue the Character of mine hart, toward the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke
good of our Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. I say no more, but God giue you
vnderstanding in all things. <hi>Ride on with your honours; and, because of
the Word of Truth,</hi> bee courageous and stout <hi>Nehemiahs. Such a man as
I, flee? Nehem.</hi> 6.11. The deaw of Gods grace bee vpon you and your
children. And thus, with my vncessant prayers for you, I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>The most humble seruant of you all, to bee
commanded in the Lord, IOHN GEE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>