<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The Bysshoppe of London to all persons, and curates, within his dioces of London.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1555</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103088_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B00958</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3285.2</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103088</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The Bysshoppe of London to all persons, and curates, within his dioces of London.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Homelies sette forth by the righte reuerende father in God, Edmunde Byshop of London, not onely promised before in his booke, intituled, A necessary doctrine, but also now of late adioyned, and added therevnto, to be read within his diocesse of London, of all persons, vycars, and curates, vnto theyr parishioners, vpon sondayes, &amp; holydayes</title>
                 <author>Bonner, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cawood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1555</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>73, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface_to_parsons_and_curates_in_the_diocese_of_London">
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ The Bysshoppe of London to all persons, and curates, within his dioces of London.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch as the people of my dioces, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng within your seueral cures, &amp; charge, do (as in dede of reason they maye) loke for to haue at theyr pastours hand, or at the least way, by his prouision, &amp; meane, good instruction, and teachinge, especiallye howe to serue and please God, and how also otherwyse to do their dutie, as to any one of them in theyr degre doth appertayne. And forasmuch also as there is not now a dayes that multitude, and plenteth of preachers, whiche in tymes past hath ben, and by Gods grace, hereafter shalbe. And fynallye, for that euery one of you in your owne person, is not able to discharge the office of preaching, which many good folke do great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wyshe, and desyre ye could, and woulde. Therfore desyrynge to haue somethyng done onward, til God of his goodnes prouide something better, I haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with my chapleyns, &amp; frendes, to haue these Homelies prynted, that ye may haue somewhat to instruct, and teache your flocke withall, requyrynge, and charginge euerye one of you, that diligentlye, vpon the sondayes, and holydayes, ye reade to youre flocke, frutefully, and deliberately, one of the said Homelies. And thus fare you well.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Geuen at my house in London, <date>the fyrste daye of Iuly. M.D.LV.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>