<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An advertisement of Mons. the KING.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103517_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02324</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12455</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103517</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An advertisement of Mons. the KING.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A collection of some modern epistles of Monsieur de Balzac. Carefully translated out of French. Being the fourth and last volume</title>
                 <author>Balzac, Jean-Louis Guez, seigneur de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 <publisher>Bowman, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Crooke, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, Leonard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sergier, Richard 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>46, 249, 9 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="advertisement">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>An advertisement of Mons. the <hi>KING.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nderstanding of the bad <hi>intelligence,</hi> which by the unhappinesse of the times hath grown between <hi>Monsieur de Balzac,</hi> and the <hi>Author</hi> of this book, we could not but partake of the discontents of sundry <hi>honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> personages; and judging it very reasonable, that men that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually doe good services to the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and from whom it should expect better yet hereafter, should be divided in wills and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. <hi>We</hi> have endeavoured to dispell those <hi>clouds</hi> by the evidence
<pb facs="8"/>
of <hi>truth</hi>; the businesse was not very difficult for <hi>Vs,</hi> being we were to deale on the one side, with a <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi> man, who by the rule of his profession, takes a glory in despoyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himselfe of all <hi>interests,</hi> and to desire the love of all the world; on the other side, with a man of a <hi>franke</hi> and noble <hi>Courage,</hi> whose discretion guided him to put a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the faults of men, and the unhappinesse of the age.</p>
   <p>So that <hi>We</hi> thought fit, to tye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the <hi>knot</hi> of friendship, which (by accident) had been untied. It is commonly an easier taske to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile old friends, than to make new ones. Having then happily effected that businesse, <hi>We</hi> thought that good men, who are ever well affected to the sweetnesse of peace, would gladly receive some <hi>authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
testimonies of their good <hi>intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,</hi> and for this purpose, <hi>We</hi> have got <hi>interchangeable</hi> letters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their own hands, that confirme the sincerity of their hearts, for to present them to the publike, which cannot be distastfull to any, but to those that are pleased with nothing but <hi>disorders</hi> and <hi>contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>