<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Booke-seller, to the READER.</title>
           <author>Marriot, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103214_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01851</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11993</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103214</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Booke-seller, to the READER.</title>
                 <author>Marriot, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Poems. By Robert Gomersall</title>
                 <author>Gomersall, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 16, 12, 70, 16, 81, 15 pages, 2 leaves of plates, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="bookseller_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Booke-seller, to the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O praise the worke, were to set my selfe to sale, since the greater its worth is, the more is my benefit, &amp; not the Authors: He good man may have an Ayery, but I a reall profit. An Ayery one, I terme it, for I judge others by my selfe, who cannot feed by praises. But thus much I must needs say of it, that if ever it were worthy the reading, now the worth of it is mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied, the whole being perused by the Author, and some, not deformed peices added, which as they mend the bulke, so they take nothing from the Dignity of the <hi>Poem.</hi> But for this I put my selfe upon my Countrey. Thus farre the Authour thought it not unfit, to please thee and his youth: from hence forward, you must expect
<pb facs="3"/>
nothing from him, but what shall relish of a bearded and austere Devotion. And this, I trust will be no small incitement to thy approbatiō of the worke since it is the last: All men we know, delight in <hi>Benjamin.</hi> One thing I must not forget to acquaint thee with; Some men, (that would be wise without booke,) have excepted against a passage in <hi>Sforza,</hi> concerning <hi>Gale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>azzoes</hi> revealing his wives counsells to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, as a thing beyond Probability, or Poetry: but it shewes that they are short of History, for let them read almost the first leafe of <hi>Guicci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardin,</hi> or the eighth book of <hi>Comminés,</hi> they shall there find what they carpe at here, and that this fond opennesse, was <hi>Galeazzo's,</hi> and not the Authors weaknesse: I would say somewhat of the <hi>Levite</hi> too, but it needs not, seeing the Authours blasphemy is turned into the Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the ignorant Detractor. But I beginne to talke rather like a Maker, then a seller of Bookes: I have nothing now more to adde, but this, love the Authour, and me for bringing you acquainted.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Thine</hi> Iohn Marriot.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>