<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honourable Sir Jhon Langley knight, Lorde Maior of London, &amp; the other worshipfull Maisters, Wardeins and whole assistaunts of the Mistery of Goldsmithrie, Dianis Gray, a member of the same, wisheth vertuous prosperitie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103396_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02056</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12201</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103396</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honourable Sir Jhon Langley knight, Lorde Maior of London, &amp; the other worshipfull Maisters, Wardeins and whole assistaunts of the Mistery of Goldsmithrie, Dianis Gray, a member of the same, wisheth vertuous prosperitie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The store-house of breuitie in vvoorkes of arithemetike : containyng aswell the soundrie partes of the science in whole and broken numbers, with the rules of proportion, furthered to profitable vse: as also sunderie rules of breuitie of worke, of rare, pleasaunte, and commodious effecte, set forthe by Dionis Gray of London goldsmith. 1577</title>
                 <author>Gray, Dionis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 <distributor>Harrison (Harison), John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Norton, William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 79, 72-88, 87-118 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the right honourable Sir <hi>Jhon Langley knight, Lorde Maior</hi> of London, &amp; the other worshipfull Maisters,</hi> Wardeins and whole assistaunts of the <hi>Mistery of Goldsmithrie, Dianis</hi> Gray, a member of the same, wisheth vertuous prosperitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I had conference with my self, right honourable and worshipfull, of the great vtilitie, delectation and estimation, procured to euery Commonweale, by the sciences <hi>Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall,</hi> and how muche more vnto those coū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tries, wherein knowledge and vnderstādyng of the saied sciences doeth florishe &amp; abounde ouer and aboue other the same wātyng. And also notyng the diligence of sondrie authors of moste Nations in their vulgare langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in writyng of the premises, to profite their countries. I of good will not inferiour
<pb facs="5"/> to any other, to profite the Commonweale, whereof I am a member, so farre forthe as with moste diligence and vnderstandyng, by the goodnes of God I might haue habilitie: I was moued thereby to employe some en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour, wherein my good will in part might appeare, treatyng of the premisses, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out greate hope to preferre many thynges, in euery of the saied Sciences, as maie bee founde of rare and commodious effecte, for moste vocations and degrees of people. And for that Arithmetique is the grounde, direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and producer of the moste parte of suche Haruest, as in the fertile fieldes of the saied sciences is to bee reaped. I haue therefore framed this rude discourse of the Arte of numberyng, the first fruites of my good wil, dedicated to your wisedomes, containyng as well the sondrie partes of the saied science, in whole and broken Numbers, the same ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliyng to seuerall vses, for furtheraunce of common vtilitie, as also many and sonderie Rules of breuetie of woorke, no lesse profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then rare to bee seen in any authour, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishe or other. Besechyng your wisedomes, to haue more regarde to my good meanyng herein, then either to my boldnesse, or rude
<pb facs="5"/> order in penning of the same: &amp; as the effecte of my diligence, may procure cōtentation, or benefite to any vocation in the cōmonweale, so I maie haue cause, not onely to reioyce of my trauaile, but also incouraged to further other workes of greater consequence, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in assisted by the goodnes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> almighty, who increase your honour and worshippes with grace, wisedome, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie felicitie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>