<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADMONITION to the Christian Rea∣der, declaring the diffe∣rence betwixt the repro∣bate and true Christian in their life and death; and like∣wise of the vse and be∣nefit of this Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103183_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10825</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21097</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103183</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADMONITION to the Christian Rea∣der, declaring the diffe∣rence betwixt the repro∣bate and true Christian in their life and death; and like∣wise of the vse and be∣nefit of this Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The crovvne of life : Containing the combate betwixt the flesh and the spirit, with meditations and prayers in time of afflictions, directing to liue christianly, and die blessedly. Also a comfortable and heauenly dialogue betweene Christ and the soule. Written to comfort the afflicted consciences of all those that groane vnder the burthen of their sinnes</title>
                 <author>Robertson, Bartholomew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64, 392, that is 390, 12, 71, that is 81, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="16"/>
   <head>AN ADMONITION to the Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, declaring the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate and true Christian in their life and death; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise of the vse and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of this Booke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is true <hi>(deare Brother)</hi> that all the worde of God compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth nought else, but that wee should <hi>liue as his children, according vnto his word, and dye Christs brethren, and faithfull seruants.</hi> Now ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue compiled the most
<pb facs="16"/>
      <hi>spirituall doctrine,</hi> first, of a <hi>chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian life</hi>; and secondly▪ of a <hi>blessed death.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Of the which, the <hi>man</hi> that <hi>saw God had his greatest regard▪ Lord</hi>▪ saith he,<note place="margin">Psal. 90.12.</note>
      <hi>teach me to number my daies, that I may apply my heart vnto wisedome.</hi> So did also ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Eccles. 7.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>What<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oeuer thou takest in hand, r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mber thy end, and thou shal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uer do amisse.</hi> For what is a christian <hi>life,</hi> but a continuall meditation on Gods <hi>fauour,</hi> a life in true <hi>repentance</hi>▪ exercised in <hi>faith,</hi> keeping of a good <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> &amp; so it cannot go astray; and that a man should neuer suffer himselfe to be in such <hi>euill state,</hi> wherein he might not <hi>bee blessed,</hi> yea, and <hi>happily dye.</hi> What is it then to <hi>dye blessedly</hi>? Euen this, when a Christian not onely consid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>reth that hee is <hi>mortall,</hi> and neuer free from death, but also is resolued that hee must depart hence, and that he shall bee <hi>inheritour of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting saluation.</hi> This is that high
<pb facs="17"/>
      <hi>Science</hi> and <hi>Arte</hi> which <hi>Moses</hi> speake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h of, which is not else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where to bee had but in <hi>Gods word</hi>▪ As if he should haue said, <hi>Teach vs to rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mber that we shall dye, to the end wee may bee wise,</hi> that by thy holy Spirit, and grace, and practise of thy holy word, wee may so liue that wee may haue <hi>life euerlasting.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This holy Art to dye <hi>aright</hi> was neuer knowen by <hi>Phyloso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> and as yet is hid from all those that know not <hi>Iesus Christ the Redeemer.</hi> Indeed <hi>Cicero</hi> ges<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed at it,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Orat. pro. Publ. Quin.</hi>
      </note> where hee saith, <hi>Vita turpis ne morti quid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>estae lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum relinquit</hi>; that is, An <hi>honest life</hi> goeth before an <hi>honourable de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>th.</hi> Yet there is an vnspeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e difference, <hi>Inter v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>am ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestam &amp; Christianam, mortem honest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>m &amp; Christianam seue salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>arem</hi>; that is, Betweene an <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable life</hi> and a <hi>Christian life,</hi> betweene an <hi>honourable death</hi> and a <hi>Christian and sauing death. Augustus Caesar</hi> desired euery
<pb facs="17"/>
day <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, to wit, that he might <hi>dye well,</hi> but hee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood not by what meanes, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he <hi>hunted for name, fame,</hi> and <hi>renown:</hi> and euen so it was with the rest of the <hi>Ethickes</hi> and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, they knew that they should dye, but neuer apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the christian vertues <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ope:</hi> but onely <hi>infirmitie, corruption,</hi> and <hi>distresse,</hi> and so departed, as hee speaketh of <hi>Tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Virg. Aen.</hi>
      </note>
      <q>Vita{que} cum g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>u fugit indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata sub vmbras.</q>
   </p>
   <p>And therefore there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing contained in their <hi>records</hi> but <hi>miserie</hi> and <hi>complaint,</hi> of the <hi>shortnesse of life,</hi> as that, <hi>Totum quod est homo, miseria:</hi> that is, <hi>All that a man is, is nothing but wretchednesse.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>King <hi>Xerxes</hi> beholding his <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> and seeing the number, and <hi>considering</hi> their <hi>man-hoode</hi> and <hi>courage, wept bitterly,</hi> that after an hundred yeares, there should none of them <hi>be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ft aliue.</hi> And
<pb facs="18"/>
great <hi>Aristotle, Omnium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erribili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um terribilissimum est mors. That death of all terrible and dreadfull things, was the most terrible and powerfull.</hi> Sundrie of them haue sought and busied themselues for a remedie against the feare and terrour of <hi>death,</hi> but could not come farther, then to make it familier vnto them (<hi>as it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</hi>) that they might meete it when it approached; As <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> saith,<note place="margin">
         <hi>De nat. quaest.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Effice mortem tibi cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione familiarem, vt, si ita sors tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerit poss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>buiam ire:</hi> that is, <hi>Make thy selfe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>quainted with death, that when it commeth thou mayest meate it.</hi> Hence is it that the <hi>Aegipt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ns</hi> custome was in banqueting and greatest mirth, to cause the image of <hi>death</hi> to be borne, with this inscription, <hi>In hun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> intuens,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Herod. in enter.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>bibe &amp; fis animo hilari, post mortem enim talis e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>is:</hi> that is, <hi>Loe heere, drinke and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> glad, and remember alwayes that death shall make thee like this pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.</hi> And this was all the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="18"/>
preparation to a foreseene death.</p>
   <p>And so <hi>Agag</hi> the King of the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> when <hi>Samuell</hi> was to cut him in peeces, said,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.32.</note>
      <hi>true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the bitternesse of death is past,</hi> as if he would say, <hi>I must once dye, rather now then another time, it must once bee done, and then it is gone.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>secure Soule,</hi> at her last time grudgeth and fretteth both against <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Heauen,</hi> for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her vtmost endeauours and trauell, she can come no farther then this, <hi>Ego tenta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us rebus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus nihil inuenio in quo quiescam. After all my manifolde tryals and searches, I cannot finde any one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hing whereon to rest and repose my selfe.</hi> And when she percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the certaintie of death, she breakes out into these words, <hi>O te dementem &amp; oblitum fragilitatis t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ae,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Sen. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. quaest.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>si nunc timeas mortem cum to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>at. Foole hast thou not remembred thy weaknes, that now thou art af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of death when it thundr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>th.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="19"/>And as concerning eternall life, <hi>Plato, Cicero,</hi> and others <hi>vex</hi> and <hi>greeue</hi> themselues: for they acknowledge that mans <hi>Soule</hi> is <hi>immortall,</hi> but yet neuer dreamed of the <hi>resurrection</hi> of the <hi>body.</hi> Yea, and <hi>Cicero</hi> ioyeth in this, that once hee should come to the <hi>assembly of Soules,</hi> but whither, he did not know. <hi>O praeclarum diem,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cic. de sen.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>m ad illum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimarum concilium coetumque pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ficiscar, &amp; cum e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> hac turba &amp; colluuione de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>edam.</hi> That is, <hi>O happy day, in the which I shall take my way to the assemblie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent of Soules, &amp; shall depart from this vile and mischeeuous world.</hi> And seeing they lacked faith, the <hi>earnest of the spirit,</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> and <hi>constant confidence in God,</hi> they held <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hemselues vp with foolish magnanimitie, full of distrust and doubt. For that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt Romane Oratour could speake of the <hi>immortality of the Soule,</hi> but farther light &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge had he not, <hi>Quod si hic erro
<pb facs="19"/>
quod hominum animas immortales esse credo, libenter erro,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cic. de s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>n.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>non mihi hunc errorem quo delector dum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo ex torqueri volo.</hi> That is, <hi>If in this poynt Ierre, because I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the immortalitie of the Soule, I am an heretike with all my hart, the which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rroneous opinion so long as I breathe no man shall be able to root out of mine heart, or constrain me to forsake.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And farther, did no <hi>Ethicke</hi> come, neither had more <hi>prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> and <hi>resolution</hi> against <hi>deaths approaching,</hi> euen as the <hi>Hypocrites</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> in these our <hi>dayes,</hi> which haue no faith in <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> our Redeemer: And therefore all these <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>profane</hi> creatures, must vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand that their condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion shall bee the greater in the last day, then those <hi>Ethick Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers:</hi> for they haue a greater occasion, and more ample mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by the light which now shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth abroad by the <hi>Gospell</hi>; yet they will not <hi>rectifie</hi> their liues
<pb facs="20"/>
by <hi>true repentance</hi> conformable thereto. And therefore they haue their <hi>noluerunt,</hi> for so saith <hi>Christ,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Matth. 10.14.15.</note>
      <hi>whosouer shall not receiue you, nor heare your words, when ye depart out of that house, or that city shake off the dust of your feet.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Truely I say vnto you, <hi>it shall bee easier for them of the land of Sodome and Gomorrha in the day of iudgdement, then for that Citie. He that hath eares to heare let him heare.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reu 2.11.</note> And therefore aboue all things, we must consider of the difference betweene a <hi>Christian</hi> mans <hi>life</hi> and <hi>conuersation,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>repentance,</hi> and the life of the <hi>Infidell, Hypocrite,</hi> and <hi>Vngodly</hi>; to the end we may feele and sensibly apprehend <hi>Gods eternall and euerlasting mercy</hi> bestowed vpon vs Christians: that we may (I say) <hi>seriously</hi> and <hi>earnestly</hi> meditate night &amp; day vpon the goodnesse and fauour of our God in this specialty shewed vnto vs.<note place="margin">Psal. 1.</note>
   </p>
   <p>As for the <hi>first,</hi> the <hi>Hypocrite</hi>
      <pb facs="20"/>
hath no familiarity with <hi>God,</hi> nor <hi>sight of heauen:</hi> but vseth the precious gifts of God after the same manner, as doth the <hi>swine</hi> the <hi>akornes</hi> vnder the <hi>tree,</hi> being neuer mindefull that there is a <hi>God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> heauen,</hi> nor giuing him thankes for his temporall <hi>food, health, welfare</hi> and <hi>felicitie,</hi> much lesse meditating vpon that <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall food,</hi> but he taketh his <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure</hi> and <hi>fleshlydelight,</hi> remaining on the earth: yea, true it is, that vnreasonable beasts, haue a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life then such a reasonable creature, although hee be crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to Gods simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
   <p>But contrarily, the <hi>Christian, faithfull</hi> and <hi>hopefull,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth God his <hi>Creator,</hi> reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in him, vseth all his <hi>gifts</hi> with <hi>thankefulnesse,</hi> loueth God which hath done all things so <hi>wisely</hi> &amp; <hi>wonderously well,</hi> vseth himselfe in those both night &amp; day commeth to the Lord his God and <hi>brayeth</hi> after <hi>eternall life.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="21"/>
      <hi>Secondly,</hi> the <hi>Infidell (it may bee)</hi> hath heard that God will punish an <hi>vngodly</hi> and <hi>wicked life,</hi> with a <hi>wretched</hi> and <hi>misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble death.</hi> Yet neuer giueth place to penitency and contrition vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>till death liueth still in sinne, yet can say with the Pharisie, <hi>I thanke thee, O my God, I am not like th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> man,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Luk. 18.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>an extortioner, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iust, adulterer, or euen as this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican:</hi> and therefore (<hi>it may bee</hi>) concludeth hee shall haue <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happines,</hi> because of his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward politicall demeanour, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee hath not <hi>faith in Christ,</hi> the <hi>art to die aright,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>hearty repentance,</hi> nor anie testimony of <hi>redemption,</hi> no sweet <hi>hope</hi> that God will accept of him, much lesse is he exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the preseruation of <hi>faith,</hi> and a <hi>good conscience to the end.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 19.</note>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>Hypocrite</hi> while hee is in good temporary estate will brag of <hi>Chris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ianitie,</hi> will bee a <hi>teacher</hi> of <hi>others</hi> to learne <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> vnder the <hi>crosse,</hi> will boast
<pb facs="21"/>
of his perseuerance in time of <hi>aduersity,</hi> but <hi>when one deepe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth another,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 42.7.</note>
      <hi>by the noyse of the water-sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uts, and all the waues &amp; floud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of God are gone ouer him</hi>; then falleth all his courage, then is heauen out of his way, and the earth is sunke vnder him, there is no attention to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but hee beginnes to sing <hi>Gedeons song with impatiency,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iudg. 6.13.</note>
      <hi>Ah my Lord, if the Lord bee with vs, why then is all this come vpon vs.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But the <hi>faithfull</hi> and <hi>Christian heart</hi> maketh account, that not by <hi>prosperitie</hi> and <hi>wealth,</hi> but by much <hi>aduersitie</hi> and many <hi>cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note>
      <hi>he must enter into the Kingdom of heauen:</hi> &amp; therfore if it be well with him, he thanketh God for his bountie towards him, is no way secure, but <hi>serueth the Lord in feare, &amp; reioyceth in trembling.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 2.11.</note> And when as it is otherwise with him, then hee saith with holy <hi>Iob, shall wee receiue good at the hand of God, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> not receiue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill?</hi> and layeth stedfast hold on
<pb facs="22"/>
the <hi>crosse,</hi> and hath <hi>Dauids melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi> in his <hi>mouth: My soule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> the Lord,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal▪ 130. 6.7.</note>
      <hi>more than the morning watch watcheth for the morning.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I will wait on the Lord, for with the Lord is <hi>mercy,</hi> &amp; with him is <hi>great redemption.</hi> And if it shall be very heauy, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding hee will say with faithfull <hi>Paul,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note>
      <hi>God is faithfull, &amp; will not suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r mee to bee tempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue that I am able, but will euen giue the issue with the tentation,</hi> that I may bee able to beare it. And if flesh and bloud bee ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous, and would not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly vndergoe the <hi>crosse,</hi> yet he beleeueth, and is perswaded that <hi>neither life nor death,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.39.</note> &amp;c. nor <hi>any other creature shall be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> able to separate him from the loue of God, which is in Christ Iesus our Lord; for to him that feareth God, all things worke tog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ther for the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Fourthly,</hi> the chîldren of this world remembring that death shall separate them from their
<pb facs="22"/>
goods, <hi>honours, wiues, children, lands</hi> and <hi>possessions,</hi> and that they shall goe <hi>naked</hi> out of this <hi>world</hi> crie out, <hi>O death, how bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is thy remembran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e to a man that liueth at rest in his possessions,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eccl. 41.1.</note>
      <hi>vnto the man that hath nothing to vex him, and that hath prosperity in all things,</hi> and say with the Emperour <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>uerus,</hi> I haue beene great, and now it profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: but contrarily, the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Soule</hi> doth chuse the good <hi>part,</hi> which shall not bee taken away from it, and euery minute i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> ready to let slip these transi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie things, and saith with that holy <hi>King, Lord lift vp the light of thy countenance vpon me,</hi> thou hast giuen me more ioy of hart,<note place="margin">Psal. 4 6.7.</note> then they haue had when their wheat and wine did abound</p>
   <p>The <hi>vnprepared Hip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>te</hi> when hee falleth <hi>ficke,</hi> bethinkes him of nothing else than how his <hi>sicknesse</hi> came to him, what <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>holes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>me foode</hi> he had eate, by what meanes he got <hi>this drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="23"/>
surfeit,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 10.30</note> where he <hi>catched that cold,</hi> or too <hi>much heat,</hi> is <hi>vnquiet</hi> and <hi>impati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nt</hi> that such mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance should <hi>betide him.</hi> But the <hi>faithfull man knoweth that all the haires of his head are numbred, and that the pretious gift of his health cannot be taken away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Lords speciall pleasure,</hi> and therefore imputeth all vnto <hi>Sin, My owne wickednesse hath corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted mee,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ierem. 2.19</note>
      <hi>and my turnings backe haue reproued mee. I know there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and behold it, that it is an euill thing, and bitter, that I haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken the Lord my God, and that his feare was not in mee.</hi> And he beginneth with <hi>Paule</hi> to say: <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r this cause am I weake and sicke,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.30.31.32.</note>
      <hi>for if I would iudge my selfe, I should not bee iudged of thee:</hi> but when <hi>I am iudged of thee, I am chastised of the Lord, because I should not be condemned with the world</hi>; whereby hee is taught <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> and amendment of <hi>Life.</hi> The <hi>Wicked</hi> and <hi>Infidells</hi> doe neuer worke vpon their
<pb facs="23"/>
      <hi>Soules</hi> vntill they be <hi>sicke</hi>; then <hi>first</hi> begin they to bee <hi>holie,</hi> and before that time, all their dayes they haue beene <hi>enemies to the Word and Ministerie.</hi> But now must the Preacher be sent for, and with <hi>sugred speeches</hi> must be entreated for <hi>consolation, &amp;c.</hi> But the <hi>faithfull Christian</hi> is eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie minute in preparation to a <hi>blessed death,</hi> and neuer suffereth himselfe to fall into that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and behauior of life wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he would not die, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can say with constant magnanimitie, <hi>Come Lord Iesus my Ioy and Comforter, euery houre I attend thee, come when thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i't, I am readie.</hi> And when ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so little sicknesse ouertakes him, then saith hee (with <hi>mirth of heart) Now let Thou thie Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant depart in peace.</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Luk.</note> The <hi>Infidel</hi> and <hi>Reprobate,</hi> whenas he lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth counsell and helpe in <hi>sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nsse,</hi> hath recourse to <hi>Sathan, Witches,</hi> and to <hi>vnlawfull meanes,</hi> and saith most desperately, <hi>If
<pb facs="24"/>
God will not helpe, then helpe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi> But the Christian beleeuer knoweth, that the Lord hath forbidden all such inconuenient meanes, and vnderstandeth <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans policie</hi> and craft,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.3</note> that it is not for his good, but that his soule should separate it selfe from the true SAVIOVR; <hi>Yea,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1 Sam. 28.8</note>
      <hi>hee is assured it is an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times better to die in constant inuocation on Gods name, then to liue vnder protection of Sathan:</hi> and therefore vseth such meanes as the Lord hath appoynted, hee will not tempt the <hi>Lord his God,</hi> he will not seeke after the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie of such as God hath not promised a <hi>blessing vnto,</hi> but wil say,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.2.</note>
      <hi>Here am I Lord Iesus, let it be vnto me according to thy will, if thou wilt thou canst make me clean,</hi> but,<note place="margin">Psal. 40.8.</note> if not, <hi>Loe here I am, thy will be done, I desire to do thy good wil, O God, yea, thy lawe is within my heart.</hi> And to be short, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>this world</hi> neuer haue memorie on Gods word, (<hi>for
<pb facs="24"/>
they haue not learned</hi>) and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comfort themselues by their <hi>baptisme,</hi> nor that <hi>excellent Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper,</hi> but cause some <hi>scurrilous History</hi> and false fable to be read vnto them, with such foolishnesse, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may dispossesse the thoughts of death, and quiet their hearts; but the <hi>faithful</hi> one is <hi>acquainted and exercised in gods word, diuideth</hi> that word of <hi>truth,</hi> puts a difference betwixt <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Gospell,</hi> reioyceth in the couenant of <hi>mercie</hi> in his <hi>baptisme,</hi> seeketh <hi>comfort</hi> in the other <hi>Sacrament,</hi> wherewith he was <hi>fed</hi> and <hi>refreshed,</hi> and so ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth new <hi>trust</hi> and <hi>ioye</hi> from <hi>time</hi> to <hi>time,</hi> momentanie hee esteemeth, but as they are he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> counteth noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng of any <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y</hi> or <hi>pleasure,</hi> but that which is in <hi>Christ his red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>emer,</hi> that heauenly <hi>life,</hi> and is glad of that blessed houre. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>condly,</hi> how different is their acceptation and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of death: for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="25"/>
seeing it by euident experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that he must dye as others do, complaineth of mans great miserie, and of the shortnesse of this <hi>sweet</hi> and <hi>pleasant life</hi>; but maketh not preparation by <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> therevnto, but <hi>fretteth against God,</hi> inueigheth against his <hi>iustice,</hi> because man hath but a short time giuen him <hi>to liue.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now the <hi>true Christian</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the daily examples of humane <hi>infirmitie and corruption, groaneth</hi> because of that our first fall, lamenteth for his <hi>sinnes</hi> and <hi>wickednesse,</hi> for the which the diuine punishment ceaseth not vpon vs,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.22.23.24.41.5 6.</note> lifteth vp his <hi>heart</hi> with his <hi>hands vnto God</hi> in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, who heareth his voyce, and hideth not his <hi>eare</hi> at his <hi>breathing and crye,</hi>
      <note place="margin">57.</note> who draweth neere in the day that hee calleth vpon him, and say<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h, <hi>feare not,</hi> the Lord, I say, who pleadeth the cause of his <hi>Soule,</hi> who <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemeth his life,</hi> and will say, <hi>I will beare the wrath of the Lord,
<pb facs="25"/>
because I haue sinned against him, vntill he pleade my cause, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iudgement for mee.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mich. 7.9.</note> Hee will bring me forth to the light, and I shall behold his <hi>righteo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>snesse, O Lord thou art wise, and thy word is truth.</hi> Yea,<note place="margin">Psal. 119.</note> he attributeth the true honour vnto <hi>God,</hi> for hee doth all things <hi>iustly</hi> and <hi>well,</hi> and so prepareth himselfe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry houre of the day to <hi>a blessed departure.</hi> Againe, the <hi>Hypocrite</hi> when his heart meditateth on death, is afraid for the terrible <hi>visage</hi> and <hi>countenance thereof</hi>; for flesh and bloud can doe no lesse, for death is our enemie, and killeth vs all, <hi>but the hopefull christian</hi> openeth <hi>the eyes of faith,</hi> looketh vpon death not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law, but according to the Gospell, comforts him in his <hi>Lord Iesus Christ,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.11.</note> who hath changed the bitternes of death, and made it a sweet sleepe, and beleeueth constantly that hee shall not <hi>dye,</hi> but <hi>quietly rest,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Lord shall awake him vp by
<pb facs="26"/>
      <hi>the shout of the Arch-angell, and trumpet of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The <hi>wretched Hypocrite</hi> when hee considereth how that death shall after a most fearefull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>apprehend him,</hi> and make him an <hi>ill fau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ured Corps,</hi> which must be hidden from the eyes, and cast in the <hi>bosome of the cold Earth</hi>: Then beginneth hee to <hi>sorrow</hi> and <hi>weepe,</hi> his courage is <hi>gone,</hi> and can doe no more than king <hi>X<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rxes,</hi> who hearing men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of Earth, did say, <hi>Missahaec faciamus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Hie. in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyh.</note>
      <hi>ne{que} tristiis rerum mentionem faciamus, cum iucunda in manibus habeamus: Away with these things, for they are sorrowfull, and let vs to our iollitie and mirth.</hi> But the <hi>religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Christian</hi> proceedeth, <hi>plus vltra, a great way further,</hi> bidds feare, adue; looketh through the terrour of death, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the graue; he passeth not for the <hi>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rible dissolution of his bodie,</hi> neyther that he shall be corrupt, and rot in the earth;
<pb facs="26"/>
for he seeth a great deale fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how in the last day he shal come forth beautifull, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, and be made like the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious bodie of his <hi>Sauiour Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us Christ.</hi> Besides this, the <hi>Wicked and Prophane</hi> bethinkes him selfe on his death, and conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that once he must die, and that he cannot chuse: and here h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s wits faile him, and in this <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>gent and strait,</hi> he knoweth not whether to turne him, to what way he should betake him, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he hoysteth vp courage, plucketh vp <hi>a good heart,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f it were once done, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>at debt payd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o nature, then were it ouer. But the <hi>godlie S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ule</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fteneth not to temporary mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie, ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ither relieth on the <hi>fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>shly courage and arme,</hi> but vpon the consolation of the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie spirit,</hi> which dwelleth in him, which hee hath tasted by true faith,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.7.</note> which passeth all <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding,</hi> which also wil keep his hart and mind though <hi>Iesus Christ to eternall Life.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="27"/>Besides, the <hi>Infidell</hi> when he feeles death comming, is at his wits end, hath no counsel, that is, no <hi>faith,</hi> no <hi>hope,</hi> yea no <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne word to anchor vpon,</hi> no confidence to rest on how hee may depart from hence, but is r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>plenished with <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging tumult</hi> within himselfe; neuer casteth his eyes on the great <hi>Almightie God.</hi> But on the contrarie, the <hi>righteous Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian</hi> hath fraught himselfe with <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>hope,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 8.73.</note> and with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakeable <hi>groanes,</hi> waiting for the adoption, to wit, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>on of our <hi>bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ies,</hi> to the which he ioineth the true word of God, which cannot deceiue, giueth it place and roome in his heart, and saith powerfully and gladly,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.12.</note>
      <hi>Thou Lord Iesus art the light of the world; he that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Thee, and keepeth thy Word, shall not walke in darknesse, but haue the light of Life.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now againe, the <hi>Wicked, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling,</hi> and <hi>counterfeit Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> when he is vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r the power
<pb facs="27"/>
of death complaineth that he is forsaken, all his <hi>friends, kinsmen,</hi> and <hi>brethren,</hi> doo stand from him, and none will helpe. But the <hi>sparke</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> in the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mans heart, saith, <hi>Lord, whom haue I in heauen, but Thee;</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ps. 73.25.26.</note>
      <hi>and there is none vpon earth that I desire besides Thee, although my flesh and my heart fayle, God is the strength of my heart, and my porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for euer:</hi> for he knoweth that God giueth onely helpe from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rouble;<note place="margin">Ps. 60.11.</note>
      <hi>for vaine is the helpe of Man.</hi> Through God I shall do valiantly, for he it is that shall tread downe my enemies; for hee builds and God onely, and that if hee bee with him, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be against him for he hath the <hi>holie Trinitie</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in his heart, and manie <hi>holie Angells</hi> at his sicke bed at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for his <hi>Soule,</hi> and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to carrie it into <hi>Abrahams b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>me.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now when the <hi>Infidell</hi> doth heare that his <hi>Soule</hi> is <hi>immortall,</hi> &amp; that after this life there shall
<pb facs="28"/>
be another, wherein <hi>the blessed of the Father inherit the Kingdome prepared for them from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. 25.34.</note>
      <hi>and that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked shall goe into euerlasting pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment,</hi> then he trembleth &amp; quaketh, and would wish it were vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rue, and desireth that he might neuer rise againe: for his misbeleeuing heart doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct him, that if it be so, he is <hi>eternally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ondemned,</hi> and there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fore he wisheth that he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beene borne. But <hi>the true childe of God</hi> reioyc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th from his very heart, that there is <hi>another life prepared for him,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 5.9.</note>
      <hi>and he shall be saued from the wrath to come, and therefore sighes to be dissolued,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Phil. 1.2 3.</note>
      <hi>and to be with Christ, which is far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>; and that this wretched life might be shortly cut off, <hi>that the eternall</hi> and <hi>euerlasting</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ght <hi>beginne:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 5.15.</note> for his expectation is constant and sure, wherby he is assured of a better life to come, vnto the which hee was <hi>redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meed.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>By such and sundry more
<pb facs="28"/>
      <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>titheses</hi> and oppositions may bee easily seene the difference betwixt both the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death</hi> of the <hi>faithfull</hi> and <hi>Infidell</hi>: and therefore wee should daily and hourely consider, and neuer be contented vntill then, that wee haue <hi>Iesus Christ our Redeemer &amp; Sauiour dwelling in vs, by a true and liuely faith,</hi> accounting him our greatest treasure &amp; goods, placing all our ioy and comfort in him; and that with diligent <hi>prayer,</hi> and constant <hi>meditation</hi> by <hi>faith</hi> &amp; <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>holy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> we may euer loue that <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ternal life,</hi> aboue this <hi>temporall,</hi> bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to <hi>sinne</hi> from our harts, take pleasure in <hi>righteousnesse,</hi> learne to know a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ight the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery of this sinnefull life, neglect the pomp and traine of this world, haue inward de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ire and constant purpose after the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly mansions, <hi>loue the Lord Iesus Christ with all our s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>lesmind and strength, and daily thirst for his second comming,</hi> perseuering in a <hi>Christian calling,</hi> and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="29"/>
at all times to make a <hi>happy departure from this vale of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And this is that <hi>heauenly</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to a <hi>blessed death,</hi> by the which we are distinguished and separated from the misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing <hi>Ethicke, Turke</hi> and <hi>Iew,</hi> and from the <hi>disobydient hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite</hi> and <hi>children of this world</hi>; of the which there are a great number <hi>alas</hi> on whom the <hi>Sun of righteousnesse hath not shined,</hi> but sit as yet in darknesse, and in the shade of <hi>death,</hi> haue nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heard, nor yet can speake of <hi>Christ,</hi> indeede some might haue heard, but with the deafe <hi>adder</hi> they shut their eares at the voyce of the <hi>Inchanter.</hi> Others doe heare <hi>sermons,</hi> but yet did neuer know <hi>Christ for their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour and Redeemer,</hi> because the Word was not mixt with <hi>faith</hi> in the <hi>heare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s,</hi> such are good <hi>lip-Christians,</hi> but their harts are far from him, they boast of faith, but declare it not by their workes, and talke of <hi>eternall
<pb facs="29"/>
life:</hi> but will not learne the way to come thither.</p>
   <p>And if thou wouldest (<hi>gentle Reader</hi>) be taught aright, then must thou often <hi>read diligently, heare, and meditate vpon God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Word, exercise thy selfe daily in it, and liue according thereunto</hi>; for now there is (<hi>praised be God</hi>) the <hi>holy Scriptures</hi> in euery mans hand, and sundry and diuers comfortable and <hi>holy bookes</hi> out of that pure <hi>Fountaine</hi> which <hi>holy Fathers</hi> haue penned, by the which thou maist be taught <hi>profitable doctrine, liuely faith,</hi> &amp; <hi>holy admonitions for a Christian life and blessed death,</hi> of the which Writers, some are some what <hi>obscure</hi> for the Simple-ones, and full of <hi>disputations</hi> and <hi>logicall discourses.</hi> And to ease thee of them I haue here set downe a plaine <hi>Treatise</hi> for thy instruction, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ter my long <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience</hi> and <hi>visitation</hi> of the <hi>sicke, distr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssed,</hi> and <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ulted by S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tan, tryall of crosses in aduersities,</hi> and <hi>sense of the sting of death.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="30"/>
being long exercised of my owne proofe, I do now publish vnto thee for the benefit of <hi>gods Church,</hi> wherevnto I was much importuned by many <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>religious persons,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>I was much holpen in this Worke, by that reuerend Father</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus Molle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, <hi>Preacher at</hi> Gorli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>z <hi>in</hi> Silesia; <hi>whose worthy works are well knowne.</hi>
      </note> entreating mee to set forth these <hi>comfortable rules,</hi> hauing had so long tryall. Which I did still intend, but was hitherto hindred (<hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>than</hi> doubtlesse enuying the <hi>benefite</hi> and <hi>publication</hi> thereof) and therefore I the most vnworthy of all <hi>Christs seruants,</hi> doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce onely in <hi>Gods mercy,</hi> and say with <hi>Paul,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10.</note>
      <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> I, but the grace of God which was with mee, hath caused these to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>me to light, trusting it shall tend to the praise and glorie of God, benefite and weale of his Church, and to be a spur to euery priuate man vnto a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an life and holy death</hi>: for it is the meaner and weaker sort that it is written, to their <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dification</hi> and <hi>saluation.</hi> For it often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth, that sundry in a <hi>strange Countrie</hi> cannot haue the vse of <hi>Preachers,</hi> neither yet in <hi>warfare,</hi>
      <pb facs="30"/>
nor <hi>sailing,</hi> nor yet <hi>at home in the time of plague and pestilence</hi> can they haue frequent society with the <hi>men of God,</hi> to bee taught by them. And there are men where no <hi>plantation of the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>spel is,</hi> sigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ning for the word of <hi>grace, comfort,</hi> and <hi>admonition.</hi> In these and the like defects, this little <hi>Manuell</hi> can supply the place of a <hi>Friend,</hi> to speake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that we be not hindred in our <hi>Christian course,</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly go foward, that through the mercy of <hi>God</hi> we may make a <hi>blessed departure, and glad good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night from this world</hi>; which our <hi>good</hi> and <hi>gracious God</hi> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, for his owne <hi>mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> sake,</hi> when it shall please him to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate vs from this <hi>Hadradrimmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> and <hi>vale</hi> of miserie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <pb facs="31"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="31"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>