<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To him that is wearie and laden.</title>
           <author>Hayward, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103943_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02846</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12986</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103943</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To him that is wearie and laden.</title>
                 <author>Hayward, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The strong helper, offering to beare euery mans burthen. Or, A treatise, teaching in all troubles how to cast our burden vpon God : but chiefly deliuering infallible grounds of comfort for quieting of troubled consciences. By Iohn Haivvard</title>
                 <author>Hayward, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Beale, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Welby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 611, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To him that is wearie and laden.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ALOMON</hi> in the Prouerbs affirmeth, that <hi>he that is full despiseth a hunnie combe.</hi> And one wiser then <hi>Salomon</hi> telleth vs in the Gospell, that <hi>the whole haue no neede of the Phisition:</hi> Idlely therefore should I offer my labour in this treatise to them that are full, and liue at ease, who bearing no burden, or in their strength not feeling what they beare, would reiect my offer as a mocke, &amp; say vnto me, <hi>Brach ia da lasso potius pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda natanti,</hi> offer your hand to him that is ready to sinke in the sloud, we haue
<pb facs="6"/>
no neede, we sit safe vpon the shore.</p>
   <p>If these mens securitie be sound, I wish it may be durable vnto them: and as they haue no desire vnto, so I wish they may neuer stand in neede of the counsell conteined in this booke: this I wish them out of loue, though (out of iudgement) e know, if they belong to <hi>Christ,</hi> the tim will come, when they must beare a crosse, and follow him.</p>
   <p>But with hope of better acceptation, I offer my counsell here following vnto thee, that see<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>est the burden that thou bearest, and gronest vnder the burden that thou feelest. <hi>Salomon</hi> in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named place telleth vs, that <hi>to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry soule euery bitter thing is sweete</hi> And the Lord <hi>Iesus</hi> affirmeth <hi>the sicke</hi> to stand in neede of the Phisitions helpe. Thy burden maketh thee as fainting la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer to long for releese, and the crumes of Gods mercy, easing thy ouercharged soule, would be acceptable to thee: and the paine of thy diseased spirit, more
<pb facs="6"/>
sicke of thy tentation, then of a burning feauer, maketh thee desirous of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions helpe, thou criest in thy griefe, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus succurrite lesis,</hi> helpe my greeued estate, and the offer and assurance of helpe and health cannot but bee ioyfull vnto thee.</p>
   <p>If thy greefe and wearines be occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, by any troubles of this life, if it grow from any secular &amp; worldly cause, I haue reduced all such burdens vnto fower heades. Because either it is some want in our worldly estate, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is the burden and trouble of the multitude: or, if wee bee that way well stored, it is some trouble domesticall and neare vnto vs, either in our selues or in our house habitation or kinred▪ or if we haue peace in our habitation, ioy in our kinred, friends and seruants, with life and health as we desire, then there is some more remoued person, or more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued accident, that is the cause of greese care and feare vnto vs: or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>f a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
<pb facs="7"/>
aswell as at home, and among strangers aswell as among friends and neighbours, we liue without disturbance, yet we often finde difficulties in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our callings, or we meete with op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, and are wronged with mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, &amp; are euill rewarded for our well deseruing. Within the compasse of one of these foure heads fall all such secular and worldly burdens, and in the first place, I haue giuen aduice concerning these: perhaps not altogether such as some wise men, well seene and traded in worldly causes would giue, but surely such as an honest man should giue, and such as he must obserue, that looketh to obtaine ease and helpe from God.</p>
   <p>If thy trouble and greefe be of another kinde, if thy burden be spirituall, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e whole busines lieth more directly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and thee, and either as an honest man thou art greeued that thou canst not serue him as thou shouldest, or so humbled that thou art greeued that thou
<pb facs="7"/>
hast sinned against him as thou shouldest not, and fearest punishment for that sin: these troubles I haue reduced to two heades, for either the lustes of our flesh fighting against our soules, doe crosse vs in the waies of trueth and righteousnes, so that we cannot doe the good we would, and the euill we woud not, that we doe: and our desires being as the desires of the children of light, our deedes become as the deedes of the sonnes of darknes. Or else, hauing in time of our securitie, giuen way vnto our owne lusts, vnto the worlds allurements, and to Satans temptations, our sinnes are called to remembrance, are set in order against vs, with full mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festation of the wickednes of them, &amp; of all that wrath that they haue kindled ni heauen, and of all that punishment that they haue deserued in hell, to the incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible terror of our conscience. Vnder these two heades of the lustes of the flesh, and accusing thoughts, of the dominion
<pb facs="8"/>
of sinne, and the reward of sinne, fall all those spirituall burdens, that are heauie to the honest minde and to the humbled spirit. And of these I haue giuen aduice in the second place, that if it happen to be last learned, yet it may be longest remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred.</p>
   <p>And because the burden of accusing thoughts is euen as the gates of hell: for it is true that Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> saith. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter multiples humanae animae tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationes, among the manifold tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of the soule</hi> of man, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numberable troubles of afflictions, <hi>Nulla est maior quam conscienti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> delicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, there is none greater then the conscience of our sinnes.</hi> (Hee might haue said, none like it, none equall vnto it) for in other troubles, which are in a sort without vs, and striue to breake in vpon the heart, the troubled man (saith <hi>Gregorie) Ingressus in interiora mentis penetrali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, entering in into</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>the closet of his heart,</hi> there calleth vpon God where no man seeth: yea also he shutteth the dore of his heart against these assailing troubles, &amp; keepeth peace within. <hi>But malae conscientiae tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationem perferens, in arcano cordis, deum non inuenit: He that indureth this tribulation of an euill consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> of a wounded conscience still accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, <hi>findeth not God in the secret of his heart,</hi> hath not that free, as a retiring place, where quietly he may conser with God: but the plague beginneth within his heart, and the fire is kindled in the mouth of the spring, where the liuing waters of comfort should flow.</p>
   <p>Therefore in that argument I haue laboured to be more full, and not onely in a direct path haue led the afflicted sinner to see his sinne to bee pardonable, and himselfe to be allowed, yea comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to craue forgiuenes of it, and God also bound by promise to grant it: which
<pb facs="9"/>
he will doe, and (hauing promised) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not denie to doe, if we seeke it aright and may doe without any impeachment of his holy and seuere iustice, hauing receiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>d full satisfaction in the death and sacrifice of his Sonne. But because the old serpent is subtile, and the poore sinner is weake, and that cunning craftsmaster of all ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and snares, doeth sophistically frame many dangerous arguments, and putteth them into the minde and mouth of the affrighted and distempered sinner, making him ouer wittie to disclaime his part in God, and his inheritance in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and ouer confident in his feare, and ouer resolute in his doubting, so to driue him (if it might bee, and which the diuel doeth most desire) into finall despaire; therefore haue I at large answered those arguments out of the word of God, and with the sword of the spirit I haue eat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunder the cords of those snaring obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which the enemie had bound more
<pb facs="9"/>
fast and close then were the cordes of <hi>Gordius:</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> haue indeuoured to doe this in a plaine and familiar stile.</p>
   <p>Others dedicate their workes to hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable patrons, because they are worthy of honorable patronage: I haue no such opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of mine, I offer my labour, as a lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing seruice vnto thee. They seeke a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, I seeke a reader: not one to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance or commend what is written, but one that might profit by that which I haue written: and therefore I present it to thee, that art wearie and laden, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with my heartie praier vnto God for thee, that it may be (by Gods bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing) a meanes of thy refreshing: intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thee to read it thorough: &amp; againe to read all that part that concerneth the last burden which is the burden of accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing thoughts, to thee the most heauie. Learne thou to depend vpon God▪ to feare him, and to abstaine from sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e, &amp; he will be vnto thee a Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb facs="10"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="10"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="11"/>
and a God of comfort. Vnto whose mercy in Iesus Christ I commend thee, taking my leaue this 21. of <hi>Ianuary.</hi> From my house in <hi>Wool-church</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord
IOHN HAIVVARD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>