<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Right VVor∣shipfull Master Iohn Hayward. Maior: And the Worshipfull Iu∣rates his Brethren: And the whole Communalti of the Towne and Libertie of Fa∣uersham.</title>
           <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103581_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09386</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19683</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103581</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Right VVor∣shipfull Master Iohn Hayward. Maior: And the Worshipfull Iu∣rates his Brethren: And the whole Communalti of the Towne and Libertie of Fa∣uersham.</title>
                 <author>Tuke, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Christian and plaine treatise of the manner and order of predestination : and of the largenes of Gods grace. First written in Latine by that reuerend and faithfull seruant of God, Master William Perkins, late preacher of the word in Cambridge. And carefully translated into English by Francis Cacot, and Thomas Tuke</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Burby, Cuthbert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                            <distributor>Clarke (Clerke), Martin</distributor>
                            <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>94, 188 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_note">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶ To the Right <hi>VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull Master Iohn Hayward.</hi> Maior: And the Worshipfull <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates his Brethren: And the whole</hi> Communalti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of the Towne and Libertie of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersham.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, as many other wholsome and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly doctrines grounded vpō the word of God, haue beene and are to this day contradicted and impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: euen so it fareth with the diuine and deepe doctrine of Gods Predestination; a doctrine not more heauenly, then whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, nor more commodious, then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, &amp; yet as heauenly &amp; as commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dions,


<pb facs="6"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="7"/>
as any doctrine whatsoeuer, which the Scriptures do affoord. The Pelagians held, that God predestinated men to life or death, as he did foresee that they would by their naturall free will receiue or reiect grace offered. They taught, that it was in mans power to beleeue, or not to beleeue: they placed the causes of saluation in men themselues out of God, and held, that the Elect might fall from grace and perish.</p>
   <p>Others hold, that albeit the Lord ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth some of his meere mercy without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of any thing in them, that yet he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteth those which are reiected, because he did foresee that they would reiect his grace offered vnto them in the Gospell. Some Vbiquitaries hold, that <hi>Adams</hi> fall came to passe without Gods decree, or any ordination of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>: secondly, that no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God dependeth vpon his sample will, concerning the saluation of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or the reiection of the Reprobate: thirdly, that God doth vtterly nill the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>y: fourthly, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate may bee conuerted and saued: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>ly, that Christ dyed for the reprobates,


<pb facs="7"/>
and that it is the purpose and will of God simply, that all men without exception should be saued. Some do subiect Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto Gods eternall decree, but not Reprobation. Others, putting no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene Reprobation and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, do thinke, as God doth passe by some men of his meere pleasure, that he doth in like sort damne them of his meere will and pleasure, whereas indeed sinne is the cause why men are damned. Many of the Romish synagogue do teach, that men are elected for their foreseene faith, and meritorious works. And it is the common opinion of all Papists, that the Elect can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be certaine and sure of their election, vnlesse it be extraordinarily by some spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall reuelation, and singular priuiledge. Many also there are, which would not haue this doctrine publickly taught by the Minister; but without good reason. For first, as the Minister must not search the secrets of God which are not reuealed, so he must not suppresse or hide that which is reuealed. For things <hi>Reuealed, belong to</hi>
      <note place="margin">Deu. 29. 29.</note>
      <hi>vs and to our children for euer,</hi> as <hi>Moses</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth.


<pb facs="8"/>
Therefore as we may not search in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to those things which God will haue kept secret, so we may in no wise be wholly ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of those things which he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto vs. But this doctrine of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destination, is very plentifully and perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuously reuealed and deliuered vnto vs in the Scriptures. Secondly, as the word of God omitteth nothing which is neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be knowne, touching the saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our soules, so wee must know, that it teacheth nothing but that which is profitable, and worthy to be learned of all. For that speach of <hi>Paul</hi> to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes is true of all the writings of the Prophets and Apostles also, <hi>VVhatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer things were written, were written for</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 4</note>
      <hi>our learning.</hi> But the word of God doth teach this doctrine of Election and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, as is euident by many places therein: therefore it is necessary and fit to be taught of the Minister, and to be learned of the people. Thirdly, it is the duetie of all faithfull Ministers to teach all the counsell of God, as <hi>Paul</hi> sayth <note place="margin">Act. 20. 27.</note> hee did: but Predestination is a part


<pb facs="8"/>
of Gods counsell: therefore it ought to bee deliuered of vs vnto the people of God; alwayes remembring, that wee applie our selues to your capacities, and teach it orderly (as occasion serueth) keeping our selues in all sobrietie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the limits of the Word. Fourthly, Christ commaundeth the Gospell to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <note place="margin">Mark. 10. 15.</note> to euery creature: but this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine belongeth to the Gospell, and therefore is to bee preached vnto the vnlearned, as to the learned. Lastly, all Ministers are bound to keepe back nothing which is profitable, but to shew <note place="margin">Act. 20 20.</note> it as <hi>Paul</hi> did: But the doctrine of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destination is very profitable. For first, it letteth vs see the omnisciencie, the omnipotencie, the soueraignetie, and immutable nature of God. Secondly, it serueth to increase and confirme our faith and hope, concerning the eternall felicitie of our soules and bodyes; seeing it is not founded vpon our selues, or vpon any sandie foundation, but vpon the constant and vnchangeable good pleasure of God. Thirdly, it teacheth vs not to wonder at


<pb facs="9"/>
the small number of beleeuers, and at the hardnesse and blindnesse of many mens hearts and minds. For it sheweth, that God hath elected but a fewe, and hath <note place="margin">Math. 20. 16.</note> passed by many, leauing them vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and deliuering them vp into the hands of the Diuell. Fourthly, it serueth to strengthen and comfort vs in all affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and to arme vs against all the fiery darts of the Diuell, and the fury of his lims. For it sheweth, that nothing can separate vs frō the loue of God, and that all things <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 28, 39.</note> worke for the best vnto them that loue God, euen vnto them that are called of his purpose. All stormes and waues of woe shall passe ouer, and in the end we shall rest in the quiet hauen of euerlasting hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse. Fiftly, this doctrine stayeth vs from taking offence at the Apostacy of many professors: for it sheweth vs, that all is not gold which glisters, and that some stand for a time, and some stand fast for euer. <hi>If they had been of vs</hi> (sayth <hi>Iohn) they should haue continued with vs.</hi> Sixtly, it tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Iohn 2. 19.</note> vs to acknowledge Gods singular goodnesse towards vs, who of his meere


<pb facs="9"/>
good will toward vs, hath elected vs vnto eternall life, and the fruition of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall glory in the heauens. Seuenthly, it serueth to teach vs humility, and to beate downe the pride of our harts. For it shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that Gods grace, and not our good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, is the originary cause of our welfare and saluation. The cause, which mooued God to choose vs rather then many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, was not our foreseene preparations, or meritoriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> works, but his owne loue, and free good will toward vs. Lastly, (to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> sundry vses which might be made of this one doctrine) it teacheth vs to ascribe the glory of our saluation to God alone, and to walke thankefully before him, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifesting the gratitude of our hearts by our religious, righteous, and sober liues. To conclude, some are so far out of loue with this doctrine, that they can scarce with patience indure to heare it spoken of. And many licencious and prophane persons do very wickedly abuse it, to take vnto themselues liberty of lasci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>us and loose <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. For (say they) if I be ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>ed, I cannot be damned, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="10"/>
if damnation be my destiny, I can neuer be saued: And therefore it skilleth not how I liue; for if God haue appointed me to be saued, I shall be saued, though I do iust nothing: and it he haue determined that I shall be damned, I shall neuer es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape it, though I liue neuer so well. For Gods decree is constant, his appointment shall stand, whosoeuer sayth nay to it. But these men forget, that God doth predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate men as well to vse the meanes, as to atteine vnto the end. As he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a man to liue, so he hath appoynted the same man to vse those meanes which preserue life, as meate, drinke, rest, recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, labour, phisicke. Euen so, as hee hath appoynted a man to be saued, hee hath appoynted him to vse the meanes, and to walke in the way of saluation, as to bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue: and therefore the scripture saith, <hi>So many as were ordeined to euerlasting life beleeued, Act.</hi> 13 48. And <hi>Paul</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, that those God doth call, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> bee hath predestinated, and iustifieth those <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> doth effectually call, before he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> them. And in his Epistle to the


<pb facs="10"/>
Ephesians he teacheth, that (as God hath chosen vs vnto life eternall, so) he hath <note place="margin">Ephes. 1. 4.</note> also chosen vs in Christ, <hi>that we should be holy, and without blame before him in loue:</hi> and that as hee hath ordeyned vs vnto saluation, so hee hath <hi>created vs in Christ</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ephes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 10.</note>
      <hi>Iesus vnto good works, which hee hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined that wee should walke in them.</hi> As the Scripture teacheth vs that God hath ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vs vnto saluation: so it doth also teach vs, that hee sent his Sonne to saue vs. As God had determined that Christ should not dye in his infancie (as the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent declared) so hee did appoynt his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in lawe <hi>Ioseph</hi> to take hym and his Mother, and to flye into Egypt, when <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 2. 13.</note> sought to destroy him. By which wee see, that as GOD hath predestined the end, so hee hath also predestined the way and meanes thereunto. Hee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that desireth to be saued, must vse the meanes which God hath appointed. His damnation may not without cause be feared, who following the sway of his carnall affections, contemneth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth the meanes of grace, and will not <note place="margin">1. Sam, 2 25.</note>
      <pb facs="11"/>
walke in the way which leadeth vnto glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But wee (Beloued) reiecting all the fansies and fantastike inuentions of man, must rectifie our iudgements by the rule of Gods word, and with discreet diligence and sobrietie we ought to labour for the true knowledge and right vnderstanding of this celestiall and solacious doctrine of Gods eternall Predestination; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> doctrine not so profound as profitable, and not so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>bstruse and intricate, as many doe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine. A notable furtherance hereunto this treatise following will affoord; penned pithily, concisely, and perspicuously by a very learned and iudicious Diuine. Now (my Brethren) amōgst many other things which belong to this doctrine, there be two things which I do commend to your Christian consideration. First, the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Gods elect and adopted chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Secondly, the notes of Election vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to saluation, and the practise of those things, whereby a man may come to be in his conscience soundly perswaded, that he is a chosen vessell predestinated to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. For the first; Many and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent


<pb facs="11"/>
are the prerogatiues and immunities, wherewith the Elect are priuiledged and adorned: therefore the <hi>Psalmist</hi> saith, <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things are spoken of thee, O thou Citie of</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal, 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 3.</note>
      <hi>God.</hi> And yet as glorious and numerous as they be, they are not easily discerned and acknowledged of the world: first, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause their disgrace is common and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, by reason of the spitefull and inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate malice of the Serpent and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eed, whereby it commeth to passe, that the faithfull in all ages haue acted a part lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or shorter, in a dolefull tragedy vpon the stage of the world, so as that of all men they haue alway for the most part seemed most miserable, and least respected of man, and priuiledged of God. Secondly, because sundry slips and sinnes haue bin obserued in them. Thirdly, the vpright <note place="margin">Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 27.</note> man is such an abomination to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, as that through his cankered spite, his spitefull and rancorous hatred, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not behold and fansie his sweet and louely condition. Fourthly, the principall orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Godly are darke and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, as the <hi>Psalmist</hi> saith, <hi>The Kings daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 45. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>3.</note>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> all glorious within;</hi> and their outward estate is vsually obscure, course, and rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; not much vnlike to the Curtaines of the Tabernacle, whose outwarde coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings were of Goates haire, Rams skins, and Badgers, but the inward were of fine twined linnen, blue silke, purple &amp; skarlet, with the most exquisite embroydering of <note place="margin">Exod. 26</note> the Cherubins vpon them.</p>
   <p>The World, vnto Gods Children is as a Step-mother, and may be tearmed Gods Schoole-house, in which hee tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vp his Children as Schollers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the crosse, often correcting them with his rod of affliction. Whence it is, that the world accounts them infortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and beeing vnable to iudge of colours, through the dimnesse of her sight, thee considereth and commendeth none but such as are light, though they weare and lose their brightnesse, whiles shee is poaring on them. But although the World bee blea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e-eyed and di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sighted, yet those which are elected out of the world, do feele, and see, and can say much. And the word of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth


<pb facs="12"/>
in it many royall and notable pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges and dignities, properly belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto those whom God hath elected and adopted, some whereof I will briefly and plainely heere set downe.</p>
   <p>The first dignitie is their glorious and <note place="margin">Priuil. 1.</note> honorable stiles and titles. They are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Scriptures, The people, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, the sonnes, the building, the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie and houshold seruants of God, the brethren, the spouse, the members, the seed &amp; the sheep of Christ, the temples of the holy Ghost, the seed, the sonnes and the daughters of <hi>Abraham.</hi> They are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led liuely stones, a spirituall house, heires of the promise, Saints, faithfull, Kings, Priests, yea an holy &amp; princely priesthood, a peculiar people chalenged of God, a chosen generation, and an holy nation.</p>
   <p>The faithfull and chosen children of <note place="margin">Priuil. 2.</note> God alone haue true title to all the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward blessings of God, for they only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, <note place="margin">Isa. 1. 19 1. Tim. 4. 3.</note> and they are only Gods obedienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries. Reprobates are butindeed vsurpers of them in his sight. We lost them in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and we receiue right neither in them


<pb facs="13"/>
nor to them, but by Christ. His passions haue purchased our possessions.</p>
   <p>The Elect only can vse Gods blessings <note place="margin">Priuil. 3.</note> to a right end and in a right maner. For they only are pure (being purged in the bloud of Christ) and they only can pray with a true faith. The wicked make their riches their owne ruine, and Gods bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits their owne bane, and either abuse them, or vse them not as he commandeth them, and causeth his owne children by his grace to vse them.</p>
   <p>God hath appoynted his holy Angels, <note place="margin">Priuil. 4.</note> which for their strength and fortitude are called Gods, to guard and protect his <note place="margin">Psa. 8. 5.</note> people. <hi>The Angell of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>: Lord</hi> (saith <hi>Dauid) pitcheth round about them that foare him.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sal. 34. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> And the Apostle sayth, that they <hi>are all ministring spirits, sent forth to minister for their sakes which shall be beires of saluation.</hi> The Lord hath honoured his Elect, and <note place="margin">Priuil. 5.</note> no doubt, yet doth and will (when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth him) by preseruing them, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for them very effectually, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 36. 26.</note> also very wonderfully. Hee saued <hi>Noah</hi> from drowning, <hi>Lot</hi> from burning,


<pb facs="13"/>
      <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lias</hi> from famishing, <hi>Mordecai</hi> from mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and <hi>Paul</hi> from those bloudy Votaries, by prouiding for them very kindly. Hee saued <hi>Samson</hi> miraculously from perishing by thirst, and <hi>Daniel</hi> from the teeth of the Lions. <hi>Dauid</hi> saith, <hi>The Lord drew him out</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 18, 16, 48, 50.</note>
      <hi>of many waters, and deliuered him from the cruell man, and gaue him great deliuer anc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s.</hi> He did often and strangely also preserue our late Queene of holy and happy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, from the desperate and malicious attempts of Popish Traytors, set a worke by the Diuell to murder her. He prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged her dayes, he held the Crowne on her head, and kept the Scepter in her hand with peace and prosperitie, the time and tyranny of <note n="*" place="margin">Paul. 4. Pius 4. &amp; 5. Greg. 13. Sixtus. 5. Vrban. 7. Greg. 14 Innoc. 9. Clemon, 8</note> nine or tenne Monsters her mortall enemies, though their slaues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually plotted and practised against her, and thought the Prince of the aire thunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red against her in his <note n="*" place="margin">Pius 5. Greg. 13. Sixtus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Lieutenants (as it were from the clouds) with curses and cursed Excommunications. Lately also he hath vouchsafed an admirable deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to his Anointed our gracious King, and to vs all, from a most barbarous and


<pb facs="14"/>
horrible confusion. And of this kinde of fauour and fauourable dealing vsed of the Lord, we may reade plentifully in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and Ecciesiasticall stories. And no doubt, the wicked haue sometimes fared the better for the Electsake, as <hi>Laban</hi> did <note place="margin">Gen. 30. 27. Gen. 39. 5. Act. 27. 24. Gen. 18. 32. Iob. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>0.</note> for <hi>Iacob,</hi> and <hi>Potiphar</hi> for <hi>Ioseph,</hi> and those which say led in that dangerous voyage to Rome, for <hi>Paul,</hi> who was in their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. God told <hi>Abraham,</hi> that if there were but ten righteous persons in <hi>Sodom,</hi> hee would not destroy it for their sakes. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaez</hi> saith, that the innocent shall deliuer the Iland; meaning, that God doth often deliuer a whole countrey from perill, for the iust m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ns sake.</p>
   <p>For his Elect GOD hath altered the course of nature. He diuided the waters <note place="margin">Priuil. 6.</note> of the red sea, that his people might passe dry-shod through it. He caused the Sunne <note place="margin">Exo. 14. 22. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sh. 10. 12.</note> to stay, and the Moone to stand still, till his people had auenged themselues vpon their enemies. For <hi>Gideons</hi> sake he caused the dew to fall only vpon a fleece of wooll, and kept it from falling vpon the ground: <note place="margin">Iud. 8. 38, 40.</note> and afterwards, at his request he let it fall


<pb facs="14"/>
on the earth, and kept the fleece drie. For <hi>Hezekiah</hi> his sake he brought the shadow in the dyall of <hi>Ahaz</hi> ten degrees <note place="margin">Isa. 38. 8</note> backward, by the which degrees the Sunne was gone downe.</p>
   <p>GOD doth often preserue his chosen <note place="margin">Priuil. 7.</note> children from pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>is then, when he doth persecute the wicked. <hi>Many sorowes</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 32. 10.</note> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Dauid) shall be fall the wicked, but he that trusteth in the Lord, shall be compassed of mercy. Noah</hi> was deliuered, when the wicked were drowned. The <hi>Israelites</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 19. 16.</note> passed, whē the <hi>Egiptians</hi> perished. Whē <hi>Sodo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> was burned, <hi>Lot</hi> was brought foorth. When <hi>Ierico</hi> was sacked, <hi>Raha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> was saued. When <hi>Abab</hi> was slaine, <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bosaph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t</hi> escaped. When <hi>Ierusalem</hi> was to be destroyed, the Lord commanded <note place="margin">Ezek. 9. 4.</note> the godly to be brāded, that they might be preserued. Moreouer, when the Lord deliuereth his own people, then he doth sometimes thrust the wicked into their dangers. <hi>The righteous</hi> (sayth <hi>Salomon)</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. 11. 8.</note>
      <hi>escapeth out of trouble, and the wicked shall come in his stead.</hi> And as he doth vsually crosse their cursed counsels, so he doth


<pb facs="15"/>
often times curse theyr malicious and bloudie enterprises, and cracks them vpō their owne crownes, and breakes them vpon their own backs. <hi>Haman</hi> was han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on that galowes which he himselfe <note place="margin">Hest. 7. 9</note> had prepared for <hi>Mordecai,</hi> whom the King did greatly aduance. <hi>Daniel</hi> was brought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>om the Lions, and his accusers <note place="margin">Dan. 6. 23, 24.</note> being cast into the den amongst them, were deuoured of them. God preserued <hi>Shadrak, Meshak</hi> &amp; <hi>Abednego</hi> in the hot <note place="margin">Dan 3. 22.</note> fiery furnace, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lew the men with the flame of the fire, that brought them forth to be burned. The Lord deliuered good <hi>Ieh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>shaphat,</hi> and caused his enemies that <note place="margin">2. Chron. 20. 23.</note> came against him, to help forward their owne destruction. The Lord hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vs frō their barbarous and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirsty Catholiques, and hath for the honour of his mercy pulled the rotten house of their diuelish muentions vpon their owne heads. <hi>His name be praysed for euer and euer, Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Christ hath altered the nature of affsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions <note place="margin">Priuil. 8.</note> vnto his elect and faithfull mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. For whereas they are cast vpon


<pb facs="15"/>
the wicked, as punishments due vnto them for their sinnes wherein they liue, they are inflicted vpon the Godly by <note place="margin">Psal. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 31, 32. Hab. 12. 6.</note> God, as a mercifull Father that desireth the amendment of his children. Because our hearts are drossy, the Lord, as our most skilfull founder, casteth vs into the furnace of afflictions, that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine vs. Because we are subiect to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse and goe astray, the Lord impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs within the pales of aduersitie, and hedgeth vs about with the thorny quick-set of the crosse, that we might be kept in some compasse. <hi>Dauid</hi> sayth, <note place="margin">Psa. 119 67.</note>
      <hi>Before I was afflicted, I went astray, but now I keepe thy word.</hi> Because wee are by nature vntoward to that which is good, the Lord vseth the crosse as a Schoolemaster to instruct vs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Dauid</hi> sayth, <hi>It is good for me that I haue beene afflicted, that I may learne</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psa. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 71.</note>
      <hi>thy Statutes.</hi> Because wee are by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture inclined to the loue of the world, the Lord, as our Nurse, doth weane vs from the loue thereof, by affliction, as the Mother or Nurse driueth her Child


<pb facs="16"/>
from the brest, by rubbing it with some bitter thing. To be briefe, the Lord by afflictions ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>eth our faith and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>neth vs humility, and teacheth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to esteeme of prosperity. By af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>s bee maketh vs to take experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or his loue, and of those graces which he hath giuen vs. By afflictions he learneth vs to be mercifull vnto the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable. for the sense of sicknes, and the feeling of pouerty through Gods bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, is a notable meanes to make vs pity the poore and the sick. The Apostle sayth, <hi>Our light affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ction, which is but for</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 17.</note>
      <hi>a moment, worketh vnto vs a far most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and an eternall weight of glory;</hi> though not as a cause procuring it (for wee are <note place="margin">Ephes. 2. 8. Rom. 6. 23.</note> saued by grace: and euerlasting life is the free gift of God in Christ) yet as a way and meanes directing and leading vs thereto. Christ hath two Crownes, the one of thornes, the other of glory: hee that will be honoured with the last, must bee humbled and tryed with the first. Thus it is euident, that God sheweth himselfe a Father, in afflicting his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.


<pb facs="16"/>
But as for the Reprobate, his eros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses are curses, and his afflictions are fore-runners of further iudgements in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and sent of God as a seuere and dreadfull Iudge.</p>
   <p>God hath altered the nature of death <note place="margin">Priuil. 9.</note> vnto all the elect. For Christ by his death hath been the death of death, and the death of sinne, which is the sting and strength of death. First of all, God by death teacheth vs to detest sinne, and to acknowledge the seu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>ty and sharpnes of his anger against it. Secondly, by death he deliuereth vs vtterly from the body of sinne. Till death we attaine not vnto perfection, and at death sinne is wholy con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>ed. When we dye, sinne dyeth. For sinne is so nething like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uy, which falleth downe and dyeth, when the tree on which it hanged is cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. Thirdly, the Lord doth sometimes take away his children by death, that they should not see those euils which he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> purposed to plague his enemies withall. <hi>Mercifull men are taken away</hi> (sayth <note place="margin">Is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪ 57. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>) and no man vnderstand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>th that the


<pb facs="17"/>
righteous is taken away from the euill to some.</hi> So the Lord tooke away good <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siah,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n. 84. 28.</note> that his eyes might not see all the euill which hee purposed to bring vpon that place Yea such is his loue vnto his Saints, that he cannot doe that to the wicked which he would, so long as they liue amongst them. As the Angell told <hi>Lot,</hi> that he could do nothing till he was gone out of <hi>Sodome:</hi> euen so it may be <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>en. 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>2.</note> truly sayd, that Gods loue is so feruent towards his chosen, as that it sometimes keepeth him from scattering his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in those places wherein they liue. Therefore he doth often remoue them by death, that he may more freely poure out the vials of his wrath vpon the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, Fourthly, by death God learneth vs to seeke a place of rest, and to alie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ate our affections from the world; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like vnto bird-lime, would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise more easily belime our affections, that they could not soare vp to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens the place of our home. Fiftly, by death the Lord humbleth vs, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th vs, not to pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ke and plume vp


<pb facs="17"/>
our bodies lyke Peacocks, as if wee meant to liue euer. Sixtly, the Lord by their deaths occasioneth their exper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and feeling of the vertue of Christs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection. Lastly, as death is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of mortification, and endeth the battell betweene the flesh and the spirit; so it fully finisheth all earthly cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>erry-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> it transpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs ouer the tempestuous and broad Ocean of tribulations and afflictions, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the calme and quiet hauen of endlesse happinesse. But as for the Reprobate, it is to them as a boat, to cary them out of a riuer of earthly miseries, into a restlesse &amp; bottomlesse sea of infinite &amp; ineffable torments. And because their felicity (if any) consisteth in the finite fruition of worldly prosperity, God in his appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, by death as by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> knife, cutteth asunder the threed of life, and so ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth them out of their paradise, and sendeth their soules to the place of the damned, where they shall continue ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly tormented, till that dolefull and dismall day of vengeance.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="18"/>
God hath ordeined the writing of his <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>l. 10</note> word, the preaching of it, the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of the Sacraments, and his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensers of them principally and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>fit of the Elect. Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Paul</hi> sayth, <hi>Whatsoeuer things are written afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>me, are written for our learning, that we</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>om. 15. 4.</note>
      <hi>through patience and comfort of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>s, might haue hope. Iohn</hi> saith, he wrote that wee might beleeue in the name of <note place="margin">1. Ioh 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>3.</note> Christ. Therefore his writings properly belong to the children of God, And the Apestle writing to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>ans, sayth, that Christ gaue some to be Apostles, and some Prephets, and some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists, and some Pastors and Doctors. But to what end? <hi>For the reparation of the Saints, and for the edification of Christs</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>2.</note>
      <hi>body.</hi> And this is no small prerogatiue. for the Sacraments are signes and seales of Gods grace. The preaching of the Gospell is the power of God to saluation to all that doe beleeue. In his word hee hath recorded his will. And his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters are as it were his Trumpeters, which do sound in our eares the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets


<pb facs="18"/>
of his Law and Gospell, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct vs when to stand still, when to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre, and when and how to march for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. They are through his assistance our spirituall Fathers, by whom he doth procreate and beget vs vnto himselfe, for our good and his owne glory. Now all these things profit the Reprobate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, but do indeed through the rebellions corruption of they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hearts, harden and stiften them, as the Sunne doth clay.</p>
   <p>The Lord hath vnited all his elect and <note place="margin">Priui. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re children vnto Christ, by his Spirit, and by a true and liuely faith. And by reason of this vnion, they are after a sort vnited to the whole Trinity, Father, Sonne, and holy Ghost. Yea hence it is that we are partakers of Christs bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits. For as the members of the body haue neither sense nor motion, vnlesse they be vnited to the head: and as the science or griffe receiueth no nourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, except it be set in the stock and grow vp with it: Fuen so, vnlesse we be vnited vnto Christ our stock and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall


<pb facs="19"/>
head, we haue no spirituall life and motion, neither are we actually parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his benefits. But being once vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and knit vnto him, we receiue sense and sap, life and motion.</p>
   <p>All the elect and faithfull people of God, are partakers of the prayers of all <note place="margin">Priuil. 12.</note> the Godly throughout the world. The children of God haue fellowship one with an other, as with Christ their head. Whereas on the contrary, they pray for the confusion and finall destruction of his and their impenitent, pestilent, and irreconciliable enemies, and can not but hate and abandon those, whom they see to walke peruersly in wicked and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate courses, without remorse of consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and all shew of repentance. For GOD hath put a secret antipathy and mortall en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>y betweene his seed, and the seed of the Serpent. Therefore <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> sayth, <hi>A wicked man is an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the iust, and he that is vpright in his</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prou. 29 27.</note>
      <hi>way, is an abomination to the wicked.</hi> And as <hi>Dauid</hi> sayth, <hi>The wicked practiseth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 37. 12.</note>
      <hi>the iust, and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>eth his t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>th a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst


<pb facs="19"/>
him.</hi> So he also sayth thus of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, <note place="margin">Psal. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> 6.</note>
      <hi>I haue hated them that giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to deceitfull vanities.</hi> And againe, <hi>Doe not I hate them, O Lord, that hate</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psa. 139 21.</note>
      <hi>thee? I hate them with the perfection of hatred, as if they were mine vtter ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> And in the fifteenth Psalme, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning <note place="margin">Psal. 15. 4.</note> of a vile person, that is, of a wicked wretch, and the honouring of the Godly, is made an infallible note of a faithfull member of the Church. By which it appeareth that there is no sincere and solid communion betweene Gods children and the slaues of the Diuell. And therefore it is one of our priuiledges and peculiar dignities, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the loue, and louely communion of the Saints.</p>
   <p>Faith, by which we walke and liue, <note place="margin">Priuil. 13.</note> by which we are iustified and adopted, without which it is impossible to please GOD; this faith, which is a superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6. Act. 13. 48. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. 1. 1.</note> gift of God aboue corrupt and created nature, this faith (I saye) is peculiar and proper to the Elect: therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>alieth it, <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aith


<pb facs="20"/>
of the Elect:</hi> and teacheth the Thessalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Thes. 3 2.</note> that it is not common to all men. Secondly, Hope is an excellent gift of God, for it maketh not ashamed, and by <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 5</note> it the Apostle sayth we are saued, that is, by hope we expect and wait for that sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 24.</note> which by faith we apprehend, and assure our selues of, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ualu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able merits of Christ. Now, this grace is not giuen to any besides the Elect. For how can the Reprobate hope to be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, seeing they are appointed for the day of euill, and are reserued to the day <note place="margin">Prou. 16. 4. Iob. 21. 30. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Tim. 1 5,</note> of destruction, and shall be brought foorth to the day of wrath? Thirdly, Loue, which springeth out of a pure heart, and floweth from a good consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and faith vnfeigned, is giuen only to Gods Elect. For it is not possible for the Reprobate to loue God, to that end and in that manner which God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; seeing he hath cast them off from all eternity, and purposed not to giue them any sauing grace; considering also that they are by nature voyd of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itie, and do liue and dye in sinne. Now


<pb facs="20"/>
this priuiledge is the greater, because this grace is very rare and excellent. Loue is (as it were) a knife, wherewith faith shareth and cutteth out the duties which we doe owe vnto God and man, in some good and acceptable manner. Loue is the cock which letteth out the water of Gods graces out of the cisterne of our hearts. Loue is the nurse of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, the mother of equitie, the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vertue, the daughter of faith, the preseruer of pietie, the mistresse of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie, the badge of Christianitie, the bane of discord, the staffe of concord, <note place="margin">Col. 3. 14. Iob. 13. 35. 1. Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 13.</note> the keeper of the Crowne, the bond of perfection, and the note of a true dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in some sort prefers it to faith and hope, when he saith, <hi>Now abideth faith, hope and loue: but the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest of these is Loue.</hi> By which we see, that the Lord hath highly honoured vs, in that hee conferreth this glorious grace vnto none but vs. Lastly, that filiall <note place="margin">Prou. 9. 10. Prou. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 27.</note> feare, which is the beginning of wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the well-spring of life, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd the snares of death, and which


<pb facs="21"/>
makes a man to keepe the golden rule of mediocritie, is giuen onely to Gods Elect. For how can the Reprobate, who doe loue sinne, and doe not loue God, how (I say) can they feare to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>please him, because they hate sinne, and loue him? or how can the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, who are all ordeined to ineuitable and eternall perdition, be sayd to feare God as a Sonne feareth his louing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, seeing they be slaues, and conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that the word of God pronounceth him happy and blessed, who standeth <note place="margin">Psa. 112 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> in awe of GOD, and feareth to offend him? If the Reprobate be blessed, then of all men the Elect are most accursed. But wee shall say that those are bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, whom the Lord hath accursed, if we shall say, that the Reprobate doe feare God with that feare whereof I now speake. <note place="margin">Priuil. 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Chron. 14. 11. Nahum. 1. 9. Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 4</note>
   </p>
   <p>GOD accounteth those iniuries as done vnto himselfe, which the wicked offer vnto his faithfull seruants. <hi>Saul</hi> persecuted the true professors of Christ, yet Christ told him from heauen, that


<pb facs="21"/>
he persecuted him. The afflictions of Gods children, are called in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <note place="margin">Col. 1. 24</note> Christs afflictions. For such is the vnion and communion betwixt the head and the members, that if any of <note place="margin">Reuel. 11 8.</note> them smart, the head is partaker of the griefe. If any part be crazed or annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the heart is ready to mourne, the head to consult, the tongue to bewayle and vtter it, the foot to run to the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, and the hand is ready to do her duety. Euen so it is betweene Christ and his members. If any of them bee iniuriously vexed and troubled, hee takes the wrong as done vnto himselfe. And so Christ may be sayd to be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified in that great city, which is mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> that is, <hi>Rome,</hi> because hee is there put to death in his members, and is in them (as it were) slayne continually by <note n="*" place="margin">Romish authority is either heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish, or Popish, Christ di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the former, but in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> members he hath died by both, and yet doth by the latter. Zach. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 8. Math. 25</note> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish authority, as hee was by it (if wee speake properly) crucifyed and put to death. So in lyke manner the Lord sayeth, <hi>He which toucheth you, toucheth the apple of mine eye.</hi> And as Christ


<pb facs="22"/>
esteemeth of those good deeds which men do vnto them, as done vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe: euen so hee accounteth the bare neglecting, and the not relieuing of them in their wants, as if the wicked had been in this kind of duety faultie vnto himselfe.</p>
   <p>God will shorten the World, and hasten the comming of his Sonne for the <note place="margin">Priui. 15</note> Elect. And so that speach of Christ may be vnderstood, <hi>For the Elects sake those</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 24 22.</note>
      <hi>euill dayes shall be shortened.</hi> Moreouer, such is the patience and good wil of God vnto his Elect, as that hee stayeth his comming for a time, because he would (as <hi>Peter</hi> affirmeth) haue none of them to perish, but come vnto repentance, <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 9.</note> that when hee commeth, they may bee welcome vnto him, and hee to them.</p>
   <p>God doth effectually call the Elect, and none besides them, and they alone <note place="margin">Priui. 16</note> are iustifyed in his sight. For hee doth pardon them alone, and they only are <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 30.</note> clothed with the spotlesse roabes of Christs perfect righteousnes. Therefore the Prophet saith, <hi>The ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>stisement of our</hi>
      <note place="margin">Isa. 53. 5 6.</note>
      <pb facs="22"/>
      <hi>peace was vpon him. The Lord hath layed vpon him the iniquitie of vs all. For the</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>transgression of my people was he plagued. By his knowledge shall my righteous seruant</hi>
      <note place="margin">11. 12. Math. 1. 21. Iohn 17. 9.</note>
      <hi>iustifie many. He bare the sinne of many.</hi> He doth not say <hi>all.</hi> For he came to saue his owne people only from their sinnes. He did not so much as pray for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate. Now this is a very great and admirable priuiledge, and honour, that God should send his only Sonne to dye for vs few despicable wretches, and that Christ should lose his life, and shead his heart blood for vs only, whereas it was in <note place="margin">Act, 20. 28.</note> it selfe (being the blood of God) suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciēt to haue redeemed a thousand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand worlds of sinners. If a man had a medicine able to cure all diseases, and would not giue it any sauing some few, they were wonderfully indebted to him. The blood of Christ is able to heale all our soule-sicknesses, and to deliuer vs from all our sinnes: and it hath pleased him to wash vs alone in it, and to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it from the far greater part of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. By which we see, how highly hee


<pb facs="23"/>
hath honoured vs, and how deep we are in his debt. If three men were in danger of drowning or burning, and a man should come and deliuer one of them, and leaue the other two to the danger, all men might well say, that he fauoured him more then the other. By our sinnes we were all in danger to be drowned in that sulphury lake, and to be consumed with the fire of Gods wrath, as well as the Reprobates. Our sinnes deserue it. But Christ hath set himselfe betweene his Father and vs. He hath taken no notice (as it were) of them: and vs only, who are elected, he hath redeemed. As the Lord drowned the Egyptians onely in the Sea, so Christ hath ouerwhelmed our sinnes only in his blood. And as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory couered the Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue: so Christ couereth his Elect with his bloud, and hideth them, yea them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, from the wrath of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Paul</hi> calleth him, The sauiour of his body. By which we see, his grace &amp; good <note place="margin">Ephes. 5. 23.</note> will is farre greater to vs then to them.</p>
   <p>It is impossible through the vertue of <note place="margin">Priui. 17</note>
      <pb facs="23"/>
Gods decree and Christs merits, that any of the Elect should fall into the sinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the holy Ghost, into which some Reprobates haue rushed.</p>
   <p>The Elect being once actually redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <note place="margin">Priuil. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Luk. 1. 74.</note> haue liberty to serue and worship GOD without feare of any euill. They serue him chiefly for his loue, and for conscience of his commandements. The wicked seeme to serue him oftentimes, but it is for some sinester respect, as for feare of damnation (as the slaue obeyeth his Master for feare of the whip) or for feare of imprisonment, or an ill name, or else for the loue of lucre, or the desire of glory or credit with men.</p>
   <p>The elect alone do merit at Gods hāds, <note place="margin">Priuil. 19.</note> for they being alone partakers of Christs meritorious righteousnes, do also alone, it being accounted as their owne, merit euerlasting life of God. Now is not this an exceeding great fauour, that we being but wormes, should deserue euerlasting <note place="margin">Iob. 25. 6</note> happines of so high a Maiesty? It doth greatly commend the loue of God to vs, and the rather, because he hath graced


<pb facs="24"/>
vs only with the inestimable merits of his Sonne, refusing to impart them to many millions of men, as noble, as wise, as learned, as beautifull, as mighty, and as wealthy as our selues.</p>
   <p>The Elect being once effectually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, do sinne thenceforward only of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity. <note place="margin">Priui. 20</note> Therefore Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> sayth, that <hi>Whosoeuer is borne of God, sinneth not,</hi> that is, with full consent of will. For so far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth <note place="margin">1. Iob. 3. 9.</note> as he is regenerate, he doth not sinne. Wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> in the person of all true beleeuers saith, <hi>If I do that I would not</hi> (meaning euill) <hi>it is no more I that do</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 20.</note>
      <hi>it, but the sinne that dwelleth in me.</hi> But on the contrary, wickednes (as <hi>Iob</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) is sweet in the wicked mans mouth, <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ob. 20. 12.</note> he hideth it vnder his tongue, he fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it, he will not forsake it, but keeps it close in his mouth. His sinne is as his soule, and therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> saith, he can not sleepe except hee haue done euill, And the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> sheweth, that <note place="margin">Prou. 4. 16.</note> the wicked is so soldered to his sinne, as that hee will not learne righteousnes, though mercy be shewed vnto him: in <note place="margin">Isa. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 10.</note>
      <pb facs="24"/>
the land of vprightnes, where true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is commanded, countenanced and professed, he will do wickedly; neither respecting Gods mercifull dealing, nor the good ensamples of the Godly. Whereas the faithfull detest and abhor their corruptions, and struggle against them, striuing and desiring to be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them, as a prisoner of his bolts, or as those which are troubled with the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease <hi>Ineubus,</hi> called the Night-mare, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire or struggle to be rid thereof.</p>
   <p>The Scriptures do teach, that God hath <note place="margin">Priuil, 21</note> made peace betwixt the creatures and his children. The stones of the field are <note place="margin">Iob. 5. 23.</note> in league with them, and the beasts of the field are at peace with them. The Lord by his Prophet <hi>Hosea</hi> sayth, that he will make a couenant for them with <note place="margin">Hos. 2. 18</note> the wild beasts, and with the foules of the heauen, and with that which creepeth <note place="margin">Exod. 11. 7. Exod 14. 22, 28,</note> vpon the earth. Do we not reade, that the Sea made way to the <hi>Israelites,</hi> and ouerwhelmed their enemies which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued them? Do we not reade that Rauens fed the Prophet <hi>Eliah?</hi> Do we not read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">1. King. 17. 6,</note>
      <pb facs="25"/>
that the hungry Lyons fauored <hi>Daniel,</hi> and that the fire spared the three Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? Did not a Starre conduct the wise men to the place where our Lord lay? <note place="margin">Math. 2. 9</note> Did not the Lord make a couenant for his seruant <hi>Ionah</hi> with the Whale, whose <note place="margin">Iob. 41. 5, 22.</note> teeth (as the scripture saith) are terrible, and by his might he maketh the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>th to boyle like a pot? And did he no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> make a bond of peace for <hi>Paul</hi> with the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Viper, when she b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing vpon his <note place="margin">Act. 28. 5, 6.</note> hand he receiued no hurt, though the Barbarians wayted when hee should haue swolne, or falne downe suddenly dead? On the contrary, we reade that he drowned the wicked world with water, &amp; burned the filthy Sodomites with fire. He met with ambitious <hi>Absalom</hi> with a <note place="margin">2. King. 2 24.</note> tree, and slue those wicked childrē which mocked the Prophet <hi>Elisha</hi> with Beares. He made the dogs to eate the flesh of wicked <hi>Iezabel,</hi> and destroyed <hi>Herod,</hi> that <note place="margin">2. King. 9 36. Act. 12. 23. Exod. 8.</note> cruell &amp; vainglorious king with wormes. He plaged the Egyptiās with frogs, flyes, &amp; lice. Yea, the Lord hath all creatures in heauen and earth ready (whē it pleaseth


<pb facs="25"/>
him) to run vpon the wicked and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, as a grey hound vpon his game whē the leash is takē off, which he manifesteth when he sayth by <hi>Ieremy, I will &amp;c.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iere. 15. 3. Priuil. 22.</note>
   </p>
   <p>The Elect being once forgiuen of God, &amp; accepted vnto euerlasting life for the merits of Christ, haue ioy vnspeakeable, and that peace which passeth all vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing. <hi>The kingdome of God</hi> (sayth the <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 17.</note> Apostle) <hi>standeth in peace and ioy in the holy Ghost.</hi> If the health of body be such a thing, as is rather with comfort inioyed, then in words to be expressed; how great shall we think is the peace of conscience, &amp; ioy in the holy Ghost? It may be tasted, but it can not be expressed. The malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor hath great peace and quietnes with himselfe, whē the King hath granted him his pardon: euen so the elect should haue <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 7.</note> great peace &amp; tranquility of mind, when as God, the great King of heauen and earth, hath pardoned their sins, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued thē to fauour. But on the cōtrary, the Reprobate &amp; irreconciliable sinners, that sell themselues to worke wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and drinke iniquitie lyke water,


<pb facs="26"/>
haue either no peace at all, but are like the raging Sea that cannot rest, whose <note place="margin">Isa. 57. 20.</note> waters cast vp myre and dirt, or else are senselesse like stocks, labouring of a spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall apoplexy, and a diuelish dead palsy, being sunke into the gulfe of secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and hauing made a league with death and a couenant with hell.</p>
   <p>The Elect haue an Altar, whereupon <note place="margin">Priuil. 23</note> if they lay all their prescribed sacrifices, they shall be accepted of God, as smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling sweetly in his nostrils. But the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, and all their sacrifices are odious and abominable in his sight. They want our Altar Christ Iesus, who should purge and sanctify theyr offerings, and by whom they should offer them vnto the Father: and therefore their goodly sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices are but goodly sinnes.</p>
   <p>God giueth his holy Spirit to his Elect only, who in Gods appointed time ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <note place="margin">Priuil. 24</note> his habitation in them, who doth also sweep the floores of their spirits with the hand of his grace, and the beesome of his word, and trimmeth vp the houses of their hearts with the sweet and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant


<pb facs="26"/>
flowres of his spirit, and adorneth them with the costly tapestry and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ornaments of his orient and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent graces He perfumeth them (as it were) with frankincense and coales of Iuniper. He buildeth windowes within them, that they may receiue the bright and beawtifull beames and louely light, which do shine from the Sun of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes. Hee constituteth a kingdome within them: hee ruleth them with the strength of his arme, and the scepter of his word. He stablisheth his throne with iustice and mercy: he fostereth the part regenerate, he bridleth and tameth the rebell, euen the rebellious corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the heart, and by little and little consumeth it. As for the Reprobate; their hearts are the dens of the Diuell, and the cabins of sinne, stincking loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somly like a dead carryon. There is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a kingdome within them: but the Diuell is the King, Sinne is the Queene. His Throne is wickednes, his Scepter is iniquity, his Lawes are the liberty of the flesh, his rewards are death, and they


<pb facs="27"/>
are his slaues and vassals.</p>
   <p>As the Elect may haue Grace, so it is possible for thē to grow in grace: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Priuil. 25. 2. Pet. 3. 18. 1. Pet. 2. 2.</note>
      <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth vs, <hi>To grow in grace, and in the knowledge of Christ,</hi> and shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth also how we may grow. But for the Reprobate; as they are void of all true la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing grace, so they grow not there in, for they can not increase in that which they want. A man cannot grow in bignes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse he haue a body. A man cā not grow rich, vnlesse he haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iches. They may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease in sin and grow in wickednes, as clay doth in hardnes whē the weather is dry, or as the riuers do in depth &amp; bredth whē the tide commeth. Againe, whereas the Lord doth very often giue the reines to the Reprobate, and suffers them to rush headlong into horrible enormities, as the <hi>Gadarens</hi> Swine did into the Sea; hee doth mercifully preserue his owne people, and graciously keepeth them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes from declining and falling; and whensoeuer they either stumble or fall, they may recouer themselues by serious and sound repentance. But God hath


<pb facs="27"/>
not vouchsafed the gift of godly sorow and true repentance to the Reprobate. It belongs only to Gods Elect. Wee may reade of <hi>Dauids</hi> repentance, of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> falling and rising, of <hi>Pauls</hi> conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: but wee neuer read of any true <note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o turne truly, is to returne from all sinne vnto God.</note> turning that euer any reprobate made. If any of them repent, it is but for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion sake, or for feare of punishment. It is not for loue to God, or for the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of sinne for sinne, or for the consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of Gods loue vnto them. As lead being cast into the water, can not but sinke, so the Reprobate can not but sinne. And as a Mill-stone lying in the bottome of the Sea, can not come vp, so the Reprobate beeing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelmed in the bottomlesse pit of iniquitie, can not repent. Though it were possible to remoue a Mountayne out of his place, yet it were more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible to remoue a Reprobate from his corruptions. Hee may mooue, but hee will not remooue. Hee may turne, but hee cannot returne. As it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible for him to reuiue, who is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained


<pb facs="28"/>
to perpetuall death: so it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible for him to reuiue from sinne, whom the fountaine of all life hath righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teously forsaken, and deliuered for euer vnto Sathan, to hold captiue in the graue of sinne, and in the darke and deadly dungeon of iniquity.</p>
   <p>The children of God haue the spirit of prayer, and with boldnesse may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach <note place="margin">Priuil. 26.</note> vnto the throne of his grace, and put vp their suites vnto him. The King will permit a true subiect to come into his presence and speake vnto him, when a rebell or traytour shall finde no such fauour. A Kings sonne may speake vnto his father, when others are not permitted so to do. We are the sonnes of God, and the seruants of his sonne; therefore we may boldly in the name of our elder brother, present our selues before him, and put vp our supplications to him; and the rather, because he knoweth and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooueth vs. For as the Apostle sayth, <hi>The foundation of God remaineth sure, and hath this seale, The Lord knoweth who are</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2 19.</note>
      <hi>his.</hi> But the Reprobate and their prayers


<pb facs="28"/>
are abominable in his sight. They want the spirit of prayer, and either can not pray at all, or not in the right manner. Neither can they approach with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse vnto GOD, seeing they haue no part in Christ, nor Christ in them. They cannot pray with cōfidence to be heard; seeing they are destitute as well of faith, as of the fauour of God.</p>
   <p>GOD accepteth the sincere will and <note place="margin">Priuil. 27.</note> feruent desires of his faithfull and elect children to beleeue, repent and obey for faith, repentance &amp; obedience. For <hi>As</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psa. 103 13.</note>
      <hi>a father hath compassion on his children, so hath the Lord compassion on them that feare him. He will spare them, as a man</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mala. 3. 17.</note>
      <hi>spareth his owne sonne.</hi> But fathers vse to take in good part their childrens works, so they do them with care and diligence, though not so perfectly and exactly as indeed were meet. In like manner, if we will and with an honest heart desire to do well, though we do it very weakely, God doth notwithstanding take all in good part, and regardeth not the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the worke. A desire of grace


<pb facs="29"/>
is one degree of grace, and a will to do well, is with God accounted doing well. Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> sayth, <hi>If there be a willing mind, it is accepted according to that a man</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Cor. 8. 12.</note>
      <hi>hath, and not according to that he hath not.</hi> That which he saith of giuing almes, is true in the performance of all other du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. If there be in a man a ready and willing mind to beleeue, repent, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, though he do not these things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly, or so well as many of his brethren do; yet God, for the merits and interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of his Sonne, accepteth both of him and his imperfit works, and in mercy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeth him. <hi>Dauid,</hi> besides his dayly infirmities, did thrice grieuously offend God, and yet he told <hi>Salomon,</hi> that if he <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Chron. 7. 17.</note> would walke before him as <hi>Dauid</hi> his father, he would establish the throne of his kingdome, so as that he should not want a man to be a Ruler in <hi>Israel.</hi> And albeit in that place he requireth that he should do according to all his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, whereby he may seeme to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act perfect (and therefore impossible) obedience; yet if we consider all things


<pb facs="29"/>
well, it will plainely appeare, that hee meaneth no other thing, then that hee should labour and seeke to please him in all things: because hee setteth his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Dauid</hi> before his eyes as a patterne to follow, and because else-where we reade that hee maketh the same pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise vnto him, onely requiring of him, <hi>To indeuour himselfe to doe hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 Chron. 28. 7.</note> as hee had begun. Now this is a very comfortable doctrine. For when a man considereth that GOD respects his weake obedience and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest heart, and accounteth the will to doe, for the deed done, his heart is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, his conscience is appeased, his mind is setled, and beholding the infinite loue of God, he is rauished with ioy, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to magnifie his mercy, and to struggle against the corruption of his heart, to please him in doing all things which are pleasing in his sight. Now, lest we should beguile our selues (for mans heart is a mine of subtilty) in thinking we desire, &amp; will to beleeue, repent &amp; obey, whē as we either do not at al, or do but as


<pb facs="30"/>
a reprobate may doe; I will set downe some rules, which as the touch-stone trieth gold, and as <hi>Salomons</hi> sword found out the right mother, so these may serue to discouer the truth of our desires, and to deserte the goodnes of our wils. First of all, if we be grieued that we can desire and will no better then we do: second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if we do desire and will to do these things for the glory of God, and because we are perswaded that both these things and the willing of them are pleasing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: thirdly, if we striue to increase in willing and desiring, and if we feed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> them with the diligent hearing of Gods word, with holy meditations, with often prayers, and with setting before vs the ensamples of excellent men, as the Priests kept the fire vpon the altar, and fed it continually, and suffered it not to <note place="margin">Leuit. 6. 12.</note> go out: fourthly, if to our wills and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires we ioyne reformation of our liues, and in our seuerall callings labour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to serue God: fiftly, if in our hearts we prefer eternall seruing of God in heauen, before all momentany profits


<pb facs="30"/>
and pleasures whatsoeuer. Sixtly, if we had rather liue in a continuall crosse all our life long, but yet pleasing God, and being in his fauour, then spend the same in sinfull pleasures, continually displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing his Maiesty. Seuenthly, if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire and will to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rue him, and to returne home vnto him from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> sins, though wee were verily perswaded that there were no hell. Lastly, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> had rather please God, his rod of correction being alwayes exercised vpon vs, then liue without remorse of conscience against our knowledge, in profitable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant sinnes, continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>ing and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasing GOD our gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cious Father; though wee were certainely (as it were by oracle from heauen) assured that we should at the last gasp repent, and be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, notwithstanding our former rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and horrible disloyaltie. If we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire and will to beleeue, repent, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, and find these things in vs, then our desires will goe for currant, God will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of them, and approoue them.</p>
   <p>The Lord indeed suffereth his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren <note place="margin">Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 28.</note>
      <pb facs="31"/>
to fall, but it is to let them see that their standing is by his grace, and to shew them that he is not obliged with any bond of their merit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> (which are iust none) to sust<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ine and vphold them: he dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> it also, to make thē cling the closer about him, and to seeke more earnestly for his assistance as the little child skrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>th one for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> it is falne, &amp; lieth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>wling vpon the ground: be doth it to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the and to abate their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> lets thē ral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> loue, so by their f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> he mani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esteth his wisdome &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>tegrity, and sheweth his admirable cōp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> &amp; humanity, in forgiuing and in raising them vp againe. But the fals of the reprobate kindle the coales of Gods weath against them, and further their full &amp; finall perdition: they serue to increase their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and consequently their paines: they serue for punishments sometimes of former offences: and by committing one sinne in the neck of an other, they put out the light of nature, they harden their hearts, and sit themselues for further wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, euen as the stithy becomes the


<pb facs="31"/>
harder by striking. I graunt indeed, that oftentimes they are greuously galled &amp; perplexed with their sins. But it is not a sorow that causeth repentance vnto sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation neuer to be repented of, And v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>areth with them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> it doth with yong Hat-makers, or such as vse to play at Stoole-ball. In the beginning their fingers may blister, and their hands may ake, but after a while, their hands become <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ard and brawny, and are well armed for such works, and the more they practise, the lesse paine they feele: so the custome of sinning takes away the sense of the sin. And as y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> dropsy mā, the more he drinks, the drierhe is: so the reprobate, the more he falleth, the more he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nsieth falling.</p>
   <p>It is not possible that any of the Elect <note place="margin">Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i. 29</note> should be damned, or that any of them being soundly conuerted, should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>holly for a time (much lesse for euer) fall away from God and perish. For Gods decree of <note n="a" place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 19.</note> Election is constant, and his <note n="b" place="margin">Isa. 46. 10.</note> counsell shall stand. <note n="c" place="margin">Iohn 6. 37.</note>
      <hi>Him that commeth vnto me,</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>I cast not away,</hi> that is, I do not cast off or eiect him, that embraceth


<pb facs="32"/>
me with the hand and armes of a liuely faith, and testifieth the same with the fruites thereof. And whom God hath predestin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ted, called and iustified, them <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8. 30.</note> he will also glorifie. For his couenant with them is an <note n="e" place="margin">Iere. 32 40.</note> euerlasting couenant, and his gifts are w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>hout <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 11. 29.</note> repentance. <note n="g" place="margin">Cant. 8 6.</note>
      <hi>Loue is strong as death: much water can not q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>h loue, neither can the floods drowne i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</hi> Prety, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, was neuer prety. And true faith (though as small as a graine of must<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d seed) cannot altogether vanish and bee extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed: For God will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> it, hee will not <note n="h" place="margin">Isa. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 3.</note> breake the bru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed reed, nor quench the smoking flexe. Indeed faith may be shaken, but it can not be shiuered in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces▪ it may be mooued, but it can not be remooued: it may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and wax dry, but it can not weare away quite and die: Sathan may si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t and towze it, he may lay siege against it, but he cannot sack it, he shall neuer destroy it. The Sunne may set and for a time lye hid, but it remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the heauen: and faith may be couered (as fire with ashes) but yet it


<pb facs="32"/>
continueth in the heart. The fish may be in the water, though she floate not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes aloft. There is sap in the roote, when the leaues are faine off, and the top naked, and in appearance withered. So faith liueth, though it haue lost some signes of life. The S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ne and the Moone may be indeed eclip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> euen so the eye of faith may be dimmed. But as the Sun and Moone do not perish in their eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, nor lose their light for euer; euen so faith doth not perish when it is eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed: It may indeede receiue a buff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t, whereby it may (as it were) reele and stagger and fall to the ground, and there for a time lye like a man in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>woone, or fit of the falling sicknes, but it cannot dye; because God, the wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing as well of spirituall life, as of naturall, will neuer forsake it. The Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s may suffer an ebbe, but it is not st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rke dry at any time: so faith may come to a very low ebbe, but yet it will haue water al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>yes in the bottome. As a great riuer may befrozen ouer with hard ice for a time, and so co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with snow, as that it seemeth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther


<pb facs="33"/>
a Rock then a Riuer, or like to other ground; euen so faith may be (as it were) frozen ouer with thicke y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, and so hild with the snow of sinne, as that it may not bee seene at all for a time. But as there is water in the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer which is deepe; notwithstanding the frost, though it be not seene: euen so there is life in faith, though for a time it do not appeare. But when the weather is broken, when the holy Ghost begins to make a thawe, with the fresh fire of his grace, when the South wind blowes hard, and when the Sunne of righteousnes hath melted the ice, then Faith will appeare, and flow amayne, as a Riuer after rayne, and as the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters do after a thawe. Then grace, which was couered before, will shine bright and cleare, as the Sunne doth after a showre, as is euident by the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Peter.</hi> Moreouer, our Sauiour sayeth, that his sheepe shall <note n="i" place="margin">Iohn 10. 28.</note>
      <hi>neuer perish.</hi> The <note n="k" place="margin">Isa. 40. 11.</note> Lord (sayth <hi>Esay)</hi> shall feede his flock like a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard: he shall gather the Lambs with


<pb facs="33"/>
his arme, and carry them in his bosome. Hee <note n="l" place="margin">Psal. 23. 2.</note> maketh them to rest in greene pastures, and leadeth them by the still waters. <note n="m" place="margin">Psa. 41 12.</note> He vpholdeth them in their integrity, and doth set them before his face for euer. As <note n="n" place="margin">Zach. 4. 9.</note>
      <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> layed the foundation of the Temple, and did finish it: so <note n="o" place="margin">Phil. 1. 6.</note> God that hath begun his good worke in the temple of our hearts, will finish it vnto the end. They can not be taken from him by strong hand. <note n="p" place="margin">Iohn 10 29, 30.</note> For hee is greater then all, and his will to saue them is answerable to his power: therefore hee sayth, <note n="q" place="margin">Iohn 10 28.</note> Hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vnto them euerlasting life; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding also, that none shall pluck them out of his hands. Master <hi>Tinda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> sayth well: <hi>Christ is thine, and all his deeds are thy deeds; neither canst thou be damned, except he be damned with thee.</hi> They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not perish by seduction; for the Elect cannot be <note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 24. 24.</note> seduced, Neither can they of themselues fall away. For <note n="s" place="margin">Iere. 32. 40.</note> God hath put his feare in their hearts, that they shall not depart from him. A man may for a time cease to laugh, but he cannot


<pb facs="34"/>
lose the faculty of laughing. The drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard loseth sometimes the vse of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, but the faculty neuer; so the graces of God may be crazed, but yet they are not vtterly abolished. Finally, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saketh not them, For his loue is <note n="t" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>re. 31. 3.</note> euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting: those whom he loueth once, he <note n="u" place="margin">Ioh. 13. 1.</note> loueth to the end. <note n="w" place="margin">Rom. 8. 39.</note> Nothing can separate vs from hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> loue. It is like the <note n="x" place="margin">Deut. 29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Israe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ites</hi> shooes, which waxed not old. It is like the tree of life: he that once truly t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th of it, shall not dye eternally. As a Father doth not reiect his Child when he hath broken his face by falling, but rather seekes a playster: he will (it may be) lash him, but he will not leaue to loue him. Euen so our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dealeth with his Children. For he hath sayd, that hee will <note n="y" place="margin">Iere. 32. 40.</note> neuer depart from them to do them good: hee <note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 13 6.</note> will not faile them nor forsake them: but <note n="a" place="margin">1. Thess. 5. 23, 24</note> will sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ctifie them throughout, and keepe them s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fe vnto the comming of Christ. Indeed our enemies may wound vs, but they shall not win: they may vex vs, but they shall not vanquish: they


<pb facs="34"/>
may perhaps presse vs, but they shall not oppresse vs: they may cut vs, but they cannot kill vs. For GOD, who is greater then all, will not suffer vs to be <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 13. Psa, 127 4. Priuil. 30. Ioh. 1. 12 Math. 14 31. Rom. 4. 20. 2. Cor. 5. 1.</note> tempted aboue our power, and is very vigilant for vs. For, he that keepeth <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> neither slumbereth nor sleepeth.</p>
   <p>The Elect may assuredly be perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this life, that they shall be saued in the life to come. For a speciall and certaine perswasion of Gods mercy, is the very heart and marow, the life and soule of true faith. Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> sayth, <hi>We know that if our earthly house of this tabernacle be destroyed, we haue a building of God,</hi> that is, <hi>an house not made with hands, eternall in the heauens.</hi> Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, if it be not possible for men to know that they shal be saued, how could Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> say, <hi>These things haue I written vnto you that beleeue in the name of the Sonne of God, that ye may know that ye haue eternall life.</hi> To conclude, if it were impossible for a man to be in his consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence assured, that hee is the elect and faithfull seruant of God, effectually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led


<pb facs="35"/>
in time, &amp; orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ned to glory before time; to what end should <hi>Dauid</hi> inquire who of all professors are the true mēbers <note place="margin">Psal. 15.</note> of the Church mili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>āt on earth, and shall be of the Church triumphant in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens? and to what end shuld he set down <hi>y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
      </hi> marks, wherby they may be discerned? And to what purpose should <hi>Paul</hi> exhort vs to prooue our selues whether we are in the faith? Or why should he speake af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this maner vnto vs, <hi>Know ye not your owne selues, how that Iesus Christ is in you,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. Cor. 13. 5. 2. Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 1. 10.</note>
      <hi>except ye be reprobates?</hi> And wherefore should <hi>Peter</hi> bid vs be diligent to make our calling &amp; election sure? It remaineth therfore as an vndoubted truth, that the elect may be truly assured of their ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and may assuredly know (without speciall reuelation) that they shall be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Now this is a very great prerogatiue, and the greater; first, because it may be iuioyed to the end: secondly, because the longer it is inioyed, the better we are as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured: thirdly, it brings with it wōderfull ioy. For what greater ioy can a man here inioy, then to be assured of eternall ioy?


<pb facs="35"/>
Fourthly, this assurāce makes a mā mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> wary, and more vnwilling to displease God by sin, wherby nothing is deserued but damnation. Fiftly, this priuiledge is the more excellent, because they whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> wāt this knowledge altogether, can haue no solid consolation. And as for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate; they haue no more to do with this certenty, then they haue with salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As it is impossible for them to be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, so it is impossible for thē to be truly assured of their saluation. He that drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, may think he walketh, eateth, tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, seeth, whē he doth not: and he may think he is awake, whē he is not. So these dreamers may think that they shalbe sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and may sooth vp themselues as if they were cock-sure, but they are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. He that is in a swoone, doth some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times perswade himself that he seeth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny strange sights, but his perswasion is false: so the Reprobates may thinke all things runne round, they may perswade themselues they are in Gods fauour and shall be saued: but as the things are false whereof they do perswade themselues:


<pb facs="36"/>
so their perswasion must needs also be as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>alse. It is but a spirituall swoone, or d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sh, dreaming, or dizzinesse, that doth so blinde their eyes, and beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>le them.</p>
   <p>The Elect only shall be raysed vp of Christ as a Sauiour and Redeemer. And <note place="margin">Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>i. 31</note> when all people shall be gathered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, he will separate his Elect from the Reprobate. The Elect shall be placed on his right hand, and vpon them he <note place="margin">Math. 25</note> will pronounce the white and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table sentence of absolution. On the contrary, he will raise vp the Reprobate, as he is a terrible and dreadfull Iudge, he will set them on his left hand like Goates, and pronounce against them the dolefull and black sentence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. And more also, which may increase their griefe; he will vse the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect for the approbation of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon them, and vpon the wicked Angels also. They shall attend vpon him, as Iustices do vpō the Iudge at the Assises, and shall approoue his sentence; and this Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, when as he <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 2, 3.</note>
      <pb facs="36"/>
sayth, that the Saints shall iudge the world and the wicked Angels. Now as this is a great honour vnto the Elect, to sit as Iudges vpon the wicked: so it must needes minister no small griefe vnto them, to be (as it were) iudged of those whome they before haue derided, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, nicknamed, and persecuted. Thus we haue seene many notable pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges of Gods elect and faithfull chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. If <hi>Balaam</hi> prophecied of the <hi>Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> when he looked vpon them dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling according to their tribes, saying, <hi>How goodly are thy tents, O Iacob, and thy</hi>
      <note place="margin">Nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 24 5.</note>
      <hi>habitations, O Israel;</hi> wee may well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture, that God will exceedingly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest his loue vnto vs hereafter in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, seeing h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e hath honoured vs so highly in this vale of misery, and will grace vs so much after the resurrect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>, in our entrance into heauen, as that we shall iudge the World and the Angels.</p>
   <p>The last priuiledge of the Elect, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <note place="margin">Priuil. 32.</note> I will intreate, is, that God will giue them the kingdome of heauen and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting life. <hi>Feare not, little flock</hi> (sayth <note place="margin">Luk 12. 32.</note>
      <pb facs="37"/>
our Shepherd) <hi>for it is your Fathers plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to giue you the kingdome.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> saith, that God doth glorify those whom <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 30. Iohn 10. 28.</note> he hath predestinated, called, &amp; iustified. Our Sauiour saith, that he giueth eternall life vnto all his Sheep. As <hi>Ioshua</hi> brought the children of <hi>Israel</hi> into earthly <hi>Canaan:</hi> so Christ Iesus our <hi>Ioshua,</hi> will one day bring all true <hi>Israelites</hi> into celestiall <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> &amp; will crowne thē with immortall glory. To describe this bless<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d estate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, surpasseth mans capacitie, whole knowledge is as yet imperfect. For <hi>Paul</hi> out of <hi>Esay</hi> sayth, that the eye hath not seene, and the eare hath not heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Cor. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 64. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> came it into mans heart to thinke of those things which God hath prepared for them that loue him. Neuerthelesse it may in part be described, according as God hath reuealed it in his word to vs. In this estate the Elect shal be deliuered and set free frō all wants &amp; miseries, frō sin, and from all the temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than. <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>1 4.</note> They shall haue perpetuall fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with the blessed Trinity, &amp; the holy Angels. They shall haue perfic know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,


<pb facs="37"/>
and they shal perfectly loue God, <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 12.</note> who will be all in all vnto them. Their hearts shall be full fraught with endlesse &amp; vnvtterable ioyes. Their toungs shall continually sound out the prayses of God. They shal celebrate an euerlasting <note place="margin">Isa. 66. 23. Phil. 3. 21.</note> Sabboth, seruing God most purely for euer and euer. Their bodies shall be like to the glorious body of Christ; bright &amp; beawtifull, nimble, &amp; full of agility, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued &amp; susteined by the immediate po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God, without meat, drinke, sleep, labor, phisick; and therfore <hi>Paul</hi> calls thē <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 44.</note> spirituall. Lastly, to make vp their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>; the place of their abode shalbe in the highest heauēs, where there is no paines <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 1.</note> but pleasures, no wo but weale, no sinne but seruing of God, no griefe but glory, no want but welth, no sicknes but helth, no death but life, no iarres but ioyes, no wars but peace, no treachery but truth, no fighting but triumphing, &amp; no chāge, but euerlasting continuance. When a man hath liued so many thousand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeres in all y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> pleasures of paradise, as there are hours in a M. millions of yeres,


<pb facs="38"/>
he shall not atteine vnto the end, for the end is endlesse, and the time is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out time. But on the other side, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate are seuered from the solacious sight and comfortable presence of God. Their fellowship is with the Diuell and his angels in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ell fire, where they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakably tormented in soule and body, with endlesse, easelesse, and remedilesse torments. Their life is death, and their death is life, a dying life, and a liuing death. When they haue spent so many yeeres in paynes, as there be stars in the Skye, moats in the Sunne, sands on the shoare, and fishes in the seas, they shall be as farre from the end, as they were the first day: for the time is infinite, their damnation is euerlasting, &amp; their death shall neuer be put to death: their worme shall not dye, their fire shall neuer be <note place="margin">Isa. 66. 24.</note> put out, neither shall they be put out with it. But as the Salamander is alwaies in the fire, and neuer wasteth: so the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked shall bee continually scorched in hell-fire, and yet shall neuer be consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> then (Beloued) you see the


<pb facs="38"/>
Charter of the Saints in part. No earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Monarch can graunt such a one vnto his Subiects, as God hath giuen freely to his Elect. All the Countries, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and Cities that haue beene, are, and shall be, can not shew such digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, such royalties, and such immunities giuen them by man, as I haue shewed to belong to Gods Elect, and obedient children. The consideration of these be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and priuiledges should mooue vs, First, to acknowledge and lawd Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite loue. Secondly, in way of thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes to dedicate our soules and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, and all that we haue, vnto GOD. Thirdly, to admire the condition of Gods children. Fourthly, to be afrayd to disgrace them, whom the Lord doth so grace and countenance. Fiftly, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe couragiously all aduerse blasts, and all the crosses of this life. Sixtly, to alienate our hearts from the world. Seuenthly, to roll our care vpon God, and to rely vpō his prouidence. Eightly, to desire the comming of Christ, and not to feare death too múch: The soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner


<pb facs="39"/>
we dye, the sooner we come to our crownes. Lastly, the cōsideration of these benefits and priuiledges, should stir vs vp to seeke by all meanes to be enrolled amongst them, and neuer to rest, till we be in some measure certaine, &amp; certainly perswaded, that we are elected, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained to saluation. Whē <hi>Ahashuerosh</hi> had honoured <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and shewed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour vnto the Iewes, the Scripture sayth <note place="margin">Hest. 8. 7</note> that much people of the land became Iewes. So, seeing the Lord hath thus dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the Elect, let vs behaue our selues like them, and labour to be accounted of their company. <hi>Claudius Lysias</hi> gaue a great summe of money for the freedome <note place="margin">Act. 22. 28.</note> of the Romanes; how much more ought we to seeke for these freedomes and roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties, which do more surpasse the other, then the heauen doth the earth, and the precious pearle doth the poorest pibble. They are not indeed to be named, or compared together, and yet these may be had without money, though they can not be had by money. And thus much for the Priuiledges.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="39"/>
I come now briefly to set downe the notes of Election vnto life, and to shew how a man may come to be truly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded in his conscience, that he shall be saued. Let a man that would attaine to the knowledge of his election vnto sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, 1. heare the word of God often and attentiuely. For faith, whereby wee <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 17.</note> are perswaded of Gods speciall grace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, is ordinarily wrought by hearing of the word preached. 2. Let him wage warre with his infidelity, and let him not listen to Sathan tempting him to doubting, or desperation. 3. Let him beware of pride and presumption, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trusting to his owne goodnes, nor obliuious of Gods infinite iustice. 4. Let him often and earnestly pray for this benefit, and desire that GOD would giue him his Spirit, which may witnes with him that hee is the chosen childe of God. 5. Let him reuerently receiue the Sacrament, and meditate often of his Baptisme. For the Sacraments are pledges of Gods loue, and serue to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease our faith. Hee that receiueth


<pb facs="40"/>
them with an honest and humble heart, may assure himselfe of the remission of his sinnes, and of the saluation of his soule. Lastly, let him expend and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">6. Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>g with thee.</note> cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>der the notes of Election to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, by the which a man may know that hee is ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ined to be saued. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. The Iaylour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> what hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ould do to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>ed; they made him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eeue in the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, and thou shalt be saued.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <note place="margin">Act. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ue o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> for theyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>ty: <hi>We know</hi> (say<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h <hi>Iohn) that we are transl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>d f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>om death to life, because we</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Iohn 3. 14.</note>
      <hi>loue the brethren.</hi> Thirdly, the feare of God, where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y wee are loth to offend him, chiefly, because we loue him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Blessed is the man that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>12 1.</note>
      <hi>the Lord;</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Blessed, then Elected. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>y, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rty confe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sion, and lothing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nnes. <hi>He that confesseth and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saketh</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prou. 28 13.</note>
      <hi>his sinnes, shall finde mercy</hi> But God vouc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>afeth his speciall mercy only to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> people, Fif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly, confidence and affianc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in God, <hi>O Lord of hosts, blessed is</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal 84. 12.</note>
      <pb facs="40"/>
      <hi>the man that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> in thee.</hi> The condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Reprobates is cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ed. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle sayth, Our confidence hath great <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 35.</note> recompence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> reward. Sixtly, sincere and true calling vpon the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me of God. For <hi>Paul</hi> sayth, <hi>Whosoeuer shall call vpon</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>0. 13.</note>
      <hi>the Name of the Lord, shall be saued.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenthly, carefull and constant indeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to keepe all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he commandements of God. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>Blessed are they that do h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>
      <note place="margin">Reuel. 22. 14.</note>
      <hi>commandements, that their right may be in the tree of life, and may enter in through the gates into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ity.</hi> As the Lord promised to establish the kingdome of <hi>Salomon,</hi> if <note place="margin">1. Chron. 28. 7.</note> he did constantly indeuour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> keepe his commandements: so the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>e Lord will establish vs for euer in the kingdome of heauen, if we will indeuour constantly to serue and obey him. Eightly, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ient bearing of affliction for the truths <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ke. <hi>Blessed are they</hi> (sayth Christ) <hi>which suffer</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 10.</note>
      <hi>persecution for righteousnes s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>: for theirs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s the kingdome of heauen</hi> Nint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>y, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest and harty desire to be w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>hed in the blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d of Christ, and to be inu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sted in the white robes of his righteousnesse. <hi>Blessed</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <pb facs="41"/>
      <hi>are they which hunger and thirst for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes, for they shall be filled. To him that</hi>
      <note place="margin">Reuel. 21. 6.</note>
      <hi>is a thirst, I will giue of the well of the water of life freely,</hi> Tenthly, Christian humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and pouertie of spirit, when a man seemeth naked and base in his owne sight, and ascribeth all to Gods grace. <hi>Blessed are the poore in spirit, for theirs is the kingdome of heauen.</hi> Eleuenthly, a lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting <note place="margin">Math. 5. 3</note> and longing after the comming of Christ. <hi>Paul</hi> sayth, that the righteous Iudge will giue a crowne of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> vnto all those that loue his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Twelfthy, <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 15. Psalme asketh the Lord who shall dwell in his tabernacle, and rest on his holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine? and receiued answere as it were by oracle frō God, that he shall, who walks vprightly, and worketh righteousnes, and speaketh the truth frō his heart. And <hi>Peter</hi> hauing cōmanded vs to make our election and calling sure, addeth, saying, that if we do <hi>These things, wee shall neuer fall,</hi> but shall be sure and certaine. Now <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 10.</note> what these things are, he sheweth, to wit, that we adorne our hearts and liues with <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 5, 6, 7.</note>
      <pb facs="41"/>
vertue, knowledge, tēperance, godlines, &amp; loue. To cōclude, he that is sure of his Adoption, may be also certaine of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection: for none are adopted, but such as are elected. Now a man may know his Adoption, if he find in himselfe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of an obediēt &amp; louing son. I will set downe some. 1. Property. As a little child, whether in learning good, or lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing euill, is either woon by a faire word, or awed by a check, or feared by a frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning looke, or allured by a trifling gift, or stilled by seeing an other beatē before him, or else quieted by a rod; euē so Gods childrē are either affected by his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, or allured by his mercies, or awed by his threats, or skared by his frowning coūtenāce, or humbled by his correcting of others, or by his rod which is vpō their owne backs. 2. A good and wise child is very desirous to know his fathers minde or will, that so he may best know how to please &amp; humour him; and such is <hi>y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
      </hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of Gods child. <hi>Iob</hi> maketh it the note of a wicked mā, to affect <hi>y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
      </hi> ignorāce <note place="margin">Iob. 21. 14.</note> of Gods waies. 3. A good child knowing


<pb facs="42"/>
that he hath vniustly grieued his father, will not be quiet till they be good friends againe. 4. He laboureth to resemble his father in his rare and excellent vertues. 5. Hee will beare a blow at his fathers hands, (though he skorne to put it vp at an other mans,) and whē his father hath chidden or corrected him, he will not run for comfort to his fathers desperate &amp; sworne enemies. 6. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th not a seruant or brother that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>ore laborious and circumspect in his fathers businesse, then himselfe is. 7. He caryeth a thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful heart toward his father for his fatherly gifts. 8. He is glad to know his fathers p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, his lands &amp; lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es (if there be any) specially if he be an h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>e. 9. He longeth to se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> his father, and to heare of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of him in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> absence. 10. He maketh much of those loue-tokens which his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath giuē him to keep for a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of him, or for a signe of his loue. 11. He cannot without griefe indure to see his father in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ured or abused by any. 12. He hath a sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>all regard of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers credit. 13. He reioyceth at his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers


<pb facs="42"/>
prosperity. 14. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>keth his fathers company, he listeneth to his words, &amp; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to talke vnto him. 15. He loueth his mother entirely, he affecteth his brethrē and sisters, though it be but for his fathers sake. 16. He hateth the fellowship of his fathers inturious and vniust enemies, be is a friend to all his fathers faithfull friends, he contemne▪ n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. 17. He cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>eth vnto his father in the time of tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ble, and doth not cast him off. These are properties of graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, wife, and godly childre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> being applied to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e purpose in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hey are so many infallible notes of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> dutifull and louing child. Those which find them in their hearts &amp; liues, may truly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly assure themselues and know, that they are the sons and daughters of God, elected before the foundation of the world, to euerlasting life and happinesse. Those which after diligent search finde them not to be in them, must not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaire, though they may iustly indeed sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect and bewaile their estates; but let them flye to the throne of grace with hungry hearts, and incessantly desire fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>our,


<pb facs="43"/>
remembring also to vse all meanes whereby all these foresaid graces and gracious conditions may be generated, nourished, and augmented in them.</p>
   <p>These things (right Worshipfull and Beloued) I haue here set downe as a Preface to the treatise following, for your furtherance and encouragement, and being the first fruits of my labours, in this kind I do present and giue them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, in testimony of mine hearty loue, and earnest desire of your Christian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse in knowledge and in godlinesse. The God of peace, that brought againe from the dead our Lord Iesus Christ, the great Shepherd of the sheep, through the blood of the euerlasting couenant, make you perfect in all good works, to do his will, working in you that which is pleasing in his sight, through Iesus Christ; to whom be praise for euer and euer, Amen. Fauers-ham. Iune. 20. 1606.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in Christ Iesus.
Thomas Tuke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>