<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶Grace peace and mercy from God our father, and the Lorde Iesus our Sauiour, be with the beloued Reader in the Lorde.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103723_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04511</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14638</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103723</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶Grace peace and mercy from God our father, and the Lorde Iesus our Sauiour, be with the beloued Reader in the Lorde.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermo [n] made by Iohn Chrisostome : patriarche of Constantinople, of pacience, of ye end of ye world, and of ye last iudgeme [n] t. Wherunto is added an other homelie made by Iohn Brentius of the vertue of Christes resurrectio [n] tra [n] slated into Englishe by Thomas Sa [m] pson</title>
                 <author>John Chrysostom, saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 <publisher>Hill (Hyll, van den Berghe, Montanus), Nicholas (Niko—laos).</publisher>
                            <publisher>Sheffield (Shefelde), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶Grace peace and mercy from God our father, and the Lorde Iesus our Sauiour, be with the beloued Reader in the Lorde.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hree thynges there are, whiche Christ our sauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure taught con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the daye of iudgemente: Fyrste to what ioyes the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full shalbe receyued: Secondly what horryble paynes the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythfull and wycked shal abid: Thyrdely howe sodayne the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng of that daye shall be. And of this sodayne commyng he ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth in the gospelles muche and
<pb facs="3"/>
large mencion, and compareth it to the comming of the floude, to the burnyng of Sodō, to a ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenyng whiche (as it were in the twīcklīg of an eie) goeth from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> east vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> west, to a thefe y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth on a mannes house in the nyght tyme, and sayth he, <hi>In such an houre as ye thynke not,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>4.</note>
      <hi>VVill the sonne of manne come,</hi> thus not she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng when the day shall be, he dothe teache no more but that sodaynely it wyll come. Thys thyng he dyd so diligently teach, forseing that men wolde be slug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gardes &amp; idle, neither watching for the daye, nor yet preparinge them selues to the iudgemente, therfore he stil cried <hi>VVatche VVat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che,</hi> both signifing that he wold not haue vs taken vnwares, and also teachyng vs that we should be faythful seruauntes in our vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacyon,
<pb facs="3"/>
ministring righteousnes towardes our brethren, and not become tirauntes and bellye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gods, as they do whiche thynke not at al of his cōmyng: that we myght also haue oyle in our lam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes and oure lampes burnynge, suche fruites of faithe that men may se our good workes &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryfie the father whiche is in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, and so meete the Lorde our bridegrome in the ayre, to enter with him into the kyngdome of heauen. This was one of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Christes teaching concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng this matier. Nowe a man wolde thinke, that if there hadde neuer bene any more spoken of this thynge, this warning &amp; tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynge of Christ had been suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to haue made all men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, &amp; to make vs also moste chiefely whiche are in the latter
<pb facs="4"/>
endes of the world, circumspect, watchinge and prepared accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyngly to receyue the Lorde.</p>
   <p>But neyther his teachynge, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the same doctrine taught by his Apostles, whiche we reade and heare euery daye, neyther y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wryting of the olde fathers frō age to age of this mater, neither the preching and writing in this our tyme, &amp; that more is though that all the sygnes and tokens whiche shoulde go before that daye are al ready come and pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, yet can none of all these thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges make vs to watche, and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare our selues for that daye, so greate is our synnefull securitie. What I praye you wyll be the ende of this our secure and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les lyfe and synnynge? Forsothe this, that it shal be rewarded w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the payne due for the contempte
<pb facs="4"/>
of God, that our partes must be with the tirannous and flesshlye seruaunt, and with the sloggishe careles &amp; folyshe virgins, which is in that vtter darkenes where we shall haue no other chere but wepyng and gnashyng of teeth. This is an vndoubted truth.</p>
   <p>The mouthe of the Lorde hath spoken it. Let all them therfore that do desyre to be partakers of the kyngdome of God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them selues, forsake synne, labour for fayth, and set on fyre their lampes gyuyng forthe the frutes of faith, and consyder the day of the Lord to be nowe nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer at hande then euer it was, whē we shal al arise, both good, and bad. Watche therfore. The which that thou maiest be occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> better to do, I gyue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the (good Reader) translated
<pb facs="5"/>
into Englishe these two litle ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons, one of Chrisostome, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che doth emongest manye other notable lessons full ernestly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyshe thee of that daye: The other of Iohn Brentius, whych teacheth the vertue and effect of Christes resurrection. Be thou therfore (good Reader) by the reading of these once again war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to prepare thy self vnto that day, &amp; so frō henceforth now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue thy self, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> when the Lorde shal come y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> maist be founde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable, &amp; so able to stadde in his sight, that thou maiest en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with him into glory: Which graūt vnto vs all, that Lorde, that shal iudge vs al, to whom be glory for euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>