<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103779_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00261</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1035</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103779</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A bryefe and plaine declaracion of certayne sente [n] ces in this litle boke folowing : to satisfie the consciences of them that haue iudged me therby to be a fauourer of the Anabaptistes</title>
                 <author>I. B.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the reader.</head>
   <p>AFter I had setfurth thys lytle booke to the intent that the faythfull reader might therby be sterred vp and proud ked to pray wout ceasyng, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the detractours and defamours of the faythfull professours of y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> faith of Christ, might ether be made fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers &amp; sette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> furth of the same: other els so cōfounded and dashed out of countenaūce through the Godlye conuersation of the true and vnfayned professours of the pure Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e doctrine, that they might not for verye worldly shame once open their lippes to speak anye euyl worde of them: incontinent the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl who ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>h alwayes indeuoured to stoppe and hynder the glory of God and the profyte of hys membres (the faythfull congregation) put into the myndes of certayne learned men, (who also are ernest defenders &amp; setters furth of the truthe) to reporte and affyrme thys my facte, to bee a mayntenaunce and vpholdyng of the Anabaptistes opinion, whiche denied it to be lawful to Baptise the Infantes &amp; yong children which are not of yeares of descresion to know and confesse the fayth of Iesu Christ Not muche vnlyke is this subtyle practise of oure gostlye aduersarie, vnto that whyche he wrought in the tyme of Christes passion. He dyd then beate into the head of Pilates wyfe suche kynde of dreames: that she was thereby moued to send worde to her husbande that in no case he shoulde geue sentence agaynst that iust man Iesus Chryst, whom the Iewes had than broughte before hym, requiryng hym to geue sentence of death vpon hym, because he sayde that he was the sonne of God. Thys
<pb facs="2"/>
proceaded not of anye desyre that he had, that Pilate should not commyt so haynous a faut as to geue sentence agaynst that most innocēt and immaculate lambe Iesu Chryst: but of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> greate ranker &amp; malice that he bare towardes man, who could not otherwyse be restored thē by the bloudshed of that most pure and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent lambe Iesu Chryst. Euen so (most dearly beloued) in this present practise, our gostly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy intented not to roote out the erroure of the Anabaptistes oute of the myndes of men: but because he perseiueth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the very name of thē is so odious to y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> faithfull y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they thinke their bokes vnworthy to be had among christē mē: he thought y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he myghte by no meanes so sone bryng me out of credite w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the cōgregatiō as if he myght procure some man (whose au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie is greate in the congregation) to geue me the name of a fauourer of that moost wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and dyuelish opinion: and so to cause mē to refrayne this boke, least they should by the readyng therof, take any vtilitie or profyt.</p>
   <p>But, as the spirit of God shalbe my guyde, so wyl I declare, not onely that I am none of the fauourers and maintainers of that desta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errour, but also that I do (as muche as in me lieth) impugne and resist the same, so that, that wicked serpent, shalbe by the same mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes defeated of his purpose: by whiche he in tended to haue spoyled the of thy commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Fyrst thou shalt note that I am no fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of them or theyr opinions, for that I shall playnelye declare that the scriptures whyche they aledge, make nothynge for their purpose And thē, that I do in al that I may impugne
<pb facs="3"/>
them, by that I shal endeuour to establysh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> fyrmeby the scriptures: the contrarye of their opinion. For the fyrst thou shalt note, that the ground of their opiniō is vpon the order that the Euangelis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> Mark kepeth in the rehersing of the wordes of Christ to his Apostles when he sent thē to preach. Marke. xvi. Fayth saye they, dothe in the wordes of Chryst go before Bapt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>me. Necessarye is it therefore, that he that shalbe Baptised do first beleue. But the Infantes (which haue not the vse of reason) cannot vnderstande the fayth of Chryst (and muche lesse embrace and professe it) wherfore, it cannot stande with the worde of God that Infantes should be baptised. No doubt (chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten reader it is not possible that any shoulde be acceptable before God, without fayth. For so writeth Paul to the Hebrues. xi. And truth it is also, that sayth must go before baptisme, none other wyse th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n the cause proceadeth or goeth before the effect or thyng that commeth thereof, as the tree must neades be before the fruit that it beareth. And it is also infallibly true, that the Baptisme whiche is acceptable before God must neades springe out of fayth But to inferré vpon this, that the Infantes and yong chyldren oughte not to be baptised: is farwyde from the true m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>anynge of these places of scripture. And y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> shal casely appeare to theim that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>st to weygh the circumstaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the places so that thei may conceiue the whole intent and purpose of the wryter.</p>
   <p>First for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e wordes of our sauiour Christ in Mark, thei wer the word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s of commission <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>euen to the Apostles, that they shuld go into
<pb facs="3"/>
the whole world and preach the Gospell vnto all creatures. These wordes sowne, that the Apostles myght not chose them anye peculiar nacion to preach vnto, nether Iewe nor Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyle, nother Greke nor Romain. But their cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission was into al the world, yea. &amp; to preach to all creatures the Gospel of God. No naci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no estate, condicion or degree, excepted. As wel were they bound to preache to the plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man as to the prynce, as well to the labourer, as to the lorde. God hath no respect to the per son, All the sonnes of Adam are of one degree in the syght of the Lorde. Here was no menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made Infantes neither of anye other age. But I am sure ther is no man so farre wyde as once to thynke that the Apostles were here in commaunded to preache vnto Infantes. For they as beastes lacking the vse of reason cannot receiue the fayth that hath his begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of hearyng (as saynt Paull wryteth) in this text therefore is no precepte of Infantes ether for the Baptisynge of theim other elles the leauyng of them vnbaptised. The precept that is heare geuen is none other but to go in to al the world and to preach the Gospel to al nations, estates and degrees. Then is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed the promyse of the free mercye of God towardes all the worlde, that is, that whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer should beleaue and be baptised should be saued, but he that wyl not beleue shalbe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. Here is it manifest, that without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, Baptisme auayleth not. For he that wyl not beleue shalbe condempned. But heare we must beware that we do not by these wordes condemne all Infantes and yong chyldren, be
<pb facs="4"/>
cause they haue not the power to vnderstande and beleue. For this part of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> text partaineth no more vnto them, thē the other (concerning the precept of the preachyng) doth. This place of scriptur therfore, is to be vnderstanded of them onely that haue the vse of reasone to per ceiue and vnderstāde the preachyng of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell: and yet wyll not embrace it, and receyue baptisme, the signe of the washynge of theyr sinnes by the preciouse bloude of our sauiour Christe shedde for the redēption of the world. As for the other texte, that is of Paule to the Hebrues the. xi. chapit. wherin is declared that without faieth non can he acceptable to God: apparteyneth also vnto suche as are of yeres of discreciō. For in al the chapter, is ther none rehersed but such as were of age &amp; discrecion. Wherfore we maye iustly inferre herof, that it is not possible that any persone shoulde bee acceptable vnto god in hys workes, without the worke that he doeth, do proceade of a pure and sincere fayth. For as the prophet Esaye, sayth in his. lxiiii. chap. Out workes are al as the cloth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is defiled with menstruous bloud. And further, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. Paule to the Romaynes. xiiii The workes that procede not of fayth are sin Fayth it is therfore that maketh our doinges acceptable vnto God, and without fayth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng that we doo is acceptable. Wherupon I infer that excepte the congregation whych Baptise they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> chyldrē do it of faith: this their Baptisyng is synne in the syght of God, and therfore not acceptable vnto God. But if the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> do it of fayth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rusting that God shal plant in the hertes of the infantes that lyuynge fayth
<pb facs="4"/>
that may cause them to confesse his name whē they shal receyue the vse of reasō: then is this their facte no lesse acceptable before God the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> the deede of Abraham was when he vpon the fayth that he had in the promyse of God: Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusised al the males of hys housholde. For, as Circumcision was a signe or token to declare that all they that receiued it, trusted to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deamed by the Mesias that was promysed to the sayde Abraham, and as the fathers to declare thier faythful hope, dyd not onely cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumsise theim selues, but their chyldren and familes also: so is Baptisme a signe to declare that the receiuers therof, doo vnfaynedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> bloud of Chryst hath washed their sinnes, And vppon lyke trust as the fathers had, that God wyl extēd his mercy vnto their chyldren and famyly: they do baptise them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, as appeareth in the actes of the Apostles, wher is mencion made of certayne mē whose families and housholdes were Baptised whē thei, had receiued the fayth. But here it myght be sayd that in these places it is mēcioned that the whole families beleued and then receiued Baptisme. So that the infantes (whych had no beleue) remayned styll vnbaptised. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I aunswere, that if the Parentes were faithful, they coulde not chose but theyr faith would constrayne them to do as those fayth ful dyd y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> brought their chyldren vnto Christ, Marke. x. And then the Apostles I am sure were not so forgetfull but that they bare in mynde the wordes of their maister who rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thē for forbidding the children to approch hym, whych were brought by theyr faythfull
<pb facs="5"/>
parentes that he myght put hys hand on them Yea, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> doubte not but that after the example of theyr maister, they embraced the infantes declaring thē to be the inheritours of the king dome of God, and that none should enter that kyngdome: vnlesse he woulde become a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> one of them. Thus haue I declared myne opinion concernynge the Baptisme of infantes (as I trust) sufficietly to satisfy them that haue in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken me, &amp; to declare that all such sentences (in this litle boke) as doo so greatly impugne Baptisme without faith: are to be vnderstād so, that nether they that be of age ought to be Baptised without they do fyrst beleue and cō fesse Chryst: nor the infantes onles the fayth ful congregation do with one assent offer thē at the font of regeneration with ful mynd and he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>tie desire to haue them membres of the church of Christ, hauyng most sure and certayn hope that God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>oorke in thē such maner of fayth as shal cause thē at the yeares of discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to professe and folow the doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of Christ, to whom wyth the father and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> holye gost bee all honour for euer and euer▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>o be it</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>