<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE, Contayning certaine Considerations, as well for better vnderstāding the drift of this Treatise, as for auoyding all cauills, and answearing such Obiections as might be made against this Grand Protestant Iury.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103083_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15781</idno>
           <idno type="STC">26044</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103083</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE, Contayning certaine Considerations, as well for better vnderstāding the drift of this Treatise, as for auoyding all cauills, and answearing such Obiections as might be made against this Grand Protestant Iury.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe treatise : in which, is made playne, that Catholikes liuing and dying in their profession, may be saued, by the iudgement of the most famous and learned Protestants that euer were. Agaynst a minister [N.E.] who in his epistle exhorteth an honourable person, to forsake her ancient Catholike Roman Religion, &amp; to become one of his new-found-out Protestant congregation</title>
                 <author>Wright, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, xvi, 2, 3-32 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="i" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE, Contayning certaine Considerations, as well for better vnderstāding the drift of this Treatise, as for auoyding all cauills, and answearing such Obiections as might be made against this Grand Protestant Iury.</head>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The Zuinglians are to be nūbred (<hi>say the Lutherans</hi>) with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Anabaptists Nesto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians &amp; Turkes. <hi>And againe.</hi> The Zuingli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans call the Lutherās Eutichians, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwers of many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of faith. <hi>Iezler de Diuturnit. Bell. Euchar. pag. 78. Stancarus.</hi> All the Churches which those men call Reformed by the Ghospell and the Sonne of God, &amp; hold the faith of Geneua &amp; Zuricke, concerning Christ, are Ariās: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cā this he denyed, which I haue aboue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrated. <hi>So he. de Trinit. c. 8. Sturmius.</hi> By these hatefull dissentions &amp; peruerse opinions, the foundatiōs of our Religion are ouerthrowne, the chiefest articles are called in question, many heresies are brought into the Church of Christ, and the high way to Mahometisme &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme is apparently prepared. <hi>Agayne.</hi> The Lutherans (<hi>saith he</hi>) do hold the Protestant Caluinian Churches of England, France, Flanders and Scotland for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, &amp; their Martyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> for martyrs of the diuell. <hi>De ration, Cōcord. ineund. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. p. 2. &amp; 24.</hi>
      </note> FOR the better vnderstanding of what we are about to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in this Treatise; we must obserue first, that the maine drift, and scope therof, is to shew how it is farre better, and more secure to liue &amp; dye a Catholike in the Romaine Church, then a Protestant in what Congregation soeuer: not only because one of them doth <hi>condemne</hi> the other for Schismatickes, and Heretikes as vncapable of saluatiō; but also because Catholickes doe neuer affirme that Protestants liuing and dying Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stans may be saued: not for want of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="ii" facs="3"/> in Catholickes (as some doe cauill) seing they desire nothing more thē the saluation of all, but for want of true faith in Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, without the which it is impossible to please God. whereas Protestāts doe not deny, that comfort to any vertuons Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Catholike: so that for the saluatiō of<note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>or that brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> (saith D. Whyte amōg vs Protestants) <hi>ōly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth some particular mē in matters not cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>erning f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>yth</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n the way▪ pag. 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Rog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rs in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the booke of Articles. Willet Antilog pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>5. 20. D Georg Abbot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Hill. p. 101. 102. D. Doue. <hi>In matters of religiō we all agree.</hi> Persuas p. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. And if they do not agree in on faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> they be the true Church which is but o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e, &amp; hath only <hi>one Lord, one Faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme?</hi> Ephes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ntic. 6. 8. <hi>My doue is one,</hi> Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Constant▪ <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>e holy, Catholy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>, and Apostolicall Church.</hi> Cal. l 4 inst. c▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. See Suarez dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. de Ecc Sect. 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. l. de fide, spe &amp;c.</note> Catholickes, we haue not only the beliefe of Catholickes themselues, but also the iudgement of most Famous and Learned Protestants, who teach the same, eyther expressely, or at least in such tearmes, as with the help of their owne brethrē with whom they are sayd to <hi>agree,</hi> at least in all materiall points, may sufficiently be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; and in this sense are to be vnderstood the verdicts of all those which may seeme not to be so full, and sufficient as the other in this Grand Protestant Iury. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Zanchius</hi> and other Protestants af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that the Roman Church, as yet is the Church of God. Here in expresse words is not auerred, that those who liue, and die well in this Church may be saued, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelesse according to the common do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Catholikes doth plainly inough imply the possibility of saluatiō to all those who are members of such a Church. For if they cannot be saued in the Church of God, which is <hi>but one,</hi> where els should they seeke for theyr saluation? Or if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="iii" facs="3"/> but be damned in the Church of God,<note place="margin">M. Cartright. <hi>I doubt not but diuers fathers of the Greeke Church who were great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones of Free-will, are saued.</hi> M. Sparke, discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the honoring of Saints Reliques &amp; prayer for the dead, saith, <hi>VVe are not so hasty to pronoūce sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any for such errors.</hi> Acontius, cōcerning the Reall presence▪ <hi>Both those that deny it, and those that doe hold it, are in the way of Saluation.</hi> Cōcerning Transub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiatiō D. Luther writeth thus: <hi>Bread &amp; wyne are not in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Sacramēt of the Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, but the shewes or accidents of bread and wyne: for the bread is changed into the true and naturall body of Christ, &amp; the wyne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the true and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bloud of Christ.</hi> Serm. de Euch. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerninge receauing vnder one or both kinds, there is no commaundment, saith D. Luther. Concerning the Pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Supremacy, <hi>about it</hi> (saith D. Luther) <hi>he is to be borne with all.</hi> Melancton teacheth, how his <hi>Monarchy is profitable.</hi> Concerning Satisfaction. <hi>It was an error in the holy Fathers</hi> (saith D. Whitaker) <hi>yet notwithstanding they were good men and holy Fathers. Did not Iohn H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>se that worthy Champion of Christ</hi> (saith M. Francis Iohnson) <hi>&amp; other martyrs of foretymes, heare &amp; say Masse euen to their dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>g day &amp;c. Did not also diuerse of them acknowledge, some the Popes calling an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Supremacy, some 7. Sacraments, some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>uricular Confession?</hi> And Benedict Morgenstern. <hi>These things were pardonable in the Godly who held the Pope to be the Vicar of Christ, and head of the Church, the Papacy for the Church, Saintes for mediators, and the Masse for the Supper of the Lord.</hi> See the Protest. Apol. pag. 471. &amp; 684. You may find aboue three score pointes of Catholicke Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, taught by le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arned Protestants, through all the sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Section.</note> how doth such an assembly deserue to be stiled the Church of God, and not rather the Synagogue of Sathan? But if <hi>Zanchius</hi> or any other call, the Church of Rome the Church of God, although it haue some damnable errous, which hinder the profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors therof from their saluation; I hope by clearing those imagined errours from being any such barres, out of <hi>Zanchius</hi> his owne learned brethren, euery one may inferre, that <hi>Zanchius</hi> with the help of his brethren Protestants, affoardeth saluation to all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, liuing well, and dying in the Church of Rome. The helps which we haue out of learned Protestants be these: To wit that neyther the beliefe of free will, prayer to saints, the reall presence, trāsubstātiatiō, receauing vnder one or both kinds, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipping of Images, the Popes supremacy, and the monarchy of the B. of Rome, sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, merit of good workes, priuate Masse, seauē Sacramēts, or any such taught by the Roman Church, doe hinder any from being capable of their saluation: not only because they were all belieued of the holy Fathers, who notwithstanding the
<pb n="iiii" facs="4"/> belief of them haue been reputed alwayes Saints; but because diuers famous learned Protestants, brethren to all these Iury▪ men, teach the same expressely: whose names you may read in the margent, and what they say more largely in the Protestants Apology pag. 471 684. &amp;c. Which being applyed to what want soeuer occurreth in the verdicts of any named in the Iury, will make it cleare, that no such can be any impediment wherefore the same verdict ought not to passe, as currant and good. And therfore whē either <hi>Zanchius, Mornay, Serauia,</hi> or any other of these Iurers doe accuse the Church of Rome of Adultery, committing Idolatry, bringing vp children to the diuell, or of any such villanyes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the true faith, for belieuing any of these points now rehearsed; we must tell them in plaine words, that these be noe such letts as they imagine, but rather their owne false and forged crimes, meere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes, and calumniations put vpon the Church of Rome to make her odious to the commō people, or for some other base end:
<pb n="v" facs="4"/> seing their owne brethren confesse against them, saying, that the beliefe of these cānot eyther hinder their sanctity, or debarre any Catholike from obtayning their chiefest good, and euerlasting saluation; which if they had iudged to be Heresies, Idolatries, and such like abominations, it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed they would neuer teach.<note place="margin">Calu. l. 4. c. 1. n. 17.</note>
   </p>
   <p>2. Againe, we must obserue with M. Caluin, <hi>that there hath been no tyme since the creation of the world, wherin the Lord hath not had his Church, and that there shalbe also no tyme to the very end of the world wherin he shall not haue it.</hi> But now as for the Church of Rome it is certaine that it did continue the true visible church frō christ vntil the tyme of <hi>Constantine,</hi> as M. <hi>Caluin</hi> hereafter auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth: and that from <hi>Constantine</hi> vntill the tyme of <hi>Luther</hi> it neuer was interrupted is<note place="margin">M. Napier vpon the Reuelations. page 145. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 163. 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 237.</note> witnes M. Napier, who saith, that <hi>from the yeare 316. God withdrew his visible Church frō the open assemblies, to the harts of particular godly men, during the space of 1260. yeares. The Pope and his Cleargy hauing possessed the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward visible Church of Christians euen 1260. years, the true Church abyding so long latent &amp; inuisible:</hi> out of which we inferre that all whosoeuer haue been saued since Christs Church was erected, and sufficiently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>lged, haue beene saued in the Roman Church: and whosoeuer haue dyed as
<pb n="vi" facs="5"/> members cut off from her, or out of her, could neuer attaine to the hopefull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises<note place="margin">
         <hi>Calu. l 4. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. 4. D. Whitaker.</hi> Out of the Church there is no other sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>, but the seate of error &amp; pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and euerlasting destruction.</note> of their chiefest good; but miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying of their saluation could not auoide to be damned. For what M. <hi>Caluin</hi> deliuereth speaking of the visible Church is most true, to wit: <hi>That out of her lappe no remission of sinnes is to be hoped, nor any saluatiō at all.</hi> But<note place="margin">
         <hi>Milius.</hi> If Luther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ad bad orthodoxall fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪ there had byn no need of a Lutheran reformatiō. <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>o Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. Confess. Aug. art. 17. Luther saith,</hi> we dare boast that Christ was first published by vs. <hi>Epist. ad Arge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>. M. Iewell,</hi> Luther &amp; Zwinglius were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle againe the light which you had q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. <hi>Defens. Apol. part. 1 c. 7. diuis. 3. pag. 56. Pareus.</hi> In Const<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes time the Church begun to waxe fick to death, notwithstāding the Catholike Church remained. But where? In the desert, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> the world▪ withdrawne from the eyes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>en. <hi>lib. 4. de gratia &amp; lib. arb.</hi>
      </note> that there was neuer any other visible Church of God, which hath cōtinued since Christs tyme, but the Church of Rome, with her adherents, the Protestants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues confesse. For although some fondly i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine, that they had a Church; yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Luther</hi> nor <hi>Caluin,</hi> nor any other could euer point any such out, which was appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent or visible to the eye of men. For who can truly name any one Lutheran before <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> or any one Caluinist be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iohn Caluin?</hi> Verily none: and much lesse a continuall, and neuer-interrupted succession of Lutherans, or Caluinists since Christs tyme, who were not as inuisible to the world, and as vnknowne as euer were those who are as yet vnborne. A most foolish thing then it is, yea and most ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to auow that indeed there were such a company of zealous Protestants, as some are not ashamed to say, and that for aboue a thousand yeares they were all latent and inuisible: which not only is impious, and
<pb n="vii" facs="5"/> contrary to the Maiesty of the glorious<note place="margin">
         <hi>VVho will not say that it was a s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Church that had ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beginning, nor ending, no def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>nder, no reprouer, no mouth to vtter, or ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> to heare it, nor pen to write, nor place to rest in.</hi> So M. Iewell in a like mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Art. 2. diuis. 8. S. Austin, <hi>VVhat is this thou sayest? The Church to haue peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in all Nations, whē as to this end the Ghospell is preached, that it may be in all Nations? Therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the end of the world the Church i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> in all Nations, and this is the shortnes of her dayes.</hi> In Psal. 101. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>se Markes</hi> (sayth D. Willet) <hi>cannot be absent from the Church: and it is no longer a true Church thē it hath these mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s. For the only ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of them doth make a nullity of the Church.</hi> In his Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nops. pag. 69. &amp; 71. which not to haue bene among Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, for aboue a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>000. yeares wil witnes M. Nappier: but in some fashion to haue byn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in the Church of Rome is granted by M. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ny in his Verdict: which fashiō to haue bene the right and true fashion, is euinced from thence, that otherwise the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ch had perished, contrary to Christs prediction saying, <hi>The gates of Hell shall not preuayle against it.</hi> M. Caluin lib. 4. inst. c. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 4. Cal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 4. inst. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> If God did intend that the Couenant should remayne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolable, &amp; left Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme a testimony therof for Catholike children, as heere M. Caluin doth insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate; how doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> the Couen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t to this day remayne among thē in the Church of Rome? Agayne, if the fayth of Catholick parēts be sufficient to place their children in the Couen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t &amp; state of saluatiō; how much more may it be thought to establish the parents themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in that Couenāt in whom reside<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> that faith, which is so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? Moreouer, if the foundatiō of the Church halfe cast down doth remaine amōg Catholicks, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> M. Caluin teacheth, which is the true faith &amp; doctrine of Christ 1. cor. 3. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>1. who dare deny that they are in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, or that they may not be saued, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they build there vpō wood, hay, &amp; stubble, at least by fyre, seing this is the expresse doctrine of the Apostle?</note> Kingdome of Christ foretould by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; but lykewise quite opposite to that which they giue out of the essentiall notes, and markes of their church, which is the pure preaching of the Word, and the true administration of the Sacraments: which to make inuisible were rather to be thought the dreames of mad men, and bedlams, thē the solid and sound doctrine of such great Rabbins and Doctors, who for their suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vertue &amp; learning would rather be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted wise Sages by the commō people, yea &amp; to be stiled Reformers forsooth, and that of the true church of God▪ frō whence we may cōclude, that <hi>if there be no entry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lyfe, vnlesse</hi> (as M. Caluin saith) <hi>the visibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h like a Mother conceaue vs in her wombe, vnles she bring vs forth, vnles she feede vs with her breasts, finally vnles she keepe vs vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der custody, and gouernment vntill such tyme as be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ng vncloathed of mortall flesh, we shalbe like vnto Angels;</hi> and noe other visible church can be assigned since christs tyme but the church of Rome, as we haue seen: we must needes inferre, that as all whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer haue been saued hitherto, for all that
<pb n="viii" facs="6"/> tyme, were members of the Romaine church; euen so all those who desire to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue to the happy hauē of Heauen hereafter, must liue well, &amp; dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> in that church; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise they are neuer like to be partakers of that vnspeakable ioy, which is the salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their owne soules, and to liue with God for euer.</p>
   <p>3. Herehence for better vnderstāding of <hi>M. Caluin</hi> his verdict, saying, <hi>When God hath left his Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nant in France Ita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y, Germany, Spayne, England, since these Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>inces haue byn oppressed with the tyrany of Antichrist (whom he sayth is the Pope sitting in the Church of God) yet that this Couenant might remayne inuio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>able▪ first he there preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued baptisme the testimony of his Couenant;</hi> we gather that the Verdict which is set downe for him, to wit, that the Couenant of God hath remayned with them inuiolable, to be most true; for seing according to that of <hi>M. Caluin,</hi> all those who were hitherto saued, could not attayne their saluation but in the visible Church, which was and is only the Church of Rome, as we haue seene out of M. <hi>Nappier;</hi> it followeth, that in her the Couenāt of God could not but be kept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolable. Againe, if the Couenant of God was to be kept inuiolable in any company, especially in that which is the Church of
<pb n="ix" facs="6"/> Christ, the Sanctuary and Temple of God;<note place="margin">Serauia also wil help M. Caluins Verdict who saith, <hi>That the Couenant of God to this day doth remaine in the latyn Church.</hi> In defens▪ l. de gratia Minist. pag. 31. As concerning the baptizing of the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>drē o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Catholiks &amp; how they are cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned within the Couenat. Se the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test. Apol. Tract 1. Sect. 6. p. 172. 173. &amp; 174. M. Caluin. <hi>It is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called Catholicke or Vniuersall, because we cannot find two or three Churches, but that Christ must b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> torne in sunder which cannot be done. l. 4. c. 1. n. 2. But betwixt the yeare of Christ 300. &amp; 316. the Antichristian &amp; Papisticall raigne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>n, raigning vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally, &amp; without any debatable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ontradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for 1260. yeares</hi> (last past before Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) So M Napp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er vpon the Reuel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos. 37. pag. 68. And no other can be assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned to haue had this vniuersality, &amp; therfore she is the only true Church of Christ.</note> but M. <hi>Caluin</hi> enobleth the church of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me with all these titles, &amp; therfore we may well conclude in his iudgmēt, that the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of God was kept inuiolable in the Church of Rome.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, if Antichrist who is the Pope according to <hi>Caluin,</hi> doth sit in the Church of God, or which is all one, in the Church of Rome, of the which the Pope is head, &amp; the church of God be but <hi>One,</hi> as himself auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth; it cannot but follow that eyther the Couenant is kept inuiolable in the church of Rome, or no where: but to say it was kept no where, cannot be but most absurd, and therfore the other must of necessity be most true, to wit, the Verdict set down out <hi>M. Caluin,</hi> that the couenāt remayneth with them, that is, with the catholikes, and that inuiolable. Neyther can any auoyd this by obiecting, that <hi>Caluin</hi> doth not so much say that the Church, as the ruines therof, and it half throwne downe, are seene vnder the Pope: for so the church of christ saith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> had fallen, and the truth had lyed, saying, <hi>The gates of Hell shall not preuayle a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainst it.</hi> And againe, neither the <hi>Luthera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s,</hi> nor the <hi>Caluinists</hi> could be members of the true church: for the whole is fallen, and
<pb n="x" facs="7"/> the ruins of the church half thrown down, is among the Papists vnder Antichrist: if they say, they haue a new building; in that it is new, it is not christs: and who seeth not that it is better to be in the church of christ half pulled downe, then in none; seeing that ther is kept the couenant inuiolable, or els no were. To this we add, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle sayth not, that Antichrist shall sit in the ruines, or rubbish of the church; but abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutly he shall sit in the Temple of God: if thē the Temple of God be the true church as other Protestants say, and that in it he shall sit, that is, he shall raigne and gouerne as the head in the true church; how thē can the assemblies of Lutherans or caluinists be the true church? seing Antichrist shall not sit and dominiere in this? or how can the couenant be inuiolably kept in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then in the church of Rome, which is only the true church? We conclude ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that out of caluins Doctrine with the help of his brethren, his Verdict is most certayne, to wit, that the couenant of God hath remayned with the catholikes inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable, yea and in her only, and no where els, as is proued.</p>
   <p>4. Lastly we must obserue about the Verdict of <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssey Mornay,</hi> which as I find in him speaking of the church of Rome, is this.
<pb n="xi" facs="7"/>
      <hi>We deny her not the name of Church, no more</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mornay de Eccl. c. 2. As M. Caluin did proue the Church of Rome to haue fallē from the true faith of Christ, with three grosse lyes. saying that the Popes haue taught three grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous errors, to wit. <hi>That there is no God, no Christ, no Resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> Euē so Plessey Mornay following his Father Caluin, tells vs, that the Church of Rome is an Adultresse, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and bringer vp of children for the diuell. Se Caluin. l. 4. inst. c. 7. n. 27.</note>
      <hi>then the name of a man to a man, so long as he is aliue though he be neuer so sick yea we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er Spouse, in as much as she makes a part of the visible Church, so as they will suffervs vvithal to call her an adultresse. But we say she is the most heretical Church of all those that e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er were: a spouse that prouoked God to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce her a mother that bringeth vp children for the Diue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</hi> That which Plessey Mornay here saith in the commendatiō of the church of Rome we willingly admit, and haue set it downe for his Verdict: perswading our selues that he could say no lesse truth, which is more forcible then either rack, or tormēt comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lling him therunto. For otherwise no mā willingly lyeth to his owne shame; nor freely cōfesseth that which ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his owne cause. But what he vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth against the Church of Rome, for being accursed and anathematized by her, for so many errors and heresies, both in <hi>Luther</hi> &amp; <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> and other old rotten hereticall<note place="margin">Se F. Persons Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Triall, with his defence therof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Plessy, and O. E by N. D. <hi>Semel mendax semper praes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>mitur mendax.</hi> Glossa. Admitten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ū in l. Si cui crimen §. 1. ff. de Accusation. Alciat. &amp; Menoch.</note> Rake-hells of former times, we cannot so easily belieue; but rather think thē no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then notorious vntruthes, and meere slaunders, as proceeding from him who had a great talent in this black Art of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; which publickely was made knowne to his eternall shame by cardinall <hi>Perone,</hi>
      <pb n="xii" facs="8"/> before the most Christian King and Court<note place="margin">Luther. <hi>VVhosoeuer is once taken in a lye, know most certainly that he is not of God but ought to be suspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in all thinges.</hi> In Assert. Teuton. art. 25. But Plessy Mornay was conuinced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King of Frā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in 9. one day, and the exception that the Cardinall tooke agaynst him did cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne 4000. as is to be seene in the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aboue cyted. <hi>The Diuell hath his Prophets</hi> (saith Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ullian) <hi>whose badg &amp; mark is falsity &amp; ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, so that it must of necessity fall, whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is built vpon such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> ground.</hi> de praescr. c. 40.</note> of France; and therfore we purposely haue forborne to disgrace the Iury with any such foule and fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>thy stuffe, as he setteth downe in the latter part of his sentence, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>it is folly</hi> (sayth his learned Brother Vorstius) <hi>to bring in the guilty as vvitnesses in their ovvne cause,</hi> or rather to bring in one that hath byn condemned, not once, but so often, to rage, rayle, and lye, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly against his true and lawfull Iudge, but also against many other Catholickes, Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, Princes, Kings and Emperours, who all according to Plessey, should haue byn bred and borne bastards by an Adultresse, and brought vp children Idolatours by an hereticall harlot for the Diuell. But (o my Plessey) I pray thee how could she be an Adultresse, against whom Hell▪ gates were foretold neuer to preuayle? or how could that Church be Hereticall, which neuer was condemned eyther by any lawfull ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, or prouinciall Councell? or by any other iust commanding power? or how could she bring vp children to the Diuell, or be an Idolatresse, who hath brought vp all to God, that euer were brought to him since the first erecting of the Church of Christ, as we haue shewed before. These then are your malicious imputations, and
<pb n="xiii" facs="8"/> not those glorious tytles becōming Christs vnspotted Spouse, and her, who hath byn accompted alwayes the sacred Sanctuary, and the holy Temple of the liuing God. And therfore detesting your impieties, we must rather giue eare and harken to that holy Byshop and glorious Martyr S. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> who speaking of the Church wryteth<note place="margin">S. Cyprian de vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Eccl.</note> thus. <hi>One Mother</hi> (sayth he) <hi>there is by the fecundity of her issu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> copious and fertile: by her increase vve are borne, vvith her milk vve are nourished, we are animated with her spirit. The Spouse of Christ cannot play the aduoutresse, she is imaculate and vndefiled, she knoweth one house, she keepeth with chast bashfulnes the san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity of one bedd. This Church preserueth vs in God, this aduanceth to the Kingdome the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren she hath brought forth: whosoeuer deuided from the Church, cleaueth to the aduoutresse, is separated from the promises of the Church.</hi> To whom we add S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> the greatest of all the Fathers and worthyest Deuine the Church of <hi>God euer had since the Apostles,</hi> if we may belieue D. Field; who is styled lykewise the <hi>mouth of antiquity</hi> by other Protestants, giuing vs this wholsome Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell against all s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch slaunderers of the church of Rome. For writing against the<note place="margin">S. Aug. tom. 7. de vnitate Eccles. c. 11.</note> lyke lies of the Donatists, <hi>I know</hi> (sayth he) <hi>what is written in the holy and Canonicall
<pb n="xiiii" facs="9"/> Scriptures concerning the Church of Rome; &amp; the fayth therof, I know not what you say of her Apostacy, or falling from her faith. Truly as we doe read in bookes, the which you also doe honour and reuerence, of the Roman Church, and fayth therof: So also read you out of Bookes vnto vs, the which we also doe honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, how she forsooke and lost her fayth. Doth it please you, that we should belieue euery slaunderous reproach of men vpon what occasion soeuer it was vttered and obiected against the Roman Church, the which the Holy Ghost hath both deliuered, and commended vnto vs by his holy Scriptures? This indeed is pleasing to you; but whom it should more iustly please, you see well inough: but you being ouercome by obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy will not yield to the truth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>We therfore being about to looke as well into the true doctrine and verity, as into the holines and purity of this Church, from whence doth proceed the security of liuing and dying well in her lappe; we are to vse the testimonies especially of Famous Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, to the end the banners of her glorie may be carryed about, and displayed by the penns, and mouthes of our Aduersaries; that all whosoeuer are not maliciously bēt, may therby extoll and magnify the infinit goodnes of Gods prouidence, who hath made, as we may say, euē the enemies of his
<pb n="xv" facs="9"/> Church, and children, although otherwise partiall witnesses, with open mouth to cry out and blaze abroad in effect, <hi>That this is the seed, and familie of Iesus Christ, whom our Lord hath blessed:</hi> yea and hath made the<note place="margin">S. Cyprian. l. 1. ep. 3.</note> holy Ghost to inspire the ancient Fathers to warrant vs, that this is the Church <hi>to</hi>
      <note place="margin">S. Hierom. l. 3. Apol. contra Ruffin.</note>
      <hi>which misbeliefe can haue no accesse; which receaueth no forgery; and though an Angell</hi>
      <note place="margin">S Cyril. apud D. Thom. in catena.</note>
      <hi>teach otherwise, then hath byn once preached, guarded with S. Pauls authoritie, it cannot be changed; which remayneth vnspotted from</hi>
      <note place="margin">S. Gregor. Nazianz in carm. de vita sua.</note>
      <hi>all seducing and hereticall circumuention; which hath the true fayth, euen from the tymes of our for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>athers; &amp; alwaies remayneth as is fit for a citty, that ruleth the whole world, to haue euer more a sound fayth to God.</hi> Out of all which we may cōclude, that this is that blessed Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of holy ones, that houshold of sāctity, that spouse of christ, &amp; church of the liuing God, which is the <hi>Pillar and ground of truth,</hi> whose cōmuniō we may boldly imbrace, whose directions we may safely follow, &amp; rest securely in her iudgments, as in that sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred society, the which for this 1600. yeares hath yielded vp all those blessed Soules of the Apostles, Martyrs, Confessors, Virgins, and of all the rest to God, which now do raigne most gloriously with Iesus Christ the King of glory in Heauen. This
<pb n="xvi" facs="10"/> being so set downe, let vs proceed to the lury.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>