<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The Publishers Preface to the
Reader before Dr. CARIERS
Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103612_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02483</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12610</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103612</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The Publishers Preface to the
Reader before Dr. CARIERS
Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to a treatise vvritten by Dr. Carier, by way of letter to his Maiestie : vvherein he layeth downe sundry politike considerations; by which hee pretendeth himselfe was moued, and endeuoureth to moue others to be reconciled to the Church of Rome, and imbrace tha religion, which he calleth catholike. By George Hakewil, Doctour of Diuinity, and chapleine to the Prince his Highnesse</title>
                 <author>Hakewill, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 30, 130, 4, 131-306, 26, 2 pages, folded table, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="20" facs="12"/>
   <head>❧ The Publishers Preface to the
Reader before D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. CARIERS
Booke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing exactly perused (good Reader)
this Treatise here presented to thy view, and finding it both in stuffe and
stile to be learnedly and eloquently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triued;
I tooke my selfe in some sort ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged
in Christian duty, to divulge it in
print to the world:<note n="1" place="margin">I can shew it in the Authors owne Letters, that he had a purpose of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing it.</note>
      <hi>vnwittingly</hi> I
confesse to the Author: howbeit, encroaching vpon his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable
consent, who I am well assured is most forward to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fray
his talent in ought wherein the Catholike Romane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
may be aduanced: Of this firme and full resolution
he hath made effectiue proofe, not onely in words but also in
workes. The Author, as it is notoriously knowen, hath
gained<note n="2" place="margin">He hath now gotten more <hi>name and fame</hi> by running a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from vs, then by any acte that euer hee did among vs.</note>
      <hi>name and fame</hi> among the Protestants, hauing
beene a Teacher in their Colledges, a Preacher in their Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits,
a Doctor in their Schooles, a Canon in their Churches,
Chaplaine to the <hi>King</hi> his most excellent <hi>Maiestie, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in wealth,</hi> supported with the<note n="3" place="margin">The <hi>Credite</hi> he had in Court, was won by his hypocrisie.</note>
      <hi>credit</hi> of the Court,
most likely in short time to<note n="4" place="margin">He was like enough to aspire to higher pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment: but while he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, not like to attaine it.</note> aspire to higher Ecclesiasticall
preferments, had hee persisted in the course of his former
<pb n="21" facs="12"/>
profession: Yet notwithstanding all these worldly allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
which are in good sooth<note n="5" place="margin">What inti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ing baits could these be vnto him, who by his own acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, felt the state of his body such, that hee could not long enioy them.</note> wondrous inticing baites
to hooke and to hold an vnstayed soule; M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Doctor <hi>Carier</hi>
hauing from his greener yeeres wallowed himselfe in the
choisest writings of the most learned <hi>Protestants,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting
in his mature age their<note n="6" place="margin">The wauering was in his braine not in their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</note> wauering opinions with
the vniforme and setled consent of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ncient Fathers,
found the<note n="7" place="margin">Hee professeth indeed that hee found a large opposition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the new <hi>French,</hi> (as he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it,) and the old <hi>English:</hi> but betweene the <hi>English</hi> and the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>mish,</hi> none at all, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>o small as it might easily be reconciled. <hi>Chap. 2. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ct. 29.</hi>
      </note> new so opposite to the old, that at length recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<note n="8" place="margin">Or rather a counterfeit light from him, who is transformed into an Angel of Light.</note> gracious light from the Father of lights, did teare
<note n="9" place="margin">His owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation shewes, how slowly he proceeded in this businesse, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in hope of higher prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and yet in despaire of lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger life.</note> at a trice all these forementioned earthly s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ares, resoluing
not to wander any longer like a lost sheepe, but to come to
the fold of the Catholike <hi>Roman</hi> Church; and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
choosing like a zealous Moses, to be afflicted with the people of God, then to haue the pleasure of temporall sinne:
These and the like pregnant points are sufficiently debated
in this Treatise, which I wish thee (gentle Reader) to peruse
with heedfull attention, wherby the Author his paines may
turne to thy profite, if happily thou be alienated from the
<note n="10" place="margin">
         <hi>Catholike Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> I take to be as much as <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ndome.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Catholike Roman</hi> religion, alwaies presenting thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
to our Lord <hi>Sweet Iesus,</hi> that he would vouch safe to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate
thy minde in the passage of thy eternall saluation,
that thou mayest preferre light before darkenesse, trueth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
falshood, Catholike Religion before particular opinions,
<note n="11" place="margin">Had M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. done so, he had rested where he was.</note> as M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Doctor <hi>Carier</hi> hath done vpon such sound and
grounded reasons, as hee hath opened in this Treatise: And
this wishing that good to thy soule, which I wish to mine
owne, I betake thee good Reader to the direction and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
of the authour, and giuer of grace and glory.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>