<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103990_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14664</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17129</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103990</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A myrrhine posie of the bitter dolours of Christ his passion : and of the seaven vvords he spake on the crosse, composed by Ch. M</title>
                 <author>Kellison, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>13, 7, 211, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="9" facs="6"/>
   <head>THE <hi>PREFACE</hi> TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING spent some time in Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Sacred Passion of Christ, I find it to be a Sea in which is no bottome, a bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse Sea of Charitie, a bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse Sea of Mercie, a bottomlesse Sea of Grace, a bottomlesse Sea
<pb n="10" facs="7"/> of Iustice, a bottomlesse Sea of Sorrow. I find it also to be a wood in which one may loose himselfe, though neuer to his losse; a Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth or Maze in which one may sooner finde a way to get in, then to get out, yet shall neuer be out of his way; yea a Garden of such varietie of sweete and odoriferous flowers, that one can neuer gather all; hardlie can he determine where to make his first choice, yet can neuer choose amisse. VVherefore (Gentle Reader) I will not promise thee to exhaust or drawe drye this Sea for thee; I should promise an impossibilitie; onelie I will drawe out of it as much as my weake forces will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and thine and my capacitie can receaue: Nor will I shew thee all the wayes, and windings of this wood and Maze, onelie I will bring thee into some few walkes,
<pb n="11" facs="7"/> which I my selfe haue passed; nor will I gather, nor can I, all the Flowers of this Garden; onelie I will select such as were obuious to me, and of which I my selfe haue smelled; and I will of them make a posie or nosegay for thee to smell on by deuout Meditation. Thou shalt find as many diuerse smelles in this Posie, as it conteineth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Flowers. Some will smell of Christ his great Charitie in suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring so much for mans Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; some will sauour of his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice in paying so full a price for the sayd Redemption; some will smell of his great Patience, some of his obedience to his Eternall Father, some of his great Humilitie, in that, <hi>he humbled him selfe, made obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto death, euen the death</hi> of <hi>the Crosse.</hi> In breefe there is no vertue of which in this Posie thou mayst not haue an odoriferous and gratefull smell, if thou apply thy
<pb n="12" facs="8"/> internall senses vnto it. Diuers of the Saints of God tooke such pleasure, consolation, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in meditating vpon Christ his Passion, that in regard of it, they contemned all the pleasures which the world could afford. And yet I entitle this my Pamphlet, a Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhine Posie, because Christ his Dolours and Sorrowes were bitter as Myrrhe to him; though to vs they be most comfortable, because in them we contemplate his great loue and Charitie in suffering for vs; in them we behold the grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full price of our Redemption; and because I desire that not onelie Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rholikes, but also Protestants, and all they who goe by the name of Christians should reade this Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, and take some benefit by it, I abstaine from all Controuersies in Religion, that none may be deterred from reading it. Take
<pb n="13" facs="8"/> this my labour in good part, for it was vndertaken for thee; and if thou reape any good by reading it, thanke him who is Goodnes it self, and the Prime Cause, and principall Authour of all that is good; I was but his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weldie Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>