<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, LEARNED, AND TRVELY HONORABLE, HENRY, Lord HOWARD, Earle of North∣hampton, Baron of Marnhill, Constable of the Castle of Douer, Lord Warden, Chancellour and Admirall of the Cinque Ports, Lord Priuy Seale, Knight of the most Noble Order of the arter, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuy Councell.</title>
           <author>Gentleman, Tobias</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103037_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01617</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11745</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103037</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, LEARNED, AND TRVELY HONORABLE, HENRY, Lord HOWARD, Earle of North∣hampton, Baron of Marnhill, Constable of the Castle of Douer, Lord Warden, Chancellour and Admirall of the Cinque Ports, Lord Priuy Seale, Knight of the most Noble Order of the arter, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuy Councell.</title>
                 <author>Gentleman, Tobias</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Englands vvay to vvin vvealth, and to employ ships and marriners: or, A plaine description what great profite, it will bring vnto the common-wealth of England, by the erecting, building, and aduenturing of busses, to sea, a fishing : With a true relation of the inestimable wealth that is yearely taken out of his Maiesties seas, by the Hollanders, by their great numbers of busses, pinkes, and line-boates: and also a discourse of the sea-coast townes of England, and the most fit and commodious places, and harbours that wee haue for busses, and of the small number of our fishermen, and also the true valuation, and whole charge, of building, and furnishing, to sea, busses, and pinks, after the Holland manner. By Tobias Gentleman, fisherman and marriner</title>
                 <author>Gentleman, Tobias</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Budge, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 46, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, LEARNED, AND TRVELY HONORABLE, HENRY, Lord HOWARD, Earle of North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton, Baron of <hi>Marnhill,</hi> Constable of the Castle of <hi>Douer,</hi> Lord Warden, Chancellour and Admirall of the Cinque Ports, Lord Priuy Seale, Knight of the most Noble Order of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arter, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuy Councell.</head>
   <opener>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing that by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture our Country chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth a greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in vs, then our Parents, Friends, or Children can, and that we ought for preseruation thereof, oppose our liues vnto the greatest dangers: It is
<pb facs="3"/>
the part of euery Natiue to endeauor something to the aduancement and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite thereof, and not to affect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t, for that wee possesse in it, but to loue it for it selfe, as being the common Mother and Nourisher of vs all. For mine owne part, albeit my short fadome can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe no such great designe as I desire, yet from a willing minde (as hee that offerd his hands full of water to great <hi>Artaxerxes</hi>) I am bold to present this project of my honest and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap>; beseeching your L. whose <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> truely enobled you, to take the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 words">
         <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
      </gap> your protection: And prefer it to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of our most Royall Soueraigne, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending the good effecting thereof to his gracious fauor and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rtherance. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse: your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tions and endeauours hauing
<pb facs="3"/>
all bene full of virtue and goodnesse, are not the least preuailing motiues whereby his Maiesty hath so endeered you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. In this then you shall not thinke your selfe disparaged, the matter being both honest and commendable, and in true valew of as great substance, as the offer of <hi>Sebastian Cabota,</hi> to King <hi>Henry</hi> the seuenth, for the discouery of the West Indies.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Humbly at your Lordships commandement,
<hi>Tobias Gentleman.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>