<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103111_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01752</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11884</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103111</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvver to the deuillish detection of Stephane Gardiner, Bishoppe of Wynchester : published to the intent that such as be desirous of the truth should not be seduced by hys errours, nor the blind [et] obstinate excused by ignorance Compiled by. A.G</title>
                 <author>Gilby, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                    <distributor>Day, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>lxxii, lxxii-clxxxxix, clxxxxii-ccx, that is ccxi 6 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>The Prologue.</head>
   <p>GRace and peace from the Lorde the liueinge God, who hath all our her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes in hys hande to moue and stere to what shall lyke hym beste, who onely knoweth the hertes of men, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore oneli is the iudge of the thoughtes and intentes of vs all, what or whan so euer we speake or thinke. whose daye and iudgment is without regarde what man (which is but flesh and bloud, and therefore ful of erroure and blindnesse) shall dispute, and determine and iudge. I paciently loke for and a bide whan as all darnell, drake and weede shall be caste into the hell fire and all the good graine shal be gathered into God his owne garner, vnto whome we lyue all the tyme that we walke vpon the earth. And whē we die yet are we sure that we are his owne, by the raunsome that his dearely beloued sone Christ (our Lord and heade) hath paied geue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge the holy gost into our hertes as a most suer wittnesse of the same, teacheinge vs to crie. Aba father, whereby we knowe that though we die, yet we die vnto hym to lyue euer after cowpled and ioyned in one kinde and nature vnto our heade Christe, who as he is fully God, and of equale powre wyth his father, so shal he make vs like vnto hym when he shal appeare (after our porcion and
<pb n="viii" facs="8"/>
measure) partakers of his godly nature, like as he hath in hys world (though but in a sha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dowe and cloude, in regarde of the fulnesse that shalbe declared) be gonne al redy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate and begete vs a newe▪ creature, by the holy gost workinge by the worde of hys trueth, that we nowe resembling the image of God whereunto we were made, maye be continually occupyed in the workes of hys kingdome, as be these. Iustice, peace▪ and ioy in the same holy gost, geuear of al goodnes. For he that by these workes serueth Christe is acceptable to God and conmended of men Thys s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e euer lasteinge God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out begininge and without endinge, he geue me grace (to the fortheraunce of his glorie) to make answere to that deuellishe detection the sophistrie of Sathan published by Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Gardiner bishope of Winchester, for the maintenaunce of the popishe Idole, the dombe God, and poetical chaungling, wher by, not onely the true liuinge God is neglec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted his true honoure obscured and defaced, the preachinge of hys worde almoste set at nought: but also, all kindes of poperie, as i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, blessing, kissinge, shaueinge of crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, supersticiō of garmenets and such like, are craftily, by subtile pointes of the popes sophistri and wordes filthy, framed for such
<pb facs="9"/>
merchaundise, confirmed and established, as thought al the whole heape of these triffes heaped vp together were the religion of a Christian man: wher as to knowe God for our true God, and whom hehath sent, Iesu Christ, and by this knowledge to be borne a new and to kepe our selfe immaculate and vnde filed from the worlde is: the true and perfecte religiō demaūded of vs true christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. The other is but countrefaite what so euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>his sophistrie doeth name it) because our maister christ (who can not lie) doeth saie ful plaine. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>They worshipe me in vaine, teacheinge the doctrine and preceptes of men &amp;c. And where he bringeth in this texte in the ende of his boke, nothing so ful as our sauior Christ did speake it (as he knoweth well inowgh if he haue so muche Greke as he braggeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode) he addeth therunto his owne glose, as though he coulde vtter the wordes of christ the sone of God, much more wiselie by hys babling. Yet am I cōtent to let his own glose be his owne iudge in these matters. His wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des bee these. They worshippe me in vaine, with the teachinge of such as remaine in the
<pb n="ix" facs="9"/>
estate of men onely, &amp; thē teach their owne &amp; for thē selues, for al such teachinge is like the teachar that is to saye carnal. Let eueri man (that hath not his conscience al redie brenned wyth the hote pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e) marke whether hys owne glose make against him, and all the ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remonies that hys father the pope, beinge (I trowe) but in the estate of a man, and that a carnal mā, hath made, though Winchester go aboute craftily (accordinge to the cannon lawe whereof he is sworne by solemne othe doctoure and teacher) to make him more thē a man. And marke againe good christen her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, what they win by theyr gloses and mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiplied wordes, wherby in fayth it were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie easy to confute them all, euen by the testi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monies of their owne doctours (as Bucere, Ecolampadius, and Frith haue done per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlie well, if these men woulde suffer there bokes to come to lyght) For these papistes do so mixte the trueth and salsehed together (for without some ground of trueth noman woulde beleue them) that the one piece of the tale standeth commonly with the trueth and the other vttereth their salshed.</p>
   <p>And therfore speake they longe matter and are not content to saye plainely a spade but they muste necker it as they do in theyr mattens and saye, spa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ade. As for me I
<pb facs="10"/>
haue learned to cal breade, bread, &amp; to speake althinges plainelie. Therfore by the open scriptures, wyll I make them answere to their questions. For al the scripture inspired from God, is profitable boeth to teache and to reproue, to correcte and to instructe in rightuousnesse, that the man of God maye be perfecte and fite for euerie good worcke.</p>
   <p>So that if ther be any▪ good worke▪ to be taught or yll worck <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o be rebuked we must go to the scripture onely, as to the toutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone and onelye triall of al trueth.</p>
   <p>For wyth scriptures did Christe driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie the deuil, and not wyth holy water, as you are reported to saie that the deuil great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dreadeth it, and so do ye still commaunde that it shalbe made a coniured water euerie sonnedayes in▪ euery churche, to driue furth deuilles. But he thoughe he were boeth god and man, alledgeth scriptures alwayes to confirme his saienges, and commandeth his hearers to sherch the scriptures. So doe Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Paule, Iames, and Iohn.</p>
   <p>Wheras Paul beinge brought vp at the fete of Gamaliell the greate lawier, was redie inoughe to haue disputed out of the Thalmud of the tradicions of their fathers, whiche he saieth he hath ernestely studied be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of the phariseies, and interpretour
<pb n="x" facs="10"/>
of that law, and such one as by the outward wordes of the lawe could not be found fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <note place="margin">Gala. i. Phili. iii.</note> Yet dyd he accōpte all thys, boeth lerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge and outwarde holinesse (whyche other men did take as no smal gainne and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>cre) to be damage and hindrance for Chirst, whom so sone as he was called to publishe &amp; preach he did not compare wyth the docters of the Iewes, neither wyth Gamaliell, Annas or Laiphas. But knoweinge his learneinge to be more liuely than was theirs (whyche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esh and bloude, coulde teach onely carnall and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eshly thinges) went streight in to Arabie, there to publishe thys glade ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, euer teachinge by the scriptures that Christ, did come this to suffer in the flesh, and that he was after that, entred into his glorie.</p>
   <p>So do I intende (after the measure of my talent) to answere by the lernige of my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Christe, whom onely. I do take to be al sufficiens in all trueth, so that he can neither be deceiued nor deceiue, to whose wysdome no mā can adde one iote or title to make bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he hath made, to institute or ordeine (whose whether you wyll call it, because ye are so contenciouse, aboute trifles that you maye seme to saye some what) better then he him selfe hath▪ instit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ted and ordeined, or yet in speake better then'he hath spoken. And in
<pb facs="11"/>
this be halfe, I must (euen of brotherly loue) desire all indifferent arbitours and iudges of my writinges, that if they do reade any bitter worde or heare anie sharpe sentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainste the mainteiners of thys Idole: they do not impu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e it to anye pride or arrogancie but to the vnworthynes of the matter, that man shoulde be so mad to set vp a creature most vile &amp; moste weake in the steade of the Lorde of hostes whose pouer is incōparable. In the which thing, being a cause <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> so great importaunce, and weight if I should colde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or faintly speak or write I myght well be thought worthy to be one of them whome Iohn prophecieth, for theyre faynte hertes, worthie to be v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>etted vp againe, being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hote nor colde. I do feare me the plage of God hath worthyly commen vpon many in thys same royalme, for thys onely vice. But God, he is mercifull if we wil repente.</p>
   <p>As for me O Lord thou knoweste al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, thou knoweste mine herte, &amp; serchestmy thoughtes. Thou woteest that it is neither of malice nor presumption that I do write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worde in this boke, but only for the pride of the papistes, and especially for the wicked malice of proude A man, which seaketh how to destroie thy seruantes, labourethe to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse thy light sent nowe in these la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er daies
<pb n="xi" facs="11"/>
at the tyme apointed, into the worlde, prouo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth vs wyth bitter wordes, to make ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were in thy cause, calling vs diueles, and the reasones made againste Idolatrie for the an anseinge of thy glorie, he calleth the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eles wordes and saieinges, which blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies cause me that I can not geue place but somethinge answere to his worthinesse, and not geue place to such shamelesse writinges.</p>
   <p>Thoughe I coulde be content (&amp; that with good wyll so that it were no derogacion to thy glory) not onely to passe with silence all taūtes, rebukes, che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>kes, and raileinges, yea and to suffer all crueltie and tirannus tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes that he doeth excogitat or finde out againste vs: but also to kisse hys verie fote steppes, and call him Lorde at euerie worde, to kneele and lowte as do hys flatterers. But then l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e we forsake thy cause, we can not haue thy worde in worthy reuerence, magnifieinge thine enimie.</p>
   <p>Take thou in good worthe therefore (O Lorde (these oure doinges. Make thē serue thy glorie. Be mercifull to thy seruantes, and stoppe the mouth of thine enimies that thi wil may, be knowne and fulfilled among vs in erath, as it is amonge thin angelles in thine heauenly palace So be it.</p>
   <p>To your firste wordes therefore (bishope
<pb facs="12"/>
Stephane, pardone me I praye you that I do not cal you Lorde, boeth because I haue learned by scripture that Christes byshopes <note place="margin">Math. xxiii.</note> maie take no suche vaine titles, and also that you ought to calenge no suche authorite of <note place="margin">Iames. iii.</note> Lordeshipe ouer your lotte and people ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed vnto you, and Peter and Paule, the <note place="margin">i. Peter. v.</note> good shepeherdes do we name without such vaine titles of Rabby) you wil haue vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider <note place="margin">i. Chap. Howe full of iniquity that tyme is.</note> howe full of iniquitie thys tyme is. Let vs consider it for the loue of God (O bisho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes) but not takeinge iniquitie as you do, to be what so euer thinge is againste the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of your Romish father, who nowe worketh the cheife misterie of iniquitie, and euerie one of you helpeth after to his poure, in kepeinge downe the worde of God, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keinge your hipocrisie wyth contrefaite ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, and tourneinge backewarde so farre from Christe: that euerie man maye see who is the wicked man, and the aduersarie or An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tichriste, lifteinge hym selfe againste euerie thinge that is God or godlie, So that nowe your shameles writinges of your doctours and maintainers: do recorde howe you can make God, create the creatoure of heauen and er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h, and so make him a creature, that where he hath but once created the, thou maiste be out of his det and cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> him a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sande 
<pb n="xii" facs="12"/>
tymes. Oh abhominable blsasphemie A man to make God, at whose terrible ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, heauen and erth doe tremble. Oh sham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lesse iniquitie, to create thi creatoure without whome thou falleste in to duste and asshes. But you wyll saye (O bishope) that ther is no suche blasphemie in your bokes, neither can you perceiue the wickednesse of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes pardones, and pilgrimages whyche are destroied in this tyme, The Sodomatrie ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bilonical bondage, supersticiouse blindnesse of the Abbaies, whych oure kinge hath most christenlyke confounded. But for this oure mattier, I saye. I plucked halfe a leafe out of a boke lieinge tied in chaines for a Iewell in the greate cathedrall churche, Lincolne min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stre, whiche hath thys plaine greare, by these plaine wordes. O sacerdos, nonne creaui te, et dedi tibi potestatem creaudi me? quare si non sacrificas, et c. O prieste, haue I not crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted the, and geuē the poure <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o create me? And suche other shamful geare.</p>
   <p>There is none so blinde as they that wil not se. And seinge suche blindesse is in you bishopes, who shoulde haue hade the eies to haue espied thys ware longe before it hade ben brought into the churches contrarie to the worde of God: how can it be but bi your carelesse negligence, the worlde is waxen ful
<pb facs="13"/>
of blindenesse, miserie and all kindes of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, for the whiche you shal answere at the dreadfull daie whan the bloude of euery one of your shepe that perisheth shallbe required at your hande. Let vs consider yet if you please, thys wickednesse some thynge more deaplye.</p>
   <p>Paule in his firste Epistle to the bishop <note place="margin">Timo. i.</note> Timothe, saieth that the spirite telleth for cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne, that in the latter daies, some shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>hat diuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> sophistrie</note> from the fayeth, attendynge vnto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptfull spirites and doctrine of diuelles, speakeinge falsely by dissemblinge hipocrisie haueinge their consciences marked with the hote yrone.</p>
   <p>And that we shoulde not doubt of thys diuellish sophistrie and open iniquite: he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth two speciall properties, that is, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite or forbid mariage, and cōmaūde to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staine from meates whyche God hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be receiued wyth thankes geueing, as the good ceatures of God. Who foloweth the diuelles doctrine moste in these to poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: is not harde to be iudged of al the world</p>
   <p>Yet muste we futhermore consider the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es you saye which thinge we▪ are not loth <note place="margin">Beleue not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ie spirite. Iohn. iiii.</note> to do (for Iohn teacheth vs so) mistrusteinge our owne iudgment. And Iohn sayeth that euerie spirite that confesseth Iesus Christ to
<pb n="xiii" facs="13"/>
be come in the flesh, is of God. This do we all confesse, whome you call at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure heretikes, and saye that we wyll doubte in all together. But we knoweinge certenlie <note place="margin">Iohn. i. Timo. iii.</note> by the scriptures, that he was manifestely declared in the flesh to be verie man, and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectly declared in the spirite to be God in the wonderouse workinge of his miracles, was sene amonge the angelles, was beleued in the world, and receiued into glorie, where he reigneth equale wyth his father, sittinge at the ryght hand of God, from whense we no thing doubt, but we shal se him come down as the apostles dyd se hym go vp into the heauenes. Act. i. In the meane season we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue stedfastly that he is with his faiethfull church by hys holy spirite euen to the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des <note place="margin">Ephe. v.</note> ende. For the which he gaue him selfe to sanctifie it and cleuse it, in the fountaine of water bi the worde, to make it vnto him selfe a gloriouse congregacion wythout spot or wrynckle or any suche thynge, but that it shoulde be holy and wythout blame, Where contrarie wyse, you (whiche accompte your selues onely, men of the churche) and spiriri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall men, as the onelye partakers of the spirite (doe wyth out scripture or reasone) teache vs laye and lewde men (as ye call vs) onelye wyth swerde and fire, that Christe
<pb facs="14"/>
was not verie man haueinge a naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. For you saye that thys his bodie that he had maie be in. x. thowsande places at once. Whiche property, howe well it agreth with a natural bodie: al that haue any knowledge maye decerne. Againe you saye that this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of the same lengeth and breadeth that it hanged vpon the crosse: maye be closed in a little boxe, contrarie to the ordinaunce of mans naturall bodie in the creacion. And where we se nothynge but a piece of breade (for you can not teache vs by the scriptures that the breade is chaunged) we must neades beleue, that their is a bodie, besides the bread because you saye so thought there can be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiued neither quantitie nor qualitie, that is to saye, nothynge parteininge to a bodie. As for your answere of fayeth constrained to beleue thys wythout either scripture or▪ rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone, that it maye haue merite, and that all these be naturall reasons: I shall answere whan I come at those wordes.</p>
   <p>In the meane tyme marke your owne mali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciouse wickednesse, how you wil haue▪ Christ to haue a bodie, nothynge lyke the naturall bodie of man, but insensible and infinit yet by your subtilties to be comprehedend, and wythin your listes, bandes and boxes, to be contained and haue hys measure appointed,
<pb n="xiiii" facs="14"/>
but in no parte agreable to our natural bodi which he did voultchsalfe to take vpon him.</p>
   <p>Thus after you haue denied him (by your wicked enuēcion) to be a verie mā, like one of vs (sinne onely excepted) whych the scripture teacheth plaine: After you haue denied christ to haue a verie natural bodie and verie flesh, then procede you to teach how he cometh in breade. And because you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>et Christes religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in your ceremonies as farthynges that make the heape: you set Iesu oure saniour, to come in al trifles and baggage, Yet to cloke your false speach wyth hipocrisie, you saye properly, that Christe consecrateth him selfe <note place="margin">Folio. lvi.</note> in those formes of bread &amp; wine, with which worde consecrate, you ingle by your di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ilish sophistrie. For if ye meane, he haloweth him selfe into bread &amp; wine (which your word cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>secrate doeth signifie) as lewde as you take vs, we woulde laught at your folie. If you woulde saye by that worde, he tourneth him selfe into the fourme of breade and wyne: so then your doctrine is that Christe cometh vnto vs in breade &amp; wine. And we saye that he is comen all redie in the fleshe, and in the same fleshe is gone vp to heauen, and from thense shall come to iudge all flesh. You saye lo, here is Christe. Lo, there is Christe. Loke whose spirites you be. You are of the world
<pb facs="15"/>
and therfore speake you of the worlde, and the world heareth you. And like as by faieth so also by loue, saieth Iohn, is the spirite of <note place="margin">Iohn. iiii.</note> trueth and of errowre knowne asūder. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore let vs loue together, for loue is of God, and euerie one that loueth is borne of God.</p>
   <p>He that loueth not knoweth not God, for God is loue. If we loue together God dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth in vs, and his loue is perfece in vs. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man saie, I loue God, and doeth yet hate his brother: that man is a lier. For he that loueth not hys brother, whom he seeth: how can he loue God whom he seeth not: Howe your hote bourneinge loue (whyche causeth you to bourne men that can not vnderstand your gloses) can be of god I know not: but thys wotte I well that when the people of Samaria woulde not receiue Christe, hys <note place="margin">Luk. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Apostles woulde haue had fire frō heauen to bourne them. But Christe answered. You knowe not, whose spirites you are. The sonne of man dyd not come to destroy the soules of men: but to saue them. And you by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shoppes haue your authoritie to edifie and not to destroie. But the olde serpent and his first begotten caine, thē Pharao, next, Herod and the phariseis, the olde byshopes condem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninge Christe, and you their successours, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheinge his worde with crueltie: are of a
<pb n="xv" facs="15"/>
cōtrarie spirite. And where you byd vs take <note place="margin">Take heede of carion.</note> hede of cariō, surely your glose is a very cari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, and the worde of God which you take a way frō al men saue gētlemē &amp; marchaūtes is the onely fode and life of the soule, wher it liueth as Christ him selfe wittnesseth. Not <note place="margin">Mathe. iiii.</note> by bread only liueth man, but by eueri word that proceadeth out of the mouth of God. But the blacke birdes and rauenes, the pies and deuoreinge fleshe crowes, they fede vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on flesh, and theafore vpon carion. My wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des (saieth Christe) are spirite and lyfe. My spirite sayeth God shall no longer remayne with man, because he is fleshe. Therfore whē the worde of God and the spirite of lyfe are not with your fleshly teachinge: it must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des be carion. Suche is your flieinge about the dead as about carion, for filling of your paunches. For the deade carions haue made you riche in youre monasteries, chauntries and perpetuities. The deade carions of Bec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ket, Benno, and darnel Gader, of Dunstane woulstane, Audrie and suche other haue fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led your wide throtes so full, and you carie your praye so gredily in your monthes: that you are become dome dogges that you can not barcke but onelye at them that woulde reine you of that foule carion, and leade you home to take heede of your maisters folde.
<pb facs="16"/>
And to teache plainely what is carion: we do take it to be, what so euer you do bringe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the church of Christ (as his religiō) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hys holy worde and the liuely spirite of God. The same I saye, is that stinckinge ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rion that Paulle calleth Anathema, and the prophet warneth vs we touche it not. And Iohn biddeth vs that we do not so much as saye Ane and salute the bringers therof, leste we be compted partakers of their iuell wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. I wyll passe with silence the roten rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and carion bones of your reliques and suche lyke ware, that sauoure little of the spirite of life, and of the worshipeing of god in spirite and trueth. But for thys thinge we haue in hande, lettinge slippe all other your vnsauourie cerimoneis, and carianlyke rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques: more stinckinge carion surely, and more poisenfull sophistrie causeinge deathe and murren of so many soules was ther ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in the worlde: then the gloses and drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of your idle braines about this mattier that we shal now handle, as shalbe proued plainelie by the grace of the liueinge God. Your termes of realities qualites, acceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and dimencions, sauour nothinge of the spirite of God: and therefore are they fleshe and carion. The whole course of your boke labouringe to make Christe really and natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="xvi" facs="16"/>
present vnder these fourmes, qualites and quātities: sauoureth of the rotten pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures, and stinckinge fleshli braines of your dreameinge doctours. Dunse, Thomas de Aquino, and petrus Lombardus. Therfore is this the carion, wherof we muste be ware This is the diuellishe sophistrie wherwyth the world hath bene so lōg bewitched in such sorte, that in the steade of the liuelie feading of their soules by the worde of God, the breade of lyfe: you haue filled theire eares and eies with darcke termes, dombe signes, and deceiueable shadowes, allwaies beate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge and burninge the poreshep bleatinge a gainste the filthy stinckinge carion, of your popeishe and I dolatrouse tradicions. What other thinge (let all men iudge betwexte vs) are these sophisticall termes of realitie, quan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titie, accedentes, dimentions and alteracions whyche are the onely foundacion of your boke, and the establishement of thys fleshly doctrine: but the vsuall termes of the subtile sophistes of Cambrige and exforde, and the Sorbonistes of parise? They can not be founde in the bokes of the holy spirite of the holy scripture of God▪ and therfor are they fleshely sophistrie and stinckeinge carion. Thys your boke all grounded vpon man, which is but flesh, vpon the darcke sentences
<pb facs="17"/>
and blind termes of blind teachers, as Iohn Damascene and such other: can be likened to nothinge so well as to carion. The whiche mattier is picked out of the maister of the sentences or carionouse sophismes, chouse whether you wyl call hym. And where you woulde seme to be most spirituall about the words of Christ, Hoc est corpus meum: ther you are all to gether carnalle and fleshly.</p>
   <p>You wil haue a carnall chaunge, a carnal presence, a carnall sacrifice, A piece of paste (as we saye) fleshe and bloude (as we saye) to be carnally worshipped wyth fonde ges<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. A creature to be made the creatoure. A vile cake, to be made God and man. Which doctrine (beinge examined by the spirite of God the triar of all trueth) shalbe founde I<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dolatrouse carion.</p>
   <p>The residue of your preface would haue vs captiue to you Christes vikeres, to your <note place="margin">Seeke the trueth, at the ministers of the church.</note> doctours and mainteners. These haue you alwayes heretofore called the churche of Rome. But nowe that you maye deceiue (if it be possible) the verie electe: by a false name calling it Christes church. But in verie dede it is the sinnagog of Sathan and the church of Antichriste: because you are in liueinge so contrarie to Christe, and because you set▪ and establish therin the ceremonies of Antichrist
<pb n="xvii" facs="17"/>
and bannishe the pore shepe from the worde of theyr shepherde, seldome or neuer preache<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge vnto them Christe, but your owne bag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gage, nor yet sufferinge the pore lambes to reade and feade of hys worde and pasture. But we all are not so folishe thus to be enchaunted. We haue Iesu Christe before oure eies crucified, by your predicessours, which boasted them selues to be the church▪ Whome alone we learne to knowe, to heare and to folowe nowe in these latter daies, because your fathers, boeth of Rome and of Englande: haue led vs out of the waye vn whoreinge in to Babilon, and haue hitherto taught vs to worshipe suche thinges as by their nature are no goddes, But nowe seing that we knowe God (yea rather seinge that we are knowne of God) we wil not returne agayne to your weake Idoles and your beg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gerie ceremonies, to the whiche you woulde haue vs slaues and do seruice a freshe. But marke and take it for an answere. We haue <note place="margin">Gala. iii.</note> begone in the spirite, and we nether wyll nor can be made perfite by the fleshe. We wyll make subiecte our senses and captiue our vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derstandinge to all trueth of goddes holy word, but to no lies of your idle braines and couetous conspiracie, We are no longer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the schole of your popeish tradicions, for
<pb facs="18"/>
we are all the children of God because we haue beleaued in Christe Iesu</p>
   <p>For so many of vs (sayeth Paulle) as are baptised, we are clade with Christe, so that there is no Iewe nor Greke, no exception of yoman from Ientleman, or man from womā but wee are all one in Iesu Christe, Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wil we stād in the liberti wherin Christ hath deliuered vs, and we wyll no more be wrapped with your seruile bondage, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge that whoso trobleth vs shal receiue his iudgement who so euer he be. Therefore, all the fruites of the fleshe, and al the workes of darckenesse set a parte, adulterie, Idolatrie, and suche like: we will walke in the workes of the spirite, loue, Ioye, peace, gentlenesse, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie, goodnesse, faith, mildenesse and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brenesse. And we wil glorie in nothinge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aue onely in the crose of oure Lorde Iesu Christ, by whome the worlde is crucified vnto vs, and we vnto the worlde, beinge fully par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded that Christe is the good shepeherde that putteth his soule for his shepe, and that <note place="margin">Iohn the x.</note> al you bishopes are but hirlinges, workyng for wages, whiche scatter the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oke, &amp; barcke not for the sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>pe. But he knoweth his shepe and is knowne of them. His voice onely, wil they heare, hym onely, wyll they folow, and he onely geueth vnto them euerlasting lyfe,
<pb n="xviii" facs="18"/>
they shall neuer perish. No man shal be able to take them out of his hande: for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and he be all one. Thus are we (beinge grounded vppon oure heade and maister Christ, by faieth) the very true church of Christe againste the whyche the gates of hel can not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile.</p>
   <p>❧ An answere concerneinge the true vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandeinge and wisdōe that God geueth to all men that aske it in sure fayeth wherin is declared the true vnderstandinge of these wordes. Hoc est corpus meum.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>