<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A SVPPLEMENT TO THE BEGINNING OF C. IVLIVS CEASAR DICTATOR.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103242_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23422</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103242</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A SVPPLEMENT TO THE BEGINNING OF C. IVLIVS CEASAR DICTATOR.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of tvvelve Cæsars : emperours of Rome: written in Latine by C. Suetonius Tranquillus, and newly translated into English. With a marginall glosse, and other briefe annotations there-upon</title>
                 <author>Suetonius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 272, 39, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="supplement">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A SVPPLEMENT TO THE BEGINNING OF C. IVLIVS CEASAR DICTATOR.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>IVLIAN</hi> linage, as most men are perswaded, is descended from <hi>Ascanius Iülus,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Aeneas</hi> by <hi>Creusa:</hi> which <hi>Iülus,</hi> after he had left <hi>Lavinium,</hi> built long <hi>Alba:</hi> wherein also he reigned. Others, grounding vpon a more assured evidence, have thought it good to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive the same rather from <hi>Iülus</hi> the son of <hi>Ascanius.</hi> For when after the death of (this) <hi>Ascanius▪</hi> the Kingdome of the Latines was devol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved<note n="*" place="margin">or retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto</note> againe upon <hi>Sylvius</hi> the sonne of <hi>Aeneas</hi> and <hi>Lavinia,</hi> the charge of Religion &amp; sacred ceremonies of the Latin and Troian Nation both, remained yet still in the race and progenie of <hi>Iülus:</hi> out of which are sprung the Iulij. These (Iulij) with certaine other most noble families of <hi>Latium, Tullus Hosti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> King of the Romanes, after he had rased <hi>Alba,</hi> translated to Rome, and raunged among the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. Late it was, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>re they rose and mounted to high place of Magistracie; but were recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned almost in the last ranke of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of auncient Nobilitie: &amp; of them, the <hi>Iüli</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>are the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. For <hi>C. Iulius,</hi> (sonne of <hi>Lucius</hi>) surnamed also <hi>Iülus,</hi> was Consull together with <hi>P <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Rufus,</hi> in the yeare after the foundation of <hi>Rome</hi> citie<note n="*" place="margin">or rather 265, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy annexed unto Titus Livius.</note> 264. And<note n="*" place="margin">By the computati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfius, T. Livius, C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siodorus &amp; others.</note> seaven yeeres after,<note n="*" place="margin">C. Iulius, or Iūlus.</note> his sonne, with <hi>Q. Fabius Vibulanus</hi> (Consull) the second time. Againe, some space of time comming betweene, <hi>Vopiscus Iulius,</hi> sonne of <hi>Caius</hi> and Nephew of <hi>Lucius,</hi> bare the Consulshippe with <hi>L. Aemilius<note n="*" place="margin">al. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercus</note> Mamercinus</hi> third time Consull, in the yeere<note n="*" place="margin">or 28<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid of Dionyfius.</note> 280. I finde likewise, that in the yeere<note n="*" place="margin">more tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 303</note> 302. <hi>Caius Iulius,</hi> sonne of <hi>Caius,</hi> and nephew of <hi>Lucius,</hi> was a decemvir for the enacting and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of Lawes, and that in the former Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that Magistracie: as also, that <hi>Caius Iulius</hi> sonne of <hi>Caius</hi> and Nephew of <hi>Caius,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Consull with <hi>Marcus Geganius Macerinus,</hi> in the yeare<note n="*" place="margin">307, by Livius ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> 306. and the selfe same man a second time, with <hi>Lucius Verginius Trirostus</hi> in the yeere<note n="*" place="margin">319. 320. 4<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>7</note> 318: and immediately in the<note n="*" place="margin">So <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</note> yeere next following, a third time, with the same <hi>Verginius</hi> now twice Consull. And thus much for the <hi>Iūli.</hi> For to reherse and collect all them of that familie, together with the honorable places of everie one, which were many in number, and of sundry kindes; is not our purpose: and besides, the thing it selfe is apparent and upon record in the publick Registers.</p>
   <p>Moreover, I have observed in the <hi>Iulian</hi> line, a certaine house also of the <hi>Mentones:</hi> and among them, one <hi>Caius Iulius,</hi> colleague in the Consulshippe with <hi>T. Quint<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s Pennus Cincin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus,</hi> in the 322. yeere after the foundation of the citie. I finde likewise, <hi>Caius Iulius Denter</hi> to be master of the Horsemen, when <hi>Caius Claudius Cr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ssus Sabinus Regillensis</hi> was Dictator, for to hold their solemne assembly of Election, in the yeare 405. There were besides of these Iulij, others going vnder the name of <hi>Libones:</hi> and of the same race one triumphed; to wit, <hi>Lucius Iulius,</hi> sonne of <hi>Lucius</hi> and nephew of <hi>Lucius;</hi> companion in the Consulate which <hi>Marcus Attili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Regulus,</hi> in the yeere<note n="*" place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ply Pomp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>n 2<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> of the tribe Pompun<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> 486. But, as touching <hi>Caius Iulius</hi> sonne of <hi>Lucius,</hi> and surnamed <hi>Caesar <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> whom <hi>Suetonius</hi> also ment in the 55. chapter of <hi>Iulius Caesar,</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth in his <hi>Brutus,</hi> and in the second booke of his Oratour, I doubt, whether this addition (<hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo,</hi>) should not be taken as a by-name. For, otherwise there is in our <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ands a peece of siluer coine, with the inscription of <hi>Lucius Iulius,</hi> sonne of <hi>Lucius,</hi> and surnamed <hi>Strabo.</hi> The Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gramme of the former is extant among the Antiquities of <hi>Rome</hi> citie, in this maner.</p>
   <p>
      <q>C. Iulius, L. F. Caesar Strabo, AEd. Cur. Q. Trib. Mil. Bis XVIR. AGR. D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nd. ADTR. IV D. Pontif.</q>
   </p>
   <p>To conclude, I have met with writers, who reckoned also among the Iulij, certaine* <hi>Annales:</hi> which, for mine owne part verily, I could never yet light upon, in searching the Records &amp; Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles. But in the eight booke of the Familiar Epistles (of <hi>Cicero</hi>) and namely in the seaventh letter there, of <hi>M. Caelius</hi> unto <hi>Cicero,</hi> there is mention made among others, of one <hi>L. Iulius,</hi> sonne of <hi>Lucius, Pomp. Annalis:</hi> where the writing (as I suppose) is not very certaine and
<pb facs="4"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> acknowledge. For besides that the better corrected Copies call him <hi>Villius,</hi> (for <hi>Iulius</hi>) <hi>Liuie</hi> also hath expresly &amp; plainely written in his fortieth booke, that one <hi>Lucius Villius</hi> a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune of the Commons, made a Law which prouided and ordained, in what yeere of mens age they might sue for everie kinde of Magistracie, and be capable thereof. Whereupon, unto that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> was giuen this surname, to be called <hi>Annales</hi> Thus farre <hi>Liuius.</hi> Hereunto may <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> moreouer; that the Kinred <hi>Iulia,</hi> is reckoned in the Tribe <hi>Fabia</hi> (and not <hi>Pomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>),</hi> as we have noted in the fortieth chapter of <hi>Augustus.</hi> I am of opinion therefore, that safer <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> account the <hi>Annales</hi> among the <hi>Villii,</hi> and not the <hi>Iulii.</hi> But thus much hereof, by the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ay, and as it were passing by; Now proceede we to the rest.</p>
   <p>In the linage <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> then, there was a familie also of the <hi>Caesars.</hi> But what the reason should be of that surname, it is not certainely knowne; no more, than who he was, that first bare the saide <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. For, before <hi>Caesar</hi> the Dictator, and his father and grandfather, there were <hi>Iulii</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Cae<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ares.</hi> As for example; He, who (as <hi>Livie</hi> witnesseth in his 27. booke) was in the second <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>unick warre sent from the Senate to <hi>Crispinus</hi> the Consul, about the nomination of a Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour. As for the terme <hi>Cae<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ares,</hi> those usually the Romane tongue surnamed so, who were borne, either by r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>pping their mothers wombes▪ or with a<note n="*" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> bush of haire growing on their heads, or else<note n="*" place="margin">cum <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. Some adde moreouer the tale of an Elephant slaine in <hi>Africk,</hi> which the inhabitants there call <hi>Caesar:</hi> and vpon that verie cavse, this surname first befell unto <hi>Caesar</hi> the Dictatours <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. But <hi>Spartia<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>us</hi> and <hi>Servius,</hi> the Authors hereof, are of the meanest credite and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. For not his progeny alone, of all the <hi>Iulii,</hi> had this surname, but many others besides of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, both long before and also together with him.</p>
   <p>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> before <hi>Iulius <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> the Dictator, there were, Sext. <hi>Iulius,</hi> sonne of <hi>Caius,</hi> nephew of <hi>Lucius,</hi> together vvith <hi>Lucius Aurelius Orestes,</hi> in the yeere after the foundation of <hi>Rome<note n="*" place="margin">
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>.</note>
      </hi> 596: Also <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Iulius</hi> sonne of <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>us,</hi> nephew of <hi>Sext,</hi> was colleague vvith <hi>L. Marcius Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> in the beginning of the Sociall vvarre in the yeare after the cities foundation<note n="*" place="margin">597. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue said Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</note> 662. and in the next yeere after, <hi>Lucius Iulius</hi> so<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ne of <hi>Lucius,</hi> and Nephew of <hi>Lucius,</hi> bare the Consulate with <hi>Pub. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Lupu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</hi> Neither before these, were anie of the <hi>Caesars</hi> reno<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>med or aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the highest Office<note n="*" place="margin">663.</note> of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. Many▪<note n="*" place="margin">Consul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship. Frater pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truelis.</note> yeeres after, out of the same familie, <hi>Lucius Caesar,</hi> son of <hi>Sextus</hi> and cosi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> Germane to that <hi>C. Iulius</hi> Caesar, who beg at the Dictato<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>r, and attained only to the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, who also died at <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>sae</hi> without any evident sicknesse, euen as he did his shoes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> in a morning, that <hi>L. Caesar</hi> I say, came to be Consull.</p>
   <p>Well. <hi>Caesar</hi> the Dictator was borne at Rome (when <hi>Caius Marcius</hi> and <hi>Lucius Valerius Flaccus</hi> were Consuls) vpon the fourth day before the Ides of <hi>Quintilis,</hi> which moneth after his death, was by vertue of the Lavv <hi>Antonia</hi> called for that cause, <hi>Iulie,</hi> His bringing up hee had vvith his mother <hi>Aurelia,</hi> daughter of <hi>Caius Cotta,</hi> and his aunt by the fathers side <hi>Iulia,</hi> the vvife of <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</hi> Whereupon grevv the love that he tooke (a Petritian though he vvere) to the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Fa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>tion; and the hatred he bare to <hi>Sulla.</hi> The Greeke and Latine tongue, the precepts also <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of Oratorie, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e learned of M. <hi>Ant<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nius Gu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>pho,</hi> a French man borne. Who being of an <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>it and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> memorie, courteous besides in his behauiour, and of a kinde &amp; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> nature, taught the Greek and Latine, Grammer, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>itbal, first in the house of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ius <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> in his ovvne; and got much there<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>; such vvas the bountie of his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> that hee never compounded vvith <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> for any vvages or revvard. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> vvonderous <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and apt to learne, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>a and framed naturally for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
   <p>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> speech vvas trimly <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>arnished, (<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Domesticall <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>cquaintance) by his mother <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> spake the Romane tongue purely and elegantly: like as the <hi>Muciae, Laeliae, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> honorable Dames did, in vvhose families there arose Oratours of great <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>