<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Readers,
Instructions for their voiage into
this new world.</title>
           <author>Healey, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103684_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68132</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12686.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103684</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Readers,
Instructions for their voiage into
this new world.</title>
                 <author>Healey, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The discouery of a new world or A description of the South Indies : Hetherto vnknowne by an English Mercury</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 244 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Readers,
Instructions for their voiage into
this new world.</head>
   <p>THere are diuers inquisitiue <hi>Scepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi>
(vnpartial reader, for such I
would haue thee to be,) who since this new
<hi>Discouery of the South Indies,</hi> vpon
some ouer-sight of mine owne, in not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
sufficient intimation of the grounds
whence I had the first light of the said
<hi>Discouery,</hi> as also of the manner where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
I haue proceeded vpon the said grounds
haue out-runne their owne iudgments in
descanting farre otherwise of this worke,
then a fauourable censure would euer
haue held it to deserue, and being either
lead with too much zeale to the well deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
vertues of <hi>that Reuerend man</hi> that
long agoe laid the first proiect of this <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery,</hi>
or with (it may be a true) obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation
of some imperfection in mee that
now of late haue raised this new building
vpon that old foundation: haue taken oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
both to thinke him lesse worthy of
their good conceites, and also to proclaime
me a iust deseruer of the seuerest and most
<pb facs="6"/>
exemplary censures. Which wrong done
vnto him (whome I must euer reuerence)
hath bound mee to make an ingenuous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement
of mine owne forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
in the first edition of this present
worke, rather then to sit still and see his
reputation exposed to the misconstructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
to which my negligence is (&amp; in some
iudgements, iustly) imagined to haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
the first and originall cause. But let
this protestation be (if it may be) suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
to remooue the weight of siniste im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations
from his grauity, and lay them
vpon mine owne youthfulnesse, that I dare
engage my life, there is no man in the
whole world, who hath either conuersed
with himselfe in person, or his workes in
print, that euer will surmise this present
copy to haue had any testimony of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement,
or approbation to bee any
way befitting his place, or (which is more)
his profession. Wherefore to giue a full
answere vnto that grosse misprision of
theirs, who imagine the worke it selfe to
haue beene of his writing and publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in the forme wherein it now passeth;
whereby they take occasion to taxe him of
<pb facs="6"/>
diuers (in their iudgement) immodest,
light, scurrilous, and ridiculous passages
therein. I doe here absolutely auerre, and
giue notice to all that shall hereafter take
view hereof, This worke was neuer his, he
neuer saw it, neuer dreamed of any such
matter, vntill hee met it in the hand of
another man. There was indeed a little
booke some 8. or 9. yeares agoe that came
from <hi>Franckford,</hi> which some few (I know
not vpon what illumination more then
ordinary) affirmed to haue passed the file
of his muse, which if it be true, it can be no
way in the world either preiudiciall to his
learning, (seeing it hath all perfection fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
an absolute poeme) nor to his grauity
or profession, seeing it was a birth of his
youth; wherein neuerthelesse I will a vow
that hee hath towred aboue the capacities
(at least aboue the imitation) of all those
ouer-weening iudgements that dare any
way presume to traduce his originall. In
iust defence of which worthy worke, I cast
defiance in the teeth of all that malice or
traduce him, that it is neither any way
scurrilous, immodest, light, nor ridiculous:
and I will giue the proudest <hi>Critique</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
that liues, as many yeares as hee and his
fellowes haue bin fooles, either to parallell
it, or to pick any the least touch out of it,
which cannot bee defended euen till his
wittes that shall oppose, be drawne as dry
as euer <hi>Dutchman</hi> left cup.</p>
   <p>But as touching this present pile of
<hi>English,</hi> it is mine, it hath no further al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liāce
to his, then chalke hath to cheese, for
as these haue no cohaerence in their nearest
proprieties (which translations should ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
want) but onely in their generall kind
of essence as they are both corporeall sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances;
no more doth this worke any way
resemble his in fashion, stile, or discourse,
but onely in the inuention and proiect. As
for the passages in it, which some pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
to bee scurrilous or immodest, there
may perhaps bee some indeed that carry
not that pondrous respect in them which
an ancient iudgement, or retired grauity
may seeme to require: I grant it, what
would yee haue more? they are flashes of
youth: <hi>semel insaniuimus omnes;</hi> And
I pray yee (that censure mee so ruthlesly)
which of you all is there, but one time or
other in the forenoone of your daies, hath
<pb facs="7"/>
had his <hi>vagaries</hi> in the world, and hath
flowne out sometimes as well as I? Oh but,
not inprint, saies some seuerer <hi>Critique!</hi>
Alas yet had <hi>Ouid</hi> his <hi>Amores, Seneca</hi>
his <hi>Lusus in Claudium,</hi> and others as
graue as hee, their exorbitances now and
then as vnguirt as others! But that these
weakenesses (for so I confesse they are) in
mee, should be made as staines to the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
of another, of one whose learning,
life, and workes now extant may serue as
purging fires whereat all those that hence
haue taken occasion to wrong him thus,
might long agoe haue lighted their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
were it neuer so immense; that my
lightnesses should bee reputed as births of
his worthines! Oh that my pen (whereby
since I have ignorantly iniur'd him, I doe
thus willingly and freely cleare him) could
but make them see what an vniust con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction
they haue made of an ignorant
(and I protest vtterly vnwilling) offence!
But since mine owne vnwarinesse gaue
first occasion of those vnkinde, and more
then foolish callumniations which igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
draweth from mine error, to staine
his goodnesse with; all the satisfaction I
<pb facs="8"/>
can giue him, is to shew my selfe willing to
make a faire way againe for his deserts,
in the bosomes of such as hence take their
occasiō of dislike, by proclaiming this truth
to all that shall read it, that this present
<hi>Discouery of the South-Indies</hi> is none
of his, but had this forme giuen it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
his knowledge, by one who will euer
acknowledge his worth &amp; grauity to haue
beene vtterly ignorant of any vnfit phrase
whatsoeuer included in the whole booke.
Hee whom my contrition, and this satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<hi>(COLLATERALLY)</hi> cannot content,
is without mercy, and I assure my selfe will
dye without merit, if hee bee not quickly
shipt away for this new <hi>Continent,</hi> with
letters of commendation to all our friends
in <hi>Cockscombaya.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>As for you (gentlemen and frinds)
whose iudgements haue giuen gracious
acceptance to this our <hi>Imaginary world,</hi>
I will euer endeuor to further your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments
with the best inuentions that
the labours of a yong scholler can produce.
You, (right <hi>Iouiall</hi> spirits) and none but
you, are they to whom I consecrate these
my trauels, since none but you can discerne
<pb facs="8"/>
the sence which they include. Onely in
one thing I must intreate your fauorable
Censures, and that is, in my allusions here
and there vnto the names of some cities of
fame and respect, both of our owne, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:
assuring you (as your true exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
of the particulars may assure you
better) that I had no intent to intimate
any collation or reference of the state or
maners of those I describe, vnto theirs to
which I allude. Let this protestation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
cleare me from sinister imputations,
and you from all vntrue suppositions.</p>
   <p>And know all you that haue not yet seene
these Lands, but intend to take a view of
thē hereafter, that you must first of al take
one of that <hi>French</hi> Doctors pills, <hi>Despo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillez
vous de tout affection,</hi> and this
will enable you fully to endure the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of all ayres in this clime. Secondly
you must neuer trauell single, but two, or
three in a company, for one you know may
apprehend more then another can, and
those before, that haue miscaried in this
voiage, as you haue heard, incurred their
misfortunes onely by neglecting this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,
and by too much conuersing with
<pb facs="9"/>
those of the <hi>Foolianders</hi> nation. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
you must go ouer the country thrice, ere
you shalbe able to make any exact plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
of it: Once for <hi>Strabo,</hi> once for
<hi>Socrates,</hi> and once for <hi>Merlin Cocaius;</hi>
The first for the <hi>Geography,</hi> the second
for the <hi>Morality,</hi> and the third for the
<hi>Language,</hi> and <hi>Etymology.</hi> No more at
this time, but aboord when you please and a
good gale of wit go along with you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>His, that is his.
IOHN HEALEY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>