<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTERS ADVERTISSE∣ment to the Gentleman Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103899_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02775</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12903</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103899</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTERS ADVERTISSE∣ment to the Gentleman Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pierces supererogation or A new prayse of the old asse : A preparatiue to certaine larger discourses, intituled Nashes s. fame. Gabriell Haruey</title>
                 <author>Harvey, Gabriel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 199, 100-120, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="advertisement">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>THE PRINTERS ADVERTISSE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Gentleman Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vrteous Gentlemen, it seemed good to M. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour Haruey, for breuity-sake, and bicause he liked not ouer-long Preambles, or Postambles to short Discourses, to omit the commendatorie Letters, and Sonnets of M.Thorius, M.Chewt, and diuers other his affectionate frendes of London, and both the Vniuersities. Which neuerthelesse are reserued to be prefixed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted, or annexed, either in his <hi>defensiue Letters,</hi> enlarged with certaine new Epistles of more speciall note; or in his <hi>Discourses ofNashes S. Fame,</hi> already finished, &amp; presently to be published, as these shall like their interteinem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>t: of whose fauorable &amp; plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible Welcome, diuers learned and fine wittes haue presumed the best. Howbeit finally it was thought not amisse, vpon conference with some his aduised acquaintance, to make choice of some two, or three of the reasonablest, and temperatest Sonnets (but for va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety, &amp; to auoyde tediousnesse in the entrance, rather to be anne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed in the end, then prefixed in the beginning of the present Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses): one of the foresayd M. Thorius, an other of M. Chewt, and the third of a learned French Gentleman, Monsieur Frege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Gautius, who hath published some weighty Treatises, aswell Politique, as Religious, both in Latin, and French; and hath acquainted M. Doctour Haruey with certaine most profitable Mathematicall deuises of his owne inuention. The residue is not added by me, but annexed by the Autor himselfe: whom I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly recommende to your curteous Censure, and so rest from ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troubling you with my vnpolished lines.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
      <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
   </gap>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>