<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A
LETTER VVRIT∣TFN
BY A GENTLEMAN
OF GOOD WORTH, TO
the Author of this booke.</title>
           <author>Philosilpnos, </author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103861_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02649</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12779.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103861</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A
LETTER VVRIT∣TFN
BY A GENTLEMAN
OF GOOD WORTH, TO
the Author of this booke.</title>
                 <author>Philosilpnos, </author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A nevv discovrse of a stale svbiect, called the metamorphosis of Aiax : vvritten by Misacmos, to his friend and cosin Philostilpnos</title>
                 <author>Harington, John, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 120 pages, illustrations, music, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A
LETTER VVRIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TFN
BY A GENTLEMAN
OF GOOD WORTH, TO
the Author of this booke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, I haue heard much of
your house, of your picturs,
of your walks, of your pōds,
and of your two boats, that
came one by land, and the
other by sea, from Lōdon bridge, and met
both at Bath bridge: all which God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
(if I liue another sommer) I will come
of purpose to see; as also a swimming
place, where if one may beleeue your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Fraunces, Diana did bath her, and
Acteon see her without hornes. But to
deale plainly with you, there be three spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
things that I haue heard much boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted
of, and therefore would willingliest
see. The one a fountaine stāding on pillers,<note place="margin">43. Can.</note>
like that in Ariosto, vnder which you may
dine and suppe; the second a shooting
close with a xij score marke to euery point
<pb facs="3"/>
of the card, in which I heare you haue hit
a marke that many shoote at, viz: to make
a barren stony lād fruitfull with a litle cost;
the third is a thing that I cannot name wel
without saue-reuerence, and yet it sounds
not vnlike the shooting place, but it is
in plaine English a shiting place. Though,
if it be so sweete and so cleanely as I
heare, it is a wrong to it to vse saue reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
for one told me, it is as sweet as my
parlor, and I would think discourtesie, one
should say, saue reuerence my parlor. But
if I might entreate you (as you partly
promist me at your last being here) to set
downe the maner of it in writing, so plaine
as our grosse wittes here may vnderstand
it, or to cause your man M. Combe (who
I vnderstand can paint prettilie) make a
draught, or plot thereof to be well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued,
you should make many of your
friends much beholding to you, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
you might cause reformation in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
houses that you wish well vnto, that
<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ill thinke no scorne to follow your good
example. Nay to tell you my opinion se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouslie,
if you haue so easie, so cheape,
and so infallible a way for auoiding such
<pb facs="3"/>
annoiances in great houses: you may not
onelie pleasure manie great persons, but
doe her Maiestie good seruice in her pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace
of Greenwitch and other stately hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
that are oft annoyed with such sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours,
as where many mouthes be fed can
hardly be auoided. Also you might be a
great benefactor to the Citie of London,
and all other populous townes, who stand
in great need of such conuayances. But all
my feare is, that your pen hauing beene
inured to so high a discourse,</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Of Dames, of Knights, of armes, of loues delight,</hi>
   </p>
   <p>will now disdaine to take so base a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Of vaults, of sinkes, priuies &amp; draughts to write.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But herein let a publicke benefit expell
a priuat bashfulnesse, and if you must now
and then breake the rules <hi>de slouilitate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
with some of these homelie wordes,
you see I haue broken the ise to you, and
you know the old saying, pens maie blot,
but they cannot blush. And as old Tarlton
was wont to saie, this same excellent
word saue-reuerence, makes it all maner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.
Once this I dare assure you, if you can
but tell a homelie tale of this in prose as
<pb facs="4"/>
cleanlie, as you haue told in verse a baudy
tale or two in Orlando mannerly, it may
passe among the sowrest censurers verie
currantly. And thus expecting your
aunswer hereto, at your conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient
leysure, I commit
you to God this of
1596.</p>
   <signed>Your louing cosin.
PHILOSILPNOS.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>