<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my louing Brother Mr.
SAMVEL WARD.</title>
           <author>Ward, Nathaniel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103040_Bo1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14745</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25046</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103040</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my louing Brother Mr.
SAMVEL WARD.</title>
                 <author>Ward, Nathaniel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iethro's iustice of peace : A sermon preached at a generall assises held at Bury St. Edmunds, for the countie of Suffolke. By Samuel Ward Batchelour of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Ward, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Marriot, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_brother">
   <head>To my louing Brother M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>.
SAMVEL WARD.</head>
   <p>BRother, if you meet with your <hi>Iethro's</hi> counsell
returned from beyond the seas, and as much
beyond your expectation preserued aliue, as his
sonne in law was against <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> Iniunction, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell
as much as you will, but bee no more offended
then you haue cause. <hi>Ioab</hi> sinned wider on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
hand in destroying <hi>Dauids Absolom,</hi> contrary
to his serious charge, yet <hi>Ioab</hi> was pardoned, and
yet no brother. I haue noted you hitherto inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
for your owne publishing of any thing of your
owne; whether out of iudgement, modesty, curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity,
or melancholy, I iudge not: but when others
haue aduentured them with fruit and acceptance,
into the light, I haue seene you rest content with
the publique good The like leaue I haue taken,
expecting like successe, assuring you and my selfe
of the generall welcomnesse and vsefulnesse heerof
<pb n="72" facs="40"/>
to all whom it concernes, which are the greatest
number of the land, euen so many as haue any refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
to Sessions and Assises, if not all sorts of
Christians. Onely I feare that the corruption of
our times is growne so grosse and <hi>Eglon</hi>-like, that
it doth not <hi>Ebud</hi>-like enough sharpen the poynts,
and send them home to the heft, that they may
reach to the quicke. I had my selfe added thereto a
proiect and perswasion for the redresse of many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buses
crept into offices and officers, hauing spent
so much time in the study of the law, and execution
of some offices, as made me weary of the errours I
saw, and heartily wish the reformation of them:
but fearing I haue learned too much bluntnesse &amp;
plumpnesse of speech among the Lutherans, which
is here as prime a quality, as smoothnes with you,
as also loth to meddle out of mine orb, in my se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
thoughts I suppressed it. And so wishing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
this, many diligent, conscionable and ingenuous
Readers and Appliers, and to them Gods blessing
and the fruit intended, I take my leaue. From <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing</hi>
in <hi>Prusia.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your brother in the flesh, in the Lord, and
in the worke of the ministery.
<hi>NATH. WARD.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>