<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the READER.</title>
           <author>Goffe, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1627</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103197_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01837</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11978</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103197</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the READER.</title>
                 <author>Goffe, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Deliuerance from the graue : A sermon preached at Saint Maries Spittle in London, on Wednesday in Easter weeke last, March 28. 1627. By Tho. Goffe, Batchelor of Diuinitie, lately student of Christ-Church in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Goffe, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mab (Mabbe), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1627</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, the maine word in the Text of this following Sermon, is the <hi>Graue:</hi> and in a <hi>Graue</hi> of silence, after that once speaking, it had for euer beene laid, but that I was loth to leaue it in a deeper <hi>Graue</hi> then any <hi>Ezechiels</hi> Valley afforded, the throat of Detraction; which <hi>Dauid</hi> iustly cals an <hi>open sepulcher.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal. 5▪</hi>
      </note> I doe with all humilitie thanke the Bestower of all gifts, who enabled mee to conceiue these vnworthy Meditations, who strengthen'd me to vtter them, and for whose sake I had an honourable, learned, and religious Audience, whose deuout Attention did much encourage me in that holy Taske. But it seemes my weake labours were not of the nature of those things, which <hi>decies repetita placebunt</hi>: for the <hi>Rehearser</hi> could not taste them <hi>once,</hi> who rather <hi>hunted</hi> after a prey for his enuie, then to performe the great and pious businesse he vndertooke. Pitty it is, that a Christian, a Scholler, a Preacher, could not thinke me a fellow-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister with him in all, both of the same Church and Gospel! for so the courteous imparting of my Notes to him many dayes before, proues that I reputed him a fellow-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer with me. It may therfore iustly be expected by all that know how sensible I must needs be of so publike and so vndeseru'd a prouocation, that I should pay him again in his owne coine: and how easily could I whet my Penne, and giue the reines to an vnbridled, but iust anger? But <hi>non sic didici Christum,</hi> I haue learn'd of Him to be ready to forgiue, who teacheth vs to beare with wrongs; not because out of <hi>basenesse</hi> wee cannot reuenge, but out of <hi>Religion</hi> we will not. Therefore I will not smite an Hebrew, one that should be of my Brethren; whose memory I neuer intended to bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb facs="3"/>
with more of my Sermon then he pleas'd, nor speake I, because he left out the most part; nay, in effect the whole Sermon in rehearsing: it neither deseru'd, nor did I euer desire an exact rendring; but what was wanting on his part in <hi>memory,</hi> or as himselfe profest in <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,</hi> to make vp with malice, shew'd his <hi>zeale</hi> to be voyd of <hi>discretion,</hi> and his <hi>emulation</hi> of <hi>Religion.</hi> For my expressions, (vpon which he bestow'd some vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeming tearmes of derision) I know no reason, why I should euer change one particle of that poore language which God hath lent me, to honour him withall, in hope to be vpon all occasions supplied, out of the <hi>empty store</hi> of <hi>Rheumatick</hi> &amp; <hi>extempory Barbarisme:</hi> yet who-euer shall truly weigh the whole body of my discourse, shall find it, for the most part, squar'd by the comely Phrase of the Scripture, which I shall euer esteeme the <hi>Well-spring</hi> of <hi>Diuinity:</hi> If otherwise, this small worke of mine owne will disapproue me: For I am forst to that which I neuer affected, to put my selfe vpon the iudgement of diuers Readers, whether this Sermon deseru'd the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of that one Rehearser. From whose lame Repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I appeale: and let this Sermon speake for it selfe, as it was then spoke by my selfe, who in the Pulpit neuer vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any thought, but with an vnfained intent to honour God, and none but God; and to benefit my Audients <hi>soules</hi> not <hi>eares;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Hooker Eccle. pol. lib. 5. par. 30.</hi>
      </note> To their surmises, who thinke I gaue any cause to be tax't, I say <hi>no:</hi> to other whisperers, <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> So I commit my Sermon to thy reading, and thy selfe to the Almightie.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my Studie in</hi> East-Clanden <hi>in</hi> Surrey,
<date>April. <hi>17. 1627.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus, THO. GOFFE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>