<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Worthington, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103650_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15726</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25999</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103650</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Worthington, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ground of a Christians life : Deliuered in a sermon at Harwood in Lancashire, the first day of December 1618. By Robert Worthington minister of Gods word at Acceington</title>
                 <author>Worthington, Robert, minister of Gods word at Acceington</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 76 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle prophesied that in<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 5. 2. Tim. 4. 3.</note> the last dayes shold come perillous times, when men hauing a shew of godlinesse should denie the power therof: &amp; refusing wholsome dostrine, through their itching eares, should get them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues an heape of teachers. What proud Anabaptist, that vaunteth himselfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the stage of vaine Imagination, or secure Papist, that trusteth to the broken staffe of Egypt, can free himselfe from such spirituall maladies? who leauing the key of knowledge, and fountaines of liuing water, haue digged vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
<pb facs="3"/> broken cisternes. And no maruell: since Satan cantransforme himselfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11. 14.</note> an Angell of light, how can he worke in the darkened vnderstanding, and the heart not truly humbled? He that dare enter combat with the Lord of glorie, wisdome and soueraigntie, and offer dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in the full and onely point of mans redemption; how boldly will this politicke and puissant enemie inuade Gods Church, wrastling with vs about that staffe of faith whereby we stand, &amp; seeke to strip vs of that shield which is<note place="margin">Ephes. 6. 16.</note> able to keepe backe all his fierie darts? What soldier is there in Christs campe, if he do but watch, that shall not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his subtill enterprises? Christs watchword was not in vaine, <hi>Watch &amp; pray, lest ye enter into tēp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 26. 41.</note> nor his prayer needlesse for his seruant Peter, <hi>I haue prayed for thee,<note place="margin">Luk, 22. 32.</note> that thy faith faile not.</hi> For what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter treacherie then to strike at the root? (witnessed in the Gunpowder treason,
<pb facs="3"/> hatched by Satan and his instruments,) or what greater follie, then to build an house without a foundation? To this purpose is my weake &amp; vnperfect labor at this time, the which I had thought to haue shrowded vnder some Christian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, but considering with my selfe, I thought so small a worke deserued not a patronage of anie worth: and the rather therefore haue I sent it to the broade world to seeke for it selfe, trusting that there is no faithfull heart that will denie so plaine and needfull a doctrine enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment. Yet I feare that if it shall ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meete with Atheist, Anabaptist, Papist, or earthly worldling, it is like (without Gods mercie) to finde as litle friendship as Christ the author of faith did among the Gadarens. But howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,<note place="margin">Math 8. 34.</note> I haue at the earnest desires of some, as also for the defence of my selfe, if haply anie popish surmiser or other se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret opinionist should arise in opposition (it being preached in a countrey where
<pb facs="4"/> are many aduersaries of our faith) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed to commit that to publike view which before I deliuered in open assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, not aduenturing to change my style, lest I should bewray my selfe of follie, in bringing vnto light a groundlesse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: it being like to be perused by shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower iudgements then manie of those who were present whē it was at the first diuulged. Wherfore I beseech thee (gentle Reader) that if by Gods blessing thou shalt gaine to thy selfe hereby, either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of thy iudgement, or confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in thȳ iudgement, or thy will proucked to a more constant vigilancie ouer thy wayes, remember to returne to him that rent of thankfulnesse vnto whom thou art bound, from whom thou receiuest euery good and perfest gift: praying withall for the vnitie of Gods Church, the propagation of the Gospell, that through the meanes of grace, in sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and out of season, thy faith being strengthened, when this life of faith
<pb facs="4"/> shall be finished, Christ the obiect of thy faith may assigne thee the end of thy faith, seating thee in his celestiall Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem with true beleeuers.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ Iesus, Robert Worthington.</signed>
      <dateline>Acceington.</dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>