<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface of the author to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1559</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103098_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01662</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11800</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103098</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface of the author to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The treasure of Euonymus : conteyninge the vvonderfull hid secretes of nature, touchinge the most apte formes to prepare and destyl medicines, for the conseruation of helth: as quintesse [n] ce, aurum potabile, hippocras, aromatical wynes, balmes, oyles perfumes, garnishyng waters, and other manifold excellent confections. Wherunto are ioyned the formes of sondry apt fornaces, and vessels, required in this art. Translated (with great diligence, [et] laboure) out of Latin, by Peter Morvvying felow of Magdaline Colleadge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Gesner, Konrad</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1559</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 408 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The preface of the author <hi>to the Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <argument>
      <list>
         <item>i Of the inuention of liquors and oyles destilled.</item>
         <item>ii Of the scope and end of this booke. Whereof more also shalbe spoken about the end of the Preface.</item>
         <item>iii The praise of them that can be content to make commō the best and most effectuous medicins they haue.</item>
         <item>iiii How much the dressing and maner of preparans auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in euery thing.</item>
      </list>
   </argument>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Art of destillatiō (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they call <hi>Chymia, Alchimia, Alkimia, Chemia Suidas</hi> calleth it, and <hi>Alchemia)</hi> hath inuented many profitable things for mās life, and in Phisicke also certain meruelous thinges, and praise worthy, if a man prepare them righte and diligentlye. For the lacke of knowledge, Couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or negligence of Phisitions and commun Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries is the cause why many such preparations are set litle by: and worthily, if you respect that which they prepare: vnworthely, if ye marke the Art it selfe, whiche certes is most excellent and most profitable: which semeth to be the cause why it lay hid so long, and began to come in vre ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry late. Some ascribe vnto <hi>Hierom</hi> of <hi>Brunsvvick,</hi> which about .lxx. yeares past practised Phisick at <hi>Argentyn,</hi> the originall of getting out waters, as they cal them, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors and oyles out of simple medicines by the strengthe of fire: but they are much deceiued, for this Arte was not inuented by him, but wryten in our Dutch tung and first set out by him. In mine opinion this inuencion is so aū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient as the inuencion of the very <hi>Chymia,</hi> which I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose was celebrated first and put in wryting by men that
<pb facs="4"/>
vsed the <hi>Punicall</hi> or els the <hi>Arabicke</hi> tonge, a litle after the age of the Grecian Phisicions, Of those I speake that writ almooste the latest, as <hi>Aetius, Oribasius, Actuarius, Psellus.</hi> In certain libraries in <hi>Italy</hi> euen at this day, are there extant certain wrytinges of <hi>Chymia</hi> by certain late <hi>Grecians,</hi> namely a certain Philosopher called <hi>Stephan:</hi> al so a boke intituled of the chaunging of metals, which cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munlye are called <hi>Chymia,</hi> or <hi>Arcymia.</hi> There is also a boke to be had of <hi>Alchymia</hi> made by <hi>Auicenna</hi> vnto <hi>Assis</hi> a Philosopher. <hi>Geber</hi> (the Nepheu of I canne not tell what great <hi>Mahomet)</hi> who is celebrated as a captain and prince of this science, what age he liued in I can not easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly say. Although I iudge him not to haue bene the first in uentor of this Art, but one that broughte it to lighte and renouned it. This man in his worke intitled <hi>Summae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionis,</hi> discoursinge excellentlye and disputinge manye things of destillacion generallye, writeth that diuers ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of destilling are knowne almost of all men, euen as an auncient inuenciō, yea in his time also, no new thing. Certain late wryters declare the wrytinges of <hi>Alchymia</hi> not only of <hi>Albertus Magnus, S. Thomas, Rhaza,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicenna, Arabik</hi> Phisitions, but also of <hi>Aristotle, Plato</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> at the least wise mention to be made by thē of it: to whome I geue small credence, not that I thincke this studye to be the newer, but certes that it was ether vnknown to these philosophers or mentioned in no place. Some there be that expound feetly and wittily al the fei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Poets, and chieflye that of the golden fleece, sought by the <hi>Argonautae,</hi> vnto the multiplying of Golde or Art of enterchaunging of metalles. Some also ascende higher, and make the first men by and by after the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nidg of the world, authors therof. Some simplely make it most auncient, and affirme that no certainty is to be had of the first inuēters. At <hi>Padvvay</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> in our time was found a most auncient monument, namely an erthen pot, hauing written vpon it this <hi>Hexasticon.</hi>
   </p>
   <q xml:lang="lat">
      <lg>
         <pb facs="4"/>
         <l>Plutoni sacrum munus ne attingite fures,</l>
         <l>Ignotum est vobis hoc quod in vrna latet.</l>
         <l>Nanque elementa graui clausit digesta labore,</l>
         <l>Vase sub hoc modico, Maximus Olibius:</l>
         <l>Adsit foecundo custos sibi copia cornu,</l>
         <l>Ne praetium tanti depereat laticis.</l>
      </lg>
   </q>
   <q>
      <lg>
         <l>This sacred to God <hi>Pluto</hi> (theues) ware that ye touch not,</l>
         <l>Vnknown is it to you all, this that is hid in a pot.</l>
         <l>For the elements hath ishut vp digested with much pain,</l>
         <l>In this smal vessel the great <hi>Olibius</hi> certaine.</l>
         <l>Plenty with thy fruteful horn as a gard be thou present,</l>
         <l>Least the price pearish of this liquor most excellent.</l>
      </lg>
   </q>
   <p>Within this pot was an other litle pot with the inscription of these verses.</p>
   <q xml:lang="lat">
      <lg>
         <l>Abite hinc pessimi fures</l>
         <l>Vos quid voltis cum vostris oculis emissitiis?</l>
         <l>Abite hīc vostro cū Mercurio petasato caduceato{que}</l>
         <l>Maximus maximo donum Plotoni hoc sacrū facit</l>
      </lg>
   </q>
   <q>
      <lg>
         <l>Away frō hēce ye mighty theues, trudge els wher &amp; go by,</l>
         <l>What seke ye with your spying eies, why do ye por &amp; pry</l>
         <l>Hens with your hatted <hi>Mercury,</hi> and with his rod also.</l>
         <l>This gift is sacred by the greatst vnto the greatest <hi>Ploto.</hi>
         </l>
      </lg>
   </q>
   <p>Again, within this little pot was found a light yet bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning betwene two Phials, the one of Gould, the other of Siluer, ful of a certain mooste pure liquor, by the vertue wherof they beleue that this lighte had burnte manye a yeare, as did noote in their collections and gatherings of old auncient inscriptiōs or Poesies <hi>Petrus Appianus</hi> and <hi>Bartholom eus Amantius Hermolaus Barbarus</hi> also in his
<pb facs="5"/>
Corollarium or addicion vpon <hi>Dioscorides</hi> made mention of this same thing, wheras he entreateth of waters in cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun. There is also (saith he) a heauenlye water, or rather diuine of the Chymistes, whiche boothe <hi>Democritus</hi> and <hi>Mercury Trimegistus</hi> knewe: callinge it sometimes a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine water, somtimes a <hi>Seythicall</hi> liquor, somtimes <hi>pneu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> that is, spirit of the nature of the firmament, and of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> fift essens or substance of things: wherof potable gold, and that philosophers stone much spoken of, but not yet fond, consisteth. Hereupon also is the name geuen vnto the art calling it <hi>Psammurgicall,</hi> and misticall, and <hi>Annophysiall</hi> and holy, and greatest: as thoughe it had certaine secreate letters, and such as it should be conueniente to kepe and restrein the profane commun people from. This kinde of liquor, as I suppose, dothe the Epigram signifye of late found within the field of <hi>Padua</hi> nie vnto the village called <hi>Atesta,</hi> made vpon earthen or bricke mettal, and therfore frail, and broken vnwares by the handes of a man of the country digging the ground in the same place. The remē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance wherof least it should pearish we haue added here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the very wordes. <hi>This holy gift to the God, &amp;c.</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore. Therfore it appeareth that the study of this Art was of moste antiquitie amongste the Barbarus nacions, but deriued vnto the Romains and Grekes somwhat late, ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther before perauenture that the Romains obteined the dominion of a great part of the worlde: or if sooner yet co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertly &amp; reteined emongst a very fewe. <hi>Cicendulae</hi> y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> shine in the night (saith <hi>Cardane)</hi> teach vs that a liquor may be made that may shine in the dark. It is made certes by the putrifying of those things that haue most erceding bright<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, light &amp; perspicuitie. I dout not but it is possible to be made, wherof and how, I am vncertain. But these things are almost besides our matter, sauing that it mighte seme vtterly that the way to sublimate &amp; destil, as they term it, hath had his original of the Chimists, &amp; continued also al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wais
<pb facs="5"/>
w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> their art: was opened vnto the mē of our parte of the world thē first, whē as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world being made known bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thimpery of the Romains, sundry kinds of spices also &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners medicins vnknown befor to the men of <hi>Europe,</hi> &amp; to the Grekes &amp; Latins also, began to be brought in: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward also more, what time as the <hi>Mauritans</hi> &amp; mē lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the <hi>Arabik</hi> tung &amp; doctrin, possessed a great part of <hi>Spain,</hi> wherby certain bokes of learned mē cam vnto vs: &amp; amongst the latter sort, as I think, the works of one <hi>Bulca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sis Benaberazeris</hi> who in the place wher he intreteth of the preparation of medicins, teacheth also of many things to be sublimated &amp; destilled. About the age of the same mā al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most, I think <hi>Iohannes Mesue</hi> was famous, whō we read to haue liued about y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yere of our Lord. 1158. But be mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioneth none other destild waters thē of Roses &amp; Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wod. Mē say <hi>Auicenna</hi> florished the yere of our Lord. 1149▪ who also speketh of Rose water destild. The vsa of metalli things sublimated is far more auncient, at the leaste wise touching the tradition or tretises of authors, &amp; like wise is the vse of oyls that are made by descension or downwarde as in <hi>Rasis &amp; Aetius.</hi> A certain mā (whose name I spare to rehers,) writ of late that these maner of destilled liquors wer not vnknown to the latter Greke writers, vsing this argument, that destilled liquors are sometimes named in the writings &amp; works of <hi>Actuarius,</hi> And in dede he nameth in sōe places <hi>Rhodostagma,</hi> as in his <hi>Iulep</hi> against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cogh: &amp; a litle folowing in an other <hi>Iulep intybostagma.</hi> But w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> these words is signified nothing els thē a simple syrup of Roses or Endiue. <hi>Rhodostactum</hi> doth <hi>Agenita</hi> describe in his. 7. boke, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. 15. cha. with these words. Sieth .ii. sextars of the iuice of Roses y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> nails wherof are takē away, one ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of hony skimming it til the .iiii. part be consumed. Ye a litle before also he describeth <hi>Hydrorosatū</hi> rosed water, that also far differing frō a destiled liquor, or water destild for it consisteth of .iiii. pounds of Roses the nailes takē a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way .v. sextaries of water: ii. sextaries of hony.
<pb facs="6"/>
The <hi>Arabians</hi> also or their expositors, when they speake of the water of any plant, they vnderstand the decoctiō of it in water: and likewise <hi>Nicolas Myrepsus</hi> that writte in <hi>Greke</hi> of the compositions of medicines, whome it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be a verye late wryter, by the barbarous woordes that he vseth very oft: wherin I maruel this, that no mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made by him of waters or oyles prepared in Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mistical instruments. Only the oyl <hi>Capnistum</hi> or smoked, that is destilled by descention, doth he describe, as <hi>Aetius</hi> also. Moreouer, the thinges that the Chimistes make may I comprehend in .ii. kindes for the moste parte, that they be ether liquors or Massy things, the liquors againe are ether watery or oyly: and these ether aiery or fiery. The Massy things, are ether such as rest in the bottom: or such as are caried vpwarde: and that .ii. waies, ether as pure bodies and substauces, as they which they cal sublimated, quick siluer. &amp;c. or Sout for the remedies of the eies wyth Phisicions. There be also other artificial manner of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parings, wherwith the purest and most effectual parte in medicines is drawne out, and as it were the forme is se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the matter.</p>
   <p>And although I am not greatly trauailed nether in the Chymistical nor in the other manner of preparings, but by the way haue got the kuowledge of certain thinges, partly by mine own experience in some things, &amp; partlye of myfrends: yet what so euer and how much so euer this is, I wil communicat it with the studions of Phisick: not as though I entend to teach perfectly and absolutely the very Art of destilling and preparing of other things, but as it were wryting vnto such as now already are not all voyde and withoute knowledge of these things, hauing ether experimented them selues or red other mens wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. For I haue nothing so exrellēt or secrete, but I co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet it might ge abrode to the publik and common profit,
<pb facs="6"/>
and although in smal wealth, yet haue I ben euer of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ready to communicate and make any man priuye of any cunning I had, which som referre vnto simplicitie or childishnes, other some better to the liberalitie of my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position. There be some that do vtterly cloke and kepe se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete their things, and that diuers kinde of men: some for Ambicion, that they maye haue wherewith to excell and pas other menne: some also for couetousnes, to get gayne thereby: other thorowe the ignoraunce of the aunciente wryters, as thoughe there were not put in wrytinge ether the same or far better by men of antiquitie, whiche now are despised of many, and a folish and vnsaciable lust is ther alwais to find out new things. Ther wantes not such as think, great and effectual medicins shuld be kepte secrete for this cause, least vncunning men, as many prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticioners be, without al reason almost, and al learnynge, might abuse them, and conuert those thinges whiche are inuented for the helth of mē, to their destruction. To such wold I answer, As no kind of euil ought to be committed for this intent that any good thing might follow therof: so that which is good ought not to be left vndone, leaste som euil might ensue, for the world shal neuer be without them that wil abuse good things and profitable inuenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But good men, simplely suche good thinges as they haue, they make them common, and wil not stick nor cese to do so because they feare, that certain leud persons may do hurt therby. But I wil leaue of this disputation, thye do I protest sincerely &amp; as I thinck withal my hart, that I couet by my example to stur vp learned and good Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that laying apart al Ambition, Couetousnes, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Enuy, if they can bring any excellent thinge vnto our profession, that they wold do it gentlely and publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. As for the vnlearned certes, they in ministring not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly these great and effectual medicines, of whiche sorte we
<pb facs="7"/>
shal put diuers in wrytinge heare, but meates also and most common drinkes, out of time, do hasard and brynge mens liues manye times to diseases and deathe: and it is well known that <hi>Hippocrates</hi> writ how our <hi>Ptisan</hi> mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred not in due time, was the cause of death to a certaine man sick of the Pleurisy. These therfore ought to be lefte partly to their ignorance, partly to their leude malapart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But they that haue nede of the Physicion are to be admonished to do that in Phisicke, that all men are wont to do in al other Artes: that is, to chuse good Physicions, and learned, and such as exercise and practise this Art by their profession, both with reasōs, as a part of Philosophy and also in the very actions and doinges of cures. But I return to the purpose. The preparing therfor (as I say) is of the greatest moment and weight in euerye matter. In Rhetorik vtterans, gesture, and pronunciation more al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most moue the mindes of the hearers, then the very argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is handled. Hereupō it cometh that things put in meter and in numbers, do delite so greatly: which if a man vtter in proos, they shalbe taken for cold, dnl and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishe. Hereof cometh it that one beinge asked the question what was the chiefest thinge in an orator, answered pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation: what was the next and the third: the same. Shewes and plaies, that thei delite the hearers and behol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders so greatly, it is much more long of the form and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their forniture and preparance then of the matter plaied or shewed. In like maner in the verye thinges and workes, the forme, the fashion, figure, maner, aswel of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as of Art, finally a certain preparation is more mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and commended then the matter. Likewise in physsk, the conninge to prepare thinges aright, and the descression to minister them aptly, haue the greatest moment and skil moste. Nether is it of greater force what thou ministrest, then in what maner. And althoughe there be manye cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumstances
<pb facs="7"/>
to be considered, that thou maist exhibit the medicin aright, yet the maner, and the preparing is with in the medicine, and is at it were the form therof and part the other circumstaunces are withoute it, as time, place, and such things as are to be considred about the sickman. But letting pas other waies of dressing and preparing at this presēt, we wil onli touch those, bi the which al the ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue and faculti or operation is separated from the substāce of the medicins, so that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> more liquid and moyst, the more pure and subtil part of euery remedy or medicin, maye be bad seuered and drawn out from the grose and erthy part: whether it be gathered into a liquor drawn out of the sam remedy or medicin or into an other certaine ertarnall. &amp;c. which the barbarous wryter <hi>Arnold</hi> calleth <hi>Eruirtuare</hi> to <hi>outuerteuat,</hi> or <hi>Excorporare,</hi> to outcorporate. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, if sumthings shal seme to be written somwhat curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously or double diligently, ye must consider that suthe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain not to the Physicions of the common people and pore fooke, but to such as abound more with riches and ease, &amp; haue plenty of seruants, or such as remain in Prynces or Kings courts: or also to Philosophers, that busilye searche out the meruelous mutacion and vertues of natural thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and in them delite them selues. To conclude, let no man maruel that so great and longe commendacions and praises are added to certain medicines, as vnto the <hi>Quint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>essences</hi> as they call them, to <hi>Aqua vities,</hi> &amp; made ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mes, and that vnto some meruelous vertues are attributed, as to sharpen the wit and memory, to cōserue the senses and youth. &amp;c. When as euen by the auncient Grekes &amp; Latins also we read such effects and operacions to be ascribed to Triacle and other preseruatiues and compositions, speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by the Arabians vnto diuers things, yea euen of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> also vnto Triacle. Ther be som that I wil not auow, and whose credit I leaue to the authors, whose names I
<pb facs="8"/>
write euery where. But it is said before alreadye, that we wryt all these thinges for the learned and discreate men, which for the most part shall iudge more easily how much credit is to be geuen to euery thinge. Althoughe in verye many it is not sufficient to be furnished with lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and iudgement, excepte experience and practise be ioyned also therwith. But I make an end heare of my Preface.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>