<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AND to the intent that the world may know, how much these mercenary men of ours tooke vpon them, by propoun∣ding and procuring to sell our Libertie, and Treasury to Princes and forraine States: we haue set downe word by word, the Articles of the League betweene his Maiesty of Spaine, and our Countries, to which League they per∣swaded our Commons in the yeere 1617.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103461_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02254</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12390</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103461</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AND to the intent that the world may know, how much these mercenary men of ours tooke vpon them, by propoun∣ding and procuring to sell our Libertie, and Treasury to Princes and forraine States: we haue set downe word by word, the Articles of the League betweene his Maiesty of Spaine, and our Countries, to which League they per∣swaded our Commons in the yeere 1617.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The proceedings of the Grisons, in the yeere 1618 : VVherein are truely and cleerely laid open the lawfull and vrgent causes of calling an assembly of the commons: and of their due proceeding and honourable prosecution of iustice, which they were enforced to vse against some false and perfidious patriots, in a full congregation, and with absolute power met together at Tosana. Imprinted and published by commandement of the lords the heads, the counsailours and commons of the three confederations of the renowned free states of the Grisons: in maintenance of the truth, and romoouing all manner of calumniation</title>
                 <author>Graub D.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="articles">
   <pb facs="43"/>
   <head>AND to the intent that the world may know, how much these mercenary men of ours tooke vpon them, by propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and procuring to sell our Libertie, and Treasury to Princes and forraine States: we haue set downe word by word, the Articles of the League betweene his Maiesty of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and our Countries, to which League they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded our Commons in the yeere <hi>1617.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>Articles drawne and to bee agreed vpon</hi> the <hi>9.</hi> of March <hi>1617.</hi> by the most Illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Don Alfonso Casale,</hi> Councellor and Embassadour for the Catholique Maiestie in <hi>Switzerland;</hi> in the name and behalfe of the most Illustrious Prince <hi>Don Pietro di Toledo,</hi> Gouernour of the State of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> on the one party: and the Lords the Heads and Deputies of the Three high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federations Generall of <hi>Grisons</hi> on th other partie: with the good liking and approbation of his Maiestie, and of the said Three Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations Generall.</p>
   <p>WHereas there hath euer beene a good, sincere, and faithfull amitie, neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
<pb facs="43"/>
and correspondencie betweene the Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi> and the Three Consederations Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall; the which, euer since the High and Mighty Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> hau<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> beene Lords of that State, hath beene continued by their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties: therefore both the parties, vpon dye consideration of the happinesse, profit and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, which ariseth from the good affection, sinceritie, and louing intelligence betweene them; and to the intent that all cause of iealousie and diffidence might bee remooued, which hath or might heretofore happen betweene the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie of <hi>Philip</hi> the third, and the said Three Confederations Generall; and that a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good intelligence, faithfull neighbourhood, and a reall and mutuall vnion might be esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished betweene them: they haue to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory of GOD, and to the publique good and safety, ioyntly resolued to conclude this present Capitulation, Treatie, and Vnion, to stand in the full force and vertue of a continuall and hereditary League.</p>
   <p>And therefore the most Illustrious Prince and Lord, <hi>Don Pietro di Toledo</hi> Generall of <hi>Millan,</hi> in the name and behalfe of his Maiestie, and his successors Dukes of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi>
      <pb facs="44"/>
on th' one party, and the High and Noble Lords the Presidents, Councellors, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalties of the Three Confederations Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall on the other partie, doe promise, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene his Maiestie as Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Subiects of the said Duchy, and the Three Confederations Generall, with all their Subiects in <hi>Valtelina, Bombio,</hi> and the County of <hi>Chiauenna,</hi> shall be a true, sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and perpetuall amitie, correspondencie, neighbourhood, and vnion; so at neither par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie shall suffer themselues to be imployed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any seruice or occasion, to the preiudice and hurt of the other; nor shall suffer that through their Countreys or their Subiects, any pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, counsaile, or aide shall bee giuen directly or indirectly, which may secretly or openly damnifie either party, but that they shall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose and resist them with all possible diligence and power. And when either of the parties shall know or vnderstand any secret practice or attempt, whereby may bee engaged the preiudice and hurt of the other; that then they shall without delay giue notice thereof, and procure with all diligence and faithfulnesse to diuert the same.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="44"/>
And because his Excellencie vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that the Three Confederations Generall would willingly that the Fort built in the yeere <hi>1603.</hi> vpon the Confines of <hi>Valtelina</hi> were demolished, as a pawne and pledge that they were againe restored into the good fauour and assured confidence of his Maiestie; hee promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, in testimonie of his Maiesties good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the Three Confederations Generall, That, so soone as this said Capitulation shall be concluded, sworne, and signed by both the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, forthwith the Fort and Sconce belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to it, shall effectually and really be demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished: and that the said Fort shall neuer be re-built, so long as the Contents of this Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation be faithfully and inuiolably kept, and no second cause bee giuen his Maiestie of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and doubt of them, as was in the yeere <hi>1603.</hi> And forasmuch as the said Lords Presidents, Councellors, and Comminalties of the Three Confederations Generall, doe know that the reason of that diffidence and doubt, which caused the building of the Fort was, in regard of the League and passage granted to the State of <hi>Venice</hi> the yeere before; they therefore promise for themselues and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors,
<pb facs="45"/>
neuer to renew the said League or pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, nor to giue their consent thereunto, so long as this Capitulation shall continue.</p>
   <p>That commerce, negotiation, and passage shall bee free through both their Countries, and for all their Subiects without exception of persons, of what qualitie and condition so euer: but with this prouiso, that in their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of credence there be no scandall, nor bring in with them prohibited bookes, and that in time of Pestilence or Plague, the ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes be obserued. And concerning the Toll of Cattle or other commodities, which shall be brought into the State of <hi>Millan,</hi> they shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the like liberties with those already gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to such Swisse Cantons as are confederate with his Maiestie.</p>
   <p>And in case it so happen that his Maiestie shall haue neede of the Souldiers of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to defend his Duchy of <hi>Millan,</hi> he shall haue a Leauy granted him by the Three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federations Generall, of foure thousand men at the most, and two thousand at the least, (but all to be voluntaries;) reseruing notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing a power in the Three Confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Generall, to grant a greater number at
<pb facs="45"/>
their pleasure: The choise of the Collonell and Captaines to bee made by his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Embassadour: who hauing made the said Leauie, hee shall agree with the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell and Captaines chosen, for their Armes and Pay.</p>
   <p>And in case his Maiestie would cause to passe into his Duchie of <hi>Millan,</hi> through the Countrey of the Three Confederations Generall, or of their Subiects, any number of forraine Souldiours, for the preseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and defence of his Duchy or other his States, free passage shall bee granted to his Captaines and Officers, so as their Troopes consist of no more then two hundred men, and that they bee alwaies distant one dayes iourney the one from the other. Euery Troope also shall haue his Captaine or Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and also one Commissary appointed by the Three Confederations Generall, at the charge of his Maiestie, to see that good order and discipline be kept, for the auoiding of all inconueniences; which Souldiours shall pay for their victuals, and other customes, and shall beare themselues quietly &amp; peaceably through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Countrey.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="46"/>
They shall beare no other Armes but Sword and Dagger, if they bee on foote; and they on horsebacke, nothing but their Pistols: and in case it shall appeare by proofe, that these Souldiours haue damnisied the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of the Three Confederations Generall, that then his Maiestie shall be bound to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution.</p>
   <p>On th' other side, if it should so happen that the Three Confederations Generall were set vpon in hostile manner by any Prince, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate, or free State, that then his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie shall be bound vpon euery their demand, to send to their succours two thousand foot, and two hundred horse, vpon his owne expence till the warre bee ended: and in case the Three Confederations Generall should stand in neede of greater succours, his Maiestie shall be bound to send them forthwith: But if the Three Confederations Generall shall finde it more for their aduantage, or like it better to have money then Souldiours; that then his Maiestie shall truely pay them ten thousand Crownes a moneth so long as their warre last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and shall lend them sixe Peeces of Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie and Munition thereunto belonging, as
<pb facs="46"/>
farre as the vttermost bounds of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Chiauenna,</hi> with condition that the warre being done, the Artillerie bee restored. It shall bee lawfull for the Three Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Generall and their Subiects, to buy at the Faire of <hi>Como</hi> and <hi>Palanza</hi> in the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of <hi>Millan,</hi> all sorts of Graine for euery mans vse and necessitie, with like freedome as those Swisse-Cantons doe, which are in League with his Maiestie.</p>
   <p>His Maiestie as Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his wonted Princely Liberalitie, and to testifie his gracious fauour to the Three Confederations Generall, promiseth to pay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Exchequer of each Confederation Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall yeerely, vpon <hi>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Iohn Baptists</hi> day, three thousand Florens, worth three shillings nine pence Sterling a-piece: This paiment to beginne the first <hi>Saint Iohn Baptists</hi> day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Sealing and Swearing of this Vnion.</p>
   <p>And when any difference or dispute shall <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>se betweene his Maiestie and the Three Confederations Generall, two Arbiters shall be chosen of either party, who shall meet at <hi>Chiauenna</hi> or <hi>Lorico,</hi> as the one or other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> shall be Plaintiffe or Defendant; and these
<pb facs="47"/>
differences betweene them in two moneths to bee cleerely determined and decided. And in case any difference arise betweene priuate persons of both the States, that then the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe shall call the Defendant before his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate and Iudge: but in case they cannot here be agreed, and their difference compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that then each of the Parties shall haue choise of one able man well experienced in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of Iustice, out of the Aduersaries Countrey: and then to cast Lots which of these two shal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the difference.</p>
   <p>That this present Capitulation shall bee no way preiudiciall to the League and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-*Riuersall, made and giuen by the Three Confederations Generall with the Crowne of France: but that, that League and Letter shall still remaine in their force, and their owne proper words.</p>
   <p>That this present Capitulation shall bee perpetuall and hereditarie; his Maiestie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing on his part the holy Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Sacred Romane Empire, the High and Mighty House of <hi>Austria,</hi> his League with the Catholique-Cantons of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and all other his ancient Leagues and Treaties. And
<pb facs="47"/>
on the other part, the Three Confederations Generall reseruing the Sacred Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, their League and Letter-*Riuersall with the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> their perpetuall Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the High and Mighty House of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stria,</hi> their Confederation with the Cantons of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and all other their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Leagues which haue beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly inuiolably and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally kept and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>