<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL SIR IOHN Brograue Knight, his Maiesties Atturney generall of the Du∣chy of Lancaster.</title>
           <author>Ockould, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103905_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02841</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12981</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103905</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL SIR IOHN Brograue Knight, his Maiesties Atturney generall of the Du∣chy of Lancaster.</title>
                 <author>Ockould, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The times, places, and persons of the holie Scripture. Otherwise entituled, The generall vievv of the Holy Scriptures</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Ockould, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 141, that is 241, 7 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL SIR <hi>IOHN Brograue</hi> Knight, his Maiesties Atturney generall of the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of Lancaster.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worshipfull, the written copie of this booke comming to my hands, was thought worthy the presse by men of good iudgement and learning, for that it might bee profitable to many, aswell those that intend the studie and profession of Diuinitie, as to all other good Christians. The Author of the booke is vncertaine to me: but his worke manifesteth, that he was learned, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious: which mooued me (though with no small charge) to impart the same to all, and to make it publike. And for that the same wanteth the Authors name, I thought fit it should not want a Patron: neither knew I any other more worthy, to whom I might recommend the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage thereof, than your worship, in regard of that seruice, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I stand bound to your selfe, and that most worthy societie of Greyes Inne. It may please you therefore to accept the same in good part. And I shall euer remaine yours to be commanded.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Richard Ockould.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>