<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The abundaunte grace of the holie ghost maye dayly prouoke, tempt and stere vp the heart of oure mooste noble and vertuous King EDVVARDE the .VI. king of England, Fraunce and Irelande. Defendour of the Faith, and in earth the supreme heade of the Churches of England and Ireland: earnestly to promote the Gospell of Christ, to the mayntenaunce of true religion and vertue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103091_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01657</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11797</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103091</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The abundaunte grace of the holie ghost maye dayly prouoke, tempt and stere vp the heart of oure mooste noble and vertuous King EDVVARDE the .VI. king of England, Fraunce and Irelande. Defendour of the Faith, and in earth the supreme heade of the Churches of England and Ireland: earnestly to promote the Gospell of Christ, to the mayntenaunce of true religion and vertue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godly inuectiue in the defence of the Gospell : against such as murmure and woorke what thei can that the Bible shoulde not haue free passage, veray necessary to be red of euery faythfull Christian</title>
                 <author>Gerrard, Philip</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The abundaunte grace of the holie ghost maye dayly prouoke, tempt and stere vp the heart of oure mooste noble and vertuous King <hi>EDVVARDE</hi> the <hi>.VI.</hi> king of England, Fraunce and Irelande. Defendour of the Faith, and in earth the supreme heade of the Churches of England and Ireland: earnestly to promote the Gospell of Christ, to the mayntenaunce of true religion and vertue.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN</hi> I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered and wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed often with my selfe that the lest part of amitee faithfull loue and duety, which eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man oweth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde his natiue countrey. (My mooste gracious and drad soueraigne lord) is not shewed in the gentle admonyshyng his coūtrey menne of suche faultes, perilles, and daungers, whiche either bee eminent or els playnly apparant: yea, and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to attempte this thing when
<pb facs="3"/> he seeth that there is geuē some great and plentifull occasion. Euen now therfore I thought it good to set furth this Inuectiue in the defence of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des holy woord, against all coūterfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Christians wilfully minded, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che stubburnely resiste the promoting of Chrystes blessed Testament.</p>
   <p>I truste wel therfore that your high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes especially, and all your nobilitee, with other your true and faythefull subiectes, that haue earnest heartes to promote Goddes glory, and to seeke for his heauēly kyngdome, wil take in good part this my enterprice. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in although ther want fine handling, liuelye colours, the conueighance of Rhethoricke, and also quicknesse of Witte: yet for al that, there hath wan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted no iote of good will, for though I may most iustly confesse, I geue place vnto all men in good learnyng, yet I maye truely say, I am inferiour vnto fewe in good affection towardes the same. Therfore after this my rude and base stile of Inueiynge, I haue here set forth the minde and pleasure of <hi>GOD,</hi> thynges veray commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouse and fruitefull for the weale of this noble realme, profitable to auoide
<pb facs="3"/> contencion and to sette amongest vs a louely societie of liuyng. Nowe in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as I entreate of causes so neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary (most noble &amp; victoriouse Kyng) I conceiue no smal hope, that no man if godly exhortaciō may haue place in his heart, will refuse accordingly to note &amp; print the same most firmely in mind: especially such as the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet speaketh against, they haue eies and cannot see, they haue eares and heare not, for they shall well and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>silye perceaue that stubburnnesse of mind, hardnes of heart, the contempt of Goddes holy woord, the forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the great benefites and Godly goodnesse of <hi>GOD,</hi> to bee thynges most greuously condempned in holye Scripture. Again those that be alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ady bent and kendeled in affection to attayne the knowledge and due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience that apperteine to Christes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wyll and Testament, shal perceiue manifestly theim selfes to knowe the summe and effecte of their creacion. Wherof we shuld al be fully taught, and often admonished also that we ar not borne to spend our time in pastime and vanities of this miserable world: but to be busied in al seriouse &amp; God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="4"/> matters, chefely desiryng to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed in Goddes holy religion, to liue innocently, yea and to excell in al kynd of vertues. For who so desireth not to liue well (as Diogenes wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) liueth vainly. That is to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a vaine life, whē men rather shew them selfes beastes mortal, then men Immortal, regardyng altogether the bodye that vile and beastely parte of man. But nowe (the pamperyng of it laied apart) yf we would considre the great and exuberant glory of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite or solle of man: if we wold weigh what strength power and vertue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in the minde, wee woulde bee sone perswaded to folow Godly thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges and flee the wicked. But more it is pitie, suche is the miserable misery of the world in these daies, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the saiyng of the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete: Woe is me, al is ful of sinners, whiche offend of purpose and malice. Esaie the .xxiiii. These wilfull offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders (my soueraigne Lorde) bee suche as maliciously spurne agaynst the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely woorde of <hi>GOD,</hi> and enuy at your graces pore subiectes enbracing and readyng the same: vsynge subtyll and wicked perswasions to discorage
<pb facs="4"/> men from the readyng therof, whiche thing forsoth both requireth correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and spedye confutacion for the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryshmente of the younge and tendre knowledge that <hi>GOD</hi> hath sente a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongest vs. Vndoubtedly the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouse and cankered stomackes are so playne and plentiful in diuers places against the word of God, that no tong can be still, ne yet heart permit with a dissemblyng countenance to winke at the great ignorance &amp; subtile cōueigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, especially of suche as haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken on theym to bee the lyghte of the worlde and guides ouer the simple to conducte theym to the true woorde of <hi>GOD.</hi> This thynge is soo euydent, that euery honeste hearte woulde so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe to see it, and take peine to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it, and wee oughte to bee earnest in this. For who so regardeth the wyl of <hi>GOD,</hi> wyl openly defend the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the of his Gospel, and labour al that he can to winne mennes heartes to it. Yea, and to attempte this thyng, the vertue of Goddes word geueth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull strengthe and boldenes.</p>
   <p>Euen nowe in consideracion of this. I as one hyghly reioysyng to see the glorie of <hi>GOD</hi> so liuely set furthe
<pb facs="5"/> emongest vs, but sorowyng agayne in my hearte to beholde the supersticy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouse and ignoraunt sorte so lyttell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, thoughte it full time to sette forthe this Inuectiue, trustynge that after the readyng of it, suche as haue wytte, reason and iudgemente, wyll remembre them selfes, aryse and most reuerently mete the truth face to face, and be no longer disceiued with coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfaited, coulered, and cloked thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but from hens forthe ioyeouslye take in their handes the holy Bible, and esteme it as the moste diuine and Godly thyng that euer came amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest vs: yea and laboure with hande and foote vsyng sobre &amp; catholicke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortacions to allure mē vnto it. This shoulde be a meane to sette for euer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongest vs a publique quietnes, true loue, sure and faithfull frendshyppe. By this meane forsoth we shoulde ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshe Ypocrisie and ignoraunce, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che bee euer brawlyng and stande in contencion for euery colde Ceremonie and tryfelyng tradicion. For trewely where Ignoraunce, Disdayne, the contempte of Goddes woorde gooe at their libertie, there must nedes aryse contencion, brawlyng, sedicion, and
<pb facs="5"/> controuersie in Opinions. Yea where an obediente and humble heart wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth toward the truthe, there for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lyght occasion, thus men contend. Thou art an Hereticke saith one, thou arte a Papist saieth an other, by this forsoth the worde of <hi>GOD</hi> is sore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domaged, by this meane Godlye and brotherlye exhortacion is put out of place, yea by this meane Sathan wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth his wyll and pleasure and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneth mennes heartes towarde the shining light to their owne condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion and vtter confusiō. Now ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (my deere soueraigne) who wold not lament? and for veray pitie tendre the poore simple people readye to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish or rather thus perishing for lacke of true erudicion, and broughte into such amased dulnes through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarietie of preachers, that thei know not well whom to truste. It is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore necessary to set trouthe forward, and to exhorte all men to cleaue faste vnto the worde of <hi>GOD,</hi> yea, and to admonishe theym not to contende for small tryfles and lyghte occasions: but to vse sobre and familier commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicacion in matters of oure religion, for yf they pondre well howe GOD
<pb facs="6"/> abhorreth contencion and discord, thei wyl bee sore ashamed to enter into it.</p>
   <p>And that it soo long contineweth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongest vs, (most prestant prince) ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny are much to bee reproued, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly suche as be profound in eloquence, expert in tonges and great in science, for they shine and shewe gloriouse to the world and dooe nothyng, but bear lumpyshe heartes toward the truthe.</p>
   <p>They might compas thinges to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyde all contencion, and fynd meane to frame vs al to bee of one mynde in the woorde of God. And in thus doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng they shoulde appease the Ire of GOD, and worke moost strongely in the defence of this noble realme. For this cannot be denied, that weale pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique is made sure and perpetuall, where the worde of GOD is thanck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully receaued, and the Kyng faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obeyed of his louyng subiectes. This thing cannot come to passe (most redoubted Kyng) tyll there bee a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint against such as vse outragious wordes against the readers of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor till the heartes of your graces subiectes be made more agreable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the truth, no nor til the Cleargie be brought also in such loue and acquain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance
<pb facs="6"/> with the holy Bible, that they wil shew them selfes as ready to sow as they be nowe to reape, and forgeat to trust so muche as thei do to the sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of their prosperitie and worldly dignitie: remēbryng this that they ar not to be estemed as hed rulers of the worlde, but as ministers apoynted to dispose those thīges that thei ar char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged withall, not the offices of menne but of GOD. This office wherwith they are so streightely charged is to feede the people with the woorde of God, wherfore (most gracious King) now to conclude. Although I am not so able as willyng to put men in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of their dueties in these thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and to refourme their folysh and wicked contencion, yet I trust youre grace will so gently considre my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that this rude Inuectiue maye fynd fauoure in your graces syght to gooe forth, to the encouragemēt of al youre graces louyng subiectes vnto the woord of GOD. Vnto whō most humbly with heart &amp; minde we ought to pray, both that your highnes maye spedely folowe vertuouse kynge Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sua, whiche mooste gently exhorted his people, willyng them to be excea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng
<pb facs="7"/> diligente to take beede vnto all thynges that were written in the law of the LORD, makyng also heartie request vnto them to cleaue faste vnto the Lord their GOD, and also that all the nobles and commons of this your realme may answere your grace again, (as the people did Iosua) God forbid but that wee shoulde serue the Lorde our GOD. The Lord will we serue and his voice wyl we obey, that is the holy Bible and Christes blessed Testament. Yf God geue them grace thus to dooe, then this your graces no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble realme shal alwaies be most strōg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warded and defended, &amp; the Lord (accordyng to his promise) shall geue your highnesse prosperous successe in al youre affaires, whose mercifull hande may alwaies defend your noble estate.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties faithful and humble seruaunt Philippe Gerrard yeoman of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre vnto your grace.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>