<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Letter To Author]</title>
           <author>W., N.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103128_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01764</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11900</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103128</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Letter To Author]</title>
                 <author>W., N.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvorthy tract of Paulus Iouius, contayning a discourse of rare inuentions, both militarie and amorous called imprese : VVhereunto is added a preface contayning the arte of composing them, with many other notable deuises. By Samuell Daniell late student in Oxenforde</title>
                 <author>Giovio, Paolo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Robinson, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter_to_author">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>TO HIS GOOD FREND SAMVEL DANIEL, N. W. Wisheth health.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>I Knowe not whether to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse your nature (good M. DANIEL) or blame your shamefastnesse, which so much laboreth (as the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enemy of your good name) to defraude your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors of their deserued Lawrell, &amp; in despight of arte to depriue vs of so delicate inuētions, which the best wits in <hi>Europe</hi> haue dedicated to posteritie: wherein surely, you iniurie your countreymen publikely, vnnaturally your frends, and vnaduisedly your selfe. But what can you pretend? The seueritie of Censors, the nice delicatenes of Courtiers, or the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetie of Philosophers? What Philosophy taught you that? That which is currant may abyde the touch, the yong <hi>AEglets</hi> dare looke vpon the Sunne, and that which is eloquent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly polished may abyde the presse. Why then may not your <hi>Iouius</hi> looke any man in the face, hauing arte to direct him, authoritie to defend him, all humanitie to pleade for him. If you misdoubt his grace in the Vniuersitie,
<pb facs="4"/>
the Muses will giue him their voyces, if the suffrages of the holy virgins in the Courte, they are <hi>Graces</hi> themselues. If onely the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude <hi>Odi profanum vulgus &amp; arceo.</hi> For I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose you remember the olde prouerbs: that it is great trouble to make a Couche for a dogge, for that turning himselfe so variably, no man knoweth where to place the Pillowe: and so mutable and vnconstant is the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that it is not for a wise man to indeuour to feeede their humour or fit their fancies. Yet doe not thinke that euery prudent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is like to wanton Mistresse <hi>AEmilia,</hi> who would ordinarily flout the first line she read: or to curious <hi>Gonzaga,</hi> surnamed the Carper, who no sooner heard a pretie inuention, but would recompence it with his gentell girkes: Or to <hi>Theodorus</hi> scollers, which receiued eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing with their left hand, which their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster gaue with the right, or to the <hi>Hidropicus,</hi> who hauing no iudgement of tastes, yet neuer liketh any sawce, and cōdemneth all Cookes. Therefore I would wish you as your frende, neuer to sinotther so sweete inuentions, for feare of Censors, who in words perhaps will debase it, which in deede they conceiue not, and controll that they cannot amende, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther following the counsell of the wise, nor the example of the vertuous.</p>
   <p>There is another point in your last letter, wherein you seeme to marre al that you haue
<pb facs="4"/>
made, and dash that which so cunningly was deuised. For sooth you blush to open another mans shop, and sell <hi>Italian</hi> wares as though you were a Bankerupt in philosophie, and could not afforde any pritie conceipt without borowing or embeselling. I pray you Syr, shal <hi>Castilio</hi> be more reuerenced for his courtier, then <hi>D. Clarke</hi> admired for inuesting him with so courtlie robes? shall <hi>Menander</hi> be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternized for his <hi>Comedies,</hi> and <hi>Terence</hi> forgot who gaue them credit: Shall <hi>Lambin, Cardan,</hi> and <hi>Scaliger,</hi> and the most excellent Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of nature, <hi>Plinie, Matthiolus</hi> &amp; <hi>Tolet,</hi> shall they be lesse reueréced, for perfecting know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, thē the old Philosophers for a shadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inuention? shal the witte and capacitie of antiquitie sit in her throne, and disposition &amp; iudgement of posteritie keepe the dore: no reason, the one deuised, the other disposed. <hi>Iouius</hi> therefore is bound vnto you, both for absoluting and blazing his inuetions abroad in this famous Iland, and wee are beholding vnto you for reuealing them to vs: wherein truely both arte in translating, &amp; knowledge in iudging, iustly may chalēge their fees. You cannot forget that which <hi>Nolanus</hi> (that man of infinite titles among other phantasticall toyes) rruely noted by chaunce in our Schoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, that by the helpe of translations, al Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces had their ofspring, and in my iudgement it is true. The <hi>Hebrewes</hi> hatched knowledge.
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>Greece</hi> did nourish it, <hi>Italie</hi> clothed and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified it, &amp; the artes which were left as wards in their minoritie to the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> by Translators as most carefull Gardiners, are now deduced to perfect age and ripenesse. Cōcerning the nakednes of your stile (which troubleth you without the colours or florish of <hi>Rhetorique) Tullie</hi> commendeth it, al Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slators approue it: and no man maketh so much accōpt of the glossoas of the substance: of the gay suie bush as of the wine: Neither could it preiudice you at all (if it were naked as in deede it is pure) because you haue not done it as the <hi>Sybaritae,</hi> that bad their guestes a whole yere before the feast, to make some expectation of a sumptuous banket. A toye would require all brauerie: Vanitie all orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and an Asse had neede of all his trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings. But your argument is such as can both moue and delight, tickle the eare and satisfie the minde. And our time also hath learned to lothe that od riming vaine, and to persecute the letter is cleane out of fashion, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon by a bad portraiture of wit, and is ended by a ripe direction of iudgement. But why doe I rather aunswere the capcious, then sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the graue and modest, who at the first vewe (I dare presume vpon their wisedome) will subscribe to the supremacie of the wit of your newe Science. For if Courtiers are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly rauished in vewing the Picture of <hi>Fia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metta</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
which <hi>Boccacc</hi> limned. If Ladies enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Bandel</hi> or <hi>Ariosto</hi> in their Closets. If Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers imbrace their Phisition <hi>Ouid</hi> in extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of their passion: then will Gentlemen of all tribes, much rather honor your <hi>Impresa,</hi> as a most rare Iewell, and delicate <hi>Enchiridion.</hi> For there is not published a florish vpon fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, or <hi>Tarletons</hi> toyes, or the sillie Enterlude of <hi>Diogenes:</hi> You prosesse not <hi>Artem iocandi</hi> or <hi>Potādi:</hi> You discourse not of <hi>Apuleius</hi> Asse: You trifle not as <hi>Cornelius</hi> the <hi>Brabantine,</hi> who <note place="margin">Anno. 158.</note> published an <hi>Encomion</hi> of <hi>Tuftmockados:</hi> But you present vs an order to frame <hi>Deuises,</hi> in shew glorious, in forme plain, in title straūge; the which is so much the more to bee estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, being deriued frō the most pure springs <hi>Lucas Contile,</hi> and <hi>Rusoelli,</hi> whom I cannot name without some Preface to their commō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. What should I recount <hi>Dominicus</hi> and <hi>Alciat,</hi> with whom you seeme to haue beene very familiarly acquainted, which addeth much credite to your woorke, and notably hath giuen light to your studies. But concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the arte of <hi>Imprese,</hi> I neede not draw the petigree of it, sith it is knowne that it descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the auncient <hi>Algiptians,</hi> and <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dcans,</hi> in the Schoole of <hi>Memphis:</hi> who deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed meanes before Charecters were founde out, to vtter their conceiptes by formes of Beastes, Starres, Hearbes, (as you haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) and these notes were called <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>.i. sacrae notae.</hi> This Philosophie was increased by <hi>Orus Niliacus,</hi> and <hi>Pythagoras:</hi> &amp; was more plainely reuealed by <hi>Clcmeus, Pausanias, Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus:</hi> &amp; in this last age reuiued by <hi>Pierius Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerian.</hi> But to what end serued this? to shadow suerly their purposes and intents by figures. So counsayled <hi>Plaeto:</hi> So practised the first pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of Philosophie. As by the picture of a Stork they signified <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. By a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> pollicie. By an Oliue peace. By a Gote lust: drawing these Charecters frō the world, as from a volume wherein was written the wonders of nature. Thus was the first foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations layd of <hi>Imprese:</hi> From hence were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued by succession of pregnant wittes <hi>Stem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata</hi> Coates of Armes, <hi>Insignia</hi> Ensignes, and the olde Images which the <hi>Romaines</hi> vsed as witnesses of their Auncestors, <hi>Emblemes</hi> and <hi>Deuises.</hi> Then what was the intēt of these En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes and <hi>Deuises?</hi> What cause can bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for them? What did they import? <hi>Iam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicus</hi> saieth that they were conceiptes, by an externall forme representing an inward pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose: So <hi>Fergusus</hi> the first Scottishe King did beare in his Standard a <hi>Lion geules,</hi> to bewray his courage testifie his stomacke, and dismaie his aduersarie, which being well marshalled, is borne for the atchiuement of the Kinges euer since. So did the <hi>Athenians</hi> beare their Owle: the <hi>Thebans</hi> their <hi>Sphinx:</hi> the <hi>Switzers</hi> their Beare. But among all inuentions, sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe
<pb facs="6"/>
for witt &amp; art your <hi>Imprese:</hi> neither lesse renowmed then the <hi>Insegnes,</hi> nor lesse heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call then the Armes called by <hi>Paradin Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bola Heroica,</hi> by <hi>Simeon deuises illustra. Minoes</hi> a man otherwise excellently qualified in all humanitie, semeth neither perfectly to define <hi>Impreses,</hi> nor artificially to distinguishe them from <hi>Emblemes.</hi> The sole worde <hi>Symbolum</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery way is to large and generall a terme for them, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, that note by which we know or cā cōiecture any thing, is <hi>Symbolum.</hi> Now in this scope and generallitie, how is it restrayned, how doth he measure and fit that word for <hi>Imprese? Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitur hic Symbolum pro argumento seu nota qua quod piam occultatur, sed doctis auribus intelligē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum proponit ur.</hi> There is great ods (my good freend) betwixt this adumbration and your substantial definition. If we respect the forme it is lame, and why so? because there is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per difference to supporte it. And this is an infallible grounde: for seeing it comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all the former, <hi>Standards, Liurees &amp; Armes,</hi> it is rather an vniuersall note then a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <hi>Idea:</hi> if we regarde the circumstaunces, it is very superficiall: if the final ende, confused. Now to come to the difference of <hi>Emblemes,</hi> and <hi>Impreses,</hi> what subtilitie doth he shewe in it? <hi>Symbolum est genus, Emblema species:</hi> This motion is to vniuersall, rather tending to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the <hi>genus</hi> then to define the <hi>species:</hi> but
<pb facs="7"/>
the difference must bee borowed, from the properties: and because this is a case worthie to be demurred, let vs consult more curious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with our artistes, let vs conferre with our professor, what distinction maketh <hi>Iouius?</hi> I must excuse him as <hi>Traian</hi> did a certain Poet, <hi>Plus est in arte quam in artifice.</hi> For as <hi>Minoes</hi> iudgeth of him, <hi>Artem hanc incheauit potius quam persicit.</hi> But in deed these two conceipts are allied by so greate affinitie, their intents and pictures so vniforme, and cōsonant: that without sharpe insight wee cannot discypher their difference. <hi>Emblema</hi> is deriued of <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>interponere, inserere: quicquid interseri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ornatus gratia,</hi> whether the inuention bee embrodered in garmentes grauen in stone, enchased in golde, wrought in Arras: and in my opinion there is great <hi>imparitie</hi> betweene them, both in body and soule. They are disse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by sondrie Cognisances, established by reason and confirmed by reading, and may bee authorised, by experience. The mot of an <hi>Impresa</hi> may not exceede three wordes. <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems</hi> are interpreted by many verses. An <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presa</hi> is not garnished with many different I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, <hi>Emblemes</hi> are not limited. In <hi>Deuises</hi> it is enacted that the figure without the mot or the mot without the figure should not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete the Authors meaning. In <hi>Emblems</hi> is more libertie and fewer lawes. <hi>Impreses</hi> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest the special purpose of Gentlemen in war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb facs="7"/>
combats or chamber tornaments. <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems</hi> are generall conceiptes rather of moral matters then perticulare deliberations: ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to giue credit to the wit, then to reueale the secretes of the minde. What should I say more. This <hi>Impresa</hi> is that perfect <hi>Symbolum:</hi> for antiquitie to bee reuerenced: for worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse admired: for pleasure embraced. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me (I pray you) if I rainge a little &amp; chase a discourse in this so wide a Forrest: let me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde some monument of the olde Registers of <hi>Greece.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Agamemnon</hi> Soueraigne at the seige of <hi>Troy,</hi> bare in his sheild a <hi>Lion</hi> saliant, with this mot <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phitruo</hi> being encamped against the <hi>Thebans,</hi> caused to be portrayed vpon his <hi>Target. Cum quadrigis sol exoriens,</hi> and breathed life into that body by this soule, <hi>In ardualaurus. Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temesia</hi> to testifie her selfe a loyal wife to her Lorde and King wore in her Tablet an <hi>Elio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropium,</hi> rising and falling with the Sunne, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this mot, <hi>Persoluet vota pictas,</hi> which was verified, for she enterred the ashes of her slain husband, in no other Tombe then in her owne body, so that death could scarse di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorse them. But let vs come nigher hande. <hi>Vascus Gama</hi> being diswaded from the <hi>Indian</hi> voyage (neuer before attempted) erected a globe elumined with Starres, vpon a piller of golde, with this sentence <hi>Vndique par:</hi> respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
<pb facs="8"/>
the auncient verie. <hi>Vnaique ad superos tantundem est viae.</hi> Haue: not our Printers also of late honored this proffession? Haue they not bene at emulation for ingenious <hi>Deuises. Stephen</hi> glorieth in his tree, and moderateth those (that loue to moūt: by loftie witts) with this Posie: <hi>Noli altum sa pere. Plautin</hi> beareth <note place="margin">The tree of good and ill.</note> a compasse in a hande: stretched out of the cloudes which measureth all, <hi>Constantia &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore.</hi> I will omit <hi>Griphin's Episcopus:</hi> I will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all artificers, who commonly buy such in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions at the second hand. I will not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with Courtiers, I will passe ouer the knowen <hi>Impreses</hi> of <hi>Moore</hi> and <hi>Cromwell,</hi> a payre royall of nobles. And now I will bring you to Church. A certain English Prelate, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uised a Lambe in a thorne bush, pitifully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed, yet casting his eyes cherefully vppon the Sunne with this mot. <hi>Ne cede.</hi> Tell me how you like this <hi>Heroycall Impresa</hi> of <hi>Curtius Gonzaga.</hi> An <hi>Egle</hi> flying on high against the <note place="margin">Tune cede malis sed cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra audētius.</note> Sunne, with this word <hi>pur che,</hi> a parte of that verse of <hi>Petrarche. Pur che ne godan gli orchi, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan le piuine.</hi> For that which delighteth my eyes burneth my fethers. A frend of mine, whom you know, M. P. climing for an <hi>Egles</hi> nest, but defeated by the <hi>mallalent</hi> of fortune, limned in his studie a <hi>Pine</hi> tree striken with lightning, carying this mot. <hi>Il mio sperar,</hi> which was borowed also from <hi>Petrarch. Allor che fulminato e morto giaacque il mio sperar che</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
he deuised also a Pinnace or small Barke, tos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with tempestious stormes, and in the saile was written <hi>expectanda dies,</hi> hoping as I think for one Sunne shine day to recompence so many glomy and winter monethes. Therfore now to conclude, seeing your argument is plausible, the arte a noueltie, your first fruites ripe what reason is there, why you should pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatly bestowe them of some one gentleman: especially cósidering that you can please him no way better, then to pleasure his countrey mé. For who doth not know M. <hi>Dimmock,</hi> to be a gentleman by famely worshipfull, by loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie vnspotted, by office the Princes Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion: so also by curtesie worthy the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle? what neede you thé to feare the mallice of the weakest enemy that may bee a carping tongue, hauing him for the Champió of your booke, whom her Maiestie hath vouchsafed the Champion of her person, or why feare you least our old <hi>Academicks</hi> improue your art for a toy, seeing that wisdome is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated to Nightcaps, neither must wee depend vpon the verdite of some conceled Philosophers.</p>
   <p>Thus am I bold to animate and encourage you to your credite, which if I haue done to long, so vppon occasion did <hi>Tullio Plato, Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca:</hi> if rudely ascribe it to simplicitie, if sleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the rarenes of your arte: if to copiously
<pb facs="9"/>
to a feruent desire: for seeing that <hi>in verbis est aliquod praemium,</hi> I had rather shewe my selfe to prodigall to my frends, then a snudge: which when you haue read, fier it. From Oxenford the xx. of Nouember.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Yours,</salute>
      <signed>N. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>