<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The dedicacion of this present woorke, vnto the right honora∣ble lorde Thomas duke of Norffolke, by thenprynter, Richard Grafton.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1543</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103772_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02638</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12766.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103772</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The dedicacion of this present woorke, vnto the right honora∣ble lorde Thomas duke of Norffolke, by thenprynter, Richard Grafton.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The chronicle of Ihon Hardyng : in metre, fro [m] the first begynnyng of Engla [n] de, vnto ye reigne of Edwarde ye fourth where he made an end of his chronicle. And from yt time is added with a co [n] tinuacion of the storie in prose to this our tyme, now first emprinted, gathered out of diuerse and sondrie autours of moste certain knowelage [et] substanciall credit, yt either in latin orels in our mother toungue haue writen of ye affaires of Englande</title>
                 <author>Hardyng, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1543</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, ccxxxviii, 1, clx leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ The dedicacion of this present woorke, vnto the right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lorde Thomas duke of Norffolke, by thenprynter, Richard Grafton.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Orde Thomas of Norffolke duke moste gracious</l>
      <l>Of noble auncestrie and blood descended</l>
      <l>A captain right woorthie and auenturous</l>
      <l>And frō Scotlād euen newely retended</l>
      <l>Wher Englandes querele ye haue reuenged</l>
      <l>In the behalf of our noble kyng Henry</l>
      <l>I wyshe you all health, honour, and victorie</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ And because it hath pleased almightie God</l>
      <l>In the right title and quercle of Englande</l>
      <l>To vse your stocke as an iron rod</l>
      <l>Wherewith to scourge the falsehood of Scotland</l>
      <l>In whom is no truthe ne holde of any bande</l>
      <l>Ihon Hardynges chronicle, as me thought was</l>
      <l>Moste mete to bee dedicated, to your grace</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ For Hardyng a true herted Englysheman</l>
      <l>An esquier valiaunt hardie and bolde</l>
      <l>And not vnlearned, as the time was than</l>
      <l>Serched out of chronicles, bothe late an olde</l>
      <l>All that euer by thesame hath bee told</l>
      <l>How frō the begynnyng, Scotlāde dooeth reigne</l>
      <l>Vnder kynges of Englande, as their soueram</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>¶ And Hardynges owne self, hath the partie bee</l>
      <l>That from Scotlande, oft tymes hath brought</l>
      <l>Their seales of homage and fealtee</l>
      <l>Vnto the kyng of Englande, as he ought</l>
      <l>Vnto whom the Scottes then sued and sought</l>
      <l>Yeldyng to liue in humble subieccion</l>
      <l>Of Englandes gouernaunce and proteccion</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ But that people of their propre nature</l>
      <l>Hath euen from the first, been so vntowarde</l>
      <l>So vnstedfast, inconstaunte and vnsure</l>
      <l>That nothyng maie possibly bee more frowarde</l>
      <l>So haue thei continued from thens foorthwarde</l>
      <l>Neuer gladde to bee in quiet and rest</l>
      <l>But to defeccion, aye readie and prest</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ Wherefore Thon Hardyng, to his lorde &amp; mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</l>
      <l>Whom in his tyme he serued without blame</l>
      <l>Edwarde, first duke of Yorke, and after</l>
      <l>Kyng of this realme, the fourthe of that name</l>
      <l>In this chronicle affermeth of thesame</l>
      <l>That thei will rebell, till by prouision</l>
      <l>The kyng of Englād shall haue made theim both</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ And in deede Englād, hath oft been cōstreigned one</l>
      <l>The Scottes slackenesse in dooyng their homage</l>
      <l>To pricke forewarde, whē thei would haue refrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</l>
      <l>With y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sharpe spurre of marciall forceage</l>
      <l>And to abate their wantonnesse of courage</l>
      <l>With the iron rodde, of due correccion</l>
      <l>As oft as thei attempted defeccion</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ For y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Scottes will aye bee bostyng &amp; crakyng</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="3"/>
Euer sekyng causes of rebellion</l>
      <l>Spoyles, booties, and preades euer takyng</l>
      <l>Euer sowyng quereles of dissension</l>
      <l>To burne and steale is all their intencion</l>
      <l>And yet as people, whom God dooeth hate &amp; curse</l>
      <l>Thei alwaies begynne, and euer haue the woorse</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ Englande hitherto hath neuer lacked power</l>
      <l>As oft as nede wer, the Scottes to compell</l>
      <l>Their duetie to dooe, and menne of honour</l>
      <l>Englande hath had, as stories dooe tell</l>
      <l>Whiche whensoeuer the Scottes did rebell</l>
      <l>Wer hable at all tymes, theim to subdue</l>
      <l>And their obedience, to England renue</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ Emōges y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whiche noumbre, your noble father</l>
      <l>In the twelfth yere of Henry the seuenths reigne</l>
      <l>By aunciente recorde, as I can gather</l>
      <l>Beeyng of suche credence as cannot feigne</l>
      <l>Yode into Scotlande their pryde to restrein</l>
      <l>With sēbleable power (as bookes dooen auowe)</l>
      <l>And like commission as your grace had now</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ That season he did so valiauntely</l>
      <l>The Scottes vanquishyng and puttyng to flight</l>
      <l>That thei ranne awaye moste shamefully</l>
      <l>Not hable of hym tabide the sight</l>
      <l>Nor hable to sustein, the brunt of his might</l>
      <l>Soondrie castelles, he raced down to the grounde</l>
      <l>Whiche to the honour of Englande did redound</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ Kyng Iamy also, makyng greate braggue and vaūte</l>
      <l>Hauyng his armie not a myle of that daie</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>
Your father as a captain valyaunt</l>
      <l>Made in a moment, for feare to runne awaye</l>
      <l>The Scottish kyng, sēding foorth heraldes tway</l>
      <l>Chalenged your father, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> many a proude woorde</l>
      <l>Battayle to wage, and trye it by the sworde.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ And choose thou sir Earle, {quod} kyng Iamy then</l>
      <l>Whether we shall fight, armie against armie</l>
      <l>Orelles I and thou, trye it manne for manne</l>
      <l>For sparyng bloodshed, of either compaignie</l>
      <l>That if it chaunce me, to haue the victorie</l>
      <l>Nought shall I demaunde, for Englandes losse &amp; thine</l>
      <l>Sauig Barwike toune, for euer to bee mine</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ Then to the heraldes, saied this noble knight</l>
      <l>Shewe to your kyng, that in this place purposely</l>
      <l>Battayle for to wage, my tentes haue I pight</l>
      <l>I am not come to flee, but to fyght sharpely</l>
      <l>As where he standeth, he maye see with his eye</l>
      <l>And fyrst where he would, bloodshed saued to bee</l>
      <l>Therof am I no lesse desirous then he.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ Secundarily, where it is his likyng</l>
      <l>That I a poore Earle, and of meane estate</l>
      <l>Maye combattre, with hym beyng a kyng</l>
      <l>That our two fightes, may ceasse all debate</l>
      <l>He dooeth me honour, after suche highe rate</l>
      <l>That I must nedes graūt, my selfe bound in this case</l>
      <l>Humble thankes to rēdre to his grace</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ Now as for the towne of Barwike, it is knowē</l>
      <l>(Which your lorde requireth in case I bee slaine)</l>
      <l>Is the kyng my souereins, and not mine owne</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>
So that graunte therof, in me dodeth not remain</l>
      <l>But thys maie ye bear worde to your lord again</l>
      <l>My person and lyfe, aduenture I shall</l>
      <l>More precyous to me, then the round worlde all.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ When kyng Iamy, by his heraldes twoo</l>
      <l>Spedefullye returnyng, had due knowlage</l>
      <l>Muche otherwyse, then he loked for thoo</l>
      <l>Of the Earles stout aunswer and message</l>
      <l>Fled out of hand, and would no battayle wage</l>
      <l>So that your father, retourned home victour</l>
      <l>With coumfort, laude, praise, ioye and honour</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ The same your father, in the fyfth yere</l>
      <l>Of our moost noble kyng Henry the eyght</l>
      <l>When hys grace and his armie at Turney were</l>
      <l>And the same kyng Iamy, of Scotland streyght</l>
      <l>Agaynst England, his banner dyspleyght</l>
      <l>Vanquished the Scottes, &amp; w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> your helpyng hād</l>
      <l>Slew there king Iamy, and brought him to Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ Agayne in the .xv. yere of the same reygne</l>
      <l>Your selfe in proper personne, full courageous</l>
      <l>Set forth against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Scottes, without dysdeygne</l>
      <l>Lyke a captayne valyaunt and venturous</l>
      <l>Wher ye brēt Iedworth, a toune right populous</l>
      <l>Wyth diuers victories, that your grace then had</l>
      <l>Whiche made all Englande, to reioyse &amp; be glad</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ The yere folowyng also, as bookes testify</l>
      <l>The Scottes came, with an houge power</l>
      <l>Of .lx. thousande men vnder the Duke of Albany</l>
      <l>Besiegyng Warke castel, thynkyng it to deuour</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>
But heryng that your grace, dyd approch y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> houe</l>
      <l>The Scottes trembled, and so dyd theyr Duke</l>
      <l>And cowardly fled, to their shame and rebuke.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>¶ Sembleably, by thys your last viage</l>
      <l>Nowe thys last October and Nouember</l>
      <l>Made into Scotlande, to their great damage</l>
      <l>It dooeth as me semeth, ryght well appere</l>
      <l>That when pleaseth our king to send you thether</l>
      <l>Your house in hys ryght, is appoynted by God</l>
      <l>To bee to the Scottes, a sharpe scourge and rod</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Wherfore thys chronycle of Ihon Hardyng</l>
      <l>I haue thought good, to dedycate to your grace</l>
      <l>Because the same in euery maner of thyng</l>
      <l>Doothe best set out the nature of that place</l>
      <l>With distaunce of tounes, and euery myles space</l>
      <l>Besechyng your grace to take in good parte</l>
      <l>Myne honest labours and beneuolent harte</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>