<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader.</title>
           <author>A., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103585_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04380</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14493</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103585</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader.</title>
                 <author>A., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The triumph of faith : A very godly, fruitfull and comfortable treatise on Rom. 8. verse 37. Penned by Daniel Ienkinson Master in Arts, late of Emmanuel Coll. in Cambridge, and found in his studie at the time of his death</title>
                 <author>Jenkinson, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Macham, Samuel 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 50 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, as it was bountifull loue to his louely <hi>Ionathan,</hi> that moued the sweet Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Israel, King <hi>Dauid,</hi> to show such kindnesse to <hi>Mephibosheth, Ionathans</hi> sonne, as to cause him to eat continually at the Kings Table, <hi>2. Sam. 9.13.</hi> so it is Christian loue to my deceased (loue worthie) Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, that hath mooued me to giue this his obscured fatherlesse Orphan, falling into my hands, the best pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment I was able, vz. to liue (as I hope) continually in the houses, and
<pb facs="3"/>
somtimes hands (and if God blesse my wish) euen in the harts of true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; as yeelding a liuely sent and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant smel of those great Graces which abounded plentifully in the godly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: and which too soone were nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the bud, and by vntimely death restrained from the vse of the Church, if it may so be sayd without offence to the highest Prouidence, vnder cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and condition of his most righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous will. If this poore Orphan In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant the legitimate issue of a childe in yeeres, but of a man for gifts, and an olde Christian, may chance to please, and grow acceptable for his fathers sake, or his owne sake, where hee may conuerse; there is some hope, that in due time (the Lord permitting) some of his Germane brothers may
<pb facs="3"/>
beare him companie, on this fashion, as good companions for all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, in this wearie pilgrimage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the celestiall Canaan, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto both this and the rest do giue true aime, if I take not my aime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse. And so hoping, that after the reading heereof, thou wilt confesse thy selfe the abundant reaper of my Loues fruit, I leaue thee in his watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full protection, who alone sanctifieth all meanes of sauing knowledge and graces vnto his children, crauing but thy prayers for my paines, and resting</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>one that desires thy true good vnfainedly <hi>I. A.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>