<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORABLE HENRY, Lord CARY, Baron of Leppington, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>G., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103932_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02893</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13038</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103932</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORABLE HENRY, Lord CARY, Baron of Leppington, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>G., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Laus pediculi: or An apologeticall speech, directed to the vvorshipfull masters and vvardens of Beggars Hall. Written in Latine by the learned Daniel Heinsius. And from thence translated into English by Iames Guitard, Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Heinsius, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 21, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORABLE HENRY, Lord CARY, Baron of <hi>Leppington,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>IS confest, that Authors should bee as proper in their Dedication, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite in their expression. Nor know J which is the greater felicity. For the latter, let but the Censurer become a Reader, and J thinke the Worke will vindicate it selfe; though the name of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Composer may be enough. The
<pb facs="3"/>
former J must defend: whether the Present be according to the Presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, honorable; the Author would make a man beleeve it so: and if it be not, yet let the plea bee heard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore condemnatory sentence. Howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, let me not be mistooke; my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication is in the abstract, the strein of wit. Let Poets (for J count this Pamphlet but poeticall prose) bee in the same degree of priviledge with Painters. Jt undervalueth not the Pencill of the herein admirable, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian Brower,</hi> that his drawghts be but revelling Beggars and drunken Bores: <hi>Stultitiam simulare loco sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia summaest.</hi> So the lively ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of naturall rudenesse, to the eye of apprehensive curiosity, may seeme the height of artificiall feat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.
<pb facs="3"/>
My Lord, you have a transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency above others from Nature and Fortune. Nor can such a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified Spirit affect but transcendent objects: among which I suppose this to be such Chymistry of conceit, as can extract a specious discourse, not from a barren but a contrary subject. This doth the Translator present to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with himselfe,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>To your Lordship in all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of service,</hi> I. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>