<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right woorshipful, Maister Henry Sadleyre Esquyer, Sonne of the right Honorable, Sir Raphe Sadleyre Knight, (one of her Maiesties, most ho∣norable priuie Counsayle, and Chauncellour of her Duchy of Lancastre:) And also to Mistrisse Dorothy, wife of the said Henry: Nicolas Denham: wisheth the fauour of God, with the increase of the knowledge of assured saluation, in IESV CHRIST.</title>
           <author>Denham, N.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103963_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02928</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103963</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right woorshipful, Maister Henry Sadleyre Esquyer, Sonne of the right Honorable, Sir Raphe Sadleyre Knight, (one of her Maiesties, most ho∣norable priuie Counsayle, and Chauncellour of her Duchy of Lancastre:) And also to Mistrisse Dorothy, wife of the said Henry: Nicolas Denham: wisheth the fauour of God, with the increase of the knowledge of assured saluation, in IESV CHRIST.</title>
                 <author>Denham, N.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvay of lyfe : A Christian, and catholique institution comprehending principal poincts of Christian religion, which are necessary to bee knowne of all men, to the atteyning of saluation. First delyuered, in the Danish language for the instruction of those people, by Doctor Nicolas Hemmingius, preacher of the Gospell, and professor of diuinitie, for the Kynge of Denmarcke, in his Uniuersitie of Hafnia: and about three yeares past, (for the commoditie of others) translated into Latine, by Andrew Seurinus Velleius: and now first, and newly Englished, for the commodity of English readers: by N. Denham, this yeare of our redemption. 1578</title>
                 <author>Hemmingsen, Niels</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 191, 191-199 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right woorshipful, Maister <hi>Henry Sadleyre Esquyer, Sonne of <hi>the right Honorable, Sir</hi>
      </hi> Raphe Sadleyre Knight, (one of her Maiesties, most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable priuie Counsayle, and Chauncellour of her Duchy of Lancastre:) And also to Mistrisse Dorothy, wife of the said Henry: Nicolas Denham: wisheth the fauour of God, with the increase of the knowledge of assured saluation, in IESV CHRIST.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongest those</hi> seuen speciall Sages of the Gréeks, there was one, which béeinge desirous to leaue to a certayne follower of his sect, some speciall token woorthy of remembraunce: commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto him (as the special<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest thing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hée could deuise) this <hi>Symbole</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> (that is) <hi>Follow thou God.</hi> Wherby it is to bée perceiued, that euen the very heathens, indowed onely, with the lighte, and wisdome of nature, and not able to pearce farther, than their reasoninges, and argumentes taken of the visible creatures, which they saw, and perceyued with their senses) would stretch: did not only conclude, that there was a God, which was the woorkemayster, and disposer of all those thinges, and that hée was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall: but also that hee was to bee feared, and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the sight, and presence of him, to bée desired.</p>
   <p>For whilest that they considered, the globe, and compasse of the Firmament, and the earth, with all the noble, and variable furniture therof, as the Sunne, the Moone, the
<pb facs="3"/>
Starres, and vnder them, the varietie of the other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in their kindes, and lastly, the excellencie of the woorkemanshippe of the frame of the body of man: they were induced to gather therof, this conclusion: that the woorkemayster, of these thinges, was, not onely much more beautifull, and excellent, but that hee was, also, to bee honoured, and to bee wished for, by presence to bee inioyed. Hereof spronge vp many contentions, and sundry deuises amonge them, concerninge the way, as well how to woorship him, here vpon the earth, as also to seeke some shorte, and ready meane, to come to the sight, and beeholding of him. But notwithstandinge, in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they wanted the direction of him, which is the leader into all trueth:<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> they tyred themselues in their owne fonde immaginations, and, not onely in steade of the true woorshippinge of him, frequented Idolatries, most horrible, and execrable: but also, to come (as they supposed) to the sight of him, attempted meanes, moste pernitious, and dampnable. In so much, that diuerse of them, willinge to hye themselues apace, to bee in presence, with that immortality: could finde no better, or readier way, then speedily, to murder, and kill them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. Which dooinges of theirs, notwithstandinge they were heynous, and wicked, and missed of the ende, and purpose, for which they were doone, (for this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,<note place="margin">Ihon. 3.</note> that <hi>Hee which beeleeueth not in the Sonne of God, the anger of God doth abyde vpon him:</hi> And agayne the Apostle sayth:<note place="margin">Heb. 11. &amp; Rom. 14.</note>
      <hi>It is impossible without fayth to please God:</hi> yet it is apparaunte thereby, what earnestnesse was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongest thē, both to séeke (according to their owne blinde iudgementes) what this God should bee: and also, which should bee the waye, not onely to walke, but rather to make haste, and speede vnto him. Which, if they that do professe the name of Christ, would consider, and but compare themselues in these circumstaunces, with these
<pb facs="3"/>
men, beeinge but Heathens, and voyde, both of the true knowledge of God, the creatour, and also of him,<note place="margin">Ioh.</note> which is the onely way, and would, but sumwhat considerately conferre together, the blynde diligence of the one, with (as it may bee very well termed) the diuelish, and secure necligence of the other: their forwardnesse in seekinge after that, which by all their toylinge, and tyringe of themselues, they could not truely finde out, with our backwardnesse, in not keping, and imbracing that which (without our laboures) is fréely geuen vs, and sayed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes: their feruency, in desiringe to finde and runne the way, to that which they wished for, with our coldenesse in walkinge the right way, which is playnely drawne foorth, and delineated béefore vs: to bee shorte, their perswasions of themselues, by this visible Sunne, with our dulnesse: who, by that true, and bright shining Sunne, which is the brightnesse and wisdome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, will not bee instructed, nor mooued: If (I saye) they would with some earnestnes, consider these things: it were not to bee doubted, but as they doo detest, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre, the name and conuersation of the Heathen: so they would loathe (in such matters as séeme, to bée the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiest of all others) to bee eyther by others accoumpted, or in their owne consciences to bee condempned, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours vnto them. But, to leaue all other partes of comparison, and onely to speake of one poyncts, which concerneth our present purpose: it was taught amongst them, and practised by such as were of the best, and most reasonablest amongest them, as a moste necessary, and principall doctrine: that they shoulde not alwayes heere continue, <hi>But passe from hence: and that there was an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie of the Soule, which beeinge seperated by death, from the body, should, eyther, for the well, and vertuous walkeinge heere, (accordinge to their accompting of a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous lyfe) bee gathered into a certayne place of pleasure,
<pb facs="4"/>
with the Goddes, or els, for not followinge the morall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes in following vertues, and eschewing vices, should not inioy the sight of the Goddes, but should by them bee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This was the Summe of (as I may terme it) their naturall, and blinde religion. Thus much euen nature her selfe, in that her corruption, had taught them. And therefore the better to stirre vp their hearers, to walke vertuously, and with the more desire, in that path, which they supposed to bee the right waye: they vttered, and commended vnto them, and their posterity, many pithy, and sauoury sentences, as: <hi>Philosophia continu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> mortis meditatio,</hi> that is: <hi>the loue or studie of wisdome, is the continuall meditation of Death:</hi> And, <hi>Ad Ens Entiū sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per contendendum,</hi> that is: <hi>Wee must euer bee walkeinge towarde the cheefe beeing of beeinges,</hi> (whereby is ment, God himself,) with infinite such others, to tedious, here to be recyted, as in their bookes dayly handled, are plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully to bee seene. But wee, which do beare the name of Christians, which liue at these dayes, in which (by the great mercy of God) such infinite treasures of Heauenly wisdome, and knowledge of Christian doctrine, is pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red foorth vpon vs: yea wee which haue, for their shado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, and false, a cleare, and perfecte religion: for their crooked, and vncertayne by path, a streyght and most as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured highway: for wisdome naturall, the wisdome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine: for <hi>Plato, Aristotle,</hi> and their Schollars, the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, Christ, and his Apostles:</hi> for the doubtfull ende of the pathe, which they taught, the certayne, and assured ende of the way which wee are instucted to walke in: are yet notwithstanding, in respecte of them so dull, and so carelesse of all these thinges, yea, and so litle ashamed of this comparison with them: that wee are litle, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pricked forward, with the consideratiō of our more plentifull blessinges; litle, or nothing consider our owne
<pb facs="4"/>
contempt, and ingratitude: seeme to make lesse accompt of <hi>Christ,</hi> his <hi>Apostles,</hi> and <hi>Ministers,</hi> then the heathen did of <hi>Pythagoras, Plato, Aristotle, and their Sectaries,</hi> and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: seeme, neyther by the promises of God to bée al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured, nor, by his threatninges to bee feared: to be short, seeme neither to feare to runne headlong into that path, which leadeth to destruction, nor to regarde to walke in that way which guideth to saluation. It is therfore to bée feared, least that come to passe, in this comparison, which our Sauiour <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> himselfe pronounceth in the <hi>12.</hi> of <hi>S. Math.</hi> comparinge, the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and regarde of the Quéene of the South, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge from the farthest partes of the world, to heare the wisdome of <hi>Salomon,</hi> with the negligence, and contempt of the Iewes: in refusinge to bee taught by Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, comming amongest them: and likewise in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the repentaunce of the <hi>Niniuites, at the hearinge of Ionas:</hi> with their obstinacy, and rebellion, in refusinge to heare the Sonne of God himselfe: namely, that as hée there cōcludeth of them both: that aswell the Queene of the South as also the <hi>Niniuites,</hi> béeing prophane people, and heathens: shall rise in the last iudgemente, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne that adulterous, and obstinate nation: so that these heathens, shall then also arise, though not to theyr own saluation, yet to the condempnation of those, which (glorying in the name of Christians) haue so litle regard to walke the right way of eternall saluation. Which way of Saluation, forasmuch, as it hath beene, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse woorthy instrumentes, of the Church of Christ, in these our latter times, and ages of the world: tryed, and disseuered from that bypath, which leadeth to destruction and is (by the woorde of God, wherin that right way is set foorth, and offered) sufficiently cleansed, from all brambles, and weedes of incombraunce, which both for wante of good husbandinge, and walkinge in, had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growen,
<pb facs="5"/>
and hidden the same from many: and is now at the length, made so playne, and visible, that it may bee seene of all those, which doo not wilfully eyther cloase vp their eyes, that they will not see it, or if they doo see it, yet will not suffer their foote once to treade within it: a godly man (considering this) may, with sorow, and gréefe of minde, iustly meruayle, why there bee so many, which will not know it: so fewe, that doo regarde to know it: and why, fewer hauing found it, and beeing set into it, do so sclenderly goe forwarde, and continue their course in the same. That wée may the better conceyue the causes of these thinges: let vs first consider, wherin this waye of Saluation doth consist. The knowledge therof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth, in the right vnderstanding of these two thinges, namely of the <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Gospell.</hi> Wheras the Law therefore setteth foorth vnto vs the Iustice of God, and is set before vs, that wee may playnely sée therein, as it were in a glasse, both what God requireth of vs, and also how weake, and vnable wée bée to fulfill the same, that wee seeinge our owne, both deformitie, and imbecillity, should seeke for a cleanser, and a stronger, that may hath cleanse vs, and fulfill it for vs: and by this meanes to bée ledde to the Gospell, which setteth foorth the same vnto vs: here, the first sorte, hauinge beene trayned vp, and noozeled in another manner of doctrine, concerning the Lawe and the Gospell, and hauinge not learned, the true endes, and right vses of them, for the which they were geuen: are so obstinately bente agaynst this true knowledge of the right way, which is in them conteined: that they will suffer themselues by no meanes, to bee brought, once to enter their foote into it. The seconde sorte of people, are méere <hi>Athaeistes,</hi> and such as hauinge beene alwayes full fed like <hi>Epicures,</hi> and thorowly pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered vp, with all kindes of worldly volupteousnes, and pleasures of the flesh: are so lulled a sleape in them, by
<pb facs="5"/>
the subtilty of the Deuill, who holdeth them fast snarled: that they haue no leasure, once to bethinke themselues, nor to regarde, eyther what <hi>GOD</hi> is, or his <hi>Lawe,</hi> and <hi>Gospell,</hi> neyther yet, what nor where they themselues bée, nor how they came, or for what cause they are placed in the worlde, nor how they shall departe foorth of it, nor what shall become of them after this lyfe, and so neyther passe for Heauen, or Hell, <hi>GOD,</hi> or the Deuill: and therefore, no woonder, though they care not, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiringe, and much lesse for walkinge in this way: bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as they suppose themselues, (in such a way, as there neyther is, nor can bée any better. The thirde sorte, which doo finde it, and doo enter, and walke into it, and yet are oftentimes stayed, and hyndered in their course: are euen the most holyest in this lyfe, and the very electe of God: who hauing entred into it, and purposing with a good Conscience to walke forwarde in the same: are notwithstandinge oftentimes, through the malice of the Deuill, (continually warring against them, and séeking to plucke them foorth of that way, into the bypathe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction with him, and through the frailty of their own flesh, and the continuall allurementes, and baytes of the world, are oftentimes so drawne aside, and hindered, yea so bewitched, and dazeled: that it oftentimes séemeth vnto them themselues: that they néede not so earnestly, and so dilligently regard, to continue still their walking in the same. Hereof it commeth to passe, that, (by the permission of God) they béeing eyther drawne backe, or stayed from going forward, or pluckt for a season beside the way: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heynous, and horrible offences, are by them commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: which aduauntage (as long as they héedefully kept themselues, within the limittes of the right way of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation) the Deuil could not haue of them. When <hi>Dauid</hi> demaūded of the Lord, <hi>Wherwithall, a young man should cleanse his way,</hi> and the answere of the holy ghost within
<pb facs="6"/>
him was this: <hi>By rulinge himselfe according to the worde of GOD,</hi> was then no doubt, both mindefull of this way, and diligently troade, and walked in the same: but, beeing a litle stayed therin, hée was drawne aside, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the most horrible offence of Murther, and Adultrie: but God hauing compassion vpon him, and not suffering him, vtterly to loose the right way of his Saluation: ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his <hi>Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Iustice</hi> togeather, and sending them vnto him, by the Prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi> did both mercifully set him in the right way agayne (after hée had repentauntly acknowledged his declining from the same) and also ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal, iustly scourged him for his wandring &amp; digression. The lyke may bée found of <hi>Ezechias, Manasses, Peter,</hi> and diuerse others: which (in reading of the holy Scriptures) are almost euery where to bee found, and here, for expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of tediousnesse, are omitted. So that albeit, the godly man, or woman, bée sometimes hindred in the wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this course, from goinge forward, or be plucked backewarde, or séemeth (as it were) set quite beside the way, wherby (as the examples aboue recited do declare) many horrible offences, and wicked actes, pleasant to the Deuill, are by them committed: yet, this hope they haue lefte them: that God will not suffer them (with the obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate wicked, &amp; carelesse vngodly,) to perish vtterly from the right way, but that hée will reatch forth his mercifull hand of direction vnto them: which (they hartily repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge, and taking holde of) will set them in the streyght, and right way agayne: wherin if they shall perseauere, and continue vnto the ende: they shalbe sure (as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour <hi>Christ</hi> himselfe hath promised) to bée vndoubtedly saued. For, so hée himselfe sayth in <hi>Math. <hi>Hee that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth to the ende, shalbe saued:</hi>
      </hi> And agayne: <hi>Continue vnto the ende, and I will geue thee a Crowne of lyfe.</hi> Thus wée sée the diuersity of the people, which lyue, &amp; remaine, euen amongest vs which professe the name, and religion
<pb facs="6"/>
of <hi>IESVS CHRISTE,</hi> how, and in what manner they bée affected, to the knowledge of this way of eternall lyfe, and Saluation. Whereof, some, (by meanes of a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer false receiued opinion déepely rooted in them) bée ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinate, and wilfully will not learne it: some, are negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente and carelesse, that they passe not for it: the thirde sorte yet imbracing it, and reioysing to walke in it: are notwithstanding (through diuerse, and infinite impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and hinderaunces) either stayed, or plucked back, or aside from it: and yet notwithstanding, by the mercy of God, are called backe againe by earnest repentaunce, and are agayne set therin: wherein they walke here vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, and continue their course in the same vnto the ende, depart this life in walkinge in the same, and at the ende of this way, enter into the Citie of eternal rest, and saluation. The true doctrine wherof, béeing in this litle Treatise both learnedly, and also clearely, &amp; plainly set foorth, by this godly learned man, béeing such a one, as by the iudgement, and opinion of diuerse of the best lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of this our time, hath deserued, not the least cōmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion, of the Church of Christ: when I had perused, and conferred with my fréend, I thought very méete, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, to conuert into our vulgare spéeche, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, &amp; comfortable instruction of all those, to whom it shall please God, to geue eyes to sée, eares to heare, hearts to conceiue, and féete to walke aright, in the ready way to lyfe, therin set downe, and deliuered: as in the diligente reading, and meditating of the same, shall (I hope) to the comfort &amp; sound instruction of the Christian Conscience, more playnely appeare. For, as the Doctrine therein conteyned, is, both necessary (and as touchinge the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce therof) is such, that the true Christian man, or woman, may not bée without the knowledge, and practise therof, in this life, if they desire to attayne to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and vnderstanding of their saluation in the lyfe to
<pb facs="7"/>
come: so is it (asmuch as is requisite therunto) both pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, very playnely, and also familyarly, aswell in plain spéech as easy Methode, set downe, and deliuered: &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with good aduisement, and deliberation handled, and diuulged. Touching the Author himselfe, it is sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne amongest the learned, what hée is: as béeinge such a one, which hath not the lowest roome, amongst the best, and moste approoued Christian writers of this our age: brought vp from his infancy, in the studies, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises of learning, and godlynesse, notably qualified, and furnished aswell with liberall artes, and languages: as principally in the study, &amp; profession of Diuinitie: which profession hée hath woorthely and diligently executed (as by his owne testimony set downe in his Epistle before this booke, is to bée séene) by the space, and continuance of thyrtie yeares: béeinge therunto called, by the Kinge of <hi>Denmarcke,</hi> to supply the place of his publique reader, and professour of <hi>Diuinitic,</hi> in his vniuersitie of <hi>Hafnia,</hi> where with great fame (as I heare) hee at this day con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth. Touching the perticuler matters, conteyned, and handled in the booke, ther are such (as I haue already sayd, and in the diligente perusinge therof shalbe better perceiued) that the knowledge of them in a Christian, may not bée wanting. And I doubt not but the Christian reader (if hée haue any desire to aspire to the knowledge of Iesus Christ) hauing a while busied himselfe therin: shall freely in his owne conscience confesse, as much as I haue héere spoken. For, if hée desire (in short summe, and bréefely, and yet sufficiently) the perfecte, and right vnderstanding of the Law of God, what it is, how many, and what the true vses therof bée, to what end it is geuē vnto men: also, what the Gospell is, and to what ende it is geuen, what wée must necessarily beléeue of Christ, (as it is consonant to our common fayth:) How hée is our <hi>Mediatour, Redeemer,</hi> and Sanctifier: by what meanes
<pb facs="7"/>
hée declareth and setteth foorth his benefites vnto man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, what his benefits be toward vs: what is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered &amp; learned of the Sacraments, aswel of Baptisme, as of the Supper of the Lorde: besides diuerse other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary doctrines, of the right woorshippinge, and seruice of God, of prayer, and diuerse other places which (as I haue sayd) in the diligent perusing of the same, shall more euidently appeare, to the Christian reader. If hee desire (I say) to bee instructed, exhorted, or comforted, in these thinges, hee may here finde them, both soundly, &amp; plainly expounded. All which poinctes, being by other most god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; learned pastoures of the Church of Christe, notably, and pithily in these latter times set abroade vnto the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of the worlde, to no small benefit of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Christ: yet by reason of their buckling with the aduersaries of the trueth, in refelling their corruptions, and cauilling obiections, they were forced, to write with greater stile of woordes, and more Schoolelyke, whereby their woorkes became more conuenient (in some poincts) for studentes in Diuinitie, then for the common peoples perceauerance, and Capacitie. Which things I speake, not that I would dehorte any from the reading, and dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent exercisinge of them: yea I doo rather most hartely exhorte them therunto: but this I say, to the ende, to take away the offence, which (as I my selfe haue heard (some haue taken (though vndeseruedly) when they perceyue thē in some places (for the causes afore recyted) to write eyther somewhat longer then they thinke méete, or sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more artificially then they doo conceyue. Which offence, (not geuen, but vniustly taken,) they should easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let fall, if they woulde consider the causes aforesayde, which violently drew those learned men, and by an ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitable necessity, enforced them so to doo. From which tediousnesse, (if they will needes so accompte it) they
<pb facs="8"/>
are in this small treatise delyuered: where so sundry great occasions were not geuen to the Author: For as hée aunswereth here but to few obiections, so, writinge his booke for the common sort, hée frameth his answeres and solutions, bothe shorte, and easie. Which woorke (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sundry other learned, and fruictfull laboures written of Diuinitie, by him, which are extant, and set abroade in the Latin tongue:) the sayde Author wrote, and deliuered abroad, at the first, in the <hi>Danish language,</hi> for the instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and consolation of the people of that nation, and spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for such of them, as could not gather y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> knowledge of godlynesse, foorth of other languages, wherein it was written: which béeing so written, and set abroad, it was, by diuerse learned men of the same Region concluded vpon, for the woorthynesse thereof, to bée turned into the Latin spéeche, to the ende, that other faithfull heades, and teachers of the Church of Christ, séeing thesame, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing it to bée, both sound, and comfortable, might the sooner conuerte, or cause the same to bée conuerted, into their owne seuerall languages: and commend the same, to those porcions of the Church, and flock of Christ which are to their seuerall charges committed.</p>
   <p>Which Treatise béeing now at the last, conuerted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our common language, by mée, for the causes aboue rehearsed: I here dedicate, and present (Right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) vnto you both: beséeching you to accept the same, as an argument, and testimony of that well willing affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which (by sundry your gentlenesses exhibited, and shewed) you haue, deseruedly, raysed vp in mee. And albeit, I can not iustly auouche it, to bée any recompence for any parte of the same: neither yet doo proffer it to that ende: yet rather then I would incurre the compasse of that sentence of the <hi>Philosopher, Perit quod facis ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: <hi>That is loste which is doone to an vnthankefull person:</hi>
      </hi> I had leiffer by proferinge that litle, that I may make
<pb facs="8"/>
auoydaunce therof. I beseeche almighty God preserue you bothe, and confirme, and increase in you, vnto the end, those good giftes of his grace which hée hath already béegun in you: and so illuminate you with the light of his holy spirit, that yée may both sée the right way, and seeing it, you may haue a desire to walke in the same: and that walkeing daily forwarde in the same, and so conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing vnto the end: you may passe, in at that gate, which leadeth from the sourginge, and daungerous Sea of this transitorie lyfe, into the Hauen of perpetuall rest, and quietnesse, there quietly, peaceably, &amp; ioyfully, to beholde the glorious face of <hi>IESVS CHRISTE</hi> to whom with the Father, and the holy Ghost, bée prayse and dominion for euer. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Woorships humble at commaundement: N. <hi>Denham.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>From London <date>this XXV. of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober, the yeare of our Redemption. 1578.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>