<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right noble Lady Ladye Margret Countes of Marsheale.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103342_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01930</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103342</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right noble Lady Ladye Margret Countes of Marsheale.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of the famous historye of Penardo and Laissa : other ways callid the warres, of love and ambitione. Wherein is described Penardo his most admirable deeds of arms, his ambition of glore his contempt of loue, with loves mighte assalts &amp; ammorus temptations: Laissas feareful inchantment hir releif hir trauells and lastly loves admirabel force, in hir releiving Penardo from ye fire, doone in heroik verse, by Patrik Gordon</title>
                 <author>Gordon, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waters (Walters), Joris (George)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Dordrecht</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>280 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Right noble Lady Ladye Margret Countes of Marsheale.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>LOng haue I wishid my Muse, to sound thy prayse</l>
      <l>The worthe, the fame, the due, to the belonge,</l>
      <l>But she onlernd vn fit, for such a phrayse,</l>
      <l>Denyit to doe, say, think, so heighe a songe:</l>
      <l>Since on thy worthe, both heaune, and earthe still gaize</l>
      <l>She should but shame her self, and do the wronge</l>
      <l>Better quod she be sobre silent, still,</l>
      <l>And spair to speek, then speek, and speek but ill.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>O but quod I, to speek her praise, her worthe,</l>
      <l>Out of my faith, my trueth, my zeall my loue,</l>
      <l>Faith, trueth, lone, zeall, and duetie, breaths it furthe</l>
      <l>As shal my pure, eleir, simple meining proue:</l>
      <l>Her nature myld, heighe place, and royall birthe,</l>
      <l>Her witt, her worthe, her vertue, from aboue.</l>
      <l>Has croun'd with garlants, of immortall glorye,</l>
      <l>Then none ean writt amisse, that writts her storye</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Whill thus my barrene Muse, and I contend</l>
      <l>Thy worth, wit, vertue, and thy geighe desairt,</l>
      <l>Commands me write, and speek, and praise furthsen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
      <l>To eurye countrey, province, place, and pairt,</l>
      <l>But comeing to (what should I say) in end.</l>
      <l>O then I stand, I pause, I think, in hairt</l>
      <l>Words does my witt, wit does my words eonfuse</l>
      <l>Nou this, now that, a thousand things I chuse,</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <l>So infinite, thy endles graces be</l>
      <l>That what I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ould, I would, Zit can not doe</l>
      <l>Witt moketh witt, arte skorneth arte, in me</l>
      <l>And wealth, deludeth wealth I know not how</l>
      <l>When I should end, I but begine to sie,</l>
      <l>A world of worlds rair worthines, in yow,</l>
      <l>Then this I say, nor will I write no more,</l>
      <l>None is, shall be, nor was lyk the before</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>