<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE WILLIAM Lord CRAVEN, Baron of Hamsted-Marshall, &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103512_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02320</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12452</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103512</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE WILLIAM Lord CRAVEN, Baron of Hamsted-Marshall, &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The letters of Mounsieur de Balzac. Translated into English, according to the last edition. By W.T. Esq</title>
                 <author>Balzac, Jean-Louis Guez, seigneur de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Clutterbuck (Clotterbuck), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 80, 83-401, that is 410, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE WILLIAM Lord CRAVEN, Baron of <hi>Hamsted-Marshall,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>My LORD,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot to know your Lordship, is an ignorance next Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risine, but to be knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, is an honour my am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition hath alwayes aymed at, but which my want of merit, or euill fortune, neuer yet attained. In making this tender of my truest seruice, I offer you the Votes of all (who not poysoned by that Viper Enuie) iustly extoll courage in youth, not forced to action, but by the only spurre of glory. The vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersall world (among the wonders of our age) numbers you: and our world hauing
<pb facs="3"/>
the happinesse to boast her selfe your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, cherisheth you, as a man shee hath long time laboured to produce. This <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent</hi> is but a Translation; which yet may (happily) as well for the generall benefit, as particular choice, bee equall to an origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, you can best iudge: I haue therefore in part, vindicated my selfe from those who may accuseme of not knowledge, or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. I submit all to your censure; and with this small testimony of my deuotion to true Nobility, doe here sue to haue these first fruits of my labours, placed vnder the protection of so Honourable a Patron; whose vertues, as they are worthy to bee admired by all, so shall they, together with this so noble a fauour, bee euer duely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>My Lord,</salute>
      <signed> Your humblest seruant,William Tirwhyt.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>