<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Courteous and Courtly La∣dyes
of England.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103424_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02152</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12294</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103424</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Courteous and Courtly La∣dyes
of England.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Penelopes vveb : VVhere, in a christall mirror of feminine perfection represents to the view of euery one those vertues and graces, which more curiously beautifies the mind of women, then eyther sumptuous apparell, or iewels of inestimable value: the one buying fame with honour, the other breeding a kinde of delight, but with repentance. In three seuerall discourses also are three speciall vertues, necessary to be incident in euery vertuous woman, pithely discussed: namely obedience, chastity, and sylence: interlaced with three seuerall and comicall histories. By Robert Greene Master of Artes in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hodgets, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Courteous and Courtly La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes
of England.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that (Gentlewomen) I had finish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
this worke of <hi>Penelopes</hi> Web, and
was willing to commit it to the
Presse, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ell to parlye with my selfe,
whether I should stay it as <hi>Apelles</hi> did <hi>Venus</hi> pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
halfe vnfinished in the Printers fourmes: or
thrust it out as <hi>Myson</hi> did a ragged table bescratcht
with a pensell. <hi>Apelles</hi> was froward, and <hi>Myson</hi> too
forward, both faulty, and euery man hath his folly.
It may be some will thinke me of <hi>Antisthenes</hi> fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
that layed platformes of euery mans life, and
yet the Philosopher was more vvise in his precepts
then vvary of his ovvne gouernment: and count
me very oeconomycall that seeke to sette dovvne
the duety of a vvife, &amp; to deliuer principles to such
a purpose. If <hi>I</hi> haue intermedled too far, it is (Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlevvomen)
in discouering the vertues of your sex,
not in censuring seuerely of your actions: for <hi>I</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
but the vievv of those vertues that naturally
<pb facs="4"/>
are, or incidently ought to be as well in virgins that
sacrifice to <hi>Vesta,</hi> as in wiues▪ that make secrete
vowes to <hi>Lucyna. I</hi> reprehend not (as one think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
all generally to be vertuous,) but perswade as
one wishing particularly euery one should lyue
well and dye better. If any that are enuyous
grudge at my dooing, <hi>I</hi> straight for refuge flye to
your good words, which <hi>I</hi> count as a sufficient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensory
against such as loue to backbyte. Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
therefore my Booke to your pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ronage, least
the gates being too big for the Citty, the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
should seeme to swell and bring foorth a
Mouse, <hi>I</hi> wish you all such happy
successe as you can desire
and <hi>I</hi> imagine.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Robert Greene.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>