<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE IMPARTIALL READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103208_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11615</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21857</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103208</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE IMPARTIALL READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Calderwoods recantation: or, A tripartite discourse : Directed to svch of the ministerie, and others in Scotland, that refuse conformitie to the ordinances of the church. Wherein the causes and bad effects of such separation, the legall proceedings against the refractarie, and nullitie of their cause, are softly launced, and they louingly inuited to the vniformitie of the church</title>
                 <author>Scot, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Alsop, Bernard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 50 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE IMPARTIALL READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant (impartiall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that to perswade or contend for Redresse without Authority, little preuailes, and oft times exposeth such Motions to Contempt or Malice: yet the loue I owe to the Peace of the Church, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth me to sollicite Conformitie in a matter of great consequence. If any challenge my insuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, or interest; let them know, that I much more estimate the weake endeuours of good meaning, then the more learned shewes of Pharisaical Ostentation; That I am as well lyable to giue account of my Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, as the Arch Pillars of most profound Learning; and that armed with these Reasons, I care not what the most Censorious Criticke or <hi>Thraso</hi>-like Brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadochio can degorge against me. One fauor I craue, That thou wilt not curiously enquire what I haue beene, or pry into my former Errors (for which, I humbly begge pardon from the Mercy-Master in Heauen, and from his Vice-gerent, my dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb facs="3"/>
vpon Earth) but consider with iudgement what now I am, and how affected to the Truth. I haue in this ensuing home-spun Discourse freely expressed my selfe touching the Controuersies which haue long troubled the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> In it I neyther wrong the dead, cast con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt vpon the liuing; neyther leuell I at any mans person, further then, in the inquirie of Truth, may conduce to the aduancement thereof, and publike good. In this pursuit, I haue left all extrauagant Wanders, and balk'd all circulating Complements (too common both to Wits and Writs in this Age) and haue runne poste in the high way; wherein if I haue stumbled, I expect lesse harme, or more pitty. What I haue written, is without Art or Insinuation; perhaps it may proue the lesse gracefull: yet I hope it shall finde correspondence in the mindes of those that are not imbarked in partialitie, and loues the whole better then a part.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Amsterdam,</hi>
         <date>this <hi>29.</hi> of Nouemb. <hi>1622.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>