<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Reader</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103743_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07229</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17626</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103743</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Reader</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dysclosyng of the canon of ye popysh masse : with a sermon annexed vnto it of ye famous clerke of worthy memorye. D Marten Luther</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 <publisher>Copland, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hitprick, Hans, pseud</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>23 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the Reader</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>rom the begīnyg <note place="margin">Genes. i,</note> or at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fyrst entra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unce after the cee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aciō good chrystē reader God in hī selfe <note place="margin">Iohan, ii,</note> for seynge the way warde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mannes harte, and how prone and readye it was, vnto wyckednes, and howe, ablyuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of the benefytes that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of hys lorde Gods han▪ de <note place="margin">Esal, i,</note> became not thankefull vnto hys myghty God, But vanys, <note place="margin">Roman, ii,</note> shed in the Imagynacyons of <note place="margin">Ieremy, iii▪</note> hys froward stomake, and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shipped the workeman shyp of the handes of a caranous car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas subdued to all vanyte and forgat hys creatour, the whych <note place="margin">Exod, xxiii,</note> vngentelnes hathe bene of all other vyces, mooste earnestlye
<pb facs="3"/> reprehended by the, mouthe of God euen from the beginnīge, and not onelye reprehended but also wyth sharpe threates and cōmynacyons, of hys moost sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred woorde appoynted to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <note place="margin">Roman, i.</note> dampnacion Besides that he gaue them vp to theyr har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes <note place="margin">Deut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>iii</note> luste and plaged them with swearde, famyne and pestilence Therfore good chrysten reder, lyfte vp thyne eyes and behold <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>. Iohan, ii,</note> the abhomynacion of Idolatri <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Thess ii,</note> so shamefullye vsed in these da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yes of our tyme and not onelye vsed but with force and mayne <note place="margin">Psalm, ii</note> fortefyed and vpholden wyth fyre and faggot crudelytye and strength, and that sosore vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <note place="margin">Math. xv,</note> that the eternall worde of God is clerely banysshed exiled and put too bed Howe sayste y<seg rend="sup">u</seg>
      <pb facs="3"/> to this detestable and among al other the moost shameful mase <note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, xii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> and gasyng stocke the wyckede masse the vpsprynge of Sathā the inuencyon of the deuyll the fayre frute of the Romish raue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng, <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>el. ix.</note> Antechryste and the lader hous of al his shauen posteritie <note place="margin">Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>my, xv</note> Beholde it and abhorte it or el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les take it for a warnyng. God wyll abhorte the and cast the in to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> lak that burneth with fyre and brimstone wherfore I harte <note place="margin">Apocal. xx.</note> lye beseche the; w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all brotherly affeccyon, marke in thys lytell <note place="margin">phyli. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</note> volume or fewe lynes the tayle of the Dragon, of Gog and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gog. the wasters of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ore flock <note place="margin">Ezechiel xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. viii</note> of Chryste the maynteyners of myschefe the studyers of super sticyon the fortefyers of
<pb facs="4"/> of the malignaunt Chyrche the <note place="margin">Psalm, xxvi</note> gylders of the tryple, Crowne / and thou shalte playnlye par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue <note place="margin">Coloss. ii</note> in an hondreth wordes. the shamefull legerdemayne &amp; craftie Iugglīg that cost them <note place="margin">Math. xiii,</note> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> study not of a fewe hondreth years, and the sweate of manye browes, for the whych bothe their pot and spytte, walke the merielier, vnto thys houre, It <note place="margin">Exod, xvi</note> is cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed the Canon of the mys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheff a (of the Masse I woulde saye) that is to say the rule and order that they haue taken to fynysh theyr slayne sacryfyce, &amp; too brynge it to an ende. But what turmoylyng, strugglynge w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>astlynge quid pro quo. wyth <note place="margin">Cor, xi.</note> my wayes is best hold thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de fro my throte there was tyll they had broughte it to the mys<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shapen
<pb facs="4"/> for me, that it is nowe in Polidorus Virgilius dothe <note place="margin">Lib, v, ca, x,</note> plainlye manyfest. Whervnto also y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> hast a sermon ānexed, of the famous Clerke &amp; discloser of the Popes Iuggling box &amp; of worthi memorye D. Martin Luther. Reade it I pray y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a sober Iudgement and conferte y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Idolatries of the old time w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the obhominable Idolatry, in our tyme after the comming of Chryste the pure and true light and y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> shalt se it farre passe. Oh <note place="margin">Math, vi</note> most mighty father for y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> tender loue that thou barest to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole <note place="margin">Iohn, iii.</note> world in that thou delyueredest thyne onely and swete sonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sus <note place="margin">Hebr, x,</note> Chryst that holy and suffici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent <note place="margin">Math, xxi,</note> sacryfice, for the lyfe of the whole world Haue mercy vppō vs &amp; deliuer vs from y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> snares
<pb facs="5"/> of Sathan, and from the dyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lysh yock of this detestable I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrye and open the eyes of <note place="margin">Psalm. xlv,</note> oure. Magystrates that they may prosperously fortefye they <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, iiii,</note> blessed woorde, as they haue be gonne graciously and to deface the bloudye kyndume of Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ <note place="margin">Apocal, xviii</note> and send the communalte obedyēt stomackes and hartes <note place="margin">Roma, xiii</note> to fortefi theyr Prynces quarel in all godlynes and ryght And that all chrysten reames, maye accorde in peace and vnyte and so to be incorporate in the misty <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>imoth, ii,</note> call body of God all myghte, <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> whose head is chryste Iesus to whome I commyt the w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the encrease of hys knowledge. Amen.</p>
   <closer>Reade and then Iudge</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>