<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The preface to the gentle Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103647_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15587</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25852</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103647</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The preface to the gentle Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A compendious or short treatise, gathered out of the chyefe and principall authors of phisycke : conteynyuge certeyne preceptes necessary to the preseruacion of healthe, and longe continuaunce of the same: verye pleasaunte and profitable to reade</title>
                 <author>Wingfield, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Stoughton, Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>68 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Culinary arts</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ The preface to the gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He sharpenes and quicke<note place="margin">Ingeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</note> capacitie of mannes wyt (whych is the best gyfte, &amp; greatest treasure, graū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<note place="margin">memoria.</note> to mankynd:) The memorie, trusty, firme, &amp; strong in reteyning &amp; keping thynges cōmitted to her custodi: are not so much necessarie or expediente to the hauynge of a perfecte and exacte knowledge of the tongues and liberall faculties (wherein all treasures of science &amp; wysedome are comprehended,) as<note place="margin">Juditi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪</note> is a pure and sincere iudgemente. Furthermore, to haue so vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt or vpryght iudgement, true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to iudge &amp; esteme euery thyng to be as it is, is a thing very hard and difficulte: Not onlye for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the great varietie and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sention in opinions, but also for
<pb facs="4"/>
the vayne and vncerteine confec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures whych be in many sciences, as Palmestry, Pyromancie, and Astrology, and other faculties vn leful by the lawes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> God &amp; man. Wherfore onles man know such secrete mysteries and hyd operaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note place="margin">Experien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia.</note> of nature bi experience, he can neuer come to the knowledge ther<note place="margin">Longa vi ta ad sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entie cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitionem necessaria</note> of, the iudgement is so amased, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, and ouerwhelmed wyth darkenes.</p>
   <p>Moreouer, experience also is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentymes vncerteine and fallible, bothe for the imbecillitie of oure iudgement, and also for that oure lyfe tyme is feble, frayle, and of shorte continuaunce.</p>
   <p>Wherfore of these premisses the noble Physicion Hippocrates of most worthy memorye dyd plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye gather, that no man can come to the perfecte and exacte knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="4"/>
of learnyng in short continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, so that it is requisite that life be prolonged, And there is no man so dul, no such lacke wyt, but that knoweth wel inough, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thys thyng may be easely performed if he vse wysedome and diligent pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uision in the ordryng therof, Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thyng to be true, not only expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, but also the diligent and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert cure of phisycke is a sure wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and testimonie. For it is dayly sene, that feble and weake bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ies by thys prouidence and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion in liuynge, lyue as longe as those which be valeaunt, lusty, and strong. To the confirmaciō wher of, Plato and Aristotle beare me witnes, that a man of excellente lernyng and wisedome named He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>odicus, which was in all hys lyfe as feble and syckely as anye man liuyng at that tyme, by suche pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence
<pb facs="5"/>
and order in diete, to haue iyued vntyll he was an hundred yeres olde. I lette passe manye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of whom Plutarche maketh mencion, whyche althoughe they were verye feble and weake, yet they by obseruynge these precepts of liuyng, and vsyng great diligēce to preserue the same, haue lyued long tyme wythout any greuous or paynefull syckenes. Whyche thynges considered and kept in re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membraunce, causeth many not a lytle to meruell what shoulde bee the cause of so sodaine a chaunge &amp; alteracion in our bodies at thys tyme frō their nature which haue ben before vs. For now adaies if a man lyue to fyfty or. lx. yere, it is thought a great age. And the most parte of men ere this tyme euen in their florishyng youth are attached with fearful death which shaketh
<pb facs="5"/>
of their freshe colour, their bewty, and their strēgth. And yet the case is playne, that mans lyfe myghte continue as longe nowe as it hath done afore tyme, if we in leadyng forth thereof wolde vse suche dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and circūspectiō as dyd our progenitors. Whiche thynge I speake not as any derogatiō vnto gods honor, as who say, that we can appoint or constitute ani time, excepting alway y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> power of God which is wonderfull &amp; also merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful aboue mans reasō or counsell, preseruing, or striking, whō, whē, or wher it shal like his diuine pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er. For oftentymes as holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth record, horrible syn hath ben y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cause of short life. And as it<note place="margin">Gen. xvi.</note> is writtē y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first boke of Moses in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first age, one mā liued as long as. v. or. vi. do now, but shortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, lyke as men, so dyd synne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease on the earthe.
<pb facs="6"/>
Wherefore the Lorde sayde: my spirite shal not alway striue in mā because he is fleshe, and his dayes shall be a. C. &amp;. xx. yeres, but none at all, or very few doth approche nere vnto thys age: And truely to speake as I thynke our imtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, continuall bankettyng, and dayely ingurgitacions of meates and drinkes, is greate occasion of short lyfe nowe adayes. The spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of glotonie so triumphyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge vs in his glorious chariot called welfare, driuynge all smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feastes and bealye guttes as hys prisoners afore him into the dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of surfet, where they be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented wyth sondrie painfull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seases, driuen, drawen, and finally drowned. Such miserable nature remayneth in some mē, that to liue idel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y and voluptuously, they wyl chose rather to be sycke then to be
<pb facs="6"/>
whole: rather to haue payne then pleasure, rather to dye then to liue. For thys is not a rare thyng, but in dayly experience, that by suche reuell, gourmandise, and daily sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetyng, many cruellye are putte to deathe, oftentimes in floryshynge youth, in the most pleasaunt tyme of their lyfe. Wherfore the saying of the wise man Salomon is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye on them verified, mo dye sayth he by surfet and intēperance, then dothe by battell and outward bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilitie. For the reformacion wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to restraine their prompte disposicion from suche beastlie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and wantō appetire: I haue gathered of the moste principall writers of phisicke, this compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious extract, wherin are contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned certein obseruacions and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptes very necessary and profita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to the prolōging of lyfe: which
<pb facs="7"/>
beyng well obserued, put in due execution, and discretelye ordred, doth conserue and keepe oure lyfe longe in health, wythout the why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the all pleasures be paynful, ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vnprofitable, &amp; yet fewe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider this (the more pitie it is) but thys omittyng, I haue proceded in this place wyth ouer farre cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstaunce, and also wyth some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to much libertie of wordes, more then in a preface is requisite, for that it greueth me that mēns myndes be taken prisoners, and subdued to glotonie and intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. And nowe wyll I come to my matter purposed and fyrst en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpryse begon (whych excepte I be muche deceyued) shall m<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nister to the diligent rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders, both commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. ❀ (∴) ☜</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>