<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Booke of Armorie The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103621_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16401</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3314</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103621</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Booke of Armorie The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The gentlemans academie. Or, The booke of S. Albans : containing three most exact and excellent bookes: the first of hawking, the second of all the proper termes of hunting, and the last of armorie: all compiled by Iuliana Barnes, in the yere from the incarnation of Chris 1486. And now reduced into a better method, by G.M</title>
                 <author>Berners, Juliana</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 95, 1 leave, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Heraldic works and genealogies</term>
                    <term>Games and recreations</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="39"/>
   <pb n="42" facs="39"/>
   <head>The Booke of Armorie The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere in this booke following is expressed the genealogie of coate-armors and how a perfit Gentleman shall bee knowne from an imperfit clowne, both howe bondage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in angels, and after succeeded in mankind, as insueth in the stories of the children of Adam and Noah, with the diuision which Noah made of the world in three parts, to his three sonnes, also of the three colours in armes figured by the nine orders of angels, and in the colours is made mention which is royall, &amp; which worthy, &amp; of royalties which
<pb facs="40"/>
is noble, which is excellent. In this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course shall not be omitted, the vertues of Chiualrie, nor any other notable or famous thing, fitte for the pleasures of renowned persons, as the Worke, not my report shall witnesse: therefore who so liketh, let him reade, and leaue to reade when he leaues to like, the gray haires this workes aged tropheis, shal promise graue matter, no light delight, therfore for his age do him reuerence, and for thy profit loue: In whose conclusion shall follow the blasing of all maner of armes in Latin, French, and English.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>