<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader the Authour wisheth Grace, Peace, Salvation.</title>
           <author>H., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103940_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02837</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12976</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103940</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader the Authour wisheth Grace, Peace, Salvation.</title>
                 <author>H., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The eqvall vvayes of God : tending to the rectifying of the crooked wayes of man. The passages whereof are briefly and clearly drawne from the sacred Scriptvres. By T.H</title>
                 <author>Hayne, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN Reader the Authour wisheth Grace, Peace, Salvation.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, GODS wayes revealed are not only written for mans perusall, but also put to his considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as being beyond all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; for God demands of him, <hi>Are not my wayes equall?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ezek. 18.29.</note> As if what the <hi>better sort</hi> of men readily acknowledge, the <hi>worst</hi> could not in reason deny; what <hi>the one</hi> set their hearts on, and freely <hi>blesse God</hi> for, the other, convinced by evident truth, could not <hi>but approve. These wayes of God</hi> I have indeavoured to trace out so farre as cleare Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture gave me light, and common consent of mens judgement went along with me. Further disquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might perhaps trench on <hi>things unrevea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> are a tree of knowledge still <hi>forbiddē by God;</hi> or prove <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">1 Ti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 6.4.</note>
      <hi>strife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout words and vaine disputes, which tend not to godly edification.</hi> The former
<pb facs="3"/>
being as culpable as it was to presse too neare <hi>Gods holy Mount;</hi> the later proceeding usual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>envie, contention, railing, evill surmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing.</hi> Moreover in laying open <hi>these</hi> equall and plaine wayes of God I have not used subtile, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther discourse or dispute, which elsewhere hath its place and use:<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.25.</note>
      <hi>sua se jactet in aula;</hi> but such, as <hi>Paul</hi> cals, <hi>wholesome words of Christ,</hi> borrowed from the Scriptures treasury; such as his practice allowes,<note place="margin">Act. 26.25.</note>
      <hi>words of sobernesse and truth,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Plat. in Sym.</note> and have made, as <hi>Socrates</hi> desired, <hi>truth my chiefest aime.</hi> As for the structure of my speech; it is, if not, as <hi>Socrates</hi> further said, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, such as offered it selfe; yet farre from the <hi>quaint straine</hi> now affected.<note place="margin">Eurip. in Phoe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>· <hi>Truth is amiable and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable of it selfe, and needs not to bee clothed in phrase fashionable to the time, and the humour of curious eares;</hi> especially seeing we finde, that the stile of speech accounted by the Mint masters thereof very elegant, holds fashion not an age, yea not much longer than the variable garbe of our outward habite: for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving shewed it selfe to the world, it comes to the touch, and soone is exploded (for so usually it fals
<pb facs="3"/>
out) as being affected or phantasticall, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise lyable to some just exception. But truth is constantly the same, still keepes the same splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, still beholds us, as the Sunne, with the same glorious eye. And where it meets with most mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine and true eloquution fitted to the matter &amp; circūstances therof (in w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> regard it is praise wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy) it gives more grace and lustre to the speech, thē possibly it can borrow from the same. Againe, I have indeavoured for truth &amp; <hi>plainnesse;</hi> for plainnesse, that I might not be misconceived, nor have what I reach out with the right hand, to be laid hold on with the left; for truth, that I might avoid contention; for <hi>Socrates</hi> found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,<note place="margin">Plat. Symp.</note> that it was an easie matter <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>to gainsay</hi> Socrates, <hi>but not the truth:</hi> much more may I, who am lesse able to propound it. Furthermore may you please to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that in the first composure of this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, it was onely cast into certaine heads, and intended by me for mine owne better understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of these matters, without any minde to make it publike; and now is made yours by the Presse at the instance of some loving friends, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine better thoughts of it, than I my selfe
<pb facs="4"/>
could hope, or perhaps it deserves, for in a friends censure sometimes it happens,
<q>Vt veris addat multa faventis amor.</q>
Some indeed have conceived that the plainnesse and briefnesse thereof may be usefull to men of plaine hearts and of not so deep apprehension; &amp; to such, whose time is much taken up with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie or frequencie of imployment. Which surely it is more likly to doe; If as I in setting the whole frame together laid aside all prejudice and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie: So the Reader come to the perusall thereof with like affection. Which I humbly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to doe. And then know, that what you herein finde sound and good, <hi>is Gods;</hi> give him <hi>the glory of it;</hi> what weake and defective, is mine, I acknowledge it; and shall be ready to doe what in <hi>Plato</hi> I am advised. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">Plat. de Rep. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
      </note> not so to like mine owne, but that I will use and yeeld to what others have better &amp; more exact.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.9.</note> The best mā <hi>here knows but in part;</hi> and if each would beare his part without jarring, the musick would be sweet and harmonious. No man can attaine all, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore must not hope in himselfe, nor expect from others an unerring perfection. Wherefore much
<pb facs="4"/>
the rather I am emboldened to intreat, and assure myselfe to finde your Christian love, and favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Candor in the reading and reflecting your thoughts on this treatise, which I earnestly crave of you: and committing it to your perusall and your selfe to Gods blessed guidance; beseech the same God, who is the <hi>God of truth,</hi> to lead us into all truth: who is the <hi>God of peace</hi> to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with us in the way of peace: who is the <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all our good;</hi> during the time of this life to keep us in his feare and favour: and in the life to come to bring us to eternall blisse, purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed for us by <hi>Iesus Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all Christian services, <hi>T. H.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>