<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the same Right Honorable very good Lord, Sir CHRISTOPHER HATTON Knight, Lord high Chancelor of England.</title>
           <author>Harvey, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103904_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02779</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12908</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103904</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the same Right Honorable very good Lord, Sir CHRISTOPHER HATTON Knight, Lord high Chancelor of England.</title>
                 <author>Harvey, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discoursiue probleme concerning prophesies : how far they are to be valued, or credited, according to the surest rules, and directions in diuinitie, philosophie, astrologie, and other learning: deuised especially in abatement of the terrible threatenings, and menaces, peremptorily denounced against the kingdoms, and states of the world, this present famous yeere, 1588, supposed the greatwoonderfull, and fatall yeere of our age. By I.H. physition</title>
                 <author>Harvey, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jackson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Watkins, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 128, 127-133, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the same Right Honorable very good Lord, Sir CHRISTOPHER HATTON Knight, <hi>Lord high Chancelor of England.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing lately in the Epistle to my former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, Right Honorable very good Sir, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged sufficient causes, &amp; incouragements of my presuming to direct that slender Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet vnto your woorthy Lordship: I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose it shall not now againe seeme greatly needfull, either to repeate the same causes, or to annexe any other thereunto: albeit in modest hope of like Honorable fauour, I continue the like boldnes in presenting your Lordship with a Treatise, not much vnlike either for quantitie, or qualitie: Sauing onely, that the very present Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as well in some generall considerations, as in regard of certaine speciall circumstances, both publique and priuate, may respectiuely mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster some reasonable occasion, if not of more fauorable acceptation, yet haply of more inward liking. No man either knoweth better, or can deeplier consider, than your Lordship, how notoriously and perilously the world hath continually from time to time beene abused, and in sort cose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with supposed prophesies, and counterfet soothsayings, deuised either for vnknowen, or for vngracious, and lewd causes: intending at least Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall sturs, but commonly fostering tragicall commotions. Not onely forraine histories, both old and new, in all languages, as well learned, as vulgar: but also our owne British and English Chronicles (as your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship best remembreth;) beside a number of other famous books, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny old smokie paperbookes, are very copious, and ouer plentiful in affoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding examples of this couenous, and imposturall kinde. Amongst which notwithstanding, no examples euer were, or are more dangerous, and ieo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdous, than those, which daily experience both in England, and in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other state or Commonwealth of the world, eftsoones suggesteth; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euery new occasion, strange accident, perilous exigence, or whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer other notable occurrence, againe and againe reuiued, by way of fresh, and currant matter to serue present turnes, and to feede the working hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of busie and tumultuous heads, continually affecting some innouati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or other. But of all the residue, what comparable to the terrible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended prophesie, euen now notoriously in <hi>Esse,</hi> concerning the imagined mightie, and woonderfull casualties and hurliburlies of the present yeere 1588? In which respect of so vniuersall fame, I was earnestly mooued, and importuned by certaine worshipfull Gentlemen, and diuers other my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar friends, to vndertake some little trauell in examining the naturall causes, and artificiall reasons of the said supposed prophesie, so far as any my reading, or vnderstanding might extend, to furnish any such scholler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly insight, or inquitie thereinto. Whereupon at last I was rather ouerru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, than persuaded, to yeeld vnto that motion; partly acknowledging
<pb facs="5"/>
mine owne insufficiencie, partly considering, that I could not any way (to mine owne contentment) discusse that one particular, without some rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable conference of many other semblable particulars, and euen some generall Tract vpon the whole Argument of such putatiue, and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Prophesies. Which very Tract being also at length by them extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by me dispatched, as my present leisure would permit: I am now no lesse instantly requested and sollicited, not onely by the said first moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, but also by certaine other of equall calling, that haue sithence had the perusall thereof in writing, to publish the same with all conuenient expedition: as a Treatise of much publique, and priuate vse at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant. Which albeit my selfe am not any way to acknowledge, otherwise than in affectionate desire to worke what possible good I may, euen with the meaner and baser sort: yet in case your Right Honorable wisedome shall likewise either in whole, or in part admit thereof: I am in all dutie and reuerence, humbly to submit, and wholy to commit the same vnto your onely allowance, or disallowance, to be either published, or suppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed at your Honorable pleasure. A matter in it selfe nothing woorthie so noble, and graue consideration: but as per accident it may happen to stay the wisdoms of some busie, and troublesome persons, not so well disposed, or so discreetly aduised, as might in common respects be wished. Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it I am also wholy to refer euery such circumstance vnto your most Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable determination: whereon I finally relie, as the onely definitiue sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of life, or death vnto this small Treatise. Which accordingly awai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth your good Lordships pleasure and appointment: as also my selfe, to the vttermost of my poore abilitie, am euer to attend your Honorable commandement: euen so for this instant taking my humble leaue, with dutifull recommendation of your Lordship vnto the accustomed fauor of God, who long preserue your most Honorable estate.</p>
   <p>At Kings Lin in Norfolke: this xiiij. of Ianuarie. 1588.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your good Lordships most humble in all dutie,
Iohn Haruey.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>