<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103242_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13126</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23422</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103242</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of tvvelve Cæsars : emperours of Rome: written in Latine by C. Suetonius Tranquillus, and newly translated into English. With a marginall glosse, and other briefe annotations there-upon</title>
                 <author>Suetonius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 272, 39, 1 page, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT yee may with better contentment reade these Historicall reports of the twelve first CEASARS, which SVETONIVS hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered most truely, compiled as compendiously, and digested right methodically; I have thought it good with some few advertisments praemised, to commend the same unto you.</p>
   <p>First therefore, whereas by the iudgement of the best learned, and the Analogie of other Histories, hee seemeth to affect nothing so much as uncorrupt &amp; plaine trueth, (the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall vertue of an Historiographer) for bearing to meddle with those <note n="*" place="margin">Nerv<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>, Traia<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>▪ and Hadri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nus <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> secretarie he wa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Emperours in whose daies he flourished; because he would not thrust himselfe into danger by revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, nor betray the libertie of a writer in concealing the faults; much lesse incurre the note of Flatterie, extolling above measure the good parts of Princes then living; and to that purpose penned their lives, who were lately deceased, as one said very well, <hi>eadem libertate qua ipsi vixerunt:</hi> if happlie in prosecuting of this point, he hath recorded ought that may be offensive to chast and modest mindes, yee shal do well to glaunce over with your eye such places lightly, as I with my pen touched vnwillingly.</p>
   <p>Secondly, for as much as he continueth in generall the Narrations of the said Princes, from before their Nativitie unto their Death &amp; Funerals: and in the severall discourses, of their ages, affaires, vertues, vices, feature &amp; lineaments of bodie, first, after an uniform maner, proposeth throughout certain heads summarily, and then exemplyfieth the same in due order by perticulers (a most lightsome method and way of teaching) keeping him selfe still to the Subiect matter, without any digressions at all: my advise is, that for your more expedite course in reading the whole, yee direct your minde thereunto. Now, for that his IVLIVS CHASAR sorteth not with the rest, but appeareth <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> as whose aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestours, birth, childhoode, &amp;c. be not set downe; (which maime I impute rather to the iniurie of time, than unto the purpose or oversight of the Authour) I have in some sort supplyed that defect, with the labours of LEVVIS VIVES, TORRENTIVS and others, which I finde praefixed in the last and best Editions.</p>
   <p>Thirdly, considering that brevitie is many times the mother of Obscuritie, may it please those among you, who are not so conuersant in such concise writings, as admit not one word superfluous, to have recourse, for the clearing of some doubts unto the margin, as also to those briefe Annotations, which for their sakes, out of mine owne readings, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the select observations of BEROALDVS, SABELLICVS, TORRENTIVS and CASAVBONVS I have collected. Which also will ease them of many difficulties that his succinct style and termes, not elswhere obvious, interlaced, may otherwise breed.</p>
   <p>Finally, if there happen to occur some Errata, that might escape either my pen in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or the ordinarie diligēce of meane Correctors in the printing ye will of your iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious candour, I hope, either passe them over with connivency, if they be literall, or else taxe with some easie censure in case they bee materiall: So long as for your full satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, ye may with small paines before yee begin either to read or iudge, correct what is amisse, according to the Examen and Review annexed to the end of all.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>