<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Morton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103393_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07803</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18181</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103393</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Morton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A direct ansvver vnto the scandalous exceptions, which Theophilus Higgons hath lately obiected against D. Morton : In the which there is principally discussed, two of the most notorious obiections vsed by the Romanists, viz. 1. M. Luthers conference with the diuell, and 2 The sence of the article of Christ his descension into hell</title>
                 <author>Morton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 31, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He speciall occasion of this Answer (Christian Reader) was in thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, lest thou shouldest stumble vpon me, as vpon a <hi>Falsificator,</hi> who professe my selfe a publisher of <hi>truth.</hi> I haue read my Aduersarie his pretended <hi>Motiues,</hi> and haue since also vnderstood of his true motions, which occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to reuolt; and comparing them together, I could not but recken him among the number of that people, who (as histories relate) did first execute men, whom they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Malefactors, and then afterward examined their cause. For if <hi>T. H.</hi> had not first run out in a passion, and afterwards deuised pretext of Reasons, which he calleth his <hi>Motiues,</hi> the law of charitie and of humanitie would haue chalenged him to haue consulted with those Authors whom he doth impugne, with whom the Motioner did then stand in the termes of brotherhood. As for my selfe, I perceiue he hath read my <hi>Apologie,</hi> in which there are many hundreds of testimonies alledged out of the Romish writers, wherein they are found to contradict one another almost in euery question, and to conuince their owne men of manifest slaunders against Protestants, and almost in euery Article to iustifie the grounds of our Religion: out of all which <hi>M. Higgons</hi> hath singled out onely fiue, which (it may seeme) he thought to be more singularly false then
<pb facs="4"/>
any others. These haue I examined, and after due triall am now prouoked to expostulate the matter with my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersarie, as <hi>Iacob</hi> did with <hi>Laban,</hi> saying: <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 3. 1. v. 36. 37.</note>
      <hi>What haue I trespassed, what haue I offended, that thou hast pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued after me? Seeing thou hast searched all my stuffe, what hast thou found</hi> (suffer me to change a word) to charge me withall? <hi>Put it here before thy brethren and mine</hi> (either Protestants or Romanists) <hi>that they may iudge betweene vs both.</hi> I can say no more, but laying open the parcels, wish that the <hi>Brethren of both sides</hi> would iudge betweene vs: &amp; both are in some sort chargi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hereunto, not onely by my Aduersaries chalenge, who intitleth this part of his booke thus, <hi>Trie before you trust;</hi> but much more by the Apostles authoritie, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all men (concerning things of this nature) to <note n="*" place="margin">1. Thess. 5. 21.</note>
      <hi>Trie all things,</hi> and <hi>to keepe that which is good.</hi> The Lord <hi>Iesus</hi> blesse vs, and by his preuenting Grace prepare vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies for a comfortable appearance before him in the great day of <hi>Triall.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy friend and seruant in Christ Iesus,
TH. MORTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>