<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶After the Sermon en∣ded, the Turke confessed in the Spa∣nish tongue before the face of the congregation, the Preacher out of Pulpit propounding the questions and receiuing the answers by skil∣full Interpretors, in summe as fol∣loweth.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1586</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103823_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02614</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12744</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103823</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶After the Sermon en∣ded, the Turke confessed in the Spa∣nish tongue before the face of the congregation, the Preacher out of Pulpit propounding the questions and receiuing the answers by skil∣full Interpretors, in summe as fol∣loweth.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The baptizing of a Turke : A sermon preached at the Hospitall of Saint Katherin, adioyning vnto her Maiesties Towre the 2. of October 1586. at the baptizing of one Chinano a Turke, borne at Nigropontus: by Meredith Hanmer, D. of Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Hanmer, Meredith</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1586</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="text">
   <pb facs="45"/>
   <head>¶After the Sermon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the <hi>Turke</hi> confessed in the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> tongue before the face of the congregation, the Preacher out of Pulpit propounding the questions and receiuing the answers by skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Interpretors, in summe as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</head>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
      <hi>INprimis,</hi> that hee was verie sorie for the sinful life which he had lead in times past, in ignorance and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and hoped to obteine pardon in <hi>Iesus Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, hee renounced <hi>Mahomet</hi> the false Prophet of the <hi>Moores, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racens</hi> and <hi>Turkes,</hi> with al his abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, and blessed GOD which had opened his eyes to beholde the truth in <hi>Iesus Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, hee confessed there was but one God, he beleeued the Trinitie of persons, the Father, the Sonne, &amp; the holy Ghost, and the same to bee one God in vnitie, which is to bee blessed for euer.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly hee confessed and affirmed, that hee beleeued verily, that <hi>Iesus
<pb facs="45"/>
Christ</hi> was and is the sonne of God, &amp; God from euerlasting, the onely true <hi>Messias,</hi> &amp; sauiour of the worlde, that he suffered for the sinnes of al that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him, and that there is no way to be saued, but onely by the merits of the death and passion of <hi>Iesus Christ.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Lastly, he desired hee might be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as one of the faithfull Christians, &amp; bee baptized in the faith of the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Trinitie, promising from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth newnes of life, and fruits accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto this profession.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>¶In the middest of the congregation, there was a comely Table set, couered with a faire linnen cloth, and thereon a Basen with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. After the congregation had blessed God for his great mercies, and after sundry godly Praiers and Collects, according vnto the reuerend order of holye Church, suche as broght him thither, desired his name might be <hi>William,</hi> so was he baptized: <hi>In the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holie Ghost.</hi>
      </hi>
   </p>
   <trailer>Praise be to God.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>