<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader Grace and peace from God. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>W., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103322_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25631</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103322</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader Grace and peace from God. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>W., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vnfouldyng of sundry vntruths and absurde propositions : latelye propounded by one I.B. a greate fauourer of the horrible heresie of the libertimes</title>
                 <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Thomas 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>159, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="2" facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader <hi>Grace and peace from</hi> God. &amp;c.</head>
   <p>THe dayes are dangerous wherein we liue, and the time of the dissolution of all thinges draweth nigh, which maketh Satan by himselfe and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments, dayly more and more to oppose him selfe against the trueth, which if it were not plainely and plentifully prooued by the wonderful swarmes of Atheistes, Epicures, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptists, Pelagians, and the Family of loue, which this our corrupt age doeth vnhappily hatch and ouermuch cherish, yet, by the blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous and wicked assertiōs of this man, in some measure confuted in this booke, we haue an euident demonstration and to plaine a proofe. But as this may in some measure make many slide, to see sundry, fostered in the bosome of the church, who both closely &amp; openly goe about to take hir by the throte so on the other side, this may somewhat cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs, that we may yet behold some passage graunted to the defence of Gods religion, whilest that vnder our godly magistrates, the confutations of such assertious, may be suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="3" facs="2"/>freely to passe, and be published. Wherin it is thy duetie (good reader) not onely to shew thy selfe thankefull to the Lord for this his mercie, but also to vse this and all other holy meanes, to preserue thy selfe safe and sound from this and such like daungerous &amp; deadly infections of thy soule, which that thou mayest the better performe, I beseech thee labour diligently in the worde, be feruēt in prayer vse continuall meditation, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent dayly conference, with them, that be sound and sincere harted to god &amp; his truth, &amp; then no doubt but vsing that meanes that God hath ordeined, thou shalt find his plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful blessing vpon thee &amp; thine, not in know ledge onely but in practise and obedience al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, which God graunt for his Christes sake. At London the xxvii. day of this May 1581.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine euer in Christ Iesus T. W. the Lordes most vnwoorthie</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>