<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HER MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE MARIE BY THE GRACE OF GOD QVEENE OF GREAT BRITAINE, FRANCE, AND IRELAND.</title>
           <author>M., Ch.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1639</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103990_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14664</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17129</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103990</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HER MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE MARIE BY THE GRACE OF GOD QVEENE OF GREAT BRITAINE, FRANCE, AND IRELAND.</title>
                 <author>M., Ch.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A myrrhine posie of the bitter dolours of Christ his passion : and of the seaven vvords he spake on the crosse, composed by Ch. M</title>
                 <author>Kellison, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kellam, Laurence 2</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1639</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>13, 7, 211, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO HER MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE</hi> MARIE BY THE GRACE OF GOD QVEENE OF GREAT BRITAINE, FRANCE, AND IRELAND.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OVR Maiesties Greatnes, Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (descended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you from a King of France,
<pb n="4" facs="4"/> your Father, surnamed Great, from a Great Queene your Noble Mother, from Kinges your Brothers, from Queenes your Sisters, and from the Great Monarch of Great Britaine, an other Charles the Great for his Princelie vertues, whose Beloued Spouse you are) daunteth me, &amp; maketh me afrayd to approach to so great Maiestie with so litle a Present, as is this litle Pamphlet. But your Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitie, affabilitie, yea and Princelie Humilitie, which graceth your Maiestie, and is graced by it; as it hath wonne you the loue of all your Subiectes, euen of them
<pb n="5" facs="4"/> who differ from you in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and hath made you not onelie amiable, but also admirable to all the world: so it encourageth me, and biddeth me be bold, and euen assureth me, that this my Present, though litle and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportionate to your Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, will be Graciouslie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of so Gracious a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, as proportionate at least to your Benignitie and Pietie. My Present, Most Gracious Queene, is a Posie, and not whatsoeuer, but a Myrrhine Posie, gathered out of the Paradise and Garden of Christ his sacred Passion, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed of the bitter sorrowes
<pb n="6" facs="5"/> and dolours he suffered for vs and of the words also h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> spake on the Crosse: Of whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Posie, if your Maiestie vouch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>safe to smell by your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed and deuout Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, the verie smell will be Soueraigne for your soule, and will chase away all the euill odours of whatsoeuer euill tentations. Other Myrrhe preserueth our bodies from putrefaction; this Myrrhe will preserue the soule from all corruption of Sinne. This Myrrhine Posie of Christ his Dolours, your Maiesties pietie will daine to place in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some and breast of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout Soule, and your Blessed
<pb n="7" facs="5"/> Sauiour with it; that you may say with the Spouse in the Canticles: <hi>A Bundle of Myrrhe, my beloued is to me, he shall abide betweene my breasts.</hi> God Almightie, who hath endowed your Maiestie with many guifts of Grace and nature; who hath giuen you such Constancie in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Fayth, that amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest many contrarie winds of Doctrine, you haue not beene so much as shaken; VVho hath conserued you pure <hi>as a Lillie amongest thornes;</hi> VVho hath blessed you with a Royall Issue, which, though as yet it be younge and litle, is no litle strength to
<pb n="8" facs="6"/> the Kingdome: He, I say blesse your Maiestie, and ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Noble King Great Charles your deare Spouse, with Grace Peace, and Prosperitie, in you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Kingdome of Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and with Glorie, and Eternall Peace, and Felicitie in the Kingdome of Heauen. This is, and this euer shall be the prayer of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>YOVR MAIESTIES. <hi>Most Humble and Obedient Subiect</hi> CH. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>