<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THOSE HONOVRED, NO∣BLE, AND RIGHT Vertuous Friends, my Visi∣tants in the Marshalsey: AND, TO ALL OTHER, MY VNKNOWNE FAVOVRITES, who eyther piuately, or publiquely wished me well in my imprisonment.</title>
           <author>Wither, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103319_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15656</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25920</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103319</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THOSE HONOVRED, NO∣BLE, AND RIGHT Vertuous Friends, my Visi∣tants in the Marshalsey: AND, TO ALL OTHER, MY VNKNOWNE FAVOVRITES, who eyther piuately, or publiquely wished me well in my imprisonment.</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The shepherds hunting : being, certaine eglogs written during the time of the authors imprisonment in the Marshalsey. By George VVither, gentleman</title>
                 <author>Wither, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Norton, George</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>124 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THOSE HONOVRED, NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE, AND RIGHT Vertuous Friends, my Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in the <hi>Marshalsey:</hi> AND, TO ALL OTHER, MY VNKNOWNE FAVOVRITES, who eyther piuately, or publiquely wished me well in my imprisonment.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble Friends: you whose vertues made me first in loue with <hi>Vertue:</hi> and whose worths, made mee be thought worthy of your loues. I haue now at last (you see) by Gods
<pb facs="3"/>
assistance and your encouragement, runne through the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>rgatory</hi> of imprisonment: and by the worthy fauour of a iust <hi>PRINCE,</hi> stand free againe, without the lea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>t touch of deiected base<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Seeing therefore I was growne beyond my <hi>Hope</hi> so fortunate, (after acknowledgement of my Creators loue, together with the vnequall'd Clemency of so gracious a Soueraigne) I was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to thinke by what meanes I might expresse my thankfulnesse to so many well-deseruing friends: No way I found to my desire; neyther yet abilitie to performe when I found it. But at length conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with my selfe what you were, (that is) such, who fauour honestie for no second reason but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause you your selues are good; and ayme at no other
<pb facs="3"/>
reward but the witnesse of a sound conscience that you doe well, I found that thankfulnesse would proue the acceptablest present to sute with your dispositions; and that I imagined could be no way better expressed then in manifesting your cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesies, and giuing consent to your reasonable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. For the first, I confesse (with thankes to the disposer of all things, and a true gratef<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ll heart towards you,) so many were the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected visitations and vnhoped kindnesses re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued both from some among you of my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and many other vnknowne Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>illers of my Cause, that I was perswaded to entertaine a much better conceit of the <hi>Time</hi> then I lately conceiued, and assured my selfe that
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>VERTVE</hi> had farre more followers then I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed.</p>
   <p>Somewhat it disturbed mee to behold our ages Fauourites, whilst they frowned on my honest en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises, to take vnto their protections the egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giousts fopperics: yet much more was my content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nt, in that I was respected by so many of <hi>You,</hi> amongst whom there are some, who can and may as much dis-esteeme these, as they neglect me: nor could I feare their malice or contempt, whilst I enioyed your fauours, who (howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you are vnder-valued by fooles for a time) shall leaue vnto your post<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ritie so noble a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, that your names shall be reuerenced by Kings, when many of these who now flourish with
<pb facs="4"/>
a shew of vsurped <hi>Greatnesse,</hi> shall eyther weare out of beeing, or dispoyled of all their patched re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, grow contemptible in the eyes of their beloued Mistresse the <hi>World.</hi> Your <hi>Loue.</hi> is is that (enabling mee with patience to endure what is already past) hath made mee (also) carefull better to prepare my selfe for all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture misaduentures, by bringing to my considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what the passion, of my iust discontentments had almost quite banished from my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</p>
   <p>Further, to declare my thankefulnesse, in making app<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rant my willing minde to be commanded in any seruices of loue, which you shall thinke fit (though I want abilitie to performe great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters)
<pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="8"/>
yet I haue according to some of your requests beene contented to giue way to the printing of these <hi>Eglogues,</hi> which thoug<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> it to many seeme a sleight matter, yet being well considered of, may proue a strong argument of my readinesse to gi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e you content in a greater matter: for they being (as you well kn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>w) begotten with little care, and preserued with lesse respect, gaue suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>idence that I meant (rather then any way to deceiue your trust) to giue the world oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of calling my discretion in question, as I now assure my selfe This will: and the sooner, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause such expectations (I perceiue) there are of I know not what <hi>Inuentions,</hi> as would haue beene frustrated though I had employed
<pb facs="8"/>
the vtmost and very best of my endeuours.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding, for your sakes, I haue here ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured once againe to make tryall of the w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rlds censures: and what hath receiued <hi>beeing,</hi> from your <hi>Loues,</hi> I here rededicated to your <hi>Worths,</hi> which if your noble dispositions will like well of: Or if you will but reasonab<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>y respect what your selues drew mee vnto, I shall be nothing displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed at others cauils, but resting my selfe contented with your good opinions, scorne all the rabble of vncharitable detractors: For none I know will maligne it except those, who eyther particularly malice my person, or professe th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>mselues enemies to my former Bookes; who (sauing those that were incensed on others speeches) as diuers of you (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb facs="9"/>
to your protestations) haue obserued, are eyther open enemies of our Church; men notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously guilty of some particular Abuses therein t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>xt, such malicious <hi>Crittickes</hi> who haue the repute of being indicious, by detracting from others; or at best such Guls, as neuer approue any thing good, or learned, but eyther that which their shallow ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions can apply to the soothing of their owne opinions, or what (indeede rather) they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand not.</p>
   <p>Trust me, how ill soeuer it hath beene rewarded, my loue to my Country is inviolate: my thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse to you vnfayned, my endeuour to doe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man good; all my ayme content with honestie: and this my paines (if it may be so tearmed) more
<pb facs="9"/>
to auoid idlenes, then for affectation of praise: an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> if notwithstanding all thir, I must yet, not onel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> rest my selfe content that my innocency hath esc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> ped with strict imprisonment (to the impayring <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> my state, and hinderance of my fortunes) but al<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> be constrayned to see my guiltlesse lines, suffer th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> despight of ill tongues: yet for my further enco<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> ragement, let mee entreat the continuance <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> your first respect, wherein I shall finde that com fort as will be sufficient to make mee set light an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> so much contemne all the malice of my aduersaries that ready to burst with the venome of their own<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> hearts, they shall see</p>
   <lg>
      <l>My Minde enamoured on faire <hi>Vertues</hi> light</l>
      <l>Ascends the limits of their bleared sight,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="10"/>And plac'd aboue their <hi>Enuy,</hi> doth contemne,</l>
      <l>Nay, sit and laugh at their disdaine and them.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>But <hi>Noble Friends,</hi> I make question neyther of yours, nor any honest mans respect, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will no further vrge it, nor trouble your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: onely this Ile say, that you may not thinke <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e too well conceited of my selfe; though the <hi>Time</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ere to blame in ill requiting my honest endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ours, which in the eyes of the world deserued <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>etter, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>et somewhat I am assured there was in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ee worthy that punishment which when God shall <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>iue mee grace to see and amend, I doubt not but <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>o finde that regard as will be fitting for so much <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>erit as my labours may iustly challenge. Meane
<pb facs="10"/>
while, the better to hold my selfe in esteeme with you, and amend the worlds opinion of <hi>Vertue,</hi> I will study to amend my selfe, that I may be yet more worthy to be called</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Friend,
GEO. WYTHER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>