<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the READER.</title>
           <author>Harris, R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103816_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B13906</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12853</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103816</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the READER.</title>
                 <author>Harris, R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo sermons: the one preached before the iudges of assize at Oxford. The other to the Vniversitie. By Robert Harris</title>
                 <author>Harris, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bartlet, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 26, 6, 29-66 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue been long pressed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triue many Sermons (of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science) into one discourse, and to annex thereto some Cases for an Essay. I haue thought a little of the motion; but finding my selfe partly preuented by my betters, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intercepted by more pressing occasions, I giue vp; onely thus farre I haue yeelded, namely, That my rude notes should bee scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and in case they shall be deemed of any vse, then to bee published vntranscribed. Some of them haue passed (it seemes) the censure, and are now vnder view; touching which, vnderstand thus much; First, that these two elder were preached in the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity, and addressed to the then Auditory and occasion. Secondly, that I haue vnderhand, (vpon the same and other texts) other Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meas, which (haply) may more comply with
<pb facs="4"/>thine estate and temper, if so, it is at thy li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to leaue these, and to whit those, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I shall haply expresse more fully what in the Assize Sermon time and importunity made mee forbeare. Thirdly, that I haue no conueniency of writing much at home, or of seeing any thing printed abroad, and therefore if things be not all out to thy mind, diuide the blame betwixt the Printer and importunity. I haue no more to say but this; Compare <hi>Iudas</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> together, marke the ones misery, the others confidence, and accordingly make thy conclusion.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in Christ, <hi>R. HARRIS.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>