<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ANSWER
TO THE LETTER.</title>
           <author>Misakmos, </author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103861_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02649</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12779.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103861</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ANSWER
TO THE LETTER.</title>
                 <author>Misakmos, </author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A nevv discovrse of a stale svbiect, called the metamorphosis of Aiax : vvritten by Misacmos, to his friend and cosin Philostilpnos</title>
                 <author>Harington, John, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 120 pages, illustrations, music, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE ANSWER
TO THE LETTER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y good Cosin, if you haue heard
so well of my poore house with
the apurtenaunces, it were to be
wished for preseruation of your
better conceit thereof; that you
would not see them at all, they will seeme to
you so far short of the report: for I do compare
my buildings and my writings together, in
which though the common sort thinke there
is some worth and witte, yet the grauer Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surers
do finde many faults and follies; And
no maruell for he that builds and hath gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
litle, and writes and hath read litle, must
needes be a bad builder, and a worse writer.
But wher as you are disposed either in the way
of praise, or of play, to extoll so much the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest
roome of my house, as though you prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
it afore the best; your commendation is
not much vnlike his curtesie, that being inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by a crabbed-fauourd host to a neat house,
did spit in his hostes face, because it was the
fowlest part of the house. But such as I haue
you shall be welcome to, and if I may know
<pb facs="5"/>
when you will begin your progresse, I will pray
my brother to be your guide, who will direct
your iestes in such sort, as first you shall come
by a fine house that lackes a mistresse, then
to a faire house that mournes for a maister,
from whence, by a straight waie called the
<hi>force</hi> way, you shall come to a towne that is
more then a towne, where be the waters that
be more then waters. But from thence you
shall passe downe a streame that seemes to be
no streame by corn fields that seeme no fields,
downe a street no street, in at a gate no gate o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
a bridge no bridge, into a court no court,
where if I be not at home, you sall finde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
a foole no foole.</p>
   <p>But where as you praise my husbandry, you
make me remember an old schoole fellow of
mine in Cambridge, that hauing lost fiue shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
abroad at Cardes, would boast he had sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
two candels at home by being out of his
chamber, for such be most of my sauings. Yet
this one point of husbandrie, though it maie
well be called beggerly: yet it is not for all that
contemptible, &amp; thus it was. Finding a faire
and flat field, though verie stonie, as all this
countrey is: I made some vagrant beggers (of
which by neighbourhood of the Bathes, here
<pb facs="5"/>
comes great store) to gather all the stones that
might breake our arrowes, and finding an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie
meane to water the ground with a fat wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
I haue bettered my ground (as you say) and
quite rid me of my wandring guests, who will
rather walk seuen mile about, thē come where
they shall be forst to worke one halfe houre.</p>
   <p>Now Sir, to come to the chiefe point of your
desire, which requires a more ample answer,
but for a preamble you must be content with
this. You tell me, belike to encourage me, that
my inuention maie be beneficiall, not onely to
my priuate friends, but to townes and Cities,
yea euen to her Maiesties seruice for some of
her houses: trust me I doe beleeue you write
seriouslie as you terme it herein, and for my
part I am so wholly addicted to her hignesse
seruice, as I would be glad, yea euen proud, if
the highest straine of my wit, could but reach,
to anie note of true harmonie in the full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort
of her Maiesties seruice, though it were
in the basest key that it could be tuned to.
And if I should fortune to effect so good a
reformation, in the Pallace of Richmond, or
Greenewich (to which Pallace, manie of vs
owe seruice for the tenure of our land) I doubt
not but some pleasāt witted courtier of either
<pb facs="6"/>
sex<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> would grace me so much at least; as to say,
that I were worthy for my rare inuētion, to be
made one of the Priuy (and after a good long
parenthesis) come out with chamber, or if they
be learned &amp; haue read <hi>Castalios Courtier,</hi>
they will say, I am a proper scholer, and well
seene in <hi>latrina lingua.</hi> But let them mocke
that list, <hi>qui moccat moccabitur.</hi>
   </p>
   <l>Who strike with sword, the scabbeted them may strike:</l>
   <l>And sure loue eraueth loue, like asketh like.</l>
   <p>If men of iudgement thinke it may breede
a publike benefite, the conceit thereof shall
expell all priuate bashfulnesse; and I will
herein follow the example of that noble La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
that to saue the liberties of Couentry, rode
naked at noone through the streetes thereof,<note place="margin">Camden in his Britānia.</note>
and is now thought to be greatly honored, and
nothing shamed thereby.</p>
   <p>Further whereas you embolden my pen,
not to be abasht at the basenesse of the subiect
and as it were leading me on the way, you tell
me you haue broken the y<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e for me, to enter me
into such broad phrases, as you thinke must
be frequent herein: I will follow your steppes
and your counsell, neither will I disdaine to
vse the poore helpe of saue reuerence if neede
be, much like as a good friend of yours and
<pb facs="6"/>
mine, that beginning to dispraise as honest
a man as him selfe, to a great Noble man,
said, he is the veryest knaue, sauing your
Lordship: But the noble man (ere the wordes
were fully out of his mouth,) said, saue thy self
knaue or be hangd, saue not me. Euen so I must
write in this discourse, sometime indeede as
homely (sauing your vvorship) as you shall
lightly see, and yet I will endeuour to keepe me
within the boundes of modestie, and vse no
wordes, but such as graue presidents in Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,
Law, Phisicke, or good Ciuilitie, will
sufficiently warrant me.</p>
   <p>Sure I am that many other country<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>men,
both Dutch, French, and Italians, with great
praise of wit, though small of modesty, haue
writtē of worse matters. One writes in praise
of folly. 2. an other in honour of the Pox. 3. a
third defendes vsury. 4. a fourth commends
Nero. 5. a fift extols and instructs bawdery.
6. the sixt displaies and describes <hi>Puttana
Errante,</hi> which I here will come forth short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in English. 7. a seuenth (whom I would
guesse by his writing,<note place="margin">This matter is discoursed by Rables, in his 13. chap. of his fift booke.</note> to be groome of the
stoole to some Prince of the bloud in France)
writes a beastly treatise, only to examin what
is the fittest thing to wipe withall, alledging
<pb facs="7"/>
that white paper is too smooth, browne paper
too rough, wollen cloth too stiffe, linnen cloth
too hollow, satten too slippery, taffeta too thin,
veluet too thicke, or perhaps too costly: but he
concludes, that a goose necke to be drawne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
the legs against the fethers,<note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> moyē de me torcher le culle plus Seigneurial, le plus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, le plus expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent que ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mais fut veu.</note> is the most
delicate and cleanely thing that may be. Now
it is possible that I may be reckned after these
seuen, as <hi>sapientum octauus,</hi> because I will
write of A Iakes yet I will challenge of right
(if the Heralds should appoint vs our places)
to go before this filthy fellow, for as according
to Aristotle, a ryder is an <hi>Architectonicall</hi>
science to a sadler, and a sadler to a stirop ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker
&amp;c. so my discourse must needes be Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectonicall
to his, sith I treat of the house it
self, and he but of part of that is to be done in
the house, &amp; that no essentiall part of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse:
<q>for they say there be three things that
if one neglect to do them,<note place="margin">This may be omitted in reading.</note> they will do them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues;
one is for a man to make euen his reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,
for who so neglects it will be left euen
iust nothing; as other is to mary his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
for if the parents bestow them not, they
will bestow them selues; the third is that,
which the foresaide French man writes of:
which they that omit, their lawndresses shall
<pb facs="7"/>
finde it done in their linnen. VVhich mishap
a faire Lady once hauing, a seruing mā of the
disposition of Mydas Barber, that could not
kepe coūsell had spyed it, &amp; wrate in the gros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest
termes it could be exprest, vppon a wall,
what he had seen, but a certaine pleasant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited
Gentleman, corrected the barbarisme,
adding rime to the reason in this sort.</q>
   </p>
   <l>
      <q>My Ladie hath polluted her lineall vesture,</q>
   </l>
   <l>
      <q>With the superfluitie, of her corporall disgesture.</q>
   </l>
   <p>But soft, I feare I giue you too great a tast
of my slouenly eloquence, in this sluttish argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
VVherefore to conclude, I dare vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take,
that though my discourse will not be so
wise as the first of those seuen I spake of, that
praises folly: yet it shall be ciuiller then the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,
truer then the third, honester then the
fourth: chaster thē the sift, modester then the
sixt, and clenlier then the seuenth. And that
you and other of my good friends may take the
lesse offence at it, I will cloth it (like an Ape
in purple,) that it may be admitted into the
better cōpany: and if all the art I haue cannot
make it mannerly enough, the worst punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt
it can haue, is but to employ it in the house
it shall treat of, only crauing but that fauour,
that a noble man was wont to request of your
<pb facs="8"/>
good father in law, to teare out my name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
it be so employed; and to him that would
deny me that kindnesse, I would the paper
were nettles, and the letters needles for his
better ease: or that it were like to the Friers
booke, dedicated as I take it to <hi>Pius quintus;</hi>
of which one writes merily, that his holinesse
finding it was good for nothing else, imployed
it (in steed of the goose necke) to a homely oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation,
and forsooth the phrase was so rude,
the stile so rugged, and the Latin so barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,
that therewith as he writes, <hi>scortigauit
sedem Apostolicam.</hi> He galled the seat A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolicke:
and so I commend me to you, till
I send you the whole discourse.</p>
   <signed>Your louing cosin and true friend.
MISAKMOS.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>