<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[To The Reader]</title>
           <author>Hart, Ames</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103826_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68143</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12887a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103826</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[To The Reader]</title>
                 <author>Hart, Ames</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The anatomie of vrines : Containing the conuiction and condemnation of them. Or, the second part of our discourse of vrines. Detecting and vnfolding the manifold falshoods and abuses committed by the vulgar sort of practitioners, in the iudgement of diseases by the vrines onely: together with a narrow suruey of their substance, chiefe colours, and manifold contents, ioyning withall the right vse of vrines. ... Collected, as well out of the ancient Greeke, Latine, and Arabian authors, as out of our late famous physitians of seuerall nations: their authorities quoted and translated out of the originall tongues, together with some of the authors owne obseruations. By Iames Hart of Northampton. Neuer heretofore published</title>
                 <author>Hart, James, of Northampton</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 127, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <p>of vrines, to wit, such as do decline from any one extreame,
what concerneth the same, may easily, by that which hath
bene said of the same extreame, be vnderstood. Now if any
shall enquire what is the cause I spend so much time about
this subiect: I answer, it is by reason of the old inueterate o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,
or rather errour, which most people haue conceiued
concerning this strumpet; whom for this cause I haue here
vnmasked, and layed open to the view of euery one that will
not shut his eyes in the cleare Sunne-shine; and that to the
end that none may be circumuented by the fraud and coze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
of such as abuse her for their owne benefit. But lest any
should imagine these things to be but fancies fetcht from
mine owne braine, therefore not contented to set down mine
owne positiue opinion, I haue both backt, fortified and flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
it with the bulwarks of the best writers of ancient and
later times, whose owne words I haue truly translated, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting
thee likewise, learned Reader, to the marginall quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
where for thy recreation and better satisfaction, not
the names of the authors onely, and the particular places, but
the very words of the originall are often set downe, that so
it may more euidently appeare, that this latter iurie finds her
guiltie, as the former great enquest after the inditement
found <hi>Billa vera.</hi> The condemnation must then of necessitie
follow, since the parties offending hauing had these three last
assizes allowed them to pleade for themselues, haue said no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.
This sentence I referre to this<note n="*" place="margin">The hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Court of Parliament.</note> sage assembly, who, as
I hope, will take this publicke businesse, as a matter of no small
moment, into their serious considerations. But me thinkes I
heare some say, what is then the vse of vrines in discerning
of diseases? or serueth it for no vse at all? I answer, that so
farre am I from abrogating this so ancient and necessarie
a signe, receiued by all our ancient and late writers, which
I do highly esteeme, and account of the same being rightly
<pb facs="3"/>
vsed, howbeit as it is commonly vsed, it is most shamefully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused.</p>
   <p>The right vse of vrine then is,<note place="margin">The right vse of vrines.</note> together with all the rest
of the signes and seuerall circumstances of the disease (in
such diseases I meane where it is of any force or validitie, in
some diseases being of no vse at all) to giue vs notice of the
nature, together with the changes and alterations, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
what is like to be the issue of the same. The Physitian is
therefore first to enquire diligently into the nature of the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease,
together with all the other signes and circumstances
thereof: and then, comparing all together, to giue forth his
best and most assured iudgeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t.<note place="margin">Foolish custom of the countrey people.</note> Most foolish therefore and
absurd is the sottish custome of the countrey people now a
dayes, bringing the vrine to the Physitian, it may be in some
old oylie or inkie bottle, and then to demand of him as of some
<hi>Delphian oracle,</hi> the whole nature of the disease, the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents
age, and diuerse other things wherewith they ought to
acquaint vs, as also with all the other signes and circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of the disease: euen as the client is to lay open his cause to
the Lawyer, how learned soeuer, and skilfull in his profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.
It is yet not vnworthie the obseruation, that one and the
same vrine hath often diuers and seuerall significations, and
therefore vnlesse by diuerse other signes and circumstances
limited, can neuer affoord vs any certaintie, as hereafter
both in the colours and contents the ensuing discourse shall
make manifest. And thus may the right vse to the wise and
vnderstanding easily appeare; especially to such as haue bene
or yet shall hereafter be admitted vnto such mysteries. And
therefore ignorant Empiricks, women, and many other such,
haue no share or interest in these affaires, as not being able to
diue into the depth of the premisses. And as for cleargie men,
they cannot be ignorant, that they ought to be employed about
businesses of an higher nature. And if they will haue a care
<pb facs="3"/>
of the soules entrusted to them, they need not trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
with their bodies. Now that one signe, in some disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
onely to be obserued to be of any vse, should with a Papall
prerogatiue assume all authoritie vnto it selfe, is both against
common sense,<note place="margin">The pulse in many diseases to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the vrine.</note> daily experience, and the authorities of the
learned. The pulse will pleade for a preheminence aboue the
vrine: and to iudge of this, as of a number of other signes,
it will of necessitie require the Physitians presence. Now
that the vrines in many diseases, and those of vndoubted
danger, do often shew thee no more then the ground thou go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est on;
and that many other signes besides are of necessitie to
be obserued, hath bene at great length related in the former
tractate, and shall yet more plainly and particularly in this
which followeth appeare. And for thy more particular infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,
I haue set downe the seuerall significations of vrines,
and that according to the opinions of such Authors as haue
written of them; together with some particulars which haue
neuer yet bene published by any English writer that I haue
as yet seene, as by the contents of the bookes and chapters may
appeare. Some things also which haue bene by others written
and auouched for vncontrolled truths, I haue confuted as
false and erronious: and that, as I thinkt, by vnanswerable
arguments, illustrating the same with varietie of ancient
and recent authorities, together with plentie of pertinent
examples, being true historicall relations, obserued both by my
selfe and other Authors: the which howsoeuer they do not
simply proue; yet do they not a little illustrate the matter in
hand, and make it more perspicuous to the meaner sort. Now
whereas I sometimes insert something of the ignorance and
vnsufficiencie of some offenders, some may, perhaps, reply,
that it may sometimes befall a good Physitian to faile as well
as any of them. I confesse Indeed, <hi>Bernardus non videt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia:
He is a good horse that neuer stumbled.</hi> Neuer to
<pb facs="4"/>
faile is a priuiledge denyed to any of the ofspring of sinfull
Adam:<note place="margin">Quand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>que b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus dormitat H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus. Horat.</note> howbeit the learned Physitian building vpon rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
and experience, keepeth alwayes an orderly and metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall
course in all his proceedings: and if he may sometimes
erre (as being a man and not a God) how much more then an
ignorant Empiricke, a shee-Physitian (such a one as now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
in Northamptonshire, and in whom I wonder that any
that hath any braines in his head can see any sufficiencie)
that I say nothing of a medling Minister that neuer was
trained vp in that profession; shall they I say be obnoxious to
error in so intricate an Art, wherein they haue no interest,
as being meere vsurpers vpon other mens right? Besides, the
vulgar not being able to iudge of the sufficiencie of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
Physitian, preferreth often the paines of some ignorant
Empiricke, (soothed vp it may be by the successe of some ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall
cure) before the labors of the most learned &amp; honest ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist.
But my meaning is here of an ordinary erronious course
of practising, euē against the rules of art, &amp; the very grounds
&amp; principles of this physicall profession. Of such errors I could
haue set downe a multitude, besides those few which I had
by relation, either from the patients themselues, or else from
some of their most familiar friends and acquaintances, who
haue protested, that they will be readie to iustifie the same vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
their oathes.<note place="margin">Casuall cures sometimes suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, do not proue a suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ies thus practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ing.</note> Neither yet let this suffice, that some of their
proctors pleade for them a number of happy and successefull
euents; since that thus we may often magnifie the most vile
wizard, and most ignorant old wife in the countrey: this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
taken from issue and euent being a meere Paralo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gisme,
a fallacie and deceit, taking that often for a true
cause which is no cause indeed, as in the conclusion of this
discourse shall more plainly appeare. And in this I appeale to
the learned and honest Artist, not to such a persons parasite,
who taketh for good and current coyne what soeuer commeth
<pb facs="4"/>
out of his mint, nor yet their otherwise honest, yet in this
point, too partiall patients, in this particular blinded with
the mist of ignorance, or a preiudicate opinion of such mens
supposed sufficiencie, they themselues not being able herein
to discerne betwixt right and wrong.</p>
   <p>Now that this hath bene no<note n="a" place="margin">An vsual &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ie custome to browbeat &amp; ouerthrow er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture, and to pleade for truth.</note> vnusuall custome to brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat
and ouerthow errors, euen in this profession, and for the
maintaining of truth to pleade against imposture, might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily,
as well by ancient as later authorities, be euinced, which
would be too tedious here to relate. But amongst many, one
late writer I cannot passe by (the learned <hi>Libauius</hi> I meane)
who hath wrestled with many such monsters; as namely <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelius,
Hartmannus, Scheunemannus,</hi> the impudent
Priest <hi>Gramau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s,</hi> and that famous, I meane infamous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postor
<hi>Ambaldus,</hi> author of that counterfeit<note n="b" place="margin">This Panacaea was a certaine medicine made of saffron, quick siluer, vermili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, antimonie, and certaine sea shels made vp in fashion of trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular lozenges, stamped and sealed with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine strange characters, and sold at a very deare rate, the very name im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting asmuch as a medicine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses; and was in as great, or greater esteeme among the Germanes, as euer Aurum potabile once here amongst our selues. <hi>Liban contra Ambald &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fens. syntagm. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>can. chym. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Henuingum Scheunem.</hi>
      </note> Panacea, like
our <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> supposed good against most, if not all
infirmities; who notwithstanding, for his ignorance not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
able to vndergo the triall and examination of the Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians
of the Citie of Ausburg, was most iustly by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state
banished the same, and so his fame after a while turned
to fume or smoke. And haue we not of late dayes had here
at home<note n="c" place="margin">D. Gwin. &amp; D. Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>igh <hi>against</hi> aurum potabile, D. Cotta <hi>against this and diuers ignorant erronious practisers.</hi>
      </note> some maintainers of truth and opposers of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture,
some liuing euen at this day? And against this same
abuse in particular, besides <hi>Forest, Euritius Cordus</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished
in Latine a learned booke: so did likewise <hi>Guilielmus
Adolphus Scribonius,</hi> the learned <hi>Langius</hi> in some of his
Epistles, and many others also, as hereafter shall appeare. But
I am not ignorant, that whosoeuer will publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sh any thing in
this last and learned age, cannot chuse but vndergo the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
of many iudges, as witnesseth the worthie<note n="d" place="margin">Hieron epist. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>32. partis tertia referente Langio.</note>
      <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>erome.</hi>
Some will perhaps say the stile is too meane and plaine: and
others, if there were any elegancie in it, would cry out, he
<pb facs="5"/>
playes the Orator (perhaps odious in handling vrines) not
the Physitian. And some preoccupied with a partiall and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicate
opinion, like the diseased of some cholericke feauer,
to whō the sweetest things seeme bitter: so whatsoeuer fruite
groweth in some mens gardens, be it neuer so good, will giue
no content to some mens ouer curious &amp; nice relishes: so hard
a thing is it to practise this one point, <hi>Omnibus placeto.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Howsoeuer, kinde Reader, if thou come with a desire to
submit thy selfe to the rules of reason, to haue thy iudgement
rectified if erronious, and with an earnest desire to be fully
informed of the truth, let not my labour be lost, but peruse,
I pray thee, this tractate, wherein thou mayest perhaps finde
something for thy satisfaction. And howsoeuer, perhaps, the
cookerie may not giue thee full content, yet remember the
matter is but meane, in the which I haue had a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
to the matter it selfe, then to the curious manner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering
the same; and a greater care to satisfie the simplest
vnderstandings (for whose cause I haue principally pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished
these may paines) then with the ornaments of an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
to please the eares of the most learned. <hi>Optimum condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum
fames: A good appetite needeth no sauce.</hi> The
Germanes in diuerse places of Saxony, in stead of currants
bake their cakes with blacke Poppy seeds: and in stead of
stewed broth boyle wilde or horse radishes with their beefe.
The French findeth a good rellish in his soure sauces: and a
Spaniard maketh often as great account of a Lemmon, as an
English man of a pecce of powdered beefe. Whatsoeuer it is,
and howsoeuer liked, yet my principall purpose was and is to
profit the publicke. If I should pleade a priuiledge from back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters,
and immunitie from malignant tongues, I should su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
for that which hath bene denyed the greatest and worthiest
personages of ancient and later times. And some varlets
haue bene found, who would rather fire the famous temple of
<pb facs="5"/>
Diana, then not minister matter to talke of them. And as for
my selfe, I deny not but I shall find some of the offenders here
mentioned, who will snarle and grumble at my so plaine and
vnpartiall reprouing of their faults. Some, who should haue
shewed better example, conscious to themselues of their owne
guiltinesse, haue broken the ice already, &amp; as I am informed,
haue much repined at the Preface of my former tractate.<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 18. 23.</note>
      <hi>If I
haue spoken euill be are witnesse of the euill: but if well,
why smitest thou me?</hi> If they can iustifie their actions, let
them publish their apologie, and let the Reader iudge. But if
they can do nothing else but maligne other mens labours, and
themselues loyter, I wish them to be filent.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Carpere vel noli nostra vel ede tua.<note place="margin">Martia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Bring forth thy birth, or barke not thus at mine.</l>
   </q>
   <p>But all they can say, moueth me no more then the barking
of a dog, or the yelping of a foxe, as knowing that,</p>
   <q>
      <l>Obsequium amicos, veritas odium parit.<note place="margin">Terent.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Flatterie gets friends, but truth oft enuie finds.</l>
   </q>
   <p>It is for thy sake therefore, kind and vnpartiall reader, who
hast learned to value vertue at her highest worth, that I haue
vndertaken this taske: which I acknowledge to be so far frō
perfection, that I confesse I haue but with a rude pencill pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed
out the lineaments of this picture, giuing hereby fit op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
to some cunning <hi>Apelles</hi> to perfect the same here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.
<hi>Homo sum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Terent.</note>
      <hi>humani à me nihil alienū puto:</hi> A man
I am, and as all the sonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> subiect to error. <hi>But let
the righteous reproue me,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 141. 5.</note>
      <hi>it shall be as a precious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and shall not hurt my head.</hi> So intreating thy pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
to take these my paines in good part, not to be too sharpe
and censorious, nor yet too open eared to hearken to enuious
inuectiue speeches of any whose sores are here lanced, and to
keepe one eare open for thy friends iust apologie, I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy euer vnfained, well-wishing friend, a fauourer of the
publicke good, and a profest enemie to all fraud and
imposture,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>AMES HART.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>