<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
GAVDIVM POPVLI, HVMILIME CON∣SECRATVM REGI: COR PLEBIS
</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103504_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14755</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17148.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103504</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
GAVDIVM POPVLI, HVMILIME CON∣SECRATVM REGI: COR PLEBIS
</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Three treatises religiously handled : and named according to the seuerall subiect of each treatise: The mourning weede. The mornings joy. The kings reioycing. Published by R.M. minister of Gods word. Perused and allowed</title>
                 <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 48 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="15"/>
   <pb facs="15"/>
   <head>
      <figure>
         <head>GAVDIVM POPVLI, HVMILIME CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SECRATVM REGI: COR PLEBIS</head>
      </figure>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost noble and renowned king, most deare and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted soueraigne, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was this sage sentēce <hi>Happie is that realme where either Philosophers be Kings, or kings philosophers,</hi> more truly verified then at this time; nor neuer had nation more need then we the people of this land, duly to cōsider of it, in al thāk fulnes towards God, and in all loue and loyaltie towards your Maiestie.</p>
   <p>The consideration whereof hath euen compelled mee (the vnworthiest of your Graces ministerie) to compile, though in a most rude and ill-digested sort, (either for
<pb facs="16"/> want of leysure, or learning, or both) this present pamphlet, sprowting forth into three braunches, carrying their titles accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the chiefe argument, or subiect whereupon they are framed.</p>
   <p>The middle braunch (wherevpon ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue vseth to rest) drawing her sweetest sap from you our singular good soueraigne, and therefore as due to your Maiestie, (not in my name, that am altogither vnworthy to be named) but in the name and behalfe of all the ioyfull subiects of our <hi>Deuonian</hi> Countrey or Shire; the same is presented, (an vnworthie present truely for a king) to the most leasurable pervsing (if at least euer there may be leysure allotted to looke vpon it) and to the princely protection of your gracious fauour: the rather, for that your grace is not onely a fauourer, but a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto all those that seeke by any means (how simple soeuer) to further the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Gospell.</p>
   <p>Most humbly praying your royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie, fauorably to passe ouer al the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
<pb facs="16"/> of this rough and vnfiled worke, pardoning the workman for his loue and loyalties sake; and finally to receyue this poore mite, of a ministers good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, into the treasury of your noble mind; among the rich iewels of the learneder sort of this land, that either are, or may be offered: nor for the repairing, but for the comforting &amp; refreshing of you our king, &amp; vnder God vnto vs a most sacred sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie. Beseeching the supreme Maiesty, who sitteth in the mercie seate, in <hi>sancto sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> betweene the Cherubims, to blesse your highnesse with a glorious raigne, and to make the people of all your Graces Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, zealous, thankful, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient subiects, first to God, next to your Maiestie; Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>