<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>Gouge, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103279_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01971</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12113</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103279</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposition of the Song of Solomon: called Canticles : Together with profitable obseruations, collected out of the same. Perused and published by William Gouge, preacher of Gods Word in Black-Friers, London</title>
                 <author>Finch, Henry, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 128, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Great priuiledge it is, that the
Lord hath committed vnto vs his
diuine Oracles:<note place="margin">Rom. 3: 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> but vnto those,
to whom the tongue wherein they
were written is strange and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne,
or the mysteries themselues obscure and
hard to be vnderstood, what is the benefit of that
fauour, if the language be not interpreted, and the
mysteries opened? shall not these Oracles be <hi>as the
words of a sealed booke?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Read <hi>Isa.</hi> 29: 11, 12.</note> It is needfull that as
the letter of the Scripture bee interpreted, so the
mystery thereof vnfolded. Euery booke of holie
writ requireth a faithfull and learned interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:
but some more then other: among and aboue
those some, this <hi>Song of Solomon:</hi> and that in
regard of the excellency, and of the difficultie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
Two things commend the excellency of it:
First, the <hi>Author;</hi> Secondly, the <hi>matter.</hi> The
principall Author is the same that <hi>by inspirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="4"/>
gaue the whole Scripture:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Tim. 3. 16</note> the immediate
Pen-man of it was a King,<note place="margin">1. King. 4. 29. 30, &amp;c.</note> the most wise and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
King that euer was. The matter is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<note n="b" place="margin">Reade this Exposition Chap. 1. Ver. 1.</note>
      <hi>a blessed, &amp; sweet coniunction between
Christ &amp; his Church,</hi> one of the most comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
mysteries of our Christian faith. Two things
also argue the difficultie of it. 1. The very phrase
and stile, which being poeticall is the more obscure.
2. The manie Rhetoricall allegories, and hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall
metaphors which are hard to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood
and rightly applied. The <note n="c" place="margin">A Song of Songs which is Solomons.</note> title of this Booke
pointeth out all these points. 1 Plainely it is sayd
to be <hi>Solomons.</hi> 2 A <hi>Song</hi> is a kinde of <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie,</hi>
and <hi>Poesies</hi> are commonly adorned with alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories
and figures. 3. For the <note n="d" place="margin">Bern. pro sui excellentia hoc carmen merito <hi>Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca canticorum</hi> appellatur si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut is quoque cui canitur <hi>Rex Regum.</hi>
      </note> excellency of it, it
is termed a <hi>Song of Songs. i.</hi> a Song that sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passeth
all other songs. <note n="e" place="margin">In Midr. Rom. 3. 2</note> The Iewes (to whom <hi>the
Oracles of God were first committed)</hi> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
all the bookes of the Scripture <hi>holy:</hi> but
this <hi>the holy of holies:</hi> whereby they intimated
the excellencie of it. <note n="f" place="margin">Hier. in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aem: in Ezech. nisi quis apud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>os aetatem sacerdotalis ministerij .i. trigefimum annum imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerit, Canticū canticorum legere non permittitur.</note> They permitted none to read
it alone till he were thirty yeere olde: whereby they
implied the difficultie of it. Is it so difficult? sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
it needeth a learned interpreter. Is it so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent?
<pb facs="4"/>
Surely it deserueth the best paines of a
faithfull interpreter. Heerein therefore (good
Reader) thou art much beholding to the learned
Author of this booke, who hath taken so good pains
in expounding this rare <hi>Song.</hi> Such is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,
such the worke, that neither father nor child
need to bee ashamed of one another. The Author
is a man of great place and note in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth;
his humility will not suffer him to haue his
name made known. Though by profession he be not a
<hi>Diuine;</hi> yet in knowledge of those learned tongues
wherein the Scriptures were written, and in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding
of the mysteries contained in them, he
is a very deep &amp; profound <hi>Diuine.</hi> The many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
treatises which he hath made, some in Hebrew,
other in English some heretofore published, other
still lying by him, are euidences of more then I haue
sayd. As for this present Treatise, I obserue sixe
worthie points in it to commend it vnto thee.
1. A true interpretation of the Hebrew text. 2. A
sound exposition of the sense and meaning of the
words. 3. A fit application of the Metaphors, and
allegories. 4. A fruitfull collection of doctrines,
and obseruations. 5. Perspicuit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e. 6. Breuitie.
<pb facs="5"/>
These two last seldome meet together;<note place="margin">Hor. - breu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s esse laboro Obscurus fio.</note> for some, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
to be briefe, are obscure; other, labouring
to be perspicuous, are taedious: when they meete
together they are admirable helpes to vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
memory, affection and all. Thus I haue shewed
thee (Christian Reader) that this <hi>Song of Songs</hi>
is worthie to bee expounded; yea that necessarie
it is, it should bee expounded: that the Author of
this worke is well able to performe so weightie a
worke; and that he hath taken good paines in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming
it. Do thou vse his paines for thine owne
good. If thou aske me why I meddle so farre in it,
as to publish it, I answere, <hi>For thy good;</hi> had it
not been for me, thou haddest not seene it: for it
should seem that the Author long since wrot it, and
let it lie in his studie, not minding to publish it, I
being of late with him about other businesse, espied
it: and reading it desired him to publish it: he vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie
denied me. I then intreated him to bestowe
it on me; he gaue it me. Thus it was mine. But
should I keepe such a pearle of so good vse to all
that will vse it, close and secret to my selfe? Then
might I iustly be censured, as enuious of thy good.
I enuie it not: I would I could doe thee more good;
<pb facs="5"/>
thou shouldest be sure to pertake thereof. But that,
while I seeke to auoide the blame of <hi>Enuie,</hi> I may
not seeme ambitious, know that in this whole worke
there is nothing of mine, but all is the Authors own.
Hee hath also by him, a like <hi>Exposition of the
Prophesie of Hosea;</hi> and other treatises: I hope to
preuaile with him for the publishing of them, when
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e shall see the fruit of these his labours. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence
which I desire is, that thou helpe both the
Author of this booke, and the Publisher thereof
with thy prayers to God.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord,
VVILLIAM GOVGE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>