<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
AA
</title>
           <author>Parke, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103230_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01864</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12003</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103230</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
AA
</title>
                 <author>Parke, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the great and mightie kingdome of China, and the situation thereof : togither with the great riches, huge citties, politike gouernement, and rare inuentions in the same. Translated out of Spanish by R. Parke</title>
                 <author>Gonzáles de Mendoza, Juan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 410, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head type="illustration">
      <figure>
         <p>AA</p>
      </figure>
   </head>
   <head>To the Right worshipfull and famous Gentleman, M. <hi>Thomas Candish</hi> Esquire, increase of honor and happie attemptes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now aboue fiue and thirty yeares passed, right worshipfull, since that young sacred, and prudent Prince, king <hi>Edward</hi> the sixt of happie me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, went about the discouerie of <hi>Cathaia</hi> and <hi>China,</hi> partly of desire that the good young king had to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the Christian faith, and partlie to finde out some where in those re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions ample vent of the cloth of England, for the mischiefs that grew about that time neerer home, aswel by contempt of our commodities, as by the arrestes of his merchantes in the Empire, Flanders, France, and Spaine: foreseeing withall how beneficiall ample vent would rise to all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees throughout his kingdome, and specially to the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of the poore sort distressed by lacke of worke. And although by a voyage hereuppon taken in hande for this purpose by Sir <hi>Hugh Willobie,</hi> and <hi>Richard Chauncellour</hi> a discouerie of the bay of Saint <hi>Nicolas</hi> in Russia fell out, and a trade with the Muscouites, and after another trade for a time with the Persians by way of the Caspian sea en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued, yet the discouerie of the principall intended place followed not in his time, nor yet since, vntill you tooke your happie and renowmed voyage about the worlde in hande, although sundrie attemptes, at the great charges of diuers honorable and well disposed persons, and good worshipfull merchants and others haue beene made since the death of that good king, in seeking a passage thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="3"/>
both by the North-east, and by the Northwest. But since it is so (as wee vnderstande) that your worshippe in your late voyage hath first of our nation in this age discouered the famous rich Ilandes of the <hi>Luzones,</hi> or <hi>Philippinas,</hi> lying neare vnto the coast of <hi>China,</hi> and haue spent some time in taking good view of the same, hauing brought home three boyes borne in <hi>Manilla,</hi> the chiefe towne of the said Ilands, besides two other young fellowes of good capacitie, borne in the mightie Iland of <hi>Iapon,</hi> (which hereafter may serue as our interpretors in our first traficke thither) and that also your selfe haue sailed along the coast of <hi>China,</hi> not farre from the Continent, and haue taken some knowledge of the present state of the same, and in your course haue found out a notable ample vent of our clothes, especially our kersies, and are in preparing againe for the former voyage, as hee that would constantly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuer in so good an enterprise: we are to thinke that the knowledge and first discouerie of the same, in respect of our nation, hath all this time beene by the Almightie to you onely reserued, to your immortall glorie, and to the manifest shew of his especiall fauour borne towards you, in that besides your high and rare attempt of sailing about the whole globe of the earth, in so short a time of two yeares and about two monethes, you haue shewed your selfe to haue that rare and especiall care for your countrie, by seeking out vent for our clothes, that ought vpon due consideration to moue many thousands of English sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to pray for you, and to loue and honor your name and familie for euer. For as you haue opened by your at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the gate to the spoile of the great and late mightie, vniuersall, and infested enimie of this realme, &amp; of al coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries that profes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e true religion: so haue you by your great care wrought a way to imploie the merchants of Englande in trade, to increase our Nauie, to benefite our Clothiers, and (your purpose falling out to your hoped effect) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue more of the poorer sort, then all the hospitals and almes houses can or may, that haue beene built in this realme, since the first inhabiting thereof.</p>
   <p>And Sir, if to this your late noble attempt, it might
<pb facs="3"/>
please you, by your incouragement, and by the help of your purse to adde your present furtherance for the passage to be discouered by the northwest, (for proofe whereof there bee many infallible reasons, and diuerse great experiences to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e yeelded) our course with our commodities to the rich Iland of <hi>Iapon,</hi> to the mightie empire of <hi>China,</hi> and to the Ilandes of the <hi>Philippinas,</hi> for the vent that you haue found out, should be by the halfe way shortened, and you should double and manyfolde treble the credite of your fourmer late enterprise, and make your fame to mount, and your self to liue for euer in a much higher degree of glorie, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise it might be, or that by any other mean you could possibly deuise: In which action so highly importing the generall state of this lande I haue perfect experience that many worshipfull and wealthie marchants of this citie and other places would most willingly ioyne their purses with yours: and to play the blabbe, I may tell you they attende nothing with greater desire and expectation, then that a motion hereof being made by some happie man, your selfe and they might friendly and seriously ioyne together for the full accomplishing of this so long intended discouerie. And to descende to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ome particulars, there is one speciall reason that giueth an edge vnto their desires, proceeding from the late worthie attemptes of that excellent and skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful pilot M. <hi>Iohn Dauis,</hi> made for the search of the aforesaid northwest passage these three late yeares, hauing entred into the same foure hundred leagues further than was euer hitherto thoroughly knowen, and returned with an exact description thereof, to the reasonable contentment for the time, of the aduenturers, and chiefely of the worshipfull M. <hi>William Sanderson,</hi> whose contributions thereunto, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they haue beene verie great and extraordinarie, yet for the certaine hope or rather assurance that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth vpon the report of the Captaine himselfe and all the rest of any skill employed in these voyages, remayneth still constant, and is readie to disburse as yet to the freshe setting on foote of this enterprise entermitted by occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our late troubles, euen this yeare againe for the finall perfection of so profitable and honorable a discouerie, a
<pb facs="4"/>
farre greater portion then in reason would be required of any other man of his abilitie. And albeit sir, that you haue taken in your late voyage, besides the knowledge of the way to <hi>China,</hi> the intelligence of the gouernement of the countrie and of the commodities of the territories and prouinces of the same, and that at the full, according to the time of your short abode in those partes, yet neuerthelesse for that of late more ample vnderstanding hath beene in more length of time, by woonderfull great endeuour ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by certaine learned Portingals and Spaniardes of great obseruation, and not long agoe published in the Spanish tongue, I haue for the increase of the knowledge of the subiectes of Englande, and specially for the illuminating of the mindes of those, that are to take the voyage next in hande to <hi>Iapan, China,</hi> and the <hi>Philippinas,</hi> translated the same worke into english, and committed it to print, pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing ouer <hi>Paulus▪ Venetus,</hi> and sir <hi>Iohn Mandeuill,</hi> because they wrote long agoe of those regions: which labour to say trueth, I haue vndertaken at the earnest request and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of my worshipfull friend Master <hi>Richard Hak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit</hi> late of Oxforde, a gentleman, besides his other mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde learning and languages, of singular and deepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight in all histories of discouerie and partes of Cosmogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie: who also for the zeale he beareth to the honour of his countrie and countrimen, brought the same first aboue two yeares since ouer into this court, and at this present hath in hande a most excellent and ample collection of the sundrie trauailes and nauigations of our owne nation, a matter long intended by him, and seruing to the like be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall and honorable purpose, which I hope will shortly come to light to the great contentation of the wiser sort. In the meane season, hauing nowe at length finished accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my poore skill and leasure this my translation, I thought best to dedicate and commende the same to your worshipfull patronage, as the man that I holde most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of the same, and most able of our nation to iudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right of the contentes thereof, and to correct the errors of the author whensoeuer you shall meete with them: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching you to accept in good part the trauaile and good
<pb facs="4"/>
meaning of the translator: and so wishing vnto you, health, increase of knowledge, with fortunate and glorious successe in your further couragious attempts, I leaue you to the protection of the almightie.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From London
<date>the first of Ianuarie, 1589.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your worships alwaies to command,</hi> Robert Parke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>