<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface</title>
           <author>Harcourt, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103420_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02198</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12340</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103420</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface</title>
                 <author>Harcourt, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An aunsvver to George Giffords pretended defence of read prayers and devised leitourgies : with the vngodly cauils and vvicked sclanders comprised in the first part of his book entituled, A short treatise against the Donatists of England. By Iohn Greenwood Christs poore afflicted prisoner in the Fleete at London, for the trueth of the gospel</title>
                 <author>Greenwood, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 8, 2, 5-66 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>The preface</head>
   <epigraph>
      <q>
         <bibl>1. Cor. 2.</bibl>
         <p n="11">11. What man knoweth the things of a man if not the Spirit of man which is in himself: Euen so the things of GOD know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no man if not the Spirit of GOD.</p>
         <p n="12">12. Now we haue receiued not the Spirit of the world, but the Spirit which is of God, that we might knowe the thinges of GOD giuen vnto vs.</p>
         <p n="13">13. Which things we also speak, not in the words taught of mans wisdome, but in wordes taught of the Holy Ghost, we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare spiritual thinges to spiritual thinges.</p>
      </q>
   </epigraph>
   <p>My first writing being about that spiritual exercise of praier and true inuocacion of Gods reuerend name, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the distressed soule of man, loaden with the burden of sinne, compassed also about with so many deceitfull enimies, contynual assaults of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, rebellion of the flesh, entisements of the world etc. seeketh daylie help of God the Father, giuer of all good giftes, hauing thorough. <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> free accesse by the direction of his holy spirit, for all occasions to vnburden yt self of whatsoeuer grief, or occasion of thankes yt is moued with: I ought still▪ and by Gods assistance shall keepe me in the meeknes of the spirit, not witstanding his vnchristian railinges, sclanders, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches against me and the truth. I then shewed that no other prayer could vtter and ease the seuerall occasions and distresses of this conscience▪ and that no other mans writing could speake for this soule vnto God, but the heart and mouth of him that prayeth for himself, or is chosen the mouth of many, vttering to God his or ther mindes for their present wantes or occasions of thanckes giuing, according to the will of God, as neede and occasion vrgeth, and the spirit giueth vtterance. And I furder proved that onlie this prayer pleaseth God, and is grounded of faith; to this effect I brought many reasons out of Gods worde, admiring the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of this age, wherin (hauing had the gospell of Christ thus manie yeares in our owne language to search and try al things by) whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations do make no other prayer to God then reading ouer certeine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of wordes vpon a booke from yeare to yeare, moneth to moneth, day to day <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the same matter and words as they were stinted, euen out of that <hi>Port<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>is,</hi> englished out of Antichrists masse-booke; besides priuate rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of mens writings instead of praying. And seing this counterfeit shew of worship and pretended prayers was made common marchandize in euery assemblie by this Antichristian priesthood, and that al men euery where were compelled to bowe downe herevnto, and to offer by such coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit sacrifices; I perceaved the first principle of Religion (which is to inuocate the name of the true God, through the meditation of Christ in spirit and truth, with heart and voyce, for our present wantes according to the wil of God) was never yet sincearly taught by these time-seruing
<pb n="5" facs="8"/>
Priests: But as an agreeable service to the humors of earthlie minded men which haue not the spirit of God, this ware was thrust vpō al people, they well knowing, that such a ministerie and such a Church of wordlings could neuer haue stood, without such a Samaritan worshipp and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptian calf; and like earthlie deuised to counterfeyt a Religion, al men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyned to some. And long have I heard this pretended worship inveyed against by many (sometymes zealous) for the errours and confused or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der therof: Yet could I not heare anie to sett downe or teach, which was the true prayer that only pleased God, manie contriving divers formes of wordes, as though they had knowen the heart of man, counselled them to reade them, day vnto day, yeare vnto yeare, at evening, morning, dinner, Svpper <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by portion, measure, and stint, as an offering to God what state soever the soule were in; not teaching the difference betweene reading vpon a booke, and prayer vnto God, all this tyme. So that true and only prayer hath not beene taught al this tyme, and those that knewe how to pray aright neglect it, this reading being most easie as they thinke, and they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>test therunto, compelled in the publique assemblies thus to mocke with God, after the manner of the papists mattins, true zeale no where founde, but in the persequted remnant.</p>
   <p>These my first writings, caryed abroade by such as desired true instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and willing to make others partakers of such benefites as God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted vnto them, yt fell into <hi>Mr. GIFFORDS</hi> hand; Who (as yt see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth being a marchaunt of such ware▪ fynding the gayne of the priesthood to depend here vpon, or as he saith (<hi>the peace &amp; vniformitie of the Church</hi>) made head vnto yt; and that not with purpose (as the fruite of his labour sheweth) to edifie others, but standing himself a minister to this <hi>Liturgie,</hi> having made shipwrack of that conscience he sometimes was thought to haue; with all bitternes of spirit, and carnal wisdome, having no more sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of grace in his writings, then there is taste in the white of an egge, fleeth vpō me with vncharitable raylings, sclanders <hi>&amp;c</hi> And loadeth not only me, but al the faithfull that walke by the rule of Gods worde, with opprobrious titles, of <hi>Donatists, Brownists, Anabaptists, Heretiques, Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiques, seditious, foolish, frantick, &amp;c.</hi> to bring not onely vs, but the truth of God into contempt with our Sovereigne Prynce, and all that feare God: for he ceaseth not with laying al reproches he can devise vpō our persons; as one of those <hi>Locusts, Reu.</hi> 9. whose similituds are like vnto hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses prepared to battell, whose faces like men, but theyr teeth as the teeth of Lyons; But also perverteth, blaspheameth, and by al meanes de faceth the truth offered him. Wel seyng the natural man perceaveth not the things of the spirit of God▪ (I speake not here of the giftes of the spirit but of the grace of God which sanctifieth the same, many hauing <hi>Charismata</hi> that haue not <hi>Charin.</hi>) And seyng I am alreadie thus rent, Gods truth deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by me, troden vnder his feete, I will followe the councell of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> who forewarneth me that <hi>he vvhich reproveth a skorner receaueth to himself shame, and he that rebuketh the vvicked himself a blot</hi>: And so tourne me from him, leauing him to the consideration of his owne words:
<pb facs="9"/>
where hee saieth in his Epistle to the reader, He that seemeth most zealous in Religion and refrayneth not his tongue, hath but bitternes in his heart in stead of heauenly zeale. And though nothing els can be looked for at theyr handes that are Apostate from that light they have sometymes themselves published, (of which sorte the worlde was never more full) yet for the good of Gods chosen scattered abroade, and for the defence of Gods trueth I cannot holde my tongue: And for the more playnenes, I will answeare as to him, though I minde not to haue anie more to do with him, till God giue him repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Wishing grace by the direction of Gods holy spirit to him that readeth, to weigh both sides vprightly, and to follow the truth to his owne saluation. <hi>IO. GRENWOOD.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>