<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Poem]</title>
           <author>Vpcher, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103412_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02135</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12275</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103412</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Poem]</title>
                 <author>Vpcher, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Greenes Arcadia, or Menaphon: Camillaes alarum to slumber Euphues in his melancholy cell at Silexedra : Wherein are descyphered, the variable effects of fortune, the wonders of loue, the triumphs of inconstant time. A worke, worthy the yongest eares for pleasure, or, the grauest censures for principles. By Robertus Greene, in Artibus Magister</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Smethwick (Smithick, Smythicke), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <l>DElicious words, the life of wanton wit,</l>
   <l>That doth inspire our soules with sweet content,</l>
   <l>Why hath your Father <hi>Hermes</hi> thought it fit,</l>
   <l>Mine eyes should surfet by my hearts consent?</l>
   <l>Full twentie Summers haue I fading seene,</l>
   <l>And twentie <hi>Floraes</hi> in their golden guise:</l>
   <l>Yet neuer viewde I such a pleasant <hi>Greene,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>As this whose garnishe gleades comparde, deuise.</l>
   <l>Of all the flōwers a <hi>Lilly</hi> once I lou'd,</l>
   <l>Whose labouring beautie brancht it selfe abroad.</l>
   <l>But now olde age his glory hath remou'd,</l>
   <l>And greener obiects are mine eyes abroad.</l>
   <l>No Countrey to the downes of <hi>Arcadie,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Where <hi>Aganippes</hi> euer springing wels</l>
   <l>Doe moist the meades with bubbling melodie,</l>
   <l>And makes me muse what more in <hi>Delos</hi> dwels.</l>
   <l>There feeds our <hi>Menaphons</hi> celestiall Muse,</l>
   <l>There makes his Pipe his pastorall report:</l>
   <l>Which strained now a note aboue his vse,</l>
   <l>Fore-tels hee'le ne're come chaunt of <hi>Thoacs</hi> sport.</l>
   <l>Reade all that lift, and read till you mislike,</l>
   <l>To condemne who can, so Enuie be not Iudge:</l>
   <l>No, reade who can, swell more higher, lest it shreeke.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Robin,</hi> thou hast done well, care not who grudge.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Henry Vpcher.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>