<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE Lordes of her Highnesse most Honorable Priuie Councell.</title>
           <author>Ingmethorpe, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103018_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01597</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11727</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103018</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE Lordes of her Highnesse most Honorable Priuie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Ingmethorpe, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The troubles of Geneua : VVith the warres which the Duke of Sauoy hath made against it these three yeeres space. And the great victories which God hath lately giuen to the citizens of Geneua. Trulie translated according to the French copie. by W.P. The map of Geneua</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Nelson, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE Lordes of her Highnesse most <hi>Honorable Priuie Councell.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a thing of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie great conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) to behold The Woonderfull worke of almightie God, in strengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge those that continuallie fight for the defence of the true &amp; sincere Religion of Christ Iesus: as hath beene seene within this Island, which in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison to the worlde, is but as a handfull: yet is the same so defended (by the prouidence of almightie God) from spoiling &amp; subuerting, that neither forrain practises abroad, nor ciuil discord, or priuy pretended treasons at home, or the inuasiō of the mightiest enemie can once preuaile against it: as hath of
<pb facs="3"/>
late yeares bene manifested, to the great amazement, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe, and confusion of the chiefest complotters of such bad actions. And this (right Honorable) is not seene onely in this Island, but generallie euen in all Nations, Cities, or Townes, where Gods truth is aduanced, preached, &amp; preferred before Idolatrie and superstition: as appeareth by that famous City of <hi>Geneua,</hi> where God is rightlie honoured, and his worde sincerelie preached. Of which Cittie, (right Honourable) this discourse ensuing trulie describeth, and aswell laieth open their troubles, sustained by the inuasion of the Duke of Sauoy and his forces, for the time of these three years, as also the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels and vnlooked for victories which almightie God hath giuen the Cittizens of <hi>Geneua,</hi> against the Sauoyans theyr deadlie enemies: Thus presenting the saide discourse vnto your Honours, beeing trulie published in the English tongue, according to the French Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, I humblie take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors most humble <hi>T. N.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>