<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND Religious Lady, the Coun∣tesse of Deuonshire, health and peace in Christ Iesus.</title>
           <author>V., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103956_Bo1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04766</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14896</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103956</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND Religious Lady, the Coun∣tesse of Deuonshire, health and peace in Christ Iesus.</title>
                 <author>V., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ouranognōsia. Heauenly knowledge : A manuduction to theologie. Written in Latin by Barthol. Keckerm. done into English by T.V. Mr. of Arts</title>
                 <author>Keckermann, Bartholomäus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 168, 4, 169-181, 7 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="103"/>
   <pb facs="103"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND Religious Lady, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesse of Deuonshire, health and peace in Christ Iesus.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL that is mine own in this little booke, namely, these short directions how to examine our selues, before wee goe to the Lords Table, how to behaue our selues there, and how to try our selues afterward, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered for their sakes, which loue the most concise method and way of Preparation, I make bold to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrate vnto your name, and that in a double respect: <hi>First,</hi> in regard of your Honours great goodwill and
<pb facs="104"/>
bounty to my Vncle, my Lords and your Ladiships seruant, of whom (set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aside the affectiō of a Kinsman) I dare say thus much without flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, that he is one that truly feares God, and is faithfull in all his busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Secondly,</hi> in regard of your Honours great affection to the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and exceeding good respect to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Ministerie thereof, which doth make your name renowned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the whole Land now, and will make your memory blessed hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The Lord keepe you and all yours, and remember you in mercie according to all the good you haue done to the house of God, and the Officers thereof. I betake your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Gods holy protection, and humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours to be commanded in the Lord Iesus, <hi>T. V.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>