<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the most Reverend Father in God, VVILLIAM Lord Arch-bishop of Canterbury, Pri∣mate of all England and Metro∣politane, Chancellor of the Uni∣versity of Oxford, and one of his Majesties most ho∣nourable privy Councell.</title>
           <author>Hardwick, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103844_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02639</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12766</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103844</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the most Reverend Father in God, VVILLIAM Lord Arch-bishop of Canterbury, Pri∣mate of all England and Metro∣politane, Chancellor of the Uni∣versity of Oxford, and one of his Majesties most ho∣nourable privy Councell.</title>
                 <author>Hardwick, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Conformity with piety, requisite in Gods service : Delivered in a visitation sermon at Kingston upon Thames September 8. 1638. By William Hardwick priest and curate of Reigate, in Surry</title>
                 <author>Hardwick, William, priest, curate of Reigate</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Cartwright, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Slater (Slaughter), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 27, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the most Reverend Father in God, VVILLIAM Lord Arch-bishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of all <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politane,</hi> Chancellor of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and one of his Majesties most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable privy Councell.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Reverend father in God,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Know your <hi>Grace</hi> cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that so meane a person every way as my selfe, and one altogether unknowne to your <hi>Grace,</hi> should pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to offer so poore a <hi>Sermon</hi> to your sacred hands: neither am I ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant how much this my <hi>ambition</hi> will expose me to further <hi>Censure:</hi> But God Almighty knowes, 'tis not your <hi>greatnesse,</hi> but <hi>exemplary Piety</hi> and <hi>goodnesse,</hi> which hath imboldned me to shroud these Papers under your <hi>Graces</hi> Wings. And' tis no small encouragement
<pb facs="3"/>to me, to heare how ready your <hi>Grace</hi> is, not onely to countenance the <hi>Labours</hi> of the <hi>Learned</hi> of the times, but also the meanest endeavours of the <hi>poorest Priests,</hi> who ayme at the <hi>peace of Holy Church,</hi> whose <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> next under our <hi>Blessed Saviour,</hi> and our <hi>pious Soveraigne,</hi> your <hi>Grace,</hi> to the admiration of all men, continually seekes to <hi>Advance.</hi> This your <hi>Graces</hi> Charity towards Others, hath made me to <hi>adventure to</hi> cast this <hi>Sermon</hi> at your <hi>Graces</hi> feet: which as it aimes at, what your <hi>Grace</hi> delights in, <hi>Piety and Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> so in all humility it begs your <hi>Paternall Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction;</hi> which if it have the <hi>happinesse</hi> to Obtayne, I doubt not but the <hi>Reader</hi> shall find no small <hi>benefit</hi> by it: And I the meanest of those who wait on <hi>Gods sacred Altar,</hi> shall daily sollicite the <hi>throne of Mercy</hi> for your prosperous successe in the affaires of the <hi>Church Militant,</hi> that so, when you shall have finished your Course, your <hi>Grace</hi> may be crowned with <hi>glory</hi> in the <hi>Church Triumphant:</hi> and this shall ever be the prayer of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>your Graces in all humility,</hi> William Hardwick.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>