<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE SIR EDVVARD DENNY, Lord Baron of Waltam, all peace and happines in this life, with the blessed hope of the life to come.</title>
           <author>W., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103312_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B16379</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25656</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103312</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE SIR EDVVARD DENNY, Lord Baron of Waltam, all peace and happines in this life, with the blessed hope of the life to come.</title>
                 <author>W., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lots wife : A sermon preached at Paules Crosse</title>
                 <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Flasket, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 173, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE SIR EDVVARD DENNY, Lord Baron of Waltam, all <hi>peace and happines in this life, with the blessed hope of the life to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He particular respects, whereby I am and haue been these ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares indebted to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, haue made me (<hi>Right Honorable</hi>) a long time carefull to finde out some good occasion, whereby I might make knowne my dutifull affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to you: And forsomuch as I knew nothing either more sutable for mee to present, or more acceptable to your Christian deuotion, then a meditation of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and iudgements of God, I haue therefore prepared you a sauourie meate to ruminate vpon, and such (as I thought) your soule loued; which yet I must confesse, I haue not newly taken for you with my bow and quiuer, as <hi>Esau</hi> did his venison, but I haue fetched out of my former store, as <hi>Iacob</hi> did a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>id out of the flocke: And yet I had not so done neither, but that <hi>Rebeccah</hi> bad
<pb facs="3"/> me; and not <hi>Rebeccah</hi> onely, but many other of my Christian and louing friends, haue most earnestly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned me thereunto: yet what I haue yeelded to their intreatie, I haue dedicated to your protection, as part of payment of my more especiall dutie. If any man shall thinke the Text too short for such an Auditorie, let him acknowledge, it is a peece of the bread of life, which while we breake it, increaseth in our hands, as the few loaues wherewith our Sauiour fed so many thousands; yea rather let him think that we our selues are too short, too weake, and too shallow to sound but the depth of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie Diuinitie, and <hi>Who is sufficient for these things?</hi> If any man shall thinke either the Text, or the Sermon to be too salt (indeed a Salt-stone giues taste vnto both) yet let him consider againe, that the age is corrupt wherin we liue, &amp; it is now no time to annoint, but to search men in their sins. God giue vs all grace to know our selues in truth, to reforme our selues in wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to waite for the rewards with patience. And thus I humblie take my leaue; beseeching God, who hath laid in your person a foundation of an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable familie, to continue and increase your Honor, to the glory of his name, the supporting of his Church, and to the good of the state wherein you liue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors true affected in all Christian loue and dutie, R. W.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>