<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Authour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103342_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01930</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12067</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103342</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Authour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first booke of the famous historye of Penardo and Laissa : other ways callid the warres, of love and ambitione. Wherein is described Penardo his most admirable deeds of arms, his ambition of glore his contempt of loue, with loves mighte assalts &amp; ammorus temptations: Laissas feareful inchantment hir releif hir trauells and lastly loves admirabel force, in hir releiving Penardo from ye fire, doone in heroik verse, by Patrik Gordon</title>
                 <author>Gordon, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waters (Walters), Joris (George)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Dordrecht</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>280 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="140"/>
   <head>To the Authour.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>NAture and arte contending which should proue</l>
      <l>Most fauourd of the muses did ordaine</l>
      <l>Old <hi>Orphaeus</hi> their Iudge who broght his loue</l>
      <l>From <hi>Plutoes</hi> kingdome and from hellish payne</l>
      <l>But he excus'd him self his workes wer torne</l>
      <l>And with, tymes rusly Canker cleane outuorne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Yet Sayd that he would wish them to ane vther</l>
      <l>Whoes lynes could weall decyd their wrangling stryff</l>
      <l>And soe thy braue <hi>Penardo</hi> did discover</l>
      <l>Wheirby aste seem'd to be bereaft of lyff</l>
      <l>Whilst thou hir conqur'our to thy greater grace</l>
      <l>Makst arte to nature euin in arte giue place.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then since thu'rt arts Controler, natures Chyld,</l>
      <l>Stird vp by vertue to encreass thy fame</l>
      <l>Leaue not <hi>Layssa</hi> thus from loue exyld</l>
      <l>For saue thy self non dare attempt the same</l>
      <l>And as thou dost in vs sweet thoghts Inspyre</l>
      <l>Soe goe thou one and we shall still admyte.</l>
   </lg>
   <pb facs="141"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>