<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Errours escaped in the Printing. With certaine Additions to be inserted.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103899_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02775</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12903</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103899</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Errours escaped in the Printing. With certaine Additions to be inserted.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pierces supererogation or A new prayse of the old asse : A preparatiue to certaine larger discourses, intituled Nashes s. fame. Gabriell Haruey</title>
                 <author>Harvey, Gabriel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 199, 100-120, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="120"/>
   <pb facs="121"/>
   <pb facs="121"/>
   <head>Errours escaped in the Printing. With certaine Additions to be inserted.</head>
   <p>
      <table>
         <row>
            <cell role="label">Page.</cell>
            <cell role="label">faultes.</cell>
            <cell role="label">amended.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>26</cell>
            <cell>forangoy, read</cell>
            <cell>agony.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>31</cell>
            <cell>scholeth,</cell>
            <cell>schooleth.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>bewixt</cell>
            <cell>betwixt.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>67</cell>
            <cell>railing stile, without the two prickes, or colon.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>85</cell>
            <cell>very Minister</cell>
            <cell>euery Minister.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>90</cell>
            <cell>instringment</cell>
            <cell>infringement.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>98</cell>
            <cell>not will</cell>
            <cell>will not.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>107</cell>
            <cell>looker-on</cell>
            <cell>lookers-on.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>121</cell>
            <cell>such sweating</cell>
            <cell>such a sweating.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>139</cell>
            <cell>or discourser</cell>
            <cell>or a discourser.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>147</cell>
            <cell>thy riot</cell>
            <cell>by riot.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>201</cell>
            <cell>suprises</cell>
            <cell>surprises.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>205</cell>
            <cell>at the least</cell>
            <cell>or the least.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>219</cell>
            <cell>Orientall</cell>
            <cell>Orient.</cell>
         </row>
      </table>
   </p>
   <p>KNow also, Gentle Reader, that it was the Writers meaning to deuide this Treatise into three bookes: the Second beginning at the <hi>Aduertisement to Pap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hatchet, and Martin Mar-prelate:</hi> the Third at, <hi>So then of Pappadocio:</hi> but in the Originall, or vncorrected coppy there was not any such diuision expresly sett-downe: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were the Additions following, inserted in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per places, but annexed to the end of the Third booke, &amp; noted thus.</p>
   <p>In the <hi>First Booke,</hi> page 46. after <hi>Cloude,</hi> insert. What speake I of one, or two Inglish Paragons? or what should I blason the gallant, and braue meeters of Ariosto, and Tasso, alwayes notable, sometimes admirable? All the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest Italian, French, and Spanish Poets, haue in their seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="122"/>
Veines Petrarchised, that is, looued wittily, not grose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, liued ciuilly, not lewdly, and written deliciously, not wantonly. And it is no dishonour for the daintyest, or diuinest Muse, to be his scholler, whom the amiablest In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, and bewtifullest Elocution acknowledge their master. All posteritie—</p>
   <p>In the <hi>Second Booke,</hi> Page. 77. after <hi>edifieth,</hi> insert. Plato comparing Aristotle, and Xenocrates togither; Xenocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, quoth he, needeth a spurre: Aristotle a Bridle. And if Princes, or Parlaments want a goade, may not Subiects, or Admonitions want a snaffle? Is there pretence, for Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to aduise the wisest, or for Zeale to pricke-forward the highest: and no reason for Prudence to curbe Rashnesse, or for Autoritie to reane Licentiousnesse? May Iudgement be whoodwinked with friuolous traditions: and cannot Phantasie be enueigled with newfangled conceites? Superstition and Credulitie—</p>
   <p>In <hi>the same booke,</hi> Page. 87. after <hi>Innouation,</hi> insert. And I hope he was not greatly vnaduised, that being demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his opinion of the Eldership in question; answered, he conceiued of the <hi>Eldership,</hi> (as it is intended, and motio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in England) as he thought of the <hi>Elder-tree,</hi> that whatsoeuer it appeared in shewe, it would in triall prooue frutelesse, seedelesse, bitter, fraile, troublous, and a friend to surging waues, and tempestuous stormes. And being further pressed touching the forward Zeale of dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Martin Seniour, liuely Martin Iuniour, pert Penry, lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty Barrow, and some other bragge Reformistes: (for that rowling stone of Innouation, was neuer so turled and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, as since those busie limmes began to rowse, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturre them, more then all the Pragmatiques in Europe): when young Phaeton, quoth he, in a presumptuous reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
<pb facs="122"/>
would needes rule the Chariot of the Sunne, as it might be the temple of Apollo, or the Church of S. Paule, or some greater Prouince (for the greater Prouince, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, or Monarchy, the fitter for Phaetons reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion): his sudd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ine ruine ministred matter of most lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table teares, to his deare mother, and louing Sisters; in so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that they were pittifully chaunged, as some write into <hi>Elder-trees,</hi> as some, into <hi>Poplars. Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>fleuit Clymene: sic &amp; Clymencides altae:</hi> as it might be the mournefull Church, and her wailing members, wofully transmewed into <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> or <hi>Poplars.</hi> Good my Masters,—</p>
   <p>In the <hi>Third booke,</hi> Page 205, after <hi>Pollicie,</hi> insert. that Learning was to be commended, but Lucre, and Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt to be studied: that he soweth in vaine, which moweth not his own aduantage: that nothing was to be bestowed, without hope of vsance: that Loue, or Hatred auaile not, but where they may preuaile: that Affections were to be squared by occasion, and Reasons to be framed by proffit: that names of partialities, sectes, and diuisions, either in Ciuill, or Religious causes, were but foolish wordes, or pelting termes; &amp; all were to be estimated by their valuatiō in esse: that the true squire, &amp; right Geometricall compasse of things, is habilitie, the onely thing, that by a soueraine prerogatiue deserueth to be called <hi>Substance:</hi> that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chawcers English, there can be little <hi>adling,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much <hi>gabbing,</hi> that is, small getting, without greatly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and cogging: that it was—</p>
   <p>These fower Additions in their seuerall bookes, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende to the correction of the curteous Reader: and so take my leaue.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>