<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE VERTV∣OVS, RELIGIOVS, AND MOST WORTHY LADY, the Lady IANE CORNEVVAL∣LEYS, Widdow: Grace and Peace from God the Father, through our Lord Ie∣sus Christ.</title>
           <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103147_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09026</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19314</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103147</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE VERTV∣OVS, RELIGIOVS, AND MOST WORTHY LADY, the Lady IANE CORNEVVAL∣LEYS, Widdow: Grace and Peace from God the Father, through our Lord Ie∣sus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The grounds of diuinitie : plainely discouering the mysteries of Christian religion, propounded familiarly in diuers questions and answeres: substantially proued by scriptures; expounded faithfully, according to the writings of the best diuines, and euidently applyed by profitable vses, for the helpe and benefite of the vnlearned which desire knowledge. To the which is prefixed a very profitable treatise, containing an exhortation to the study of the word, with singular directions for the hearing and reading of the same. By Elnathan Parr minister of the word, at Palgraue in Suffolke</title>
                 <author>Parr, Elnathan</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Samuel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 304 pages, x 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE VERTV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS, RELIGIOVS, AND MOST WORTHY LADY, the Lady IANE CORNEVVAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEYS, Widdow: Grace and <hi>Peace from God the Father, through our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MADAME,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Present vnto you these my weake and homely labours, being the first fruits of my paines in this kinde, humbly desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that your Ladiship wold vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to patronize them. That which hath emboldened me to dedicate them to your worthy <hi>Name,</hi> is Partly
<pb facs="3"/>A minde willing in the best mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure I can, to testifie my thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse for your many vndeserued fauours, whereby I confesse you may iustly challenge more then my Mediocrity can euer performe: Partly, your loue vnfeigned, and sincere profession of the Gospell, (whereby you are an honour to your Degree and Sexe) cleerely eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced many wayes, during your abode in <hi>Suffolke:</hi> which, as it is a sweete testimony to your owne breast, that you are beloued of God, and hath made you farre and neere honoured by all such which loue God: so also it hath made mee very confident, that your Ladiship will fauourably ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept these my thankefull ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours. Goe on I humbly beseech you (good Madame) goe on in that good way which you haue chosen: and constantly continue, as a bright
<pb facs="3"/>Starre, to shine (without waning, or being ecclipsed) to the directing, confirming, and comforting of many, as hitherto you haue done. And, for my part, I shall neuer cease (among many other) to stand vp as an humble Suppliant to God; that you may bee more and more strengthened in his Grace, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Eternall Spirit, that as you haue already, by your zeale in Religion, prouoked many: so you may perseuere vnto the end, in this holy course, and bring on, and encourage others by your sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular example: Then shall your Name bee still more honourable while you liue here, and your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count furthered in the day of our Lord IESVS. And thus humbly tendering my best seruice to your Ladiship, and to the hopefull Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> FREDERICKE, your ioy, (vpon whom I beseech God
<pb facs="4"/>to double the glory of all his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors) and wishing vnto you both, and to your whole fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all temporall and eternall blessings by Iesus Christ: I humbly take my leaue, and alway rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Bound to your Ladiship to my vttermost in all Christian duty, Elnathan Parr.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>