<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHILDREN of Men.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103145_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08799</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19084</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103145</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHILDREN of Men.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The sinners sanctuary. By Thomas Packer, his Majesties servant</title>
                 <author>Packer, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Blackmore (Blackamore), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 108 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE CHILDREN of Men.</head>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>
         <hi>ROM. 3.23.</hi>
      </bibl>
      <q>For all have sinned and come short of the glory of God.</q>
   </epigraph>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ome now,<note place="margin">Isa. 1.18.</note> and let us reason to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, saith the Lord; though your sins be as scarlet, they shall be as white as snow; though they be red like crymsin, they shall be as wooll.</p>
   <p>Have I any pleasure at<note place="margin">Ezec. 18.23</note>
      <pb facs="3"/>
all, that the wicked should die, saith the Lord God? and not that hee should returne from his waies, and live?</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">31.</note>Cast away from you all your transgressions, whereby yee have trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressed, and make you a new heart, and a new spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: for why will ye die, O house of Israel?</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">1 Sa. 12.23.</note>I will teach you the good and the right way.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">24.</note>Onely feare the Lord, and serve him in truth, with all your heart: for cōsider how great things he hath done for you.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>Wee must serve the Lord, our God,<note place="margin">Deu. 28.47</note> with joi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse and with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of heart, for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of all things.</p>
   <p>Trust in the Lord with all thine heart,<note place="margin">Pro. 35.</note> and leane not unto thine owne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding.</p>
   <p>In all thy waies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him,<note place="margin">6.</note> and hee shall direct thy paths.</p>
   <p>Blessed is that man that maketh the Lord his trust.<note place="margin">Psal. 40.4.</note>
   </p>
   <p>And be not conformed to this world;<note place="margin">Rom. 12.2</note> but be yee transformed by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of your mind, that ye may prove what
<pb facs="4"/>
is that good, that accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and perfect will of God.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Augustin.</note>Doe not understand that thou maist beleeve, but beleeve that thou maist understand; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding is the reward of Faith.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Iohn. 11.40</note>Jesus saith unto <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> Said I not unto thee, that if thou wouldest be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, thou shouldest see the glory of God?</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Act. 18.27.</note>When <hi>Apollos</hi> came into Achaia, hee helped them much, who had beleeved through grace.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Isa. 7.9.</note>If ye will not beleeve,
<pb facs="4"/>
surely yee shall not bee established.</p>
   <p>We beeleve, and know,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.69.</note> that thou art Christ, that Sonne of the living God.</p>
   <p>Teach me good judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and knowledge,<note place="margin">Psal. 119.66.</note> O Lord; for I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved thy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
   <p>It belongeth to every private man to judge of the doctrine of religion,<note place="margin">Brentius.</note> [for satisfaction of his owne conscience] and to discerne the truth from falshood.</p>
   <p>That Religion which<note place="margin">Lipsius.</note> is sincerely taken out of
<pb facs="5"/>
the holy Scriptures, is the true, and Christian Religion.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Andrad.</note>For they containe the most ample Canon, that is, the rule, and square of Piety, Faith, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">August.</note>They have delivered unto us, that there is but one God, and one Christ; one Hope, and one Faith; one Church, and one Baptisme.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Ferus.</note>They are the sole rule of veritie; and whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver differs, or contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth the same, it is error, and cockle, with what
<pb facs="5"/>
shew soever it commeth forth.</p>
   <p>They are all plaine to him that understandeth,<note place="margin">Pro. 3.5.</note> and right to them that finde knowledge.</p>
   <p>All those things which appertaine to faith,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> and direction of life, are laid downe plainly in the holy Scriptures.</p>
   <p>They are manifest to them,<note place="margin">Epiphan.</note> who repaire unto them, with a religious heart.</p>
   <p>Let not our Religion therefore consist in our fantasies; for any truth,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> whatsoever it be, is better
<pb facs="6"/>
than any thing, that can of our own head be devised.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Aug.</note>Godly humility doth more easily finde out the Maker of the stars, than proud curiosity the order of the starres.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Booke of nature into the book of Grace.</note>The depth of Predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and the manner of Regeneration are diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult points of divine my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries, which a studious Divine, an illuminated spirit cannot find out.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>Let us religiously adore these things by faith, and not curiously search into them by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, further than Gods
<pb facs="6"/>
Word doth allow.</p>
   <p>This is the perfection of the regenerate;<note place="margin">August.</note> If they acknowledge themselves to be imperfect.</p>
   <p>The doctrine of the holy Ghost doth not encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage curiositie,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> but infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth charitie.</p>
   <p>When the soule is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome by the fever,<note place="margin">Chrysost.</note> or fiery heat of imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then it questioneth; but when it is sound, and in good temper, it reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not, but faithfully beleeveth.</p>
   <p>As zeale must erect our discretion,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> that wee run
<pb facs="7"/>
not too slowly; So dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion must direct our zeale, that we run not too fast.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Aug.</note>God will reveale wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome onely to such as walke continually in the way of peace; not in the way of precisenesse.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Harsnet.</note>Tell me, what is not contained in the ten Cōmandements, which of a Christian is to bee performed?</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Lactant.</note>When God opened his truth unto us, he would have us know those things only which it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooved man to know for
<pb facs="7"/>
obtaining life: But of those things, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained to curious, &amp; profane desires, he spake not, that they might bee hidden. Why then doest thou seeke those things which thou canst not know? neither art thou more blessed, if thou knowest them?</p>
   <p>Grace teacheth a man to put his knowledge in practice.<note place="margin">Harsnet.</note>
   </p>
   <p>He desires to be taught,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> that he may walke; not that he may talke, as too many doe.</p>
   <p>Adde to your faith ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.5.</note>
      <pb facs="8"/>
and to vertue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">6.</note>And to knowledge temperance; and to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance patience; and to patience godlinesse:</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">7.</note>And to godlinesse brotherly kindnesse; and to brotherly kindnesse charitie.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">8.</note>For if these things be in you, and abound, they make you, that you shall neither be barren, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Luther in</hi> Luke 6.</note>Let us first repose Faith in God alone; and
<pb facs="8"/>
then let us direct our works to the benefit of our neighbour.</p>
   <p>As many as will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low God,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Idem in</hi> Ephes. 5.</note> and walke in love, and I shew forth their faith by their works, are neither the sons of God, nor heires of his kingdom.</p>
   <p>What doth it profit,<note place="margin">Ia. 2.14.</note> my brethren, though a man say hee hath faith? can faith save him?</p>
   <p>The end of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is Charity,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.5.</note> out of a pure heart, and of a good conscience, and of faith unfeined.</p>
   <p>By faith which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived<note place="margin">Haymo.</note>
      <pb facs="9"/>
in the heart, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed with the mouth, and adorned with good works, the just man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth eternally.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Cyprian.</note>Life is here lost, or wonne; everlasting sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is here provided for, by the due worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God, and the fruits of faith.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Epiphan.</note>For in the age to come, after a mans death, there is no more helpe by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting, no more calling to penance, no more exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of Almes.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Epiphan.</note>It is as the corne, that swelleth not, after it is
<pb facs="9"/>
reaped, neither can bee spoiled with the wind.</p>
   <p>The garners are sealed up, the time is past,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> the combat is finished, the lists are voided, and the garlands are given.<note place="margin">Aug.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Let us therefore bee at one with the word of God, while we are in this life, for when we are gone out of this world, there shall bee no more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction, or satisfaction; there remaineth no more, but the Judge, the Gao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and the Prison.</p>
   <p>When wee were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.10.</note> we were reconciled
<pb facs="10"/>
unto God, by the death of his Son.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Heb. 9.26.</note>Once in the end of the world hath he appeared to put away sin, by the sacrifice of himselfe.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Acts 10.43.</note>To him give all the Prophets witnesse, that, through his name, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever beleeveth in him, shall receive remission of sinnes.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Bellar.</note>Wee confesse, that Christ hath truly, yea most fully satisfied God the Father for us, and for the whole world.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Aug.</note>JESUS CHRIST taking upon him the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment
<pb facs="10"/>
but not the fault, hath therby blotted out both the fault, and the punishment.</p>
   <p>Let us hold fast the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of our faith,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wavering, for hee is faithfull that promised.</p>
   <p>The rule of Catholike faith is certain &amp; known.<note place="margin">Bellar.</note>
   </p>
   <p>There is nothing more knowne,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> nothing more certain, than the holy Scriptures, which are contained in the writings of the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles.</p>
   <p>They are Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> which be of sound
<pb facs="11"/>
Faith, and good life.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Idem.</note>Hereticks doe violate faith by beleeving false things of God.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Tertul.</note>Whatsoever favoureth against the truth, is an heresie, be it never so an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienta custome.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Aug.</note>And schismatiks (though they beleeve the same things with us, yet) doe fly from brotherly Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, by their wicked di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Idem.</note>Wherefore neither doth the Heretick belong to the Catholike Church, because hee loveth not God:</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>Nor the Schismatike,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> because he loveth not his neighbour.</p>
   <p>Pure Religion,<note place="margin">Ja. 1.27.</note> and undefiled before GOD, and the Father, is this, To visit the fatherlesse, and the widowes in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction; and to keepe himselfe unspotted from the world.</p>
   <p>If true charity,<note place="margin">Casarius.</note> and humility be wanting, we ought not to presume, and trust to the habit on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Religion.</p>
   <p>Let us search,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.40.</note> and try our waies, and turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine unto the Lord.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <note place="margin">25.</note>The Lord is good to them that wait for him; to the soule that seeketh him.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">30.</note>For hee doth not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict willingly; nor grieve the Children of Men.</p>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>1 PET. 2.17.</bibl>
      <q>Feare God. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor the King.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>