<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, M. WILLIAM TOT∣HIL, and M. FRANCIS DRAKE, Esquiers, Iustices of the Peace, &amp;c. and to the no lesse religious and vertuous Gentlewomen, Mrs. KA∣THERINE TOTHIL, and Mrs. IOAN DRAKE, their wiues, the increase and perpetuitie of all Happinesse, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Hart, I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103842_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02762</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12891</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103842</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, M. WILLIAM TOT∣HIL, and M. FRANCIS DRAKE, Esquiers, Iustices of the Peace, &amp;c. and to the no lesse religious and vertuous Gentlewomen, Mrs. KA∣THERINE TOTHIL, and Mrs. IOAN DRAKE, their wiues, the increase and perpetuitie of all Happinesse, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Hart, I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The bvrning bvsh not consvmed : wherein (either vnder all deepe sense of wrath; or hardnesse of heart, one may iudge, whether he be the childe of God, or not, &amp;c. Chiefly receyuing satisfaction concerning the sinne against the Holy Ghost. Perused by I.D. and diuers other diuines)</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 158, 6 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, M. WILLIAM TOT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HIL, and M. FRANCIS DRAKE, <hi>Esquiers, Iustices of the Peace, &amp;c. and to the no lesse religious</hi> and vertuous Gentlewomen, Mrs. KA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THERINE TOTHIL, and Mrs. IOAN DRAKE, their wiues, <hi>the increase and perpetuitie of all Happinesse, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Worshipfull,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S my wandering thoughtes were mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing which way I might best acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with perpetuall thankes, that duetie which my best loue
<pb facs="3"/>
oweth vnto your many vndeser-ued by-past kindenesses: this little Booke (then readie for the Presse,) did steppe foorth, proffering so to accomplish my desire, as that nothing (saue time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse Time in the generall dissoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) should bee able quite to blotte out, and deface the memory of this my wish: which since it hath nowe so faithfully performed, I beseeche you to accept thereof: that like vnto PHILIPS little Boy) it may put you in minde, not onely that there is a terrible endlesse wrath prepared for wilfull, finall, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent sinners: but also that (if need bee) it may helpe you how to shunne the same.</p>
   <p>Gladly it would haue singled foorth some one of you, but that the strict bonds both of Nature and grace, which in loue hath so vnited you (as though you had but one soule) did strictly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the same: wishing me rather, that (since such a fast Gordian knotte had
<pb facs="3"/>
alreadie tyed your affections) I should likewise doe my best to vnite you in a peece of Paper: Not that thereby I should any thing adde vnto your hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse: (whose Cuppe already run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ouer with a plentifull measure, pressing downe of all blessings) but that thereby I might shewe, how farre my fainte and weake wishes extend: that as already vppon Earth, GOD hath buylt you a sure House vppon a Rocke, so also that you would endeauour to buylde your selues vppon the Rocke CHRIST IESVS: that at last when (at the all-shaking voyce of the Arch-Angell, and Trumpet of GOD, sounding) downe-rayning Fire with floods of horrors, blowne with the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestuous whyrlewinde of indignation, shall ouerwhelme the wicked, and seeme to dossolue the whole frame of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: You (like his Doues) may finde a sure shelter in the holes of this Rocke, vntill (Iudgement finished,) with
<pb facs="4"/>
all Saintes, you may mount with Him, to possesse for euer those infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite vnspeakeable Ioyes, the greatnesse whereof can not bee knowne, vntill possessed.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in duty, much and euer bound, <hi>I. HART.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>