<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Iohan Bale to the christen reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103829_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05038</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15180</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103829</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Iohan Bale to the christen reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatyse made by Johan Lambert vnto kynge Henry the .viij. concerynge hys opynyon in the sacrame [n] t of the aultre as they call it, or supper of the lorde as the scripture nameth it. Anno do. 1538</title>
                 <author>Lambert, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Straten, Derick van der (Theodoricus Plateanus)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Wesel</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Iohan Bale to the christen reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Moses described the pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matyue churche for the first. ij. ages of Adam and Noah (most gentyll reader) he ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Moses.</note> omytted the malycyouse murtherer Cain, nor yet the hatefull scor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner Cham, but set them both fourth in their lyuely colours of reprobate uessels<note place="margin">Lucas.</note> and wylfull persecuters of the same. Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke in like case with the other Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lystes, forgate neyther Iudas nor yet the hypocrytysh clergy of the Iewes, as he worte the Gospell &amp; Actes, whose wret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched hartes vnsacyatly thursted for tho se innocētes bloude, whych purely confes<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed the lorde. A lyke maner in writynge obserued Egesippus, Eusebius, &amp; other<note place="margin">Eusebius.</note> historyanes, i the dscripcyō of that lyue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly churche whych folowed immedyatly after the Apostles tyme, as is euident to them that hath redde their workes. Whych godly maner of writynge, the vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>olēce of Sathā wolde in no case suffer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se to procede or contynue, least the mad mastryes of hys mody mynysters were therby perceyued, and darkenesse so kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne
<pb facs="3"/>
for darkenesse.</p>
   <p>Yet was not the currysh nature of that Cainysh generacyon, churlyshly reiectyn<note place="margin">Cain.</note> ge the gentyll uoyce of God, for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges folowynge, all hyd to thē whych had both eyes and syght of the lyuely scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. But they wele perceyued at all ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes that they were both spyghtfull mur therers and theues, for all their counter fett colours of holynesse, prelacy, preste hode, chastyte, ghostlynesse, and soch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dregges the deuyll, in the kynde that they vsed them. If the congregacyon of God do now fynde such ernest writers,<note place="margin">Writers.</note> as the seyd Moses, Luke, and Eusebius were, whych wyl not in these dayes rocke the cradle of Iesabel, Apoca. 2. or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the prelates &amp; tyrauntes in all their idolatrouse whoremōgynges, they maye wele thynke they haue no lesse godly treasure than they were thē to the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, tyme for tyme and age for age.</p>
   <p>For what els seaketh the greatter nombre of men lerned, but to lawde for<note place="margin">Lerned.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uere, to prayse for pleasure, and to please for aduauntage? encoragynge the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked tyraūtes of Sodome in all their blas phemouse euyls. Yea, and a wonderfull
<pb n="3" facs="3"/>
matter is it, to se▪ as the lawes are wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cked, how the prestes, the lawers (I spea ke not of the godly) and the wytlesse ma gystrates, sturre about them, to haue the<note place="margin">Lawes.</note> tyrāny of thē in all poyntes perfourmed. They stāpe, they leape, they runne, they backbyte, they cōplayne, they accuse, they hate, they reuyle, they slaūdre, they why sper in that care &amp; that care, &amp; sūtyme geue fytlhy rewardes, to brīge their cruel <hi>purpose aboute, &amp; to depryue the īnocētes of lyfe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But whan the lawes are ryghteou se than is it no worlde for them, but they<note place="margin">Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> kepe sylence as monkes were wont to do. They dwell at hōe, they slepe, they drea me, and vtter nothynge at all▪ They lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke lyke the foxe that feareth the whyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, and lyke the wolfe that doubteth the shepeherde or hunter. For their nature is not to maynteyne the ryghteousnesse of the lawe, but busyly to call vpon, to stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vp, &amp; to quycken the tyranny therof. For they are the naturall mynysters of<note place="margin">Tyra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> tyranny, and in that peruerse offyce, the fearce promoters of Antichrist, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell slaues of the deuyll. Of thys spyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full rable of rude rashe ruffyanes, was he cytie of Norwych yet neuer clere, in
<pb facs="4"/>
the whych thys persecuted seruaunt of God Iohan Lambert, otherwyse called Iohan Nycols, was borne, &amp; from thēs exyled for hys christen beleues sake.</p>
   <p>I haue reddein the chronycles of that<note place="margin">Norwych.</note> cytie, that it hath bene dyuersly oft pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for the slaughter of innocētes. And in the yeare of our lorde a. M. S. and. vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. I behelde it in effect most wonderfull, beyng than but a ladde of. xi. yeares of age. As their blynde byshopp &amp; clergy, by their full consent, had brent a yonge man there, aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r the most tyrannouse ma ner (I thynke) that euer was seane, only for hauynge the lordesprayeri Englysh, and for not allowynge that prayer in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne idolatrously to besayd to their dead<note place="margin">O theues</note> sayntes, neyther folowed in them nor yet in their clergy repentaunce for that cru ell slaughter. No, neyther lent fastynge, fyshe eatynge shryft palme sonday, good fryday, clyppe clappes, crosse crepynge, easter daye, nor yet the receyuynge of their maker, as they call it, whych all im medyatly succeded, coulde brynge them ones in remembraunce, that they had therin done amys.</p>
   <p>But se what folwed by the ryghtfull
<pb n="4" facs="4"/>
hande of God. On tuysdaye in Easter we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke, whych was than opon saynt Markes<note place="margin">Fyre.</note> daye, soch a fyre sodenly kyndled in the stretes of their cytte, as in fyue dayes &amp; as manye nyghtes folowynge coulde scar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sely be quenched. The euydent sygnes of that destructyon, are yet to thys present houre to be seane there in dyuerse places, the people neuer knowynge from whens that fyre came. And yet styll they, by the blyndenesse of their curates, not only remayned without repentaunce, but also<note place="margin">Vnpeny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent.</note> consented to murther vpon murther, as apered in sir Thomas of Eccles, in an ol deman of Bongay, and in mastre Byl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, whom they put to cruell deathe also for their christen beleues.</p>
   <p>If they haue borne them the boldar,<note place="margin">prestes</note> for that they haue seane their prestes not moch harmed by that fyre, or no lesse ther after to prospere than afore, they fowly haue deceyued thēselues through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of the scriptures. For God only chasteneth here in thys lyfe, those whom he loueth and intendeth to saue. Hebre. 12. As for the prestes whych commenly witholde the truthe of God in vnrygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tcousnesse, God hath geuen them ouer
<pb facs="5"/>
to themselues, Roma. i. whych is the most terryble plage vpon earthe. They are the sede &amp; ofsprynge of that wycked one, re<note place="margin">Antichrist</note> serued to the lattre vengeaunce. whom Christ shall destroye in hys lattre com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge, for beleuynge lyes, and fordoynge here the operacyon of errour. 2. Thes. 2. Moreouer Christ hath terrybly thrette▪ ned, that it shall be moch worse with that generacyon of infydeles in that last iudgement day, than with Sodome and Gomor, or Tyre &amp; Sydon, luce. 10. whych had sore ponnyshmentes here.</p>
   <p>How many the afore named cytie hath spirytually slayne, by vniustly withol<note place="margin">Norwych.</note> dynge the scriptures of God, whych only mynystreth lyfe to the sowle, the lorde of beauen knoweth, and wyll to their confu syon, make it open at that lattre iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment daye. Therfor I counsell them to re pent in due season, and from hens fourth towashe theîr handes cleane from inno cent bloude, not with Pylate but with Paule, whych after hys conuersyon ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nomore a persecuter of christianes▪ And as concernynge their cytiezen sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme,<note place="margin">Lamber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>▪</note> Iohan Lambert, whom they for hys faythe reiected, though, he was not
<pb n="5" facs="5"/>
for them, yet was he for Christ. And I doubt not of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t, but thys treatyse solowyn ge, whych beynge in the pryson, he wro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te vnto the kynge as a reckenynge or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counte of hys faythe concernynge the chefe artyclè wherof he was accused, shall be able to declare hym a true wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse<note place="margin">Martyr.</note> and seruaunt of God, detestynge all false and idolatrouse worshyppynges. The sprete of the father eternall, and of hys sonne Iesus Christ, be euermore with thē that fauer hys truthe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faynedly, &amp; seke therafter to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyō their lyues, &amp; not after the corrupted examples of synnefull men. So be it.</p>
   <trailer type="illustration">
      <figure>
</figure>
   </trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>