<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND, MOST GRAVE, LEAR∣ned, and worthy Prelate, and Father in GOD, My Lord Bi∣shop of Winchester.</title>
           <author>Guild, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103525_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02353</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12485</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103525</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND, MOST GRAVE, LEAR∣ned, and worthy Prelate, and Father in GOD, My Lord Bi∣shop of Winchester.</title>
                 <author>Guild, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Moses vnuailed: or Those figures which serued vnto the patterne and shaddow of heauenly things, pointing out the Messiah Christ Iesus, briefly explained : Wherevnto is added the harmony of all the prophets, breathing with one mouth the mysterie of his comming, and of that redemption which by his death he was to accomplish ... By William Guild, minister of Gods Word at King-Edward in Scotland</title>
                 <author>Guild, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 <publisher>Purslowe, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                            <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Budge, John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 183, 17, 62, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND, MOST GRAVE, LEAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and worthy Prelate, and Father in GOD, My Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Winchester.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in the Creation dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes went before light, or as the dawning pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes the brightnesse of the day, &amp; as</hi> Ioseph <hi>obscurely at first behaued himselfe vnto his Brethren, and</hi> Moses <hi>couered with
<pb facs="3"/>
a vaile stood before the people: Euen so</hi> (Right Reuerend) <hi>in the detection of the glorious worke of mans Redemption, mysticall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises went before mercifull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, darke shaddowes were the fore-runners of that bright substance, obscure types were har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingers to that glorious Anti-type the Messiah, who was comming after, and</hi> Leui's <hi>Law with its fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue and vailed Ceremonies, was the viue resemblance, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and pointing out that cleere Lampe and Lambe of God, the expresse Image and ingrauen Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Father: So that as folded in swaddling clouts, and lying in a Crib, hee was seene and
<pb facs="3"/>
shewne vnto the Wise-men that came from the East; so inuolued in typicall ordinances, and lurking vnder shaddowish signes, hee was offered and exhibited vnto the Iewes that saw his day but afarre off; the eclipsed and dimme light of the Moone (as it were) as yet onely glimmering, or the twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling brightnesse of starry Lamps as yet onely dazedly glistering: Vntill the true</hi> Phosphorus, <hi>that glorious Sunne himselfe did arise in the Horizon of our humanitie, dispersing the beames of his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and manifesting himselfe to be that onely light of the world, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to them that sit in the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of darknesse, for comfort and
<pb facs="4"/>
illumination, and to the ioy of all in heauen and earth, the Lambe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe onely opening that sealed Booke, and vnfolding the truth of former hid mysteries.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Then that Ladder of Heauen, and Leader to glory, was more brightly seene, then</hi> Iacob <hi>saw the same formerly in a dreame. Then that true Tree of Life planted in the earth of our nature, was plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viewed without the limits of that heauenly Paradise. Then that heauenly Manna which the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gaue from aboue, most aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly offered it selfe, vnto the refreshment of all hungring Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites. And that blessed Rock from Citie to Citie, and place to place
<pb facs="4"/>
following them, most cleerely gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed out the comfortable waters of Life, for euery one to drinke, and neuer to thirst after. Then the true curing Serpent was graciously re-erected on high for all men to behold with the eye of Faith, and then all the Mosaicall sacrifices, and rudimentall Rites, which like the</hi> Baptist, <hi>pointed out</hi> Christ Iesus <hi>to bee that Lambe of God that takes away the sinnes of the world, vnfolded themselues in their former darke shaddowish sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, and while they remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in vigour, albeit (like</hi> Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>before his sonnes birth) they were dumbe and obscure signers, yet ceasing, and in their departure
<pb facs="5"/>
(the substantiall body filling vp the roome) with their eternall fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, opening their mouth as it were, they said that which before they signed, and gaue a heartie congratulation and welcome to their accomplishing verity, as night giues place to day;</hi> Leui <hi>thus yeelding to a more excellent High Priest; and</hi> Hagar <hi>the bondwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, vnto her free Dame</hi> Sarah.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Herein how Euangelicall light hath discouered the meaning of Legall obscuritie; and how</hi> Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons <hi>Bells sounded neuer but Christ Iesus and him Crucified; nor his siluer Trumpets, but the ioyfull Iubile of soules freedome; his many sacrifices pointing out
<pb facs="5"/>
that one all-sufficient: And how the successiue diuersitie of types of sundry things, places, persons, and actions, &amp;c. from time to time couchedly involued, and cunningly conueyed, the blessed mysterie and deepe secret of the abysse of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>searchable loue to mankinde, and extense of mercy past comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as by secret water-spouts from posterity to posterity, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the vigorous hope of the faithfull; who with</hi> Simeon <hi>longed to see the Saluation of the Lord Herein, I say, the paines that I haue taken, is briefely (for the case of the Reader) to point onely (as it were) at the same in order as they occurre in Scripture, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>with succinct breuity to auoid tediousnes, as great plainnesse and perspicuitie as I could, to auoid</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Marke.</note>
      <hi>obscurenesse. And comparing some things for conueniencie of case onely (which prettily may be so compared) wherein I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the purpose of the Holy Ghost a typicall resemblance euer, of any answerable verity is not to be sought. And keeping still in all (I hope) the Analogy of faith, as the right measure of the Temple, the patterne on the Mount, and iust Ballance of the Sanctuary.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>This Treatise then (Right Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and most worthy Prelate) as a testimony of my most indeared affection, I haue dedicate to your
<pb facs="6"/>
Lordship, and shrowded the same vnder the wings of your Learned patrocinie, by experience hauing in my own person found (especially at your Lordships late beeing in</hi> Scotland) <hi>yet more thē courteous regard, and most kinde respectiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse euer vsuall by your Lordship towards all, but chiefely towards those who are Fellow-labourers in the Sacred dispensation af that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mysterie with you: Whereby not onely I, but the hearts of many with me, who had that happy occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of your Lordships acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, are so warmed (though vnder a cold Climate) and infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the Reuerend memory of your Lordships humanitie, and
<pb facs="7"/>
other singular holy vertues, and rare gifts (wherewith your good GOD hath indued you; and which as a strong chaine hath linked so that singular regard of your Prince vnto you, as that sooner, I perswade my selfe, their bodies shall beginne to resolue into ashes, then that fire of affection in their conquered and captiued hearts shall cease, to bee vigorous and burne.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>As some sparkles then, (my Lord) hereof for my part, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and bursting forth towards the place of your Lordships re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidence, receiue these succinct Lucubrations, consecrate to your Lordships Name: subiected to
<pb facs="7"/>
your Censure, and to bee disposed as your Lordship shall thinke fit thereof. Of whose most gentle and gracious acceptation, as I rest assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: So, as for others, I hope, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian loue, and charitable affection shall be my Censurer of all, regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding chiefely my honest ayme here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And where others are inabled to do better, or to amend my Labours, beseeching the Lord to inable them more &amp; more, and to enlighten my minde with them, that mine eyes being anointed with the eye-salue of his Spirit, with</hi> Dauid <hi>I may know the secrets of his Law, and that neither I may enuy their rich gift with an euill eye, nor yet despise my owne poore mite with a
<pb facs="8"/>
wicked heart: but indeuouring to gaine something with my small Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vnto my bountifull Master, I may not incur neither the bitter reproofe, nor deserued iudgement of an euil or vnprofitable seruant at his hands. Beseeching which God to thrust out many faithfull Laborers into his Haruest, and to continue your Lordship in a long and happy life, with a success-full blessing vpon your Lordships go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment &amp; trauels, to the cōfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> and edification of his Church, rests</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships in all hearty and most affectionate duty in Christ,
WILLIAM GVILD</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>