<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>An Aduertisement vnto the Reader.</title>
           <author>Plattes, Gabriel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103067_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15527</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25796</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103067</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>An Aduertisement vnto the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Plattes, Gabriel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Saints by calling: or Called to be saints : A godly treatise of our holy calling to Christ, by the gospell. VVith the seuerall gifts proper vnto the called: and their counterfeits in the hypocrites which are not partakers of this effectuall calling. Written by Thomas Wilson minister of Gods word, at S. Georges Church in Canterbury</title>
                 <author>Wilson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 413, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>An Aduertisement vnto the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>COurteous and Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; there bee foure seuerall things which I purposed to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in this whole Dialogue &amp; Treatise. First, for the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to deliuer so neere as my iudgement could attaine, all those workes of the Spirit, euen in their particulars, which are peculiar vnto Gods elect children, who liue to be partakers of an outward effectuall Calling: that when the manifold riches of Christ his grace should be in some sort discouered and laide foorth to their eye to view and looke vpon them, it might stir them vp to a marueilous loue and thankefulnesse towards him, who hath called them to such riches &amp; honour: Also, that finding themselues endued and blessed with such graces as they shall learn from the Word, to belong onely to the chosen of God, it may settle
<pb facs="6"/>
them in the perswasion and full assurance of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection to life.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Secondly, for the Manner: Because euerie one of the workes of Christ in his elect, hath his counterfet in the reprobate, which liue in the Church, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take onely in a generall vocation; therefore I haue somewhat endeauoured to descry what the truth of euerie grace wrought in Gods Children, and to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer it from that apparence and shadow which an Hypocrite hath of the same grace; for this purpose, that whether the godly Reader would proue himselfe and make triall of his owne sincerity, either in the whole worke of Christianity, or in some special part or duty thereof, heere he may find what may further him.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Thirdly, for the Order, I haue followed so precise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and truly, as euer my skill would direct mee; that very order of causes in this whole Treatise, which God himselfe doth keepe, in the bestowing and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the graces, propounding them to the Reader to be considered, as they haue necessary and naturall coherence one with another, and dependance one vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another; setting causes afore effects, and giuing cheefe place to the principall effects. By this meanes the carefull Christian in the search of himselfe, shall by effects be able to finde out causes, the roote by the
<pb facs="6"/>
fruites, and how to value each grace and fruite, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his proper worth. Also, the Conscionable Minister, which hath not (as yet) thought vpon such an order, and shall approue of this as good &amp; sound, may in his teaching helpe himselfe to deliuer such things first, as by order of nature ought to haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency, for the better edification of their hearers.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Finally, as touching the Persons for whose sake I wrote this Dialogue; I meant it, though not onely, yet cheefly for the godly vnlettered Christians, to further them in this knowledge, how to examine their owne estate before God. As for the more Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they can helpe themselues in this part of our Christian science: or else may fetch direction from other manner of Lights then mine. Whatsoeuer it is that I haue performed, I pray thee good Reader take it in good part, make thy profit of it, and praise God for all. Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord,
Thomas Wilson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>