<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣thy, my much Honoured friend, Syr Christopher Hatton, Knight of the Ho∣nourable Order of the Bath.</title>
           <author>Gibbons, Orlando</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103065_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01689</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11826</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103065</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVOR∣thy, my much Honoured friend, Syr Christopher Hatton, Knight of the Ho∣nourable Order of the Bath.</title>
                 <author>Gibbons, Orlando</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first set of madrigals and mottets of 5. parts : apt for viols and voyces. Newly composed by Orlando Gibbons, Batcheler of Musicke, and organist of his Maiesties honourable chappell in ordinarie</title>
                 <author>Gibbons, Orlando</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Barley, William, Assignee(s etc.) of.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>5 parts books (4, xx, 4, xx, 4, xx, 4, xx, 4, xx pages), 1 coat of arms, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, my much Honoured friend, Syr <hi>Christopher Hatton,</hi> Knight of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Order of the Bath.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SYR:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is proportion that beautifies euery thing, this whole V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerse consists of it, and <hi>Musicke</hi> is measured by it, which I haue endeauoured to obserue in the composition of these few Ayres, but cannot in their Dedication: for when I compare your many fauours with my demerits, your curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Eare with these harsh Notes, there appeares so plaine a disproportion betweene them, that I am afraid, least in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring to your Patronage Songs in some tune, my action heerein should be out of all tune; yet haue I made bould to honour them with your Name, that the world may take notice, rather of my want of abilitie, then good-will to be gratefull. By which little outward demonstration, you may easily guesse at the greatnesse of my inward affection, as skilfull <hi>Geometricians</hi> doe obserue the true stature of the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by sight of the foote onely. Experience tels vs that Songs of this Nature are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually esteemed as they are well or ill performed, which excellent grace I am sure your vnequalled loue vnto <hi>Musicke</hi> will not suffer them to want, that the Author (whom you no lesse loue) may be free from disgrace. They were most of them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed in your owne house, and doe therefore properly belong vnto you, as Lord of the Soile; the language they speake you prouided them, I onely furnished them with Tongues to vtter the same: they are like young Schollers newly entred, that at first sing very fearefully, it requires your Patience therefore to beare with their imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: they were taught to sing onely to delight you, and if you shall take any pleasure in them, they haue their end, and I my wish, a full recompence for my pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed labours, and a greater encouragement to present you with some future things more worthy your Patronage: till which opportunity, I rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours euer to command
Orlando Gibbons.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>