<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Ʋnto the Church and con∣gregation of God which is in L. Guido desi∣reth grace and peace, and the mercie of God, through Iesus Christ our Lorde: And perpe∣tually to perseuere in the knovvledge of the holy Gospell of the sonne of God. Amen.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103536_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12476</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103536</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Ʋnto the Church and con∣gregation of God which is in L. Guido desi∣reth grace and peace, and the mercie of God, through Iesus Christ our Lorde: And perpe∣tually to perseuere in the knovvledge of the holy Gospell of the sonne of God. Amen.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The staffe of Christian faith : profitable to all Christians, for to arme themselues agaynst the enimies of the Gospell: and also for to knowe the antiquitie of our holy fayth, and of the true Church. Gathered out of the vvorks of the ancient doctors of the church, and of the councels, and many other doctors, vvhose names you shall see here follovving. Translated out of Frenche into English, by Iohn Brooke of Ashe next Sandvviche. With a table to finde out all that which is contayned in the booke</title>
                 <author>Brès, Guy de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 382, 10 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Ʋnto the Church and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of God which is in L. Guido</hi> desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth grace and peace, and the mercie of God, through Iesus Christ our Lorde: And perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to perseuere in the knovvledge of the holy Gospell of the sonne of God. Amen.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>NOVVING AND CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the vvarre and combat that yee daylye suffer to mayntaine and keepe the true and pure Christian do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the ancient and true Church of God, agaynst a sort and heape of glorious decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, vvhich hyde and boast themselues vvith false ensignes, of the name and title of the auncient Church, and of the auncient Doctors: I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated vnto you (my vvelbeloued frendes) this present booke, entituled: The Staffe of the Faith, gathered out of the vvorkes of the auncient doctors of the churche, and of the counselles, and out of many authors: to the ende that thereby you may learne vvholy, to fight against your ennemies, vvith the same staffe vvith vvhich they doe fight agaynst you, that is to say, the auncientes. I doe not tell you hovv this staffe, shall keepe you from the danger of your ennemies only, I vvill content my selfe in speaking but one vvorde, touching the same, (that is to say) that you shall not only obtayne and get victory of your ennemies, but also send them avvay vvith their mouthes stopped. Therefore I desire you in Gods name, that ye be not slothfull nor negligent, to study therein often, and to haue those
<pb facs="5"/> sentences therein alledged readily at yovr fingers endes, that thereby the kingdome of Iesus Christe be auaunced, and the dominion of the deuilles and infidels destroyed and abolished.</p>
   <p>I doe knovve very vvell that manye people haue accustomed to saye, vvhen it is spoken vnto them of the auncients, speaking vvithout eyther iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or reason, in saying that as touching the Auncientes, they haue nothing to doe vvith them, for they vvvere men as they: but that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themselues only vvith the vvorde of God. I vvoulde not altogither denie or gainesaye them in that, if they vvould not reiect thereby God and his giftes, by thinking to reiect men and their doctrine. Therefore vve ought to take good heede vnto men vvhen they speake of themselues, and also vvhen God speaketh by them. The same vve may knovve, vvhen their doctrine is confirmable and agreeing to the rule of all right, vvhich is the vvord of God the doctrine of the prophets &amp; Apostles. Furthermore, vve vvould not haue you ignorant, that the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers haue ordayned and established a great many of ceremonies, and thinges in the churche respecting the time and personnes, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie of those that dayly come vnto the knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Gospell, asvvell of Ievves as of panims and Idolaters: But they haue done that onely but for a certaine time, to the ende they might dravve to the Gospell all nations, and let and stoppe the vvay of the Heritickes and ennemies of the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke faithe, from gayning and vvinning the vveake in faithe. For vve ought not to maruayle, if the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers haue done many thinges in that time,
<pb facs="5"/> vvhich novv can not serue, nor profite vs any thing at all, inasmuch as they haue serued but onely for their time. For the Apostles haue ordayned some thinges vvhich novve ought not to be follovved nor kept. As vve doe reade in the actes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, that the counsell that vvas celebrated by the Apostles in Ierusalem,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 15.</note> decreed that vve should ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staine from bloude, and from the fleshe of beastes that vvere strangled: VVe knovve vvell inough that this ordinance novv hath no more place, and is not in force among the christians,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Titus.</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</note> nor ought to haue, bicause that all thinges are cleane and purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through the vvorde and prayer. Then vvee see that that decree, vvhich hath bene decreed by the holy spirite &amp; by the Apostles, to haue bene made, bicause of the personnes, and to serue onely but for that time.</p>
   <p>Iudge novve, if an ordinance made by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles to support the infirmitie of men, hath bene set foorth, and aftervvardes abolished: vvhat oughte vve to iudge of those vvhich are of lesse importance vvhich haue bene ordayned by men, a great deale inferior and of lesse estimation then the Apostles? There is no doubt, that forasmuch as they haue bene ordayned to serue onely for that time, that novve vve may let them alone and forsake them, bicause that there is neyther Ievves nor Turkes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, but christians, at the least as they saye.</p>
   <p>Also vve ought not vpon this to holde our peace or hide the vnshamelesse malice of many, vvho (ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelesse calling themselues christians) vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of antiquitie, and of the auncient doctors, doe forge and inuent of their ovvne vvicked and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye
<pb facs="6"/> brayne, naughty and most detestable errors: and aftervvard say that the auncient fathers haue vvritten so, and preached so: and by that meanes make the poore vvorld being seduced to beleeue it. And yet the malice is so great in them, that all they that vvill not receiue and allovve, that vvhich their brayne hath inuented vnder the name of holy men, they crye after them vvith open mouth, to the fire, to the fire vvith the Heritickes. They reiecte the doctrine of the fathers. Alas O my God and Lord thou knovvest our hearts: and the heartes of these lyers, that vve doe not desire but that in all and through all, be it through life or death, that thy son Iesus Christ, and his doctrine, may be onely recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, loued and vvorshipped: And for this are vve apoynted as sheepe to be slayne: vve are nought set by, mocked, beaten, banished, chased from tovvne to tovvne: To be short vve are esteemed and counted as the most vile &amp; stinking filthynesse of all the vvorld, troden dovvne vnderneth the feete of the vvorldlinges: But for all that vve possesse our soules in patience, looking for the righteous Iudge vvhich vvill iudge all the vvorld, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the doctrine of men, but according to hys holy vvorde, for vvhich vve are had novve in suche abhomination to the vvorlde.</p>
   <p>Furthermore they vvhich dayly accuse vs vvith so greate rage and furye, against the auncient doctrine of the Apostles and Doctors, shall at the last ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knovvledge their malice and liuing, that they haue declared in their bookes, corrupting and marring the bookes of the auncient fathers of the churche: If I durst, I vvould gladly name one vvho in that
<pb facs="6"/> occupation or science hath serued out his prenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyppe, for that cause is called our maister, in his booke that he hath intituled. The bouckler of the faithe: vvherein he declareth the subtiltie of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and craft, alledging the auncient Doctors in Latine, after translating them into Frenche, and at euery place where he found Sacrificium, or the like manner of speaking, in steade to put in sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, or holy mysterie, he hath translated them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvayes the holy mysterie of the Masse, and so by that meanes they finde that vvorde Masse in the bookes of those good fathers, vvhich they neuer thought nor did. I beleeue he thought that his booke should not come but only in the handes of yong children, or else he thought that he had to doe but vvith beastes like vnto himselfe. There is no man though he haue but small iudgement and vnderstanding, vvhich reading that booke, but that he may see at the first dashe hovv he lyeth, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayeth and reuoketh it agayne, and neuerthelesse he is heard and accounted as halfe a God: not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the poorest sort, but of the greatest in the vvorlde. In the meane time vve ought not to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle at this, that such gallants haue bene so hardy and ouerbolde, forasmuch as they vvere supported and maintayned of Kings, Emperors, Princes, and Magistrates, and that they vvere the best vvelcome to their Court.</p>
   <p>I remember that I haue reade in the Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call histories, that in the time of the auncient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,<note place="margin">Euseb. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi>
      </note> there vvere abusers and seducers of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that sovved their pestilent venim amongst the doctrine of the auncients: Of that Denise bishop
<pb facs="7"/> of Corinth complayned very much, saying, that many haue sovvn in his Epistles much vvicked doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. Therefore thinke, that if they haue bene so hardy and bolde that they durst corrupt the vvry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges of the auncientes, yea vvhilest they vvere yet aliue. VVhat vvill they doe novve? at the least they vvill doe asmuch, as their auncient fathers, that is to saye those Apostates ennemies of the fathers.</p>
   <p>Novv notvvithstanding their shamelesse malyce they rebuke and checke vs vvith a vvhores face, that vve are ennemies of the fathers, despisers and contemners of their doctrine, and disturbers of the vvorld. I vvould to God that they vvould permitte and suffer vs to compare our doctrine openly, and before all the vvorld vvith theirs, to the end that all men might knovve vvho be the contemners and ennemies of the fathers: somuch it vvantith that vve should be found condemners and ennemies of those good fathers, that altogither it vvoulde be seene that the same doctrine that vve hold &amp; keepe at this day, is the very same for vvhiche manye of those good fathers haue shead their bloud: and vvould shead it, if they vvere novve aliue.</p>
   <p>It seemeth that the same is not true that I haue spoken, that if the fathers vvere yet aliue, that men vvould put them cruelly to death, as most vvicked Heritickes. Yea they vvhich at this daye doe boste and brag them selues to be their obedient children, and make bucklers of their bookes.</p>
   <p>Vnderstand and hold fast in minde (dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) behold this present booke may serue vs for a certayne argument, of that vvhich is composed and faithfully gathered togither, out of the very bookes
<pb facs="7"/> of the auncient Doctors: That if I vvould present this present booke (vvherein there is nothing in it of mine, but altogither of the auncientes) for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of my faith to those enemies of the fathers, I doubt not but presently I should be as a moste vvicked Heretick, condemned to be burned quicke into ashes. Novve see (dearely beloued) and iudge iustly before God according to your ovvn consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, vvhether vve be the ennmies of the fathers or they.</p>
   <p>The auncient fathers haue sayde that the breade of the supper abideth alvvayes breade, not being transubstantiated or chaunged: I doe demaund of you in good faith, vvherefore or vvhat is the cause that they shead dayly so abundantly the bloude of the poore children of God? Is it not vpon this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poynte, or for this cause, that the fathers haue beleeued and mayntayned vvith a common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, as you shall see in that booke vpon the arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Lordes supper? I leaue it to your ovvne iudgement. Furthermore vve doe reade that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers, of vvhom these here doe aduance, and bost them selues to keepe and mayntayne their doctrine, haue broken in peeces the images of Iesus Christe, and of the Saintes, that haue bene set vp in the temple of the christians, saying that it is against the Christian doctrine to haue Images in the Church.</p>
   <p>VVhat is he that doubteth, that if the good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vvere yet liuing, and that they shoulde so breake the Images as they did in that time, but that they shoulde be out of hande, or vvith all speede condemned as heretickes to be burned, yea if they
<pb facs="8"/> escaped so. For vve do see many dayly vvhich doe not escape so good cheape, but they haue done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them all the torments and paynes that these vvorshippers of the fathers can inuent or imagin.</p>
   <p>Then vvhen you shall reade the doctrine of the fathers contayned in this present booke, iudge vvhether it may be confessed and maintayned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly before these vvorshippers of the fathers vvithout daunger of lyfe. In the meane time, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire you (my deare brethren) that ye feare not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon your bodie and lyfe, for a doctrine so iust, holy, and good: and let vs reioyce in this, that vve holde the true auncient doctrine of the Prophets, Apostles and Doctors of the Church.</p>
   <p>And as touching you, O ye Princes, Iudges, and Magistrates, betvveene vvhose handes this present booke shall happen to fall: I desire and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you, in the name of the liuing God, and of his sonne Iesus Christ our Lorde vvhich hath shed out all his bloud vpon the crosse for the loue of vs, that you doe giue right iudgement vpon the poore faithfull people, of vvhome your prisons are at this time full, through the furor and madnesse of those vvorshippers of the fathers, and bee no more the hangmen of that vvicked Vermine: for it is not counted a thing honest nor meete among men, that the Kings, Emperours, Princes, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates shoulde bee made the hangmen of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>Sapi.</hi> 6.</note>Be ye then more ashamed than euer you vvere, bicause that you beare the name of God, and the povver to gouerne the people is giuen you from God, not for to abuse it in punishing the good, and
<pb facs="8"/> defending the vvicked, but to maintayne and ayde the good, and to punish the vvicked (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles haue taught vs.) But alas my God, into vvhat blindenesse is the vvorlde fallen into, to esteeme and thinke that they vvhich holde and keepe the true auncient doctrine are heretikes.</p>
   <p>O you Iudges and Magistrates, doe you not see dayly in your prisons, the poore children of God, to eate and drinke very scarsly bread and vvater, and to be cast most vilely and filthily into a lovve dunge on vvith the venimous beastes, lying as the poore beastes vpon a little stravve hauing their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and legges broken vvith the racke?</p>
   <p>Doe you not see (I say) on the other side those goodly masters vvhich beare such great zeale to the auncient fathers, to haue their bellye altogither stuffed vvith vvine and delicate fare, coming forth from their bankets and feastes vvith a face as red as fire, or like to a Butchers boule, comming forth to passe avvaye the time, for to examine the poore faythfull people, vvhich are not sought for at the table vvhere good cheare is, but in a most filthie and darke dungeon: they are poore children of God tyed and bounde vvith chaynes, vvith a pale face and thinne cheekes, brought before those fat bellies and firie faces through their ouermuche drinking and quaffing of vvine, and the first vvords they speake is, come hither thou vvicked here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, avvay thou dāned seducer of the people, thou hast the deuil vvithin thee. And assone as the pore children of God did thinke to haue spoken for their defence, the fatte bellies quicklye put their hands to their Bible, but it is another Bible than the olde
<pb facs="9"/> olde or nevve testament: For they can do nothing but prouide faggots, and crie to the fire, to the fire vvith those vvicked heretickes, I knovve not vvhere they haue learned to doe so. Haue they lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that of the Prophetes and Apostles? It appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth no. Neyther haue they learned it of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers. For they shall finde vvithin this present booke, that they haue spoken and done altogither othervvise: therefore they declare that it is a rage and a madnesse that they haue conceyued against the truth for to extinguishe and abolishe it vtterly, and all those that maintaine it: For libertie to speake is taken from vs. Those that vvould speake, their tongues are cut out of their heades? and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervvardes are burned.</p>
   <p>In the meane time O ye Iudges and Magistrates, vvhich haue the publicke charge, haue regard from henceforth vvhat you doe in condemning them to death. You cannot condemne them to death ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye condemne all the good and auncient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to death vvith them. VVhat order doe you call this to condemne to death as Heretickes the Saintes and their doctrine, vnto vvhom they crye and dayly pray vnto in their Letanie, saying, O Sancte Augustine, O Sancte Cypriane, O Sancte Hieronime. &amp;c. Ora pro nobis, that is to say, O Saint Augustine, O Saint Cyprian, O Saint Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, and so consequently of the other, pray for vs. And in the meane time they condemne them, and their vvritinges, and all those that follovve theyr doctrine to be burned, as the experience dothe dayly teach vs.</p>
   <p>Therefore ye that Iudge the people haue a good
<pb facs="9"/> respect vnto that that you haue to doe: for it is not onely vnto vs that you doe adresse your selues, but also to the sonne of God, vvhich hath sayd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, he that toucheth you, toucheth the apple or sight of mine eye. The same hath bene vvell shevv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Paule, VVhen he persecuted the poore fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, crying from heauen after him,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 9.</note> Saule Saule vvhy persecutest thou me? he did not persecute him in his ovvne person, but he persecuted him in his members, vvhich are all the faithfull that beleue in him.</p>
   <p>Euen so (my deare brethren) vve shall rest in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and shall not be ashamed to be condemned vvith all those good and auncient fathers of the church, and not onely vvith them, but also vvith all the Prophets and Apostles. Then vvhen you see your selues bound and brought before the Iudges, to receiue sentence of death and condemnation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you, behold vvith you the Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles and the auncient doctors bound vvith you to be condemned in the same torment. Be ye ioyfull and reioyce to be enrovvled in their bande, for to beare vvith them, the yoke of Iesus Christ? perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere valiantly in the doctrine that you haue already receiued, for no man can hurt you. Ought vve not greatly to reioyce of this, that the persecuting ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes can doe our bodyes no more hurt, then a vvolfe or theefe of the vvoods, vvhich can but murther or kill vs. Let vs reioyce, for our names are vvritten in heauen. VVe haue yet this good turne (thankes be vnto our good God therefore) that the persecutors can do vnto vs no vvorse then to to put and place vs vvith our good God in the
<pb facs="10"/> company of Angelles and all the blessed soules in heauen.</p>
   <p>VVhat is he that vvould not desire to goe playe vvith so happy a company eternally and vvithout ende?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> Yea to be in glory vvhich the eye hath not seene, and eare hath not heard, neyther hath entred into mans minde, the thinges vvhich God hath prepared to such as loue him.</p>
   <p>Againe, forasmuch as they esteeme and court vs so vvicked and abhominable, and crye so spitefully after vs, as after the vvickedest people of all the vvorld, to make vs and our doctrine odious vnto the people: They commaund them not to heare or harken vnto vs, they make the simple people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, vvhen they haue them vnder confession, that if they doe not accuse vs, they shall be damned.</p>
   <p>Their craft, subtiltye and enuye agaynste the truth is to be maruayled at. In the meane time I vvould vvillingly that they vvould accord and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree vvith vs to conferre their doctrine vvith ours, their crosse and persecution vvith ours, their lyfe vvith ours, theyr church vvith ours: By that means vve should plainly see vvhether they be the childrē of God or vve. First of all haue not vve the baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me purely administred, as vve doe reade that the Apostles haue administred it vvithout any inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, but onely according to the vvord of God? Let one reade the Scriptures, and he shall see vvho it is that hath added to the Sacramentes, eyther vve or they.</p>
   <p>Furthermore let men behold the persecutions that they suffer for their doctrine, the number is soone counted, for there is not one vvhich hath
<pb facs="10"/> suffred death for their doctrine: neuerthelesse Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ hath promised that his church shal haue persecution in the vvorld, saying, ye shall be hated of all men for my name.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.</note> Hovv can they be hated of all men sith that they be in all places the best vvelcome? Hovv commeth it that one shoulde thinke to doe sacrifice vnto God in putting them to death? I did neuer knovve any.</p>
   <p>I doe accord and agree in this, that they are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times taken prisoners, but it is in the good feastes and bankettes, and in the best seates of the table: and vvhereas the children of God are bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vvith fire, they here are burned throughe the heate of VVine. Their innocent fleshe is hevven and cut in peeces, but it is at the table vpon their treachers. They are rotten and consumed vvith the Goute of Naples, insomuch that they fall in peces.</p>
   <p>They are melted and melted againe many times in a yeere. Besides all the dangers they put them selues into both day and night to runne after other mens vvyues, in great danger of their life. And yet some vvill say that they are not persecuted: It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that they be, for one shall see a great many more among them to dye Martyrs, of the paines that vve did speake of euen novv, then of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall diseases or sicknesses. They are then Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres, no man can denie, yea, but it is of the diuell: and vvhat is he that doubteth of it?</p>
   <p>And as concerning their life it is knovven vvell inough and manyfested vnto all men: Their good vvorkes and godly fruites vvhat it bringeth in all places, destroying and corrupting all the vvorlde, asvvell spiritually as corporally. This I am sure of,
<pb facs="11"/> that forasmuch as I haue touched and medled but vvith the doore of their kitchin, they vvill say I am a vvicked Hereticke: But vvhat then? Shoulde I hold my peace for their menaces and iniuries? No, no, God forbid, but rather I vvill crye vvith open mouth after them, bicause they haue so corrupted and destroyed the Lordes Vineyard.</p>
   <p>Alas, alas, my God vvhat is he that ought not but to lament and vveepe vvith bloudy teares, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the vvorld to be so led into the bottome of hell, so many poore soules led to perdition. O Lord regard thy poore people, haue some pitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion on them, for vvhom thy sonne our Lorde Iesus Christ hath offred to thee his body and bloud in a sacrifice: and suffer not that thy poore sheepe be so put as a pray for to be deuoured of al beastes.</p>
   <p>For vve are dayly assaulted vvith so many enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, that sathan riseth agaynst vs, for to make vs forsake and abandon our Lord Iesus Christ, and to renounce his Gospell: One day vve haue vvarre agaynst the Heretickes Anabaptistes, an other day agaynst Libertines, Epicures, Arians, Dauidistes, and agaynst dissemblers, and consequently, against the vvorshippers of the fathers, through vvhose zeale the children of God are put to death. Haue not vve then great neede of vveapons? It appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth yea, if vve vvould not be taken in their snares, as many at this day are, through the iust iudgement of God.</p>
   <p>Therefore if there be any time to pray, or to vvatch, it is novve: Let vs then vvatch and praye, to the end vve may auoyde all those dangers, and perseuer and continevve to the ende.</p>
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <p>You haue bene the first of your citie (dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) I also doe hope in the Lord you shall not be the last: But as you haue bene vntill novv the example and myrror of the poore ignorant people, to dravve them to the true light of the spirite, I doe hope through the grace of God, that nothing shall hinder you to continevve vnto the end on so holy a vvorke.</p>
   <p>For the poore ignorant people seeing the peace and vnitie, and the promptnesse and good courage that is in you to receiue the holy doctrine, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strayned through your holy life and conuersation to come vnto the knovvledge of Iesus Christ, and consequently to saluation. Forasmuch then as the Lord doth vnto you dayly so much good, or shevv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto you so much of his grace, shevving vnto you from day to day his maruaylous vvorkes, set to so your handes in the vvorke of the Lord, so long as he giueth you time and life, that you doe not leaue for your children that shall come after you, an euill example of life: but instruct them in that holy doctrine that you haue receiued, to the ende they may knovve after your death, that they had fathers and mothers that feared God, and vvell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed in his vvord, and that they haue not recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the gospell in their mouthe onely, but also in their handes. And that they vvere not dissemblers, but true confessors of the name of God.</p>
   <p>Dispose and bestovve then vvhilest you haue time so vvell your affayres, and businesse according to the meanes as God hath giuen you, that youre successors may haue none occasion to complayne, that you haue left them an euill example: That
<pb facs="12"/> they say not after that you are dead, vve haue had parents &amp; ancesters, vvhich haue had great knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, but they feared more to lose the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytie and freendship of the vvorlde then of God.</p>
   <p>O hovv much ought you to feare the same, for it vvill turne to your great confusion.</p>
   <p>Remember also that vvhich the Apostle spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.</note> saying, if there be any that prouideth not for his ovvne, and namely for them of his housholde, the same denieth the faithe, and is vvorse then an infidel. Therefore all faithfull people ought to take god heede and marke vvell those vvordes, for it is a great euill to denye the fayth.</p>
   <p>Take good heede you be not an offence to any man, I doe meane in doing euil, be gentle curteous &amp; mercifull the one to the other, not rendring euill for euill,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.</note> but render good for the euill. Liue so holy that if men vvold punish &amp; persecute you, that they doe not punish any thing in you but righteousnes, and good life. And in that doing you shall declare your selues to be the children of God. VVatch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvayes, praying that you be made vvorthy, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd al things that are to cōe, &amp; that you may stād before the son of God, after the end of your dayes.</p>
   <p>I beseeche our good God and father, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his great goodnesse &amp; mercy hath done so much good for vs, to adopt vs for his children to the eternall inheritance of heauen, that it woulde please him through his goodnes to ioyne and knit you in such sort togither (my dearly beloued bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and sisters) through the bonde of his holy spirite, which by the same will gouerne and leade you to eternall life. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>