<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS Epistle Introductory to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103545_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02362</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12496</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103545</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS Epistle Introductory to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Child-birth or, The happy deliuerie of vvomen : VVherein is set downe the gouernment of women. In the time of their breeding childe: of their trauaile, both naturall, and contrary to nature: and of their lying in. Together with the diseases, which happen to women in those times, and the meanes to helpe them. To which is added, a treatise of the diseases of infants, and young children: with the cure of them. Written in French by Iames Guillimeau the French Kings chirurgion</title>
                 <author>Guillemeau, Jacques</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Bill, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 247, 15, 118 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS Epistle Introductory to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough that man be the most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect &amp; absolute of all other cretures, neuerthelesse, so weake is he by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; so subiect to infinite infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that Diuine <hi>Hippocrates</hi> hath urged him, to be euen sicknes it selfe from his very birth: He is not fit (saith he) to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in any businesse while be sucketh: because h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e wholly depends vpon the helpe of another: afterward when he comes to more yeares, hee grows stubborne, and vnruly, and wants a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ster to giue him instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Againe, when he is growne to the prime of his age, hee becomes audacious and proud. At last in his declining time, he falls into misery, hauing nothing left him, but the remembrance of his labours ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pliny</hi> noteth, and experience shews it to be true that the ill sent only of a Candle new put foorth, is enough to destroy a child in the mothers wombe, so that shee may be forced to fall in trauaile, and be deliuered before her time, vnlesse her strength be the greater to resist the
<pb facs="4"/>
offence. And although the child stay the full time that nature hath prefixed him: yet commonly he is not able to get foorth, or come safely into the Worlde (yea though the birth be naturall) without the helpe not onely of the Mother, and himselfe: but also of the Mid-wife and other women about her ready to receiue and cherish him: And which is worst of all; if he be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced awry, or else be weake and faint, or else if the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife be at the farthest of her skill; then if they will saue the child, and so consequently the mother from death: they must call a Chirurgion to deliuer her, and bring the child into the world: which (that I may touch it by the way without taxing any) is commonly done too late eyther through the wilfulnesse of the kinsfolks, or obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy of the Midwiues.</p>
   <p>But grant that the childe comes into the world of it selfe, without the helpe either of Chirurgion or Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife: yet (as it is commonly said) he drawes his death after him: the which may be plainely perceiued by the cryes and laments which he maketh as soone as he seeth the light, as if hce craued for helpe and succour. For if he should continue in that case that hee comes from his mothers wombe, clogged with his bed or after-birth, without doubt this bedde being putrified, would infect the child, and at length kill it. Besides, oftentimes if there were not helpe to make a free passage, in the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament, yard, or other naturall places, that are some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times closed vp, there could neither sustenance be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, nor excrements expelled, which would cause the child to be stifled, and choked vp.</p>
   <p>Many times also the head, and other parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,
<pb facs="4"/>
(as the bones and legges) happen to be ill shapen, yea broken and out of ioint, which would neuer come of themselues, into their proper and naturall place. There, then is it necessary that the Chirurgion vse his helpfull and skilfull hand: So that euery man may plainly see the necessity and Antiquity of this worke: since that the first practise in Chirurgery, that euer was done in the world, was the <hi>Omphalotomia,</hi> or cutting of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, which <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> practised on their first child.</p>
   <p>These therefore are the Motiues that haue induced me to publish this discourse, and therin to treat of such diseases as happen to women with child.</p>
   <p>And heerein I haue endeuoured to helpe them both in their naturall, and extraordinary trauaile: and to ease them in all such accidents, as may happen vnto them in their childbed: being the rather incited there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, by reading the complaints of Women, related by <hi>Soranus. O malè occupatum virorum genus! oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidimur nos non morimur: &amp; ab illis qui inter vos peritissimi existimantur perperam curatae. Vos de qualibet leuissimâ vestratum affectionum, libros ex libris facientes, bibliothecas Voluminibus onera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis; de nostris intereà diris et difficillimis cruciatibus nullâ vel exiguâ mentione facta.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>O men, how ill doe you bestow your time, and paines! Alas, wee women die not, but are tormented euen to death: For those that are accounted the most expert and skilfull among you, take not that care of vs which they should: you fill whole Libraries with large volumes &amp; writings of euerie light and triuiall disease of your
<pb facs="5"/>
owne making little or no mention at all, of our cruell and insupportable torments.</p>
   <p>I had purposed aboue fifteene yeares since, to haue written somwhat concerning this subiect in my books of Chirurgery: but hauing more maturely considered thereof, I thought it fitter to write a Treatise of it by it selfe: which it deserueth both for the difficultie of the subiect, and for the variety of the matter which I was desirous to obserue therein: And indeede this worke excelleth all other, which are practised vppon the body of man: whether ye respect the Antiquity, Necessi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y, or dexterity thereof.</p>
   <p>For the Antiquitie: without doubt the first worke in Chirurgery, that euer was in the worlde, was the cutting of the Nauell which, (as is saide before) <hi>Adam</hi> practised vppon his first borne.</p>
   <p>Concerning the necessity: some perhaps may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, that the bringing a bed of women, is not so necessary a worke as these following:</p>
   <p>To stay the fluxe of bloud, whether it bee in veine or Arterie; to vse the Trepan; to open the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyema,</hi> or suppuration in the breast; to cut one that hath the Dropsie; or to let bloud skilfullie: For the fluxe of bloud it may bee further saide, that vnlesse it bee stopped by leesing the bloud, the life also is endangered. But we must consider, that the bloud oftentimes staying of it selfe, and experience eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently shews, that nature, which is wise and prouident doth commonly restraine, and stop it. I haue beene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent in many skirmishes, (yet farre enough out of gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shot, where I haue dressed many that were wounded,
<pb facs="5"/>
who haue had the great vessels in many parts of their bodies cut, and bruised, hauing lost much bloud vppon the hurt, and yet it hath stopped and stayed of it selfe. Some wil say, that he who hath his scull cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ft by a wound is in danger of death, if the bloud that is shed vpon the Membrane, be not taken foorth by the meanes of the Trepan; For this bloud would be wholly putrified, and withall, corrupt the braine, the chiefe instrument of life, and whose vse is more then necessary. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing wee see, that in many, the filth and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ter comes foorth by the Nose, Eares, and mouth, without being trepanned, yea, that it passeth euen through their bones. Wee may say the like of such which haue the Dropsie, or <hi>Empyema,</hi> the breast of the one is full of Corruption, &amp; the others belly full of water: they both choake and stifle, vnlesse the Chirurgion make incision: in the one making a Paracentosis, in the other opening the Pleura.</p>
   <p>Yet neuerthelesse we see, that he which hath an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyema</hi> or suppuration doth oftentimes expell the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and filth, by the mouth or vrine (the waies beeing manifest, by which nature doth vnburthen her selfe) and he that hath the Dropsie auoideth the water, eyther by vrine, or stoole, yea, and by sweat, or by some little vent which Nature makes in some part of the body, as in the Nauell or legges: which we obserue by daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in many men: and therefore wee may perceiue, that these practises are not alwaies, so necessary, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite.</p>
   <p>For letting bloud; you will say, that hee hazards his life, (and that sodainely) who beeing oppressed, and
<pb facs="6"/>
troubled with a great paine of his head or side, is not speedily let bloud? because the bloud that boyleth in his veines, striueth onely to come foorth; I will answere: that Nature very often sends it foorth by the Nose, Mouth, Eies, and Eares: by stoole also, and other parts, disburthening her selfe to the sicke Mans ease and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: But It is not so in the deliuery of women; for if the entrance of the wombe be closed, (as it is seene in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers) whether it be naturally, by reason of a strong and thicke membrane, which shutteth vp the passage: or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wise, because some scarre happening there, hath hardned, and shrunke vp the sides of the necke of the said wombe: it would be impossible that nature should euer be able to separate, and breake through th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments: for as for the one, it is hard for a penne or quill to passe there, and for the other, you cannot put in a small probe through the little hole which is in the middest of the membrane. And yet I haue had the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience thereof in two women, which were neuer the lesse with child, as I will shew more at large heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. So that either the Chirurgions helpe must bee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, or else both the Mother and the child would die mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serablie.</p>
   <p>Some may obiect vnto mee, that the Mother might open the passage her selfe by tearing the parts so bound by the scarre, &amp; breaking through the said membrane? But what will you answere me, for her which hath her child turned awry and lies double in her wombe, and falleth into a Convulsion, or fluxe of bloud, or both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The Mother not being able eyther to turne it, or pull it foorth, especially if the head of it bee intangled
<pb facs="6"/>
and fastned betweene the bones of <hi>os Pubis,</hi> so that it is impossible to turne it, safe and sound, except the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion vse his industry and skill.</p>
   <p>Now for the dexteritie: there is no comparison be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene this and other practises; for there be no workes to be done in Chirurgery; where it is not necessary, to haue the benefit either of daylight or candle light, and the part which is to be handled, and dressed must be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent and laid open to the eye.</p>
   <p>Whereas contrariwise in this worke as well by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the company present, as also, least the woman should be afraid, the very entrance, whereby hee should put in his hand, they are constrained to hide: and then his hand being there, he must search for the child) how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer it be placed) not being able to see it. And if there be found two, three, or foure Children, yea, sometime fiue (as <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> reporteth, hee saw in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, a Woman that brought foorth to the number of threescore and fiue children, beeing deliuered euerie yeare of fiue) then (I say) I leaue you to iudge what skill and dexteritie the Chirurgion ought to vse in seeking them one after another if they come amisse.</p>
   <p>On the other side, as often as a woman is well deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the helpe and hand of the Chirurgion, there life is giuen to two, to wit: to the Mother and the childe. And therfore as this worthy man saith, <hi>In partu in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocatur dei auxilium: quaeritur enim &amp; parturien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; nascentis salus.</hi> When a woman is in trauaile, they call vppon God for helpe: because they desire to saue both the Mother and the child. Now in all other pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises, though they attaine to their wished end, yet can
<pb facs="7"/>
there bee but one onely saued at once. Whereby it may be iudged, that this practise is both for the Antiquitie, Necessitie, and dexterity thereof, the most laudable and commendable of all others.</p>
   <p>To make the which more easie, and the better to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct the young Chirurgion: I haue gathered together all that I could possibly, out of that which I haue obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this forty yeares and aboue, wherein I haue practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed it, and seene it practised, in the greatest families both within, and without this Kingdom, where, thanks be to God, good vse hath beene made of me. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all I haue not refused nor disdained to go vnto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, mooued partly by Charity, and partly to make my selfe more and more experienced therein.</p>
   <p>Hauing then conferred together, what eyther the Graecians and Latines both ancient and Moderne haue written, with that I haue beene able to obserue: and hauing reduced it all into one, I haue put it into French in fauour of those who are not so well learned, and haue not the knowledge of the Greeke or Latine tongues.</p>
   <p>Some will say (to diminish that little honor, which I might get by this my labour) that the Ancients haue written the greatest part heereof. But they shall learne from the mouth of this great Oracle, <hi>That there is no lesse witte and vnderstanding required, to bee able to iudge of Sciences formerly written, then to bee the first Authors of them.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I know Moreouer, that in the Doctrine, and much more in the phrase, some will find many things to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended. But I intreat the Reader, that he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it in as good part as I offer it him: and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
<pb facs="7"/>
exhort others, (that are more experienced, then I am: to doe better. Let them shew me my faults friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and I will not refuse, willingly to retract them: after the example of that diuine <hi>Hipocrates,</hi> who freely confessed his, saying openly, that <hi>he had gotten more dishonor, then either glory, or credit, by practising of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke.</hi>
   </p>
   <trailer>
      <figure>
</figure>
   </trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>