<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Fletcher, Phineas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103235_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01883</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12023</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103235</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, Phineas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fall of man, or the corruption of nature, proued by the light of our naturall reason : Which being the first ground and occasion of our Christian faith and religion, may likewise serue for the first step and degree of the naturall mans conuersion. First preached in a sermon, since enlarged, reduced to the forme of a treatise, and dedicated to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie. By Godfrey Goodman, her Maiesties chaplaine; Bachelor in Diuinitie, sometimes a member both of Trinitie Colledge in Cambridge, and of Saint Peters Colledge in Westminster</title>
                 <author>Goodman, Godfrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lee (Lea, Leigh), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 445, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
which I can so fitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend
to thy dailie and
continuall thoughts, as is the
meditation of Gods eternall
prouidence: how God (many infinite ages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the foundations of the earth were laid)
hath so ordained the course of this world, that
according to his owne iust appointment, all
things might succeed, and fall out in their due
times and seasons, either for the manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, or iustice▪ and this proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
not including a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>one the great necessary,
and naturall causes for the preseruation of
this vniuerse (suppose the motion and course
of the heauens, the preseruation of elements,
and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ike), but also to comprehend the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie
and free actions of man; so that God
<pb facs="13"/>
working in man works according to the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of mans nature, the freedom of mans will
subsisting with the ouer-ruling hand of Gods
prouidēce (for thus the causes are subordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted),
and God working in nature, doth no
way destroy his owne workes and that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
order, which he himselfe hath appointed
from the beginning.</p>
   <p>This prouidence doth not onely extend it
selfe to the great and most noble actions of
man (suppose the gouernment of kingdoms, &amp;
Empires, and whatsoeuer else may concerne
the life and saluation of man), but it descends
much lower, and as it cōprehends the care and
protection of dumbe beasts, so it stoopes euen
to the meanest and basest action of man, as the
falling downe of his haire, &amp;c. for wheresoeuer
God begins the action, and makes a creature
of nothing, there the same God with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting
and subsequent prouidence, must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
his own worke; for if it be left to it self,
it will againe returne vnto nothing.</p>
   <p>For euery man daily to consider, how God
hath dealt with him in his prouidence, I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
<pb facs="13"/>
it is a most Christian and godly medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
free from all superstitious vanitie, such
as I doe greatly recommend to thy practise,
such as I my selfe (sinfull and wretched man
that I am) haue cōtinually found in the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e
course of my life; what neither blind fortune,
nor the trickes and subtilties of wit, nor the
power and strength of man, could euer haue
compassed, I haue found that God in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence
hath freely wrought and effected. To
let passe all other things which are proper and
priuate to my selfe (if thou pleasest to peruse
this hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly Pamphlet), I thinke it not vnfit
to acquaint thee with this one accident.</p>
   <p>When first I made choice of my text, I had
thought to haue finished it within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe
of one houre, and hauing waded into it,
(supposing it to be a subiect which did well
deserue my labours), God did so dispose of it,
that this whole treatise doth onely containe
the first part or branch of the text. Secondly,
hauing gathered some obscure and straggling
notes for mine owne priuate vse, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>as I
may boldly say, that no man did euer more
<pb facs="14"/>
abhorre the Presse then my selfe; solemnly
protesting that I would sooner bee rackt or
prest to death for silence, rather thē any w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rds
of mine should once hinder the Presse▪ wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
from my heart, that there might be some
generall vacation, that new bookes might for
a time cease, that wee might finde at length
some leisure to peruse, reuiew, and reprint the
old Fathers; not contenting our selues with
patcht peeces, and broken sentences, but that
they might be heard ingeniously to speake for
themselues. For as we doe recommend the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
of Scriptures, so let vs not neglect the
best Commentaries and Expositions of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
that so the heate of our zeale, which
now is wholy wasted in controuersies and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions,
might then be spent in the practise
of pietie and deuotion, &amp;c. Notwithstanding
this my resolution, yet I was easily moued
(and the rather because I doe not remember
any booke written of this Subiect) to publish
this treatise.</p>
   <p>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> perusing whereof foure things there
are, wherewith I thinke fit to acquaint thee:
<pb facs="14"/>
first, though (I confesse) I haue herein made
vse of other mens workes, yet I did forbeare
to set downe any quotations, not that I desire
to wrong them, but that I think it vnfit, when
occasion did not moue me, or necessitie inforce
me, there to vse many needlesse and idle quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.
Secondly, though the punishment and
fall of man appeares chiefly and principally in
respect of his preparation to grace; yet my
selfe supposing at this time, that I speake only
to the naturall man, I thought fit to forbeare
speaking of that subiect, vntill first I should
make it appeare, that there is a sanctifying
grace, which is no way tyed or intailed to our
nature, which I haue reserued as a fit subiect
to bee treated of in the third branch of my
text. Thirdly, in the latter end of the second
part, speaking of the vanitie of the creatures,
if therein according to the condition of that
subiect, I shall somtimes intend (though much
against mine owne naturall disposition) in
this my long tedious discourse, to giue thee
some case and recreation, I hope it shall proue
no way offensiue, no not against the seuerest
<pb facs="15"/>
and strictest discipline of the Church; seeing I
can therein iustifie my selfe, by the practise
and president of most deuout Fathers, and
others most reuerend Diuines in all ages.
Fourthly, speaking there of many worldly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,
my intent is, onely to discouer them to
be but shadowes, in respect of a true blisse, that
so euery man might fall into some dislike with
himselfe; yet (I confesse) that many things
may, and ought still to be continued, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
the state and condition wherein we liue,
as namely <hi>the ceremonies of Honor,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
   <p>My desire is, that thou wouldest iudge of
the whole, by the whole; of the parts, by the
parts: for if the whole be taken together, I
hope I shall not be found wanting or defectiue
to my intended scope. If sometimes I prooue
somewhat obscure, God (who knowes the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets
of my heart) can beare me witnesse, how
free I am from the least affectation of obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie;
and therefore you must either blame my
weakenes, as not conceiuing things aright, or
not able sufficiently to expresse mine own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits:
or else you must consider the subiect
<pb facs="15"/>
matter whereof I write, which being very
difficult in it selfe, must necessarily admit
words of Art to vnfold it. To conclude, I
thought fit to continue this treatise, in the
same forme wherein it was first framed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting
that the God of truth should giue a
gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ter blessing to the relation of a truth; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
would my time or leisure permit me to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
it. And if it shall please God, that this
booke finde happie successe, so that some lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
good may thereby redound vnto Gods
Church, whereby I shall be the more incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
to proceede in those parts which yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine;
though I purpose to giue full satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
(as farre foorth as it lies in my power),
yet if possibly I can, I will tye my selfe to the
houre-glasse: ingeniously confessing, that as all
other builders are commonly mistaken in their
first workes, so my sel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e haue erred in laying
the foundations, or setting vp the porch of
this building.</p>
   <p>Thus being men of the same kind, brethren
descended from one stocke, but especially as
fellow-members incorporated into one body,
<pb facs="16"/>
vnder one misticall head <hi>Christ Iesus,</hi> in the
most holy communion of his Saints, well wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and praying for each other, <hi>I doe most
humbly and earnestly beseech God, that
either thou maist receiue some smal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
by my labours, or that thou maist be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow
thine own labours elsewhere more
profitably:</hi> and so committing thee
to his grace, prouidence and
protection, I rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Stapleford Abbats, <date>the 3. of
Iune, 1616.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Thine in all Christian
duty and seruice
<hi>Godfrey Goodman.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>