<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103779_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00261</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1035</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103779</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A bryefe and plaine declaracion of certayne sente [n] ces in this litle boke folowing : to satisfie the consciences of them that haue iudged me therby to be a fauourer of the Anabaptistes</title>
                 <author>I. B.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="20"/>
   <head>To the reader.</head>
   <p>NOthing cā be so plain, so manifest or op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>: but the cauillour (who seketh nothing els but doubtes) wil finde abosidaunce of mattier therin, to make the same, at the fyrste syght to appeare harde, obscure and darke. In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, he the lyueynge of the faythfull beleauers in C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>histe neuer so Godly and agreable to the truth, be it neuer so quiet, peaceable and ciuile: yet wyl the aduersaries fynde mattier ynough to deface it so, that the simple people shal iudge none other but that they be heretykes, &amp; they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> lyues, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ominable, theyr sayinges &amp; doynges sediciouse, disquiet and sclaunderouse. What man can deuyse to wryte more Godlye then Paule dyd to the Romaynes? And yet were there some that sayed he woulde haue men to synne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>o the intente that the mercye of God myght be the more aboundaunt in the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of the same Roma. iii. Who coulde leade so godly a lyfe, in suche austeritie, and harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse as Iohn the Baptiste dyd? And dyd not the Iewse saye that he had a dyuell in hym? To be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>fe, who conlde frequent the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of synners and misleueynge people, wyth so perfyte crample of lyueynge, haueynge so great force to drawe them from theyr wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to folowe his example, as Christe dyd? And dyd not the Pharisies reporte hym to be a frende and maynteyner of euyll lyuers and open s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ners? Math. ri. The same schole mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster that instructed these false detractours: hath also, and doeth daylye, instructe oure pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ame his documentes, and playne lections. The deuyll I saye, leaueth not hys olde pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>actyse, but kepeth his dearelye beloued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>re wythal. Yf any man preache or wryte of
<pb facs="20"/>
the iustificacion by fayeth, and doe therin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the vnworthinesse of vs and our workes whyche can desetue nothinge towarde our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification: incōtinent they c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e out vpon hym heretyke, he sayeth men shal be saued thought they lyue neuer so vngodlye. Vf he speake any thynge concernynge the abuse of the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and sacramentes: what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rclamacions do they make? howe do they reporte hym to be a sacramentarye? Yf he speake anye thynge of Baptisme: declaryng that neyther the holynes of the water, neyther of the oyle, can gyue the grace therin promised, and that the was shynge in the founte auayleth not them that obserue not the profession they make there: howe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable an anabaptiste shall he be compted? Of the supper of the Lorde, who can wryte or speake any thynge concernyng the abuse ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but he is charged wyth the vtter deniall of the same? That thou therfore (christen reader) mayst so wythdrawe thy credyt frō these false reporters, that thou wylte but once thynke it possible that they maye belye these men, whom they cal men of the newe learnyng: I haue set forth thys lyttle boke wherein thou mayste se what fayth they haue, that beare thys euyl re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte. And that thou mayste thereby be prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked fyrste to trye the spirites whether they be of God or not, and after to credyt them euen as thou shalte fynde them worthye. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe teacheth the, that it is not all golde that glyttereth, and we haue learned by experience, that it is not all Gospell that the prieste prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth. Trye the golde therfore by the toutche stone▪ &amp; the priestes preachinge by the worde of God. Prou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> the spirites, and knowe for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentie
<pb facs="21"/>
that, that spirite is not of God? whyche denieth that Christe is come in the fleshe. And what other thynge is that, then to denye that hys comynge in the fleshe is the sufficient and onelye satisfaction for oure synnes? Who so euer he be therfore, that denieth vs to be frelye redeamed by Christe wythout any part of our desertes: the same denyeth Christe to be come in the fleshe. If thou proue them therfore, once to haue denyed on thys wyse that Christ came in the flesh: I besech y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>, euen for Christes sake: to trye theyr reportes by the scripture or thou credyt them. And thē as thou fyndest them so take them. The Lorde open the eyes of thyne herte that thou mayst se the hydde and secretes ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominacions.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>