<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Praeface to the Christian Readers touching our 2. Questions and their Defense following.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103093_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04214</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14333</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103093</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Praeface to the Christian Readers touching our 2. Questions and their Defense following.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A defence of a treatise touching the sufferings and victorie of Christ in the worke of our redemption : Wherein is confirmed, 1 That Christ suffered for vs, not only bodily griefe, but also in his soule an impression of the proper wrath of God, which may be called the paines of Hell. 2 That after his death on the crosse he went not downe into Hell. For answere to the late writings of Mr Bilson, L. Bishop of Winchester, which he intitleth, The effect of certaine sermons, &amp;c. Wherein he striueth mightily against the doctrine aforesaid. By Henry Iacob minister of the worde of God</title>
                 <author>Jacob, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>211, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>A Praeface to the Christian Readers</hi> touching our 2. Questions and their Defense following.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a iust thing with God (deare brethren) to punish in his dissolute people sinne with sinne: and where one iniquitie is not repented, to binde others there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. Which thing surely we may to well see is com to passe and befallen vs in England deseruedly at this day. Who after so long, plentifull, and comfortable enioying of the Gospell (the most precious blessing of God in this life) are now all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most generally com to this, that we haue lost the loue thereof. What remayneth then for vs, when we set so light by this Heauenly grace forgetting our first loue which once wee seemed to beare towards it, and wherein now wee ought to haue abounded, but that God should punish this our hainous and generall sinne with others, and among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers send vs delusions euen strong delusions to broch &amp; beleeue lyes, seeing we shew so small affection and so little pleasure in his truth. The Lord in iustice then (no doubt) doth punish vs with such delusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of error as are now so rife in our land at this time, more then in times past when as the Gospell hath ben soundlyer preached and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beloued among vs, then now it seemeth to bee. Now so much the more dangerous this mischief is, as also it must needes proue yet still, because it is offered vnto vs forsooth by the frendes of the Gospell, and fathers of the Church as they desire to be called, yet being indeed sole Commanders in Religion, very Lords ouer mens cōsciences, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulsiuely ouerruling their brethren and Gods deare flocke; contrary to the<note n="“" place="margin">Mat and 2 2 Cor. 1. Cor. 1. Pet.</note> expresse Scripture, and all well ordred Ancient and present tymes. How needfull then is it that the Lords faithfull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers forget not themselues in these deceiptfull dayes, nor that great charge which the great Pastour of the Flock hath layd vpon them, but to bee watchfull and diligent and for no respect of persons to suffer any part of the gracious truth of God to bee disgraced by men: chiefly that part and point (if we can discerne what it is) which by the corruption thereof raiseth and maintayneth most of our other vaine corrupt and contentious quaestions which now swarme among
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>vs, yet which easily would bee cut cleane downe if the word of God alone might beare sway, as we see it to be brought to passe this day by the blessing of God in other Reformed Churches of forraine Countryes. For my part, being occasioned at this time more specially to speak of <hi>2.</hi> of these foresaid corrupt doctrines, J am not vnwilling (though vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually yoked) to defend the truth in them. It hath pleaseth M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Bilson the now L. Bishop of Winchester to begin among vs a new matter of faith neuer heard of before in England (but only in the dayes of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery) touching the All sufficiency of the meere Bodily Sufferings of Christ, and to maintaine an other which was neere worne out, of his going downe to Hell in Soule. In both which because my conscience assured mee that hee was much mistaken, and laboured that others should mistake also, I thought it not besides my duty (the Lord offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me opportunity) to maintaine the truth, and that in all plainenes and evidence of the Scripture as God inabled me with. This now a while since being published (wherein my trust is I caryed my selfe no otherwise then J ought) the Author and maintayner of the contrary hath so of late intertayned it, as seemeth to mee and to many others wonderfull. Wonderfull, not for strength of reasons nor for exquisit matter such as neuer before was delivered, though his learning J acknowledge and will not but reverence his gifts: but wonderfull his answer is and altogeather extraordinary, considering that such in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable bitternes, disdaine, skoffing, reproch, and furious rage doth so abundantly com from him therein against my poore selfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet by the mercy of God a true Christian, a Minister of the Gospel, and one (I praise the Lorde) which euer haue bin carefull to bee free from the scandalls of the World. Though heerein J boast not, but rather (with the Apostle) will boast of mine infirmities. Verily this now J haue learned by his writing better then euer I conceaued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; namely what great oddes he maketh and desireth to be made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene himselfe a Lord Bishop, and an other being but a Preacher of Gods most holy word. Well: this is the Rhetorike and the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Conclusion against my treatise. But all this is besides his Matter, which nevertheles may haue peradventure som weight in it. It may peradventure. Wherefore J see a double necessity vrging me to reply therevnto. First to the end that his exceptions and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, (that is to say, his wholl matter) may appeare yet better to be so weake and vnsufficient as indeed they are. See: that those vncivill
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>reproches (I will not say vnchristian revilings) being the bewty and forme of his booke, may appeare to be but the froth of a distempered stomacke, the colour of reason and iust cause which he casteth on it, being taken away. As touching the matter therefore thus I purpose to deale. I will begin with his later writing, which he calleth a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion, because he mainly directeth it against mee, taking in by the way also all such places &amp; points in the former Treatise as do right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerne our matter in hand. Finally, as touching his reproches and cruell words I intend wholy to passe ouer them, seeing for them neither is he any whit the better, nor my selfe the worse.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>