<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103026_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14184</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24499</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103026</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A demonstration of the trueth of that discipline which Christe hath prescribed in his worde for the gouernement of his Church, in all times and places, vntill the ende of the worlde : Wherein are gathered into a plaine forme of reasoning, the proofes thereof; out of the scriptures, the euidence of it by the light of reason rightly ruled, and the testimonies that haue beene giuen therevnto, by the course of the churche certaine hundredths of yeares after the Apostles time; and the generall consent of the Churches rightly reformed in these latter times: according a they are alleaged and maintained, in those seuerall bookes that haue bin written concerning the same</title>
                 <author>Udall, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--East Molesey</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 102, 2 pages, 1 folded leaf of plates, table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>INfinite and vnspeakeable (Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
Reader) are the miseries frō
whiche Iesus Christe our Sauiour
hath freed vs, and the benefites
and blessings, wherewith in this life
he beginneth, and for euer will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
to adorne vs. The considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
whereof (if our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>thankfulnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
his Maiesty, were any way propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionable,
to that which we endeuour
vnto towards men) shoulde make vs
continually to deuise, &amp; all the daies
of our life to studie howe wee might
shew our selues (at least in some sort)
carefull to glorifie his blessed name,
aboue all thinges that we desire, by
how muche as his loue towardes vs,
excelleth whatsoeuer can else (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to our wish) befall vnto vs: but
if we do with equall ballance (on the
other side) looke into the course of
mans life, howe well this dutie is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed;
we shal see, that men declare
themselues rather bent to spit in his
face, and to defie him, then any way
to honour him as their head and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne:
<pb facs="9"/>
for (to saye nothing of the
prophane life, and godlesse couersati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
wherewith the generall number,
that professeth Iesus Christ, is wholy
defiled) wee see that many nations,
people and languages are very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
to receiue Iesus Christe as their
priest to sacrifice for their sinnes, but
that he should become their king, to
prescribe lawes vnto them, whereby
they may bee ruled, is of all other
things the most vnsauory, yea (if it be
offered) the most grieuous tydinges,
and vnreasonable request: wherein,
albeit manye nations that haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced
that whore of Rome, are
heynously sinnefull against his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
maiestie: yet is there none in the
whole worlde so far out of square as
Englande, in reteyning that popishe
hierarchie, firste coyned in the midst
of the mistery of iniquitie, and that
filthie sinck of the Canon law, which
was inuented and patched together,
for the confirming and increasing of
the kingdome of Antichrist: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
as great indignitie is offered vnto
<pb facs="9"/>
Iesus Christ, in cōmitting his Church
vnto the gouernement of the same,
as can be, by meane vnderlings vnto
a king; in committing his beloued
spouse vnto the direction of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse
of the Stewes, and enforcing
hir to liue after the orders of a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelhouse.
For the reformatiō wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
while some haue written, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
according to their callinges,
carefully stoode, howe heynously it
hath beene taken, howe hardly they
haue bene vsed, and what shamefull
reproches haue beene offered (euen
vnto the course of the Gospell) for
spyte that hath beene borne vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,
almost by all estates and
degrees, lamentable experience hath
taught many of vs: but our posterity
shall knowe it more particulerly, and
the Church thoroughout the world
shall discerne and iudge of it more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently,
when their bodies are rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
in the dust, &amp; their soules (if they
repent not) in eternall and intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
torments; who haue reiected a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest
so holy, profitable and reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable;
<pb facs="10"/>
yea, and handled the intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
for the same so cruelly, vnchristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anly,
and vnlawfully: but they would
gladly perswade themselues (if their
conscience would let them) that they
haue onely executed iustice vpon vs
as malefactours, and they perswade
men that we desire a thing, not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted
by the worde, not heard of in
the Church of God, vntill within this
few years, nor tollerable in any chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
common-weal whatsoeuer: The
whiche monstrous slaunders, albeit
they haue bene manye wayes, and by
many men of most worthie gifts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected,
and made knowne in those se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall
bookes that haue bene publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
concerning the same: yet haue
I thought it necessarie (in another
course) to write also of it. The course
of my enterprise, is first in respect of
the fauorers of the desired reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
secondly of the aduersaries of
the same, the fauourers of it, are also
of two sorts; ministers of the word, &amp;
priuate persons, &amp; both I hope, may
haue profit by it. Concerning the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
<pb facs="10"/>
when these wofull troubles that
were renewed vpon vs (by that wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
subscription, that was euery
where vrged) did begin to increase, I
thought it meete to betake my selfe
vnto that which I had read, or might
any way by studie finde out, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the cause, and collected all into
a briefe sum, and referred euery thing
vnto some head; whiche beeing euer
present with me, might furnish me to
answere in the defence of the trueth,
though it were of a sodden, by which
(thorow the blessing of God) I found
such profite in my seuerall troubles,
that I thought it a course not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
vnprofitable for others also,
and vpon that occasion betooke my
selfe vnto a more serious meditation
about the matter, and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
the thing with diuers very wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
men; I found encouragement &amp;
hartening on, generally by all whom
I made acquainted therwith: so that
I trust (the iudgments, yea and wishes
also of others, so iumping with mine)
many ministers that loue the cause,
<pb facs="11"/>
and haue not so thorowly studied it
as were meet they should, may reape
some profit therby. Now concerning
priuate men that loue the cause, som
haue great affaires in hand, and haue
no leasure to read the seuerall books
of this argumente: some when they
read, are not of sufficient capacity to
conceiue the force of a reason, or to
make vse of it, to enform themselues
in the grounded knowledge of the
cause thereby: some (which is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
falt of our religious gentlemē)
will take no paines to read, some are
poore and not able to buie the books
which might let them see the cause,
al these (I hope) may finde helpe in
some measure hereby. Nowe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the aduersaries vnto the cause,
they are of two sortes also, they that
know it, and they that are ignoraunt
of it: the former, if they write anye
thing against it, are contented to deal
in so rouing a course as may rather a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise
vnto great volumes, then soundly
to saye anye thing againste the cause:
Wherein D. Whitgifte, but especially
<pb facs="11"/>
D. Bridges, haue giuen vs an euident
example: and these with others of
their iudgment (though non in these
latter dayes, haue written more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learnedly
then they, of any argument
of diuinity whatsoeuer) are cōtented
to make the world belieue (if mē will
be so wilfully seduced) that our argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
be no arguments, that they be
grounded vpon false foundations, &amp;
that we are not able to conclude our
cause in any forme of reasoning. The
course that is here taken (I trust) shall
shew that they are liars: the other sort
of aduersaries be they that be meerly
ignorant of any thing, either for it or
against it; and perswading themselues
that the sway and shew of the worlde
must needs cary the truth with it, do
(like blind bayardes) boldly venture
to say any thing against it, and think
they do wel. Now of all these sorts of
people, I haue to request some thing;
I hope I shall obtaine my request (at
the least) at the hands of some of thē.
The first sort of fauorers (which be the
ministers) I intreat, that as they ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="12"/>
the glory of God, and honour of
the cause which they stand in; so they
would diligently imploy themselues
in this, that they may be founde able
to defend the same by sounde and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident
grounds out of the worde, &amp;
so muche the rather, for that the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries
doe greatly triumph, when
they meete with one that professeth
the cause, and is not able to defende
it, and confute the gainsayers of it.
The secoud sort of fauourers, be the
priuate persons that loue the cause,
whom I beseech to be carefull (as of
all other pointes of religion) of this,
that they growe in the knowledge of
the word of God, whereby they may
be able, vpon their owne knowledge
to defend the truth, and not giue the
enemie any occasion to think or say,
that they be of that minde, because
such and suche ministers, whom they
do affect, do thinke so. Now concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the former sort of aduersaries,
to wit, they that know it, I pray them
to looke into their owne hearts, and
they shal finde they mislike it; eyther
<pb facs="12"/>
because it correcteth their excessiue
pompe and maintenaunce, or requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
more trauaile in their ministery,
then they are willing to vndergo, or
at the least, controlleth that dissolut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
of behauior, wherin they willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
wallow: and if it would please god
to bring them to a serious meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of this, that it is the will of the
mighty God (before whō they must
be called to giue an account) whiche
they doe resist, they would (I doubt
not) more carefully looke about thē.
And lastly for them that being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
of the cause, speake euill of that
they know not: let them (if they will
bee admonished) vouchsafe to reade
this little book, and wey the reasons
with an vpright iudgment, which shal
cause thē (at the least) to suspend their
sharpe censures, which so vsually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
in their ordinary communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
&amp; concerning vs al, let vs know
(for one day we shalbe sure to feel it)
that the controuersie is not about
goats woolle (as the prouerbe sayth)
neither light &amp; trifling maters, which
<pb facs="13"/>
may safely be folowed or reiected (as
in deed the enemies of this cause do
confidently affirme) but about no les
matter thē this, whether Iesus Christ
shalbe king or no; For if none is said
to be a king, but he that ruleth by the
scepter of his lawes, then the turning
out of these orders which christ hath
prescribed in his word, for the ruling
of the Church, is to giue him the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
and denye him the authority be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
to the same, and so (in trueth)
to make him an Idol, making him to
cary a shew of that which he is not, &amp;
(with the crucifiers of him) to put a
reede in his hand, in stead of his yron
rod; and crowning him with thorns,
in stead of the crown of greatest glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;
which is the cause that so many
Atheists spit in his face, and so many
godles persons, do make but a iest of
him: but when he commeth to shew
him-selfe in his glorious maiestie; it
shalbe said vnto all these sorts of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries:
<hi>Those mine enemies whiche
would not that I should raigue ouer them,
bring hither, and slea them before me.</hi>
      <pb facs="13"/>
Luk. 19. 27. The which fearefull sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,
that we may auoide, let euerye
one of vs (as may stand with our seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
callings) carefully endeuor, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce
this kingdom here, which (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
other assurances giuen vs from
the Lord shalbe a testimonie vnto vs,
that we shall haue part in that glory,
which shalbe reuealed herafter. Now
concerning the order of this booke;
to direct thee (good reader) vnto thy
further instructiō, in the points ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
Thou hast in euery chapter, diuers
proofs out of the holy word of God,
which must be the things wherewith
thou mayest safely informe thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science:
then shalt thou finde (also
arguments drawn from reson right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ruled by the same word: and lastly,
(because our aduersaries charge vs,
that we desire a thing not known vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the olde writers, nor agreed vpon
among the newe) thou hast here the
witnes of them both in so plentifull
and vniforme wise, as may plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare,
that al godly learned men of al
times, haue giuen testimony vnto the
<pb facs="14"/>
trueth of it. The most of the thinges
that are here expressed, I acknowledg
to be gathered out of the books that
haue bene published, and are extant
(purposely) concerning this argumēt;
as may appeare in the seueral points,
wherein thou art sent vnto thē. Now,
lest either thou shouldst be deceiued
with a diuers impression, or think me
to missealleadge the authors, I am to
shew thee what books I haue follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
The 1. book of T. C. twise printed,
I folow the latter; of Ecclesiast. discip.
I folow the latine, printed 1574. and
the last booke of D. Whitgift, which
containeth all the former in it. The
rest (as I take it) haue bene but once
printed, and therefore cary no doubt
in them. If thou bee satisfied here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,
giue God the glory: and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
the cause by prayer, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
good meanes that thy calling
may affoord: and pray for vs, that we
may neuer shrinke, nor be ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen
by the strength of them that
fight against it.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>