<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ TO the right high and mightie prince, Edward, Duke of Somerset, Etle of Hertford, Viscount Beauchamp, lorde Seymour, Gouernor of the persone of the Kynges Maiestie of Englande, and Protector of all his Realmes, Dominions and Subiectes, his lieuetenaunt generall of all his armies, bothe by lande and by sea, Tresore and Erle Marshall of Englande, Gouer∣nor of the Isles of Gernsey and G¦er∣sey, and knight of the moste noble ordre of the Garter: Iames Harryson Scottisheman wisheth healthe, ho∣nor, and felicitie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103818_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02726</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12857</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103818</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ TO the right high and mightie prince, Edward, Duke of Somerset, Etle of Hertford, Viscount Beauchamp, lorde Seymour, Gouernor of the persone of the Kynges Maiestie of Englande, and Protector of all his Realmes, Dominions and Subiectes, his lieuetenaunt generall of all his armies, bothe by lande and by sea, Tresore and Erle Marshall of Englande, Gouer∣nor of the Isles of Gernsey and G¦er∣sey, and knight of the moste noble ordre of the Garter: Iames Harryson Scottisheman wisheth healthe, ho∣nor, and felicitie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exhortacion to the Scottes : to conforme them selfes to the honorable, expedie [n] t, and godly vnion, betwene the twoo realmes of Englande and Scotlande</title>
                 <author>Harrison, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>¶ TO the right high and mightie prince, Edward, Duke of Somerset, Etle of Hertford, Viscount Beauchamp, lorde Seymour, Gouernor of the persone of the Kynges Maiestie of Englande, and Protector of all his Realmes, Dominions and Subiectes, his lieuetenaunt generall of all his armies, bothe by lande and by sea, Tresore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and Erle Marshall of Englande, Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Isles of Gernsey and G<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey, and knight of the moste noble ordre of the Garter: Iames Harryson Scottisheman wisheth healthe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Allyng to mynde (as I do oft) moste excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Prince, the ciuill discencion and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal enemitie, betwene the twoo Realmes of Englande and Scotlande, it bryngeth me in muche marueill, how betwene so nere neighbors, dwellyng with in one land, compassed within one sea, alied in bloude, and knitte in
<pb facs="2"/>Christes faithe, suche vnnaturall discorde should so long continue. Vnnaturall, I maie wel call it, or rather a Ciuill warre, where bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, kynsmen or countreymen be diuided, and seke y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bloud of eche other: a thyng detestable before God, horrible to the worlde, and pernicious to the parties, and no lesse straunge in the iyes of reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men, then if the lymmes and membres of mannes body, should fall out within them selfes, as the hand to hurte the foote, or the fote the hande. If any vtilitie or gain should growe thereby, it were the lesse maruail, but when there doth nothyng ensue, but suche fruite as warre bryngeth furthe, whiche is fackyng of tounes, subuersion of holdes, murder of men, rauishinēt
<pb facs="2"/>of women, slaughter of olde folke and infantes, burnyng of houses and corne, with hunger and pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, twoo buddes of thesame tre: and finally, the vtter ruyne of the whole kyngdom, I wonder that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emōgest so many pollitique rulers as be, and haue been in both real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, the nuschief so long spied, the remedy hath not yet bee sought. Who is so blynd that doth not see it, or who so harde harted, that doth not pitie it? I omitte here to speake of the greate afflicciōs and miserie, whiche Scotlande hath susteined by warres in tymes pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, a matter ouer lōg to be reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and yet to great to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. But to come to later tyme, what hath been doen within these sixe yeres, sithe the warres wer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uined,
<pb facs="3"/>how the coūtrey hath been ouer runne, spoyled and heried by Englishemen on the one side and by our awne warremen or rather robbers on the other side (to speke nothyng of the plague of God) it would greue any harte, to thinke. If this miserie fell onely vpō the mouers and mainteiners of suche mischief, it were lesse to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but thei sitte safe at home, and kepe holy daie, when the feldes lie ful of their bodies, whose deathes thei moste cruelly and vuchristiā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue procured. If Edēbrough, Lieth, Louthian, Mers or Tiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale had tongues to speake, their loude complainte would perse the deafe eares. But what nedeth spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, when their iyes maie se plain enough, what their deuillish har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="3"/>haue deuised. This miserie is muche to be sorowed and more to be sorowed, then their wickednes to be detesied, whiche haue kynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the fire, and still late on bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to feede thesame. In whom if either respect of Religion, whiche thei professe, or zeale of Iustice, whereunto thei are sworne, either feare of God, or loue to their coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey, did any thyng woorke, thei would refuse no trauaill, nor tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of body nor mynde, no, nor death (if it wer offered) for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of theim, whose distruccion thei haue wrought. And these bee onely twoo sortes, the one is of suche, as either for feare of their Hypocrisy to bee reueled, or euill gotten possessions to be transiated would haue no peace nor cōcord:
<pb facs="4"/>the other bee suche as for a lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse libertie and doyng wrōg vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punished, would pull out their heddes from all lawe and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Such and none other be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaries to our cause. If these. if. sortes (I saie) should fele but half the miserie, whiche the poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be driuen to suffre, thei would not be halfe so hastie to ryng <hi>alar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</hi> These be thei whiche profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syng knowledge, abuse the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of the nobilitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaltie, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> destrucciō of bothe, hauyng peace in their mouthes, and all rancor and vengeaunce in their hartes, pretendyng religion, perswade rebellion, preachyng o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, procure al disobedience, semyng to forsake all thyng, pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse all thyng, callyng themselfes
<pb facs="4"/>spirituall, are in deede moste car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and reputed heddes of the Churche, bee the onely shame and slaunder of the Churche. If these people would as earnesty trauail for the concord of bothe realmes, as thei indeuour with toothe and naill to the contrary, these mische<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues aforesaied, should either not haue happened, or els at the least, not so long haue continued: by whose lure, so long as the nobles and cōmons of Scotlande be led, I am in dispaire of any amitie or frendship betwene these two real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. GOD bryng their falsehed once to light, and turne their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie vpon their awne heddes.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>BVT</hi> to my purpose, seyng the mischief so greate, the aucthors so many, the mainteinaunce so strōg,
<pb facs="5"/>and so few that seke amendement: in declaraciō of mine earnest, zeale and vnfained affeccion towardes my coūtrey, I in default of other, put my self in prease. And though least able, yet moste willyng and desirous of the honor and quiet of bothe realmes, whiche cause, seing it correspondeth to vertue &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, me thought it conuenient to seke for the same, a patrone ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Godly, whereby your grace entered my remembraunce, whose procedynges hetherto haue made manifest to the worlde, what an ardent zeale ye beare, to thad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of all veritie &amp; truth: So that all men conceiue certain hope that by your high wisedom, pollicie, and other Princely ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, the stormes of this tempesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="5"/>worlde, shall shortely come to a calme. And seyng God hath not onely called you to the height of this estate, but so prospered your grace in all affaires, bothe of war and peace, as your actes bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to theirs, whiche beare moste fame: your grace cānot me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite more towardes GOD or the worlde, then to put your helpyng hande to the furtheraunce of this cause. Hereby shall you declare an incōparable seruice to the kynges Maiestie of England, whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng young of yeres, is yet ripe in vertue, to gouerne any kyngdom, whose excellent giftes of nature, and inclinacion to all Godlinesse considered, the world is in opiniō, that he shalbee nothyng inferior to the greate honor and glorie of
<pb facs="6"/>his father, whose praises I ouer passe, fyndyng my selfe vnable to expresse them in any degree. But sith your grace, as a person moste electe, is called to the gouernan̄ce and tuiciō of his persone, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teccion of his realmes and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, all mennes expectacion is, that hauyng so apte a moulde to worke vpō, you shall so frame his you the with verteous preceptes, Godly examples, and sincere edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion, as he shall proue a Kyng equal with those, whom old histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, do moste commend. Wherein your graces laude cannot wante, beyng so worthie a gouernor of so noble a kyng: and muche more if by your pollicie, diligēce, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspeccion, he shal at his perfect yeres bee restaured to the whole
<pb facs="6"/>isle of Britayn, wherunto as he is iustely entitled: So God the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of al iust causes, shal bryng your attēptes therin to good suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse. For the furtheraunce where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I haue declared myne opinion in writyng, whiche, with humble harte. I offre and dedicate vnto your good grace: not as a gyfte worthie so greate an estate, but yet not vnmete for my purpose, ne for the tyme &amp; occasion present, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in though I neither perswade my cause so pithihely, ne open it so li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely, as to so weightie a matter is requisite: Yet it maie serue either for a testimonye of myne honest meanyng, or minister occasion to better learned men, to dilate this argument more largely, whereby all warre and hostilitie maie cease
<pb facs="7"/>and peace and concord take place. GOD the verie aucthor of peace, euer preserue your grace, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of the same, and furtheran̄ce of all Godlinesse: and graunte to the Kynges Maiestie of England his righteous possession of the whole monarchie of Britayn, to thad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncemēt of Gods glory, cōfort to his lie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <figure>
      <figDesc>English coat of arms</figDesc>
      <p>DIEV ET MON DROVT</p>
   </figure>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>