<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authors Apo∣strophe to his Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103354_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04390</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14511.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103354</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authors Apo∣strophe to his Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Englands iubilee, or Irelands ioyes Io-pæan, for King Charles his welcome : With the blessings of Great-Britaine, her dangers, deliuerances, dignities from God, and duties to God, pressed and expressed. More particularly, Irelands triumphals, with the congratulations of the English plantations, for the preseruation of their mother England, solemnized by publike sermons. In which 1. The mirrour of Gods free grace, 2. The mappe of our ingratitude, 3. The meanes and motiues to blesse God for his blessings. 4. The platforme of holy praises are doctrinally explained, and vsefully applyed, to this secure and licentious age. By Stephen Ierome, domesticke chaplaine to the Right Honourable Earle of Corke</title>
                 <author>Jerome, Stephen</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stationers’ Society, Dublin</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Ireland--Dublin</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 214, that is 204 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_book">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Authors Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strophe to his Booke.</head>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> BOoke, to the <hi>Court,</hi> there free commence thy Suite,</l>
   <l>Admittance plead thy <hi>Prince</hi> to resalute:</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Which graunted, cordially congratulate,</l>
   <l>His welcome home to <hi>Peeres, Plebeans, State.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> There with the rest, thine <hi>Io paean</hi> sing</l>
   <l>For his arrivall safe, (chiefe for thy <hi>King</hi>)</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Prayse heavens <hi>Blest Centinell,</hi> whose eye did watch</l>
   <l>To keepe them, (us) from Powder, Plot, Fire, match.</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And if some scoffe, thou out of season came,</l>
   <l>(As snowes in Summer, or in Harvest raine,</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Or as some pardons, executions done)</l>
   <l>Apologize, it's well thou camest thus<note n="*" place="margin">Est aliquid prodire tenus si non detur ultra.</note> soone.</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Since all that <hi>Time,</hi> which lent thee speaking <hi>breath</hi>
   </l>
   <l>Thou staidst for presse, well nie, till prest, to <hi>death;</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Yet lame<note n="a" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.3.4. <hi>chap.</hi> 18. <hi>vers.</hi> 24.25.26.</note>
      <hi>Mephibosheth,</hi> thou bringst a heart,</l>
   <l>Better then <hi>Ziba,</hi> though he act first part.</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Say more, how <hi>Tyme,</hi> so clipt, swift <hi>Fames,</hi> flig wing:</l>
   <l>That till <hi>Novembers fift,</hi> she scarse did bring</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Those gladding newes, to our <hi>Hibernian</hi> coast,</l>
   <l>Of <hi>Charles</hi> returne, which we desired most.</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> So oft our trusts were voyd, so guld our Ioyes,</l>
   <l>By flying (Lying) Fictions, Newes, Tales, Toyes.</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> So fluctuate we were, twixt Hopes, and Feares,</l>
   <l>As feathers pendent, in the windes, and ayres:</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> That Hearing truths, by common votes, shoutes, cryes,</l>
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <l>We scarse durst trust our eares, without our eyes:</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> For even when <hi>Prince</hi> was come, <hi>Plebean</hi> crew</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Vox populi,</hi> cries still, too good for true:</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> But when trueths <hi>Trumpe,</hi> by vulgar breathes was blowne</l>
   <l>Our Ioyes reviv'd, as out of Feares dead sowne</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> As when hot <hi>Phoebus,</hi> gleames, to life doth bring,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Hymens</hi> dead seeming<note n="b" place="margin">Sylphae Culex Scarabei Cicada cancri, saepin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> mori &amp; revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viscere censen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ab Aristot. anim. lib. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi> Idem affirmat Vincent. de Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licibus lib. <hi>20</hi> ca. <hi>151.</hi> Idem Isidor. lib. <hi>12.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi> Aelian. lib. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>29.</hi> De Muscis alij de alijs infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis.</note> infects, Batts, in spring</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> Our <hi>Sunne</hi> reshines from that eclypsing cloud,</l>
   <l>Of doubts, and dangers which her lightes did shrewd,</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> As out of fearefull dreames, in which she slept</l>
   <l>Our <hi>Irish</hi> Muse, wakes, laughes, who earst had wept</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> In <hi>Cyntheas</hi> circuite. (Circle of one Moone)</l>
   <l>Mournefull <hi>Melpomine,</hi> mirthfull is become</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> And now as nimble <hi>Corybant</hi> she praunceth</l>
   <l>In our <hi>Ioyes Iubilees,</hi> she friskes, Trips, daunceth,</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> That anchored in her Port, she safe doth rest,</l>
   <l>Fre'd from windes, (waves) of doubts, which tost her brest</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> And with a foote as swift as <hi>Pegassus,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>To mother <hi>Albions</hi> coast, to scattered us,</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> Swarmes from her <hi>Hive</hi> whom <hi>Tyme</hi> Hibernifieth,</l>
   <l>Live <hi>King,</hi> Live <hi>Prince,</hi> our glad <hi>Thalia</hi> crieth:</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> Let after ages, <hi>Caesar, Charles,</hi> enroule,</l>
   <l>Their names, Fames, facts, Fates in eternall scroule.</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> That in their <hi>Nestors</hi> yeares, desired dayes,</l>
   <l>Our poore Plantations, may their hopes (helps) rayse</l>
   <l>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> Whose Times expir'd, above the Planets Seaven</l>
   <l>(As they plant us) great <hi>Iove</hi> plant them, in Heaven.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>