<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right woorshipfull Sir Christopher Heydon knight his ost courteouse Creditour of many his bounties and benefites.</title>
           <author>Haward, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103875_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02806</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12939</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103875</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right woorshipfull Sir Christopher Heydon knight his ost courteouse Creditour of many his bounties and benefites.</title>
                 <author>Haward, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The line of liberalitie : dulie directinge the wel bestowing of benefites and reprehending the comonly vsed vice of ingratitude. Anno. 1569</title>
                 <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 131, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right woorshipfull Sir Christopher Heydon knight his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ost courteouse Creditour of many his bounties and benefites.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N requiting courtesies good turnes, and benefites recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at others handes (ryght worshipful,) heedily ought we to folovv the fertile and frut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ful groūdes: which yeld in profit the manifold doubled gayne of the labour cost and traueile that their tyller and husbandly mā employed vpon thē, and charyly fle the sovver and naughty nature of barren soyle: whyche after many tillinges, great charge bestovved of payne and costes, in fine, aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svvere scarsely or not at all the ovvne seed agayne. worthie to be resembled to insacia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble svvalovving goulfes deuorīg stil, vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out shevv of any recept. And forsomuch as (according to thaduise of Cato,) it behoueth him that presumeth to geue precepts and to aduertise others, vvarily to take regard he
<pb facs="3"/>
deserue not reprehension himself for that he rebuketh others for, I thougt it more thē high tyme after so many benefits and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesies, so muche traueyle and costes sondrye vvayes at diuers tymes abundantly receiued by me and had of your vvorshypps greate bountye ioyned vvith courtesie, to shevv novv at length some profe of the nature of the soyle vvhervpon so franckly you haue employed the same. Concerninge vvhiche point of gratitude and thankfull nature cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting in requiting benefits, courtesies, and plesours receyued at your vvorships hādes, although in habilitie manye doe, in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvill yet vvell meaning and thankfulnes, no one shall surmount ne passe me. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit that blind Fortune through vvant of eysight povvring out or pinching in blind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly her giftes vvithout regard, graunteth to some habilitie to surcharg by geuing: and againe pincheth others some by abridging their povver to be able to aunsvvere lyke for lyke receyued: yet sith that (as Tullye sayth) the best and principal part of requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="3"/>
benefites and yeelding condigne than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes for benefites and courtesyes receiued re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth in the minde, vvhiche vvhen it hath vnfaynedly declared it self to be vvillinge to requite vvhat hath bene receiued, is to be thought to haue made recompēse aboū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly: As one thorough eased herevvith of the heauy charge vvhervvith the huge bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of your bounties, and Fortunes pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching parcialitie oppressed me, amyd this narovv streyte of my disabilitie not fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but triumphing ouer Fortunes blinde despyte, I present your goodnes (loe) vvith a mind vvelmeaning, and thankfull hart: supplyeng that defect vvith the certein ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the mind, vvhich the frayle and fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vvelth of the body vvill not permit me to do. A simple present for your vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie personage: and inferiour in valevv far to any of yours receiued: yet suche as shall suffyse to discharge me of Ingratitude. In vvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he self same seking to requite your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit passed, I must of force yeeld me your double dettour. Touching my self, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or your
<pb facs="4"/>
gentle a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ceptaunce of my pore goodvvill: touching this my pore presēt for your graū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted patronage, vvhiche simple gift of mine vvithout al regard had to your passed deser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes (which on my part notvvithstādīg may in no vvyse be vvrapt vp in obliuion,) of very devv for titles sake may challenge to be dedicated to your vvorship. For vvhy to speke frely and yet voyd of all suspicion of flatterie, (the verity vvherof I referre to the report and iudgement of infinite vvellnigh and those credible,) vvho is he to vvhome the report of your vvorshippes name hath come, but vvith the same report hath lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvyse heard your vvorthie renoume, and verteues vvelnigh of al sortes, suche as may challeng and claime your deserued crovvne of immortalitie. Amonge vvhiche vvhat shall I recompt your rare sobryetie, greate lenytie, paslyng familiaritie, commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble policie, gentle grauitie, pregnant vvise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, deepe discrecion, large liberalitie, paynefulnes to plesour all honest perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="4"/>
ample hospitalitie, to the admiration and vvellnigh astonnyeng of all that see suche rare gyftes so plentifullye placed in your ovvne person: vvith an infinite nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber vvelnigh of vertues besides, in the lest of vvhiche resteth trevv vvoorshyppe. For vvhyche causes vvith one voyce (as if they had conspired together) all Norfolke soundeth eche vvhere your immortal prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se. In nomber of vvhyche company, sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plest I, yet depest bounden, acknovvledge amonge the rest my vovved devvtie vvith happy acclamacions and vvellvvyshyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges testifieng my conceyued perfitte ioyeng at your haypie estate, and desyrous vvhat in my sclender povver doth consyst (for vvitnes of my assured vvell meanynge mynde dedicated to your vvoorshyp alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,) to record by my simple skil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed vvith āple testimonie of vvellnigh infinite, your vvelldeserued prayse vnto posteritie. wherein for your vvonted good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and beneuolēce accept in good part my
<pb facs="5"/>
well vvillinge hart, and seclude me not from your fauour passed. Thus I leaue troubling your vvorshippe vvhom to the great vvelthe and earnest contentacion of all your contrey vvith many others confy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, God of his goodnes preserue and increase in prefit helthe vvith abundaunce and felicitie to his plesour.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your vvorships depe dettour.
Nicolas Havvard,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>