<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>G. H.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103612_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02483</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12610</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103612</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>G. H.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to a treatise vvritten by Dr. Carier, by way of letter to his Maiestie : vvherein he layeth downe sundry politike considerations; by which hee pretendeth himselfe was moued, and endeuoureth to moue others to be reconciled to the Church of Rome, and imbrace tha religion, which he calleth catholike. By George Hakewil, Doctour of Diuinity, and chapleine to the Prince his Highnesse</title>
                 <author>Hakewill, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 30, 130, 4, 131-306, 26, 2 pages, folded table, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="answer">
   <pb n="22" facs="13"/>
   <head>G. H.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T seemes you had not so exactly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>used
this ensuing Treatise, as in the front
you pretend, in as much as you tell vs,
that the Author thereof from his gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
yeeres wallowed himselfe in the
choisest writings of the most learned Protestants;
whereas himselfe in his first chapter and fifth Section,
professeth, that <hi>when he first tooke himselfe to the studie
of Diuinitie, setting aside all respect of men then aliue, and
of Writers that had mooued or maintained Controuersies,
farther then to vnderstand the question that was betwixt
them, he fell to the reading of the Church Historie and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
Fathers, which had no interest on either side:</hi> Indeed
he telleth vs before this, he read ouer our <hi>English Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles,</hi>
and except this Were his wallowing in the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest
writings of the most learned Protestants, I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand
not out of his owne relation what was:
Once I am sure he affirmes meere vntruths touching
<hi>Caluins</hi> doctrine (which I take it hee vnderstands by
<hi>Caluinisme</hi>) faining him to teach, that the <hi>Sacraments
of the Church bee nothing but signes and badges of that
grace, which a man hath before, by the carnall couenant of
his Parents faith,</hi> and that <hi>Priesthood can doe nothing but
preach the word, which lay men may do also if they wil:</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions
so directly opposite not only to <hi>Caluins</hi> words,
but his grounds and reasons, that it makes me suspect
he neuer reade him nor so much as his <hi>Maiesties</hi> either
Apologie or Premonition; in both which he plainely
and largely impugneth the Bishop of <hi>Romes</hi> vsurped
power in spirituals, which the D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. notwithstanding
<pb n="23" facs="13"/>
denieth,<note place="margin">Cap. 2. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>t. 36.</note>
and that in his letter to his <hi>Maiestie</hi> himselfe.</p>
   <p>But you found the treatise, you say, both <hi>in stuffe
and style, to be learnedly and eloquently contriued:</hi> It may
be said of eloquēce without learning, as of the Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale,
that it is <hi>vox &amp; praeterea nihil, A sounding brass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
or tinkling Cymball:</hi> Neither doe I see how that can
well be called a learned peece of worke, which trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
of Christian religion, alleadgeth not so much as
one passage of Scripture throughout, nor alludeth to
any by way of proofe; and quoteth of the Ancients
onely, S. <hi>Augustine</hi> twice, but not against vs, and
<hi>S. Ambrose</hi> once, but against his meaning, as shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
in his proper place: and among latter Writers
Sir <hi>Francis Bacons</hi> Essayes, where no such thing as hee
quotes is to be found, and <hi>Caluins</hi> life written by <hi>Beza,</hi>
which rather makes much against himselfe, then in
any sort for him; besides this, hee borroweth a sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
or two out of <hi>Aristotles</hi> Politikes, which he fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth
vpon the Fathers, and this is the learned
stuffe you so much bragge of.</p>
   <p>From the worke you passe to the Author, <hi>who gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
fame</hi> (you say) <hi>amongst the Protestants, hauing beene
a Teacher in their Colledges, a Preacher in their P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>lpits, a
Doctor in their Schooles, &amp;c.</hi> So was <hi>Nicholas</hi> amongst
the Deacons, and <hi>Iudas</hi> among the Apostles, and
<hi>Reuben</hi> among the Patriarchs, and <hi>Saul</hi> among the
Prophets, and <hi>Iulian</hi> among the Christian Emperors,
and <hi>Nestorius</hi> among the Bishops, and <hi>Sergius</hi> among
the Monkes, and <hi>Lucifer</hi> among the Angels, and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>
among the children of God; <hi>Hee went out from vs
because he was not of vs, for if he had beene of vs, he would
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aue continued with vs.</hi>
      <pb n="24" facs="14"/>
      <q>Stella cadens non est stella, cometa fuit.</q>
His falling away proues him to haue beene a blazing
but neuer a fixed starre: Which that I haue good
reason to thinke, his owne words written with his
owne hand, and taken out of his common place
booke, shall testifie, where he proposes the question.</p>
   <q>IAN. 5. 1611.<l>An quis possit esse in statu gratiae, quiest</l>
      <l>extra externam obedientiam Ecclesiae.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Which hee thus resolues: Catholicus extra externam
obedientiam Ecclesiae, vel in Scismate natus, velper
loci interdictum eiectus, potest tamen esse in vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>one
Catholica. Ergò potest esse in statu gratiae.</p>
   <p>Potest habere animam perfecte vnitam. Ergo potest
esse in vnione Catholica.</p>
   <p>Potest habere intellect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m vnitum, scilicet per veram
fidem, &amp; voluntatem vnitam, scilicet per veram chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem.
Ergo potest habere animam perfecte vnitam.
Ergo sinon potest habere corpus vnitum, est tamen in
statu gratiae, modo nihil prius cupiat, quam vt sit etiam
in externa obedientia, &amp; abstineat propter commune
bonum Ecclesiae, non propter bonum priuatum.</p>
   <p>From whence in my iudgement it cannot well be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
otherwise, but that while his body was with
vs, his soule was vnited to <hi>Rome,</hi> and that euen before
his leauing vs, he left no stone vnmoued for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
good of that Church.</p>
   <p>
      <pb n="25" facs="14"/>
Lastly, for that <hi>vniforme and setled consent of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
Fathers,</hi> and those <hi>pregnant points and sound and
grounded reasons</hi> of the Author which the Prefacer
pretends; it will easily appeare at first view, that the
former appeares not in this Treatise: and for the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
they may appeare to the vnlearned and vnstable,
who like children are <hi>carried</hi> about with euery blast
of vaine doctrine; but to such as are sound <hi>in the faith
which was once deliuered to the Saints,</hi> and grounded
in the principles of Christian religion, I am sure his
reasons can neither appeare <hi>sound nor grounded.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Those foure quotations of Scripture which are set
by the Prefacer in his margin (being more by foure
then are to be found in the Treatise it selfe) the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of my marginall notes inforced me to omit; and
yet if I had figured them as I finde them there, the
Reader in searching would haue missed them, the 11.
and 19. of <hi>Iames</hi> being put for the 1. and the 17. the
15. to the <hi>Heb.</hi> for the 11. and <hi>Psalm.</hi> 83. 12. for 84. 11.
But herein it may be hee followed the diuision of the
vulgar edition, and the rest I am content to impute to
the Printer.</p>
   <q>Hanc veniam petimus{que} damus{que} vicissim.</q>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>