<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>P., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103841_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02629</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12757</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103841</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>P., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sicily and Naples, or, The fatall vnion : A tragoedy. By S.H. A.B è C. Ex</title>
                 <author>S. H. (Samuel Harding)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 64, 85-96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Publishing this <hi>Tragoedy</hi> I have so farre sinn'd against the modesty of my friend, that there is nothing sufficient to to excuse mee, but thy favour: Those that have dar'd dislike it already, would grow proud, if by presenting it to the common view, I did not shew for what a nothing I esteeme their censures; whatsoever syllable there be, that they ever cavill'd at, is therefore not omitted, that thou may'st have wherein, or to laugh at their vaine Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticising, or to shew thine owne candour; I doubt not but in thy approbation they shall see, what poore imaginary <hi>Hercules's</hi> they were that had no other Monsters to combat here, but what themselves made. That it was envy'd the glory which it might have receiv'd from the Stage, may be one reason to commend it to thee, since in this kinde there is little now adaies not applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but what is good: And for mine owne part I was never so maliciously uncharitable, as to goe about to undoe at once, the Stationer, and my Friend's credit. Thou shalt pardon mee this onely fault, that I have hereby dull'd that praise, which thy selfe might'st have receiv'd in making a good play, since I have layd before thee so faire a copy to write by. I dare not hope but it will be equally unexpected, and unwelcome to the Authour, to see the world acquainted with this toy, (as hee usually termes it,) which himselfe hath by this even learn'd to forget: Thy accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance shall be my apology to him, and indeed I may justly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge of thee a more than ordinary good will, since I have ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded the losse of his love, onely that I might shew my selfe</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy friend, and servant <hi>P. P.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>