<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧The occasion of this
trauell, and the pre-instruc∣tion
for it.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103684_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68132</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12686.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103684</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧The occasion of this
trauell, and the pre-instruc∣tion
for it.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The discouery of a new world or A description of the South Indies : Hetherto vnknowne by an English Mercury</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                            <distributor>Blount (Blunt), Edward</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 244 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="12"/>
   <head>❧The occasion of this
trauell, and the pre-instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
for it.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>INE acquaintance with
trauellers of all sorts, is
both well knowne to our
Vniuersitie men, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded
by the curteous
correspondence that haue
beene euer held betweene strangers and me:
whether this of <hi>Homer</hi> mooued mee to
this humour,
<q>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </l>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>:</l>
      </q>
Or were it that mine vnquenched thirst
and desire of knowledge, togither with the
applausiue carriage I found in these men,
were the motiues to these effects, I
knowe not. I was already fully acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
with all the rarities of mine owne
Nation: and falling into a discourse
of the profit of trauell with two Aliens of
my neare acquaintance <hi>(Peter Beroaldus,</hi>
      <pb facs="13"/>
a Frenchman, and <hi>Adrian Cornelius
Droge,</hi> a Dutchman) wherein wee had
many delightfull passages about compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
of languages, conditions, and cities;
at last, In troth (quoth <hi>Beroaldus)</hi> I know
not as yet what trauell meanes, if hee that
leaues his natiue soyle to passe but into a
neighbour countrie, or ouer a neighbour
riuer (admit it bee the Rhine, or the Tweed)
deserue this name (as vulgar opinion seemes
to allow) whereas hee neuer changes eyther
skie, ayre, or soyle: I see not (if this bee
true) any profit or worth in the world,
contained in trauell. My parents &amp; friends
at <hi>Montauban,</hi> haue written very often
for my returne, as though I were farre
from them: whereas I (beleeue mee) haue
imagined my selfe all this whole two yeares
at home: for how little a way is it from
<hi>Mount-auban</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> from <hi>Paris</hi> to
<hi>Callis,</hi> from <hi>Callis</hi> to <hi>Douer?</hi> Truely
when I thinke of the land, it seemes about
an elle: in the Mappe a finger-breadth: in
the forme of the heauens, iust nothing.
Nor see I any reason why that <hi>France</hi>
should hee held my natiue soyle more then
<pb facs="13"/>
all <hi>Europe:</hi> for if you stand vpon diuersity
of language, how many languages (I pray
yee) haue yee in <hi>Europe</hi> quite different
from the <hi>French?</hi> If the conditions of the
nations mooue yee, view not <hi>Europe,</hi> but
view the whole world, and euery Prouince
thereof, leaning to the qualities of those
that adioyne vpon it, as the <hi>Polipus</hi> turnes
into the colour of euery stone shee comes
neere! O <hi>Beroaldus</hi> (quoth I againe) but
we do enuie at the licence you haue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne
trauell: wee (wretches) that like
Tortoyses, are bound to our owne houses,
whilest you haue taken suruey of all the
worlds singularities, and now that you are
filled with their knowledge, you set them at
nought thus. Might I but view the Snowie
<hi>Alpes,</hi> or the shady <hi>Pyrenes,</hi> oh how much
should I thinke my selfe beholding to mine
eyes at my resting time, when all that I had
seene should turne to my benefit, and store
mine vnderstanding with a fresh fraught
of knowledge! Ah how much (quoth <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roaldus)</hi>
doth absence promise him that
would bee present, and how vaine are the
hopes that attend on ignorance! friend,
<pb facs="14"/>
when I was at home, vnexperienced, I
thought as you do; but triall hath now taught
me to see mine owne simplicity. A trauell
of so small toyle yeelds easie satisfaction:
and in this, your expectation shall exceede
your experience in all those nouelties. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine
parts are so like ours, that you cannot
thinke them strange to yee, though you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
saw them before. And what is there in
all the knowne world, which mapps, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
cannot instruct a man in, as perfectly
as his owne eyes? your England is described
by <hi>Cambden:</hi> what vnderstanding man
is there, that cannot, out of him, make as
perfect a description of any cittie, riuer, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument,
or wonder in all your Ile, as well as
if hee had viewed it in person himselfe?
What part of <hi>Europe</hi> is there that affoords
more to a strangers eye then is related by
one pen-man or other? The seuerall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
of the people are all described already:
as farre as eyther pen or experience can set
downe: but neither can giue any vniuersall
knowledge. The <hi>French</hi> are commonly called
rash, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> proud, the <hi>Dutch</hi>
drunken; the <hi>English</hi> the busi-bands; the
<pb facs="14"/>
      <hi>Italians</hi> effeminate; the <hi>Swethen</hi> timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roas,
the <hi>Bohemians</hi> inhumaine; the <hi>Irish</hi>
barbarous and superstitious: but is any man
so sottish, as to thinke that <hi>France</hi> hath no
staid man at all in it; <hi>Spaine,</hi> no meacock;
or <hi>Germanie</hi> none that liues soberly? They
are fooles (beleeue it) that will tie mens
manners so firme vnto the starres, that they
will leaue nothing to a mans owne power,
nothing to the parents natures, nothing to
nurture and education. View this <hi>Pernas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus</hi>
here, whereon we liue: Suppose here were
a Colledge of <hi>Italians, Spanish, French,
Danes, Dutch</hi> and <hi>Polacques?</hi> doe you
thinke to finde more varietie of dispositions
in this company of Students, then you may
doe amongst your owne <hi>English?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Turne yee therefore which way yee
will, I cannot see how this halfe a foote
trauell can benefit vs any waye, excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
that wee may reape some annimation
to learning by the sight of such great Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,
as <hi>Whitaker, Raynolds, Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,
Beza, Iunius, Lipsius,</hi> and such
like as those vvere. Indeede I holde,
that your <hi>Drake</hi> and your <hi>Candish</hi> were
<pb facs="15"/>
trauellers, as also <hi>Sebastian Delcano,</hi>
the <hi>Portughesse,</hi> because their voyages put
girdles about the whole world: Nay I will
allow <hi>Chrystopher Colono</hi> that name
also, for his discouerie of the West <hi>Indies,
Francesco Piccaro,</hi> and <hi>Almagro</hi> for
<hi>Peru, Hernando Magellano</hi> for the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luccaes,</hi>
and <hi>Sir Hugh Willoughbye</hi> for
his Northren discoueries: together with
all such as eyther haue first found out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne
regions, or haue brought them to
order. And truly (I will tell you two plaine)
my minde doth prompt me with some noble
enterprise of this kinde, such as the world
might gaze at, and all posterity record with
admiration. With that hee blusht, and held
his peace, as if he had blabd some bold secret.
Yea <hi>Beroaldus</hi> (quoth <hi>Drogius</hi> to him) &amp;
dare you not speake it out? doe you imagine
to torture our mindes with setting them on
worke vpon doubtfull inquiries, or is your
modest secret (hetherto so closely suppressed)
afraide to aduenture vpon so many eares at
once? Nay speake what ere it bee, wee haue
cleere browes (looke you) open eares, and
faithfull hearts: nor can your vnknowne
<pb facs="15"/>
enterprise come to light eyther vvith more
securitie, or fitter occasion. Well <hi>Drogius</hi>
well, (quoth <hi>Beroaldus)</hi> you take my si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
in no good sence, but mixe it with
your coniectures, that though great
matters neuer goe but (like as Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
doe with their numerous traines) with
a great preamble of ambiguous tearmes;
yet that I should not doe so, but vent a
pondrous conceite, a birth that my braine
hath trauelld a yeare with, all naked, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any praemonitions. In truth I resolued
at the first to let you know it: marry not
with-out some graduall proceedings, and
materiall preparations, without which, I
know well how fond the vvisest proiect
doth commonly seeme: but now I see my
selfe chayned to a head-long discouerie
mauger my beard, vnlesse I should giue
you iust cause to call my loue to you both,
in question. Wherefore you shall know it:
sooner (I assure you) then I did intend,
but with no lesse willingnesse: Onely ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
you, that you haue already heard mine
intended premonition.</p>
   <p>It hath euer offended mee to looke vpon
<pb facs="16"/>
the Geographicall mapps, and finde this:
<hi>Terra Australis, nondum Cognita.</hi> The
vnknowne Southerne Continent. What good
spirit but would greeue at this? If they
know it for a Continent, and for a Southerne
Continent, why then doe they call it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowe?
But if it bee vnknowne; why doe
all the Geographers describe it after one
forme and site? Idle men that they are,
that can say, this it is, and yet wee know
it not: How long shall wee continue to bee
ignorant in that vvhich vvee professe to
haue knowledeg of?
<q>
         <l>Certé si nemo vnquam</l>
         <l>—vv—Fragilem truci</l>
         <l>Commisisset Pelago ratem</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>If none had euer beeen
So bold as to expose
the slender barke vnto the Oceans teene</p>
   <p>Then vvee might haue had some excuse
for our obstinate (wee may euen as vvell
confesse it) and notorius idlenesse: But
seeing all is opened now; seeing there is
not a ship-boy but knows all the vvindes,
<pb facs="16"/>
creekes, shelfes and harbours of the whole
world; slie vpon this slouth of ours, this
more then female feare, this vaine careles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
that vvittingly and willingly robbes
vs of another world. What colour haue vve
for it? vvhat feare vve? shadowes, or our
selues? there is heauen, there is earth in
that continent, &amp; there is men, perhaps more
ciuill then wee are. Who euer expected such
wit, such gouernment in <hi>China?</hi> such arts,
such practise of all cunning? wee thought
learning had dwelt in our corner of the
world: they laugh at vs for it and well may▪
auouching that they of al the earth, are two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey'd
men, the <hi>Europians</hi> the one eyd, and all
the world else, starke blind. But admit there
be no men in this climate: it is a shame for
a wise man either to feare or complaine of
solitarinesse.</p>
   <p>These thoughts haue fired my brest full of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:
and whilest others neglect them, haue
kindled a bold attempt in mee, beyond the
rest. I see the land lye vnknowne; no man
dreames of it; I will assay to discouer it.
Your enterprise <hi>Beroaldus</hi> (quoth I) is
great, and almost more then mortall
<pb facs="17"/>
power can execute. Howeuer it succeede,
I applaude your generous spirit, as like your
owne: but as you said, great matters, as they
require many praemonitions, so doe they
more premeditations. Haue you therefore
cast your full account of the dangers, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
hopes, expences, and all other such ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents
as must attend this your attempt?
There is heauen you say: there may bee so,
and yet you bee kept from the sight of it by
perpetuall darkenesse.</p>
   <p>There is earth; but you may bee driuen
out of that by beasts and serpents: There
are men: but perhaps you had rather want
their company, when you know them, then
haue it. If one of you <hi>Patagonian</hi> Giants
should catch your and eate you quite vp,
where are you then my fine discouerer? It is
good thinking of those things, but it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
trying. O sir (saith <hi>Beroaldus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine)
you know not that the Cape of good
hope lies ouer against this land. We must
hope, and wee must dare. Those bug-beares
of dangers at fit to fright babies: but they
anymate bolder spirits. If we should sticke
at them, wee should neuer looke out at our
<pb facs="17"/>
owne dores. That was the cause <hi>America</hi>
lay so long vnknowne, and had done still
(for ought I see) but that GOD sent a
<hi>Doue</hi> from Heauen, which plucking of an
Oliue branch from this Continent, taught
vs by that, that there was yet more land, and
lesse sea then wee dreamed of: O how sacred
shall his name beheld with all posterity! His
statue shalbe aduanced, for vs al to gaze vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
whilst earth keepes her foundation. It is
as great a glory (thinke I) to bee called <hi>The
new worlds discouerer,</hi> as her <hi>conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</hi>
And why may not wee haue that suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse,
and the like glory? I am the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited
to this, by that ancient, and famous
prophecy of <hi>Seneca,</hi> which remayneth vnto
vs to fulfill.</p>
   <q>
      <note place="margin">Seneca in Mc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea.</note>
      <l>—Venient annis</l>
      <l>Secula seris, quando Oceanus</l>
      <l>Vnicula rerum laxet, &amp; ingens</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ateat Tellus.</l>
   </q>
   <p>—When certaine years are spent
Hereafter; shall the spumy Ocean shew
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>is secret store, and ope to mortals view
—A larger continent.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="18"/>
What can be spoken more plaine, to point
out this discouery? Here did <hi>Drogius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie:
What Man? beware how you raise
so great a building on so weake a foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
Your <hi>Doue</hi> hath fulfilled your Poets
coniectures, all of them, alreadie. The
summe of yeares is now runne: <hi>Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi>
is that large continent. Dreame you of
any other either age, or discouery? I know
the generality of your opinion (quoth <hi>Bero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aldus)</hi>
but I doubt of the truth, for Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
are alwaies <hi>de futuro:</hi> and what if I
prooue the countrie <hi>America</hi> to be knowne
to former ages? If I doe, <hi>Senecaes</hi> wordes
are no presage, but an intimation of a thing
done. Now I am fully perswaded that some
part of these west <hi>Indies</hi> was that <hi>Ophir,</hi>
where <hi>Salomons</hi> and <hi>Hirams</hi> nauy had
their gold. For whereas there are fiue seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
opinionists touching this, <hi>viz. 1. Raba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,
Maurus</hi> and <hi>Nicholaus de Lyra,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming
that <hi>Ophir</hi> was in the <hi>East-Indies.
2. Volateranus,</hi> and <hi>Ortelius,</hi> auoutching
it to bee an Island in the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Ocean,
from an apocryphall relation of one <hi>Lewis
Venetus; 3. Gaspar Varerius,</hi> who affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="18"/>
all that was contayned in <hi>Pegu, Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi>
and <hi>Sumatra,</hi> to be whilom called by this
name. 4. <hi>Francis Vatablus</hi> whom <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
also (as <hi>P. Martyr</hi> saith) did follow: who
said that <hi>Hispaniola</hi> was <hi>Ophir. 5. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam
Postelius, Goropius Becanus,</hi> and
<hi>Arias Montanus,</hi> all which auoutch direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
that <hi>Ophir</hi> was this continent in which
<hi>Peru</hi> lieth. Of these the two last, and likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est,
make for vs, I care not which you take.
The first two, <hi>Varerius</hi> hath ouerthrowne,
horse &amp; foote: to ad more were too superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.
Sufficeth only that I proue him errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
in putting <hi>Pegu, Sumatra</hi> &amp; <hi>Malaca</hi>
for <hi>Ophir.</hi> And first, holy writ saith plaine,
that those two nauies were two years out, in
each of their voiages to <hi>Ophir:</hi> but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> space
of 10. months, or 12. at the most, will serue
to passe and returne from the red sea to <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matra:</hi>
how then can this proposition of
time agree with his opinion? what can <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerius</hi>
say to this: that nauigation was not
exact then, as the <hi>Portugalls</hi> haue made it
since, and therefore in such a vast roome for
ignorance, the nauies might spend the more
in a wrong course.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="19"/>
Well sir, but how came <hi>Salomon</hi> to the
knowledge of this farre distant land? From
God you say, I beleeue yee. So then, hee that
taught him that there was such a land, and
that there was gold in such a land, and
aduised him to send thither, would not hee
(thinke you) shew him the right way the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?
Againe, the time of their being out is
alwaies set downe but one: at the end of
which they euermore returned, neither stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
longer, nor comming sooner: which
proues the distance of the place, and not the
error of the sailers. Lastly, the very name
speaketh for vs as plaine as may: <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>
do but transpose one letter, and they are all
one. Let mee therefore hold you for incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
obstinates if you confesse not that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica</hi>
was knowne long before <hi>Senecaes</hi>
time. You are victor <hi>Beroaldus,</hi> quoth I, and
may now lawfully triumph: But admit that
it was knowne to <hi>Salomon,</hi> and his naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gators;
doth it follow therefore that it was
discouered to the whole world besides, and
such as had no commerce at all with the
<hi>Iewes?</hi> or might not the memory of it bee
vtterly extinct before the later times of
<pb facs="19"/>
the <hi>Romaines?</hi> Which if it were, your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
and <hi>Senecaes</hi> presage are both ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne.
Nay nay, quoth <hi>Beroaldus,</hi> I am
not so easily disheartened with shadowes of
reason. This sit doubt of yours, giues mee the
stronger foote-hold. History is not silent in
this discouery, but preserues the memory of
it euen vnto the last posterities of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi>
For you know that from <hi>Salomon</hi>
to the building of <hi>Carthage</hi> was little lesse
then 150. yeares. But the <hi>Carthaginians</hi>
(as <hi>Aristotle</hi> witnesseth, nor can I beleeue
that they did this in their Citties infancie)
after a tedious nauigation did finde an Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
beyond the <hi>Gades,</hi> (which can bee
none but this) situate in the <hi>Atlantike</hi> sea;
wherevpon they made a law (which is a true
signe that neither did they people it, nor the
rest of the world, as then, commonly knew it)
that none should euer saile thether againe;
fearing least the wealthy and pleasant soile
should allure the Citizens to leaue <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi>
and go dwell there. Now the <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
hauing this knowledge of it from <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi>
how should it bee euer kept from
<hi>Rome?</hi> But sirs, kicke against the truth as
<pb facs="20"/>
long as you list, or yeeld to it as I doe: I am
most firmely perswaded that <hi>Senecaes</hi>
large continent is yet vndiscouered, and
staies to yeeld vs this glorie, if we dare ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
on it. For my selfe; I am comming (my
world) after so many vowes, and delaies,
now I come at last, all fraight with hope and
confidence, either to vnmaske thee to <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi>
or to lay my bones in thee. And you
(my friends and fellowes) if there bee any
true vertue, or loue of glory in your breasts,
goe and share with mee in my fortunes in
this great enterprise. Shame goe with those
frozen bosomes that affect nothing but se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity
and in glorious estate; that like no se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher
but of the nations earth where they
first breathed. <hi>We shall thirst, we shall be
sicke, wee shall perish,</hi> O base hearing! vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seemely
for a Philosopher once to think vpō!
And shaming the thoughts of trauellers, of
such as seeke out a new world, and scorne
this olde one. There wanteth nothing but
a good will. If yee bee men take that will
vnto yee, arme your selues against weake
opinatiuenesse, and let vs undertake that
iourney which may be perhaps, delightfull,
<pb facs="20"/>
and cannot but proue glorious vnto vs how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer
it may seeme laborious. If not, lusk
at home with vigour without honor: I will
finde some that shall beare mee company in
this famous enterprise, whose after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne
you may perhaps enuy too late. Here
he stopt his speech, and beheld vs with an
eye somewhat disturbed. His pithy speech
(whereof I cannot rehearse the tenth part)
mooued vs much, and so did our desires
of nouelty and glorie: briefely, wee assen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
and resolued all to assay this great dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie,
and embarked our selues in a ship
called <hi>The Fancie,</hi> taking our leaues of all
our friends and acquaintance.</p>
   <p>After three daies wee arriued on the
<hi>Belgique</hi> shores, and at the weekes end in
<hi>Aquitane:</hi> but <hi>Drogius</hi> staied behinde
at <hi>Delfe,</hi> and <hi>Beroaldus</hi> left mee here
and departed vnto <hi>Monutauban,</hi> against
both their wills: exposing mee to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rision
of all mine acquaintance, after
their great expectation of this our discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
vnlesse I would proceede, and aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
vpon all those vnknowne perills
alone. Yet this vnexpected departure
<pb facs="21"/>
of theirs did not ouer-come my resolution,
but I would needes forwards, and hauing
(after two yeares) passed the <hi>Canaries,</hi> the
coasts of <hi>Affrica,</hi> and <hi>Monomotapa:</hi> At
last I arriued at that promontory
of <hi>Tenter-belly,</hi> which
is called <hi>Il Cabo
Negro.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>