<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS FAITHFVLL friends, and verie deare brethren in Christ, Mast▪ Roger Ofield, Robert Washborne, George Smith, Thomas Shipton, Iohn Field, Robert Iones, Iohn Harper, Iohn Hounsell, and all the rest of his Christian ac∣quaintaunce in London, as well as though they were particularlie na∣med, together with all those that els where in the land, vnfaignedly feare the Lord, and looke for the glorious appearing, of his sonne and our saui∣our. T. W. wisheth all spirituall goodnes &amp; heauenly comfort in this life, and in the end the eternall glori∣fication of their bodies and soules, in euerlasting blisse through Christ.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103076_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15341</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25624</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103076</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS FAITHFVLL friends, and verie deare brethren in Christ, Mast▪ Roger Ofield, Robert Washborne, George Smith, Thomas Shipton, Iohn Field, Robert Iones, Iohn Harper, Iohn Hounsell, and all the rest of his Christian ac∣quaintaunce in London, as well as though they were particularlie na∣med, together with all those that els where in the land, vnfaignedly feare the Lord, and looke for the glorious appearing, of his sonne and our saui∣our. T. W. wisheth all spirituall goodnes &amp; heauenly comfort in this life, and in the end the eternall glori∣fication of their bodies and soules, in euerlasting blisse through Christ.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Large letters : Three in number, containing much necessarie matter, for the intruction and comfort of such, as are distressed in conscience by feeling of sinne, and feare of Gods wrath. Written heeretofore by T. W. for some deare friends of his, and now published and printe for the raising vp of such as labor vnder the heauie burthen of an affected spirite</title>
                 <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Ward, Roger</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 133, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO HIS FAITHFVLL friends, and verie deare brethren in</hi> Christ, Mast▪ Roger Ofield, Robert Washborne, George Smith, Thomas Shipton, Iohn Field, Robert Iones, Iohn Harper, Iohn Hounsell, and all the rest of his Christian ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintaunce in London, as well as though they were particularlie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, together with all those that els where in the land, vnfaignedly feare the Lord, and looke for the glorious appearing, of his sonne and our saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>T. W.</hi> wisheth all spirituall goodnes &amp; heauenly comfort in this life, and in the end the eternall glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of their bodies and soules, in euerlasting blisse through Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y loue in the Lorde, and the affectiōs of my hart in him, haue bin in some measure of soundnes, (I humbly thanke God for it in Christ)
<pb facs="3"/> strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carried generallie tovvardes all the Israell of GOD wheresoeuer, and more particularlye tovvardes you my good Breethren: vvhereof ouer and besides, the assured testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of mine owne soule, I haue for faithful witnesses, the Lord himselfe in heauen, and many of his saints vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon earth, and amongst others you your selues. Causes leading me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to are manye: but as in respect of God, none more powerfull, than his grace and holy spirite, shed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into my heart: and as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of you, none more effectuall than sundry sincere fruites of your faith, and the comfortable feeling of the communion of saints, in which holy fellowship standeth, not onely the spiritual felicity and good of the whole bodie, but the very ioy and contentment also, of euerie sounde member therein. For outward kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses that I haue receiued from you, I must &amp; will euerie where, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my selfe much beholding vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="3"/> you. And yet this I may vvith all boldnes professe, that as that is not the on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly or principall cause, moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me to affect you: so though I haue beene beholding to you all, yet not to all alike, but to some more than to other some. Which also I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearse not now, either to breed anie disdaine or emulation in you, one of you towards another, for that vvere to breake the bond of charity and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the spirit: or to less<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour though neuer so small, that I haue receiued from you, for that wer to depriue you of your praise, and to declare my selfe ingratfull: nor craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilie clavving after the maner of the vvorld, to craue newe benefi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, for that vvere nothing els but deceit and flatterie to procure mine own good, from all vvhich corruptions, I haue hitherto as in respect of my selfe and you, through Gods goodnesse beene graciouslie freed. But to let you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that your benefits haue not bene bestowed vpon an vnskilfull or
<pb facs="4"/> an thankefull person, but vpon such a one, as by the light that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from God, hath, vveighing them in an equal ballance, esteemed of them according to the goodnes of the gift, and the christian affection of the Partie giuing. The thinges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, which haue most speciallye lincked mee fast in the Lorde vnto you, are your precious faith towards God, vnfaigned loue to the saints, christian consciences amongest your selues, and holie praiers in presence and absence, one of you for an other and all of you I am assured, for the holy causes and faithfull members of the whole Church, and amongest the rest, euen for me pore and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man that I am. In which duties of yours, as my heart hath greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioiced in the lord, for the graces that in great mercy, he hath bin pleased to vouchsafe vnto you, &amp; I my selfe haue as in some sort, though not to the ful, in regard of your spirituall fauours performed to me, by reson of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="4"/> and wants in my selfe, aunswe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them again with the like, (I write not as a vaine glorious boaster): so I doubt not, but that therby God him selfe hath receiued glorie at your hands, his childrē goten much good, and you your selues reaped a gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous measure and increase, of religy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous knowledge, and dutifull obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. As for the worldly fauours that you haue shewed me, and bodily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites that vvay, I confesse my selfe to be far behind hand with you, and much indebted in deed, though not in affection surely, and readinesse of good vvill, for so my heart is verie large (in humilitie I speake it) ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I wish better witnesses of it than your selues, yet in regard of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vvherein still my griefe grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth great, and increaseth daily vpon me, as vvell by the feare that I haue of my future wants, as by the feeling of my former and present disabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Hovvbeit, sith thys is the Lords doing, and that he is pleased thereby
<pb facs="5"/> to sift me, and to sound you (mee for my patience and comfortable indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of these necessities, and you for your faithfull obedience and vnfaig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned loue) I can not but vvith some measure of spirituall ioy, vndergoe mine owne lacks, and againe recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my spirites, because hauing to deale vvith God and his seruaunts, (vvho haue learned from his holie example greater than all exception, to accept of men according to that they haue, and not according to that they haue not) I rest resolued, my good vvill shall bee accounted as a deed, specially sith I am ready euery vvhere, vvithout flatterie in my self, or favvning vpon you, to acknovve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to the glorie of God, and the good of his people, the great good turnes that by you, I haue receiued euen from the Lords ovvne handes. And yet gladly vvould I, if I could tell hovve, some vvay recompence, though not all, yet som part &amp; peece thereof. And in that respect indeede
<pb facs="5"/> haue I long looked &amp; vvished for, as some good occasion from you, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it might haue pleased you all, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you, to haue imployed and vsed me to my pore vttermost: So, some sufficiencie in my selfe, at the least<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in some mean measure to haue requited that ouerflowing heape, of your kindnes and holy loue. But hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto (I deliuer it with my griefe of heart, as a man sensiblie seeing and feeling gods hand vpon my selfe, both that and other waies also) my expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation and hope hath bene frustrat, and my power very short and skant. A small thing the Lorde vvas pleased some years ago, to inable me in two or three Letters, to performe for the comfort of some of my christian ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, (whose conflicts in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science vvere great and many) which lying by mee, vvith some other sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thinges that I haue done, and I beeing earnestly requested to make that cōmon to many, which was writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten for some particulars, &amp; lay at it
<pb facs="6"/> vvere buried in forgetfulnes, by me, the same also being at the last ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewed by some good breethren whome I much loue and reuerence in the lord, I was at the length ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come &amp; could not choose but yeild. Wherein though some perhaps may suppose that I labour, in publishing an vnnecessarie &amp; impertinent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, because these ignorant dayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Doctrine for building of men vp in knovvledge and iudgement, and these carelesse and contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous times, abounding vvith all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of loosnes and levvdnes, craue rebuke rather, and exhortation for care and conscience in the dueties vve knovve, as a more fit and meete argument for this dissolute age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> yet being assured of this, both by mine owne knovvledge, and other mens faithfull reportes, that sundrie there are abroad in this land, and amongst the rest, euen some of you and yours, that as in regarde of your spirituall combats and bickerings, and the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="6"/> assaultes and temptations you haue found therein, had need of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heauenly comfort, I could not but as in a generall care, for all the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted ones, to vvhome I wishe all the comforts of God, as to my ovvn soule: so in particular good vvil to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardes you your selues (vvhose in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard comfort, and outvvard ioy, I vvould bee glad and ready to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure at all times, and by all meanes, if I could tel hovv, but acquaint you and them (specially sith it is one prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall portion of the svveet Manna, that the lord hath prouided for you) vvith such pleasaunt and delightfull consolations, &amp; that out of the word as God by his spirit hath vvrought in mee, for the peace of mine ovvne heart, and by me, though vnvvorthie euery way, communicated vnto som others. What root they may take or effects they may bring forth I knovv not. Sure I am of this, my earnest praiers vnto God, as in regard of his religion and vvorship, and heartie
<pb facs="7"/> purpose in my selfe, as in respect of Christian good vvill, is, that all that mourne in our Sion, might reape some good by the same: vvhich if it cannot bee effected, either by meanes of my sinne that medle ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or by reason that the svveet things published, cannot so seasonablie or for lacke of oportunitie come to their knovvledge, or because that through diffidence they fore-close the vvaie and passage of consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto themselues, (in all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye of vvhich desertes, I shall surelye mourne muche) yet my hope and heartes desire is, that all of you (my good friendes) might receiue some vvorthie fruite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as vvell those amongest you that haue not as yet tasted of thys bitter cuppe, (a matter that you must looke for, and make an account of, if euer you vvill feele hovve sweete the Lord is indeed) vvhile you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue GOD sitting you, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing you vvith the best armour of
<pb facs="7"/> proofe that can bee, before the day of battaile dravve nigh: as those that haue beene or are tried (that beeing the verie state and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Gods children) God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your present distresses, prouiding for you, and reuealing vnto you, the present comfortes of his most faithfull vvorde, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible trueth, that so both the one sort and the other, hauing the povv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of your ovvne sinnes, in the suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes of his sonne, if not vtterlie remooued and cleane taken avvay, yet verie much lessened, and as it vvere beaten dovvne, you might not onelye the more earnestlie, oppose your selues agaist satan in his sleights and haue an assured hope of a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ioyfull victorie, against him and his assaults, but also may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to stand, yea to ouercome in the day of euill, and to be more than cōquerors thorow him, that hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued you &amp; washed you in his bloud, vvho I doubt not shall shortly and
<pb facs="8"/> mightilie also tread him and all his forces whatsoeuer, down vnder your feet. Now the very god of peace san<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctify you and al yours thorowout: &amp; I pray God, that your whole spirite and soule, and bodie, may bee kept blameles vntill the comming of our Lord Iesus Christ: vvhereof I doubt not, because he is faithful which hath called you, who also wil doe it. Good brethren pray for vs, that we may be readie in all things with vnfaigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to do the Lords vvill. At Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the tenth of of this December. 1589.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours readie and assured euer in Iesus Christ.</hi> T. W. <hi>the Lord his vnworthy seruant.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>