<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>William Turner to the gentle Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103034_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A14053</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24360</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103034</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>William Turner to the gentle Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A new boke of the natures and properties of all wines that are commonly vsed here in England : with a confutation of an errour of some men, that holde, that Rhennish and other small white wines ought not to be drunken of them that either haue, or are in daunger of the stone, the revine, and diuers other diseases, made by William Turner, doctor of Phisicke. Whereunto is annexed the booke of the natures and vertues of triacles, newly corrected and set foorth againe by the sayde William Turner</title>
                 <author>Turner, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="34"/>
   <head>William Turner to the <hi>gentle Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ORASMVCH AS</hi> both Christian charity, and the common ciuil loue that euerye man oweth to his countrye, woulde and doth require that all Christians and men liuing ciuilly togither in one common countrye, shoulde one helpe another with such giftes, either of the minde, as learning, knowledge, wisedome, and cunning, or with bodily giftes, as riches, strength and all kinde of mans helpe, if they be more rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly replenished therwith than their neighbors be: Methinke we that professe the science of Phisick, and can shewe great helpe and comfort vnto our brethren and countrymen, as wel as men of other countries, to wete, Italians, Germanes, and Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards haue done, might iustlye be accused of vnkindnesse, if none of vs (being so many) would take in hand to declare in the English tong, the manifolde and worthie vertues of the great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle made by <hi>Andromachus:</hi> and of the Triacle <hi>Salt,</hi> which is called in Latine <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theriacalis.</hi> Wherefore seeing that hitherto
<pb facs="34"/> I haue not perceiued any man to haue taken that labour in hand, for the loue that I owe vnto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God and his people, my countrymen of England, I will aduenture as well as I can, to declare the nature, vertue, propertie and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the forenamed Triacle, and also of the Triacle <hi>Salt.</hi> And bicause I am not minded to bring out any new thing of mine owne inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I entend for to gather the summe of this whole matter out of an olde Graecian, named <hi>Galen,</hi> the most famous writer of Phisicke that wrote this .xiiij. hundred yeare in all Europa, Asia, or Africa, and out of another famous Graecian named <hi>Aëtius,</hi> a man of great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: who gathered into a booke that is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode in Latin, all the most notable compositions that his predecessor (noble <hi>Galen</hi>) lest behind him, and a great number of compositions of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, written before <hi>Galens</hi> time by noble Phisitions, wherof <hi>Galen</hi> made no mention: and also of no small number of excellent compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions of medicines inuented by learned Phisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions after <hi>Galens</hi> time. If this my paine taken in this matter shall be perceiued to be thankefull vnto thee, and to be well taken, if God sende me longer life and health, I will set something more
<pb facs="35"/> forth to the profite of all my country men, both my friendes and foes also. The maner of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the great Triacle, and Triacle <hi>Sale,</hi> and <hi>Mithridatium,</hi> maye be had both in Galen to Piso, and also in Aetius. Wherefore if there be any Apothecaries of Lōdon, that dare take in hande to make these noble compositions, they may know now where to haue thē: or if that for lacke of some simple medicines, not easilye to he had in England, they dare not aduenture vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the making thereof: they maye haue them made alreadye from Venice, as faithfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded at this time, as euer any Triacles haue bene made there these .xl. yeres. But now let vs reherse the vertues and properties of these excellent medicines. And first of the great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>