<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ George Baker to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103060_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01658</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11798</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103060</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ George Baker to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The newe iewell of health : wherein is contayned the most excellent secretes of phisicke and philosophie, deuided into fower bookes. In the which are the best approued remedies for the diseases as well inwarde as outwarde, of all the partes of mans bodie: treating very amplye of all dystillations of waters, of oyles, balmes, quintessences, with the extraction of artificiall saltes, the vse and preparation of antimonie, and potable gold. Gathered out of the best and most approued authors, by that excellent doctor Gesnerus. Also the pictures, and maner to make the vessels, furnaces, and other instrumentes therevnto belonging. Faithfully corrected and published in Englishe, by George Baker, chirurgian</title>
                 <author>Gesner, Konrad</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 <publisher>Denham, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 258 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                    <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ George Baker to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, although I haue giuen the onset to publish in our owne naturall tongue, this most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent worke of Distillation, for which cause, it should not be the lesse estéemed, although some more curious than wyse, estéeme of nothing but that which is most rare, or in harde and vnknowne languages. Certainly these kynde of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cannot abyde that good and laudable Artes shoulde be common to many, fearing that their name and practise should decay, or at the least shoulde diminishe. The intension truely of such persons séemeth much like them which gape for all, and woulde all haue, leauing nothing to anye body, but that which they must néedes forgo, not considering that we are not borne for our selues onely, as <hi>Plato</hi> sayth, but for the profite of our countrie. Surely, if that I did not feare to be to long in this Preface, I would prooue howe all Artes and sciences may be published in that tongue which is best vnderstanded: as for example, <hi>Hippocrates, Galen, Paulus Aegineta, Aecius,</hi> were Grecians, and wrote all in the Gréeke, to the perfect vnderstanding of their countrie men. Also <hi>Cornelius Celsus</hi> being a Latinist, wrote in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e. <hi>Auicen</hi> and <hi>Albucrasis,</hi> Arabians, wrote in the Arabicke tongue. The eternall fame of which worthye men shall neuer be extinguished or drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in obliuion, nor their noble works for euer be out of remembrance. For what man is as yet aliue that euer was able to counteruayle them, yea the best learned in our dayes, doe most hyest estéeme of them aboue all, without whose, workes all Phisitions in the worlde be but blynde, and not able to make any perfite Arte. Peraduenture some will obiect and saye, that if we were without their works, there are other of later wryters which shoulde suffice. To the which I will aunswere, that they haue written nothing, but that their grounde was first layde by them, &amp; further, as M. <hi>Iohn Canape</hi> D. of Phisicke sayth, I wyll giue them this gyft, except they first reade <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> they shall neuer vnderstande what they reade, nor make any perfect worke. Therefore not without good cause <hi>Guido</hi> calleth <hi>Galen</hi> the lanterne of light. And nowe in these our dayes, we sée howe other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions doe followe their examples. For what kinde of science or knowledge euer was inuented by man, which is not nowe in the Italian or French▪ And what more prerogatiue haue they than we English men (of the which many learned men haue made sufficiēt proofe within th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se few yeres, fully to furnish &amp; satisfie our Nation with many goodly works.) For our English is as méete &amp; necessary for vs, as is the Greeke for the Grecians, though in the translation we be constrayned to make two or three words sometyme for one. For if it were not permitted to translate but word for word, thē I say, away with all translations, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which were great losse to the cōmon weale, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that out of one language into another haue ben turned many most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent works, the which the best learned haue both receyued &amp; approoued to the
<pb facs="4"/>
singular commoditie of all men. And among all the workes which haue bene translated into our natiue tongue, I doe thinke concerning the matter, there was neuer the lyke to this as yet. For herein you shall learne the manner to separate by Arte the pure and true substance as well manifest as hidden, the which in Phisicke is a great helpe to the taking away of diseases, harde or rebellious to be cured. And moreouer, that by the Chimicall Arte, those medicines which are harde and hidden, their forces and vertues are plainly manifested and prooued, and the grosse iuyce being mingled with the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till and fine substance, are thereby digested and separated, as we may sée by the drawing of the oyle of Golde, Iron, Copper, or Tynne. Also by Distil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation are corrected the malignitie or venimous qualities therof, as in oyles of Quicksiluer, of oyle of Vitrioll, Antemonie, artificiall Saltes, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other purging medicines. Furthermore, we sée plainely before our eyes, that the vertues of medicines by Chimicall distillation, are made more vail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, better, and of more efficacie than those medicines which are in vse, and accustomed. In tryall of the which, we doe daily prooue to our great credite, and our pacients comfort. For make tryall betwéene the one and the other, and you shall sée that the decoctions, Iuices, Syrupes, or such lyke, shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come neare to the dystilled waters, Oyles, Balmes, artificiall Salts, and extraction of Rootes, leaues, flowers, and fruites, of woode, Barkes, Gummes, Mettals, and such others, so that two or thrée drops of the oyle of Sage doth more profite in the Palsie: Thrée droppes of the oyle of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall for the falling sickenesse: Thrée drops of the Quintessences of Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rle for the Sincope or swounding: Thrée droppes of the oyle of Brimstone or Turpentine for the Astmatikes: One droppe of the oyle of Cloues, for the colde payne in the téeth: Thrée droppes of the oyle Ammoniacke for the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases of the splene: One dramme of the water of the oyle or salt of Guaia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, for the French poxe. One dram of the oyle of Walwort for the goute: Thrée droppes of the oyle of Iron for the Dysenteria, or other whyte fluxes: Thrée droppes of the oyle of Crystall for the stone: Thrée droppes of the oyle of Cloues or Baye berries for the Cholicke: Thrée droppes of the oyle of Antimonium for the Leprosie, doth more than one pound of those decoctions not dystilled. And another thing is to be noted, that the diseased people, principally those which are delicate, doe detest all things which doe not agree to their myndes, and delight not onely in the pleasantnesse of the taste, but also the sight of the eye, and the littlenesse of the quantitie of the medicine, the which I thinke, no man will denie. But this I will say, that thorowe the fire there is some hote qualitie in the medicine, but that qualitie is easie to be corrected, as in the administring of them are plainlye taught. Peraduenture some in the sight of the furnaces, and other vessels wyll bee lothe to meddle with so busie matters, as the preparing of the Mettalles, and drawing of Quintessences. For the which looke what excellent medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine any standeth in néede of, there be in this Citie which are most excellent in the preparing or drawing of any of them, to whom if you resort, they will
<pb facs="4"/>
faithfully deale, among whome none to be dispraysed. I doe know some most excellent, as one mayster Kemech an Englishe man dwelling in Lothburie, another, mayster Geffray, a French man dwelling in the Crouched friers, men of singular knowledge that waye, another named Iohn Hester dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on Powles wharfe, the which is a paynfull traueyler in those matters, as I by proofe haue séene, and vsed of their medicines to the furtheraunce of my Pacients healthes, and also one Thomas Hyll, who for his excellent knowledge in this Arte, is not to be left out, who dyd also take paynes in this worke, but before it coulde be brought to perfection, God tooke him to his mercie: There are yet others excellent men, which for breuitie I leaue at thys present. so finishing this my simple Preface, desiring God to further the studie of all those which faithfully and truely meane in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyse of this so noble an Arte, desiring all those which shall finde any fault, that they will friendlye admonishe me thereof, or else to note them in the margent of their owne bookes for their priuate vse and commoditie, till such time as it shall be new printed agayne, and then if it shall please them to giue me their olde Bookes so corrected, I will deliuer them newe for them. And as for those finde faultes, which will doe nothing themselues, I wey them not, for I had rather be seruiceable to my Countrie, than to please some particular persons, as the Lorde doth knowe, who ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and guydes vs all in the right way. Amen. From my house in Bartholmewe lane beside the Royall exchaunge in London, this xxj. day of Februarye. <hi>1576.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>