<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE INHABI∣TANTS OF THE Island of great BRI∣TAINE, Vnitie and Felicity.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103163_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01759</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11895</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103163</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE INHABI∣TANTS OF THE Island of great BRI∣TAINE, Vnitie and Felicity.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The epistle of Gildas, the most ancient British author : who flourished in the yeere of our Lord, 546. And who by his great erudition, sanctitie, and wisedome, acquired the name of sapiens. Faithfully translated out of the originall Latine</title>
                 <author>Gildas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cooke, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>134, 327, that is 325, 1 page, portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_British_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE INHABI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TANTS OF THE Island of great BRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAINE, <hi>Vnitie</hi> and <hi>Felicity.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F all men are generally so much addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted unto the monuments of fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed ages, and every Country particularly
<pb facs="5"/>
unto the antiquities of the Land wherein they inhabit, which is the reason that this our owne Island so much delighteth in behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ruines of <hi>Vero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamium,</hi> the renowned Towne of the <hi>Romans,</hi> the huge and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full stones on <hi>Salisburies</hi> plaine, the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the <hi>Britanes, Thonge</hi> Castle the first seate of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> the trenches and Fortresses of the <hi>Danes,</hi> and the Abbey of <hi>Battaile</hi> the
<pb facs="5"/>
trophey of the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> that I may omit the quoines of the old. Emperours, the tombs of conquering Kings, with the Armes, swords and Launces of famous men, being all held in estimation, of purpose to reward with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall commendation the worthy actions of deceased persons, and to leave us examples to imitate their right No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enterprises: How much more are wee then bound with affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate
<pb facs="6"/>
eyes to behold this ancient Author <hi>Gildas,</hi> who doth not onely present unto our view the lively Image of this Land, how in glory of beautifull Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in pollished order of good husbandry, &amp; in industrious trafficke of merchandise, shee shined above a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand yeeres agoe (at which time some ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant men suppose she was onely over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growne with a wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="6"/>
with Barbarisme) but also that she did as then bring forth unto the world learning, wisdome and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious vertue, which above all these are most highly to bee honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And although some fresh water soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers (who never saw the large Sea of ancient writers) may imagine every shallow brooke of our late pamphle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to bee the very Ocean of learning, yet when overpassing our
<pb facs="7"/>
mechanical Chroniclers I looke into <hi>Malmsbury</hi> and <hi>Hungtington,</hi> and others such as these, yea and above them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to venerable <hi>Bede</hi> and <hi>Gildas,</hi> me seemeth that traveiling over the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren <hi>Alpes</hi> I descend downe into pleasant and fruitfull <hi>Italy,</hi> or sayling beyond the rude <hi>Ethiopians</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> I arrive on the coasts of the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Country of <hi>China.</hi> But falling on this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of antiquitie (<hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>
I meane) I found my selfe instantly so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted unto him, that what for mine owne recreation, and what to deceive the tedious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of my lingring imprisonment: and lastly, that they who are not able, for want of the tongue to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase the knowledge of him in his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Latine, should not remaine altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther destitute of so great riches, I painted him out though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfully,
<pb facs="8"/>
yet howsoever in our <hi>English</hi> language: In w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> attempt, I found two especiall difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the one he was in many places (through the negligence of them in whose hands he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted) so over-eaten with the rust of time, that I could scarcely discerne his lively Portrature, the other his sentences were so long and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure, that they would be harsh and disliking to the reader, yet love overcomming all, and
<pb facs="8"/>
pleasure drawing mee forward, I adventured as touching the first, to ayme at this Image, &amp; give a guesse where I could not determine the certainety, and for the last to set himselfe (as neere as I could) according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per fashion, knowing it to be as undecent to turne his grave spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches into idle words, and his long periods into short sentences, as to picture a sad man with a pleasant looke,
<pb facs="9"/>
and to draw the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfet of a reverent Iudge not in his robes but in some light at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire: Wherefore I must intreate for the obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie the readers atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the tedious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse his patience, and for mine owne enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise his pardon.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The cause why <hi>Gildas</hi> alledgeth almost only the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note>One silly writer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfully noteth how <hi>Gildas</hi> (leaving all au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of men) fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth only the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, little conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that he intending
<pb facs="9"/>
to reproove the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved lives of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Prelates, could finde no Patrons so worthy and able to protect him, as the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who bent all their powers to batter downe the enormous offences of Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; as for the Church having not long before (by the conclusion of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive persecution) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome her most grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous enemies, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly
<pb facs="10"/>
afterwards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countring with her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall rebells, the horrible <hi>Arians</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, she could hardly yet finde a time to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse these abuses, and for the Doctors who were some of them but lately dead, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as yet unborne, the later were not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, and the former had not by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of time received their strength and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for if I may compare small things unto great
<pb facs="10"/>
Authors are like coates of Armes, which by antiquitie purchase commendations.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gildas</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures not after the vulgar Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
   </p>
   <p>Another matter not onely cavilled at by the former carper, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served also by <hi>Pollidor Virgill</hi> is, that in most of the citations of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, he very farre differeth from the vulgar translation; a thing not much to bee merveiled at, for it is not unknowne unto the learned, how in old time there were many
<pb facs="11"/>
Translations of the Bible, for extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of which dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous varietie, and establishing of Gods Word in one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect uniformitie, Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of Pope <hi>Damasus,</hi> Translated the Old Testament out of the Hebrew, and also the New Testament out of the Greeke, whereof <hi>Gildas</hi> could not be ignorant, sithence he flourished about one hund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed
<pb facs="11"/>
yeeres afterwards, and was a man of great knowledge and wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; but in respect this Island had beene long corrupted with Heretickes, and now oppressed with Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, it is likely that the Church in <hi>Britaine</hi> (by reason of the tumults of such rebellious and outragious enemies) wanting her due pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence, could not as yet display the banner of this reformed Bible, but marched under the
<pb facs="12"/>
Ensigne of some other Translation which our Authour speaking ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally to the whole Land) hath for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie unto the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fashion (as it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth) vouchsafed here to use, being especially as apt as any other to reprove the disorders of the Iland, and no way patronizing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Arians</hi> or <hi>Pella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians</hi> (the most deadly cankers as then of the Christian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth) or any other
<pb facs="12"/>
heresie, that hath ever since lifted up her vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous head against the Church of God.</p>
   <p>Another thing very much to bee lamented and merveiled at is,<note place="margin">The reasons why <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> was at this time so defiled with vices.</note> that not onely the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Princes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the Spirituall Rulers (whose lives should be a light unto the rest, and salt to preserve the soules of men from corruption) had at this time many of them so degenerated from all goodnes, as not only it
<pb facs="13"/>
provoked the justice of God to dispossesse them of their Country and give it to their deadly foes the Saxons, but also made <hi>Pollidor Virgill</hi> suppose that <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> did never after the persecution of <hi>Dioclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> perfectly returne unto the unity of the Catholicke Church againe; an opinion by <hi>Gildasses</hi> owne words refelled, for he sheweth how after the stormy winter (as hee calleth, it of this persecution,
<pb facs="13"/>
succeeded the flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing spring of true Christian and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke religion; but the Author himselfe decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth some notorious causes of the ruine of as well Civill as Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall discipline, and the first was heresies, for upon this fruitfull seede of the Gospell, came the <hi>Arians,</hi> and scattered the darnell of their detestable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, yea (as he saith) all other damnable Sectaries breathed out
<pb facs="14"/>
upon the Land, their venemous poyson, and not onely this, but also from the very bowels of <hi>Britaine</hi> was borne that accursed wretch <hi>Pellagius,</hi> and shortly after the death of <hi>Gildas</hi> were the <hi>Britaines</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with the darkesome cloud of the <hi>Quartodecimani</hi> (who varied frō the Church of God in celebrating the feast of Easter, these truely were the mothes that did eate the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the governmēt
<pb facs="14"/>
of the realme. Another was bloudy warre (the depraver of Civill dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, and the Author of disorder, that for many yeeres built here his Fortresse, who as hee commandeth for the time all Spirituall and nationall Lawes to silence, so hee corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the manners of all Countries through which hee marcheth; by the power of warre were Infidels planted in the Land, who as they were professed
<pb facs="15"/>
foes of the faith of God, so were their lives defiled with all offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and these also in all likelihood infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the <hi>Britaines</hi> with the plague of their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. After the warres were ended, and <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> together with the <hi>Saxons</hi> (like Sheepe and Goates) continued in one fold, altogether for a while the scourge of misery (which cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stised the Christian <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes</hi>) terrified them from transgressing the
<pb facs="15"/>
Commandements of God, yet plentifull peace (the Nurse of sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suality) so lulled them afterwards asleepe in her lap with a seeming but deceitfull security, that hereupon sprung the last cause of their confusion (to wit) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding wickednesse sprouting out from the roote of abundant wealth: For according unto <hi>Moses; Incrassatus est dilectus, &amp; recalcitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit; incrassatus, impin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guatus, dilatatus dereliquit
<pb facs="16"/>
Deum factorem suum, &amp;c.</hi> and even as the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Israel</hi> did sit them downe to eate and drinke, and then arose to play, untill the fury of our Lord was pawred out upon them; so the <hi>Britaines</hi> growing fat in worldly pleasures, and foule in hidious sinnes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued on in their earthly contentments, untill the sword of the <hi>Saxons</hi> (which was scarcely as yet put in the sheath againe) was by
<pb facs="16"/>
the sufferance of God drawne out afresh to deprive them of their pleasant Country. But although mine Author <hi>Gildas</hi> discovereth the defects of Princes and Prelates, yet let no man thinke that any Subjects can for the deadly sinnes of their Superiours, either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive or disobey them, since neither <hi>David</hi> did for his adultery with <hi>Bersabee,</hi> and murther of his faithfull servant <hi>Vrias,</hi> lose his royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb facs="17"/>
nor yet the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the chaire of <hi>Moses,</hi> was any whit diminished, although <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisees</hi> for a time possessed the same, but that the <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> who were clensed were sent to the Priests (although unworthy of their Primacy) and <hi>Caiphas</hi> himselfe (albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it he was the persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of <hi>Christ Iesus</hi>) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesied, because he was high Priest of that yeere; all which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse against the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes
<pb facs="17"/>
who have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versely maintained the contrary. Neither yet let any man falsly imagine, that the Land was wholly as then drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in iniquities, for (as <hi>Gildas</hi> doth in 2 places apparantly manifest) there were diverse at that very time, whose vertues he doth most highly commend and reverence.</p>
   <p>Now before I doe harbour in the Haven of my desired end, I must of necessitie passe
<pb facs="18"/>
by three rockes of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding danger, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives (I meane) of <hi>Gildas,</hi> against some sorts of people most happily combined un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Majesties go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the first the <hi>Britanes,</hi> the most aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient inhabitantes of this Island, the other the <hi>Irish</hi> together with the <hi>Scottish,</hi> and <hi>Pictes</hi> who next possessed part of the Land, and last the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> who have very long enjoyed the most
<pb facs="18"/>
large and fruitfull por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Country. The <hi>Britaines</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the pen of Sir <hi>Iohn Price</hi> (a learned Knight and writer of theirs) suspect <hi>Gildas</hi> for a Libeller, but doe hardly also sustaine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Authors, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge also out of him any thing that may seeme disgracefull to the Nation, unto whom truely as I have ever borne all due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect and tender affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, so doe I most
<pb facs="19"/>
humbly crave their pardon in a word or two without offence, to defend their wise and worthy Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men whom I may well compare unto a father who (correcting his childe) telleth him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his faults and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, or unto the Prophets who in old time reproving the <hi>Israelites</hi> did lay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before their eyes but their sinnes and offences, or to the man in the Gospell who
<pb facs="19"/>
labouring to make his vine bring forth the desired fruit; dresseth the roote with unsavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dung. He doth not declare as now (O re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Britaines</hi>) how yee releived your friends the <hi>Galles</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the invincible Legions of <hi>Caesar,</hi> how valiently yee defended your Land against his conquering army, how one King of a little cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of your Island (<hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lures</hi> or South-Wales I meane) maintained
<pb facs="20"/>
warre against the whole power of <hi>Rome</hi> and the world, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards onely by mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune falling into the hands of his honorable enemies, was by them held in equall estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for worthinesse, with <hi>Perses</hi> the succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sour of <hi>Alexander</hi>▪ but for valour with <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the great himselfe, he nameth not your victorious <hi>Vortimer,</hi> nor yet your invincible <hi>Arthur</hi> who in twelve foughten fields over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw
<pb facs="20"/>
your cruell enemies the <hi>Saxons,</hi> he leaveth those discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to his Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle which <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Huntinton</hi> in the actions of <hi>Arthur</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, hee revealeth now onely your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, but why? because hee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your abuses; hee chasticeth your vices, because hee would cherish your vertues; he aggravateth your offences <hi>ut sugeret mel de petra oleumque de
<pb facs="21"/>
saxo durissimo,</hi> that hee may strike the fire of grace out of flinty hearts, and bring the oyle of Charity out of stony minds; he saith the <hi>Romanes</hi> did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor yee, not so much with Armes as with the threates of their countenances, but tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not how before that yee encountred (as most true it is) with their puissant power, and what was it (alas) for the naked to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist the armed, for them
<pb facs="21"/>
who were altogether unskilfull in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of fight to joyne in battell with the best practised souldiers, and one little Island to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with the whole world? Yee fell with the generall calamity of the earth, into the subjection of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> Empire. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards (they say) ye were unfaithfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause yee killed them who were left in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie over yee: And who can tell what oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
<pb facs="22"/>
they offered yee to execute that slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon them: wee see the cruelty that commonly all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querous exercise on their subjects; experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth that all almost are tyrannous, and few or none mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate; yee wrought the like stratagem as the <hi>Cecilians</hi> did, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards on the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>; why are yee so soulely condemned as unfaithfull, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it succeeded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily?
<pb facs="22"/>
For ye were upon this occasion troden under the feete of your enemies; it is a Proverbe that never Rebell prevaileth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his Prince, and what is the reason? but this, if hee prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth hee is no Rebell, but usurpeth rather the title of a reformer of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, I doubt not but King <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, if they had not obtained the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all garland, had beene
<pb facs="23"/>
registred for rebellious traytors, although now they are ranked among the famous Princes: so actions are measu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not according to the intents, but after the events. But hereupon ensued your misery and reproach, ye were againe overcome (as he saith) without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance, and therefore not accounted valiant! and did not the Iewes (who were truely as couragious a Nation as ever was on the
<pb facs="23"/>
earth) open the gates of <hi>Ierusalem</hi> to <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> because they could notwithstand him? did not the <hi>Persians</hi> (those conquerours of the world) flye the face of the <hi>Macedonians?</hi> and the <hi>Persians</hi> and mighty <hi>Macedonians</hi>▪ submit themselves to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines?</hi> did not those nations who for war-like glory excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all others, runne away as sheepe before these <hi>Italian</hi> Lyons? and why
<pb facs="24"/>
should we then accuse the <hi>Britaines,</hi> (who were in respect a small handfull and never knew the Art of war) if they resisted not the <hi>Romanes</hi> who had three parts of the world at their commandment, and were the most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert souldiers that ever marched on the earth? The <hi>Britaines</hi> upon this became captives! and what Nation was not in subjection to the <hi>Romaines</hi> who held the earth as a slave in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage
<pb facs="24"/>
and ruled her Kings as if they were but servants? These things (noble <hi>Britaines</hi>) <hi>Gildas</hi> somewhat bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly recounteth, but why? that he may with the knife of correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pruine avvay your superfluous and dead branches and leaves of vaine glory and other vices. But although he swayeth throughout his vvorke in great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie, yet can he not so conceale the fire of his fatherly affection,
<pb facs="25"/>
but that it flameth ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> very often to your sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular commendation. Yee were at the first termed unfaithfull, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what occasion I have declared; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards hee showeth your faith in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est degree, in professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (I meane) of the Christian religion, in suffering terrible perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, in obtaining most glorious martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: your flight is objected as reprochfull vnto ye, but when?
<pb facs="25"/>
before yee had the knowledge of warfare, but after ye had atchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the art thereof, hee writeth how under the cōduction of <hi>Maximus,</hi> ye overthrew, though unjustly, yet most vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly two Emperours of the world: but the lively blood of <hi>Britaine</hi> being extended into forraigne Nations, and there extenuated, and lastly, by misfortune extinguished, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trailes and heart of the Island began at home
<pb facs="26"/>
to grow weake and cold, which made her body so long oppressed with the invading dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases of the <hi>Scottish, Pictes,</hi> and <hi>Irish,</hi> and lastly, almost killed with the deadly plague of the <hi>Saxons</hi>: and did not the like befall unto the <hi>Romanes</hi> themselves who having wasted their strength in over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming and keeping other Countries in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, became in the same sort weakned at home, and so fell in
<pb facs="26"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he end to be a prey, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd spoile unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hers? All this is but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he course and chance of fortune, or rather the high pleasure of God, to teach us that in this world there is nothing permanent. And againe our Authour not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning himselfe, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth out into a singular report of your vallor, when (in the reproofe of <hi>Maglocune</hi>) hee saith that your Souldiers were so couragious, as their countenances in
<pb facs="27"/>
battle were not unlike the terrible lookes of young Lions. But that I may passe to the rest, and so conclude this point, he doth so high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extoll the Country, Castles, and Cities of <hi>Britaine,</hi> as truely I am out of doubt the Island hath never since that time flourished in the like glory as then it did: and who so think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth mee deceived, let him but looke into the histories of the <hi>Romans,</hi> where he shall reade of
<pb facs="27"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he Emperors, that did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n this land of <hi>Britaine</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ontinue or finish their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ives, where among <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he rest hee shineth in most eminent Majesty, who shutting up the temple of hellish ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>atry, did first set open the gates of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, and of her peaceable God, Iesus, I meane that <hi>Constantine,</hi> vvho being borne in <hi>Britaine,</hi> &amp; of a <hi>Britaine</hi> Saintly Mother, tooke on him the Emperiall dignity, in this very
<pb facs="28"/>
Island, vvhere so many governors of the vvorld vvould never have made their royall resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, had not the Country beene both fruitfull and civill, but barren and barbarous as the <hi>Romanes</hi> at their first entrance supposed the same to be. Lastly, he manifestly declareth that the land vvas as then also furnished vvith learning, because (vvriting generally an epistle unto the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try) he useth the Latine
<pb facs="28"/>
tongue, which as it had beene a great folly in him to doe, if the same had not beene univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally understood, so doe I verily thinke if the like worke in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine were at this time presented unto the realme, it would little profit without an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter.</p>
   <p>The next sort some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what bitterly taxed by <hi>Gildas,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The excuse of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vective of <hi>Gildas</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Scottish and Irish.</note> are the <hi>Scottish, Pictes,</hi> and <hi>Irish,</hi> who are reproved as blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and barbarous: but
<pb facs="29"/>
when? before ever they received the light and heate of civility, which from the Sunne of the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire did spread throughout all Countries, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly made a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular preparation to the Almighty Grace of the holy Ghost, that afterwards replenished the whole world; but after they had accepted discipline, and were reduced into better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and cheefely above all had imbraced Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb facs="29"/>
and Catholike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, then behold what these <hi>Benjamins</hi> proved, who by the British <hi>Iacob</hi> (<hi>Gildas</hi> I meane) are termed <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> rapaces</hi> ravenous Wolves? see if that was not truely fulfilled in them which was right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophesied of that worthy <hi>Benjamin</hi> S. <hi>Paul,</hi> which is <hi>Mane rapit ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere dividit escas,</hi> in the morning or at the first they gained their boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by spoyling, but in the evening or at the
<pb facs="30"/>
last they distributed their foode or baites; what foode? but to satisfie the hungry soules of men: what baites? but to catch such fish as might serve for the festivall table of our Saviour: Looke into <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Cornewall,</hi> and see how many Townes beare yet the names of <hi>Irish</hi> Saints, who harboured there, not as before to punish the <hi>Britaines</hi> with death, but to draw them to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="30"/>
of eternall life! Peruse the histories of the Countries beyond <hi>Humber,</hi> you shall read how the <hi>Pictes,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who sometimes broke downe the Northerne fortifications, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded the Land, did afterwards beate down the Bulwarke of hell, delivered the soules which sinne did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in bondage, and made them the blessed captives of Christ, men undoubtedly of rare
<pb facs="31"/>
holinesse, and unspot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted conversation, had they not beene a little blemished with an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious opinion, about the celebration of <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> which as venerable <hi>Bede</hi> signifieth continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the longer among them, because inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in a farre removed region of the world, they had not heard of the Cannons of the Church which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the contrary. Moreover as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our did feede them bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily,
<pb facs="31"/>
whom before he refreshed spiritually, so did they of <hi>Scotland,</hi> not onely with the bread of life, releeve their neighbours, but also received the <hi>Britaines</hi> (when they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulsed out of their Country by the <hi>Saxons</hi>) into their bosome, and suffered them quietly to inhabit by them in <hi>Cumberland</hi>; and with like charitable affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on entertained also the <hi>Saxons</hi> with their Prince <hi>Edgar,</hi> when they fled
<pb facs="32"/>
from the countenance of the victorius <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching their old barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous misbehaviour (which <hi>Gildas</hi> here mentioneth) we have no more reason to upbraide the <hi>Scottish</hi> therewith, then to cast in the teethes of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined <hi>Italians,</hi> what their Country was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Saturne</hi> did first instruct them in civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, being a time so overgrowne with rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="32"/>
as the Poets doe thereupon wittily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scant, that men of that age were borne out of the trunckes of trees. For in processe of time by carefull diligence commeth the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and amendment of Countries, and by carelesse negligence fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the corruption and destruction of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
   <p>The last are the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>English,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The excuse of his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veare cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suring of the <hi>English.</hi>
      </note> called by him a people odious to God and man, to
<pb facs="33"/>
God, because they were Idolatrous Infidels, to man, because they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and oppressed the Christian <hi>Britaines,</hi> and although he enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth himselfe in the dispraise of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let no man never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse suppose that he uttereth this of any malice as stung with the dreadfull miseries with the which they vexed his Country: For who knoweth not that the <hi>English</hi> were in his age ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb facs="33"/>
of Christ, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Land: But according to <hi>Esay, In the dennes wherein dragons did formerly dwell, greene reedes and rushes did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards grow</hi>; and after the sentence of <hi>Hosea; Where it was sayd ye were no people of mine, there shall the same persons bee named the sonnes of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</hi> Yea the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Liberds, the Beares, and the Wolves shall (as the Prophet writeth) quietly lodge and live with Oxen,
<pb facs="34"/>
Sheepe, Kiddes, and Calves, <hi>and a little child</hi> (no doubt the Sonne of the Virgin) <hi>shall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne them all.</hi> For if ever the wilde Olive were changed into the rightfull Olive of our Lord, or if ever tree brought forth the true fruits of goodnesse, then were both these undoubtedly verified in the <hi>Saxons</hi>: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they came but lately into the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, yet having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, they laboured di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently,
<pb facs="34"/>
and underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the race of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian life, they ranne most swiftly, and gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the garland victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously; and who so thinketh I exceede in their commendation, let him but cast his eyes round about this Realme, and hee shall see the Churches and Monuments of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (some fevv onely excepted) altogether founded by them; and that vve may leave the dead buildings, and
<pb facs="35"/>
come to the lively stones of the heavenly <hi>Ierusalem</hi>; how are the Provinces, shires, and Parishes of the Land se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally adorned with mighty number of <hi>English</hi> Saints, and if we may measure by the Governours, what the people were (since un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the examples of their Rulers, the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are commonly conformable) let us but consider the royall off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and we shall finde that
<pb facs="35"/>
never in any land so many Princes left their worldly estates to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Christian pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and draw in the Yoake of our Saviour, and never so many of Kingly blood were canonised in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Register, as in this our Country; what shall I say more, <hi>In om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem terram exivit sonus eorum,</hi> their renowne is spread over the whole world, and their glory fixed above the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; in so much as
<pb facs="36"/>
      <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury</hi> deriving the Pedegree of holy <hi>Edward</hi> the Confessour, sheweth a descent, not onely of Kings but also of Saints so as to the Church then among us those Words of <hi>Esay</hi> may be fitly applyed, <hi>Reges ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient tibi</hi>: and againe, <hi>Mamilla regum lactaberis,</hi> Kings shall doe service unto thee, and with the teates of Princes thou shalt be nourished. Let us leave the heavens and returne to the
<pb facs="36"/>
earth, was the glory of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> which now mounted in blessed vertues aboue the Skie, bounded here below, onely in the Cloystures of Monasteries? No, but as the shaddow fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the body, so likewise ensued all commodities requisite in a well ordered regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and first as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching learning (which manureth the mindes of men, and maketh them in due season bring forth their time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="37"/>
fruites) they foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ded both the Vniversi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ties of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>bridge</hi>: For the ancien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> lawes, the most excel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lent helme which stea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the state, the bridle which restrayned di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempered wils, and the very soule of the body of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, they were by them chiefely framed: and did their prayse onely consist in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of pietie and peace? and was not their war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like glory equall to
<pb facs="37"/>
their civill govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? not so truely: but as a well compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted body hath bones and sinewes sutable to the head, so was their powerfull strength an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to their other vertues, and not-onely of singular proofe at home; but also obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a most high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation abroad in forraigne Countries: All which heroicall actions they accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in lesse than five hundred yeeres not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
<pb facs="38"/>
they were during the same time almost continually ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther invaded by stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or molested by unquiet neighbours.</p>
   <p>And thus have I somewhat inlarged my selfe in declaring the undoubted worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of these three Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, because I shall be enforced in this my translation to discover their ancient imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; neither have I used this commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation as sugar; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="38"/>
these distastfull pills may bee the better swallowed, but of purpose to shut up their mouths who otherwise might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps despightfully up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braide them with these old offences; which truely they have no more reason to doe, than those irreligious tongues who (audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously talking of the blessed Apostles) call Saint <hi>Peter</hi> the denyer of his Master, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,
<pb facs="39"/>
Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> the Publican, for if wee should be esteemed as we have beene, what were we other than the children of wrath; but by the grace of God we are as we are, and I beseech Christ his grace may not be voyd in us.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">How the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended of the blood royall of these three Nations.</note>And now verily it is with great applause to be received, that it hath pleased God to make the royall lines of these three severall people to meete in the
<pb facs="39"/>
Center of his Majesties person: For of the first I meane the <hi>Britaines</hi>) he is come by his last and best knowne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scent out of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to wit the daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> the seventh, whose Grandfather <hi>Owen Theoder</hi> was of their Princely blood: For the second, as cleere as the Sunne, hee is by due originall lawfull King of <hi>Scotland</hi>: and for the third, it is knowne to those who have any experience
<pb facs="40"/>
in antiquities, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Margaret</hi> (from whom all the Kings of <hi>Scot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>land</hi> have these fiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> hundred yeeres issued) was the onely true in heritrice unto her great Vncle <hi>Edward</hi> the Confessour, and her Grandfather <hi>Edmund Ironside</hi>; and in one word to all the Saintly <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> so as a lineall right hath from that time hitherto remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>Scotland,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>William</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering
<pb facs="40"/>
      <hi>Norman</hi> did by the sword (as especiall descider of kingdomes) not onely obtaine the actuall possession of the Realme, but also ever since leave the same unto his posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And yet moreover that none of the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> race may in his Majesties enjoying of the Kingdome, finde themselves agrieved, God in his wisedome also disposeth (as to the whole realme it is most apparent) that he
<pb facs="41"/>
likewise rightly deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth his title from the off-spring of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour. Yea and that the <hi>Danish</hi> too (if any now remaine who were planted here by their puissant Lords) may have no cause to repine, behold the Queene his Majesties Wife and their Sonne our Prince, or excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hope, are come of the <hi>Danish,</hi> among whom that renowned <hi>Canatus</hi> was sometimes King of this Land, in
<pb facs="41"/>
whom it is hard to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine whether, his devotion to God, his great conquests, or his generall clemeney de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: In all which is to be consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered hovv God of his goodnesse hath in one man conjoyned these mighty houses, vvhich were not onely for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scent and Country sometimes so diverse, but also in deadly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred so far disagreeing, and in bloody wars so
<pb facs="42"/>
violent and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, not unlike the frame of a perfect bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which is contrived of the foure contrary and repugnant ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and also that those people which since the confusion of <hi>Babylon</hi> were ever seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, should as loving brethren be now uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his Majesties Kingdome, even as the Rivers which arising from contrary regions of North and South doe notwithstanding
<pb facs="42"/>
fall into one maine Sea, and are made in the end one mighty wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;<note place="margin">How the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Britaines</hi> are united in this Realme.</note> For as you shall perceive in this ensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing treatise, the <hi>Britaines</hi> and <hi>Saxons</hi> were not onely sundry Nations, but also in discord most dissenting: to number the battailes that were fought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, were an endlesse labour, they confronted either o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers many hundred yeeres in continuall hatred, three Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="43"/>
were most diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, their lawes &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes divers; the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> distressed and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possessed of their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, fertile, and Native soyle, and driven by the power of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries to live poore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the barren moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of <hi>Cambria</hi> or <hi>Wales,</hi> the English in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaders raigned and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed freely of all the rest of the Land, untill it pleased the God of peace to make an end of all controversies.
<pb facs="43"/>
The English in time having overcome them received the <hi>Britaine</hi> into the body of their Common-wealth and kingdome, they never excepted at the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie that had beene betweene their lawes and ours, they saw how in this very realme the <hi>Normanes</hi> had agreed before under one selfe-same rule and regiment with the Kentish <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> notwithstanding their legall customes were of another fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion:
<pb facs="44"/>
For as by skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Musitians is made of sundry instruments one delightfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort, and as by Lapida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of diverse colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red stones, one most rich Iewell, and as of the Starres (which va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in severall motions) proceedeth the perfect harmony of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens: So of these sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Countries, and customes of <hi>Britaines, Saxons, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> is now framed one most excellent
<pb facs="44"/>
Commonwealth: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet was it object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the <hi>Britaines</hi> having beene long star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with oppressing povertie, would gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily raven on the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish riches and Posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, for they were then neerer the time of Christ, and so more perfectly instructed with his Charity, who received the needy and sometimes prodigall child, to bee partaker with his wealthy elder brother, who rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="45"/>
him that entred into his worke at the latter end of the day, with as large hire as the other, who labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the morning, who accepted into his favour as well the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles as the Iewes. And what insued hereupon? hath any English-man beene hereby deprived of his profit? No sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but although there have reigned 5 Kings and Queenes succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively descended of the <hi>Britaine</hi> Nation, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="45"/>
wee have had Generalls, Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, Iudges, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, there was never as yet any Welchman (as we call him) boulstred out by their authority to afflict the English with any injuries. The cōmodities that flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from this blessed union were many: first the charitie betweene both Nations, a thing most acceptable in the sight of God; the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="46"/>
with the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of so worthy a people; the enriching of the same by making the marches and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Country (which heretofore lay waste by reason of the warre) now subject to industrious husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry: the incorporating of that Land as a limbe now of <hi>England,</hi> which was not onely some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a continuall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary, but also ever ready to entertaine and assist any forraigne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion:
<pb facs="46"/>
the fortifying of the power of the realme with the forces of those vvho deteined them before vvith dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord at home from augmenting their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion abroad: the finishing of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakeable charges of vvarre and expenses in maintaining garrisons on the fronteyres: the stincking of all spoyle and stuffe; and the ending of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion of Christian blood.</p>
   <pb facs="47"/>
   <p>And novv if it bee easier to imitate a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer example, than bee the beginner of any action; vvhy then doe not the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Scottish</hi> seeing this vvith farre more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse conjoyne in one? If discorde hath heretofore raigned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, the like hath also raged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Britaines</hi>; if the Lawes of the one are diverse from us, the Lawes of the other have beene
<pb facs="47"/>
as different, if the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities of warre with the <hi>Britaines</hi> have beene so great and grievous, no lesse have also beene those with the <hi>Scottish</hi>; if the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Britaines</hi> and us, are so great and gracious, why should not the same be also in like sort betweene us and the <hi>Scottish?</hi> the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Britaines</hi> were in language most unlike, the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Scottish</hi> are of one
<pb facs="48"/>
tongue; and if the names of persons and places doe not much deceive us, the Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne people of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are either descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> or at the least very much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termingled with the <hi>English</hi> blood, besides that, it is to be suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed that many of them are issued from the <hi>Britaines,</hi> since their confiners in <hi>Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (which was a part sometimes of <hi>Scotland</hi>) have heretofore beene
<pb facs="48"/>
      <hi>Cambro</hi> or Welch <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi>: For Nations by Neighbourhood passe one into another, even as wee perceive by neerenesse of property the purest of the water to become ayre, and the finest of the ayre to change into fire; the <hi>English</hi> might also have justly conceived a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie against the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> in admitting them into the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the kingdome, least (as the Lawyers say) they should have accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="49"/>
themselves in their <hi>remitter,</hi> and upon this occasion have claimed their ancient possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Land where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in fore passed ages they were (as they thought) wrongfully deprived; which can no way be objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the realme of <hi>Scotland</hi> who (saving the most righteous ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of our Soveraigne Lord to the Crowne) can make no lawfull challenge of her fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers inheritance, but
<pb facs="49"/>
commeth as a Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Virgin with the royall portion of a Kingdome, to bee joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in marriage with her husband <hi>England</hi>; the banes betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> were bid with many a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble battaile, and the match was made with blood shed; but the union of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> was begun in loving wedlocke, and established in lawfull descending issue; Since it hath therefore plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="50"/>
God to graft them both in one stocke, let no man seeke to rent them into two sundry trees, or rather breake them a sunder, since he hath formed them into one body, let none la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to dissever the members of the same; since hee hath created them into one little world, and encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed it about with one mighty sea, and now after thousands of yeeres reduced into one entire regiment,
<pb facs="50"/>
let none presume to cut in two that webbe which God hath wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in one, or separate what hee hath joyned, or spurne against his providence.</p>
   <p>It is no new thing to see the greatnesse of Kingdomes encrease by the union of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries;<note place="margin">How other Kingdomes have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased by Vnions.</note> for to omit the <hi>Assirians, Persians,</hi> and <hi>Macedonians,</hi> who not onely flourished in the former and more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne ages of the world, but also for the
<pb facs="51"/>
situation of the regions are farre distant from us, and to consider a little of the <hi>Romanes</hi> and other more fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and adjoyning Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions who have in latter dayes growne to the height of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne, did not those Iron legges of <hi>Daniels</hi> statue, the Cittie I meane that swayed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the universall world, gather her first arising strength, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving divers Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries (which shee sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued)
<pb facs="51"/>
into the corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of her common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth? did not the <hi>French</hi> by combining sundry Dukedomes and Earledomes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (of which some to our cost and losse we have good cause to remember) become the most ample and fruitfull Kingdome of all Christendome? was not <hi>Spaine</hi> within these few hundred yeeres distracted in severall pettie Dominions, the beames of whose glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="52"/>
by intermariages conjoyning in one are growne, doe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shine through many parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to the East and West <hi>Indians?</hi> The Dutchy of <hi>Burgundy</hi> the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Christendome, was not sometimes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in the small prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities of <hi>Flanders, Henault, Holland,</hi> and the rest, all which are now by uniting of houses gathered into one Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet of exceeding beauty? But let us
<pb facs="52"/>
leave travailing abroad and returne home in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our owne Country; were not the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>English</hi> severed in seven smal kingdomes, and afterwards by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest brought into one whole Monarchie? Were not the <hi>Britaines</hi> or <hi>Welch</hi> divided in three sundry regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and hath not the force of the <hi>English</hi> fornace melted all their crownes into one mighty streame of gold, and like the rod
<pb facs="53"/>
of <hi>Moses</hi> devoured all the rods of the <hi>Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>: and if we but enter into the histories ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our owne Iland or otherwise of these forraigne Nations, shal we not every where easily finde, that as by divided Kingdomes there came nothing but discord, poverty, and debasements, so from united powers groweth tranquility, plenty, and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence: we see the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a great poole
<pb facs="53"/>
conserveth it selfe, which if it were sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in small plashes would be quickely ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dryed up with the sunne, or soked downe in the earth, and it is well noted by Saint <hi>Gregory,</hi> writing upon Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> that at the comming of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Rome</hi> was in her perfection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause shee was contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and how the
<pb facs="54"/>
Kingdome of the <hi>Iewes</hi> ranne then to confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in regard it was distributed into sundry Seignories, grounding his reason on those words of Christ, with which I will end this point, <hi>Omne regnum in se divisum desolabitur,</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Kingdome divided in it selfe shall fall to desolation.</p>
   <p>Shew not therefore your selves (as the Poet saith) so farre removed from the Sunne (which is the authour of wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome)
<pb facs="54"/>
that ye should seeke with envie to hinder the raysing of that frame which God hath so charitably buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but rather as the same Poet in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of <hi>Dido</hi> uttereth, that a <hi>Trojan</hi> and <hi>Tirian,</hi> shall by her with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall affection bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected, so let us all with one voyce, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Scottish</hi> shall by us now with love alike be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained. Neither yet if the matter it selfe can
<pb facs="55"/>
be concluded, let there bee any difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the name of this Kingdome:<note place="margin">How uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nations have beene called by one gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall name.</note> for as it hath beene usuall to unite Nations, so hath it beene as common to call united Nations by one name; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Greece</hi> had in times past beene divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into many Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, yet being all subjected afterwards under the dominion of one, the former names vanished away,
<pb facs="55"/>
and the whole was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned by the name of the Empire of <hi>Greece,</hi> the like was of <hi>Italy,</hi> whose severall governments being gathered into one were all intituled by one name; the <hi>Aquitanes, Celtes,</hi> and <hi>Belgickes</hi> were in former ages comprised under the name of <hi>Galles,</hi> and having beene after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards severed in sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Provinces, are now almost all conjoyned in one entire famous
<pb facs="56"/>
Kingdome, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the name of the most puissant part thereof is termed <hi>France</hi>; our Ancestors not many yeeres since did familiarly know <hi>Castil, Arragon,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which are all now universally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into one migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty name of <hi>Spaine</hi>; so were the West <hi>Saxons, Mercians, Norfolcians, Northumbers,</hi> and the rest of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignties, changed by our Monarch <hi>Egbert</hi>
      <pb facs="56"/>
into the potent and glorious name of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>: and <hi>Scottland</hi> doth in like sort not onely comprehend the <hi>Scots</hi> but also the <hi>Hebri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> and others;<note place="margin">How con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently the name of <hi>Britaine</hi> agreeth to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the whole Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> If therefore this hath beene so greatly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctised, let us not refuse to follow so many worthy presidents, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially since it is not required at our hands that we should assume a newfound name, but the most ancient name of the whole Island,
<pb facs="57"/>
the most famous name by which it hath beene knowne to all the mighty Emperours of <hi>Rome,</hi> and blazed throughout the world, the most learned name as the bookes of the <hi>Latines,</hi> and all other tongues and languages doe largely witnesse, and lastly the most ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall name of all the inhabitants, for what are the <hi>English, Scottish,</hi> and <hi>Welch,</hi> but three parts of the whole large and most beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="57"/>
Island of <hi>Britaine?</hi> And surely as it were absurd in familiar speech of <hi>London</hi> to tearme it after the names of the particular Wards or companies of the City, and not according to the entire Corporation, or to call any Shire of the Realme, after the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds or divisions of the same, and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the well knowne title of the whole Country, so is it as farre against all
<pb facs="58"/>
reason that our little world of <hi>Britaine</hi> being now included in one Kingdome, should be dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>evered in names that would but ever rubbe up the remembrance of former injuries, and be Nurses of dissenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which his Majestie not unlike that anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Romulus</hi> seeketh providently to abolish, and making a skilfull mixture of the <hi>English, Scottish,</hi> and <hi>Welch,</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth now to severe them all into three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct
<pb facs="58"/>
orders, of the Nobility, Gentry, and Cominalty, of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Realme of great <hi>Britaine,</hi> vvhich being of three sundry people framed into one happy Soveraigntie, I beseech the Almighty Trinity, to bring to a most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Vnitie.</p>
   <p>Thus have I vvith<note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion.</note> more good vvill than good skill presumed upon the mention of these three people to leape rashly into the matter of the union,
<pb facs="59"/>
vvherein although I may bee condemned for vvant of discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet no man shall ever accuse mee for lacke of indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>