<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103225_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01853</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11995</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103225</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The tragedie of Lodouick Sforza Duke of Millan. By Robert Gomersall</title>
                 <author>Gomersall, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Marriot, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 70, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Argument.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Odovicke Sforza,</hi> after hee had cunningly supplanted the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chesse from the wardship of her sonne <hi>Galeazzo,</hi> as cunningly practizeth to beethe murtherer of him, of whom he would seeme to be the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector. To this end he was to remoue this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment. <hi>Isabella</hi> daughter to the Prince of <hi>Calabria,</hi> and Grand-childe vnto <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> was wife to <hi>Galeazzo.</hi> A wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of a spirit as high as her birth, and equall to <hi>Sforza</hi> in all things but the sex: shee percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the stupidity of her husband, and how that whatsoeuer she proiected for his safety, he discouered to his vncle, for his ouerthrow, makes her father secretly acquainted with all the passages, desiring him to vindicate his son in law from the vsurpation of his Protector. This could not be so priuately dispatched, but that <hi>Sforza</hi> had an incling of it, whether out of his owne reach hee guessed it: or by his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewes sottishnesse he vnderstood it. To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent then his owne ruine, whilst he intends his Nephews, he ventures on those remedies which the height of feare rather rusheth on, then chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth,
<pb facs="7"/>
which more expresse and exchange, then remoue, or auoyd a danger. He knew the French claime to <hi>Naples,</hi> to the prosecution of which he sollicites the yong King; whom either his right, or inconsideratenesse quickly armes vnto the action. But before his comming, hee by continuall messengers deludes the old King, and makes him beleeue that there was no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of his comming, and that the French iourney vnto <hi>Naples,</hi> as it was onely the childe of rumor, &amp; had no being but frō fame, so in a very short space, in the age of a wonder it would vanish and expire. Thus was <hi>Ferdinand</hi> perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from his necessary defence, till hauing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly vnderstood that all defence would be too late, the French being already very strong vpon his frontires, cheated, not conquer'd, hee dyes and leaues his sonne <hi>Alphonso</hi> heire of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and his troubles. The French King being now entred in person into <hi>Italy, Galeazzo</hi> dyes of a poyson at <hi>Pauia,</hi> when <hi>Sforza</hi> has brought this worse poyson into his Country. But the French growing prodigiously victorious, and almost by the very seeing ouer comming their opposites, <hi>Sforza</hi> begins to be apprehensiue of his owne danger, and striues to rid himselfe of these incumbrances, in the which a too much prouidence had intangled him. A consideration
<pb facs="7"/>
without doubt necessary, but almost past the season, it being neer vnto an impossibility to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell him now, whom it was far from any diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty at the first not to admit. So that this se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond resolution did onely proclaime the folly of the first, which either in wisdome hee should not haue ventur'd on, or, in honesty not haue altred. But howsoeuer, hee enters into a new league with the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and giues the French after their victorious returne from <hi>Naples</hi> halfe an ouerthrow at <hi>Taro.</hi> And now when hee thinks himselfe confirm'd in his Dukedome, when he as little fear'd ruine, as he deseru'd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation; the French King dyes suddenly, to whom <hi>Lewis,</hi> the true Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tular Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi> succeeded, with him <hi>Sfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaes</hi> late friend, the <hi>Venetians</hi> conclude a league. Thus <hi>Sforza</hi> being left alone, raiseth two armies vnder the conduct of the two <hi>Sanseuerins,</hi> men, whom hee had highly fauour'd and aduanced. But it is scarce seene, that a faithlesse Master should haue a trusty seruant, and hee that hath no respect to his owne word, shall in the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mest of his necessities, finde all others promises but words. The elder reuolts, and the yonger, without the least show of resistance, flyes, and <hi>Sforza</hi> himselfe is so closely pursued, that he can scarce get away safe into <hi>Germany.</hi> The French
<pb facs="8"/>
abusing their late victory, the <hi>Millanesi</hi> with a generall consent, recall <hi>Sforza;</hi> who, like a mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting snow, ouerflowes all before him, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers most of his Duchy, with the same easinesse that he had lost it. The strength of his Army consisted especially of Swizzers, whom the late ouerthrow of the warlike Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and these Italian wars, had raised to the height of admiration. But to be valiant is not to haue all vertues: these were as strong in treachery, as in battle, they lead <hi>Sforza</hi> in the habite of a Swizzer into the French camp, through which in the same habit they had promised to conduct him. Thus hauing beene twice betrayd, and now a prisoner, after a ten yeers harsh confining hee dyes in <hi>France,</hi> hauing liu'd in his misery, longer then in his Duchy, and leauing instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to succeeding Princes that height should not be their ayme, but integrity; and that they would not (that I may vse the words of our Poet) tempt their starres beyond their light.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>