<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Authour.</title>
           <author>Hall, S.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103841_Fr1_10</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02629</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12757</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103841</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Authour.</title>
                 <author>Hall, S.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sicily and Naples, or, The fatall vnion : A tragoedy. By S.H. A.B è C. Ex</title>
                 <author>S. H. (Samuel Harding)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 64, 85-96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>To the Authour.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>THe <hi>Fatall</hi> sisters sure are <hi>muses</hi> growne,</l>
      <l>Else whence proceeds this <hi>Fatall Ʋnion?</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Or <hi>Muses Fatall</hi> sisters wee discry</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Those</hi> in thy <hi>Play, these</hi> in thy <hi>Tragedy:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>I'th front o'th booke, a <hi>troope</hi> all <hi>prest</hi> to be</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Guards</hi> to thy <hi>Naples,</hi> and faire <hi>Sicily,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>So many <hi>lines,</hi> and thou their <hi>center;</hi> Quils</l>
      <l>To <hi>impe</hi> thy <hi>winged Pegasus,</hi> and <hi>rills</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Paid to thy <hi>Hippocrene,</hi> a <hi>tribute</hi> show,</l>
      <l>Which we as subjects to thy <hi>crowne</hi> do owe,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Leaves</hi> to thy <hi>Laurell;</hi> not to decke thy head,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>
But strew the way, wherein thy <hi>buskins</hi> treade,</l>
      <l>As at thy <hi>Muses marriage;</hi> whom till now</l>
      <l>We thought confin'd by some o're-maiden vow</l>
      <l>To live encloystred; and for want of men</l>
      <l>Wooe images, and pictures; but thy <hi>pen</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Has made her now a <hi>Mother;</hi> see her <hi>laid</hi>
      </l>
      <l>In <hi>Geniall sheetes,</hi> where she's no more a <hi>Maid,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>But a <hi>chaste Prostitute;</hi> nay more I'le sweare</l>
      <l>She is, O— a <hi>female revisher:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>For which, as a <hi>crackt Vestall,</hi> some did strive</l>
      <l>With vaine attempts to <hi>bury</hi> her <hi>alive;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Things hid'in wide-sleeve gownes, all you can see</l>
      <l>Of Artists in them is, they'r come t' <hi>A.B.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Men that thy play, as some new lesson con,</l>
      <l>And <hi>hacke,</hi> and <hi>mangle</hi> thy blest <hi>Ʋnion;</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Poore fooles! I pitty thē; how would they looke,</l>
      <l>If at the barre BEN JOHNSON were their booke?</l>
      <l>His <hi>fox</hi> would on these <hi>geese</hi> revenge thee so,</l>
      <l>We should no hissing but i'th <hi>Common</hi> know;</l>
      <l>Nor neede they other halter, <hi>Catiline</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Affords them <hi>rope</hi> enough, in each <hi>strong line:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>But thou may'st pardon them, whose spight has made</l>
      <l>Thee famous, whilst, like the sad owle affraid</l>
      <l>Of wrens, thou hast unto thy <hi>Ivy</hi> fled,</l>
      <l>And where thou thought'st to <hi>hide,</hi> hast <hi>crown'd</hi> thy head:</l>
      <l>They now must stand, and gaze with us, which bee</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Alas too ignorant</hi> to <hi>censure</hi> thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>We know not whether we should <hi>wring</hi> our hands,</l>
      <l>Or <hi>clap</hi> them at thy poëm, which commands</l>
      <l>As much our <hi>griefe</hi> as <hi>pleasure,</hi> not an <hi>eye</hi>
      </l>
      <l>That <hi>reads,</hi> but <hi>acts</hi> in teares thy <hi>Tragedy:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Nay we are more then <hi>actours,</hi> thou may'st call</l>
      <l>Us <hi>mourners,</hi> and thy play a <hi>funerall:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Champions all steele, (which ne're shed drop but those</l>
      <l>Forc't from their veines, not by their friends, but foes,)</l>
      <l>At each sad <hi>accent,</hi> sweare they'r stabb'd i'th eye,</l>
      <l>Betray their babies there, and downe-right cry.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <l>But when we turne our eyes, and marke thy veine.</l>
      <l>Streight our too much of joy is all our paine,</l>
      <l>We stand enchanted, every <hi>word</hi> appeares</l>
      <l>A <hi>charme, lines circles, letters characters,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Which ravish us to phrensie: had wee seene</l>
      <l>It acted, sure <hi>thy</hi> Tragedy t'had bin;</l>
      <l>Our <hi>claps</hi> had <hi>thunderstrooke</hi> thee, thou would'st call</l>
      <l>This hand a <hi>club,</hi> that <hi>Brontes</hi> iron maule,</l>
      <l>T'other <hi>Pyrachmon's,</hi> the loud scene would be</l>
      <l>Their forge, (the <hi>Aetna</hi> of thy <hi>Sicily,</hi>)</l>
      <l>Thundering upwards: but thy <hi>Muse</hi> doth need</l>
      <l>No claps, or loud applause, (like swans which breed</l>
      <l>Onely in noyse) to give her issues birth,</l>
      <l>No <hi>Hums,</hi> nor <hi>Dam-me-boyes</hi> to set her forth:</l>
      <l>Scorning all glory that is not her owne,</l>
      <l>Nor needing a <hi>Blacke-Fryers</hi> shaven crowne,</l>
      <l>(As some,) to wispe her temples, though put forth</l>
      <l>So poore, that <hi>six-pence</hi> charge buyes all she's worth;</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>She'le out-blaze bright <hi>Aglaura's</hi> shining robe:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Her scene</hi> shall never change, the world's her <hi>Globe.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>S. HALL. <hi>A. M. C. Exon:</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>