<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Dedication]</title>
           <author>Gouge, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103284_Fr4_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01974</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12116</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103284</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Dedication]</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods three arrovves : plague, famine, svvord, in three treatises. I. A plaister for the plague. II. Dearths death. III. The Churches conquest over the sword. By William Gouge Doctor in Divinity, and preacher of Gods Word in Black-Friers, London</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Brewster (Bruster), Edward</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 128, 8, 129-176, 16, 177-436, 12 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="102"/>
   <pb facs="102"/>
   <opener>
      <salute>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, ROBERT, Lord RICH, <hi>Baron</hi> of <hi>LEEZ,</hi> and <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>WARWICK.</hi> AND, TO THE RIGHT Honourable, the Countesse of <hi>WARWICK,</hi> His most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Consort.</hi> All <hi>Honour</hi> that may make to their true <hi>Happinesse.</hi>
      </salute>
      <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Divine <hi>Providence</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all things are wisely ordered) hath by a most sacred, neare, firme, and inviolable band knit you <hi>two</hi> together, and made you <hi>one.</hi> Most meet it is therefore that the like honour be done, and the like respect testified to the one as to the other:
<pb facs="103"/>
especially where there is just cause of an answerable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect: as the Author of this Treatise here dedicated to your Honours, hath for the dedication thereof to you both. For,</p>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <salute>SIR,</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>THis <hi>Treatise</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of <hi>Warre.</hi> Your <hi>Lordship</hi> is knowne to be a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Warre.</hi> It setteth out <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shua,</hi> a <hi>Generall</hi> of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted spirit. Your spirit hath been proved to be such an one. It sheweth how <hi>Moses,</hi> when he tarried at home, was very sollicitous for his countrimen in the field. And is not such your care? Vpon mention made of <hi>Moses,</hi> there commeth to my mind this great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation (<hi>He is faithfull in all my house</hi>) given to him by God himself. <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> he was in his own obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of al Gods ordināces which belonged to him. Who of so eminēt a place, more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent then your Honour herin? <hi>Faithful</hi> he was also in deputing to the Lords
<pb facs="103"/>
            <hi>service men fit for their function. The abundance of able and faitDhfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> in <hi>Essex,</hi> and other places where the <hi>Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi> of <hi>Church-livings</hi> appertaineth to y<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Honour, is the seaie of your <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes</hi> in this respect. The greater is the glory of this kind of piety, because therin you do patrissare, tread in the steps of your worthy Father of blessed memory. What infant could not be copious in setting out the dignity of this piety, whereby God is so much honoured, his Church edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, many distressed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences comforted, and millions of soules saved. There is yet further a more particular bond of rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which bindeth me in person and paines to yeeld all homage unto y<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Honour, that is, the small inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance I hold within your Lordships <hi>Royalty at Hadly</hi> in <hi>Essex.</hi> Hereto I might adde the benefit of
<pb facs="104"/>
your <hi>Predecessours</hi> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity on the <hi>Free-Schoole</hi> at <hi>Felsted</hi> in <hi>Essex,</hi> where I was trained up three yeares together: and the continuall favours which from your youth you have shewed to me, your selfe as well as I being trained up at <hi>Eaton,</hi> and thence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
         </p>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
   <floatingText type="letter">
      <body>
         <opener>
            <pb facs="103"/>
            <salute>MADAM,</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>THere are in this <hi>Treatise</hi> many points concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Devotion:</hi> not unfit for a <hi>devout Lady:</hi> such an <hi>elect Lady</hi> as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated his Second <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle</hi> unto: a <hi>Lady</hi> whom <hi>all that knew the truth lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the truth,</hi> and <hi>for the truths sake:</hi> a <hi>Lady</hi> whose children <hi>walked in the truth:</hi> an evidence that the Lady who loved the truth her selfe, was carefull to communicate that to her beloved chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, which she had found to be sweet and comfortable to her own soule. And this for the <hi>Mothers</hi> honor doth the Apostle there mention. I that have long knowne your <hi>Honour</hi> (even from the child-hood of your
<pb facs="103"/>
now well grown daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, two worthy La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, as with your religious care in their good education, so with your owne pious course of life, wherin I make no question but that still you continue) could not omit so faire an opportunity of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifying that duty which I owe you. Hereby that which is made publique for the view of all, is in speciall dedicated to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that having a particular interest there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, you may be more diligent in perusing it. The principall points herein handled, which may best whet on your pious devotion, concerne <hi>Prayer,</hi> the <hi>Manner</hi> of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that Heavenly duty, the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Efficacy</hi> thereof, when it is made in <hi>faith,</hi> and
<pb facs="104"/>
the benefit of <hi>persevering</hi> therein, at least so long as just occasion giveth occasion of <hi>persisting</hi> without fainting. These and other like points are handled in this Treatise, which may be (as I suppose) use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to your devout mind.</p>
      </body>
   </floatingText>
   <p>By these and many other enducements hath he beene emboldened to tender this small evidence of much respect to your <hi>Honours,</hi> who, as he humbly craveth a gracious acceptance, so he faithfully promiseth to continue at the Throne of Grace</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours Sollicitour, WILLIAM GOVGE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>