<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR THOMAS LAKE, Knight, of CANONS, in Middlesex.</title>
           <author>Guy, Nicolas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1626</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103587_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02414</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12543</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103587</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR THOMAS LAKE, Knight, of CANONS, in Middlesex.</title>
                 <author>Guy, Nicolas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pieties pillar: or, A sermon preached at the funerall of mistresse Elizabeth Gouge, late wife of Mr. William Gouge, of Black-friers, London : With a true narration of her life and death. By Nicholas Guy, pastor of the church at Edge-ware in Middlesex</title>
                 <author>Guy, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Miller, George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1626</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 52 pages</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, SIR THOMAS LAKE, Knight, of CANONS, in Middlesex.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Parable of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the Gospel must bee my Apologie for the publication of this Sermon to the eye and censure of the world,<note place="margin">Luke <hi>11.</hi>
      </note> the which at the first when I preach't it, I thought not worthy your iudicious eares in my priuate Church: but being ouercome by the importunity of the reuerend Diuine, Master <hi>Gouge,</hi> I condescended (though sore against my will) to giue way to his desire: thus haue I made
<pb facs="3"/>
a Vertue of Necessity, and as it is in the Prouerbe, <hi>Vnica fidelia duos de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>albaut parietes:</hi> I haue both satisfied his pious desire for the preseruation of the memory of his vertuous and religious Wife: and also (hauing no better to present your Honor withal) I am bold to offer this, as the poore man brought water in his hands to <hi>Artaxerxes</hi>: only as a testimony of my willingnesse to returne something to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors hands, from whom I haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued so much (euen all the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance that now I haue) either imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from your Honour, or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately by your Honours procurement. It was my happinesse to be trained vp by that Illuminate Doctor, Prelate &amp; Pillar of our Church, your Brother, and the now most reuerend and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, <hi>Lord Bishop of Bath and Wells</hi>; and since to be sustained by your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. So that I may iustly say with the Psalmist,<note place="margin">Psal 27.10</note> When my Father and my Mother forsooke mee, the Lord
<pb facs="3"/>
tooke me vp, and committed mee to the charge of one Brother, of prime place in the Church, for my spirituall estate; and to your Honour, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Brother, of principall place in the common wealth for my tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. Now besides your Honours fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to me in particular; your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reall fauours and great affection to the Church and Churchmen, both when you were in publike place of Honourable imployment to our late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gracious Soueraigne, King <hi>Iames,</hi> of euer famous and happy memory; and also since your priuate retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, may iustly challenge the best of our Labours to be consecrated to so learned and noble a Patron of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Besides these former respects, your Honour hath yet another inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest in these my weake endeuours: because you went chiefe amongst ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthy and worshipfull Auditors, which honoured the Funerall with your presence. In all these respects, I
<pb facs="4"/>
hope your Honour will fauourably be pleased to accept that of mee, which Almighty God doth of vs all, a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling heart and desire. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells vs,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12.</note> in his second Epistle to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, that God accepts vs accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which wee haue, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which wee haue not. If in this your Honour pardon my ouer-great presumption, you shall more and more make me</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Obliged in all the bonds of respect and seruice to your Honour, <hi>Nicolas Guy.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>