<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honorable especiall good Lord, Sir CHRISTOPHER HATTON Knight, Lordhigh Chancelor of England.</title>
           <author>Harvey, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103904_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02779</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12908</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103904</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honorable especiall good Lord, Sir CHRISTOPHER HATTON Knight, Lordhigh Chancelor of England.</title>
                 <author>Harvey, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discoursiue probleme concerning prophesies : how far they are to be valued, or credited, according to the surest rules, and directions in diuinitie, philosophie, astrologie, and other learning: deuised especially in abatement of the terrible threatenings, and menaces, peremptorily denounced against the kingdoms, and states of the world, this present famous yeere, 1588, supposed the greatwoonderfull, and fatall yeere of our age. By I.H. physition</title>
                 <author>Harvey, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jackson, John 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Watkins, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 128, 127-133, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honorable especiall good Lord, Sir CHRISTOPHER HATTON Knight, <hi>Lordhigh Chancelor of England.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable very good Lord, there is scarsly any forwarde Graduate, or student in either Vniuersitie; or any reasonable fauorer and welwiller of learning, either in citie or countrie, far or neare, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out England; that hath not often heard sufficient report, togither with many Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable commendations as well of your good Lordships especiall regard, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall recourse to all kinds of liberall, and fruitfull learning; as also of your bountifull, and in truth magnificent fauor to all sorts of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, any way well reputed in their seuerall faculties, and profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions. The very actual euent it selfe, and so many right woorthy, and notable effects of wise and well aduised proceeding, not a yeere, or two, but euen these many yeers togither from time to time continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, still and still importing so prosperous, and happy successe; declare abundantly vnto the world, that the very originall grounds, &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall foundations of so exceeding worshipfull, and honorable build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, were, and are, as soundly and substantially laied on your behalf, as either any good learning could aduise at first, or any good wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome might deuise at last. So that partly your yoonger studies at Common-law, and arts of humanitie: partly your riper studies of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil-law, the Mathematiques, Ethiques, Politiques, histories aswell forrein, as domestical, and other most notable both general &amp; special instructions, of priuate, and publique gouernment: partly your elder and final studies about Courtly affaires, matters of State, the actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all seruice of your Prince, &amp; Countrey (wherin continually appeered sundry visible, and infallible proofes of your Honorable industry, and wisdome) haue finally bred that absolute perfect experience, &amp; that deepe sound iudgement in your Lordship for all matters and occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of whatsoeuer weight, or importance; that becommeth so great a Lord of the state, so high an Officer of the Realme, so deere a Counseller of hir most excellent Maiestie, and so mightie a Iudge or Praetor of this whole kingdome, and common-wealth, as now at last, thorough the gratious especial fauor of God, and Prince, you are
<pb facs="3"/>
woorthily prooued: euen as woorthily by the common voice of the people, and vniuersall assent and consent of all degrees (which some haue termed Gods owne verdict; some the very suffrage of nature; some the definitiue sentence of vertue hix selfe) as any your praede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, aduanced to the same dignitie in our memory; notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any their especial desert, or appropriate meetnes for that place and preeminence. Insomuch, that the whole realme vniuersally; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry estate particularly; and in maner euery person singularly, doth congratulate this your late so very high praeferment, and authoritie, as most woorthily conferred vpon a most woorthy person: whose ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued Honorable wisdome, and assured manifold sufficiency, euen for the weilding and ordring of greatest matters, hath long sithence so euidently &amp; fully appeered to euery cleere cie, not wilfully bleared or dimmed, that generally euery one, but specially the wiser, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeter sort deemeth your L. at all points correspondently prepared, and furnished for the best discharging and perfectest accomplishing of so weightie a function, (aswell in the Queenes most gratious and high Court of Chancerie, as otherwise, wheresoeuer, or howsoeuer the laudable administration, and execution of that most Honorable office, is required,) with vniuersall good credite, publique reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, generall applause, and as it were euen a common Recognizance, or praesentment of al intier reuerence, and true honor, wherunto God hath specially framed, &amp; inhabled your Lordship. Mine owne poore selfe, as one of the last, and least, albeit depending vpon respects, and remaining a good space in doubt, thorough due consideration of my vnwoorthines, and insufficiencie, (which regard hitherto withdrew me, from praesenting either my selfe, or any my simple doing to the view of so honorablie wise, and graue a person:) neuertheles at length resolued, not to ouerslip that small opportunitie of particular cōgratulation, which heretofore with good succes I had used, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of conuenient occasion cōpetently ministred therunto, euen with your Honorable predecessor, my very especial singlar good L. whilest he liued. I haue already mentioned your bounteous long approoued fauor toward learning, and the professors therof; neither can I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get in generall so assured an argument, &amp; praegnant testimony, as so many famous Dedications, Inscriptions, Praefaces, Titles, Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; Letters missiue, extant in your Right Worshipfull, and Right Honorable most renowned name, do continually suggest &amp; affoord:
<pb facs="3"/>
neither am I ignorant in special, what inward, and outward affection your Honor hath carried aswell to the Mathematiques, as to other the wisest, and auaileablest Ciuill faculties: wherof no man hath ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gathered more worshipfull flowers, or reaped more Honorable fruits, than your considerate wisedome, euermore accompanied with sound, and effectuall iudgement: and finally, I could name euen par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular men, that haue been fauorably entertained and accepted of your noble Honor, in the foresaid respects, and therfore remaine ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deepely, and affectionately bounden vnto your good Lordship: amongst whom namely my eldest brother hath long sithence recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himself, and will ouer acoordingly make the same most dutifull reckoning. These, and such like arguments of incouragement, haue now after some deliberation, so forcibly praeuailed with me, and so effectually imboldened me, that by meanes therof, I haue aduisedly praesumed aboue my simple qualitie, to offer vnto your woorthy L. by way of humble, &amp; officious Dedication, my Annuall Kalender, or briefe Almanacke, for the famous praedestined yeere following; togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Astronomicall Diarie, the compendious discourse vpon the Eclipses, and the short Astrologicall Prognostication, thereunto appending. A slender Pamphlet, and trifle in effect: yet such, as first, (not fully fiue yeeres expired) M. Iustice Meade, my verie especiall good Countryman, and right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deere friend; then (vpon the credit of his curteous recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation) the late Lord Chancelor, your antecessor, my Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable singular good Lord (the woorthy memory of both which, I am alwaies accordingly to reuerence and honor) vouchsafed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in as fauorable maner of allowance, and defence, as my selfe in reason could wish, or in affection should desire. May it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise please your excellent Lordship, Right Honorable Sir, of your accustomed Noble goodnes, to deigne me like fauor, in accepting this Schollerly exercise, of long practised and still allowed vse; as I am respectiuely to esteeme of your Lordship, as of a greater, &amp; more conspicuous person, than the better of them, (be it vttered without any note of praeiudice, or derogation to the better of them, either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly:) so I shal account my selfe more streighly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and more extraordinarily bounden in al possible duties and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices vnto your magnificent good L. than euer I was vnto either of them: to whom notwithstanding I must needes in good reason; and
<pb facs="4"/>
ought alwaies in good dutie; &amp; wil gladly in good affection, reknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my selfe very deepely, and intirely beholding. I dare not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, nor cannot challenge any great speciall, or extraordinary skill, either Theoricall, or Practicall, either in the Mathematiques, or otherwise, in any profound science, either Contemplatiue, or Actiue: but whatsoeuer my smal habilitie is, either in matter of learning, or any other seruiceable way; or howsoeuer it may haply prooue tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the gratious fauor of God, &amp; mine own studious diligence; it is, and shal alwaies be ready in most dutiful, &amp; carefull maner, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend your most Honorable pleasure: so far as it may like, or content the same, by way of probation or otherwise, to vouchsafe me any por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the fauor, as to command any my studie, industrie, trauell, or seruice, euen to the vttermost extent of my whole possibility anyway whatsoeuer. Which I must not stand to inlarge, or amplifie at this praesent, but am to refer, &amp; (may I respectiuely be so bold, vnder cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and vpon humble petition) to recommend the entire proofe and triall of any such seruiceable dutie, to the onely consideration, and appointment of your deepe wisedome: fearing least I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie praesumed ouermuch, in troubling your L. ouerfar, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly crauing pardon for interrupting your other most serious and weightie affaires; I beseech God, long continue your good Lordship in perfect health, and stedfast honor, to the assured and inestimable vse, both of hir soueraigne Maiestie particularly, and vniuersally of the whole Realme: which neuer more, than at this instant, needed the carefull, prouident, circumspect, and intierly sound assistance of such wise trustie Counsellors, and Nobles, as hir gratious Highnes, and this peaceable gouernment haue effectually found your woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Lordship; vnto whom not onely I, but infinite other of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and estates, most hartily, and vnfainedly wish all felicitie. At Kingslynn in Norfolke: This xx. of August. 1587.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your good Lordships most <hi>dutifull, and affectionate:</hi>
IOHN HARVEY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>