<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO EVERY ONE THAT SEEKETH AFTER the truth in sinceity: Salutations.</title>
           <author>Smyth, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103006_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12557</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22877</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103006</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO EVERY ONE THAT SEEKETH AFTER the truth in sinceity: Salutations.</title>
                 <author>Smyth, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Paralleles, censures, observations : Aperteyning: to three several writinges, 1. A lettre written to Mr. Ric. Bernard, by Iohn Smyth. 2. A book intituled, the Seperatists schisme published by Mr. Bernard. 3. An answer made to that book called the Sep. Schisme by Mr. H. Ainsworth. Whereunto also are adioyned. 1. The said lettre written to Mr. Ric. Bernard divided into 19. sections. 2. Another lettre written to Mr. A.S. 3. A third letter written to certayne bretheren of the seperation. By Iohn Smyth</title>
                 <author>Smyth, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 2-136, that is 137, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO EVERY ONE THAT SEEKETH AFTER the truth in since<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ity: Salutations.</head>
   <p>NOt every thing, Gentle Reader, which a man writeth privately &amp; sodaynly to his frend is fit to be published openly to the view of the world: neyther did I think that this lettre written to Mr. Bernard in private vppon three dayes meditation should have been made publique in print to every mans eye &amp; censure: which had I thought should have come to passe, I would with better advyse &amp; le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sure &amp; so with more mature judgment have conceaved &amp; penned it. But seing it is justly occasioned through Mr. Bernards importunity in his late published book intituled the Seperatists Schisme, &amp; his slaunderous misconstructions &amp; misreports vp &amp; downe the country be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind my back, that this lettre of myne is strongly suspected of error, bitternes, rashnes, vncharitablenes, &amp; imputations of thē like nature: &amp; by reason thereof my se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> falleth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the hard &amp; vnknowne, &amp; happily vndeserved censure of many well affected to the truth: whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eat I cannot but be much wounded, both in myne owne soule inwardly, &amp; in my good name outwardly, which is alwayes better &amp; mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e to be esteemed then a good oyntment: I thought it much more tolerable to adventure my self, by exposing this vntymely byrth, I meane this sodaynly conceaved &amp; penned lettre, to the variable cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of the multitude: thē by burying it in darknes &amp; silence, like vnto one stil borne to superinduce a strong presumption of iustly imputed blame vppon my self by reason of this present lettre: Therefore I doe earnestly intreat every one frend, or other, into whose handes this present writing may come, to esteeme it, as it is indeed, even a sodayne private lettre of one frēd vnto another: &amp; not to respect it as it now falleth out to be a publique wriring proclaymed as it were vppon the house top: I cannot nor may not with fidelity alter one sentence or word of it, but as Mr. Bernard hath it copyed in his hands, so have I published it word for word without any the least chandg to my knowledg, least Mr. Ber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nard should say it is not the lettre he had from mee &amp; that his slaunderous collections &amp; aspersions cast vppon mee in respect of the lettre may be perceaved by them that read this lettre, &amp; compare it with his book, notes, &amp; speeches: And seing necessity enforceth the identity of this lettre without correction eyther of matter or wordes, I beseech the Gentle Reader frendly &amp; favorably to construe all things, &amp; interpret them in the better p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rt▪ promising that if any eyther error in matter: or tartnes of speech be manifested vnto mee as my sinne, I shal willingly confesse &amp; repent it before the world.</p>
   <p>And so vppon hope of a favorable construction I desire to advertise further that Mr. Bernard had in his hands this lettre of myne six or seven monthes before he published this his book intituled the Seperatists Schisme▪ which book as may be perceaved by this letter, compared therwith, is principally directed in opposition &amp; reprehension thereof: but how litle cause Mr. Bernard had so to doe, may now appeare. For he should have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered before he had opposed: but that which he doth oppose is indeed answered alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the lettre by prevention &amp; anticipatiō that I shal not need to make answere a fresh to Mr. Bernard, he being now twise answered, once before his book was published, &amp; now againe since by Mr. Henry Ainsworth: Only I desire the reader to be advertised that ther are some particulars wherein Mr. Ainsworth hath lest mee &amp; the truth in the open playne field to shift for our selves: In regard whereof, as also bicause of Mr. Bernards mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aledging &amp; misconstruing divers parts of my letter written vnto him, I have thought
<pb facs="3"/>meet, not barely to publish this lettre, but parallele-wise to compare Mr. Bernards book▪ Mr. Ainsworths answer, &amp; this my lettre together, as also to annexe a few animadversiō<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> &amp; observations aperteyning therevnto, that by this meanes the agrement &amp; difference being discovered, the truth may appeare where it is.</p>
   <p>Now although it be a greevous thing vnto me to raise vp adversaries against me with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out cause, especially brethren of true Churches: yet seeing I am necessarely interessed to defend the truth manifested in myne owne writings, which I cannot possibly doe but by way of opposition, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>for it commeth to passe that will I, will I, I must needes answer the opponent, left I betray the truth which by due order I am particularly called &amp; singled out to defend. Wherfor for more evidence sake I have caused this lettre written to Mr. Bern. to be divided into 19. Sections, &amp; in every Section wher need required, I have made parallels, animadversions, &amp; observations for severall purposes as the reader shal perceave in perusing thē: Finally vppon perswasion of frends▪ &amp; for further cleering of the truth I have annexed two other lettres, the one written to Mr. A.S. a Minister of the Church of England conteyning certayne principall &amp; mayne groundes of our cause which I desire may diligently be considered of every one that is willing to see the truth: the other writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten to ce tayne brethren of the Seperation for the confirming &amp; establishing of them in the truth, against the assaults of Sathan transforming himself into an aungel of light ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the better to deceave the simple: &amp; howsoever it be needlesse to publish any thing further for the cleering of the truth of our cause out of those mysts &amp; foggs which sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>til disputers &amp; pleaders for cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uption have like jannes &amp; jambres those Egiptian jugle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s cast before mens eyes, that they cannot readely discerne a true serpent from a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>alfe: yet bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause new adversaries arise dayly with new shifts &amp; cavils therfor it is not amisse to dis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cover their forgeries also that at the length it may evidently appeare that the truth hath devoured error as Moses Serpent did the Enchanters: So desiring every one that loveth the Lord &amp; the truth especia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly Mr. Ainsworth &amp; Mr. Bernard to judg wisely of my cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, &amp; not to take any thing in the evil part which is a strong fruite of the flesh, I cease, wishing the truth may be honoured though men be shamed, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN SMYTH.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>