<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Worshipfull my very worthy friends, Mr Nathanael Henshaw of Valence in Essex, Mr Benjamin Henshaw of Cheap-side in London, and Mr Thomas Henshaw of Saffron-Walden in Essex.</title>
           <author>Winterton, Ralph</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103073_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01645</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11778</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103073</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Worshipfull my very worthy friends, Mr Nathanael Henshaw of Valence in Essex, Mr Benjamin Henshaw of Cheap-side in London, and Mr Thomas Henshaw of Saffron-Walden in Essex.</title>
                 <author>Winterton, Ralph</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gerards meditations : written originally in the Latine tongue by Iohn Gerard Doctour in Divinitie, and superintendant of Heidelberg. Translated and revised by Ralph Winterton fellow of Kings Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Gerhard, Johann</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 <publisher>Buck, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Daniel, Roger</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 323, 13, 155, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>To the Worshipfull my very worthy friends, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Nathanael Henshaw</hi> of Valence in Essex, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Benjamin Henshaw</hi> of Cheap-side in London, and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Thomas Henshaw</hi> of Saffron-Walden in Essex.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is reported by <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> that <hi>Licinius</hi> grew so stupid, that if he had not been put in minde by others, he had forgot himself to be a Prince. If I should forget the <hi>HENSHAVVES,</hi> I should for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get my self to be a man: For an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull man is no man, but an enemie to God and man: so the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians</hi> were wont to call him. Where bounty hath an hand to give, thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse should have an hand to write <hi>received.</hi> I have formerly record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with mine own hand your names in the catalogue of my benefactours:
<pb facs="8"/>
And that hand should deserve to be cut off, if it should now expunge them. The old copie may decay: I thought good therefore now to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new it. <hi>Gerards Meditations</hi> had never seen <hi>English light</hi> for me, if yours and others bountie had not set my head on work to finde out some occasion to give publick testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of my thankfulnesse: If <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard</hi> had not been, I might still have been to seek for an occasion. As often therefore as <hi>Gerard</hi> and I live together, at every impression you may challenge at my hands a new expression of my service. This debt I shall be alwayes readie to pay, but not as men pay money: for that being once paid can be required no more: But this I shall be alwayes paying, and still remain your debter.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Ità testor R. WINTERTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>