<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶An exhor∣tation to the stu∣dy of holy scripture.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1561</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103820_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02613</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12742</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103820</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶An exhor∣tation to the stu∣dy of holy scripture.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ensamples of vertue and vice, gathered oute of holye scripture. By Nicolas Hanape patriarch of Ierusalem. Very necessarye for all christen men and women to loke vpon. And Englyshed by Thomas Paynell</title>
                 <author>Hannapes, Nicolas de, patriarch of Jerusalem</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Tisdale (Tysdale), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1561</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>808 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>¶An exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of holy scripture.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou shalt shewe thy sonne in that daye, saying.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deute.</hi> 12.</note> Thys is that which our Lord did vnto me, when I came oute of Egipt. And it shall be as a signe vnto thee vpon thine hād, and for a remēbraunce before thine eyes, that our Lordes law may be alwayes in thy mouthe. For in a strong hand our lord brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght thee out of Egipt.</p>
   <p>Ye shall not do that, that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth good in your owne eyes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deute.</hi> 13.</note> but that I commaund you, that do you only vnto our lorde, nor thou shalt put nought thereto, nor take ought there from.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>Thou shalt read thys<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> lawe before al Israell in their eares.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Deute.</hi> 31</note> Gather the people together, men, women, and chyldren, and the stranger that is within thy gates, that they may heare and learne, and fear our Lord your God. And kepe and obserue all the wordes of thys law.</p>
   <p>Let not the boke of this law depart oute of thy mouthe, but record therin day and nyghte, that thou maist obserue and do according to al that is wrytten therin, for then thou shalt make thy waye prosperous, and then shalte thou doe wiselye.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iosu.</hi> 1.</note> Thou shalt not decline from the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of thys law neyther to the ryght hand, nor to the left, that thou maist do al thinge wiselye that thou takest in hand.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>All the wordes of God are pure and clean, for he is a shield vnto all them,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Prouer.</hi> 30.</note> that putte theyr trust in him. Put thou nothyng vnto hys wordes, leaste he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue thee, and thou be found a lier.</p>
   <p>Crye nowe as loud as thou canste, leaue not of, lyfte vp thy voyce lyke a trompet, and shew my people theyr offences,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esay.</hi> 58</note> and the house of Iacob their sinnes.</p>
   <p>Wo be vnto those folish pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that followe theyr owne spirite,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ezech.</hi> 13</note> and speake where they se nothing.</p>
   <p>Searche the scriptures,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.</note> for they are they, whych testifye of me.</p>
   <p>What so euer thynges are wrytten,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.</note> they are wrytten for our learning, that we thorowe
<pb facs="7"/>
pacyente and comforte of the scriptures, might haue hope.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 4.</note>Al scripture geuen by inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God, is profytable to teache, to improue, to amende, and to instruct in rightwisenes that the man of God maye be perfecte and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto al good workes.</p>
   <figure>
</figure>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>