<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREMONITION of the Title and Vse of Characters.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103620_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68130</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12648</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103620</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREMONITION of the Title and Vse of Characters.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Characters of vertues and vices : in two bookes: by Ios. Hall</title>
                 <author>Hall, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bradwood, Melchisidec</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <distributor>Edgar, Eleazar</distributor>
                            <distributor>Macham, Samuel 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 176 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A PREMONITION of the Title and Vse of Characters.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>READER,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Diuines of the olde Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens were their Morall Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers: These receiued the <hi>Acts</hi> of an inbred law, in
<pb facs="4"/>
the <hi>Sinai</hi> of Nature, and deliuered them with manie expositions to the multitude: These were the Ouerseers of maners, Correctors of vices, Directors of liues, Doctors of vertue, which yet taught their people the body of their naturall Diuinitie, not after one maner; while some spent themselues in deepe discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of humane felicitie and the way to it in common; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thought best to applie the generall precepts of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse or decencie, to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb facs="4"/>
conditions and persons: A third sort in a mean course betwixt the two other, and compounded of them both, bestowed their time in draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the true lineaments of euery vertue and vice, so liuely, that who saw the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals, might know the face: which Art they significantly termed <hi>Charactery.</hi> Their papers were so many tables, their writings so many spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king pictures, or liuing ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whereby the ruder mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude might euen by their
<pb facs="5"/>
sense learne to know vertue, and discerne what to detest. I am deceiued if any course could be more likely to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile; for heerein the grosse conceit is led on with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and informed while it feeles nothing but delight: And if pictures haue beene accounted the books of idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, beholde heere the benefit of an image without the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. It is no shame for vs to learne wit of Heathens, neither is it materiall, in whose Schoole we take out a
<pb facs="5"/>
good lesson: yea, it is more shame not to follow their good, than not to leade them better. As one therefore that in worthy examples hold imitation better than inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I have trod in their paths, but with an higher &amp; wider step; and out of their <hi>Tablets</hi> haue drawen these larger portraitures of both sorts. More might be sayd, I denie not of euery vertue, of euery vice: I desired not to say all, but enough. If thou do but read or like these, I
<pb facs="6"/>
haue spent good houres ill; but if thou shalt hence ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure those vices, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou thoughtest not ill-fauoured, or fall in loue with any of these goodly faces of vertue; or shalt hence finde where thou hast anie little touch of these euils, to cleere thy selfe, or where any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in these graces to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it, neither of vs shall need to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of our labor.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>