<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HIGH AND Mightie Prince, Henry, by the grace of God, Prince of VVales, Duke of Cornewall, Earle of Chester, and Heire apparant of the Crowne and Diademe of this kingdome of great Brittaine, France, and Ireland.</title>
           <author>Scot, Patrick</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103610_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05280</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15424</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103610</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HIGH AND Mightie Prince, Henry, by the grace of God, Prince of VVales, Duke of Cornewall, Earle of Chester, and Heire apparant of the Crowne and Diademe of this kingdome of great Brittaine, France, and Ireland.</title>
                 <author>Scot, Patrick</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first step, towards heaven or, Anna the prophetesse : her holy haunt, to the temple of God. Preached at Standish Church in the Countie of Lancaster. By VVilliam Leigh, Batchillor of Diuinity, and pastor there. With the second edition of great Brittaines deliuerance, newly corrected, and enlarged by the author</title>
                 <author>Leigh, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Johnson (Jonson), Arthur.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 191, 208-249, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb n="154" facs="84"/>
   <pb n="155" facs="84"/>
   <head>TO THE HIGH AND Mightie Prince, <hi>Henry,</hi> by the grace of God, Prince of VVales, Duke of Cornewall, Earle of Chester, and Heire apparant of the Crowne and Diademe of this kingdome of great Brittaine, France, and Ireland.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ardon me (my gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious good Lord, &amp; deare Prince) if out of a loyall heart I present vnto your Princelie viewe, what I conceiued vpon these late in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Treasons, in solace of my soule, after the Lord had made the land so glorious by deliuerance: I say, <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance</hi> out of the hands of cruell e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, who strook at our fairest tree, to haue cut it downe, both roote, bole, and branches, if the Lord had not beene propitious. And because your
<pb n="156" facs="85"/>
excellency is the highest straine in all expectance, and the Heire apparant to that crowne and dignitie, whose vndoubted right, they haue so wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by sinister thought, word, and worke, as in former ages the like was neuer deuised in any Nation, nor (by the grace of God) euer shall: I haue made bold in these fewe leaues, and lines, to lay open the danger, with the deliuerance; and the rather to your Highnesse: for that in feeling sort, you may iustly say, <hi>Quorum pars magna fui</hi>; I haue had my part of both: for man hath endangered me, but God hath deliuered mee. If in the deliuerie and proiect of this my speech, your highnesse shall finde lesse <hi>Method</hi> then <hi>Matter,</hi> I hope your clemency will beare with my passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate heart, more affected to grieue for them who deuised the mischiefe, and to ioy for our selues that missed it, then I can well expresse, without a
<pb n="157" facs="85"/>
troubled stile. One saith wel, <hi>Vt luctus sic laetitiae loquūtur leues, ingentes stupent:</hi> As are our sorrowes, so is our solace: in their Mediocrities they speake, but in their extremities they are silent, and say nothing. What maruell then, if this our rauishment of so great ioy for the deliuery, and deepe griefe of horror because of the danger, either enioyne mee si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or if I speake, make me to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my thoughts with such passion as little passeth of the Method, so it meete with matter, to expresse the meaning of a melting heart? <hi>Nescit ordinem amor,</hi> Loue is lawlesse: and a loue thus boyling, how can it but shed ouer, and keepe no current, other then in your Royal acceptance, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer seasoned with such heauenly suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance, as is gracious both to GOD and man. <hi>Digna prorsus &amp; rara virtus humilitas honorata;</hi> It is a rare vertue when humility is honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="158" facs="86"/>
and honour is humbled: the blaze whereof I saw in your Princely coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, when at your Highnesse Court at Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> it pleased your excellency to licke vp the dust of the Sanctuarie there, (vpon the Lords day:) and after the Sermon ended, to yeeld such grace in publike to the Preacher, as that he might kisse your Princely hand: which euer sithence hath strucke so great an impression of exceeding loue, and loyaltie in my poore heart, as by the grace of God, I shal neuer leaue to pray for your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, as I am most bounden: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so by all meanes studie, how either my loue or life may expresse the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and duty I owe for so gracious an aspect. Gold and siluer I haue none: such as I haue, I giue: In the name of Iesus Christ of Nazareth, be you esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished. Yet if it please your good grace to receiue this simple New-yeares gift, with the least acceptance,
<pb n="159" facs="86"/>
and as the first fruit of my labours in your Highnesse seruice: It may be, I shall with <hi>Ianus,</hi> looke backward to the olde yeare, and out of my small store, offer a pearle of an higher price. Till when, and euer, I pray God safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to keepe your Royall person, to his glory, your owne comfort, and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glands</hi> ioy.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Graces Chaplaine, most humble at command.</hi> W. Leigh.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>