<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, his especiall deare frend, M. Gabriell Haruey, Doctour of Lawe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103899_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02775</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12903</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103899</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, his especiall deare frend, M. Gabriell Haruey, Doctour of Lawe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pierces supererogation or A new prayse of the old asse : A preparatiue to certaine larger discourses, intituled Nashes s. fame. Gabriell Haruey</title>
                 <author>Harvey, Gabriel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 199, 100-120, 14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL,</hi> his especiall deare frend, M. Gabriell Haruey, Doctour of Lawe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Weet M. Doctour Haruey, (for I cannot intitule youwith an Epithite of lesse va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, then that, which the Grecian, and Roman Oratours ascribed to Theophra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus, in respect of so many your excellent labours, garnished with the garland of matchlesse Oratory): if at any time either the most earnest persuasion of a deare frend, and vnusually most deare, and constant, adiured thereunto by the singular vertue of your most prayse-worthy, and vnmatchable wit: or the woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull admiration of your peerlesse conceit, embraued with so many gorgeous ornamentes of diuine Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique: or the doubtlesse successiue benefit thereof, deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the glory of our English Eloquence, and our vulgar Tuscanisme (if I may so terme it); may worke any plausi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or respectiue motions with you, to bewtifie, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich our age, with those most praise-moouing workes, full of gallantest discourse, and reason, which I vnderstand by some assured intelligence be now glowing vpon the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile, ready to receiue the right artificiall forme of diuinist workemāship: thē let I beseech you, nay by all our mutuall frendships I coniure you, (loue, and admiration of them, arming me with the placarde of farther confidence) those, and other your incomparable writings, speedily, or rather
<pb facs="6"/>
presently shew thēselues in the shining light of the Sunne. That by this Publication of so rare, &amp; rich Discourses, our English Rauens, the spitefull enemyes to all birdes of more bewtifull wing, and more harmonious note, then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, may shrowde themselues in their nests of basest ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scurity, &amp; keepe hospitality with battes, and owles, fit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorts for such vile carions. Good Sir, arise, and confound those Viperous Cryticall monsters, and those prophane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of our Commonwealth; which endeuour with their mutinous, and Serpentine hissing, like geese, not to arme the Senatours, and Oratours of Rome, but to daunt, astonish, and if it were possible, to ouerthrow them. And sithence the very thunder-lightning of your admirable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, is sufficiētly auailable to strike them with a lame Palsie of tongue, (if they be not already smitten with a sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celesse Apoplexy in head, which may easely ensewe such contagious Catharres, and Reumes, as I am priuy some of them haue bene grieuously disseased withall) misse not, but hitt them suerly home, as they deserue with Superero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. You haue bene reputed euermore, since first I heard of you in Oxford, and elsewhere, to haue bene as much giuen to fauour, commende, and frequent such, as were approoued, or toward in learning, witt, kinde behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, or any good quality, as may be required in any man of your demerit: an vndoubted signe, how much you loath Inuectiues, or any need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>les contētions. I would, (as many your affectionate frēds would) it had bene your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to haue encountred some other Paranymphes, then such, as you are now to discipline: most vnwillingly, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, but most necessarily, &amp; not without especiall consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, being so manifestly vrged, and grosely prouoked to defend yourselfe. But you haue ere now bene acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="7"/>
with patience perforce: and I hope the most desperate swasher of them will one day learne to shew himself hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, or wiser. And thus recommending your sweet ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, with your grauer studies, to the highest treasury of heauenly Muses; I right hartely take my leaue with a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of that Muse, that honoreth the Vrany of du Bartas, and yourselfe: of du Bartas elsewhere; here of him, whose excellent Pages of the French King, the Scottish King, the braue Monsieur de la Nöe, the aforesayd Lord du Bartas, Sir Philip Sidney, and sundry other worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages, deserue immortall commendation. I thanke him very hartely, that imparted vnto me those fewe sheetes: and if all be like them, truly all is passing notable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nd right singular.</p>
   <div type="sonnet">
      <head>Sonet.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>THose learned <hi>Oratours,</hi> Roomes auncient sages,</l>
         <l>Persuasions Pith, directours of affection,</l>
         <l>The mindes chiefe counsail, rhetoriques perfection,</l>
         <l>The pleasaunt baulmes of peace, warres fierce outrages:</l>
         <l>Sweet Grecian <hi>Prophets,</hi> whose smooth Muse assuages</l>
         <l>The Furies powerfull wrath, poisons infection:</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Philosophers</hi> (by Causes due connexion,</l>
         <l>Match't with th'Effects of Nature) future ages</l>
         <l>Embrauing with rich documents of Art:</l>
         <l>
            <pb facs="7"/>
The wisest <hi>States-men</hi> of calme Commonweales:</l>
         <l>The learned <hi>Generall Councels,</hi> which impart</l>
         <l>Diuinest Lawes, whose wholesome Physique heales</l>
         <l>Both Church, and Layety: <hi>All</hi> in <hi>One</hi> beholde</l>
         <l>Ennobled Arts, as Precious stones in golde.</l>
      </lg>
      <p>From my lodging in Holborne: this of Iune. 1593.</p>
      <p>Your most affectionate,</p>
      <p>Barnabe Barnes.</p>
      <p>Hauing perused my former Sonet, if it may please you Sir, to do asmuch for your deare frends, <hi>Parthenophil,</hi> and <hi>Parthenophe,</hi> they shall haue the desired fruite of their short exercise, and will rest beholding to your curteous accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: which they would be glad to reacquite in the loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingest manner they may. And so most affectionatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend themselues vnto your good selfe: whose vnble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mished fame they will euermore maintaine with the best bloud of their hartes, tongues, and Pennes. We will not fay, how much we long to see the whole Prayses of your two notorious enemyes, the <hi>Asse,</hi> and the <hi>Foxe.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="sonnet">
      <head>Sonet.</head>
      <lg>
         <head>
            <hi>Nash,</hi> or the Confuting Gentleman.</head>
         <l>The Muses scorne; the Courtiers laughing-stock;</l>
         <l>The Countreys Coxecombe; Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
               <desc>•…</desc>
            </gap>nters proper new;</l>
         <l>The Citties Leprosie; the Pandars stew;</l>
         <l>Vertues disdayne; honesties aduerse rock;</l>
         <l>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> vile champion; slaunders stumbling block.</l>
         <l>
            <pb facs="8"/>
Graund Oratour of Cunny-catchers crew;</l>
         <l>Base hroaching tapster of reports vntrue;</l>
         <l>Our moderne Viper, and our Countryes mock;</l>
         <l>True Valors Cancer-worme, sweet Learnings rust.</l>
         <l>Where shall I finde meete colours, and fit wordes,</l>
         <l>For such a counterfaict, and worthlesse matter?</l>
         <l>Him, whom thou raylest on at thine owne lust,</l>
         <l>Sith <hi>Bodine,</hi> and sweet <hi>Sidney</hi> did not flatter,</l>
         <l>His Inuectiue thee toomuch grace affordes.</l>
      </lg>
      <p>Parthenophil.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="sonnet">
      <head>Sonet.</head>
      <lg>
         <head>
            <hi>Haruey,</hi> or the sweet Doctour.</head>
         <l>
            <hi>Sidney,</hi> sweet Cignet, pride of Thamesis;</l>
         <l>Apollos laurel; Mars-his proud prowesse:</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Bodine,</hi> register of Realmes happinesse,</l>
         <l>Which Italyes, and Fraunce's wonder is:</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Hatcher,</hi> with silence whom I may not misse:</l>
         <l>Nor <hi>Lewen,</hi> Rhetoriques richest noblesse:</l>
         <l>Nor <hi>Wilson,</hi> whose discretion did redresse</l>
         <l>Our English Barbarisme: adioyne to this</l>
         <l>Diuinest morall <hi>Spencer:</hi> let these speake</l>
         <l>By their sweet Letters, which do best vnfould</l>
         <l>
            <hi>Harueys</hi> deserued prayse: since my Muse weake</l>
         <l>Cannot relate somuch as hath bene tould</l>
         <l>By these <hi>Forenam'd:</hi> then vaine it were to bring</l>
         <l>New feather to his Fames swift-feathered wing.</l>
      </lg>
      <p>Parthenophe.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>