<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reverend Brethren in Scotlande.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103148_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01780</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11915</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103148</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reverend Brethren in Scotlande.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe and plaine narration of proceedings at an assemsemblie [sic] in Glasco, 8. Iun. 1610. anent the innovation of the Kirk-governement : With a narration of some straunge episcopall accidents lately happened in Scotland, worthie co [n] sideration: which the wise of heart will vnderstand</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the reverend Brethren in Scotlande.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Otwithstāding I can not (as I often desired) see with my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eyes, by what meanes &amp; degrees the state of Christ his Church (there) is become so straungelie defaced, that so I might with more feeling pray, and with more iudgmēt helpe, as <hi>I</hi> could: yet have I never cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> carefully to hearkē after, &amp; diligently to inquire concerning Ierusalem. So that (of late) by sundrie intelligences, I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that the <hi>Glorie of the Lord,</hi> (can <hi>Nehemiah</hi> possibly hold in his teares?) is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from that part of Israell touching out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward administration of Christ his Kingdome by his owne Office-bearers. Oh, that our sinnes have provoked God thus to moove our <hi>David</hi> against vs! We hoped that our gratious King (according to his promise made openly in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingburgh</hi> that day before he went towardes England) would rather have remooved those
<pb facs="3"/>Reliques of Antichrist, which ever have trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the peace of Christ his church in England, wherevnto the God of peace did carrie him in a wōderfull peace, that he should prove a Prince of peace in building and beautifying the house of God. O thou highest, and most gracious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of kings, who diddest turue our Kings heart in Anno Dom. 1592. torestore Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, notwithstanding he had in anno <hi>1584.</hi> set vp Papall Bishops: give him now grace religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouslie to remember, That he hath by subscripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on sworne to defende Discipline then in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, all the dayes of his life, and That hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to a constitution of the generall Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie in <hi>Holi-rud</hi> house. And anno <hi>1602.</hi> where by it was ordayned (to prevent aspiring to the state of Papall Bishops in Englande) that those who were called by his Maiestie vnto that Parleament, and were formerlie intituled Lord Bishoppes, should from thence-forward, have no longer that title, and be called <hi>Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the Kirk to vote in Parleament.</hi> Longe have we (in these partes) expected from some of you (in whom the holy fire is not yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguished)
<pb facs="3"/>a continuance of the <hi>faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port anent th'assemblie at Aberdene</hi> But supposing that eyther <hi>feare,</hi> or want of meanes hath restreigned your zealous spirites, I have out of the said intelligences compiled this Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with all faithfulnes, though perhaps, there may be some small mistaking of the order of time. For most of myne intelligences (which I followe) shewe that the Archbishop of Glasco preached first. But one reported the Bishoppe of Orkney to be the firste preacher. It is thought meete by moe then my selfe to publish it, in hope, That, through the mercifull working of our good Lord and God, it may occasion our wyse &amp; Christian King (according to that heavenlie light, wherewith God hath indued him) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive and redresse such shamefull proceedings. 2. The Nobles, Barons, and Burroughes, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, that if such proceedings holde on, manie (besides the Englishe Nation) will (too readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie) saye: <hi>Are the Nobles, Barons, and Borroughes of Scotland (as well as the Bishopps and some Ministers there) cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the treasure of Englande, to
<pb facs="4"/>yeelde vnto the ouerthrowinge of their Law, by directions from England, which proceed frō the instigations of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of Cātorbuie? 3.</hi> The periured hyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and apostate betrayers of Christ his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to repent, if they have so much grace, or to be ashamed, if they be not past all grace, the wages of vnrighteousnes choking the spirit of God in them. And <hi>4.</hi> Such faithfull Ministers of Christ Iesus, as fight the good fight of faith, to iustifie Wisedome, by learned and modest wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, to resist the approches of Antichsist, by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient suffering, though vnto bloud: and inces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santlie to pray to God of trueth (who hath said to his Christ, <hi>Sit thou at my right hande, vntill I make thine enemies thy foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoole)</hi> to take his owne cause into his owne handes, &amp; to make our Noble King (all seduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes notwithstandinge) a worthie instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his glorie herein. AMEN.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>