<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Three Sonnets of Petrarch.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103518_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02334</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12462</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103518</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Three Sonnets of Petrarch.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two discourses of Master Frances Guicciardin : vvhich are wanting in the thirde and fourth bookes of his Historie, in all the Italian, Latin, and French coppies heretofore imprinted; which for the worthinesse of the matter they containe, were published in those three languages at Basile 1561. And are now for the same cause doone into English</title>
                 <author>Guicciardini, Francesco</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ponsonby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>9, 67 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="sonnets">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Three Sonnets of Petrarch.</head>
   <lg>
      <head>Fiamma dal ciel, &amp;c. Son. 106.</head>
      <l>1 LEwd whore that from the meanest state of life,</l>
      <l>vnt' others fal and spoile wast beastly bred,</l>
      <l>Whose whole delight doth stand on hateful strife,</l>
      <l>Let fire from heauen be poured on thy head.</l>
      <l>Oh neast of sinne, wherein now hatched is,</l>
      <l>That euill which through al the world is spread,</l>
      <l>Whilst Venus playes her maisters prize amisse,</l>
      <l>with Wine, with ease. and bowsie Bacchus eke,</l>
      <l>Old fooles, yong maids, bestride thy streetes in blis,</l>
      <l>Daunsing their roundes with Sathans dam vnmeeke,</l>
      <l>With bellowes, fire, with glasses to behold</l>
      <l>Their shame, that they do sencelesse in thee seeke.</l>
      <l>Simple thy source: most sinfull thou, now olde;</l>
      <l>his vvrath therefore vvill God of heauen vnfolde.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>L'auard Babilonia, &amp;c. Son. 107.</head>
      <l>2 NOw Babilon hath fild her greedy sacke,</l>
      <l>With wrath from Heaune, sact vp with filthy sin</l>
      <l>Which rents the same, to break at last thy backe,</l>
      <l>That fauor none from Ioue dooft seeke to vvin.</l>
      <l>From Pallas none. To Venus, Bacchus, he</l>
      <l>(in lust to swim, and sinke vp to the chinne)</l>
      <l>Oblations thine, and rights deuoted be.</l>
      <l>Redresse thereof my pined hart doth pray,</l>
      <l>(That helpe at hand, that golden helpe foresee)</l>
      <l>Restored Church, fel Idols dire decaie,</l>
      <l>Recured Faith, al falshood put to flight;</l>
      <l>The man of sinne, to beare no more the sway,</l>
      <l>The golden World restorde, and euery Wight</l>
      <l>With fruites of grace, and heauenly dainties dight.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <head>Fontana di dolore, &amp;c. Son. 108.</head>
      <l>3 THou source of griefe, thou den of wrath and ire,</l>
      <l>Schoole of deceit, old errors hydeous haunt:</l>
      <l>Earst Rome, but now fell Babel, set on fire</l>
      <l>With burning brands, such as olde Orchus Aunt</l>
      <l>With fury flung, the hart of man t'inflame.</l>
      <l>Thou forge of filth, thou vertues fal, auaunt,</l>
      <l>Sinke shall thy pride, thy sinne, and thou, with shame.</l>
      <l>How can it be but that thy Christ thy king</l>
      <l>Will beat thee downe with al thy brandes of blame,</l>
      <l>Abate thy hornes, and thee to meeknesse bring,</l>
      <l>Thou, that vvhilome of lovv beginning grew,</l>
      <l>And wonted was vvith lowlie sound to sing;</l>
      <l>With vertues olde, thy glories old renew,</l>
      <l>Least Constantine returne thy vvrack to revv.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>