<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honourable, Sr SEBASTIAN HARVY Knight, Lord Maior of the Honourable Citie of London, and to the right Worshipfull Aldermen and Sheriffes his Brethren, and to the right Worshipfull Mr Recorder, together with the whole estate of the said City, all true happinesse.</title>
           <author>Gouge, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103304_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01979</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12123</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103304</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honourable, Sr SEBASTIAN HARVY Knight, Lord Maior of the Honourable Citie of London, and to the right Worshipfull Aldermen and Sheriffes his Brethren, and to the right Worshipfull Mr Recorder, together with the whole estate of the said City, all true happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhole-armor of God: or A Christians spiritual furniture, to keepe him safe from all the assaults of Satan : First preached, and now the second time published and enlarged for the good of all such as well vse it:whereunto is also added a treatise of the sinne against the Holy Ghost. By VVilliam Gouge B.D. and preacher of Gods Word in Blacke Fryers London. A table of the seuerall points contained herein, is prefixed before the Booke</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Beale, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 626, 12 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Honourable, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> SEBASTIAN HARVY Knight, Lord Maior of the Honourable Citie of London, and to the right Worshipfull Aldermen and Sheriffes his Brethren, and to the right Worshipfull M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Recorder, together with the whole estate of the said City, all true happinesse.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable, Right Worshipfull;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Worships</hi> being (by the good guiding prouidence of GOD) the <hi>Generall, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> and <hi>Liefetenants</hi> of this <hi>Metropolis,</hi> this chiefe <hi>City</hi> &amp; <hi>Castle</hi> of the Kingdome, wherein (by the same Prouidence) I am (thogh one of the meanest, yet) one of the <hi>Watchmen;</hi> To whom ought I rather to present these fruits of my <hi>Watchmans</hi> function, then vnto your Honour and Worships? As duty in regard of your pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, so gratefulnesse also in regard of your kindnesses, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires as much. My Father, Grandfather, and other Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, haue of old from time to time beene beholding to this <hi>Honourable City:</hi> the kindnesse which they formerly receiued, is still continued to mee. Which as I doe with all humble thankfulnesse acknowledge, so from my heart I desire the <hi>Almighty</hi> to remember your Honor and Worships, together with the whole estate of this Honourable City, in goodnesse, and not to wipe out the kindnesse which is shewed to the Ministers of his Word, and to poore distressed people. Long hath the Gospell beene purely, powerfully, plentifully preached in this honourable <hi>City,</hi> and great countenance and maintenance hath by many therein beene giuen thereunto. Good orders haue within these later yeeres beene taken for the better sanctifying of the Lords Sabbath. Much reliefe is from time to time giuen to the poore. These and such like workes of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> are the beauty, honour, strength, and wealth of this <hi>City.</hi> I denie not, but that in the outward<pb facs="3"/> politicke gouernment of this great <hi>Corporation,</hi> and the many seuerall <hi>Companies</hi> therein, <hi>London</hi> may be accounted the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the earth. But the things which make it exceed in glory, are, the faire houses of Prayer and preaching the Word; the great Assemblies of Gods people frequenting the same to worship God: the spacious Hospitals and places of Charity, together with the liberall prouision therein made for reliefe of poore children and orphants, of aged and impotent men and women, of lame and maimed souldiers, and of many other like succourlesse persons; the thrones of Iustice and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with the like, wherein <hi>London</hi> may be compared to <hi>Sion</hi> the City of God, whereof great and excellent things are spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.
<hi>Right Honourable</hi> and <hi>Right Worshipfull,</hi> goe on this way, (which is the onely right way) to procure the peace and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of your <hi>City.</hi> Let the Ministry of Gods Word be more and more promoted: Let the Lords Sabbaths haue their due obseruations, let the poore be releeued, and the oppressed be succoured; let profane persons and all euill doers (the enemies of Christian Policies) be punished: In a word, let Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances be aduanced, and right iudgement executed, and so shall <hi>London</hi> be accounted the <hi>City of the great King,</hi> where he will delight to dwell, and bestow his blessing. For in these things is God highly honoured: Now God who can and will performe it,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 30.</note> hath said it; <hi>Them that honour me, will I honour.</hi> It lieth much in the power of Magistrates to procure or hinder the blessing of God in those Cities &amp; places ouer which they are set. For they being publike persons, their good deeds are by the wise God publikely rewarded, and their euill deedes publikely reuenged. <hi>Right Honourable</hi> and <hi>Right Worshipfull,</hi> accept, I pray you, the duty, and pardon the boldnes of your Watchman. And, <hi>O Lord of Lords,</hi> doe good to this <hi>City</hi> of thine, continue the peace and prosperity thereof: so prayeth</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours and Worships in all duty for euer bounden WILLIAM GOVGE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>