<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103356_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01991</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12135</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103356</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Admirable and memorable histories containing the wonders of our time. Collected into French out of the best authors. By I [sic] Goulart. And out of French into English. By Ed. Grimeston. The contents of this booke followe the authors aduertisement to the reader</title>
                 <author>Goulart, Simon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eld (Elide), George</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 646, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>IF any thinke these Histories strange, he may see the very title sayes as much: And it is good for an author to bee as good as his title: And this being a translation, it must be strange. If any thinke that by the name of Histories, all should be true, he may knowe Historiographers confesse they may write as they list. And <hi>Lucian</hi> entitles his most fabulous narrations a true His<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie: And if these be but tales, yet either hee is Maister, or he cites you his tales-maister, (more then most men will do) And very tales are heard or read by most of vs with good delight. These from good authors to good purpose are in good sort set downe. Then sit thee downe and make thy good of them: for haue thou a good memory and they will prooue memorable: that nor thou repent reading, nor he writing, nor we transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Imprinting. This is all, and of this make thy best.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>