<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the worshipfull Mr. ROBERT SHVTE ESQVIER.</title>
           <author>Lewis, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103072_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05406</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15558</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103072</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the worshipfull Mr. ROBERT SHVTE ESQVIER.</title>
                 <author>Lewis, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ignis coelestis: or An interchange of diuine love betweene God and his saints. By Iohn Lewis, minister of God words at St. Peters in the tovvne of St. Albons</title>
                 <author>Lewis, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 124, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the worshipfull M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. ROBERT SHVTE ESQVIER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>SIr</hi>: so often as I consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the breuity and frailty of this mortall life, that betweene the <hi>wombe</hi> and the <hi>tombe,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal. 39. 5.</hi>
      </note> the <hi>cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> and the <hi>graue,</hi> there is but a <hi>spans</hi> breadth: and so often as I remember,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb. 9.27.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>That it is appointed for man once to dye, and then he must come to iudgement;</hi> I cannot but with griefe admire the wilfull madnesse of this age; wherein men set their wits vpon
<pb facs="3"/>
the tenter-hookes of inuention and policie, and set their braines a worke to finde strange plots: One with <hi>Ahab</hi> to get <hi>Naboths vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi>;<note place="margin">
         <hi>1 Kings 21.</hi>
      </note> another with the <hi>rich Churle</hi> to enlarge his barnes by <hi>magnitude,</hi> and his bags by <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ester 3.5.</hi>
      </note> a third with proud <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> onely aimes at greatnesse, his aspiring minde is alwayes climbing, his desires cannot finde a <hi>Non vltra,</hi> for his preferment hath no period; a fourth with the rich <hi>Man</hi> how he may bathe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe in pleasure,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luke 16. 19.</hi>
      </note> and <hi>Sardana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palus</hi>-like become effeminate by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing himselfe to all voluptuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse;<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luke 10.42.</hi>
      </note> But that which is <hi>vnum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarium,</hi> especially necessary for our sound comfort here, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happinesse hereafter, is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, not regarded.<note place="margin">Quae possessa o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>, amata inquinant, omis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa crucian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Things which are obtained with much
<pb facs="3"/>
labour, retained with much care, and lost with much vexation, we hunt after with great eagernesse; but <hi>God</hi> who hath giuen vs, not onely our <hi>esse,</hi> but our <hi>bene esse,</hi> the fruition of whom is mans <hi>bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,</hi> is neither affected nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Luke 8.37.</hi>
      </note> With the <hi>Gadarens</hi> we preferre a few swine before <hi>Christ</hi> our Redeemer:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen. 25.32.</hi>
      </note> with prophane <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sau</hi> we sell our birth right, yea and the blessing with it, for a <hi>messe of pottage</hi>: whereas if we could but be aduised by the Heathen;<note place="margin">Virgill.</note>
      <hi>Ab Ioue principium,</hi> Let our loue begin at <hi>God,</hi> with him we should possesse peace, patience, comfort, content, helpe, happinesse, yea what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer were expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ient for life <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall</hi> and <hi>eternall:</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth. 6.33.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>If wee did but seeke God and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, all things necessary shall be added vnto vs</hi> There is
<pb facs="4"/>
no cause why we should be so loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke for the world; it is <hi>variable,</hi> soone got, soone lost; <hi>deceiueable,</hi> being but a <hi>shadow</hi> of <hi>felicity,</hi> no <hi>substance; treacherous</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> while it flattereth the body, it stayes the soule; <hi>perfidious,</hi> it complemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth with her louers, as <hi>Dalilah</hi> with <hi>Sampson,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iudg. 16.18.</hi>
      </note> but be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>raies them vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o <hi>Sathan</hi> their mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>all enemy. If wee could but looke on the world with the eye of <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>sound iudgement,</hi> and be so wise as to behold it in its proper complexion, we would not dote on so meane a creature, we would not make our seruant to be our Lord, when the <hi>Lord</hi> sues for the loue of vs his <hi>seruants</hi>: He that is <hi>vnchangeable,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Mal. 3.6. Cant 1. Leuit. 11.44. Ioel 2.18.</hi>
      </note> he that is <hi>amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> he that is <hi>infinitely holy, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely compassionate,</hi> hath a long time stood at the doore knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb facs="4"/>
desiring <hi>to come in and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>up with vs,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Reuel. 3.20.</hi>
      </note> intending to bring his prouision with him, to furnish our hearts, and at length to bring saluation to our soules, and our soules vnto blessednesse; yet like men carelesse of his kindenesse, fearelesse of his displeasure, we suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to knocke, and will not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, <hi>we are in bed with our darlings, and will not rise;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Luke 19.42.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Oh that in this our day we did but know the things which belong vnto our peace</hi>!</p>
   <p>The motiue that induceth me to commit this small worke vnto the Presse, is rather the worthines of the subiect, then any excellency of the Authors wit, it being worthy of the most aduised meditations of the best men, of our best time; wherein we shall clearely behold <hi>what God hath</hi> beene to vs,
<pb facs="5"/>
and what we ought to be toward him, the loue of the one, and the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the other.</p>
   <p>The great and meere volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary kindenesse which I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from your Worship, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any desert on my part, is a sufficient argument to perswade me to dedicate it vnto your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy selfe, beseeching you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it as a tes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>imony expressing his thankefulnesse, who shall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually acknowledge himselfe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged vnto you: The <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes Mite,</hi> a token of a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling minde, was kindely accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Although this worke be composed <hi>rudi ac crassa Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerua,</hi>
      <note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>n quid v<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ui, sed quid potui.</note> yet herein the Authors desire may no lesse be conceiued, then in that which is more exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site. I indeauour not indeede so much to please the eare, as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb facs="5"/>
the conscience, labouring ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for soundnesse of matter, then plausiblenes of phrase, and ayming more at a generall then at a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular benefit. What once <hi>Peter</hi> said vnto the <hi>Creeple</hi> that lay at the gate of the Temple, the same will I say vnto your worship.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Acts 3.6.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and Gold haue I none, but such as I haue giue I thee.</hi> And seeing I cannot expresse my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse as I would, let me be bold to doe it as I may; and what I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in action, I shal in praying <hi>God</hi> to giue you increase of grace and honour in this life<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and the eternall fruition of soule-contenting bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sednesse in the life to come.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all Christian dutie, IOHN LEVVIS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>