<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Master Perkinses Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Perkins, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103581_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09386</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19683</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103581</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Master Perkinses Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A Christian and plaine treatise of the manner and order of predestination : and of the largenes of Gods grace. First written in Latine by that reuerend and faithfull seruant of God, Master William Perkins, late preacher of the word in Cambridge. And carefully translated into English by Francis Cacot, and Thomas Tuke</title>
                 <author>Perkins, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Burby, Cuthbert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, Felix.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                            <distributor>Clarke (Clerke), Martin</distributor>
                            <distributor>Welby, William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>94, 188 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="43"/>
   <head>
      <hi>Master Perkinses Epistle</hi> to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE doctrine of Predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Gods Grace is to be founded vpon the <hi>Written Word</hi> of God, and not vpon the iudgements of men. For as <hi>Hilarie</hi> sayth well, <hi>God cannot be vnderstood but by God:</hi> And <note place="margin">De Tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. lib. 5.</note> againe, <hi>Wee must learne of God, what wee are to vnderstand of God, because he is the only author of our knowledge of him.</hi> It is also requisite that this Doctrine agree with the grounds of common reason, and of that knowledge of God which may be obtained by the light of nature; and such are these which follow.</p>
   <p n="1">
      <pb facs="44"/>
1. GOD is alwayes iust, albeit men do not vnderstand how he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. must.</p>
   <p n="2">2. GOD is not gouerned of, much lesse doth he depend vpon second cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, but doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ustly order them, euen then when they worke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p n="3">3. GOD work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>ly, to wit, propounding vnto himself is certaine end: he is ignorant of nothing: he doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> that which he cannot effect: hee doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dly behold what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>ll be, or what may be done, but hee dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>th all things vnto his glory; and therefore he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to do so.</p>
   <p n="4">4. GOD is not changed: and those things which are changed, are not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>changeable decree, all circumstances being certaine and sure.</p>
   <p n="5">5. <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> and vnsearchable iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>s of GOD are to be honoured and acknowledged.</hi> Augustine: It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> me (thou sayest) that he per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sheth, and another <note place="margin">De verb. Apost. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 11.</note> is baptized, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>oueth me, it mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ueth me as as man. If thou wilt heare the truth, it also <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>th me, because i am a man, nut of thou b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>st <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> man, I am also a man: let vs


<pb facs="44"/>
both heare him that saith, O man! Verily, if we be therefore mooued because we are men, the Apostle speaketh to humane nature it self being weake and feeble, saying; O man! Who art thou which pleadest against GOD? <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 20.</note> Shall the thing formed say to him that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it, Why hast thou made me thus? If a beast could speake and did say to God, Why hast thou made him a man, and me a beast? mightest thou not iustly be angry, and say, O beast, who art thou? and thou art a man, but in comparison of God, thou art a beast.</p>
   <p n="6">6. No good thing can be done, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse GOD doth absolutely will and worke it: and we do that which is good, so farre-forth as God doth worke in vs more or lesse.</p>
   <p n="7">7. No euill can be auoyded, vnlesse GOD do hinder it: and we auoyd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, so farre-forth as God doth more or lesse hinder it.</p>
   <p n="8">8. The will of GOD is knowne, not only by the written word, or by reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but also by the euent. For that, which commeth to passe, doth therefore come to passe, because God hath willed


<pb facs="45"/>
that it should come to passe.</p>
   <p n="9">9. A man doth not that good thing which by grace he is able to do, vnlesse God make him do it, as he hath made him able to do it if he will.</p>
   <p n="10">10. Not a part only, but the whole gouernment of the world, and the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of iustice, is to be ascribed to God, as to the author.</p>
   <p>I do now exhibit vnto thee a view and picture of this Doctrine, composed of these principles, and do publish the same, that I might, to my power, help out <note n="*" place="margin">Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ses.</note> those that stick in the difficulties of this doctrine of Predestination: and that I might cleere the truth, that is (as they call it) the <hi>Caluinists</hi> doctrine, of those reproches which are cast vpon it: and that I might mitigate and appease the mindes of some of our Brethren, which haue beene more offended at it then was fit. For I do willingly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and teach vniuersall redemption and grace, so farre as it is possible by the word. My mind is to pursue after peace, which is departing from vs: and I would


<pb facs="45"/>
haue all men so interpret my fact.</p>
   <p>I alleadge the testimonies of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient euery where, not but that euen one euident and perspicuous sentence of sacred Scripture, cōcerning any point of Doctrine and Faith, is of more value and force, then all the testimonies of the Doctours and Schoole-men: but because I hold it necessary, that there should be had an example of consent and concord in that doctrine, which is expounded in holy bookes, and is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated to all posterity. And I hope, I shall sufficiently perswade an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent iudge, that these things haue not beene lately hatched at home, which wee deliuer in our Congregations and Schooles, but that we haue also deriued and fetched them from the Fathers themselues.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>VVilliam Perkins.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>