<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Errata]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103290_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68107</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12119</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103290</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Errata]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of domesticall duties : eight treatises. I. An exposition of that part of Scripture out of which domesticall duties are raised. II. 1. A right coniunction of man and wife. 2. Common-mutuall duties betwixt man and wife. III. Particular duties of wiues. IV. Particular duties o husbands. V. Duties of children. VI. Duties of parents. VII. Duties of seruants. VIII. Duties of masters. By William Gouge</title>
                 <author>Gouge, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bladen, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 191, 196-693, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <p>A few faults escaped in the printing are noted in the end of the booke, which I desire you to amend with a pen.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <table>
         <row>
            <cell>TREAT. III.</cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>Particular duties of Wiues.</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>SVbiection,</hi> the generall head of all wiues du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, §. 2.</cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>Acknowledgment of an husbands superioritie, §. 3.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>2</cell>
            <cell>A due esteeme of her owne husband to be the best for her, and worthy of honour on her part, §. 5.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>3</cell>
            <cell>An inward wiue-like feare, §. 7.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>An outward reuerend cariage towards her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, which consisteth in a wiue-like so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, mildnesse, curtesie, and modestie in apparell, §. 9, 10, 11, 12.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>5</cell>
            <cell>Reuerend speech to, and of her husband, §. 13, 14, 15, 16.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>Obedience, §. 17.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>Forbearing to doe without or against her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands consent, such things as he hath power to order, as, to dispose and order the common goods of the familie, and the allowance for it, or children, seruants, cattell, guests, iournies, &amp;c. §. 18, 23, 38, 39, 40, 41.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>A ready yeelding to what her husband would haue done. This is manifested by her willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to dwell where he will, to come when he calls, and to doe what he requireth, §. 43, 44, 45, 46.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>A patient bearing of any reproofe, and a ready redressing of that for which she is iustly repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, §. 47, 48.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>10</cell>
            <cell>Contentment with her husbands present estate, §. 49.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>11</cell>
            <cell>Such a subiection as may stand with her subie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Christ, §. 51.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>12</cell>
            <cell>Such a subiection as the Church yeeldeth to Christ, which is sincere, pure, cheerefull, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, for conscience sake, §. 54, 55, &amp;c.</cell>
         </row>
      </table>
   </p>
   <p>
      <table>
         <row>
            <cell>TREAT. IV.</cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>Particular duties of Husbands.</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>WJsdome</hi> and <hi>Loue,</hi> the generall heads of all husbands duties, §. 2, 4.</cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>Acknowledgment of a wiues neere coniunction, and fellowship with her husband, §. 6.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>2</cell>
            <cell>A good esteeme of his owne wise to be the best for him, and worthy of loue on his part, §. 9.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>3</cell>
            <cell>An inward intire affection, §. 11.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>An outward amiable cariage towards his wife, which consisteth in an husband-like grauitie, mildnesse, courteous acceptance of her curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, and allowing her to weare fit apparell, §. 4, 15, 22, 40, 49.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>5</cell>
            <cell>Milde and louing speech to and of his wife, §. 24 25, 26, &amp;c.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>A wise maintaining his authoritie, and forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to exact all that is in his power, §. 4, 18.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>A ready yeelding to his wiues request, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a generall consent and libertie vnto her to order the affaires of the house, children, seruants, &amp;c. And a free allowing her some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to bestow as she seeth occasion, §. 18, 54.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>A forbearing to exact more then his wife is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to doe, or to force her to dwell where it is not meet, or to enioyne her to doe things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet in themselues, or against her minde, §. 18, 26.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>A wise ordering of reproofe: not vsing it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iust and weighty cause, and then priuatly, and meekly, §. 35, 38.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>10</cell>
            <cell>A prouident care for his wife, according to his abilitie, §. 46, 49, 50, 52.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>11</cell>
            <cell>A forbearing to exact any thing which stands not with a good conscience, §. 26.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>12</cell>
            <cell>Such a loue, as Christ beareth to the Church, and man to himselfe, which is first free, in deed, and truth, pure, chaste, constant, §. 61, &amp;c. and 74.</cell>
         </row>
      </table>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <table>
         <row>
            <cell>TREAT. III.</cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>Aberrations of Wiues from their particular duties.</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>AMbition,</hi> the generall ground of the aberrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of wiues, §. 2.</cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>A conceit that wiues are their husbands equals, §. 4.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>2</cell>
            <cell>A conceit that she could better subiect her selfe to any other man then to her owne husband, §. 6.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>3</cell>
            <cell>An inward despising of her husband, §. 8.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>Vnreuerend behauiour towards her husband, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested by lightnesse, fullennesse, scornfulnes, and vanitie in her attire, §. 9, 10, 11, 12.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>5</cell>
            <cell>Vnreuerend speech to and of her husband, §. 13, 14, 15, 16.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>A stout standing on her owne will, §. 17.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>A peremptorie vndertaking to doe things as she list without and against her husbands consent. This is manifested by priuie purloyning his goods, taking allowance, ordering children, seruants, and cattell, feasting strangers, making iourneyes, and vowes, as her selfe listeth, §. 42.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>An obstinate standing vpon her owne will, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her husband dwell where she will, and refusing to goe when he calls, or to doe any thing vpon his command, §. 44, 45, 46, 67.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>Disdaine at reproofe; giuing word for word; and waxing worse for being reproued, §. 47, 48.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>10</cell>
            <cell>Discontent at her husbands estate, §. 50.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>11</cell>
            <cell>Such a pleasing of her husband as offendeth Christ, §. 53.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>12</cell>
            <cell>Such a subiection as is most vnlike to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, viz. fained, forced, fickle, &amp;c. §. 56, &amp;c.</cell>
         </row>
      </table>
   </p>
   <p>
      <table>
         <row>
            <cell>TREAT. IV.</cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>Aberrations of Husbands from their particular duties.</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>WAnt of wisdome</hi> and <hi>loue,</hi> the generall ground of the aberrations of husbands, §. 3, 5.</cell>
            <cell> </cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>1</cell>
            <cell>Too meane account of wiues, §. 8.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>2</cell>
            <cell>A preposterous conceit of his owne wife to be the worst of all: and that he could loue any but her, §. 10.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>3</cell>
            <cell>A Stoicall disposition, without all heat of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, §. 12.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>4</cell>
            <cell>An vnbeseeming cariage towards his wife, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested by his basenesse, tyrannicall vsage of her, loftinesse, harshnesse, and niggardlinesse, §. 5, 15, 17, 41, 44, 53.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>5</cell>
            <cell>Harsh, proud, and bitter speeches, to and of his wife, §. 24, 25, 30, 32, 36, 39.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>6</cell>
            <cell>Losing of his authoritie, §. 5.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>7</cell>
            <cell>Too much strictnesse ouer his wife. This is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested by restraining her from doing any thing without particular and expresse consent, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king too strict account of her, and allowing her no more then is needfull for her owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate vse, §. 19, 55.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>8</cell>
            <cell>Too lordly a standing vpon the highest step of his authoritie: being too frequent, insolent, and peremptorie in commanding things friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, vnmeet, and against his wiues minde and conscience, §. 30, 32.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>9</cell>
            <cell>Rashnesse and bitternesse in reprouing: and that too frequently, on sleight occasions, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefully before children, seruants, and stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, §. 36, 38, 39.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>10</cell>
            <cell>A carelesse neglect of his wife, and niggardly dealing with her, and that in her weaknesse, §. 46, 51, 53</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>11</cell>
            <cell>A commanding of vnlawfull things, §. 26, 30, 32.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>12</cell>
            <cell>Such a disposition as is most vnlike to Christs, and to that which a man beareth to himselfe, viz. complementall, impure, for by-respects, vnconstant, &amp;c. §. 62, &amp;c. and 74.</cell>
         </row>
      </table>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>