<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103827_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05039</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15181</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103827</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of predestination [and] election made by Joh [a] n Lamberd minister of the church of Elham. Anno M.D.L</title>
                 <author>Lambert, John, minister of Elham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mychell (Michell), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Canterbury</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <head>To the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Most dere reader myne entent is not to Iudge any man, but that, when he hath red this lytle tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atyse, he may consulte or counsell with his owne conscience and so examyne the same, whether he do lyue lyke a reprobate or one that is electe of God to saluacion, for the dedes of a reprobate are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfest. Also lykewyse the dedes of the electe are not hydde. Therfore my councell is that no man dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with God why he hath ordey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the vesselles of wrath to dāp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion, yf he do S. Paule dothe make hym an answere. (Because sayth he that he myght declare the ryches of his glory on the vessels of mercy whiche he had preparyd vnto glory) for the reprobates are
<pb facs="3"/>
      
mynysters vnto the saluacyon of the electe, which are Goddes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kemanshyp created in Christe Iesus vnto good workes, vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whiche saythe saynt Paule, God ordeyned vs before that we shuld walke in them: He saythe more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, by grace ye are made saue tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rough fayth that worketh by loue the whiche faythe is the gyfte of God, and as many as haue the same gyfte of God haue cause to prayse the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther and the sone &amp; the holy ghost to whome be all honor and glory. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>