<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right Honourable Lord, Fraun∣ces, Earle of Bedford, one of her maie∣sties most Honourable priuy Councell, Knight of the Noble order of the Garter: A. G. wisheth prosperity in this world, with increase of peace, mercy, and grace, and in the worlde to come life euerla∣sting.</title>
           <author>Gee, Alexander</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103007_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01570</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11697</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103007</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right Honourable Lord, Fraun∣ces, Earle of Bedford, one of her maie∣sties most Honourable priuy Councell, Knight of the Noble order of the Garter: A. G. wisheth prosperity in this world, with increase of peace, mercy, and grace, and in the worlde to come life euerla∣sting.</title>
                 <author>Gee, Alexander</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ground of Christianitie : composed in maner of a dialogue between Paule and Titus, contayning all the principall poyntes of our saluation in Christ</title>
                 <author>Gee, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 <publisher>Waldegrave (Walgrave), Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Woodcock, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 103, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right <hi>Honourable Lord,</hi> Fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Earle of <hi>Bedford,</hi> one of her maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <hi>sties most Honourable priuy Councell, Knight</hi> of the Noble order of the Garter: A. G. wisheth prosperity in this world, with increase of peace, mercy, and grace, and in the worlde to come life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit (right Honourable) the multitude of foolish Pamphlets, &amp; friuolous toys, which in these our dayes are put in print, haue brought almost no lesse contempt of the faculty of printing, then discouragement to those that woulds write more waightye matters: yet I thought it in conscience good for me to bee no more therby discouraged from attempting any thing, which may either tend to the glory of God, or benefit of his Church, then for a man to be squaimish to eate, because he hath seene another surfet. It could not come in my minde (though it rowled too and fro towardes many) vnto whome to dedicate this rude and simple worke of mine, rather then vnto your honour, whose iust &amp; most deserued commēdation, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well
<pb facs="3"/>
in matters of religion, as also in all other politique affayres, as I spare presently to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; (because to prayse any man to his face▪ doth seeme rather fained flattery, then pure loue) so the trueth it selfe deuoid of partiality, can not vniustly conceale, nor iniuriously sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse. I coulde easily haue procured vnto my selfe many pulbacks, lets and hindrances▪ from attempting so aduenturous an enterprise, had not the assured knowledge of your Honoures singuler humility, in abasing your self to them of lower degree; fully perswaded me to the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary. Neither the worthinesse of the writer, (who is as bold as blinde Baiyard) nor the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the worke, (as it proceedeth from so base a workman) deserueth in any wise so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a patronage, but in that it redoundeth to the repairation of the ruines of Christe his Church, whereof as it hath pleased the Lorde in mercy to make you a maintainer, so you will no doubt from Day to Day, and time to time, shew your selfe a notable fauourer, yea, euen of the smallest stones in the building, which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they bee neither grauen with curious worke, or pollished with exquisite art) though some doe rashly condemne, yet I know youre honour will not reiect▪ but rather will consider, that notwithstanding the chambers of Christs
<pb facs="3"/>
church are in some places a trimming vp with beautifull worke, yet in some other places (the groundsell being scarse layd) strong oken Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, so it bee sounde, may doe more good, then fine firre if it bee weake. The worke which I make bolde at this time to shrowd vnder your protection, is briefe &amp; pithy, <hi>framed in man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of a dialogue, handling al the cheefe points of Chrstianity,</hi> with many additions, no lesse profitable then necessary, for those that desire to be further instructed in many points, where I thought it most requisite and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient. All men, yea euen the simplest, haue neede nowe to get assuraunce of saluation to themselues, not by workes without knowledge, (which bewrayeth intollerable Hipocrisye,) but first by true faith grounded vpon the rock of Gods word, and then by workes proceeding from the same; that they may bee able to giue an account of their fayth, &amp; to stop the mouth of the aduersary in the day of triall. The false Apostles are already craftily crept in, which seeke to vndermine vnstable soules, wresting and writhing the scriptures to their own dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, whose iudgement is iust: for the Lorde hath sente them strong delusions, that they should beleeue lies, that all may bee damned which beleeue not the trueth, but haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
<pb facs="4"/>
in vnrighteousnesse, &amp; as they haue not regarded to know God, so God hath deliuered them vp to a reprobate minde, to doe those things which are not conuenient. The cheefe respect and finall end of this my small labour, according to my poore Talent, is to helpe the simpler sort, whom I know (the more is the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) to be yet besotted with ignorance, whome I seeke rather to enstruct, because they bee not skilfull, then to confound the aduersary, who is very subtill. Wherefore I present this small worke vnto your honour, as a token of my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained good will, and great zeal towards you, beeing readye at all times, and in all places to perfourm all other duties, wherwith the Lord shall enable mee, with no lesse feruent prayers to the Lerde for your health of bodye to his pleasure in this life, then cuntinuall supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for the placing of your soule and body in the heauens, with our cheefe Lorde and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Iesus Christ, among the angels and bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed saints, in the life to come, of which ioy the Lorde make your honour, and all those that loue the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mming of Christ▪ partakers, for the same Christes same. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honours most bounden; Alexander Gee.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>