<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE COVRTE∣ous, and Christian READER.</title>
           <author>Gawen, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103024_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13952</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24261</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103024</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE COVRTE∣ous, and Christian READER.</title>
                 <author>Gawen, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe institution of the common places of sacred divinitie : Wherein, the truth of every place is proved, and the sophismes of Bellarmine are reprooved. Written in Latine, by Lucas Trelcatius, and Englished by Iohn Gawen, minister of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Trelcatius, Lucas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <publisher>Baker, Michael.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Burton, Francis.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 595, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE COVRTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Christian READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot long since (Courteous Reader,) a friend of mine commending this Booke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee, vpon the generall good liking conceyved thereof in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall by the learned, intreated mee for the further good of the Church, to take vpon me the Translation therof: Which, though at first, I was vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to doe, especially for that in the perusall thereof, I found it so Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall, as that it required much Art, Reading, &amp; Leasure of him that should
<pb facs="5"/> performe that businesse. Yet foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Booke for matter is neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, for Art exquisite, and for Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode more compendious then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I haue read in this kind, I haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured the imployment of that Art, Reading, and Leysure which I haue, in the Translation of the same. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as my labour hath beene the more difficult, partly, because the Treatise is Logicall, and therefore in many places are required proper and fitte tearmes of Art, wherein our English tongue is penurious; partly, because of many Greeke words very significāt, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not easily expressed word for word in our language; partly also by reason of some few faultes committed in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall Printing, (from which no Booke can bee free,) and therefore had but my coniecture at the correction thereof; so I trust it shall bee the more
<pb facs="5"/> favourably censured, if ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in be found Defectiue. Concerning my dealing herein, I haue followed the Author as neerely in sence, as my Iudgement apprehended, as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in Wordes as Discretion guided me, and as fitly in Phrase, as the Idiome of our Tongue could suffer. Onely I haue inserted here and there a Worde of mine owne, eyther for the explayning of Wordes more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure, or for the supplying of such, as in Latine are more tollerably vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstoode: All which, I haue for dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference sake noted with a Parenthesis. And withall, for the better satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Intelligent, haue placed all the obscure Latine Wordes in the Margent, as leaving them to their choyce, eyther to accept of mine Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, as it is, or allow of their own, if it be better. As for the places of scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="6"/> quoted in the Margent, I leaue them as I found them. It remayneth therefore (Christian Reader) that thou take in good part, what I offer in good will. And so I end, wishing my labour to bee for thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, and both for Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Ludlow this 9. of October. <hi>1610.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN GAWEN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>