<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, AND TRAVELY Religious, IAMES Lord STRANGE, Heire to the Right Honorable WILLIAM Earle of Darby: I. L. wisheth encrease of blessings Internall, Externall, Eternall.</title>
           <author>Lewis, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103079_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15560</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103079</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, AND TRAVELY Religious, IAMES Lord STRANGE, Heire to the Right Honorable WILLIAM Earle of Darby: I. L. wisheth encrease of blessings Internall, Externall, Eternall.</title>
                 <author>Lewis, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vnmasking of the masse-priest : vvith a due and diligent examination of their holy sacrifice. By C.A. Shewing how they partake with all the ancient heretiques, in their profane, impious, and idolatrous worship</title>
                 <author>Lewis, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                    <distributor>Whitaker, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 233, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, AND TRAVELY Religious, IAMES Lord STRANGE, Heire to the Right Honorable WILLIAM <hi>Earle of</hi> Darby: I. L. <hi>wisheth encrease</hi> of blessings Internall, Externall, <hi>Eternall.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>AS the God of Nature hath Decked that <hi>Great Man</hi> the <hi>World</hi> with diuers ornaments, it being in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more admirable then in <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety;</hi> so hath the same God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched that <hi>little World Man,</hi> with sundry en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, he being in nothing more profitable to the Church, then in <hi>Diuersity:</hi> For to <hi>some he hath giuen to be Apostles, to others to</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ephes. 4. 11, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>be Prophets, to others to be Teachers;</hi> and all this <hi>for the gathering together of the Saints, for the workes of the Ministry, for the building vp of the body of Christ.</hi> So
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>that wherein one is</hi> Defectiue, <hi>another is</hi> Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, <hi>that the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Christ <hi>may bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly instructed in all things, by the mutuall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of each fellow member.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Hence it comes to passe that some men abound with variety of</hi> Tongues; <hi>others with interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of</hi> Languages, <hi>some with the smoothnes of</hi> Doctrine, <hi>and others are acquainted with the knotty study of</hi> Polemicall Theologie: <hi>there being nothing commodious for that</hi> Mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body <hi>of</hi> Christ, <hi>which cannot be supplied by one member or other. And albeit this renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> Kingdome <hi>of great</hi> Britaine <hi>flowes with multitudes of most pregnant wits,</hi> (<hi>as once did</hi> Canaan <hi>with</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>and</hi> Hony) <hi>who are sarre more powerfully able to buckle with our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, then my selfe; yet</hi> (<hi>beeing confident in the</hi> Almighty) <hi>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>with little</hi> Dauid <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured to encounter with this great</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>of</hi> Gath, <hi>the</hi> Romish <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, hoping my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> (<hi>albeit vnpollished with</hi> Eligancy <hi>of stile</hi>) <hi>shall not bee altogether</hi> vnprofitable <hi>to the</hi> Church. <hi>The</hi> insolency <hi>of the</hi> Romish Foxes, (<hi>as in all places of this Land, so more especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi>) <hi>in those parts, where your</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>hath</hi> Command <hi>and</hi> Mansion, <hi>and my selfe</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidence
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>and</hi> Imployment, <hi>hath forced me to the search of this subiect. The setling of</hi> weake, <hi>and confirmation of</hi> sound Protestants, <hi>hath pressed it to the Presse. The bonds of</hi> Respect <hi>and</hi> Duty, <hi>wherein I am obliged vnto your</hi> Honor, <hi>bind both my selfe, and it vnto your</hi> Noble <hi>Selfe; vnto whose</hi> Patronage <hi>I</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend <hi>it, and vnder whose</hi> Name <hi>I</hi> commit <hi>it to the wide</hi> World.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>The Motiues that induce me to Dedicate this small Treatise to your</hi> Honor, <hi>are.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>First the Externall</hi> Nobility <hi>of your</hi> Birth, <hi>being so</hi> Noble <hi>a</hi> Branch, <hi>equally springing from two</hi> Illustrious Stems. <hi>Secondly, the</hi> Internall Nobility <hi>of your</hi> Grace, <hi>manifested by your so sincere affection to</hi> Religion, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in with</hi> Timothy, <hi>your</hi> Honour <hi>hath</hi> beene instructed from your Child-hood; <hi>and to the true</hi> Professours <hi>whereof, your</hi> Lordship <hi>hath vouchsafed alwayes a gracious countenance. Thirdly, your purpose to visite other Kingdomes abroad; where doubtlesse occasion will be offered vnto your</hi> Lordship, <hi>to maintaine that</hi> Truth <hi>wherein you haue beene bred, and to oppose that</hi> Falshood <hi>which you cannot but detest. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>I presumed to preferre this part of my</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
studies, vnto your <hi>Honorable Patronage,</hi> that it might remaine with your <hi>Honor</hi> as an <hi>Antidote</hi> against the <hi>Poyson</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> and <hi>Infection</hi> of the <hi>Romish Locusts.</hi> Lastly, that hereby I might render vnto your <hi>Honor</hi> some testimonie of <hi>thankfulnesse,</hi> for those manie vndeserued <hi>Fauours,</hi> which Your <hi>Lordship</hi> hath beene pleased to conferre vppon mee; that as I remaine bound vnto Your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> for euer: So heereby I might free my selfe from the staine of <hi>Ingratitude.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Accept therefore, <hi>(I</hi> most humbly beseech your <hi>Honor)</hi> this pleadge of his vnfained thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse, who shall continually pray to <hi>God</hi> to blesse your <hi>Lordshippe</hi> with aboundance of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, Wealth, Grace, Prosperity</hi> in this World, and the full Fruition of Eternall <hi>Glory</hi> in the World to come,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all seruice to be Commanded. IOHN LEVVIS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>