<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Dr. CARIERS PREFACE
TO HIS LETTER.</title>
           <author>Carier, B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103612_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02483</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12610</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103612</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Dr. CARIERS PREFACE
TO HIS LETTER.</title>
                 <author>Carier, B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to a treatise vvritten by Dr. Carier, by way of letter to his Maiestie : vvherein he layeth downe sundry politike considerations; by which hee pretendeth himselfe was moued, and endeuoureth to moue others to be reconciled to the Church of Rome, and imbrace tha religion, which he calleth catholike. By George Hakewil, Doctour of Diuinity, and chapleine to the Prince his Highnesse</title>
                 <author>Hakewill, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 30, 130, 4, 131-306, 26, 2 pages, folded table, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="26" facs="15"/>
   <head>D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. CARIERS PREFACE
TO HIS LETTER.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most Excellent and Renowned Soueraigne,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowne to all those that knowe
me in <hi>England,</hi> that for these many yeeres
I had my health very ill, and therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
from time to time vsed all the meanes
and medicines that <hi>England</hi> could afford;
Last of all, by the aduice of my Phisitians, I made mine
humble suite vnto your <hi>Maiestie,</hi> that I might trauell vnto
the <hi>Spaw</hi> for the vse of those waters, purposing with my
selfe that if I could be well, I would goe from thence to <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delberge,</hi>
and spend this winter there. But when I was gone
from the <hi>Spaw</hi> to <hi>Aquisgrane,</hi> and so to <hi>Colin,</hi> I found
my selfe, rather worse then better then I was before, and
therefore I resolued with my selfe that it was high time for
me to settle my thoughts vpon another world: And seeing
I was out of hope to enioy the health of my body, at the least
to looke to the health of my soule, from whence both<note n="1" place="margin">You might haue named Scripture as well as art, but it seemes you pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely forbore it, lest you shou'd seeme a Caluinist.</note> art and
experience teacheth me that all my bodily infirmities haue
their beginning, for if I could by any study haue prooued Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike
Religion to bee false, or by any meanes haue profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
it to bee<note n="2" place="margin">In your 2. chap. &amp; 21. Sect. you affirme the doctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng.</hi> to be that which is conteined in the cōmon pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er booke, and Church Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chisme, very nere agreeing with, or at least not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
      </note> true in <hi>England,</hi> I doubt not, but the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of my soule would haue much helped the health of my
bodie: But the more I studied the<note n="3" place="margin">Had you brought any proofe from the Scriptures &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers for the trueth of that Religion, which you call Cathol. you would haue thereby giuen vs some rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>on to thinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ou had indeed studied them.</note> Scriptures, and most
ancient Fathers to confute it, the more I was compelled
to see the trueth thereof, and the more I laboured to<note n="4" place="margin">Your recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>liation of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ō was nothing else but a renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the truth.</note> recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile
the religion of <hi>England</hi> thereunto, the more I was dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked,
suspected, and condemned as a common enemie: And
<pb n="27" facs="15"/>
if I would haue been either ignorant, or silent, I might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
with the pleasures and commodities of my preferments,
haue in time cast off the care of Religion: But seeing my
studie forced mee to<note n="5" place="margin">It is maruell you had not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by writing</note> knowe, and my place<note n="6" place="margin">Your place compelled you not to preach points of <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>mish</hi> doctrine.</note> compelled me to
preach, I had no way to auoid my griefe, nor meanes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
it: I haue therfore apprehended the opportunitie of my
Licence to tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ell, that I may withdraw my selfe for a while
from the sight and offence of those in <hi>England,</hi> which<note n="7" place="margin">Catholike Religion is not hated in <hi>England,</hi> but the religion of pretended Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes is iustly restrained.</note> hate Catholike Religion, and<note n="8" place="margin">You might as fully and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue enioyed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ence of our blessed Sauiour in the vnit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
         <hi>English</hi> Church, as the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>mish.</hi>
      </note> freely and fully enioy the
presence of our blessed <hi>Sauiour,</hi> in the vnitie of his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
Church, wherein I will neuer forget, at the<note n="9" place="margin">How can there be a dayly oblation of that which himselfe offered once for all. Heb. 7. 27. &amp; 9. 28. and 10. 10</note> dayly obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of his most blessed bodie and blood, to lift vp my heart
vnto him and to pray for the<note n="10" place="margin">When his <hi>Mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>sties</hi> reasons are answered why he should not bee already esteemed in the vnitie of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, prayer for his admission into it, will bee admitted.</note> admission of your <hi>Maiesty</hi>
thereinto: And in the meane time I haue thought it my
<note n="11" place="margin">Your due<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ie would better haue appeared in writing somewhat in defence of his <hi>Maiesties</hi> writings.</note> duety to write this short treatise with mine owne hand,
wherein before I<note n="12" place="margin">Your auowed presence at the dayly oblation (as you call it) was a sufficient declaration of your reuolt.</note> publish my selfe vnto the world, I desire
to shew to your <hi>Maiesty</hi> these two things:
<list>
         <item>1<note n="13" place="margin">How sufficiently either of these two bee shewed, I leaue it to the indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Reader to iudge.</note> The meanes of my conuersion vnto Cath. Religion:</item>
         <item>2 The hopes I haue to doe your <hi>Maiesty</hi> no ill s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ruice
therein.</item>
      </list>
   </p>
   <closer>I humbly craue your <hi>Maiesties</hi>
      <note n="14" place="margin">I wonder that any hauing affiance in his <hi>Holiness<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> pardons, should desire his <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>esties.</hi>
      </note> pardon, and will rest euer <signed>Your <hi>Mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>sties</hi>
         <note n="15" place="margin">Hee is indeed likely to bee a faithfull seruant to his <hi>Maiestie,</hi> who flies to the tents, and pleads the cause of his sworne enemies.</note> faithfull and truely deuoted seruant,
<hi>B. Carier.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>