<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right honourable and his singular good Lorde and maister, Edwarde de Vere, Lorde d'Escales, and Ba∣dlesmere, Vicount Bulbecke, Earle of Oxenforde, and Lorde great Chamberlayne of Englande, Iohn Brooke vvisheth long lyfe, vvith the increase of honor. &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Brooke, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103536_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02347</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12476</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103536</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right honourable and his singular good Lorde and maister, Edwarde de Vere, Lorde d'Escales, and Ba∣dlesmere, Vicount Bulbecke, Earle of Oxenforde, and Lorde great Chamberlayne of Englande, Iohn Brooke vvisheth long lyfe, vvith the increase of honor. &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Brooke, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The staffe of Christian faith : profitable to all Christians, for to arme themselues agaynst the enimies of the Gospell: and also for to knowe the antiquitie of our holy fayth, and of the true Church. Gathered out of the vvorks of the ancient doctors of the church, and of the councels, and many other doctors, vvhose names you shall see here follovving. Translated out of Frenche into English, by Iohn Brooke of Ashe next Sandvviche. With a table to finde out all that which is contayned in the booke</title>
                 <author>Brès, Guy de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 382, 10 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the Right honourable <hi>and his singular good Lorde and maister,</hi> Edwarde de Vere, Lorde d'Escales, and</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlesmere, Vicount Bulbecke, Earle of Oxenforde, and Lorde great Chamberlayne of Englande, Iohn Brooke vvisheth long lyfe, vvith the increase of honor. &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LTHOVGH VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue the roote of well doing (Right honorable Lorde) hath of it selfe, sufficient force to withstande, repell, and ouerthrowe, both the open malice, and secrete slaunders of euill tongues, yet notwithstanding considering howe daungerous, yea howe vnpossible a thing it is to escape that poysoned sting of Zoilus, and also that nothing hath euer ben so well done, but that this Scorpion hath eyther openly or priuily stong, I nede not to doubt, nay I may be right sure, that these my labors shal come into the hands of some, more curious than wyse, more ready to nippe and tante (yea euen withoute fault) then frendly to admonishe or amende. By occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="3"/> whereof (right honorable and my singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar good Lorde) I haue not only thought it expedient for hope of your honours fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable patronage, towardes these also my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures bestowed in translation: But also for respect of my particular duetie towardes your honor, to offer and dedicate the same likewyse to your fauorable allowance and well liking. For if in the opinion of all men, there can be found no one more fitte, for pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage and defence of learning, then the skilfull: for that he is both wyse and able to iudge and discerne truly thereof. I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing righte well that your honor hathe continually, euen from your tender yeares, bestowed your time and trauayle towardes the attayning of the same, as also the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie of Cambridge hath acknowledged in graunting and giuing vnto you such com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation and prayse thereof, as verily by righte was due vnto your excellent vertue and rare learning. Wherin verily Cambridge the mother of learning, and learned men, hath openly confessed: and in this hir con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing made knowen vnto al men, that your honor being learned and able to iudge as a
<pb facs="3"/> safe harbor and defence of learning, and therefore one most fitte to whose honorable patronage I might safely commit this my poore and simple labours. Likewyse remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring howe much and many wayes I am by dutye bounde vnto your honor, as also howe vnable I am to discharge the same: I haue thought it in respecte also of my behalfe and duty, most meete to offer and exhibite, such trauelles as my abilitie and skill can reache vnto, to your Lordship as pledge and token of my dutifull and vnfained good wil: To the ende that such profyt as by this my trauels may growe to my countrey and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthes, may be receiued vnder your Lordshyppes approbation and defence: that all men which doe reape benefyte thereby, should owe thankes vnto you in whose duety and good will I am. Wherefore hartely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring and humbly beseeching your Lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe to take on you the patronage and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of these my labors by translation that by your approbation and well liking, others may also the rather like thereof. Crauing pardon for this my symple boldnesse or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bolde symplicitie hoping also of the
<pb facs="4"/> continuance of your honors accustomed goodnesse towardes mee, and instantlye praying to God for your prosperous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, I cease further at this time to sollicite you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honors obedient ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, Iohn Brooke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>