<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>GEORGE HAKEVVIL.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103612_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02483</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12610</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103612</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>GEORGE HAKEVVIL.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvvere to a treatise vvritten by Dr. Carier, by way of letter to his Maiestie : vvherein he layeth downe sundry politike considerations; by which hee pretendeth himselfe was moued, and endeuoureth to moue others to be reconciled to the Church of Rome, and imbrace tha religion, which he calleth catholike. By George Hakewil, Doctour of Diuinity, and chapleine to the Prince his Highnesse</title>
                 <author>Hakewill, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 30, 130, 4, 131-306, 26, 2 pages, folded table, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="answer">
   <pb n="28" facs="16"/>
   <head>GEORGE HAKEVVIL.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is likewise knowen to all them that
knew you, that for these many yeres,
you haue beene more sicke in minde,
then in body, which hath appeared
not onely publikely in your Sermons
and writings; but priuately in your Conferences and
Letters: where of my selfe am in part a witnesse; but
they with whom you were longer and more famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly
conuersant, can more fully testifie it, and though
you vsed many medicines, yet one was wanting, to
wit,<note place="margin">1. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t. 3. 4.</note>
      <hi>a meeke and quiet spirit, a thing before God much set
by;</hi> it being as <hi>Dauids</hi> musicke, which stilled <hi>Sauls</hi> rage;
and this I am perswaded would haue done you more
good, aswell in regard of the diseases of your body
as your minde, then any of your other medicines, or
all of them put together: among which your last was
the <hi>Spaw</hi> waters, which I graunt, you might vse by
aduice of Physitians; but I haue withall reason to
thinke the voyage out of his <hi>Maiesties</hi> dominions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
those parts, was by you intended rather for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler
&amp; safer discouering of the sickenes of your mind,
then the recouering of that of your body: which your
selfe in this very Preface confesse vpon the matter, in
as much as being (you say) <hi>suspected &amp; condemned as a
common enemy, and hauing no way to auoid your griefe, nor
meanes to endure it, you desired to withdraw your selfe from
the sight and offence of those who hated Catholike Religion:</hi>
whereby I presume you meane such as opposed your
turbulent courses, labouring vnder pretence of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike
Religion, and olde <hi>English</hi> diuinitie, to bring
<pb n="29" facs="16"/>
in, and set vp, the new <hi>Romish;</hi> and considering you
stood so affected, it seemeth to me strange you should
purpose a iourney to <hi>Heydelberge,</hi> and the spending of
a winter there, being so profested an enemy to all <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinists,</hi>
except you hoped to conuert <hi>Abraham Scul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet,</hi>
Or <hi>Dauid Parrey:</hi> My selfe passed one whole win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
amongst them, and vnlesse their opinions be since
altered, or you had altered yours before your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
thither, or at least concealed them at your being
there, you would doubtlesse before the winter had
passed, growen more weary of them then of vs: But
being (you say) vpon the way at <hi>Colin,</hi> you found your
selfe worse, and thereupon <hi>resolued it was high time to
settle your thoughts vpon another world, and being out of
hope to enioy the health of your bodie, at least to looke to the
health of your soule;</hi> So that by your owne confession,
you made a vertue of necessitie, then resoluing to set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
your selfe, when you expected not long after the
dissolution of your body; then to fixe your thoughts
vpon God, when you perceiued you could not long
remaine in the world; which as it is lesse acceptable
to God, then for a man to consecrate the flowre and
strength of his age to him, so is it in the doctrine of
the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> lesse meritorious in it selfe, and in
reason not so exemplar to draw others: Had you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined
to forsake a falshod, and imbrace a trueth
for the meere loue of truth without worldly respects,
men would rather haue inclined to thinke that true
which you had imbraced; had you hoped to rise
higher, and liue longer, and yet not held your life or
hope of honor deare; in regard of that future life and
glory which you hoped for by the change of your
<pb n="30" facs="17"/>
Religion, you might sooner haue induced others to
follow your steps: but for a man so ambitious as your
selfe, by your owne acknowledgement, who by stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
against the streame, had put himselfe not onely
out of hope of rising higher; but almost out of breath
to, and all hope of liuing much longer, to seeke that
name and fame in dying abroad, which he saw could
not bee gotten by liuing at home; it may perhaps
worke somewhat with those who iudge of matters
onely by euents, as <hi>Geometricians</hi> measure the height
of towres by their shadowes, and are ready to turne
euery accident to an argument for their owne purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses;
but such as iudge of euents by looking into their
causes (which not many loue much to busie their
braines about, nor are indeed capable of) and frame
not arguments to their opinions; but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
submit their opinions to the sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
and force of argument; such I
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ay, I am sure it cannot
much moue.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>