<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE LORD MAIOR OF THE CITIE of London, and to the right worshipfull his bre∣thren, the Aldermen of the same Citie, Thomas Nelson wisheth happines in this life with increase of honour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103524_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14922</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18422.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103524</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE LORD MAIOR OF THE CITIE of London, and to the right worshipfull his bre∣thren, the Aldermen of the same Citie, Thomas Nelson wisheth happines in this life with increase of honour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blessed state of England : Declaring the sundrie dangers vvhich by Gods assistance, the Queenes most excellent Maiestie hath escaped in the whole course of her life. With her singular vertues and peaceable gouernment. Wherein is also shewed how greatly foraine nations doe admire and wonder thereat, together with the rare titles of commendation which the great emperor of the Turkes lately sent in his letters to her highnesse</title>
                 <author>Nelson, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Wright, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE LORD MAIOR OF THE CITIE <hi>of London, and to the right worshipfull his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the Aldermen of the same Citie, Thomas Nelson wisheth happines in this life with increase of honour.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Alling to minde (right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and VVorshipfull) the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold blessings which it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed almightie God to bestowe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this realme of Englande, wherein he hath not only placed his most sacred &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worde, but also giuen vs a most gracious, vertuous and peerelesse princes, the queens most excellent Maiestie, to be the defender and supporter of the same: who by hir sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular wisedom together with hir godly care and Christian gouernment, this land is bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with an vnspeakeable peace and plenty. VVhich great &amp; vnspeakable blessings, whē I had thorowly considered and plainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued that this lande onely inioyeth them for hir highnes sake, whom he hath wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="3"/>defended from the wicked practises and intentes of sundrie her enemies. I tooke vpon me to publish this short and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Discourse, partly to make knowne to all hir maiesties well disposed subiectes, the louing kindnes of almightie God towards hir, the loue and affection which forreine princes beare hir, and how much the verie heathen do admire at hir proceedings, and therewithall, giuing hir such honorable and due titles of commendatiōs as neuer prince nor potentate hath had the like. This Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, right Honorable and VVorshipfull, although I haue not handled it so rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally as many more learneder than my selfe, might haue performed it, yet I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech your Lordship and VVorships to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it in good sort at my hands as it is, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my selfe wholy to your graue censures, who I trust will wey my well meaning in the ballance of your accustomed curtesies. For whom I hartely pray vnto God to send you a happie and prosperous newe yeare &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to his good pleasure.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>