<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE TRANSLATOR To the Reader.</title>
           <author>T., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103512_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02320</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12452</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103512</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE TRANSLATOR To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>T., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The letters of Mounsieur de Balzac. Translated into English, according to the last edition. By W.T. Esq</title>
                 <author>Balzac, Jean-Louis Guez, seigneur de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 <publisher>Clutterbuck (Clotterbuck), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 80, 83-401, that is 410, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>THE TRANSLATOR To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout fiue yeeres since, I chanced to peruse Mounsieur <hi>Balzac's</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (they being then as I suppose) but lately come forth in <hi>French▪</hi> and as it should seeme without the Authours approbation: For of eight Editions in seuerall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, since published, this onely being the last, I was by him auowed. Hauing therefore seene this Coppy, was so farre from supposing it vnworthy the reading, as (on the contrary) finding his stile right eloquent, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnafected, his conceptions high, and the whole Booke richly adorned with great varietie of learning, appearing almost in euery Page: It raised no small desire in mee to try how his way of writing would sute with our language: I thought therefore good (as my occasions would permit, now and then for my priuate recreation) to translate certaine of his Letters, without any the least intention
<pb facs="12"/>
to put them all into English, much lesse to publish them: But hauing once begun, I found my selfe so taken with the freeedome of his discourse, together with the facil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of his expressions; and so surunded with the torrent of his witt, that though I had small hopes of wading safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through, notwithstanding it seemed euen delightfull vnto mee to bee drenched in so rich so pleasing, and so plentifull a flood, yet after diuers attempts, I at last ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued on drie land, resoluing to rest my selfe after these labours, and in priuate to inioy the content I tooke in hearing Mounsieur <hi>Balzac</hi> speake, though but broken English. But I was not long left in peace with this reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, before certaine my noble friends vnderstanding I had traualled on this subiect; did importunately so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licite me to put these Letters into Print, perswading me I should here in performe no vnacceptable seruice to my Countrey, especially to such who are vnacquainted with the French Language. Their power therefore ouer-ruling my bashfullnesse, though otherwise seconding my willing desire to bee vsefull; I held it lesse faultie to incur the hazard of publike censure, then to bee taxed of wilfull inciuillitie. So as (worthy Reader) I haue here expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them to thy view; If the coursnesse of the English ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit wherein I haue clad them, seeme vnsutable to their French attyre, or vnfashionable in thy sight: Consider I beseech thee, that beautifull creatures are not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blemished, though but plainely attyred. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you please so farre to fauour mee, as to excuse these my errours, I will herafter endeauour to become more seruiceable. You will happily not here find all <hi>Balzac's</hi> Letters Englished; yea and diuers clauses left out; the
<pb facs="12"/>
onely reason hath beene, their subiect not altogether su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to this State, nor very fitting for English eares. The rest are here presented to thy gratious accetpance, not doubting but they will prooue both pleasing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to diuers who endeauour to make right vse there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. My desires haue aimed at that end; and my greatest ambition is to haue them find courteous enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement, and to afford Publique Vtillitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Vale. VV. T.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>