<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S103111_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01752</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11884</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S103111</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvver to the deuillish detection of Stephane Gardiner, Bishoppe of Wynchester : published to the intent that such as be desirous of the truth should not be seduced by hys errours, nor the blind [et] obstinate excused by ignorance Compiled by. A.G</title>
                 <author>Gilby, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                    <distributor>Day, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>lxxii, lxxii-clxxxxix, clxxxxii-ccx, that is ccxi 6 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="ii" facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>DEarely beloued (bought wyth the same bloude, and therfore parte ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the same kyngedome) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Lorde oure God is the God of knowledge, and wyll haue suche ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauntes as by knowledge in trueth wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fleshely fantasies, either of fained god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or any fonde worship of mans madde brayne (who alwaies from the beginneinge hath renne after vanities) wyll be radie to geue answere of their faieth in him, the God of lyfe and of the hope conceiued by his one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly worde: it becometh all his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o labour for knowledge, that they maye walke vpright in the waie of their Lorde, and by no halting ignoraunce to slide furth of the same and so to prouoke his worthi displeasure. And as he is the God of loue, peace, vnitie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, and will haue vs al tied together with the bonde of loue and made therby (in hym) all one bodie: so doeth it become vs wyth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen hertes, wythout all doublenesse, one to enstructe an other, to the edifiynge of oure brethern, that in sure grownded fayth we maye loue together and so enioye the hope of our vocacion. Therfore, though mi talent bee verie smal and no principall gifte either of eloquence or learninge, but onely a loue of the trueth geuen vnto me, yet seinge the
<pb facs="3"/>
worlde is so blinded with Idolatrie, and so beewitched with popishe sophistrie, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen nowe the spirittes and powers of darck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes worcke the chiefe mysterie of iniquitie and wickednesse, to set vp and maintaine the moste weake Idole that euer was in the worlde, in the steade of the most mightie and euerliuinge God: I coulde thincke it no lesse thē my most bounden dutie, openly to beare wittnesse vnto the truthe. And where as the wordes of truth, haue bene slandrously and spitfully named the saieinges of the deuil by the spiritual crafte of a souldiour of Sathā, which by painted wordes woulde transform him self into an angel of lyght. Whose boke is spred euerie where, and receiued in manie places more reuerentlie then the blessed bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the holie worde of God. Yet no mā hath (so farre as I know) once opened his mouth or taken penne in hand, to make answere to this blasphemouse messenger of the proude Senacherib neglectinge the liueinge God, for the littel I dole that he maketh God or no God at hys pleasure, who suffreth Mise to eate him and the wicked to deuoure him. Lette all other men do as they shall thyncke good, wyth silence to let suche thynges slip. Truly if I coulde saye nothinge thereunto but onely naye, denienge Idolatrie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncynge
<pb n="iij" facs="3"/>
all supersticion therin maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: I iudge it my parte to publishe my faith, rather then by my silence to seame to consent to suche diuillishe doctrine. So also do I esteme it the dutie of the faithful in this perillous tyme, plainely to professe the Lord the liueuinge God, to be the onely God in heauen a boue and in the erth beneth: leste bi our silence for sakinge hys cause here vpon erth, we be forsaken in his heauenly palace. For lyke as in herte we do beleue to oure rightuousnes: so must we necessarily confesse to oure saluacion, as Paule teachethe. <note place="margin">ii. Corh. xi.</note>
   </p>
   <p>We must beware (as Paule warnethe, and the bishope taketh the same text) first of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>al, that our senses be not corrupted from the simplicite and sing lenesse that is in Christe, as the serpent begiled Eua. We knowe but one God. We are maried vnto one. We knowe but one Christ made man and none o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther creature for ourcause. This thing as we beleue it in herte: so muste we in mouth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse the same, if we wyll walke in the simpli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citie and sing linesse that is in Christe, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh christians. For if the hert and mouth go together, then is it sing lenesse, otherwise it is doublenesse and dissembling. But there is one other simplicitie (as it hath bene comp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, &amp; as the worde hath bene abused) which
<pb facs="4"/>
is verie folishnes. This maye we cal the sim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plicitie, that Antichriste woulde haue styl to reigne amonge vs, and therefore his champi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, when he brought in the texte of Paulle: lefte out the principall wordes (Que est in christo) Whyche is in Christe, as their olde texte hath it. And thorowe out hys whole boke, he woulde driue vs to be simple. That is to saye, to folowe as we be led like blinde men: that the proude papisticall prelates, still leadeinge vs into the pitte of perdicion, abuseing our wines and goodes, maye saye in their connentes. Let them alone, let them offer still vnto Imeages, a pice of bread or any thinge else of a good intent, all is well done that is done of a good intent,</p>
   <p>They maye worship a stocke or a stone, let them folow their auncient fathers. They are good simple soules. They do as we and oure doctours teach thē. If we let thē knowe al trueth: they wilbe as wise as we, and then they wyll smally regarde vs. Thys is their workeinge, these are their wordes, howe so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they haue clok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d hertofore, all the worde nowe seeth it. Let vs beware therfore, of this thir simplicitie, and let vs no longer thynke that this their doctrine is'true, that al should he well done that is done for a good intent, and that it is well done in all thinges to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue
<pb n="iiij" facs="4"/>
theyr doctours. For this ignorante opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that thei haue grounded in their hertes hath hitherto stopped the waie to all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and nowe letteth faith to be grounded and causeth men to continew styll in their olde errowres, wythout any desire to come out of blindnesse. Consider therefore (good reader) a gaynste their blinde lessons: that Saull was caste from hys kyngedome, for his good intent, euen because he intended to do sacrifice vnto the Lorde, of the best and fatteste of the Amalechites. And yet maye thys seme a gloriouse intent.</p>
   <p>The bishoppes of the Iewes and the I<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dolatours of al ages folowed theyr good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: euen when they put Christ and all hys prophetes and Apostles to death. The by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Norwich when he burned pore Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, folowed his good intent our other by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopes also, burneninge and murtheringe theyr bretherne in prisone and out of prisone: folowed theyr good in tentes, But God is the iudge of the intētes and thoughtes of vs al, and sercheth the verie raine and the holes of our hertes. Yea the lord our god abhorreth and the prophetes reproue vs alwayes: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we wyll do euerie man that semeth good in his owne eies</p>
   <p>Sayth not the Lorde by hys prophet E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saye.
<pb facs="5"/>
Myne intentes are not your in entēs, and mi wayes are not your wayes. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o, so farre as the heauen is from the erthe, so high are my wayes aboue your waies, and mine intentes aboue your intentes. For the beliefe of their doctours and the prelates of the churche (which thinge the bishoppe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth alwaies to establish) remembre that Christe saith, if the blynde leade the blynde: boeth fal into the pitte. And thou must doub tlesse cōmpt their writtinges euē verie blind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, in regarde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of the light of goddes moste certaine worde which must be the rule of thi life, the foūdacion of thy fayth, and the light vnto thy feete. As for theyr auncientie: be sure to take Christ for they guide, who was before all. And saye with S. Paule, fayth is of heariuge, not of the worde of any mā: but of the worde of God.</p>
   <p>Therefore saieth God the father with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen voice from heauen. This is my dearely beloued sonne in whom is my delight, heare you hym.</p>
   <p>Now if any be so fainte herted and so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded by other, that they thyncke they maye still disseinble wyth the hypocrites in their owtwarde doetnges: I sende them to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emple of Daniel, who praied with opē win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and (wyth his three companions) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused
<pb n="v" facs="5"/>
to honour the golden Image, &amp; would not dissemble outwarde worship, nother con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent them selues with the purenesse of theyr owne hertes (thoughe they myght therby haue escaped the fire) consideringe that the glorie of God coulde not be so fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dered, but rather hindered by theyr walkeinge in the waye of the wicked. Therfore saieth the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet Dauid. Happie is he that nether stādeth sitteth nor walketh (that is to saye) hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge <note place="margin">Psal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> to do wyth them, other openly or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily, by any colour or dissimulacion.</p>
   <p>Eliazar had such like counsell of hys fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, that he shoulde eate fleshe onely whiche <note place="margin">ii. Mach. vii.</note> was lawfull, and dissemble to eate the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull. But he saide it was not lawfull for him to dissemble, and so cause many to be de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiued through his hipocrisie: for so he might escape the death of the body, but the hand of God he could not auoide. For this cause did Paule reproue Peter for his dissemblinge be fore the gentiles. And he teacheth the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians <note place="margin">Galat. ii.</note> againe, that there is no companie of light and darckenesse, no dessemblinge to be partaker boeth of the cup of Christe and of deuilles.</p>
   <p>Oure membres must be the weapons ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of rightuousenes, other else of vnright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuousenesse, there is no meane for styll and
<pb facs="6"/>
ware politicke persons. And therfore sayeth our maister Christ, he that is not with me is againste me. And he that doeth not gather, doeth scatter. These wordes of Christe and suche like, and none other cause (whatsoeuer any man shall imagine) haue compelled me to publish my fayth, and in the name of the liueinge God, to make answere to one boke, whiche of all other I estemed most perilouse and poysonful, boeth for the authorite of the writter, and the subtile handellinge of hys mattier in the maytaineinge of that Idole, which al the worlde hath worshipped so ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny yeres. The name of the boke is the detec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the diuillysh sophistrie. The authour that made it is Stephaue Gardiner, bishop of Winchester, the chiefe mantainer of the popeishe tradicions, as appeareth by al hys dedes &amp; writinges. How I haue vsed my self in the same: I shall shewe at fewe wordes.</p>
   <p>Because I did take vpon hande to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute his boke: I coulde kepe no comely order but as the wordes do leade me, so am I com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pelled to go forwarde. Yet haue I not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hys whole texte in my boke (because it woulde▪ haue ben to much tediouse and ouer longe but onely his▪ chiefe, mattier and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall argumentes, whereof I truste not one hath escaped vntouched. I lest of the residue,
<pb n="vi" facs="6"/>
thinkeing it a verie vaine thinge to contende about trifles, as I should haue done of neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, in waigheinge euerie worde and ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe euerie sentence. The boke is so farre spred a broabe, that I can not belie hym but it shalbe a witnesse againste me, in euerie cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. For it was plentuousely imprinted by Iohn Herforde in aldergate strete at Lōdon, and is to be solde at the signe of the bell in poules church yarde. I haue principally and chiefe laboured to establishe the true fayeth in the liueinge God: by the reproueinge of the false and fained goodes. Secōdly, I haue taught the trwe vnderstandinge of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the supper of the Lorde, and the right vse of the same. Whiche two my chiefe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses howe faithfully I haue done them: the fathfull shall iudge, knowynge the voice of of theyr shepeherde.</p>
   <p>In mine answere to his wordes, I truste no man shalbe offended with any vnchrist an rayleinges, though great accasiō be offerred on his parte, bringeinge our argumentes so spitfully in the name of deuill, with yea, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the deuell, as though the deuell where a destroier of Idoles, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e onely hath bene theyr mainetainer and vpholder, from the be geninge of the worlde vnto this daye. Yet I do thynke nothynge lesse, then to satisfie all
<pb facs="7"/>
men wyth my writtinges, more then other haue done before mi time, with theirs, much more wittie, more lerned and godly. No, I do suppose, the hight lerned maye finde many fautes there'with, as I▪ acknowledge mi self far vnder the perfection of theyr high ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge. Neuerthelesse, I trust in God that it is not all together so rude nor vnfruitfull: but that the vnlerned (for whome it is chiefe lie written) shall encrease bi it in knowledge, caste of much supersticion, and take conforte of conscience. Whome also I beseche, euen for the loue▪ of God, and▪ as they tender their soules health: not to caste awaye this boke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they reade somethinge therin that they neuer harde before, but rather desire of theire moste mercifull father, that theyr olde errours wherwith they haue bene deceiued by blind teachers, maie be taken awaye. And if there be any that can not sodaineli caste of the olde skine wyth the serpent and forsak theyre olde ignoraunce cōfirmed with longe custome: let thē desir of God so much grace that they maye more quietlie then hath ben accustomed, heare men talke of the fayth they haue conceiued in the liueinge God. For than shal it be wel with the christian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: whē the one parte maie boldelie, and wyll redily gyue answere of the hope they
<pb n="vii" facs="7"/>
haue conceiued, and faith whereby thei trust to be saued, and the other parte wyll mekeli heare what is spoken, and quietely suffer the lambes to feede of their swete pasturs. So shall the prophecie be fulfilled. The lambe shal lodge with the woulfe, the leoparde and <note place="margin">Esaye. xi.</note> the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e shal lie together. The calfe, the lion and the shepe shall dwell together, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle childe shalbe their herde and driue them, which thinge I trust partely shall be fullfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in oure tyme vnder our little Iosias, to whom God graunt the abundaunce of hys grace. And most fully vnder the true Iosias Christe Iesu our sauiour, who onelye is the ende of all prophecies, in whome they al are made perfecte, with whome we shall enioye this perfecte peace, so many as defire to knowe the liuinge God, and whome he sent downe to saue the worlde Iesu Christ, nowe sitting at his right hande, to whome be glorie For euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. So be it</p>
   <epigraph>
      <bibl>Iohn. iiii. Episto. i.</bibl>
      <q>Who so knoweth God heareth vs. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> he that is not of God heareth not vs. And herby do we know, the spirite of truthe, and the spirite of errowre.</q>
   </epigraph>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>