<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104976_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18729</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5226</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104976</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse of the Queenes Maiesties entertainement in Suffolk and Norffolk : with a description of many things then presently seene. Deuised by Thomas Churchyarde, Gent. with diuers shewes of his own inuention sette out at Norwich: and some rehearsal of hir Highnesse retourne from progresse. Wherevnto is adioyned a commendation of Sir Humfrey Gilberts ventrous iourney</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I shoulde not good
Reader as vvell shevve
thee some matter of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light,
as publishe to the
vvorld these penned dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses,
thy vvits vvould
vvaxe a vveery of my
friuolous vvordes, and
I should gaine but little
frute by my labour and
trauell: and greater delight can not be presented,
than heere to shevv thee the good disposition of
some people, bredde vp, and nourished out of
the bovvels of thine ovvne nation. And albeit it
seemeth strange, that people nurtured farre from
Courte, shoulde vse muche courtesie, yet vvill I
prooue by the humblenesse of the common
people, vvhere lately the Prince hath passed, that
if in a manner all ciuilitie vvere vtterly decayed, it
might haue bin found freshly florishing in many
of those parties and places specifyed before: for
so soone as the presence of the Prince vvas en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
in their boundes, by a meere motion of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
and fealty, a generall consent of duetie and
obediēce vvas seene thorough the vvhole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,
and vvell vvere they that might first find oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
by any meanes to vvelcome a Courtier,
<pb facs="6"/>
and not vvith feyned ceremonies, but vvith friēd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
entertaynemente. And although it be a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome,
and most laudable manner for the poore
commons to runne in flockes to see their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,
yet there, as me thought, their desire vvas
so greate, that they hadde neuer ynough of the
sight so long vvished and desired: and such reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
and humilitie they vsed tovvardes all the
trayne, vvheresoeuer they encountred anye of
them, that the invvarde affections of the people
vvas playnely expressed by their outvvard appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
and manifest curtesies: in so much, that the
meanest persons that follovved the Court, stood
maruellously contented vvith that they savv, and
vvondered at the rare &amp; good maner of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
especially in Norvvich, vvhere the entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente
vvas so greate, that all degrees, from the
highest to the lovvest, vvere had in such admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
that it seemed another vvorlde to beholde:
vvhich nevve kinde of reuerence, and comely cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome
of the Countrey (as it may be properly
applyed) makes the old haughtinesse, and stiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked
behauiour of some places, to blushe, and
become odious, yea in soyles, that the Prince ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
keepeth hir residence, &amp; most abode in,
vvhere proude people vvill passe by many of the
Nobilitie, vvithoute mouing eyther cappe or
knee, a stubborne stoutenesse, and an vnmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="6"/>
disordered boldnesse, bredde vp and fostered
on the long familiaritie had vvith the noble mens
seruants, and dayly vievv of their maisters, vvith
vvhiche sighte they are so cloyed and vveeryed,
that theyr duetie is forgotten, and vtterly reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
that ought to be ashamed of abuse, and
shoulde vse more reuerente manners. If they
vvould (to leaue off thys audacious fashion) but
looke on dyuers Sheeres in this lande, as Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casheere,
Chesheere, Shropsheere, and other
Sheeres farre from the Court, they might soone
bee learned to clappe on more comelynesse,
and vse lesse obstinacie. And if they thynke
scorne to bee taughte at home of oure ovvne
people, it vvere good they vvere Shipped into
Fraunce or Flaunders, oure neere neyboures,
vvhere the meaner sorte are not onely knovven
by theyr garmentes and goyng, but perceyued
by theyr gestures, and humblenesse of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce
and speeche. Novve gentle Reader,
thynke no other of thys my discourse in the
commendation of courtesie, but that I reioyce
to see suche auntiente humilitie as yet helde vp
and mainteyned in Englande, vvhen pride and
vayneglory vvoulde ouerthrovve the good
dispositions of the people, and breede both
to GOD and Man a common contempte.
And, as I haue rehearsed a peece of those
<pb facs="7"/>
thinges I savve in Suffolke and Norffolke, to
further thy delight tovvards the reading of my
simple Booke, so looke for presentlye at my
handes the rest of that Progresse vvhiche I am
truely instructed of, or may come to my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie.
Thus committing to thy handes and
head the boldnesse of my enterprise, and
vievv of those Verses and matter
I heere haue sette out.
I bid thee fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvell.</p>
   <trailer type="illustration">
      <figure>
</figure>
   </trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>