<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104781_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16742</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3649</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104781</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An excellent poeme, vpon the longing of a blessed heart : which loathing the world, doth long to be with Christ. With an addition, vpon the definition of loue. Compiled by Nicholas Breton, Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Bradock, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Browne, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Deane, John</publisher>
                            <distributor>Browne, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Deane, John</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F you loue your selfe, or like to bee loued, it were good, you did first know what loue is; where it is to be sought; and how to be had: which in this little lesson following, you may happe to hit on. For if you mistake the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as many haue done, that set their wittes a woll-gathering, vpon the backe of a Woodcocke, in thinking loue to be either nothing, or at least as little worth; or such a kinde of Riddle as is scarcely worth the reading: you may happe either neuer finde what it is, repent the seeking, or not care for the hauing of it; or standing in your owne light, be but little beloued for your lost labour. But, if with the eye of a carefull heart, you will looke into the loue of the soule, there I would be glad to see you longing, and wish you (hauing not to trouble you with more words then matter) the loue of God, you to loue me as I doe you, and God to loue vs all: and so I end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, in the loue of charitie, Nicholas Breton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>