<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A PREMONITION to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104244_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03751</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13871</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104244</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A PREMONITION to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A patterne of Christian loyaltie : vvhereby any prudent man may clearely perceive, in what manner the new Oath of Allegiance, and every clause thereof, may in a true, and catholike sense, without danger of perjury, be taken by Roman Catholikes. And all the chiefe objections, which are usually made against the said Oath, either in particular, or in generall, may according to the grounds of Catholike religion bee easily answered. Collected out of authours, who have handled the whole matter more largely. By William Hovvard an English Catholike</title>
                 <author>Preston, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 61, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="1" facs="5"/>
   <head>A PREMONITION to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is one thing <hi>(Courteous Reader)</hi> which I wish thee <hi>first</hi> of all to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, to wit, what great disagreement there is among the learneder sort of our
<hi>English Catholikes,</hi> by whom the lesse learned are for the most part guided, in their opinions concerning the <hi>new Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance.</hi> For <hi>some</hi> condemne it for altogether unlawfull, nor to be taken with a safe conscience by any good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.
<hi>Others</hi> approve it for lawfull, and to containe nothing besides a profession of true
<hi>temporall</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, and therefore not to bee refused by any good Subject. A
<hi>third</hi> sort there is, who carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves <hi>negatively,</hi> and in expresse words wil neither approve it, nor condemne it, but leave every man to his owne conscience, which in very deed is to any ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious man, all circumstances considered, a <hi>tacit</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving thereof.</p>
   <p>Those who condemne it, are of <hi>two</hi> sorts, the <hi>one</hi> extreamely violent, and are not afraid to taxe those Catholikes who approve it, of flat <hi>heresie,</hi> and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="6"/>them no true <hi>Catholikes,</hi> but rather <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes,</hi> falsly pretending, That the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>depose Princes,</hi> is by all learned and good Catholikes a confessed and undoubted point of <hi>Catholike</hi> faith; That his power to
<hi>Excommunicate,</hi> and to <hi>absolve</hi> from <hi>Oaths</hi> in generall is denied in the
<hi>Oath:</hi> And that the <hi>King,</hi>
      <note place="margin">See these ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, nu 7.11.17.</note> and <hi>Parliament</hi> doe take upon them in this <hi>Oath</hi> the
<hi>Churches</hi> authority to <hi>define</hi> matters of <hi>Faith.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Others</hi> there be who are not so violent, but much misliking the former objections, they chiefly except against the <hi>Second,</hi> and <hi>Fourth</hi> Clause, how any man can truly sweare, <hi>That the</hi> Pope <hi>hath not any power to depose the</hi> King,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> seeing that he hath at the least a <hi>probable</hi> power to
<hi>depose</hi> him: and consequently how any man can truly abjure, as <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> and
<hi>hereticall</hi> this doctrine, and position, <hi>That Princes which be deprived by the</hi> Pope,<note place="margin">See these, and others answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nu. 9.13.14.</note>
      <hi>may be deposed by their Subjects, or any other,</hi> seeing that it is at the least a
<hi>probable</hi> doctrine, it being approved by the <hi>Pope</hi> himselfe, and by many other most learned Catholike <hi>Divines.</hi> And against the <hi>Oath</hi> in generall they urge, That our supreme <hi>spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> Pastor hath forbidden it,<note place="margin">See these an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, nu. 26.32.39.</note> That to <hi>take</hi> it, is <hi>scandalous,</hi> and that to
<hi>refuse</hi> it, is the <hi>safer way.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now when I perceived the best learned <hi>Priests</hi> of our Nation to disagree so much in their opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this great, and dangerous controversie of the <hi>Oath</hi> betwixt the <hi>Popes Holinesse,</hi> and the <hi>Kings Majestie,</hi> the one by his
<hi>constitutive</hi> precept <hi>first</hi> commanding it under the penalty of a
<hi>Praemunire,</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>supposing it to containe nothing but true <hi>temporall</hi> Allegiance, the other by his <hi>declarative</hi> Breves for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding it, as containing <hi>many things plainely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to faith and salvation,</hi> and that both their commandements could not be obeyed, being opposits one to the other: And considering with my selfe <hi>first,</hi> that I must needs incurre either <hi>spirituall</hi> disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by not obeying the
<hi>Pope,</hi> if his commandement were just, or, if otherwise, <hi>temporall</hi> disloyaltie by disobeying the <hi>King;</hi> and that, according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon doctrine of
<hi>Divines</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">See beneath, num. 26.</note>, the <hi>constitutive</hi> precept of a lawfull <hi>Superiour</hi> must be obeyed, unlesse it be clearely
<hi>unjust,</hi> according to that which shall be said beneath<note n="b" place="margin">num
3c.</note>: <hi>Secondly,</hi> that both the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> may sometimes erre in their <hi>Iudgements,</hi> and <hi>command</hi> that which is <hi>not just,</hi> for that their <hi>judgements are not alwayes grounded upon truth</hi>
      <note n="c" place="margin">Can. <hi>A nobis</hi> de <hi>sent. Excom.</hi> cap. 28.</note>, <hi>which never deceiveth, nor is deceived, but sometimes they follow opinion, which may often-times deceive, and be deceived: Thirdly,</hi> that I could not therefore be secure in conscience, by obeying either the <hi>Popes</hi> commandement against the <hi>Kings,</hi> or contrariwise, with <hi>blinde obedience,</hi> lest blinded with wilfull ignorance I should <hi>fall into the ditch</hi>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> either of <hi>spirituall,</hi> or of <hi>temporall</hi> disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, by not examining with <hi>judgement</hi> of discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which of their
<hi>commandements</hi> is just, and therefore to be obeyed, and that my owne <hi>conscience</hi> must be to mee the inward <hi>judge</hi> of all my actions, and omissions.</p>
   <p>And <hi>lastly,</hi> that I could not secure my <hi>conscience,</hi>
      <pb facs="7"/>by giving credit only to those, who <hi>write,</hi> and plead in favour of the
<hi>Pope</hi> against the <hi>King,</hi> without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and examining what they who write, and plead for the <hi>King,</hi> doe answer in his defence, or contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, considering that both of them may relate each others reasons, and answers falsly, lamely, or corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that in a controversie, betwixt <hi>two</hi> parties he cannot be accounted an upright
<hi>judge,</hi> who will heare, reade, and examine the reasons, answers, and allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the one side, or of the other, only in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as it shall please the <hi>adverse part</hi> to propound them for his owne advantage, and that therefore to forbid any man, who is to be a <hi>judge</hi> in a controversie betwixt <hi>two parties</hi> (as in the Court of
<hi>Penance,</hi> every <hi>Ghostly Father</hi> is to be a <hi>judge</hi> of whatsoever his
<hi>Penitent</hi> shall confesse unto him, and in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Court of <hi>Conscience</hi> every private man is to be his owne <hi>judge</hi>) to reade, heare, and understand the reasons, and answers of either side, but only in that manner as his <hi>Adversary</hi> shall propound them, is in very deed no other, than to forbid him to be an <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Iudge.</hi> All which considered, to informe my <hi>conscience</hi> uprightly in this dangerous controversie of the <hi>Oath,</hi> not betwixt <hi>two inferiour parties,</hi> or betwixt the
<hi>Defendant,</hi> or party sued, and the <hi>judge,</hi> but betweene <hi>two supreme,</hi> and independent <hi>judges</hi> in their degree, the one in <hi>spiritualls,</hi> the other in
<hi>temporalls,</hi> contending whether this <hi>new Oath,</hi> which the <hi>one</hi> commandeth, and the <hi>other</hi> forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, be a <hi>temporall,</hi> or a <hi>spirituall</hi> thing, containe a profession of true <hi>temporall</hi> Allegiance, or a deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="7"/>of true <hi>spirituall</hi> obedience, I thought it not se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure for me, to rely upon the bare relation, and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation either of the one side only, or of the other.</p>
   <p>Whereupon to finde out the truth herein according to the capacity of my understanding, and to frame my conscience accordingly, I have diligently read, and examined what bookes soever have been published, as well against the <hi>Oath</hi> in favour of the <hi>Pope,</hi> as for it in the <hi>Kings</hi> defence. And I confesse ingenuously, that those which have beene written in favour of the <hi>Oath,</hi> and of Soveraigne <hi>Princes</hi> not to be deposed much lesse to be <hi>murdered,</hi> or <hi>killed</hi> by the <hi>Popes</hi> authority (which is the only principall thing denied therin) have given me ful satisfaction in this point, out of which I have at sundry vacant times, to helpe the weaknesse of my memory, collected the
<hi>Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and <hi>Observations</hi> following, which because they doe clearely convince my understanding, and may perchance give the like satisfaction to others, and also stirre up some, who are more learned than I am, to defend their <hi>Princes</hi> right, being assaulted by such powerfull <hi>Adversaries,</hi> I thought it necessary for divers reasons to propound them to the publike view of the world, to have them examined by learned
<hi>Divines,</hi> as well in regard of mine owne good, as of the good of others: especially seeing that but few of our English <hi>Priests</hi> among so many, who in their conscience approve the <hi>Oath,</hi> dare for some world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly respects make knowne their minds herein but only to some of their trusty friends, because, as some of them who favour the
<hi>Oath,</hi> have said to me in plain
<pb facs="8"/>termes, the misery of these times is such, that by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or publikely approving the <hi>Oath,</hi> and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Kings</hi> soveraigne right in
<hi>temporalls</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst such violent opposers thereof, they shall gaine little or nothing, in comparison of that, which they shall lose thereby. So that many <hi>Lay Catholikes</hi> are in daily hazard to lose their whole estates (which is a pitifull thing) for want of being instructed by these men for worldly ends, in this controversie of the
<hi>Oath,</hi> which they in their owne conscience thinke to be very lawfull.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>One reason</hi> therefore, for which I thought it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to publish these briefe <hi>Explications</hi> of the <hi>Oath,</hi> is the great griefe I have to see some few of our English <hi>Priests</hi> both <hi>Secular,</hi> and <hi>Religious,</hi> now lately to revive againe this scandalous contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie (which for diverse yeares hath here through silence, and connivence been well appeased, and to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose themselves most vehemently against the <hi>Oath,</hi> though not by publike writings to satisfie our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings, yet by seeking to draw us to embrace their opinions against it by violence, and terrours, in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to make a <hi>Schisme</hi> among us, and to exclude us from the holy
<hi>Sacraments,</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiasticall</hi> communion, only for <hi>our opinions</hi> (as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves call it) <hi>of the Oath,</hi> against the knowne pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of many learned, and vertuous <hi>Priests,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the rest their last <hi>Arch-Priest,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Doctour <hi>Harrison,</hi> as diverse letters of his written to one of his
<hi>Assistants</hi> (which are yet extant) can give suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient testimony. But if these men had well observed,
<pb facs="8"/>in what manner Saint <hi>Austin</hi> writeth against the <hi>Donatists,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>S.</hi> Aug. <hi>Epht. 48 ad</hi> Vincent. &amp; de Bapt. <hi>contra</hi> Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist.</note> for their breach of <hi>Ecclesiasticall</hi> unity, and in commendation and excuse of Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> (who although he opposed himselfe vehemently against Pope
<hi>Stephen</hi> in the question of <hi>Baptisme</hi> admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred by <hi>Heretikes,</hi> yet they (till kept <hi>Ecclesiasticall</hi> communion with each other) doubtlesse they would have beene fearefull to have proceeded against their <hi>Catholike</hi> brethren with so little charity, but would have remembred that saying of Saint <hi>Austin,</hi>
      <note place="margin">S.
<hi>Aug.</hi> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>b 3. de <hi>Bapt</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra
<hi>Donat.</hi> 16.</note> that <hi>those men have not charity,</hi> or the <hi>love of God, who love not the unity of the Church,</hi> but feare not to make a breach thereof onely for their
<hi>opinions,</hi> and which for <hi>undoubted</hi> Doctrines <hi>of faith,</hi> they will needs obtrude not onely upon the unlearned, but also upon those who are as learned as themselves.</p>
   <p>An <hi>other reason</hi> is, the great pitty I have to see some <hi>Catholikes</hi> of good account, now lately, by the bad counsell of their <hi>Instructours</hi> under a false pretence of <hi>Catholike faith</hi> cast themselves headlong into manifest danger, not onely of a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> to the beggering of themselves, their wives, and children, but also of their <hi>soules</hi> (if ignorance doe not excuse them) by disobeying the just commandement of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <hi>Prince</hi> in point of their loyalty, and due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and giving thereby no small occasion to <hi>His Majestie</hi> to be scandalized at our Religion, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it a nourisher of disloyaltie, and all us <hi>Roman Catholikes</hi> to be disloyall Subjects, if the contrarie were not by some of us made manifest unto him. And is it not a lamentable case, and able to move a stony
<pb facs="9"/>heart to teares, that wee <hi>Lay Catholikes,</hi> whom this <hi>Oath</hi> doth chiefly concerne (for <hi>Priests</hi> can loose little, or nothing by refusing it, being subject to greater penalties, then is a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> although by perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding others to refuse it, because the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>practise</hi> the deposition of <hi>Princes</hi> is denied therein, they may perchance incurre greater danger, as liable to suspicion of disposing the Subjects mindes to Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion when time shall serve, as any man of judgement may easily perceive) that we, I say, should by any of our <hi>English priests</hi> (who should rather be a comfort unto us, then add affliction to affliction, knowing the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the lawes, to which we are otherwise subject in regard of our Religion, if <hi>His Majestie</hi> out of his great clemency were not more mercifull unto us) be compelled under paine to be deprived of <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiasticall communion,</hi> to loose all that we have in this world, <hi>liberty, lands,</hi> and <hi>goods</hi> (and which being once lost by their bad counsell, they can never be able to restore to us backe againe) onely for that we cannot be perswaded by them to approve as an <hi>undoubted</hi> doctrine of
<hi>faith,</hi> their <hi>opinion</hi> for the <hi>Popes</hi> power to depose <hi>Princes</hi> (the onely chiefe thing denied in the <hi>Oath</hi>) which in <hi>France</hi> is not permitted to be publikely taught by any of their <hi>Priests</hi> for so much as <hi>probable.</hi>
      <note n="e" place="margin">See the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>,</hi> of the
<hi>parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>parn</hi> 2 Ian. 1615. printed at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> by the <hi>Kings</hi> Printers and in the <hi>French Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> tom. 3 the yeare 16.5. pag. 327.</note>
   </p>
   <p>A <hi>Third reason</hi> is, for that <hi>His Majestie</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving this controversie to be kept still on foote more by <hi>faction,</hi> then by <hi>reason,</hi> and that the
<hi>Pope</hi> will not bee drawne to name any one <hi>particular</hi> thing, which in the
<hi>Oath</hi> is clearely unlawfull, is resolved
<pb facs="9"/>(as I heare) to maintaine his supreme <hi>temporall</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority against all opposers thereof, and that therefore his Subjects should doe well, dutifully to shunne this damnable and seditious doctrine of deposing <hi>Princes</hi> by the <hi>Pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> pretended power which is the maine scope, and substance of this <hi>new Oath</hi> (as both the words thereof doe plainely shew, and also his <hi>Father</hi> of renowned memorie, who was the maker of the law, hath oftentimes declared<note n="f" place="margin">See beneath nu. 3.</note> by publike writings) which opinion is indeed to be abhorred, detested, and abjured by all loyall Subjects in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> no lesse then in <hi>France,</hi> where by many <hi>Decrees</hi> of <hi>Parlaments</hi> it is accounted <hi>false, damnable, seditious,</hi> and bookes written in defence thereof forbidden under paine of <hi>Treason,</hi>
      <note place="margin">See beneath num. 7. and 47</note> and also by a speciall <hi>Censure</hi> of the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon Doctours</hi> (to which <hi>sixteene</hi> French <hi>Iesuites</hi> promised to subscribe) is expresly <hi>condemned, as new, false, erronious, contrary to the word of God</hi> &amp;c.</p>
   <p>The <hi>last reason</hi> is, that great desire I have not to erre through ignorance (for wilfully by <hi>Gods</hi> grace I will never erre) in the least point which may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the
<hi>Catholike faith,</hi> or my duty to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Caesar.</hi> And therefore I would have no man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that I am so audaciously arrogant, as to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me heere to teach learned <hi>Priests,</hi> who ought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct others, their duty, knowing the great weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of my owne learning in comparison of theirs, but rather to bee taught, and instructed by them, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance they shall find me to be in an errour, which as soone as any of them will vouchsafe to make manifest unto me, I promise faithfully to retract the same forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.
<pb facs="10"/>For my onely desire is to informe my conscience rightly, and to give both to the
<hi>Popes Holinesse,</hi> and to the <hi>Kings Majestie,</hi> that <hi>spirituall,</hi> and
<hi>temporall</hi> obedience respectively, which according to the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>grounds</hi> of <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> is due to either of them. But if they will be silent, and not confute with solid reasons the ensuing <hi>Explications</hi> and
<hi>Observations,</hi> and yet will still goe on with their accustomed clamours against the
<hi>Oath,</hi> and the <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> or approvers thereof, all prudent men may well presume, that they are not able to convince me of any <hi>errour</hi> and by their silence I shall be the more confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in my opinion.</p>
   <p>And if their <hi>Answere</hi> shall bee no other, then by labouring (as some of them have lately done) to procure new <hi>Breves,</hi> prohibitions, or Censures onely in
<hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> termes (as the former were) after so many hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Supplications,</hi>
      <note n="g" place="margin">See <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dringtons</hi> Theologicall D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>sputation in the <hi>Epistle,</hi> and the <hi>Conclusion,</hi> his
<hi>Purgation,</hi> and <hi>Sapplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Pope Paul</hi> the Fift. And <hi>Thomas Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone,</hi> and <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Greenes</hi> Supplication to Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the xv.</note> that His <hi>Holinesse</hi> would bee pleased to name some one
<hi>particular</hi> thing of <hi>so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> as the former <hi>Breves</hi> have affirmed, to bee in the <hi>Oath,</hi> and consequently in those <hi>Bookes</hi> which defend it,
<hi>plainly repugnant to faith, and salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> they may well suppose, that those
<hi>Catholikes,</hi> who out of a <hi>pure heart, good conscience,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faigned faith,</hi> or obedience both to their <hi>spirituall Pastour,</hi> and also to their
<hi>temporall Prince,</hi> desire to be assured of the truth in <hi>particular</hi> (for
<hi>generals</hi> being subject to deceit according to that common say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Dolosus versatur in generalibus,</hi> can give them small satisfaction) will not be daunted with such <hi>generall</hi> prohibitions, or Censures in a matter of so great prejudice, unlesse they shall clearely perceive
<pb facs="10"/>them to be agreeable to truth, and justice, they being not ignorant, that according to the common Doctrine of <hi>Divines,</hi>
      <note n="h" place="margin">
         <hi>Navar
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> Enchir.</hi> c. 27. nu. 3. <hi>Cova<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> tom 2. Relect. 1 de <hi>fractis. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragr.</hi> 7. <hi>Suar.</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>isp. 4. de
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>r</hi> see. 7. and other who
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>at
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>s.</note> prohibitions, and Censures, which are unjust, and invalid for want of a just cause, and where there is no <hi>Mortall</hi> sin, doe not bindin conscience, and will more hurt the soules of the procurers then of those, against whom they are unjustly procured.</p>
   <p>Neither can these men bee ignorant, what small account some Catholike <hi>Princes,</hi> and their <hi>Subjects</hi> both in former ages,<note n="i" place="margin">See the
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>testants</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie trac a. see 4.</note> and also in these our times, have made of some <hi>Popes</hi> Breves, Bulls, and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, for that they have supposed them to bee unjust. And besides the late <hi>example</hi> of some the greatest of our <hi>Secular Priests,</hi> in not admitting the <hi>Breves</hi> of this <hi>Popes Holinesse</hi> being prejudiciall to their pretended ends, may bee a fit <hi>President</hi> to us <hi>Lay Catholikes,</hi> not to admit easily, and without due examination such <hi>prohibitions, Breves,</hi> or <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures,</hi> which doe tend to the great prejudice of the <hi>Kings</hi> Majesties <hi>temporall</hi> Soveraigntie, and to the <hi>temporall</hi> ruine of all as his
<hi>Catholike</hi> Subjects.</p>
   <p>Wherefore it were farre more convenient in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, for the publike peace and unity of the
<hi>Church,</hi> for the honour of the <hi>Sea Apostolike,</hi> for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and particular safetie of themselves, and of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others in their soules, bodies, and goods, and for the avoiding of future scandals, and contentions; which may arise betwixt the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and the <hi>Priest-hood</hi> from <hi>new prohibitions,</hi> that these men would be a meanes to procure of <hi>His Holinesse,</hi> that either the former <hi>Breves,</hi> and prohibitions may bee buried with honour in silence, and oblivion, and every man
<pb facs="11"/>left to his owne conscience, or that some <hi>particular</hi> thing in the
<hi>Oath,</hi> which <hi>is plainly repugnant to faith and salvation,</hi> be more expresly declared, that mens minds may not bee troubled, nor the unity of the <hi>Church</hi> distracted, onely for <hi>opinions</hi> in things which may concerne the <hi>temporall</hi> rights of
<hi>Princes,</hi> but that, according to the praier of the holy <hi>Church,</hi>
      <note n="k" place="margin">The <hi>Thurs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> in <hi>Easter</hi> weeke.</note>
      <hi>there may bee one faith of mindes, and piety of actions,</hi> notwithstanding diversitie of <hi>opinions,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<hi>the Church,</hi> which <hi>is the pillar, and ground of truth,</hi>
      <note n="l" place="margin">1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 5. S. <hi>Aug.</hi> l. 1de <hi>Bapt.</hi> contra <hi>Donatist. c.</hi> 18.</note> and is no <hi>partie</hi> in this strife, shall decide the controversie, or, as <hi>S. Austin</hi> speaketh in the excuse of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> untill <hi>by the sentence of a plenarie Councell the consent of the whole Church shall confirme what is to be followed in this matter.</hi> For so long as His <hi>Holinesse</hi> will permit some learned men to write bookes in his behalfe against our <hi>King</hi> in things belonging to his supreme
<hi>temporall</hi> rights (as doth this <hi>new Oath</hi> of Allegiance) no <hi>prohibitions,</hi> or <hi>Censures</hi> can justly hinder, but that his <hi>Catholike</hi> Subjects, both
<hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Lay men,</hi> may also publish in print what may bee answered in the <hi>Kings</hi> defence. To conclude, I make no doubt, but that <hi>Truth</hi> will cause
<hi>hatred,</hi> as <hi>flatterie doth friends,</hi> but withall I am assured, that <hi>Truth is great,</hi>
      <note n="m" place="margin">3. <hi>Esdr.</hi> 4.</note> and <hi>will prevaile</hi> at last, and that <hi>Blessed are they who</hi> in the meane time till it prevaile, <hi>doe s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ffer persecution,</hi> at whose hands soever they suffer it, for truth, <hi>and justice sake,</hi>
      <note n="n" place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.</note>
      <hi>for theirs is the kingdome of heaven.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>