<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE EARLE OF ESSEX, BARON OF EWE: R. A. wisheth all grace with hea∣uen and earth.</title>
           <author>Anton, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104412_Bo1_5_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20460</idno>
           <idno type="STC">686</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104412</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE EARLE OF ESSEX, BARON OF EWE: R. A. wisheth all grace with hea∣uen and earth.</title>
                 <author>Anton, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The philosophers satyrs, written by M. Robert Anton, of Magdelen Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Anton, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 76 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="26"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE EARLE OF ESSEX, BARON OF EWE: <hi>R. A.</hi> wisheth all grace with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth.</head>
   <head type="sub">Of Mars. ♂</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble Lord, <hi>Themistccles</hi> desired the art of obliuion. I the practick of memorie, whose hell and heauen pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentiue facultie cannot produce a fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer forme of eternitie, then in the vnimitable Idea of your Mars borne honourable Father, the best of his fortunes I could wish were traduced to you, and the best of his actions deseruing a fixt constellation, as totally diffused through euery noble veine of your Honour as the best part of your essence is in your bodie the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiue part of time admits not a fairer prospectiue of Honour. The character of Mars is but his counterseit, and I could wish it yours by adoption, Arts and Armes should be like hypocrates twinnes reciprocall in their first
<pb n="34" facs="27"/>
ingredience, and borne together with a most sweet and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing sympathie. The merit of a Souldier and a Scholer hates poligamie, and are but one flesh. I know you are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly tutored in the one, and I could wish you Laurcated in the other. The poyson of the times hath no better. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote then vertue: the least <hi>doze</hi> of it makes honor nobly preseruatiue. I haue here prescribed it, and may it worke in you his phisicall operation: my dutie bound to the strick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, and most peremptorie remembrance of your Honour: administers this diet: disgest, and be a long liude pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, it is the Souldiers cordiall, and a Noble restoratiue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours humble deuoted, Robert Anton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>