<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Priscus Grammaticus de Satyra. Satyra est carmen acerbum, instrumētum mordax. &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104229_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03680</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13805</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104229</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Priscus Grammaticus de Satyra. Satyra est carmen acerbum, instrumētum mordax. &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A medicinable morall, that is, the two bookes of Horace his satyres, Englyshed accordyng to the prescription of saint Hierome. The wailyngs of the prophet Hieremiah, done into Englyshe verse. Also epigrammes. T. Drant. Perused and allowed accordyng to the Quenes Maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Horace</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>192 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>
      <bibl>Priscus Grammaticus de Satyra.</bibl>
      <q>Satyra est carmen acerbum, instrumētum mordax. &amp;c.</q>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>A</hi> Satyre, is a tarte and carpyng kynd of verse,</l>
      <l>An instrument to pynche the prankes of men,</l>
      <l>And for as muche as pynchynge instrumentes do perse,</l>
      <l>Yclept it was full well a Satyre then.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>A name of Arabique to it they gaue:</l>
      <l>For Satyre there, doothe signifye a glaue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Or <hi>Satyra,</hi> of <hi>Satyrus,</hi> the mossye rude,</l>
      <l>Unciuile god: for those that wyll them write</l>
      <l>With taunting gyrds &amp; glikes and gibes must vexe the lewde,</l>
      <l>Strayne curtesy: ne reck of mortall spyte.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Shrouded in Mosse, not shrynkyng for a shower</l>
      <l>Deemyng of mosse as of a regall bower.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Satyre of writhled waspyshe Saturne may be namde</l>
      <l>The Satyrist must be a wasper in moode,</l>
      <l>Testie and wrothe with vice and hers, to see bothe blamde</l>
      <l>But courteous and frendly to the good.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>As Saturne cuttes of tymes with equall sythe:</l>
      <l>So this man cuttes downe synne, to coy and blythe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Or <hi>Satyra</hi> of <hi>Satur</hi> thauthors must be full</l>
      <l>Of fostred arte, infarst in ballasde breste.</l>
      <l>To teach the worldlyngs wyt, whose witched braines are dull</l>
      <l>The worste wyll pardie hearken to the best.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If that the Poet be not learnde in deede,</l>
      <l>Muche maye he chatte, but fewe wyll marke his reede.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Lus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ll,</hi> (I wene) was parent of this nyppyng ryme:</l>
      <l>Next hudlyng <hi>Horace,</hi> braue in Satyres grace.</l>
      <l>Thy praysed Pamphlet (Persie) well detected cryme</l>
      <l>Syr <hi>Iuu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>nall</hi> deserues the latter place.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The Satyrist loues Truthe, none more then he.</l>
      <l>An vtter foe to fraude in eache degree.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>