<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Of Hesiodus.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104006_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03120</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13249</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104006</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Of Hesiodus.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The georgicks of Hesiod, by George Chapman; translated elaborately out of the Greek: containing doctrine of husbandrie, moralitie, and pietie; with a perpetuall calendar of good and bad daies; not superstitious, but necessarie (as farre as naturall causes compell) for all men to obserue, and difference in following their affaires</title>
                 <author>Hesiod</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Partrich (Patrich, Partridge), Miles</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 39, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>Of Hesiodus.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>esiodus,</hi> surnam'd <hi>Ascraeus,</hi> was one, as of the most anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Greeke Poets; so one of the purest and pressest writers. He liu'd in the later time of <hi>Homer</hi>; &amp; was sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Ascraeus</hi>; of <hi>Ascra,</hi> a Towne in <hi>Helicon</hi>; in which was built a tēple sacred to the <hi>Muses</hi>; whose Priest, <hi>Hesiodus</hi> was consecrate: whom <hi>Virg.</hi> among so many writers of <hi>Georgicks,</hi> only imitated; professing it in this;</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Ascraeum{que} cano Romana per oppida carmen,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. Nor is there any doubt, (saith Mel:) <hi>quin idē Virg: initio Georgicorū, hanc inscriptionem expresserit hoc versu: Quid faciat laetas segetes; quo sidere terram &amp;c.</hi> His autoritie was such amongst the <hi>Antients</hi>; that his verses were commonly learned, as <hi>Axioms</hi> or <hi>Oracles</hi>; All tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching good life, and humanitie: which though neuer so profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for mens now readings; yet had they rather (saith <hi>Isocrates</hi>) consume their times still in their owne follies, than bee any time conuersant in these precepts of wisedome; Of which (with <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>) he was first Father, whose Interpreters were al the succeeding <hi>Philosophers</hi>; Not <hi>Aristotle</hi> himselfe excepted: who before <hi>Thales, Solon, Pittacus, Socrates, Plato,</hi> &amp;c. writ of <hi>Life,</hi> of <hi>Manners,</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> of the <hi>Starres,</hi> and generall state of the vniuerse. Not are his writings the lesse worthy; that <hi>Poesie</hi> informde them, but of so much the more <hi>Dignitie,</hi> and <hi>Eternitie</hi>: Not <hi>Thales,</hi> nor <hi>Anaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras,</hi> (as <hi>Aristotle</hi> ingenuously confesseth) hauing profited the world so much with all their writings; as <hi>Homers</hi> one <hi>Vlisses,</hi> or <hi>Nestor.</hi> And sooner shall all the <hi>Atomes</hi> of <hi>Epicurus</hi> sustaine diuisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the fire of <hi>Heraclitus</hi> be vtterly quencht; the water that <hi>Thales</hi> extolls so much, bee exhausted; the spirit of <hi>Anaxamines</hi> vanish; the discord of <hi>Empedocles</hi> be reconciled; &amp; all dissolu'd to nothing; before by their most celebrated faculties, they doe the world so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much profit for all humane instruction, as this one Work of <hi>Hesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus</hi>: Here beeing no dwelling on any one subiect; but of all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affaires instructiuely concluded.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>