<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Bourne, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104686_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16518</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3432</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104686</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Bourne, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A booke called the treasure for traueilers : deuided into fiue bookes or partes, contaynyng very necessary matters, for all sortes of trauailers, eyther by sea or by lande, written by William Bourne</title>
                 <author>Bourne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 32, 1, 25, 1, 22, 2, 21, 3, 5-16, 4 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsideryng with my selfe, gentle Reader, with howe infinite paynes and labour, dyuers heretofore, men of most excellent wittes, and of passing knowledge, haue compiled their Bookes, and with what heede and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspectnesse they haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and perused theyr trauayles, and with what feare and warynesse they haue published the same. and not without good cause why, for thereby they haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened them selues, theyr name, and fame, to no small daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and harzardes: namely to the veiwe, iudgement, and report of all menne. For which cause, nowe seeyng I haue taken vpon me at this time a harde enterprise, a burthen too heauy for mee to beare or sustaine, who haue at length shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my selfe so hardly, as to publish this litle Treatise, I being altogether vnlearned, and hauing no helpe of any other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned persons, being of my selfe altogether destitute both of knowledge and learning.</p>
   <p>Wherefore I desyre thee, gentle Reader, to beare with my rudenesse, and consider that it is the good wyll which I beare vnto my natyue Countrey, for to profyte the common wealth, as much as lyeth in me, although that it be not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned lyke, yet I pray thee holde me excused, beyng altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant, lacking the capac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e both of knowledge and eperience (who hauyng taken vppon me) to publyshe this to the scannyng and trying of so many touchestones, and daungerous crimes, that I beyng so simple, should enterpryse so farre to take vpon me to open any Science.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>But notwithstanding, I doo see, that it is so needful a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be knowen vnto a number of persons, that doo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre for to haue instructions in those causes that are contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this symple volume, the which booke I doo call <hi>A Treasure vnto Trauaylers,</hi> and is diuided intoo fyue Bookes.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The fyrst booke.</note>And the fyrst booke conteyneth the particuler conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Skall Quardrant or Astrolobe, and in the like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the particuler conclusion of the Crosse staffe &amp;c. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the vse of the Horizontall or flatte Sphere, whereby to drawe or take the platte of any countrey. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The seconde booke.</note>The Seconde booke dooth shewe vnto you, if that you doo knowe the Longitude and the Latitude of any place tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then howe to knowe the distance in myles from you, or any place assygned, and by what poynt of the Compasse that it is from you.</p>
   <p>And because that London is the most famous and the most principall place here in Englande, I haue haue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med certayne principal places here in <hi>Europe,</hi> and also in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi> and in <hi>Asia,</hi> and also in <hi>America,</hi> with some of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallest Ilandes in the worlde, both their Longitude and Latitude, and their distance from the citye of London, and by what poynt of the Compasse that it is from London, and also how much that the Moone doth chaunge rather or later, then it doth at the citie of London, and what length their longest day is of. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The thirde booke.</note>The third booke is as touching the measuring of Superfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cials and sollid bodies, and howe to augment them, or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish them, vnto what proportion or bignes you list, whether that it be the tonnage of any shyppe, or the bignesse of any kaske. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The fourth booke.</note>The fourth boke is as touching the Art Statical, as to know the waight of any shyp swimmyng on the water, and such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The fyfth booke.</note>The fifth or the last boke is as touching the natural causes of sand and rockes in the Sea, and diuers such other like cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, as it doth appeare in the table of the contentes, of the
<pb facs="4"/>
Bookes. &amp;c. The which things, in my opinion, are very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie for al maner of persons, and especially vnto such as be Trauaylers: which causeth me to geue the booke vnto name, <hi>A Treasure vnto Trauaylers.</hi> For what thing can there bee more better vnto a Trauayler, either by Sea or by Lande, (Golde &amp; Siluer onely excepted then to know the distances from place to place, and to haue capacity to know the height and the lownes of any thing, &amp; how to make a Plat or Carde for any countrey. &amp;c. which is declared in the first booke.</p>
   <p>And also how necessary a thing it is for a Trauailer to know vnto what quarter of the worlde any place dooth beare from him, &amp; what the distaūce is thither,<note place="margin">Geometric perspectiue.</note> &amp; what length the day is of, whē he is the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e: as I haue knowne a great number of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons that haue trauayled vnto sundry places, &amp; whē they haue come home, they haue had no iudgement at all, as touching that place that they haue trauayled vnto, for that they haue not knowne vnto what quarter of the worlde the place is, that they haue beene at: neither in respect what the distance is thither. And these matters are shewed in the second booke.</p>
   <p>And also it is not hurtfull,<note place="margin">Cosmogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia.</note> but necessary for a Trauayler to know how to measure al manner of Superficalles, as land, pauementes, bourd, and Glasse, and solid bodies, as Tymber and Stone, and the burthen or tonnage of shyps, and the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of any thing.</p>
   <p>And furthermore it is necessary for a Trauailer in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,<note place="margin">Geometric general.</note> to haue a way to get the true waight of any thing that swimmerh on the water, &amp; in like maner to know the waight of any thing that synketh into the water, &amp; what it waigheth in the water, to be lifted frō the bottome vnto the superficiall part of the water, as it is declared in the fourth boke. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, it is very necessary &amp; conuenient for Trauaylers ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Sea or by land,<note place="margin">Staticke.</note> to haue knowledge in the natural cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of sundry things that are to be seene in trauayling, as the cause of sands &amp; bankes, as well in riuers as in the sea,<note place="margin">Naturall Philosophie.</note> and the cause of Marish ground and meddowes, &amp; the cause of cliffes on the sides of riuers, &amp; on the sea coast, with such other like matters, as is declared in the fifth and last Booke.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>And now it is possible, that some persons wyll marueyle, that I being so simple, and not learned, shoulde take vppon me to be a medler in these causes, for that they be matters that doo appertayne vnto learned men. And it is possible, that it wil be dislyked of a nūber of people, as enuie dwelleth generally in the hartes of most men, for that is the propertie of many people, to dislyke all things that are not doone by them selues, vsing to reade Bookes to no other ende, but to fynde faultes in them.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Discourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>And yet it is possible, that they will do nothing thē selues, which were a cause of discouragyng vnto any person that dooth write: yet notwithstanding it shal not discourage me, for that I am vtterly vnlearned, and therefore it shall not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke me, if any learned man dooth fynde any faulte therein: for I beyng simple and vnlearned, it is no discredite for me, eyther to be taught, or to haue the faultes shewed vnto me. For by that meanes I may refourme the faultes, either by them, or my selfe.</p>
   <p>And furthermore, I doo not intende to make any booke to teach them that are cunning &amp; learned: But the only cause of my writing of this booke is, to instruct or teach them that are simple and vnlearned: And therefore notwithstandyng, I shal the better lyke of it,<note place="margin">Bookes are written to the intent to teach the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned.</note> if any learned man should write or set out any booke, as touching these causes, to refourme this. And my opinion is this, if that any Booke be set foorth vnto the common people in the world, that then it is to the ende, to teach the symplest sort of people that are not instructed in learned causes. But if that it be any high poynt in learned causes, then it is not for the common sort of people, but to be in learned mens Libraries, and therfore as it is not written by a learned man, so in lyke manner you must not looke for fyne or eloquent schole termes, but euen to take the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the matter rudely as it is, and more to regarde the necessarinesse of the matter, whether it may doe any good in the common wealth. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>And yet notwithstanding my opinion is this, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is to be disliked of, that doth his good wil and endeuour,<note place="margin">No person is to be disliked that doth his good wyll to doe good.</note> to doo good in the common wealth, howesoeuer that it prooueth. But those persons are vtterly to be dyslyked of, that doo hurt willyngly in the common wealth, as extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners and vsurers, and conuayers of Corne and Vitayles, and other necessaries and commodityes that his countrey dooth lacke or hath neede of.</p>
   <p>And al those persons are not to be thought well of,<note place="margin">Persons that are to be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyked.</note> that doo desyre to lyue easily, abusing the good benefytes that God dooth blesse the earth with: as al licentious lyuers, as drunkardes, banketters, whoores, and whooremaysters, and such as doo vse an excesse in apparell, much aboue their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
   <p>And also those people are to be abhorred of al men, who doo annoy the earth, that vse quarrellyng and fyghtyng, robbyng and stealyng, caryng not howe they come by it, so that they may haue it, with which this our countrey of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land floweth at this day, (the more is the pytie) for what wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse is there that can be deuysed, but that it is vsed here in England amongst al degrees, which must needes procure the wrath of God to lyght vppon vs. And there is as great abuse amongest the Clergie, which should be as Lanternes to geue vs lyght, to leade vs vnto vertue.<note place="margin">Abuses of Englande.</note> But now in these dayes they be as Lanternes to leade vs vnto vice. So that al degrees of people are geuen vnto wickednesse, although that we haue the Gospel of Iesus Christ, preached dayly vnto vs, yet wickednes doth abound, for what synne or wickednesse is there, but that it is suffered and vsed, as wichcraft and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, and magical Inchantment, and coungering, which is the greatest and most abominable dishonouring of God, that may be.</p>
   <p>For in theyr magicall Inchantment and coungeryng,<note place="margin">Magical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntment is a great dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoring of God.</note> doo they not obserue houres in the making of Carecters, &amp; set vp pickturs of the Roode, and <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> and the <hi>Doome,</hi> and a number of such other pickturs, paynted, and gilded vppon
<pb facs="6"/>
Virgin Parchment, as they cal it. And then in like maner their cirkles must be perfumed, &amp; inbalmed with sweete odours, and they must haue a knaue priest, made by the Popes lawe, to hallowe a certayne portion, with a number of such vayne Ceremonies. And when that they haue the diuel, whom they doe serue, &amp; doo geue him in some cases some thing for a sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and when that they doo geue the diuel a charge to tel them any question that they would knowe, then are vsed a number of superstitious wordes, as in the name of the virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the Virgin Mary, and the head of Iohn Baptist, and a number of vaine Saintes more, besides a number of such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable Ceremonies, to the great dishonouring of God. &amp;c. And who is the cause and the procurement of these most o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and detestable matters, but a number of vaine, &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked people, yea some of thē be of no smal wealth nor calling, that do procure these matters: For if that they haue lost any thing, thē they must repaire vnto a Coniurer, to know where that is againe. And furthermore, there are some vaine &amp; foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Gentlemen, which seeke to liue pleasantly and idlely, that must liue by gaming and playe, and he must haue a familiar in a Ryng,<note place="margin">What maner of christian is he that desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar with the diuell.</note> or such other like place. But what manner of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian doo you thinke him to be, that desyreth to be familiar with the diuell? So that a great number of people that are in the world, desire to lyue idlely and pleasantly, caring not, so that they haue their pleasure here, although their soule goe vnto hel, and there to be tormented in fire &amp; Brimstone euer world without end. Wherefore God turne the hartes of those that are the cause of wickednes, and especially here in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue countrey, &amp; Realme of England, for that we haue a most gratious and vertuous Queene raigning ouer vs, and such a one as doth alwaies study for the setting foorth of the word of God and sacred Gospel of Iesus Christ,<note place="margin">The vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse of the Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie is our preseruation.</note> and dooth alwayes studie for peace &amp; trāquility. And considering the great wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes that is vsed in England, the wrath of God would haue lighted vpon vs long before this time, but only for the grace &amp; vertuousnesse of the Queenes miaesty, that God hath spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="6"/>
vs for her sake. Therefore let vs al pray vnto God for her long life and prosperity, that she may raigne long ouer vs. For surely my opinion is this, except we doo repent and turne frō our wickednesse, the wrath of God wil light vpon vs. For in these daies euery man is but for him self, the elder sort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are geuē generally al vnto excessiue &amp; huge couetousnes, and the yonger sort of people are geuen generally vnto pride and whooredome, and other vaine toyes,<note place="margin">The abuses of al degrees.</note> as idlenesse and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, so that in respect fewe or none haue the feare of God before their eyes. And if any persons doo frame them selues to liue vertuously, according vnto the lawe of God, then they shalbe but derided both of the elder sort, &amp; also of the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: for the couetous rich persons wyl say, he is a foole, he can not make shift to liue, he hath too precise a conscience: and the youngest, vayne glorious proude fooles, will say, He is a scriptured man, he wil not haue vs to be meery nor go clenly.<note place="margin">Couetousnes is called good husbandrie.</note> So that in these dayes, extortiō &amp; couetousnes is called good husbandrie: and the one of them wil commende the other, saying, He is a wise felowe, he wil liue, how fraudulētly soeuer he come by his goods. So what wickednesse soeuer that it be,<note place="margin">
         <p>Pride is clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, swearing lustinesse, drunkennesse, good fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyppe.</p>
         <p>Whoredome, friendship <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> a tricke of youth.</p>
      </note> the same shalbe commended by them that vse the like: as pride in these daies is called clenlinesse, and swearing lustines, saying, he is a lustie fellowe, and dronkennesse, good fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and whooredome a tricke of youth or freindship, so that the one sort of people doo heape vp the goods on the earth vnsaciably, and the other sort of people, spende it away most vainely and wantonly, so that the good giftes or benefytes of God, which are the riches of the world, are abused on euery side, &amp; not vsed as they ought to be, that is to say, to do good vpon the earth with that, for it was created for the vse of man to a good ende, to take his portion of it, &amp; the rest to vse vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to some good purposes at his discretion, for that God doth sende it hym, vnto that ende, and not to be heaped vp, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to throwe it away wickedly, as a number doo: Therefore men do not rightly consider, wherefore they were borne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the face of the earth.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <note place="margin">The first cause that man is borne for, is to serue God.</note>Fyrst he is borne to serue God, for that he hath created him, and al mankinde, and hath created him a reasonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and hath created al thing for his vse: as fyrst the earth, with al his mynerals, as we doo digge out of the earth, Gold, Syluer, and al other mettals, and stones, to make vs necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes to serue mans vse. And also the face of the earth, he hath created to bring foorth Trees to make vs Timber, and Grasse to feede Cattel, to make vs foode and meate: Corne to make vs breade, with al his other benefytes, which man receyueth from the face of the earth. The Sea with al other Ryuers, bringeth foorth Fish of innumerable sortes, to make vs foode and meate, yea the very Sea is for mans vse, too passe from Countrey vnto Countrey.</p>
   <p>The ayre in lyke manner, wherein are multitudes of feathered foules, for mans vse, yea the very Heauens are for mans vse, as the Sunne, Moone, and Starres, are created for the vse of man. And also he hath redeemed vs from the Originall synne of Adam, by his precious bloodde sheeddyng. Wherefore wee are fyrste borne too serue God.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">The seconde cause that man is borne is to serue his countrey.</note>And secondly, wee are borne to serue our Prince, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yue Countrey, that is to saye, to defende our Territoryes, that no other ferreine Nations doo spoyle vs of our labours, or our Prince of her dignitie.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Thirdly man is borne to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to lyue</note>And thyrdly, we are borne to prouide for our houshold, and our familie and to see that they be trayned vp, to lyue in the feare of God, and to knowe theyr duetie to their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, and to trayne them vp vnto some facultie, whereby they may get them a lyuing. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Wherfore I would wish al those persons, that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God to blesse vppon the face of the earth, with anye worldly reuenewes, or substance and liuing, to practise some thing, whereby they may doo some good vppon the face of the earth. And in like manner to trayne vp theyr chyldren in the nurture and feare of God. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>Especially the noble men and gentlemen, and they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues not to desyre to liue pleasantly and idely,<note place="margin">The causes of al degrees.</note> but to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise some vertuous thing, as martiall affayres, or such other lyke causes, as their capacitie wyll serue them. For there were two causes in the beginning of all degrees of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraltie or layetie, wherof al Noble men and Gentlemen had their originall and beginnyng, and they are worthy to be had in honour vnto the worlds ende, for their parentage, and the much the rather, if that they doo folow the rule of their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and worthy progenitors.</p>
   <p>The fyrst cause was, for their noble actes and deedes in the defending of their Country against their enemies. &amp;c.<note place="margin">The fyrst cause.</note> So by that meanes, for their valiantnesse against their enemies, they were extolled and aduanced vnto high dignitie, euerye person according vnto his desertes, and had lyuings to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne their state, and they to defend their Territories whilest the common people dyd manure and tyll the ground.</p>
   <p>And the second cause in degrees of nobilytie and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,<note place="margin">The second cause.</note> was to them that made good and wholsome lawes for the good gouernement of their common weales. Therefore I would wish al noble mē and gentlemen to folow the noble race of their progenitours: and then they are the highlyer to bee esteemed. But otherwise, what a shame and discredit, if that they do rightly consider of it, is it for them to be euil members in the cōmon weale: considering howe worthyly their ancientrie dyd attaine &amp; come vnto their callyng.<note place="margin">Good mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in a cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale.</note> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would wish euery gentleman, to practise something, that he may do good, either to defend the common weale, or els to profyt it some otherway, and not to be idle and to seeke to liue easily, whereby the common weale may be the better mayntayned, the Prince the better serued, and our Countrye the better furnished, with such persons, as are able to defende the Prince, Crowne, and dignytie, as well in their good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel, and also in their acts and deeds. And also in my opinion, they are very necessary members in the common weale in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb facs="8"/>
respectes, that are Trauaylers into other Countries, and they are able to profyt theyr owne Countrie in diuers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectes: for that hee is able to geue iudgement by his owne Countrie of other, whether it bee as touching the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the common weale, in the executing of their lawes of the manner of traffick, and in the vsage and nature of the people, bothe in their Cities and Townes, and in their Countrie, and what manner of commodities they haue, and of the situation of their Townes, and in their fortifycation, and also of what strength and force other Princes and states are of, and of the order and manner of vsyng them selues in martial affayres in the warres, and what their Artillerie is, and how they are weaponed and armed, and furnished in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery respect, which is very necessarie to bee knowne vnto the nobilitie, for that they may prouide them selues, and their Countrie for their better safetie, and also they shall knowe what thing shall annoy their enemies most.</p>
   <p>Then it is a playne case, that Trauailers into other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treies doo much profyte the common weale. For suppose this, that if we, or any Country dyd liue in that order, that we did trauaile into no place or Countrie, neither no nation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, then in processe of time wee should beecome barbarous and sauage. Therfore the Trauaylers are much to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in diuers respectes. Wherefore I wyll shewe you my opinion, what manner of people are meetest to bee trauay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. For a number of people haue trauayled, and when they haue come home, they haue had no iudgement of their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle, but haue beene vtterly ignoraunt of suche thinges as were most meetest of a Trauailer to be noted, and partlye some of them were not capable in those causes,<note place="margin">What maner of persons are the meetest to be Trauai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers.</note> and some of them many times, their heades are occupied with other vaine and foolish causes. &amp;c. as this fyrst: those people that are able to benefyt their country by their trauaile, when they are come home, ought not to bee to young: for commonlye a young man his head is occupyed with euery vaine and light cause,
<pb facs="8"/>
as with banketting, and play, and game, &amp; daunsing, and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying with women, and gazing vpon vaine toyes. &amp;c. So that his head is occupyed with no other thing, but all pleasaunt matters.</p>
   <p>Therefore he that is sent to be a Trauailer,<note place="margin">What a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailer should consider of.</note> to the ende to profyt his Country, ought to be a man that hath a stayed &amp; a modest head, and such a one as is capable, and hath a good witte with him, and learned. And if hee bee seene in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical Science, it is all the better: For then hee shall the sooner conceaue any matter. And also he ought not to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to young nor to olde, but betweene the age of .40. and 56. or 57. yeares. &amp;c. And these bee the principallest poyntes, that a trauailer should consider of. First, to consider what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Nation he is entred into, whether they bee politicke or wise, or Ciuill people, or whether they be a rude or barbarous nation: and so in his trauailing to frame his vsage according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as neare as he can, that the people may like well of him▪ for in so doing he should vnderstande the better of the state and commoditie of the Country, Citie, Towne or place: and when that you do come into any Citie or Towne, view of what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of grounde it standeth vpon, and what it may be or is sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto, and in like maner how it is fortifyed and prouided, and how it is maintayned, and whether it standeth vpon any hauen or riuer, that hath vent vnto the Sea, or any water, that hath no vent or passage vnto the Sea, but thorow or by some other Citie or Towne, before it commeth vnto the Sea. And also vnder whom it is, and howe it is gouerned, and what theyr Lawes and Ordinaunces bee: And what nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Monuments of buildyngs there be: and any other rare and notable thing that is not common: And also to learne what nation, Country, Citie or Towne that may most annoy them, and also what Countrye, Citie or Towne dooth most pleasure them, and what trade or Marchaundize they are principallest maintayned by, and what commodities are
<pb facs="9"/>
most plentiest, and what commodities or things necessariest, are most scantest, and what the nature of the soyle or ground is thereabouts, that is to say, what the ground is most aptest to bring foorth, or most vnapt, as touching Corne, Trees, and such other lyke, whatsoeuer it bee. And al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o what maner of Money and coyne is vsed, both in Siluer and Golde, and other base Money in Copper, if they haue any. And also what the people hath most pleasure in, and what they do most ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre or hate, and whether the Countrye bee a playne and champion Countrie, or Hils and Mountaynes, or lowe marsh or marishe grounde, and whether it be full of Riuers or not, and also how the Princes or the other Gouernours doo leuey their Souldiours in the time of their warres, &amp; how they doo arme them, and weapon them, and furnish them in euery re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, and what duties or customes, or tolles, or suche lyke charges are payd, whether it be of them selues, or vpon stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or any other kinde of goodes or marchandize, and what thing it is they make most store of, that they wyll not haue passe out of their Countries, with all such other lykenes, that for breuitie I doo omit.</p>
   <p>And now such persons as haue noted these causes at their returne home, are able to profyt much the common weale in diuers respects, and are persons of great valure vnto theyr Countrye, for that they are able to profyt the state, and the common weale of their Countrye in diuers respectes. For all those persons are of great valure and price, and are as special Iewels vnto their Country,<note place="margin">What persons are of valure in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale.</note> and in the common weale, that are politick, cunning, and valyaunt in mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hall affayres: for thereby their Countrye is defended and preserued from the forrayne enemies: For looke what Country is riche and welthye, then other Princes are desyrous therof, for to haue the spoyles, and the benifyts of it: wherfore by polycie and manlynesse they must be defended. Therefore men expert in marshall affayres are very necessary in a common wealth.</p>
   <p>And furthermore, all those persons, that are wise and sober,
<pb facs="9"/>
and discreet in the good gouernemēt of the common weale, such as doo maintayne vertue and suppresse vice, are persons of great valure to their Countrie, and also those persons are able by their wisdome and knowledge to benefyt or profyte their Countrie, whether it be in the teaching of good artes and Sciences, or by any other meanes, so that the common weale be the better mayntayned, are persons of great valure, and are as Iewels vnto their country, and their country is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding vnto them. But contrariwise, all those persons that are not able to profyt the common weale in any respect, and also desyre to liue pleasauntly and wantonly, and haue great liuynges and riches, and doo no good therewith: all those persons are more beholding vnto their Countrie, then their Countrye is vnto them. But if they haue great store of ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and doo couet to heape more, caryng not how they doo come by it, so they may haue it: such persons are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, and are as Caterpillers to the common weale of their Countrye, for that they doo annoy and hurt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity and the state of their Country, for that they catch and heape vp into their custodie more then dooth suffice them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, by great quantities, whereas thowsandes doo lacke to serue their turnes, that are better members in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale then they are. And all such persons, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale hath a good turne when they are deliuered of such a one: For by that meanes is dispearsed that heape of store vnto a number of persons handes besydes that whiche he would haue heaped vp more, if that hee had continued longer. So that some of the richest sort of people are not the best members in the common weale, but the worste: and yet it behoueth some persons to bee rich, and by their riches the common weale is the better maintained, as thus.</p>
   <p>The Prince of any Countrye being godlye and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, the Common Weale dooth the better flourishe, and is continually kept the safer from the forrayne enemyes:
<pb facs="10"/>
and the Noble men, and Gentlemen, that are vertuous, and giuen to practise the good gouernment, &amp; the preseruement of them selues, and the state of their Country. So then their riches doo good, and also if the Marchaunte bee rich, so that he doo not hurt his owne Country, but winneth his ryches out of other forraine Countries, or any other good and vertuous Subiect, by his riches he may doo good, if hee doo vse that hee hath to the furtheraunce of the common weale: So that it is necessarye that there should bee rich persons in the common weale, for a number of causes, so that those rich persons be vertuously bent, but otherwise they may do hurt. And thus gentle Reader, I doo make an ende, desyring you that you wyll take this simple Booke in good part, and if there be any faults committed by me, either by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce or negligence, I pray you let mee gentlye vnderstand thereof, for man cannot bee so precise, but that hee may erre. And thus I betake you vnto almightie God, the Creator of all thinges.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>By yours,</hi> William Bourne.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>