<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The prologe of the auctor.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1530</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104474_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10436</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20719</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104474</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The prologe of the auctor.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A new boke of purgatory : whiche is a dyaloge &amp; dysputacyon betwene one Comyngo an Almayne a Christen man, &amp; one Gyngemyn a turke of Machoinett law, dysputynge by naturall reason and good philosophye, whether there be a purgatorye or no purgatorye. which boke is deuyded into thre dyalogys. The fyrst dyaloge sheweth and treateth of the merueylous exystens of god. The seconde dyaloge treateth of the immortalyte of mannys soule. The thyrde dyaloge treateth of purgatory</title>
                 <author>Rastell, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Rastell, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1530</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ The prologe of the auctor.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T happenyd so but late that for dyuers besynes and other affayres concernynge my selfe I toke a vyage out of this realme and passyd ouer this narow Occy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an see, and traueylyd in to dyuers farre countreys in the eest partyes / and at the last as it was my chaunce I came into a great cytye / where I made myn abode and there taryed by the space of. xx. dayes or aboue / in whyche cytye there vseth contynually to resorte a great companye of marchauntys / whyche be borne in sondrye and dyuers nacyons / whyche be not onely Englyshmen / Frenchmen / Spanyardes / Almaynes / and other dyuers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> / but also they y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> be Turkes &amp; Saraciēs / &amp; other that be of Machametys lawe. And bycause of interchaungynge of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundyses / y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> sayd marchauntys do dayly mete togyder in dyuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cys within the same citye / and whan they haue talked togyder of thynge concernyng theyr owne besynes / yet for a recreacyon amonge them self / they be desyrous eche of other to know news &amp; straūge thynges of other contrees. And as it happenyd to me on a season to be in the companye of dyuers of those marchauntys / amonge them all specyall there were. ii. of thē / of the whyche one was a turke called ¶ Gyngemyn borne vnder Machometys law / and y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> other was a Christenman callyd ¶ Comyngo / borne in hye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> / which were of olde famylyer accoyntaūce / &amp; bothe of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m men of great wytte and of good lernynge / and specyally y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> turk / whyche was well lern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d bothe in morall phylosophye and naturall / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne whom I herde myth good communycacion / argumentys and rea sons / whych lyked me very well / and so wel pleased me that immedyatly after that I toke penne &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nke &amp; tytled it in wrytynge / &amp; reported euery argument &amp; reason as nygh as my wytte and remembraunce wold serue me / after the maner as here after foloweth in this lytell boke. And in the beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nnynge of theyr sayd cōmunycacyon Comyngo the Almayn asked of Gy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gemyn the Turke / what tythynges or news were in his contrey / whych Gyngemyn shewed hym of the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> whych y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> great Turk had lately had in dyuers places / as well of the great sege of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Rodes / as of the great batayles / whych he had lately had in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ungarye. But yet the sayd Gyngemyn was not so glad to tel the tythyngys &amp; news in &amp; about his contrey / as he was desyrous to knowe of some straūge news in other placis in Christendom. And oft tymes required this Comyngo to shew hym some new tythynges of his contrey. To y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> whyche Comyngo the Al mayne answered and shewed hym that there was a newe varyaunce in Christendome and a s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ysme begonne of late amonge the people there / cōce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nyng
<pb facs="2"/>
 theyr fayth and byleue / and sayd that there was a new opinyon spronge amōge the people / that there is no purgatory / nor that the soule of man after it is separate from the body / shal neuer be purged nor pury<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed of no synne that remayneth therin / but y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> it shal immedyatly after it is separate from the body / go to heuen to eternall ioy and saluacyon / or ellys to hell to eternall payne and dampnacyon. To whome Gyngemyn answered / and sayd that y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> opynyon was but folysh and agayns all good naturall reason / bycause that all people in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> world of what cōtrey so euer they haue be or be / or of what law &amp; secte so euer they haue be or be / aswel the Panyms / the Iewes / and you that be of Chrystes fayth / &amp; we that be of Machomets law / and all other that euer lyued or do lyue after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of any good reason / haue euer byleued and do byleue that there is a purgatory / where mannes soules shall be purged after this mortall lyfe. Therfore quod he I meruell greatly that there shuld any suche fond opi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyon begynne amonge the people now in any contrey / consyderynge y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> there is no reason to maynteyne theyr opynyon that euer I coude here.</p>
   <p>¶ The reasons of them that holde opynyō that there is no purgatory. To whom Comyngo y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Almayne answered &amp; sayd that they had dyuers reasons to maynteyne theyr opiniō therī / wherof one is this. ¶ They say y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> contrycyō whiche some call repentaunce / is that whiche is the very pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment and satysfaccyon for synne / and they say that when a man commyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyth a synne / and after is repentaunte therfore / that god of his goodnes doth forgyue hym / and that y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> repentaunce is the onely satysfaccyon that god wolde haue to be made and done for that synne. And than syth that a man whiche is a synner / by suche repentaunce hath made suche paymēt and satysfaccyon for his synne as god wolde haue to be made therfore / yf than that man shuld go to purgatory / and haue a new punyshmēt after his deth / that repentaunce that he had before shuld be but voyde.</p>
   <p>¶ A nother reason / they alege that man was ordeyned and made to haue an infynyte beynge / therfore after this mortall dethe he must haue infynyte ioy or infynyte payne. So thā he is not ordeyned to haue payn in purgatory that hath an ende.</p>
   <p>¶ A nother reason they alege and that is this. God by the order of his iustyce hath ordeyned heuen / where that good men shall be rewarded / &amp; hell where synners shall be punysshed / and in bothe those places orders and degrees / that is to say / that he whiche deserueth a great and an hye reward shall haue in heuen a great ioye / and he that deserueth a smaller rewarde / shall haue a smaller ioye / and also he that deserueth a great pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshment / shall haue in hell great payne / and he that deserueth a lesse pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyshment / shall haue in hell lesse payne. So that whether a man haue de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>seruyd a great ioy or a small ioy / a great payn or a small payne god may by his order of good iustyce rewarde or punysh hym accordyng to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruynge so that there nedeth no place of purgatory.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>¶ A nother reason they alege / that though a man be not clerely purged of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ynne when he dyeth / and though some spot &amp; tokē therof remayne in his soule wherby he is som what deformed / yet y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> soule maye do some meane and low seruyce or pleasure to god in heuen / though it be not the hyest and best seruyce / nor though it haue not the greatest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oye in heuen / yet it may haue some small ioy / and be in some low place in heuē / &amp; there haue a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oyous lyfe / wherwith it wyll be ryght well content / and so rewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d accordynge to his desert / though it be not purged and made so clene as other soules that be there / and so nedeles to ordeyn for that soule any other place of purgatory.</p>
   <p>¶ A nother reason they alege / y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> god hath ordeyned heuen to be a place of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oy / and hell to be a place of infinyte payne / &amp; yerth where we be to be a place myxte / somtyme of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oy / somtyme of payne / whych neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth but for a tyme / y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> shall haue ende. And than syth that the soule of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth beynge here with the body / it is conuenyent it shuld be purged here with y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> body. And bycause y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> god hath ordeyned this place in yerth to be a place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oy &amp; payne y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> shal haue ende / it is most cōuenyc̄t y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> the place of purgatorye shuld be here in yerth / bycause it is y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> place ordeyned for payne that shall haue an ende / &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o nedeth to put none other place of purgatory / &amp; yf the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e be any other place / where is y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> place of purgatory.</p>
   <p>¶ A nother they alege / that bycau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e the mercy of god cā not be w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssyon is euer incydent to repentaunce / therfore as sone as repentaunce is taken god of his iustyce must gyue remyssyon / &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> repentaunce and remyssyon there ought to be no purgatorye.</p>
   <p>¶ A nother ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eccyon they alege / that yf thou do an offence to god and to thy neyghbour / wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n god forgyueth it nede none other satysfaccyō to thy neyghbour bycause god is the very owner of all / and thy neyghbour hath no {pro}perte / but as a seruaūt to god / as but to make accoūpte to god</p>
   <p>¶ To whom this Gyngemyn the turke anone answered and sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d / that as for all those reasons they may be sone answered &amp; auoyded / &amp; yf thou wylt gyue to me dylygent heryng / I shall gyue the suffycyent soluc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ons to al those reasons &amp; satysfye thy mynde. And further I shal {pro}ue to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> by other argumentes &amp; by natural reason &amp; good phylosophye / y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> there must nedys be a purgatory / where y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> soule of man after y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> it is separat from the body / shalbe purged and puryfyed. To whom this Comyngo sayde / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he wold be meruelous glad to here his mynde therin. To whom this Gyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n than sayd / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he must immedyatly go in to the strete to speke with a marchaūt / to aske of hym but one short question touchyng y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> besynes of his marchaūdyse / &amp; sayd that he wold retorne agayne incontynēt / which as he sayd / he dyd / &amp; taryed not long but shortly camagayn. And as sone as euer they were mete there agayn / they begā theyr cōmunycaciō / &amp; Co myngo y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> begā fyrst to speke / &amp; sayd as hereafter now foloweth.</p>
   <trailer>¶ finis prologi.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>