<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the very vertuous and my sin∣gular good Lady, the Lady Leighton, one of the Ladies of the Queenes Maiesties most honorable priuie Chamber: the Pilgrime wi∣sheth a long and happie life, with such increase of honour, as her Ladiships godly indeuours doe deserue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104618_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16209</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3132</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104618</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the very vertuous and my sin∣gular good Lady, the Lady Leighton, one of the Ladies of the Queenes Maiesties most honorable priuie Chamber: the Pilgrime wi∣sheth a long and happie life, with such increase of honour, as her Ladiships godly indeuours doe deserue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reuelation of the true Minerua : The effect of this booke. Who on earth be gods: and by what meanes mortall men may bee made immortall</title>
                 <author>Blenerhasset, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the very vertuous and my <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular good Lady, the Lady</hi> Leighton, one of the Ladies of the Queenes Maiesties most honorable priuie Chamber: the Pilgrime <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth a long and happie life, with such increase</hi> of honour, as her Ladiships godly indeuours doe deserue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow farre little Englande (my verie good Ladie) doeth in perfecte felicitie surpasse all the large king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the worlde, that trauell and small expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience which I haue had, hath sufficiently taught mee: and in truth (were it not that the generall plentie of passing much happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, doth make a great multitude of people to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get in many respectes their dueties,) I would with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubting stedfastly beleeue that the Sunne it selfe neither doth, nor euer hath shined vppon any place, whose prosperitie might compare with this Ilandes: brought in deede to that worthie passe by the great good gouernmēt &amp; singuler industry of the Queenes Maiesties most excellent wisdome. The due consideration wherof, did moue mee continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to force my selfe in the praise of so great a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonage, and finding my weakenesse equall with mine vnworthines, I was still restrained from that attēpt, and had indeede neuer attempted but that necessitie
<pb facs="3"/> constraineth the ignoraunt to speake when the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned be silent, &amp; the truth may with great commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation be vttered out of the mouth of a childe. At my last return out of the maine Ocean, being entred into that brod &amp; boystrous bay of Portingale, there (I may truely say) amongest the moste mightie and greatest ouergrowne Seas in the worlde, the strength of my desire so preuailed, as it forced me (euen there) solemnely to vow, presently after mine arriuall I woulde indeuour to straine my breath to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most, so to sounde foorth her excellent praise, who of a barbarous Ile hath made a most florishing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. And beeing arriued in that pleasant <hi>Tempe,</hi> immediatly solitarie contemplation so ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted mee with the heauenly diuine powers, that not by imagination, but with present familiare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, I was continually conuersaunt with the <hi>Muses,</hi> with all learnings Ladies, euen with the ansient Gods and Goddesses themselues, who haue repaide my diligent seruice with a small habilitie to vse my penne as a proper instrumente against yrke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some idlenes, and a sharpe swoorde to vanquishe her brutish daughter blinde ignorance mother to error, the dreadfull vndoer of mankinde. By this meanes I filled of late fiue queeres of paper with mine owne deuises, if a mā may esteeme that his which the great worldemaker, I knowe not by what secrete di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine infusion conuaieth into him, which booke for that it is in deed but a brief repetitiō of the Queenes maiesties due deserued praises, therfore I did intitle it
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>A Reuelation of the true Minerua:</hi> in whithe discourse for that it pleaseth many of the worthiest that euer liued to vtter some speeches in the praise of her most excellent Maiestie, and to surrender and resigne ouer their titles, beeing as it woulde seemee, prouoked thereto by her maiesties due desarts, I not able to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale that part, haue abruptly rent it from the reste which made it once more beautifull. And because your Ladiships exceeding great wisdom hath made you a very worthy mēber of her maiesties most roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Courte, and hath inriched you with such credite as you may mightily defende all godly and good indeuours, hauing your place continually very neere vnto her maiesties elbow, therfore I haue set foorth this first part vnder your tuition, hoping that the matter therein contained shall please euen as many as shall reade it, and thus your Ladiships most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble seruant doth end, wishing vnto you in euery re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect your heartes desires.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>