<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Rea∣der grace and peace, from God our Father by the merits of our alone Sauiour Christ Ie∣sus, be multiplied.</title>
           <author>H., E.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104314_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B14118</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14014</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104314</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Rea∣der grace and peace, from God our Father by the merits of our alone Sauiour Christ Ie∣sus, be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>H., E.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sampsons iavvbone against the spiritual Philistine : Containing sundry godly and Christian praiers, necessarie and conuenient for all estates and occasions: by Ed. Hutchins</title>
                 <author>Hutchins, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Short, Peter</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 159, that is 259, 11 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>grace and peace, from</hi> God our Father by the merits of <hi>our alone Sauiour Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> be multiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Christian exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of sacred and sanctifying praier (christian Reader) is of that excellencie, necessitie, and efficacy, as that it neither nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, nor is possible worthily to be expressed or commended by the tongue or pen of man. For if we consider first the Author thereof who is the holy Lorde of heauen and earth, infinite in power, wisedome and mercie, we must needes confesse he would not haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and so often enioined
<pb facs="5"/>his seruants to the zealous and constant practise of this princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and most powrefull duetie, had not he who is onely wise, nay rather who is wisedome and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes it selfe, seene it to haue been most necessarie and profitable for them. 2. The manifold and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall precepts &amp; exhortations of the Prophets, Apostles, our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Sauiour Christ Iesus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and his faithfull Ministers from time to time, to admonish and incite vs to the practise here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Thirdlie if we consider the constant and continuall practise of all the fathfull Patriarches, Prophets, and Apostles, yea moreouer of the ordinary and continuall vse hereof by our most holy, immaculate, and most glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="5"/>Sauiour and of that innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable cloude of witnesses of Saints, Martyrs, and all others the faithfull seruantes of God: as <hi>Abraham</hi> and his posteritie, <hi>Moyses, Ioshua, Sampson Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon, Elias Daniel,</hi> and all the rest of the Prophetes and holie men of God, did vs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>llie in all their distresses striue with God, as <hi>Iacob</hi> did wrastle with the Angell. Fourthlie the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities &amp; occasions that daily and hourelie euen force and compell all the Lordes deere Children to the constant and faithfull pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise hereof: for whether we looke vnto the benefites of Almightie God past, present, or to come, which euerie houre and minute of our life we haue, doe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb facs="6"/>to enioie which are innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; or to the dangers, mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, afflictions, or iudgementes haue befallen vs, hang ouer our heades, or maie euerie minute seaze vpon vs, we are called, yea forciblie summoned to this holie and most necessarie duetie. Fiftlie if we regard the most gracious and mercifull promises, freelie made vnto vs to allure vs hereto, and that for our owne good. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the heauie iudgements threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and executed vpon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and carelesse neglectors of this duetie. And lastlie the continnall dailie lip-labour and fruitles and ignorant, yea sinfull blasphemous mumbling of the sottishe Idolatrous Papistes, whose constant practise in this
<pb facs="6"/>case shall rise vp in iudgement against manie millions of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, that make no conscience to consecrate some daylie opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities or howers for this spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall duetie. These Motiues (good Reader) with infinit moe which I can not remember vnto thee, ought to spurre thee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the constant and conscio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable practise of this exercise of holie and feruent prayer, and for thy helpe and furtheraunce herein, the gracious, wise, and mercifull prouidence of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie Father hath raised vppe manie of his faithfull seruants and Ministers, to set downe and publishe sundrie and diuers fourmes of godlie and Christian Prayers, for thy furtheraunce
<pb facs="7"/>and direction at all times, and vpon all occasions. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, least thou shouldest be glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and so begin to loathe this most wholesome and necessarie spirituall foode of thy soule, the Spirit of God hath disposed so, that diuers of the said treatises of prayer do carie most amiable and delightfull countenances as it were outwardlie, the rather to affect and winne thee to the loue and embracing of at least some of them. As if thy heart be set vpon treasure, there is one ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that title of, <hi>The treasure of gladnes;</hi> an other <hi>The Pathway to saluation,</hi> an other <hi>The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Garden,</hi> also <hi>The enimie to securitie,</hi> and one amongst the rest beares this title, <hi>Dauids
<pb facs="7"/>Sling,</hi> which godlie and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Treatise was manie yeares ago published by this Author, to the great comfort and benefit of many thousand the seruants of God. These goodly titles no doubt were put vppon these treatises purposelie, the rather to affect and delight the Readers with the loue of this exercise, euen as the discreet &amp; carefull Phisition doth often deale with his weake and ill affectionated stomacke and eie of his patient, who when his stomacke hath bin cloied with ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king many medicines and his tast offended with the bitternesse of them, his eie also begins to abhor the sight and colour thereof: I say then the Physition doth many times couer his med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="8"/>pill, cordiall preseruatiue, or restoratiue with fine gold, that both the eie may the rather be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted therewith, and the pallate kept from the taste thereof, and so the pattent entised to receiue the same for his owne good. Now if all these and verie manie other meanes haue bin deuised, to draw thee to the loue and liking of this most necessarie and christian du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and that for thine eternall good and saluation, what remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth but that thou at length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre with thy owne soule of these things diligently and faithfullie, and if thou hast been carelesse and negligent herein, repent and call earnestly to the Lord to renew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, direct, and assist thee: If thou haue made some conscience
<pb facs="8"/>of the daily and conscionable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of this dutie, proceed &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, knowing that he that put<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth his hand to the plough and looketh backe is not meete for the kingdom of heauē; and that only he which endureth to the end shal be saued. Thou seest how watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and malicious Sathan is now his kingdom is almost at an end, to stir vp millions of his instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēts &amp; ministers in these dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous daies of ours, as many cursed Atheists &amp; abhominable Papists, with sundry other damnable He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, and false and carnal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, to extinguish the blessed light of the glorious Gospell of Christ Iesus, and the most woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and sacred instrument there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, euen our gratious and dread
<pb facs="9"/>soueraigne, the blessed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable light, of this Israell of God. It standeth vs therefore in hand to be sober and to be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto praier, and to looke to our lampes and to our oyle, that at what houre of the day or night the Lord shall call for vs, we may bee found in the knowledge and true faith of the Lord Iesus, and in the obedience and practise of his commandements; that so we maie enter with him into that happie and glorious rest, prepared for all the adopted children of our heauenly father: which he grant vs for his Christ sake, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell in Christ.</salute>
      <signed>E. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>