<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Lodowick Flood.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104609_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16206</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3128</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104609</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Lodowick Flood.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The castle, or picture of pollicy : shewing forth most liuely, the face, body and partes of a commonwealth, the duety quality, profession of a perfect and absolute souldiar, the martiall feates encounters and skirmishes lately done by our English nation, vnder the conduct of the most noble and famous Gentleman M. Iohn Noris Generall of the Army of the states in Friseland. The names of many worthy and famous gentlemen which liue and haue this present yeare. 1580. ended theyr liues in that land most honorably. Handled in manner of a dialogue betwixt Gefferay Gate, and William Blandy, souldiars. Anno 1581</title>
                 <author>Blandie, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 30 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>Lodowick Flood.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>MIght man ascend to see the sunne, to vewe the starres in skye:</l>
      <l>No doubt vnsweete the sight would be, might he not that discrye.</l>
      <l>Thinges long desierd are sweete, thinges farre vnknowen are sought:</l>
      <l>Thinges secret seekes themselues to shewe, as nature them hath taught.</l>
      <l>Where learning vttereth witt at will, and will to councell yeldes:</l>
      <l>There councell chargeth strength to stand, with sword, with speare and shield.</l>
      <l>Of no lesse prayse the penne in towne, then is the sword in field:</l>
      <l>For to the penne, as to the sword, ech Commonwealth must yeld.</l>
      <l>A Castle calde of Pollicye, a glasse, a myrrour loe:</l>
      <l>Where nature first commendes the man, then Art the worke doth showe.</l>
      <l>Where Mars doth fight with sword in hand, where Pallas pleades with quill:</l>
      <l>Where Neptune cutts the surging seas, where Ceres shewes her skill:</l>
      <l>Here runn<gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> the streames, here striues the states, here all are viewed with eye:</l>
      <l>Here triumphe sitts, here Trophes standes, here vertues throwne on hye.</l>
      <l>The force of foes, the fence of friendes, the pathes of Pollicye playne:</l>
      <l>Where valiāt mindes, where worthy wightes, the crowne of fame may gaine</l>
      <l>Sith Blandy seekes by Pollicye, his natiue soile to saue:</l>
      <l>Yeld due to Blandy worthy prayse, which Blandy ought to haue.</l>
      <l>Some saueye Zoilous here will swell, some peeuish Pan will poute:</l>
      <l>Some fond Suffenus fault will finde, some carping Creete will doubt.</l>
      <l>Alas poore man say some, and so in verdit passe</l>
      <l>How might he write of Pollicye, that Pollitick neuer was.</l>
      <l>Can any make Mausolus toumbe, that Cetiphon did not viewe:</l>
      <l>Or who can frame a Labarinth, that neuer Dedalus knewe.</l>
      <l>All coulours are not fitt nor fine, Alexanders shape to take:</l>
      <l>All kinde of woodes serues not the turne, Mercurius frame to make.</l>
      <l>Who thinkes Gordius knot to vnknitt, must first with Phaebus talke:</l>
      <l>Who striues to fishe with Vulcans nett, he must to Cuma walke.</l>
      <l>Tush, tush, his trueth, his traeuell tryde, his care, his zeale you see:</l>
      <l>His fayth, his loue, his payne with penne, must here commended be.</l>
      <l>Who in Treponius caue doth liue, shall with Cymmerians dye:</l>
      <l>Who drinkes of Lethens floud alway, the world shall him destroy.</l>
      <l>Were it not report of prayse, of fame, of glory, of gayne:</l>
      <l>Fewe or none would warre or write, that could not prayse attayne.</l>
      <l>Had Decius died as he had done, had Perseus ventured so:</l>
      <l>Had Theseus gone to Minotaure, had fame not bad him goe:</l>
      <l>Had Hercules Cerberus sought in hell, had Iason gone from Greece:</l>
      <l>Had Caesar Hasard sword and fier, had fame not fauored these:</l>
      <l>The laborer lookes to haue his hier, the venturer hopes for gayne:</l>
      <l>The writer well may weare a Crowne, which euer shall remaine.</l>
      <l>Sith fame doth sound the golden trumpe, and holdes the Crowne in hand:</l>
      <l>Let them approch to clayme the Crowne, which next to fame can stand.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>