<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Generous Reader.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104070_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03241</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13358</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104070</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Generous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pleasant dialogues and dramma's, selected out of Lucian, Erasmus, Textor, Ovid, &amp;c. With sundry emblems extracted from the most elegant Iacobus Catsius. As also certaine elegies, epitaphs, and epithalamions or nuptiall songs; anagrams and acrosticks; with divers speeches (upon severall occasions) spoken to their most excellent Majesties, King Charles, and Queene Mary. With other fancies translated from Beza, Bucanan, and sundry Italian poets. By Tho. Heywood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Hearne (Herne, Heron), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Oulton, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Slater (Slaughter), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 284, 20 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Generous Reader.</head>
   <p>REader, of what capacity or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion soever, I present unto thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable perusall a Miscellane of sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry straines in Poetry; which me thinks should not come altogether unwelcome to such as affect variety: here thou shalt finde choice and selected Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues borrowed from sundry Authors, both for the method and matter, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant and profitable. Which though I met with in Prose onely, yet upon bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter acquaintance, I have taught to goe upon even feet and number.</p>
   <p>For such as delight in Stage-poetry, here are also divers <hi>Dramma's,</hi> never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore published: Which though some may condemne for their shortnesse, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers againe will commend for their sweetnesse.</p>
   <p>From famous <hi>Iacobus Catsius,</hi> I have
<pb facs="4"/>
extracted Emblems of risk conceit, and excellent expression in the originall; Therefore I hope not to bee rejected in our native Tongue, howsoever by mee but rudely and coursely interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
   <p>Here are moreover divers speeches, at sundry times, and upon severall occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons spoken, either to one or both of their sacred Majesties. And other of the same condition, before other Noble Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages.</p>
   <p>Besides <hi>Epithalamions (or Nuptiall Songs)</hi> with <hi>Funerall Elegies, Epitaphs, Anagrams, &amp;c.</hi> Nor doubt I, but in the service of such change of dishes, there may be found amongst them, though not all to please every man, yet not any of them but may taste some one or others palat. For the better illustration of which. I have prefixed before every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular piece its proper Argument, with Annotations and observations of all such things as may appeare difficult or forreigne to the ignorant Reader. Which I intreat thee to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb facs="4"/>
as well in plaine iake, as were they curiously insculpt in Copper. Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I cannot t' onely that I take my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eave; Reader farewell. Read perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, examine strictly, but censure chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine, THO. HEYWOOD.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="5"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>