<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT EMINENT FAVOVRER and furtherer of all noble and free-borne studies, Sr HENRY YELUERTON Atturney Generall, accomplished happinesse.</title>
           <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1620</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104664_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16660</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3566</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104664</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT EMINENT FAVOVRER and furtherer of all noble and free-borne studies, Sr HENRY YELUERTON Atturney Generall, accomplished happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Essaies vpon the fiue senses : with a pithie one vpon detraction. Continued vvith sundry Christian resolues, full of passion and deuotion, purposely composed for the zealously-disposed. By Rich: Brathwayt Esquire</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Whitaker, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1620</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 142, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT EMINENT FAVOVRER and furtherer of all noble and free-borne studies, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> HENRY YELUERTON Atturney Generall, accomplished happinesse.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Haue long sought the expressiō of my thoughts, which haue euer with all sinceritie tendred them yours: but how infirme is conceit without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demonstration? Loue is a deepe effect of the soule, which vndisco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer'd,
<pb facs="3"/>
struggles, yea strangles her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe till shee be deliuer'd. I haue many times purposed to offer some <hi>vowes</hi> next to <hi>him,</hi> whose diurnall prouidence (if nought else should in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce) and his <hi>Maiestie,</hi> whose <hi>Halcyon-raigne</hi> makes vs happy, vnto <hi>your Selfe,</hi> to giue argument of my loue, the exquisite Idea of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane life; and now haue I seconded what I intended, though not in that perfection as my intirest wishes ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. It is a great defect (and I haue noted it) not in will but worke, nor in purpose but power, to see so many extended desires limit their issue to leane effects: which fareth vsually to best-affected dispositions, where affectionatest thoughts are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in silence for want of a tongue to discouer them. I will say no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for much speech rather argues affectation, than intimacie of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: here be certaine <hi>Essaies</hi> or
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Obseruations,</hi> or what you will, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating vpon the <hi>fiue Senses,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as to their proper Obiects and Subiects they are limited: where you shall finde (as questionlesse you haue found in your selfe) the <hi>eares</hi> choicest harmonie to be Gods glory, the <hi>eyes</hi> cleerest vision his contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, the <hi>noses</hi> sweetest posie, the odours of his mercy; the <hi>tastes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull'st fullnes, meditation of his goodnesse; the <hi>Touches</hi> mouingst action, the <hi>feeling</hi> of his Passion. Many subiects I confesse excellently composed, whose Title deriues their essence from <hi>Essaies;</hi> but few re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to these Obiects, which the devout Father termes those <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes</hi> which open to all vnbounded libertie; organs of weale or woe, happy if rightly tempered, sinister, if without limit. For in what erre wee and take not the occasion (as primitiue source) from one of these? The
<pb facs="4"/>
fable of the Syrens had allusion to the <hi>eare,</hi> of Ixion to the <hi>eye,</hi> of Ata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanta to the <hi>taste,</hi> of Mirrha to the <hi>smell,</hi> of Semele to the <hi>touch:</hi> where the <hi>eare</hi> not temperately restrained was soone inchanted, the <hi>eye</hi> lightly affected was to misery exposed, the <hi>taste</hi> for want of due relishing foyled her that was vanquishing, the <hi>smell</hi> too rankly breathing brought it selfe to perishing, the <hi>touch</hi> too highly aspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, through her ambition fell to ruine. These were excellent types, and not vnbeseeming the purest and piercingst eye: now it rests, that I draw in my sailes, least my <hi>gate</hi> be too <hi>great</hi> for my <hi>worke,</hi> onely thus much I may confidently say,
<q>
         <l>If my Presumption err, my thoughts replie,</l>
         <l>It is my loue that errs, it is not I.</l>
      </q>
may I euer so direct my subiect as to render you content, whose deseruing
<pb facs="4"/>
parts make me honour you, more then that title of honour which is confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on you, vowing to rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours in duest obseruance,</hi> Rich: Brathwaite.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>