<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument of this present
Summarie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104917_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18098</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4739</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104917</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument of this present
Summarie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Spanish colonie, or Briefe chronicle of the acts and gestes of the Spaniardes in the West Indies, called the newe world, for the space of xl. yeeres : written in the Castilian tongue by the reuerend Bishop Bartholomew de las Casas or Casaus, a friar of the order of S. Dominicke. And nowe first translated into english, by M.M.S</title>
                 <author>Casas, Bartolomé de las</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Broome (Brome, Browne), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>148 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="argument">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Argument of this present
Summarie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He state of thinges happened in the Indies,
euen from the time they were most won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully
discouered also since the Spaniards
for a while began to enhabite those places,
and afterward successiuely vnto these daies,
haue in all degrees bin so maruailous &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible
vnto such as haue not seen thē, that
they may seeme sufficient to darken and burie in obliuion and si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
whatsoeuer els haue passed in all former ages throughout
the world, howe great so euer is hath been, amongst which the
slaughters and murders of these innocent people, together with
the spoiles of townes, prouinces, &amp; kingdomes, which in those
parts haue bin perpretated, as also diuers others no lesse terrible
matters are not the least. These things whē <hi>dō Bart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>w de las
Casa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s,</hi> being made of a monke a bishop at his comming to the
court, there to enforme our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. &amp; M. the Emperor, as hauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
an eiewitnes of the same, had rehearsed to sundry persons, who
as yet were ignorant thereof, &amp; thereby hauing driuen the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers
into a kind of extasie &amp; maze, he was importunately reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted
briefly to set down in writing some of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> last,
which he did. But afterward seeing sundry persons who deuoyd
of remorse and compassion, being through auarice &amp; ambition,
degenerate frō all humanitie, and who by their execrable deedes
were grown into a reprobate sence, not being satisfied with such
fellonies &amp; mischiefs as they had committed in destroying such
a part of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world by all strāge kinds of cruelties, were now again
importunate vppon the King, to the ende vnder his authoritie
<pb facs="6"/>
and consent, they might once more returne to committe the
like, or worse, if worse might be, he determined to exhibite
the saide Summarie which he had in writing and record
vnto our Lorde the prince, to the ende his highnesse
might finde meanes that they shoulde be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
which he thought best to put in print,
to the ende, his highnesse might with
more ease reade the same. This
therefore was the cause of
this present Summarie,
or briefe informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>