<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader, mercie and peace in Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Holland, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104147_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03464</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13586</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104147</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader, mercie and peace in Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Holland, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Christian exercise of fasting, priuate and publike : plainly set forth by testimonies of holy Scriptures, and also of old and late writers: wherein is shewed how religious families priuatly, and the congregations publikely, haue humbled themselues before almightie God making vse of iudgements past, auoyding euils present, and preuenting future calamities, &amp;c. Together with sundrie abuses of fasting in three generations of hypocrites: the first in the dayes of the prophets: the second in the dayes of Christ: the third in the dayes of Antichrist. Hereunto also ar added some meditations on the 1. and 2. chapters of Iob, to comfort and instruct all such as be afflicted with any crosse, either inwardly in minde, or outwardly in bodie. By H. Holland, minister and preacher of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Holland, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>Orwin, Joan.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Young (Yong), William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 230, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the Christian Reader, mercie</hi> and peace in Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue endeuoured in this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise (Christian Reader) to lay open this argument of fasting plainly and truely according to the Scriptures. First, the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious abstinence is described: next the branches of the same, the priuat and the publike with their speciall notes and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences. Thirdly, I haue shewed what causes, and reasons haue moued the faithfull, to exercise themselues in the one and in the other. The priuat fast is onely commended in the practise of the faithfull of all ages. The publike is both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by precept, and commended by practise, and was both ordinary and extraordinary. And first for the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie we haue Gods great charge and law written. <hi>1. The 10.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Leuit 23.27.16.29.</note>
      <hi>day of the 7. moneth ye shall humble your soules. 2. Ye shall doe no worke at all, vers. 29.</hi> and it shall be a feast of <hi>Kippurim,</hi> a day of reconciliation.<note place="margin">Generall ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary fast.</note>
      <hi>4. throughout their dwellings, vers. 31. 5 an ordinance</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Leuit. 16.31.</note>
      <hi>for euer.</hi> The practise and obedience of this lawe wee haue noted. Heb. 9.7. <hi>But into the second</hi> (Tabernacle) <hi>went the high priest alone, once euery yeare, &amp;c.</hi> that is, this solemne day appoynted. This law of a general ordinary fast for the Iewes, may seeme to binde vs, and might no doubt bee profitable for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiās vnder the Gospel, if it were obserued. The cause of this fast (sayth one) was that the wrath of God might not break out, or being broken out, that it might bee a meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne it home againe: the same cause remaining, wise men will conclude the effect shall continue. Againe (sayth he)
<pb facs="5"/> this exercise being a meanes to humble a man before his God, was there any degree of humiliation, necessary for that people, which is not as needfull for vs? Nay, we hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued vnder the Gos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ell more benefits then they, the abuse of Gods good gifts and graces in vs, should driue vs to the lowest humiliation that can bee, so it bee lawfull and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable by the word of God.<note place="margin">Generall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie fast. Ioel. 1. chap. ver. 14. 2. cap. ver. 16.</note> The extraordinary was either signified by prophet, and so commanded of God immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as wee see by Ioel: or published by Gods Vicegerents, princes and priests, the presidents and gouernours of Gods people, as shall appeare by sundrie examples of the Scripture in this treatise following.</p>
   <p>Superstition hath euer preuailed in the world, where Gods grace and light was wanting, to corrupt all the pure worship of God, but neuer so much abused any one exercise of religion as this of fasting. The very Heathens abuse fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting in the worship of their false gods. The priests of Egypt euer abstained from flesh and wine, and thought this a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great deuotion. The wise men of Persia, their diet was but <hi>farina &amp; olus,</hi> course bread and hearbes. The wizards of India, when they came to the priesthood of the Sunne, did euer after abstaine from flesh. The priests of Egypt fasted <hi>3.</hi> dayes before they sacrificed. So the diuell commandeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurers to fast three dayes before any magicall practise of coniuration. And to be short, Mahomet extolleth fasting: for the Turkes fasted in the siege of Constantinople, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wonne the citie, ascribe this great victorie to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting. But to passe by these Pagans, and to come vnto the Church, for this corruption crept also into it, euen from the beginning.<note place="margin">Esay. 58. Zach. 7. &amp; ca. 8. Philo. Ioseph.</note> In the dayes of the Prophets it was thought a seruice which might highly commend a man with God. In the dayes of Christ, the Essees and Pharisees did farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the former ages in the abuse of fasting. And to come vnto the Gospel, Superstition in time did so gather strength, where light was quenched, that all the pure worship of God was at last quite thrust out of Church doores. The yeare of Christ <hi>220.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Anno.</hi> 220.</note> the Montanists began to be very superstitious in the abuse of fasting, and to set vp wil-worship, as appeares
<pb facs="5"/> with Tertullian in a whole treatise of fasting for herein he doth Montanize daungerously,<note place="margin">Tertul. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunio.</note> for following their very words and phrases, he sayth: <hi>Fasting is a meanes to purge vs from sinne and death, an expiation and satisfaction for sinne and a meanes to reconcile vs vnto God.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Anno. <hi>280.</hi> August. contrae Faustum. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>30.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> Anno. <hi>360.</hi>
      </note> After these the Manichees followed, commanding and teaching men to abstaine from all flesh, egges, wine, &amp;c. Then were spread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade into many parts of the world the monasticall lawes and rites of fasting, which first began in Egypt, and from thence came into Syria, and by meanes of Eustathius crept into Armenia, afterwards by Basill into Greece,<note place="margin">Basil &amp; Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen did weaken them selues to much with fasting.</note> and of Ambrose into Italy. About this time Basill began to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort mightily vnto fasting, and yet were no lawes made to binde consciences. But Epiphanius anon after made Bishop of Cyprus, began not onely to exhort, but also to commande lawes, and the times of fasting, &amp;c. as constitutions and traditions apostolicall, cleane contrary to the doctrine, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome and libertie of the old Church,<note place="margin">Sociates story is to be noted.</note> as appeareth with So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>21.</hi> For <hi>there was no Scripture or lawe written by the Apostles</hi> (sayth Socrates) <hi>concerning fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting.</hi> And Chrysostome counts fasting a thing indifferent:<note place="margin">Chrysostom homil, <hi>4.</hi> ad po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulum Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och.</note> his very words are these: <hi>Sunt quidam ciborum inter se,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Many striue about meates: so let vs striue and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to take away this custome of swearing (sayth he) and these wicked othes which men rap out so thicke amongst vs. This is better then all fasting. The care and time wee spend about abstinence from meates, let vs spend in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and labouring to abstaine from swearing. For it is madnes (sayth he) lightly to regard things forbidden, and to striue about things</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Ieiunium est ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>aphoron. Nos concessis abstinentes, prohibita au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus?</note>
      <hi>indifferēt. We be not forbidden to eate, but we be to sweare, &amp;c.</hi> If the holy writers had well considered those words of the Apostle,<note place="margin">Chrysost. homil. in Math. <hi>47.</hi> ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>untum in choro virtutū extremū certe sortitur locum.</note>
      <hi>bodily labour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits little, but pietie is profitable vnto all things:</hi> they would not so lightly haue fallen into those high and hyperbolicall commendations of fasting, which afterwards gaue such oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to Antichrist, to abuse this exercise in the Church of God. For when the man of sinne came to sit as generall and vniuersall Bishop in the seate of pestilence, then were
<pb facs="6"/> strong lawes made to binde consciences. The Popes schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did preach and write, that <hi>fasting was a worke to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase and merite grace,</hi>
      <note place="margin">August com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth much against the like in his time: Epist. <hi>119.</hi> what would he haue done, if he had seene the the ages folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note>
      <hi>pardon of sinnes, reconciliation with God, and a speciall worke to purchase heauen, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous effectuall and profitable for the quicke and dead.</hi> I speake their owne words, as after shall appeare. Thus then thou seest (Christian reader) what an argument this is which I vndertake to commend vnto the Church of God. I know it requires more strength and time then I haue or can haue any. Notwithstanding, I was thus moued and imboldened to publish this small treatise. First, for that I finde but few to haue done any thing in this manner in eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish of this argument. I haue written therefore that the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant might better know and more practise fasting: tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting that the Lord will in time supply what here is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Next, my desire is to stirre vp the faithfull people of God, because of some dangers threatned these times against vs, by prayer and fasting to begge a generall pardon of sins, and christian courage for prince and people, and our whole armie to fight the Lords battels. And to stop the mouthes of Machiuelists,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Com. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Ier.</hi> 38 4. 2. Thes. 2.11.</note> which are not ashamed to say, that preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prayer and fasting be meanes to cast downe, discourage, and to make a people faint hearted. And this doe fooles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue because they neither beleeue nor loue the trueth. But the spirit of God speaketh the contrary, testifying vnto vs of the courage and good successe of Ioshua, Dauid, Iehosha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat, Ezra, Nehemias, after prayer and fasting.</p>
   <p>Lastly, I was moued hereunto by the spitefull speeches and writings of our common aduersaries, who falsely accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing our profession, cry in the eares of the simple, and publish in their bookes, that wee <hi>count</hi>
      <note n="a" place="margin">Rhems. T. Acts. 13. cap. annot. Num. 3.</note>
      <hi>fasting but a morall and Christian temperance,</hi>
      <note place="margin">That fasting is a matter of policie we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer held, but that abstinēce from fleshe may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded for policies sake we confesse.</note>
      <hi>a fasting from sinne, &amp;c.</hi> And yet a more manifest calumniation: <note n="b" place="margin">Luke. cap. 2. <hi>Rhe. T. annot. Num.</hi> 17.</note>
      <hi>The heretikes count fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting</hi> (say they) <hi>but a matter of policie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>To answer these accusers. First I say vpon mature and deliberat consideration, and for good policie, doe the lawes of this kingdome commende an abstinence from flesh for some dayes in the weeke, &amp;c. For maintenance of nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb facs="6"/> for breeding and increase of cattell:<note place="margin">5. Eliz. cap. 5, title. certaine politique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions, made for maintenance of the nauie.</note> and that the trade of fishing and fish markets might be continued in our land: as by the very words of the statute may appeare. <hi>Be it further enacted by the authoritie aforesayd, for the benefit and commodities of this Realme, to grow aswel in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Nauie, as in sparing and increase of flesh, victuall, in this realme, &amp;c. that it shall not bee lawfull for any person or persons within this realme, to eate any flesh vpon any dayes now vsually obserued as fish dayes, vpon paine that euery person offending herein, shall forfeite 3. pounds for euery time he or they shall offend, or els suffer 3. moneths close imprisonment, without baile or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise.</hi> To this order is yet further added a good caution, as followeth. <hi>And because no manner of person shall mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudge of the intent of this statute, limiting orders to eate fish, and to forbeare eating of flesh, but that the same is purposely intended and meant politikely for the increase of Fishermen, and Mariners, &amp; repayring of Port-townes, and nauigation, and not for any superstition to bee main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the choyce of meates: be it enacted, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer shall, by preaching, teaching, writing, or open speech notifie, that any eating of fish, or forbearing of flesh, mentioned in this statute, is of any necessitie, for the sauing of the soules of men, or that it is the seruice of God, otherwise then as other politike lawes are to be, that then such persons shall be punished as spreaders of false newes are and ought to bee.</hi> And this is the Christian policie which our friends, of Rhemes haue stumbled vpon. This abstinence commaunded by our lawes, is an abstinence for order sake, as the learned Ierome speaketh; which whosoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer disliketh is no friend to the common wealth,<note place="margin">
         <p>
            <hi>Ordinis causa, com. in Gal. cap</hi> 5.</p>
         <p>A good rule for things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</p>
         <p>
            <hi>Epist.</hi> 118. Note the word contrary.</p>
      </note> and may well be accounted a man of weake iudgement: for as Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine speaketh wisely, <hi>Quod neque contra fidem, ne{que} contra bonos mores iniungitur, indifferenter est haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, &amp; pro eorum inter quos viuitur societate seruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. Looke whatsoeuer is inioyned</hi> by order, <hi>that is not contrarie to saith, nor contrarie to good maners, that we must repute as a thing indifferent, and obserue the same
<pb facs="7"/> for that societie sake wherein we liue.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And yet I further answer the Rhemish aduersaries that our godly wise gouernours, Church, and people, doe also tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in heart imbrace the religious abstinence described and commended of God in his word, &amp; haue &amp; doe practise the same when occasions are offered and as need requireth. And this shall well appeare also by a publique fast comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by our gouernours, and kept in our Church in <hi>Anno 1563.</hi> For then, first our most gracious Queene meued with a motherly affection for the mortalitie of her subiects and people, signifieth her good liking of a Christian fast, by her princely and expresse charge,<note place="margin">Archbishop Canterburie, Math. Parker.</note> to the Archbishop then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, all which as a worthie president for all posterities I haue inserted, as followeth: <hi>Most reuerend father in God, right trustie, and right welbeloued, we greete you well: Like as Almightie God hath of his meere grace, committed to vs next vnder him, the chiefe gouernment of this realme and the people therein: so hath he of his like goodnes, ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnder vs sundry principall ministers, to serue and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist vs in this burden. And therefore considering the state of this present time, wherein it hath pleased the most high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, for the amendment of vs and our people, to visite cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine places of our realme with more contagious sicknes, then lately hath beene: for remedie and mitigation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, wee thinke it both necessarie and our bounden dutie, that vniuersall prayer and fasting be more effectually vsed in this our realme. And vnderstanding that you haue thought and considered vpon some good order to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed therein, for the which yee require the application of our authoritie, for the better obseruation thereof, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst our people, we doe not onely commend and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your good zeale therein, but wee also commaund all maner of our ministers ecclesiasticall, ciuill, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our subiects to execute, follow, and obey such godly and wholesome orders, as you being primate of all Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Metropolitane of this prouince of Canterburie, vpon godly aduise and consideration, shall vniformely deuise, prescribe, and publish for the vniuersall vsage of
<pb facs="7"/> prayer, fasting, and other good deeds,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The order of the fast com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by the Queene, and published in print by the Archbishop of Canterburie. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1563.</note>
      <hi>during the time of the visitation by sicknes and other troubles: Giuen vnder our Signet at our Mannour of Richmond the 1. day of August, the 5. yeare of our raigne.</hi> The order then prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by this Archbishop, and practised by the people was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended as followeth. <hi>It is most euident to them that read the scriptures, that both in the old Church vnder the lawe, and in the primitiue Church vnder the Gospel, the people of God hath alwaies vsed generall generall fasting, both in times of common calamities, as warres, famine, pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, &amp;c. and also when any waightie matter, touching the estate of the Church, or the common wealth was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne or intended. And it cannot bee denied, but that in this our time, wherein many things haue been reformed, according to the doctrine and examples of Gods worde, and the primitiue Church, this part for fasting and absti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, being alwaies in the scripture as a necessarie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion ioyned to feruent praier, hath been too much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. Wherefore for some beginning of redresse herein, it hath beene thought meete to the Queenes maiestie, that in this contagious time of sicknes, and other troubles and vnquietnes, according to the examples of the godly king Iehosaphat, and the king of Niniuie, with others, a general fast should be ioyned with generall prayer throughout her realme,</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Chro. 20. Ionas. 3.</note>
      <hi>and to bee obserued of all her godly subiects in manner and forme following. 1.</hi> First, it is ordained that the wednesday of euery weeke shall be the day appointed for this generall fast. <hi>2.</hi> All persons betweene the age of <hi>16.</hi> yeares and <hi>60.</hi> (sicke folkes and labourers in haruest, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great labours only excepted) shall eate but one only cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent and moderate meale vpon euery wednesday. In which said meale shalbe vsed very sober and spare diet, without va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of kinds of meate, dishes, spices, cōfectiōs, or wines, but only such as may serue for necessitie, comelines and health. <hi>3.</hi> Item, in that meale, it shalbe indifferēt to eate flesh or fish, so that their quantitie be small, and no varietie or delicacie be sought. Wherein euery man hath to answer to God, if he in such godly exercises either contemne publike order, or
<pb facs="8"/> dissemble with God, pretending abstinence, &amp; doing nothing lesse. 4. Item, those that bee of wealth and abilitie, ought that day to abate and diminish the costlines, and varietie of their fare, and increase therewith their liberalitie &amp; almes towards the poore, that the same poore which either indeede lacke foode, or els that which they haue is vnseasonable and cause of sicknes, may therby be relieued, and charitably suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured, to be maintained in health. <hi>5.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> Item, that a Sermon bee had, preached by such as bee authorized, and the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher to intreate of such matters especially as bee meete for this cause of publike prayer, &amp;c. <hi>6.</hi> Last of all, this day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this manner appointed for a day of generall prayer and fasting, ought to be bestowed by them, which may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare from bodily labour, in prayer, studie, reading, or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Scriptures, or good exhortations, &amp;c. And when any dulnes or wearines shall arise, then to bee occupied in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther godly exercises: but no part therof to be spent in plaies, pastimes, or idlenes, much lesse in lewd, wicked, or wanton be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour.</p>
   <p>I haue thus purposely set before thine eyes, Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an reader, the religious care of our good Prince and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, partly to stop the mouthes of aduersaries, which perswade men that wee despise fasting: partly to stirre vp Gods faithfull people of all degrees,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Anno</hi> 1588.</note> to renue their zeale in the true profession of the Gospell. And to conclude, we haue seene some yeares past,<note place="margin">1593.</note> a comfortable experience of Gods blessing vpon the priuate and publike fastings and prayers of Gods people in the land. Wherefore let vs in assurance of faith draw neere vnto God, &amp; humbly cast downe our solues againe, in prayer &amp; fasting, to cōfute aduersaries slāders, to euert enemies practises, to the glorie of God, protection and deliuerance of his Church, confirmation of our owne faith, soules and consciences, by and through Iesus Christ: to whom with the Father, and most holy spirit, three distinct persons, one inuisible, euerliuing and euerlasting God, be all praise for euer, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord Christ Iesu, <hi>Henry Holland.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>