<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface of Simon Steuin.</title>
           <author>Steuin, Simon</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104599_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12970</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23264</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104599</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface of Simon Steuin.</title>
                 <author>Steuin, Simon</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Disme: the art of tenths, or, Decimall arithmetike : teaching how to perform all computations whatsoeuer, by whole numbers without fractions, by the foure principles of common arithmeticke: namely addition, subtraction, multiplication, and diuision. Inuented by the excellent mathematician, Simon Steuin. Published in English with some additions by Robert Norton, Gent</title>
                 <author>Stevin, Simon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Astley, Hugh.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 1 leaf of plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Preface of Simon Steuin.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>To Astronomers, Land-meaters, Measurers of Tapistry, Gaudgers, Stereometers in generall, Monty-Masters, and to all Marchants,</salute>
      <signed>Simon Steuin</signed>
      <salute>wisheth health.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any seeing the smalnes of this Book, and considering your worthynes to whō it is dedicated, may perchance esteeme this our conceyte absurd: But if the proportion be considered, the small quantity hereof compared to humane imbecility, and the great vtility vnto high and ingenious intendiments, it will be found to haue made comparison of the extreame tearmes, which permit not any conuersion of proportion. But what of that? is this an admirable inuention? No cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly: for it is so meane, as that it scant deserueth the name of an inuentiō: for as the coūtryman by chance sometime findeth a great treasure, without any vse of skill or cunning, so hath it hapned herein. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any will thinke, that I vaunt my selfe of my knowledge, because of the explicatiō of these vtilities, out of doubt, he sheweth himselfe to haue neyther iudgemēt, vnderstanding, nor knowledge to discerne<pb facs="7"/>simple things from ingenious inuentions, but he (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) seemeth enuious of the common benefite: yet howsoeuer, it were not fit to omit the benefit hereof, for the inconuenience of such calumny. But as the Mariner hauing by hap found a certaine vnknowne Island, spareth not to declare to his Prince the riches and profits thereof; as the fayre fruits, precious mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls, pleasant champions, &amp;c. and that without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Philautry: euen so shall we speake freely of the great vse of this inuention; I call it great, being greater then any of you expect to come from me. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then that the matter of this Disme (the cause of the name whereof shalbe declared by the first difini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion following) is number, the vse and effects of which, yourselues shall sufficiently witnes by your continuall experiences, therefore it were not necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to vse many words thereof: for the Astrologer knoweth, that the world is become by computation Astronomicall (seing it teacheth the Pilot the eleuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Equator and of the Pole, by meanes of the declination of the Sunne, to describe the true Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, Lātitudes, situatiōs &amp; distances of places, &amp;c.) a Paradise, aboūding in some places with such things as the Earth cannot bring forth in other. But as the sweet is neuer without the sowre: so the trauayle in such computations cannot be vnto him hidden, namely, in the busy multiplications and diuisions which proceed of the 60 progression of degrees, minutes, seconds, thirds, &amp;c. And the Surueyor or Land-meater knoweth, what great benefite the world<pb facs="8"/>receyueth from his science, by which many dissensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and difficulties are auoyded, which otherwise would arise by reason of the vnknowne capacity of Land: besides, he is not ignorant (especially whose busines and imployment is great) of the troublesome multiplications of Roods, Feete, and oftentimes of ynches, the one by the other, which not onely mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesteth, but also often (though he be very well experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced) causeth error, tending to the dāmage of both parties, as also to the discredit of Land-meater or sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyor, and so for the Money-masters, Marchants and each one in his busines: therefore how much they are more worthy, and the meanes to attayne them the more laborious, so much the greater and better is this Disme, taking away those difficulties: But howe? it teacheth (to speake in a word) the easy performance of all reckonings, computations, &amp; accounts, without broken numbers, which can happen in mans busines, in such sort, as that the foure Principles of Arithmetick namely, <hi>Addition, Substractiō, Multiplication, &amp; Devisiō,</hi> by whole numbers, may satisfie these effects, afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the like facility vnto those that vse Coūters. Now if by those meanes wee gaine the time which is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, if hereby that be saued which otherwise should be lost, if so, the paines, controuersy, error, dammage, and other inconueniences commonly hapning ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, be eased, or taken away, then I leaue it willingly vnto your iudgements to be censured: and for that, that some may say that certaine inuentions at the first seeme good, which when they come to be practized,
<pb facs="8"/>effect nothing of worth, as it often hapneth to the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of strong mouing, which seeme good in small proofes and modells, when in great, or comming to the effect, they are not worth a Button: whereto we answere, that herein is no such doubt: for expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience dayly sheweth the same: namely, by the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize of diuers expert Land-meaters of
<hi>Holland,</hi> vnto whom we haue shewed it, who (laying aside that which each of them had, according to his owne man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, inuented to lessen their paines in their computati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) do vse the same to their great contentment, and by such fruit as the nature of it witnesseth, the due ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect necessarily followeth: The like shall also happen to each of your selues vsing the same as they doe: meane while liue in all felicity.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>