<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Author to the Reader, concerning the Topographicall Glasse.</title>
           <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104220_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03653</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13783</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104220</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Author to the Reader, concerning the Topographicall Glasse.</title>
                 <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Speculum topographicum: or The topographicall glasse : Containing the vse of the topographicall glasse. Theodelitus. Plaine table, and circumferentor. With many rules of geometry, astronomy, topography perspectiue, and hydrography. Newly set forth by Arthur Hopton Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 203, 9 pages, 2 folded leaves of plates, illustrations, maps, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Author to the Reader, concerning the Topographicall Glasse.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>COme you, whose eyes stand not in enuious head,</l>
      <l>Whose tongue with Criticke humors is not fed,</l>
      <l>And in this Glasse, vnto your comfort view,</l>
      <l>Such needfull workes that much may profit you.</l>
      <l>The grounds of Art haue brought it forth for thee,</l>
      <l>Which we haue suckt from famous Geometrie,</l>
      <l>With Theorm's mixt and demonstrations rare,</l>
      <l>Such as in hiddan Propositions are:</l>
      <l>Heer's no vaine shew: illusions haue no place,</l>
      <l>No spirit confind, no hatefull painted face,</l>
      <l>No eye-deceiuing glasse, no Cristall braue,</l>
      <l>Which from the frozen seas we often haue.</l>
      <l>But in a faire and most perspicuous light,</l>
      <l>The earthy Globe lies subiect to thy sight.</l>
      <l>Whose Center's deepe, whose continent is great,</l>
      <l>Here mixt with cold, and there with burning heat:</l>
      <l>As <hi>Phoebus</hi> beames do sparkling from him glide,</l>
      <l>Or as in torrid Zones we do abide.</l>
      <l>This frame enough for all the world to view,</l>
      <l>This Glasse layes in a small proportion true.</l>
      <l>That like an Eagle towring vp aloft,</l>
      <l>Whole regions thou mayst view and reuiew oft.</l>
      <l>Discoursing now of Europe in particular,</l>
      <l>And then of other Countries distant farre.</l>
      <l>Now of <hi>Ierusalem</hi> that was before,</l>
      <l>And then of <hi>Rome,</hi> by Tybers siluer shore.</l>
      <l>See here mount <hi>Sion</hi> and mount <hi>Moria</hi> then,</l>
      <l>That on their backes bare old <hi>Ierusalem:</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Though now mount <hi>Caluarie</hi> hath got the grace,</l>
      <l>Which erst was but an execution place.</l>
      <l>Learne here to bound the Alpes, <hi>Spaine, France</hi> and all,</l>
      <l>That yeelds those vines whence iuycie grapes do fall.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>America,</hi> the new found land beside,</l>
      <l>And eke those Southerne parts yet vndiscride.</l>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <l>See how to measure plot, and part out lands;</l>
      <l>As drest in <hi>Floras</hi> sommer robes it stands.</l>
      <l>Or as it's rent vp with the tering plowe,</l>
      <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> hid with f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>eezing ice or melting snowe:</l>
      <l>See here the height of hils, or see their ods,</l>
      <l>That Gyants meant to dart against the gods.</l>
      <l>See here the Sunne, whose beames do Comets fire,</l>
      <l>That all the world with terror may admire.</l>
      <l>Behold the Moone, and fixed Starres so bright,</l>
      <l>That guide the Pilots in the darkest night.</l>
      <l>Looke how the Planets with the whirling Sphere,</l>
      <l>To our Horizon fierie meteots beare.</l>
      <l>Gilding the blacke brow of the vgly night,</l>
      <l>With burning Dragons and such fearefull light.</l>
      <l>Looke on them all: see in this little Glasse,</l>
      <l>Their heigth so tooke as ne'r in English was.</l>
      <l>Wouldst plant a Towne, or situate a house,</l>
      <l>Or force the water take a wished course.</l>
      <l>Wouldst seeke the heigth or distance of a Towne,</l>
      <l>Or vndermine a Fort to blow it downe▪</l>
      <l>Or what wouldst do belonging to this Art,</l>
      <l>But in this Glasse thou mayst behold apart?</l>
      <l>Then vse him well, my word I pawne, he's true,</l>
      <l>Let small defects be but supplide by you.</l>
      <l>Of which few scapt my Pen, no store the Presse,</l>
      <l>Where either be, in kindnesse vse redresse.</l>
      <l>So shall my Pen not be imployd in vaine,</l>
      <l>To please thee more when I do write againe.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Arthur Hopton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>