<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, GENE∣rous, and euer-worthy Louer of Goodnesse, and Pious Endeauours, WALTER LEIGH, Esquire, SWORD-BEARER to the Honourable LORD-MAIORS of this Famous Citie of LONDON.</title>
           <author>B., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104667_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16822</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3722</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104667</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, GENE∣rous, and euer-worthy Louer of Goodnesse, and Pious Endeauours, WALTER LEIGH, Esquire, SWORD-BEARER to the Honourable LORD-MAIORS of this Famous Citie of LONDON.</title>
                 <author>B., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vveeping lady: or, London like Niniuie in sack-cloth : Describing the mappe of her owne miserie, in this time of her heauy visitation; with her hearty prayers, admonition, and pious meditations, as the occasions of them offer themselues in her passion. Written by T.B</title>
                 <author>T. B. (Thomas Brewer)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Browne, Nathaniel.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Rhodes, Matthew</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and euer-worthy Louer of Goodnesse, and Pious Endeauours, WALTER LEIGH, <hi>Esquire,</hi> SWORD-BEARER to the Honourable LORD-MAIORS <hi>of this Famous Citie of LONDON.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Worthy Sir:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Sad Sharer of the common miseries of these sad times, prompted by his owne Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, ha's, (though too weak a Pencil-Man for such a Piece) vndertaken to draw that Sorrow to the Life, that ha's drawne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousands to Death; my Title speaks my meaning; The Wounds of this VVEEPING LADY.</p>
   <p>To haue drawne Her in her <hi>Health,</hi> the <hi>Idea</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
or Conceptions of the most pure and pregnant VVits might haue been deficient, such was Her Beauty, Her Splendor, such were her change of Colours, Glorious within, and without in Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broydered Garments. But now, (such is her Change Shee ha's no Change, wearing only one Suit, and that the sad habit of <hi>Mourning.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>In thus presenting Her, I present you with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but grones, Sighs, tears, shreaks, folding of armes, bearing of brests, wringing of hands, pale looks, deiected eies, bleeding hearts, &amp; most hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy &amp; bitter condolements. How vnpleasing this might be to many, I am not ignorant; but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned by that of the <hi>Preacher, The Heart of the Wise is in the House of Mourning, &amp;c.</hi> my hopes are faire of her fauorable and gracious receiuing.</p>
   <p>To whom better to present this <hi>Lady</hi> of so many Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lords, then to your worthy Selfe, I know not; your Worship hauing been to many, &amp; now to This, Her Last, (equall in fame with any from Her First) a prime and much respected Officer, beating the <hi>Sword</hi> that most impartially guards Her, and wounds Her Enemies. Shee is now on the mending hand, and our hope (in Him, that what he wil doe can doe) is strong for the dayly decrease of her <hi>sorrowes</hi>; the speedy returne to Her <hi>solace,</hi> and fulnesse of Beauty and lustre. For which among many Thousands of Her afflicted Sons and Daughters, incessantly praying; I rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Euer Bound to your VVorshi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> pleasure: T. B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>