<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the Right worshipfull syr William Winter Knight, Mai∣ster of the Queenes Maiesties Ordi∣naunce by Sea, Suruaior of her highnesse marine causes. &amp;c. William Bourne wisheth increase of woorship vn∣to the state of honour and true felicitie.</title>
           <author>Bourne, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104686_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16518</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3432</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104686</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the Right worshipfull syr William Winter Knight, Mai∣ster of the Queenes Maiesties Ordi∣naunce by Sea, Suruaior of her highnesse marine causes. &amp;c. William Bourne wisheth increase of woorship vn∣to the state of honour and true felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Bourne, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A booke called the treasure for traueilers : deuided into fiue bookes or partes, contaynyng very necessary matters, for all sortes of trauailers, eyther by sea or by lande, written by William Bourne</title>
                 <author>Bourne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 32, 1, 25, 1, 22, 2, 21, 3, 5-16, 4 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the Right worshipfull syr William Winter Knight, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of the Queenes Maiesties Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce by Sea, Suruaior of her highnesse marine causes. &amp;c. William Bourne wisheth increase of woorship vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the state of honour and true felicitie.</head>
   <p>WHat great commoditie and profit Right worthy &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull Knight, hath alwaies redownded vnto the common weale, and gouern ours of the same, which in martial affaires and warlike discipline, haue chiefely delighted and taken great paines and care in the same, and vnto what excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fame and renowme it hath alwayes brought and exalted vnto high dignitie, those that haue taken vpon them, for their Prince and Countries prosperitie great exploytes, rather putting them selues in daunger of their liues, then their Prince and Country shoulde bee dishonoured. Then I may say without any obiection or doubt, that your woorship is one: For I my selfe can witnesse, and of my owne knowledge, know, that no person in this Land hath such great iudgement and knowledge in martial affaires by Sea, both touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the shipping, for that purpose, and also the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for the same, as your woorship hath: and as for your courage, valiantnesse, and wisdome, which is not vnknowne vnto the worlde, whereas I being most symple haue written this base and rude volume, whiche I doo call a Treasure for Trauaylers,
<pb facs="3"/>
am so bolde to dedicate it vnto your worship, not for that the Booke is worthy to be preferred vnto so wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a person, but for my bounden duetyes sake, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my good wyll towardes your worship, for that I haue most largelye tasted of your beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence towards mee, being as a poore Gunner, seruing vnder your worthinesse, hoping that your woorship will take this simple woorke in good part: the which woorke is deuided into fiue Bookes, the fyrst is Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrie perspectiue, the second Booke is appertainyng vnto Cosmographie, the thirde Booke is Geometrie general, the fourth Booke is Statick, and the fyfth and last Booke is appertayning vnto natural Philosophie, as the contentes of the matter doo appeare in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Bookes, hoping that your worship wil take this simple thing, as a true token of my good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes you, although the thing it selfe be but rude &amp; simple. And thus, I ceasse to trouble your worship any longer, at this time, beseeching the liuing God to prosper you in al your affayres, in perfect health, with all your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and familie, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>By your worships at commaundement,</hi> William Bourne.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>