<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the Right Honorable, vertu∣ous and affable Lady Margaret Countesse of Darby.</title>
           <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104926_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68420</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16955</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104926</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the Right Honorable, vertu∣ous and affable Lady Margaret Countesse of Darby.</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A thousand notable things, of sundry sortes : VVherof some are wonderfull, some straunge, some pleasant, diuers necessary, a great sort profitable and many very precious</title>
                 <author>Lupton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Spooner, Hugh</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 302, 18 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Culinary arts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>❧ To the Right Honorable, vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and affable Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> Countesse of Darby.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I haue taken some paines and trauell (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) to pleasure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit manye, by the publishing such rare, straung &amp; excellent thinges, as many could haue byn content to hide and keepe secrete: Euen so I haue byn carefull, to dedicate the same to some worthy and meete Personage, that woulde take the same th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>kful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, peruse the same willingly, and imbrace it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. And though I am acquainted with som, know diuerse, and heare of many, to whome I might well and worthely present the same: yet amongst all other, I haue chosen your good Ladishippe of goodwill and zeale (pardon my rude rashnesse I beseech you) to haue the first smell of these sweete, pleasant, straung, beautifull and precious Flowers, not growing in one Garden: but in sundry Soyles, not quickly found, but long agathering, and not all of one property, but of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse quallities. Whose Affabillitie hath allurde mee: whose Curtesie hath compelde mee, and whose Fame hath inforst me, thus boldely or rather presumptuously
<pb facs="2"/>
to offer you the same. And though at the firste it maye seeme too simple for you, yet I am certaine, that diuers thinges therin will delight you, some will also satisfy you, part therof will peasure you, sundry from harmes may shielde you, plenty of them may preserue you, and a number besides needefull for you. Beseeching your Honor not to respect the Geuer, but the Gyft: not the Man, but the Matter: not the Skill, but the Will. Whiche if you accept as willinglye, as I offerre faythfully: I shall thinke my long paynes and trauell therein fully recompenst. Thus ceasing herein any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to trouble your Honor, do commit you to the cus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tody of him, whose wisdome first framd vs, whose fauor dooth feede vs, whose might dooth maintaine vs, whose goodnes dooth guide vs, and whose power dooth protect vs.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honorable L. most humble to commaund <hi>Thomas Lupton.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>