<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In commendation of Poetry.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104175_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03504</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13626</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104175</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In commendation of Poetry.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The strange, vvonderfull, and bloudy battell betweene frogs and mise : the occasion of their falling out: their preparation, munition, and resolution for the warres: the seuerall combats of euery person of worth; with many other memorable accidents. Interlaced with diuers pithy and morall sentences, no lesse pleasant to be read, then profitable to be obserued. Couertly decyphering the estate of these times. Paraphrastically done into English heroycall verse by W.F. C.C.C</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Bailey, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>In commendation of Poetry.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the diuers currents that do flow</l>
      <l>Frōth' euer-springing fountain of all art,</l>
      <l>The perled Nectar most contēt doth show,</l>
      <l>Which Poetry full sweetly doth impart,</l>
      <l>VVhose hunny'd vapour comforteth the heart,<note place="margin">Aut pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desse vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t, aut delect are Poc<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>, aut simul.</note>
      </l>
      <l>And vnder vailed fancies that doth sing,</l>
      <l>Which doth much profit with great pleasure bring</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For cert's the truth (though truth no colours need</l>
      <l>To men of vnderstanding and ripe yeeres)</l>
      <l>VVhen she is masked in a seemely weed,</l>
      <l>More faire, more sweet, and beautifull appeares,</l>
      <l>Her tale contents the mind, and glads the eares,</l>
      <l>And makes men more attentiue to her story,</l>
      <l>That truth may still preuayle with greater glory:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For as an Image drawne in white and black,</l>
      <l>Though it be well proportioned with care,</l>
      <l>If it do other comely colours lack,</l>
      <l>To beautify the members, head, and haire,</l>
      <l>Vnto the eye appeares not halfe so faire;</l>
      <l>Nor with so much content doth fill the mind,</l>
      <l>As that pourtrayd with colours in his kind:</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Eu'n so a naked storie simply told,</l>
      <l>Though cause be true and worthy due regard,<note place="margin">Vt pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Poesis erit.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Doth not mens hearts with such affection hold,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>
Nor hath the outward sences so in gard,</l>
      <l>As doth that matter which is well declar'd,</l>
      <l>Adorned pleasantly with termes and arte,</l>
      <l>Which pearcing th'row the eares, doth moue the
heart.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This knew the learned Poets all of yore,</l>
      <l>This knew th' immortall Sages long agone,</l>
      <l>VVhose works the wisest of our age adore,</l>
      <l>Such store of wisdome in their bookes is shone,</l>
      <l>Such pleasure vnto all, offence to none,</l>
      <l>Such graue precepts hid vnder fine deuice,</l>
      <l>As eares and heart with wonderment surprise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>No fable sweet <hi>Philosophy</hi> contaynes,</l>
      <l>VVithin the sacred volumes of her cell,</l>
      <l>Dipt in the fount, which from<note n="*" place="margin">A hill cōsecrate to the Muses.</note>
         <hi>Pernassus</hi> straynes,</l>
      <l>Whereas the thrice three <hi>Nymphes</hi> are said to dwel,</l>
      <l>That <hi>Barbarisme</hi> and ignorance expell:</l>
      <l>But vnder vaile deepe secrets doth vnfold,</l>
      <l>Though bnt a tale by wanton <hi>Ouid</hi> told.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>By wanton <hi>Ouid?</hi> heauenly Poesie</l>
      <l>Pardon the rashnesse of my infant Muse,</l>
      <l>That I, a client to thy mysterie,</l>
      <l>Should vnaduised by that word abuse,<note place="margin">Vita ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recunda est, Musa iocosa mea.</note>
      </l>
      <l>And terme him wanton, did no folly vse:</l>
      <l>For though his Muse was wanton, as he playned,</l>
      <l>Yet <hi>Ouids</hi> life was chaste, and neuer stayned.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>
Nor sung he alwayes in a wanton lay,</l>
      <l>And penned pleasing ditties of blind fire:</l>
      <l>Of deeper matters much could <hi>Ouid</hi> say,</l>
      <l>As he whose soaring spirit mounted higher,</l>
      <l>Than euer Poet after could aspire.</l>
      <l>And saue the famous <hi>Homer</hi> chiefe of all,</l>
      <l>
         <note n="*" place="margin">Semper Virgilium excipio,</note> The Prince of Poets may we <hi>Ouid</hi> call.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But neyther <hi>Homer, Ouid,</hi> nor the rest,</l>
      <l>That euer tasted<note n="*" place="margin">A foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</note>
         <hi>Aganippes</hi> spring,</l>
      <l>Though but to write of fables they addrest,</l>
      <l>VVhich to th'vnskilfull no contentment bring,</l>
      <l>But with such arte and knowledge did them sing,</l>
      <l>That in their volumes scarce appeares one lyne,</l>
      <l>VVhich to the learned doth not seeme diuine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>No vice of youth, no villayny of age,</l>
      <l>No lewd behauiour of each degree,</l>
      <l>But in the secret myst'ries of the sage,</l>
      <l>And graue instructions of Philosophy,<note place="margin">Ficta quidem narratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, sed verac<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione haec dicuntur.</note>
      </l>
      <l>Clad in the habit of sweet Poesie,</l>
      <l>Is aptly cowched in some prety fable,</l>
      <l>As well the learned to discusse are able.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And not alone are vices set to view,</l>
      <l>And horrid plagues attending wickednesse:</l>
      <l>But blessed vertue with the heauenly crew,</l>
      <l>VVhich euer wayt vpon her worthynesse,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="6"/>
By them are pourtrayd forth with comlinesse:</l>
      <l>The meanest fable Poet e're did make,</l>
      <l>May stand as mirrour for example sake.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For proofe whereof read but this little booke,</l>
      <l>VVith vnderstanding, knowledge, care and skill,</l>
      <l>And thou shalt find presented to thy looke,</l>
      <l>Such wit and learning from the Authours quill,</l>
      <l>VVhich vnder fine inuentions meet thee still;</l>
      <l>So pleasant obiects that occurre thine<note n="*" place="margin">The eyes of thy mind</note> eyes,</l>
      <l>As will thy soule with wonderment surprise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And not alone shall pleasure thee awate,</l>
      <l>As thou perusest what I now present;</l>
      <l>Here thou shalt haue fit matter for eche state,</l>
      <l>If thou consider what hereby is ment.</l>
      <l>Then thinke thy time herein not idly spent:</l>
      <l>Ponder with iudgemēt what thou read'st at leasure;</l>
      <l>So may thy profit equallize thy pleasure.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>