<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE LORD
Robert Devorax, Earle of Essex and
EWE, Vicount of Hereford and Bourchier, Lord Ferrers
of Chartley, Bourchier and Lovaine, Master of the
Queenes Maiesties Horse, and Knight of the most
Honourable order of the Garter. H. H. wisheth
with his heart, grace from God the Father by
Iesus Christ, increase of al vertues, and con∣stancie
in the truth of the Gospell
to the ende.</title>
           <author>Holland, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104153_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03468</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13590</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104153</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE LORD
Robert Devorax, Earle of Essex and
EWE, Vicount of Hereford and Bourchier, Lord Ferrers
of Chartley, Bourchier and Lovaine, Master of the
Queenes Maiesties Horse, and Knight of the most
Honourable order of the Garter. H. H. wisheth
with his heart, grace from God the Father by
Iesus Christ, increase of al vertues, and con∣stancie
in the truth of the Gospell
to the ende.</title>
                 <author>Holland, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise against vvitchcraft: or A dialogue, wherein the greatest doubts concerning that sinne, are briefly answered : a Sathanicall operation in the witchcraft of all times is truly prooued: the moste precious preseruatiues against such euils are shewed: very needful t be knowen of all men, but chiefly of the masters and fathers of families, that they may learn the best meanes to purge their houses of all vnclean spirits, and wisely to auoide the dreadfull impieties and greate daungers which come by such abhominations. Hereunto is also added a short discourse, containing the most certen meanes ordained of God, to discouer, expell, and to confound all the Sathanicall inuentions of witchcraft and sorcerie</title>
                 <author>Holland, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64, 24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
HONOVRABLE LORD
Robert Devorax, Earle of Essex and
EWE, Vicount of Hereford and Bourchier, Lord Ferrers
of Chartley, Bourchier and Lovaine, Master of the
Queenes Maiesties Horse, and Knight of the most
Honourable order of the Garter. H. H. wisheth
with his heart, grace from God the Father by
Iesus Christ, increase of al vertues, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie
in the truth of the Gospell
to the ende.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Scriptures of God <hi>(right Honourable)</hi> in sundrie
places, doe most euidently teach vs, that there are two
spirituall kingdomes in this world, which haue conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual
hatred &amp; bloody wars, without hope of truce for
euer The Lord and king of the one, is our Lord Iesus,
the tyrannical vsurper of the other, is Sathan, Again,
this also we are as clearely taught, that all men liuing
without exception, are eyther true subiects of the one,
or slaues vnto the other. For albeit, the Neuters of this worlde, dreame that
they may indifferentlie view the scarres and woundes of other men, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
approch neere those bloody skirmishes: yet the truth is, they are fowlie
deceiued: for the great Lord and King hath said with his owne mouth,<note place="margin">Matth. 12. 30.</note>
      <hi>Hee
that is not with mee, is against mee.</hi> Wherefore, all that build not vp, as much as
in them lyeth, the kingdome and Citie of God, and batter downe the holdes
of Sathan, must be numbred with the rebels and enemies of our Lord Christ,
when the warrefare shalbe ended. The enemies of Christ haue euer beene
many, some open, cruell, foes without: some subtill, close conspirators with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
the house of God, most daungerous vnderminers of the Citie of God, if
they be not discouered. In this secret conspiracie, albeit Sathan haue many
Champions, and many artes, <hi>mille artes, mille nocendi modos:</hi> there is no
arte more effectuall and dreadfull in my iudgement, then those his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
faculties in Witchcrafte. I haue indeauoured (right Honourable)
in this small Treatise, according to my poore strength, to shewe the
<pb facs="3"/>
principall meanes ordained of God for to confound and to discouer them. I
doe here therefore humbly aske your Honourable protection, for the defence
of the trueth and the glory of God, against all the patrones of all such vile
artes, and horrible abhominations. Thus doeing, your Honour shall not
onely encourage me, but also, imbolden others, which are better able, and wil
be willing also, to lay open the secret delusions and practises of Sathans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions.
Nobilitie without godlines and vertue (as your Honour well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth)
is blood indeede, as a learned man speaketh, but blood without bones
and sinewes. I knowe therefore that to increase in your Honour true Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,
you are well assured, that it principally standeth in purchasing vnto
Christ and his Church, true honour and glorie, and in beating downe
(as much as in your Honour lyeth) all the holdes of Sathans
kingdome. God increase in your heart (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable)
all his good graces to his glory,
your own saluation, and the benefit
of his Church. <hi>Amen.</hi> The
yeere of our saluation.
1590.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your good Lordships euer to vse
and command in the Lord,
Henr. Holland.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>