<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE WOR∣SHIPFVLL EDMVNDE HASSELVVOOD of Ringe∣stone in the Countie of Lin∣colne, Esquier: W. P. wisheth most prosperous felicitie in this world, and in the world to come life euerlasting.</title>
           <author>P., W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104431_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A22778</idno>
           <idno type="STC">929</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104431</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE WOR∣SHIPFVLL EDMVNDE HASSELVVOOD of Ringe∣stone in the Countie of Lin∣colne, Esquier: W. P. wisheth most prosperous felicitie in this world, and in the world to come life euerlasting.</title>
                 <author>P., W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The glasse of vaine-glorie: faithfully translated (out of S. Augustine his booke, intituled, Speculum peccatoris) into English, by W.P. Doctor of the Lawes</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 70, 2 pages, illustrations, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL EDMVNDE HASSELVVOOD of Ringe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone in the Countie of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne, Esquier:</hi> W. P. <hi>wisheth</hi> most prosperous felicitie in this <hi>world, and in the world to come</hi> life euerlasting.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F GOD HIM</hi> selfe so bitterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueieth against the extreame ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his people by his holy Prophet <hi>Esaias,</hi> saying: <hi>I haue nouris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ed, &amp; brought vp children, and they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled against me:</hi> yea, if hee preferreth bruite beastes in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
<pb facs="3"/>
of their duetie before them, saying: <hi>The oxe knoweth his owner, and the asse his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters crib: but Israel knoweth not me.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>If the Persians likewise, so wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily abhorred this vice of Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, so as they extremely puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed such as they found more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receiue, than readie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite, adiudging them execrable vnto God, iniurious to nature, and vnprofitable members of a common wealth.</p>
   <p>If the Ciuill Lawe also, with good reason bindeth men by nature <hi>ad antidora,</hi> to requite a good turne receiued in duetie.</p>
   <p>I trust no reasonable man will blame me, if I seeke by all meanes possible, to shunne so foul a blemish as vnthankefulnesse is, so hatefull to God, so lothsome to man, and so
<pb facs="3"/>
repugnant to nature.</p>
   <p>Wherefore, finding my selfe deepely indebted (by your onely meanes) to all the name of <hi>Hassel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> and namely to master <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Hasselwood,</hi> your good brother, and to that vertuous gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman his wife, (a rare example of godlines and modestie) but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialy to your worship, both for them and all other your kindnesse, curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, and great frindships shewed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes mee a stranger. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no other way in the world, to requite any part of the same, then by leauing a publike testimonie to all posteritie, of my loyall loue, and hartie good will towardes you like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, to stande for the meede of so great a merite: I haue presumed to dedicate to your worship, this litle booke of S <hi>Augustines,</hi> translated by me into English, and with great
<pb facs="4"/>
labor quoted, &amp; confirmed by scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture in the margeant, as you see, very profitable to the Christian Reader, that can finde in his heart, to sequester his mind from the vice of vaine-glory, (that proceedeth from the ignorance of our owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state) the very snare of Satan, the puddle of pride, and the fountaine from whence distilleth all kinde of poysoned infection, as by the viewe of this glasse may easily appeare.</p>
   <p>Wherfore the premises due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly considered I doubt not, but that you will of your accustomed curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sye, pardon my presumption, and of your wonted Zeale to godlines, accept of my trauaile herein, and thinke me rather vnable, then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing any way to discharge my dutie whereof I am carefull, as knoweth the Lorde, who euer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue your worship and that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
<pb facs="4"/>
Gentlewomā your wife long to continue amongest vs with increase of godlinesse, and worshippe in his feare.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your worships, most faithfull friend in the Lord. W, P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>