<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the gentlemen Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104488_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04725</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1486</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104488</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the gentlemen Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Lady Pecunia, or The praise of money : Also a combat betwixt conscience and couetousnesse. Togither with, the complaint of poetry, for the death of liberality. Newly corrected and inlarged, by Richard Barnfield, graduate in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Barnfield, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 <publisher>Hodgets, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the gentlemen Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, being incouraged through your gentle acceptance of my <hi>Cynthia,</hi> I haue once more ventred on your curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies: hoping to find you (as I haue done heretofore) friendly. Being determined to writ of something, and yet not resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of anything, I considered with my selfe, if one should write of Loue (they will say) euerie one writes of Loue: if of vertue, why, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards vertue; To be short, I could thinke of nothing, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was common, or not at all in request. At length I bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoght my selfe of a Subiect, both new (as hauing neuer been written vpon before) and pleasing (as I thought) because Mans Nature commonlye) loues to heare that praised, with whose presence, he is most pleased.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Erasmus</hi> (the glory of Netherland, and the refiner of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Tongue) wrote a whole Booke, in <hi>the praise of follye.</hi> Then if so excellent a Scholler, writ in praise of vanity, why maye not I write in praise of that which is profitable? There are not two Countreys, where Gold is esteemed, lesse than in India, and more then in England: the reason is, because the Indians are barbarous, and our Nation ciuill.</p>
   <p>I haue giuen Pecunia the title of a Woman, Both for the termination of the Word, because (as Women are) shee is lou'd of men. The brauest voyages in the World, haue been made for Gold: for it, men haue ventured (by Sea) o the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thest
<pb facs="4"/>
partes of the earth: In the pursute whereof, Englandes Nestor and Neptune <hi>(Hawkins</hi> and Drake) lost their liues. vpon the Deaths of the which two, of the first I writ this:
<q>
         <l>The Waters were his winding Sheete, the Sea was made his Toombe,</l>
         <l>Yes for his Fame the Ocean Sea, was not sufficient roome.</l>
      </q>
Of the latter this:
<q>
         <l>England his Hart, his Corps the Waters haue,</l>
         <l>And that which raisd his Fame, became his graue.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>The Praetorians (after the death of Pertinax) in the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a new Emperour, more esteemed the money of Iulia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, then either the vertue of Seuerus, or the valour of Pessen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nius. Then of what great estimation, this Lady Pecunia, both hath beene in the world, and is at this present, I leaue to your Iudgement. But what speak I so much of her praise in my Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, that haue commended her so at large, in my Booke; To the reading whereof, (Gentlemen) I refer you.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>