<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface of the Author to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Lupton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104926_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68420</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16955</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104926</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface of the Author to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Lupton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A thousand notable things, of sundry sortes : VVherof some are wonderfull, some straunge, some pleasant, diuers necessary, a great sort profitable and many very precious</title>
                 <author>Lupton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Spooner, Hugh</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 302, 18 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Culinary arts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface of the Author to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F some thinke no</hi> shame to displeasure many, for the pleasuring of a fewe (gentle Reader) then I néede not blush nor feare to profit manye by hurting of none: Whiche I hope I haue done by the publishing of this my Booke abrode, not pend with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paine, nor drawne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diligence, not ended with ease. Wherein are such and so manye notable, rare, pleasaunt, profitable and precious thinges (meaning one with an other) as neuer wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> yet set forth in anye volume in our vulgar or English tongue, nay diuers of of them were neuer hetherto printed, nor written, that euer I knew: but onely that I writ them at such tyme as I hearde them credibly reported. Thinking them such rare thinges, as was worthy to be regestred. Marry I must confesse, I haue selected and pycked a great sorte out of Latine Wryters, the Authors or Wryters whereof, I haue named most commonly at the ende of the same. And some notable and precious thinges I gathered out of some olde Englishe wrytten bookes, and some also not long since prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, vnworthy to be hyd, and great pittie but they should bee knowne: which purposesly I haue placed herein, whereby I thinke verelye, manye will reade them, heare them and haue profit by them, that otherwise should neuer haue known
<pb facs="3"/>
them. For manye (I suppose) will buye this Booke for thinges whereto they are affectioned, that neuer coulde or would haue bought, or looked on the bookes, wherein all they are. So that by this meanes, they are like to winne against theyr willes. Perhappes you will meruell, that I haue not placed them in better order, and that thinges of like matter are not ioygned together. Truely there are so many of so diuerse and sundry sortes and contrary effectes, that it could not be altogether obserued. And in my iudgement through the straungenesse and varietie of matter, it will be more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirously and delightfully read: knowing we are made of such a moulde, that delicate Daintinesse delightes vs much: but we loathe to bee fed too long with one foode: And that long wandring in straunge, peasant and contrary places, will lesse wery vs, then short trauell in often troden ground.</p>
   <p>This worke might haue béene framed with finer Phrases (more dilectable to some, though not so meete for many) but that it is better to profit a great sorte, then to feede the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of a few, well assured, that the learned and eloquent can better perceiue plaine speeches: then the slenderlye lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and common sorte can vnderstand eloquent Discourses. Therfore as I haue written it to all indifferently, so wish I to manifest the meaning thereof accordingly: especially of such as are to be conceaued. Not ignorant, that there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uierse and sundry Astrologicall Aphorismes, and some other practises besides in this booke, that many both wise, learned and eloquent, cannot attaine to the vnderstanding thereof, (much lesse the common sort:) the meaning wherof I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the learned therin. But because the Planeticall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and effect in theyr howres, (whereof I haue noted some maruelous matters in this woork) should not be hidde or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, I hope shortly there will be set forth such a Rule or Platforme, that they may be thought simple witted, or slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly learned, that therby cannot finde out and know quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what howre or time any planet dooth raigne or beare rule,
<pb facs="3"/>
and at what instant the same begins, and how long the force therof dooth last: which once knowne, the thinges that I haue written herein concerning the same (well marked and obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) will not onely auoyde much mischiefe and harme: but also will procure great pleasure and profit. Untyll the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing whereof, I referre you to a little Booke, intituled or called, A briefe Treatise concerning many proper Tables &amp;c. Wherein is the Computacion of yeeres with the raignes of the Kinges of England: in which litle Booke, is a briefe and exact Table and Rule, wherby any may finde iustly and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when and how long any Planet dooth raigne, especiallye such as be of good capacitie and haue pregnant wittes. As for the duller sorte, I thinke it is too briefe and too busie.</p>
   <p>I haue deuided this into ten bookes, euery one wherof, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines a hundreth of the intituled Notable thinges: which are in all a thousand. Wishing that they may be accepted as thankfully &amp; willingly, as I haue bestowed them friendly and freely. Being bould to affirme this much, that a great deale of golde cannot counteruaile this Gyft: if but some twenty of the sayd thousand, be dil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently marked, faythfullye followed, and perfectlye practised. And thus in fewe wordes, I byd you farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Lupton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>