<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>T. N. To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104622_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16131</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3053</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104622</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>T. N. To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The morall philosophie of Doni : drawne out of the auncient writers. A worke first compiled in the Indian tongue, and afterwardes reduced into diuers other languages: and now lastly englished out of Italian by Thomas North, brother to the right Honorable Sir Roger North Knight, Lorde North of Kyrtheling</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 111 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>T. N. To the Reader.</head>
   <l>OF wordes and of examples is a sundrie sort of speache,</l>
   <l>One selfe same thing to mindes of men in sundrie wise they teache.</l>
   <l>Wordes teache but those that vnderstande the language that they heare:</l>
   <l>But things, to men of sundrie speache, examples make appeare.</l>
   <l>So larger is the speache of beasts, though mens more certaine bee:</l>
   <l>But yet so larger as conceyte is able them to see.</l>
   <l>Such largenesse yet at length to bring to certaine vse and plaine,</l>
   <l>God gaue such grace to beasts, that they should Indian speach attaine.</l>
   <l>And then they learnde Italian tongue, and now at length they can,</l>
   <l>By helpe of NORTH, speake English well to euery English man.</l>
   <l>In English now they teache vs wit. In English now they saye,</l>
   <l>Ye men, come learne of beasts to liue, to rule and to obaye,</l>
   <l>To guide you wisely in the worlde, to know to shunne deceite,</l>
   <l>To flie the crooked pathes of guile, to keepe your doings streight.</l>
   <l>As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arst therefore you vsed beasts, but for your bodies neede,</l>
   <l>Sometime to clothe, sometime to beare, sometime your selues to feede.</l>
   <l>Now vse them for behoofe of minde, and for your soules delite,</l>
   <l>And wish him well that taught them so to speake and so to write.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>