<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vvyllyam Tindale</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1531</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104977_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B16147</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24437</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104977</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Vvyllyam Tindale</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An answere vnto Sir Thomas Mores dialoge made by Vvillyam Tindale. First he declareth what the church is, and geveth a reason of certayne wordes which Master More rebuketh in the tra [n] slacion of the newe Testament. After that he answereth particularlye vnto everye chaptre which semeth to haue anye apperaunce of truth thorow all his. iiij. bokes</title>
                 <author>Tyndale, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cock (Cowke), Simon</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1531</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>c xxxiii, 6 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Vvyllyam Tindale</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He grace of oure lorde / y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> light of his spirite to se ād to iudge / true repētaunce towardes god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des lawe / a fast faith in the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifull promises that are in ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re savioure Christ / fervent lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue towarde thy neyghboure af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the ensample of Christ and his sayntes / be with the o reader and with all y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> loue the trouth and longe for the redempcion of goddes electe. Amen.</p>
   <p>Oure savioure Ihesus in the .xvj. chaptre of Iohan at his last souper whē he toke his leaue <note place="margin">Ioa. 16</note> of his disciples / warned them sayenge / the holye gost shall come and rebuke the worlde of iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. That is / he shall rebuke the worlde for lacke of true iudgement and discr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>yon to iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / and shall proue that the taste of their mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes is corrupte / so that they iudge swete to be sowre and sowre to be swete / and their yies to be blinde / so that they thinke that to be the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye service of god which is but a blinde supersti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon / for zele of which yet they persecute y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> true service of god: and that they iudge to be the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of god which is but a false imaginacion of a corrupte iudgement / for blinde affeccyon of which yet they persecute the true lawe of god &amp; them that kepe it. And this same is it that Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le sayeth in the seconde chaptre of the first epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to the Corinthians / how that the naturall mā that is not borne agayne and created anew <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> with the spirite of god / be he never so greate a philosopher / never so well sene in the lawe / ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so sore studyed in the scripture / as we haue ensamples in the pharises / yet he can not vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stonde the thinges of the spirite of god: but sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeth
<pb n="ij" facs="2"/> he / y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> spirituall iudgeth all thinges and his spirite sercheth the depe secretes of god / so that what so ever god commaundeth him to do / he neverleveth serchinge till he come at the boto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / the pith / the quycke / the liffe / the spirite / the marye and verye cause why / ād iudgeth all thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge. Take an ensample / in the greate commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement / loue god with all thyne herte / the spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall sercheth the cause and loketh on the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites <note place="margin">Mat. 22</note> of god and so conceaveth loue in his herte And when he is commaunded to obeye the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers <note place="margin">Rom. 13</note> and rulers of the worlde / he loketh on the benefytes which god sheweth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worlde thorow them and therfore doth it gladlye. And when he <note place="margin">Mat. 22</note> is commaūded to loue his neyghboure as him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>silfe / he sercheth that his neyghboure is created of god and bought with Christes bloude and so forth / ād therfore he loveth him out of his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / and if he be evell forbereth him and with all loue and paciēce draweth him to good: as elder brothren wayte on the younger and serve them and sofre them / and when they will not come they speake fayre and flater and geue some ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye thinge and promise fayre and so drawe them and smite them not / but if they maye in no wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se be holpe / referre the punishment to the father and mother and so forth. And by these iudgeth he all other lawes of god and vnderstondeth y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> true vse and meaninge of thē. And by these vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstondeth he in the lawes of man / which are right and which tirannie.</p>
   <p>If god shulde commaunde him to drinke no wyne / as he commaunded in the olde testament that the preastes shulde not: when they mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred in the temple and forbade diverse meates / 
<pb facs="3"/> the spirituall (because he knoweth that man is lorde ouer all other creatures and they his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vauntes made to be at his pleasure / and that it is not commaunded for the wyne or meate it sil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe that man shuld be in bondage vnto his aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne servaunt y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> inferioure creature) ceaseth not to serch the cause. And when he findeth it / that it is to tame the flesh and that he be alwaye so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre / he obeyeth gladlye / and yet not so superstici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouslye that the tyme of his disease he wolde not drinke wyne in the waye of a medicyne to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his helts / as David ate of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> halowed breed and as Mose for necessite lefte the childrē of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael vncircumcysed .xl. yeares / where of likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod <note place="margin">1. Reg. 21.</note> some died vncircūcysed &amp; were yet thought to be in no worse case then they that were circū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cysed / as the children that died with in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eyght daye were counted in as good case as they that were circūcysed / which ensamples might teach vs manye thinges if there were spirite in vs. And likewyse of the holye daye / he knoweth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the daye is seruaunt to man / and therfore whē he findeth that it is done because he shulde not be lette from hearinge y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> worde of god / he obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth gladlie / and yet not so supersticiouslye y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he wolde not helpe his neyghboure on the holye da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ye and let the sermon alone for one daye / or that he wolde not worke on the holydaye / neade re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyringe it / at such time as men be not wont to be at church / and so thorow out all lawes. And even likewyse in all ceremonyes and sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes he sercheth the significatiōs and wil not ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve the visible thinges. It is as good to him / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> preast saye masse in his goune as in his other apparell / if they teach him not some whate and that his soule be edefyed therbye. And as sone
<pb n="iij" facs="3"/> will he gape while thou puttest sonde as holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salt in his mouth / if thou shewe him no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son therof. He had as lefe be smered with on ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowed butter as anoynted with charmed oyle if his soule be not taught to vnderstonde some whate therbye / and so forth</p>
   <p>But the worlde captyvateth his witte and aboute the lawe of god maketh him wonderful imaginacions vnto which he so fast cleaveth y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> ten Iohan Baptistes were not able to dispute them out of his hed. He beleveth that he loveth god because he is readie to kille a turcke for his sake that beleveth better in god then he / whom god also commaundeth vs to loue and to leave nothinge vnsought / to winne him vnto the kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wledge of the truth / though with the losse of ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re lyves He supposeth that he loveth his neygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boure as moch as he is bounde / if he be not actu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>allye angrye with him / whom yet he wil not hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe frelye with an halfpenye but for avantage / or vayneglorye or for a wordlie purposse. If any man haue displeased him / he kepeth his malice in and will not chafe him silfe aboute it till he se an occasion to avenge it craftelye and thinketh that well ynough. And the rulars of the worlde he obeyeth thinketh he / when he flatereth them and blindeth them with giftes ād corrupteth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> officers with rewardes and begyleth the lawe with cautels and sotiltyes. And because the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of god &amp; of his neyghboure which is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and the liffe of all lawes and wherfore all la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes are made / is not writen in his harte / therfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re in all inferioure lawes and in all worldlye or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinaunces is he betell blinde. If he be cōmaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to absteyne from wyne / that will he observe vnto the deeth to / as the charter house monkes
<pb facs="4"/> had lever dye them eate flesh: and as for the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brenesse and chastisinge of the membres will he not loke for / but will powre in ale and bere of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> strongest with out measure and heate thē with spices and so forth. And the holidaye will he ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe so strayte that if he mete a flee in his bed he dare not kill hir / and not once regarde wherfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the holidaye was ordined to seke for goddes worde / &amp; so forth in al lawes. And in ceremonyes &amp; sacramentes / there he captiuateth his witte &amp; vnderstondinge to obey holye church with out askinge what they meane or desiring to knowe but onlye careth for the kepinge and loketh ev<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er with a payre of narow yies and with all his spectacles vppon them / lest ought belefte out. For if the preast shulde saye masse / baptize or heare confession with out a stole aboute his nec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / he wolde thinke all were marred and doute whether he had power to consecrate / &amp; thinke y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> the vertue of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> masse were lost / &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> childe not wel baptized or not baptized at all / &amp; y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his abso<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lucion were not worth a myte He had leuer y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> bisshope shuld wagge .ij. fingers ouer him / thē that a nother man shulde saye god saue him ād so forth. wherfore beloved reader in as moch as the holye gost rebuketh the worlde for lacke of iudgement / and in as moch also as their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce is with out excuse before whose faces ynough is sette to iudge by / if they wolde open their yies to se / and not captiuate their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stondinge to beleue lyes: and in as moch as the spirituall iudgeth all thinge / even the verye botome of goddes secretes / that is to saye / the causes of the thinges which god cōmaundeth / how moch more ought we to iudge oure ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye fathers secrettes and not to be as an oxe
<pb n="iiij" facs="4"/> or an asse with out vnderstondinge.</p>
   <p>Iudge therfore reader whether the pope with his be the church / whether their auctorite be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the scripture: whether all they teach with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out scripture be equalle with the scripture: whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther they haue erred / ād not onlye whether they can. And agenst the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> of their sophistrye take the ensamples that are past in the olde testamēt and autentike storyes and the present practise which thou seist before thyne yies. Iudge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be possible that any good shuld come out of their domme ceremonies and sacramentes in to thy soule. Iudge their penaunce / pilgrima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / pardons / purgatorye / prayinge to postes / domme blessinges / domme absolucyōs / their dō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me pateringe ād howlinge / their domme straun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge holye gestures with all their domme disgysin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges / their satisfaccions and iustefyinges. And because thou findest thē false in so manye thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / trust thē in nothinge but iudge thē ī al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Marke at the last the practise of oure flesh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye spiritualtye and their wayes by which they haue walked aboue .viij. hundred yeares / how they stablish their lyes / first with falsifiynge the scripture / then thorow corruptinge with their riches wher of they haue infinite treasure in sto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re: and last of all with the swerde. Haue they not compelled the emperoures of the erth and the greate lordes and hie officers to be obedient vnto them / to dispute for thē and to be their tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentoures / and the samsumims them selves do but imagen mischefe and inspire them. Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke whether it were ever truer then now / the scri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bes / pharises / Pilate / Herode / Caiphas &amp; Anna / are gathered to gether agenst god &amp; Christ. But yet I trust in vayne / and that he that brake the
<pb facs="5"/> counsell of achitophell shall scater theirs. Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke whether it be not true in the hyest degre / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> for the sinne of the people hypocrites shall ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne over them. Vvhat shewes / what faces and contrarie pretenses are made / and all to stablish them in their thefte / falsehed and dampnable lyes / and to gather them to gether for to contry vesotiltye to oppresse the truth and to stoppe y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> light &amp; to kepe all still in darkenesse. Vvherfore it is tyme to awake / and to se everye man with his awne yies ād to iudge / if we will not be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of Christ when he cometh to iudge. And rebembre that he which is warned hath none excuse / if he take no hede. Here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with fare well in the lorde Iesus Christ whose spirite be thy gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and doctrine thy light to iudge with all₊</p>
   <closer>Amen. ☜</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>