<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the friendly peruser.</title>
           <author>Armin, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104426_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21411</idno>
           <idno type="STC">773</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104426</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the friendly peruser.</title>
                 <author>Armin, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The history of the tvvo maids of More-clacke : vvith the life and simple maner of Iohn in the hospitall. Played by the Children of the Kings Maiesties Reuels. VVritten by Robert Armin, seruant to the Kings most excellent Maiestie</title>
                 <author>Armin, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Archer, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the friendly peruser.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLEMEN, Cittizens, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stickes, or <hi>quis non,</hi> I haue boldly put into your hands, a Historical discourse, acted by the boyes of the Reuels, which perchaunce in part was sometime acted more naturally in the Citty, if not in the hole. Howsoeuer I commit it into your hands to be scan'd, and you shall find verse, as well blancke, as crancke, yet in the prose let it passe for currant, I would haue againe inacted <hi>Iohn</hi> my selfe, but <hi>Tempora mutantur in illis,</hi> &amp; I cannot do as I would, I haue therefore thought good to diuulge him thus being my old acquaintance, <hi>lack,</hi> whose life I knew, and whose remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance I presume by appearance likely. Wherein I whilome pleased: and being requested both of Court and Citty, to shew him in priuate, I haue therefore printed him in publike, wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus much to euery one, so delighting, <hi>I</hi> might put life into this picture, and naturally act him to your better contents; but since it may not be, my entreaty is, that you would accept this dumbe show, and be well wishing to the substance.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours euer as he is merry and frolicke, ROBERT ARMIN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>