<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE AND TRVLY Religious Knight, Sir ROBERT CARR, Gentleman of his Highnesse Bed-chamber, and Keeper of the Princes priuie Purse: IOHN LAVVRENCE wisheth all health and happinesse.</title>
           <author>Lawrence, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104883_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05191</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15325</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104883</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE AND TRVLY Religious Knight, Sir ROBERT CARR, Gentleman of his Highnesse Bed-chamber, and Keeper of the Princes priuie Purse: IOHN LAVVRENCE wisheth all health and happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Lawrence, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A golden trumpet, to rowse vp a drowsie magistrate: or, A patterne for a governors practise : drawne from Christs comming to, beholding of, and weeping ouer Hierusalem. As it was founded at Pauls Crosse the 11. of Aprill, 1624. By Iohn Lawrence preacher of the word of God in the citie of London</title>
                 <author>Lawrence, John, preacher of the word of God in London</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 104, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE AND TRVLY Religious Knight, Sir ROBERT CARR, Gentleman of his Highnesse Bed-chamber, <hi>and Keeper of the Princes priuie Purse:</hi> IOHN LAVVRENCE wisheth all <hi>health and happinesse.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orthy Sir, when I call to minde the great fauours which you shewed to my father in his life time, I cannot but reprehend my selfe of ingratitude, in not performing that dutie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto (for his sake) I am so farre ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged: but studying how I might best testifie my grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full affection, haue here presumed to present you with the first fruits of my poore studies. I could finde no better flowers than those that spring from faithfull loue, bound with the bond of dutie, to make my labours gracious in your thoughts: If I presume too farre, pardon mee, for this my loue is sprung from the root of your bountifull kindnesse towards my father, which if euer I forget, I will not say with <hi>Dauid, Let my right hand forget her cunning,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 137.5.</note> (for that is nothing) but let <hi>God</hi> himselfe forget to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent me with any grace, or to follow mee with any bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing: Accept therefore (most <hi>worthy Sir</hi>) these <hi>mites, graines, drops, teares, cries,</hi> as it was by me <hi>sounded</hi> forth in place of publike meeting; I must confesse it hath lost what it then had, for a dead letter cannot be so patheticall as a liuing voice; neither can the pen so set it forth in writing, as the tongue in speaking. <hi>Papias</hi> who was a
<pb facs="5"/>
companion of <hi>Policarpus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eusch. Eccles. Hist. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>39.</hi>
      </note> thought that hee did not so much profit by the writings and bookes of the Apostles followers, as by the authoritie of the persons, and the liuely voice of the speakers: Whereupon <hi>Aeschines,</hi> when hee had read the Oration which <hi>Demosthenes</hi> had made against him, and withall perceiued how the people wondred at the force and excellencie of it, answered them thus:<note place="margin">Hier. Ibid.</note>
      <hi>What would you haue thought, if you had heard him pronounce it with his owne mouth: q.d.</hi> If you are thus rauished with hearing it read, how would you haue beene rauished if you had heard him speake and pronounce it? Howsoeuer, I hope you will looke more vpon my minde and honest purpose, then vpon the worthinesse of the worke: I durst not presume to shroud these <hi>vnpolished</hi> sprigs vnder so <hi>vertuous a patronage,</hi> if I did not hope, that as <hi>Dauid</hi> loued <hi>Mephibosheth</hi> for his good father <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathans</hi> sake; so you this lame worke of mine. I humbly intreat you therefore, that as <hi>Vlisses</hi> was defended vnder the shield of <hi>Aiax;</hi> so these my vnworthy lines may by your fauour, be <hi>patronized</hi> from the enuie of malicious detractors. Our tribe oweth much to you, both for lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and rewarding their labours, for which cause I know many ioine with me, to wish your whole man, soule and body, true perfect ioy in this life, and full accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of glory in the next, for the which I doe and euer will pray,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Whilest I remaine</hi> IOHN LAVVRENCE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>