<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104662_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16510</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3422</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104662</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A regiment for the sea : conteyning most profitable rules, mathematical experiences, and perfect knovvledge of nauigation, for all coastes and countreys: most needefull and necessarie for all seafaring men and trauellers, as pilotes, mariners, marchants [et] c. Exactly deuised and made by VVilliam Bourne</title>
                 <author>Bourne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 63, 1 leave, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>❧The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N my opinion (gentle Reader) which also is the saying and writing of all the Philosophers, those thinges are moste principally to be taught and maynteined, whiche in the common wealth are moste profitable and necessarie. Then may I boldely say (without iust cause of reproofe) and affirme, that Nauigation is not the least but one of the principal matters to be knowne, as this time dothe require: Considering the state and sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation of our countrie, for that we be inuironed rounde aboute with the Sea, so that we neither can go out of our countrie, neyther they that are of other countries can come at vs, but onely by Sea. These things (I say) considered, what can there be more necessarie to be taught in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth than Nauigation, considering also what Nauigation is: as Nauigation is how to direct ones course vpon or thorow the sea, where he findeth no path to any place assigned, and how to attayne the porte or place appointed in shortest time, how also to preserue the shippe and goodes in al common disturbances, as stormes, daungers by the way, and such other like &amp;c. Moreouer and besides that, it is not vnknowne howe necessarie Nauigation is, both for the transportation of our commodities, to find vent for them in other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries (whereby no small numbre of people is set a
<pb facs="5"/>
worke in England) and also the bringing of other commodities (that we haue neede of) vnto vs, by which meanes the Queenes Maiestie receyueth no small benefite for hir customes. &amp;c. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, for that Nauigation is the chiefe force and strength of our countrie, which whether it be true I referre to the iudgement of all men, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I be but simple (gentle Reader) &amp; a great number of excellent learned men in the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall Science haue written diuerse bookes of Cosmographie and Nauigation, yet notwithstā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I haue written this Regiment for the Sea with a fewe rules of Nauigation, as it were a nosegay whose floures are of mine owne gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. And albeit the learned sorte of Seafaring men haue no neede of this booke, yet am I assured that it is a necessarie booke for the simplest sort of Seafaring men: for that they shall finde here the names of the circles in the sphere, with the names of diuerse things meete for Nauigation, togither with their vses, which the most parte of Sea men do mistake or misse call: neyther do they know the vse of them being yet most necessarie for them that vse Nauigation, in whiche also there is a table of declination calculated for .4. yeres, (that is to say, for the yeare of our Lord .1573. the firste after <hi>Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sextilis,</hi> the yeare .1574. beyng the second yeare, &amp; the yeare .1575. which is the third yeare, with the yeare .1576. whiche is the yeare of <hi>Bissextilis</hi> or leape yeare it selfe) whiche the Sea men do call a Regiment, and will serue for .24. yeare without
<pb facs="5"/>
any great errour: and is exactly calculated for the Longitude of London for the instāt time of noone, and will serue all Europe and Affrica, neare vnto the coast of America without much errour, sauing in Februarie, Marche or September, whilest the sunne hath swifte declination. But in Iune and December it will serue al the world ouer: bycause the sunne hath but slowe declination, &amp;c. And also there be other necessarie rules of Nauigation to know how to handle the Sunnes declination, to knowe the altitude of eyther of the .2 Poles, (as the contentes of the booke do shewe) with other necessarie things meete to be knowne in Nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not mentioned in the booke of <hi>Martin Curtise</hi> called the Arte of Nauigation. Neyther doe I meane to write of any thing mentioned in that booke: for that it is there sufficiently declared already. And thus (gentle Readers) I desire you to beare with my rudenesse, that I shoulde take vpon me to open any science, for that I am vtterly vnlearned, and without helpe of any learned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, desiring you not to conceyue any euil opinion of me, but to take it as my good will, minding to profite my natiue Countrey as muche as lyeth in me. Notwithstanding it is possible that some people will be offended with me, that I shoulde write this simple Treatise, but then I consider agayne, and knowe, that vertue lacketh no eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and defacers, and vyce lacketh no friendes and maynteyners, so that knowledge lacketh no contempt, neyther ignorance lacketh furtherance,
<pb facs="6"/>
&amp; especially among all people there is none more ready to contemne, than the ignorāt sort: for igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce is the father of all errours and the mother of contention. And thus I drawe to ende, desiring you to take this simple worke in good part, being willing to pleasure my natiue countrie according to the simple talent that God hath giuen me And whereas you finde any errour I pray you let me gently vnderstand, for I thinke not that I cause circumspectly worke but I may be deceyued, for man cannot be so precise but he may erre, and I haue seldome heard of any the best Authours but he hath erred in some poynt: therefore in those things that he knoweth not of himselfe he muste needes follow his Authour, and if his Author doe erre he must needes fall into that errour that his Author dothe. And furthermore, a numbre of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple there be that deuise nothing els but lies and slaunders, yea, and those which cannot attayne to any thing themselues, doe hate all those that be not ignorant as they themselues be: for the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature of man is suche, that it is a corsey to their harts that any should be commended before themselues, for generally amongst all people of the earth (whiche is innumerable) euery seuerall person thinketh himselfe most worthie, imagining themselues to haue no fellowes: suche is the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill in the harte of man, pampering mans hart so with pryde to thinke he hath no fellow, whereas man of himselfe is not able to do any good thing, no not to thinke one good thought, but by the only
<pb facs="6"/>
might and prouidence of almighty God, therefore of our selues we can do nothyng that is good. And thus gentle Reader I make an end. If this sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and barbarous thing be taken in good parte, then looke for other of my workes shortly, and beare him good will that studieth for the benefite of his natiue countrie, desiryng God of his grace, that I and you may do that thing that may be to the laude, prayse and glory of God, to our commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie and soules health, to the profite of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and the common wealth of this our realme. Thus I betake you to Almightie God the creator of all things, praying him that both I &amp; you may after this life rest in the kingdome of heauen, with Abraham, Isaac and Iacob, there to remayne world without ende. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>