<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE INDVCEMENT to his Maiesties grant, made to Iohn Rouenzon, Esquire, ab∣stracted out of the Indenture of Priuiledge.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104560_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15592</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21355</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104560</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE INDVCEMENT to his Maiesties grant, made to Iohn Rouenzon, Esquire, ab∣stracted out of the Indenture of Priuiledge.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise of metallica : But not that which was published by Mr. Simon Sturteuant vpon his patent, which is now by order cancelled and made voyd, by reason of his standing out-lawed at the time of the grant, and so still continuing, and his neglect, and not performance o the workes. Whereupon priuiledge, by patent, is granted by the Kings most excellent Maiesty, to Iohn Rouenzon, Esquire, for the making of iron, and other mettals and materials with sea-cole, pit-cole, &amp;c. for one and thirty yeares. According to which patent and direction therein, this treatise, composed by the same Iohn Rouenzon, is published in print before the end of Easter tearme, viz. the 15 of May. 1613. And containeth a briefe explanation, demonstration, or discouery of the inuentions priuiledged, and the meanes, instruments, engins, furnaces, &amp;c. with the materials, things, and workes to be made by the said fewels</title>
                 <author>Rovenzon, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Thorpe (Thorp), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE INDVCEMENT to his Maiesties grant, made to Iohn Rouenzon, <hi>Esquire, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted</hi> out of the Indenture of Priuiledge.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>PON affirmation by <hi>Simon Sturte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,</hi> that hee could performe the workes, and had effected the same in small trials, the same <hi>IOHN RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VENZON,</hi> made knowne the same to the late Prince his Highnesse, who thereupon, at the humble suit of the said <hi>Iohn Rouen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon,</hi> obtained Letters Patents of priuiledge to Maister <hi>Sturteuant for 31 yeares.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Maister <hi>Sturteuant</hi> oft promised to haue performed the workes long since in the said late Prince his owne view; yet neglected it to his Maiesties hinderance of profite that might in this space haue accrued, by endeuours of others.</p>
   <p>The late Prince encouraged the said <hi>IOHN ROVEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZON</hi> to make triall if he could performe the workes; who, after many chargeable trials by himselfe and
<pb facs="6"/> friends, satisfactorily effected the same. The said Prince hauing beene gratiously pleased to assure him, that vpon such performance, Maister <hi>Sturteuants</hi> Patent should bee deliuered vp, and made voyd; and thereupon like priuiledge should bee granted to the said <hi>Iohn Rouenzon,</hi> according to the effect of his Inuentions.</p>
   <p>Maister <hi>Sturteuant</hi> stood out-lawed at the time of the grant to him made, and so still continueth, which was found by office, and his Patent seized, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, and deliuered vp to bee cancelled, which is done, his Patent made voyd, and priuiledge granted to the said <hi>Iohn Rouenzon</hi> for one and thirty yeares to worke the workes, &amp;c.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>The effect of the Priuiledge.</head>
      <p n="1">1 SOle priuiledge to make Iron and all other Mettals, Ash-mettals, Bugles, Tiles, Potters-ware, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of boyleryes, &amp;c. with many other things, with Sea-cole, Pit-cole, Earth-cole, &amp;c. The perticulars of the things are most of them specified hereafter.</p>
      <p n="2">2 Sole priuiledge for making all Instruments, Engines, and meanes, &amp;c. onely for these workes; which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments, &amp;c. are by this new Inuention conuerted to these workes, hauing beene heretofore vsed in other Sciences, Arts, or Mysteries.</p>
      <p n="3">3 Sole priuiledge for making all the new-deuised Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, Fire-workes, Instruments, Engines, Meanes and Inuentions, either for the working of the workes
<pb facs="6"/> with the said fewels, or for any other end or purpose whatsoeuer.</p>
      <p>These are granted in as absolute manner and forme as they are contained, or mentioned in the Indenture of Priuiledge, or the Schedules thereunto annexed, or shall be more fully demonstrated, specified, or mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the <hi>Treatise of Metallica,</hi> to be printed before the last day of <hi>Easter Tearme;</hi> which Treatise is this present Booke.</p>
      <div type="section">
         <head>The distribution of the Profites.</head>
         <p>The cleare yearely Profites are to bee diuided into 33 parts, whereof the said <hi>Iohn Rouenzon</hi> is to pay twelue parts to the Kings Maiesty; fiue parts to the now Prince his Highnesse; one part to the Lord Viscount <hi>Rochester;</hi> one part the said <hi>Iohn Rouenzon</hi> is to keepe to himselfe; And the residue, being foureteene parts, are to be distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his discretion, and by such proportions as hee shall thinke fit, amongst the Aiders, Assisters, Aduenturers, and Owners of the Workes.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>