<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN INFORMATION TO THE READER OF the State of BREDA Formerly.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104008_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03136</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13265</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104008</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN INFORMATION TO THE READER OF the State of BREDA Formerly.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true and briefe relation of the famous seige of Breda : beseiged, and taken in vnder the able and victorious conduct of his Highnesse the Prince of Orange, captaine generall of the States armie, and admirall of the seas, &amp;c. Composed by Henry Hexham quartermaster to the regiment of the honorable Coronell Goring</title>
                 <author>Hexham, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Delft</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Hondius, Henricus 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Moxon, James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 46, 2, 16, 4 pages, folded engraved map, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>AN INFORMATION TO THE READER OF the State of BREDA Formerly.</head>
   <p>CVRTEOVS READER, the Cittie of <hi>Breda,</hi> taken in
this yeare by his Highnesse the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> lying in the
Land of <hi>Kempen,</hi> is a part of the Dukedome of great <hi>Brabant,</hi> and
the Head-Towne of a braue Barrony, hauing 16 villages, and a wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
Towne vnder the Jurisdiction thereof. Among the which, there
is <hi>Steen-bergen,</hi> a Towne newly fortifyed, with a Strong-Fort, or
two vpon the hauen, <hi>Rosendale</hi> a great, and a very pleasant village, and
<hi>Osterhout</hi> a goodly Lord-ship. This Citty is situated, vpon a riuer
called the <hi>Marck,</hi> whose headspring beginneth some foure English
Miles aboue <hi>Hoogh-strate.</hi> It lyeth one and twentie English miles &amp;
a halfe from <hi>Lier,</hi> one and twenty from <hi>Anwerpe,</hi> 15 from <hi>Bergin op
Zoom,</hi> 15 from <hi>Turnhout,</hi> 9 from <hi>Seuenberke,</hi> and 6 from <hi>Getruyden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berke.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>This Citty, and Barronie fell by marriage to the illustrious house
of <hi>Nassaw</hi> Anno 1404, two hundred three and thirty yeares agoe:
For that yeare <hi>Count Englebert</hi> Eare af <hi>Nassaw,</hi> Espoused the Lady
<hi>Io ane</hi> the onely <hi>Inheritrix</hi> of this Barronie of <hi>Breda,</hi> and the Land of
<hi>Leck:</hi> for a long time it was the Court, and ancient ressidency of the
Earles <hi>of Nassaw,</hi> vntill such time that Duke <hi>D' Alva</hi> by his tirannie,
droue <hi>Prince William</hi> the old Prince of Orange, and Earle of <hi>Nassaw</hi>
(his Highnes Father of famous memorie) out of his ancient inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.
It hath in it a goodly Castle double moated, founded by
<hi>Count Henry of Nassaw,</hi> which if it had bene finished, according to the
model thereof, it would haue bene one of the beautisullest, &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liest
Structures of Brabant. Since the Warres began, it hath bene
strongly fortified with many Bulwarks, Horneworks, Halfe-moons,
<pb facs="4"/>
Rauelings, and a large moate round about the Towne in some pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
14. rod, or 180 foote broade, &amp; 9 or 10 foote deepe with a good
Counterskarfe without it. This Towne hath suffered much by the
warres, as by surprises, blocking vp, &amp; Seiges &amp; hath beene subiect to
many changes, some times being lost, and other-wiles regayned on
both sides: For in the yeere of our Lord 1585. <hi>Prince William</hi> of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
memorie enioyed it peaceably &amp; till <hi>Hautpenny,</hi> one of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies
Commanders, surprized it that yeare on the 25 of Iune, plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
it, and burnt diuerse houses in it, and so it continewed vnder
the power of the King of Spayne, vntill <hi>Prince Maurice</hi> (of famous
Memorie) by a braue <hi>Stratagem,</hi> vnder the conduct of Captaine <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangier,</hi>
who with 70 other vailliant, and resolute men, hid vnder a
Turfe-Schip, comming into the Castle by night, broke out of that
couert <hi>Ambuscado,</hi> cutt of a <hi>Corps degard,</hi> and tooke in the Castle, &amp;
Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> marching with part of the States Army, to second
his dessigne, tooke in both Castle, and Towne on the fourth of march
in the yeare 1590. After this (being an ill neighbour to the Busse)
<hi>Anthony Schtes</hi> the Gouenour thereof, and Lord of <hi>Grubbing donck,</hi>
had an other enterprizce vpon it, and falling on in the night with
4000 foote, and eleuen troupe of horse, those of <hi>Breda</hi> takeiug the
alarme betimes, he finding them in a readenesle to entertaine him,
was beaten off with the losse of a hundred men.</p>
   <p>Againe, Marquesse <hi>Spinola</hi> haueing (Anno 1622) layne long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>Bergin op zoom,</hi> and lost, and hurt in the space of twelue weekes
a matter of ten thousand men before it, being so repulsed by my Lord
<hi>Morgan</hi> (then commaunding with the Gouernour, the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
Captaines, officers &amp; souldiers of all Nations,) that he could not
get so much as a foote of ground of them, though he attempted and
assaulted oftentimes the outworkes, with the losse of a great many
mē, who at last by the cōming of Prince <hi>Morrice</hi> of happie memorie,
and Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> to <hi>Rossendale</hi> with the States Armie, not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
to stand them: on a sudden brake vp, and quitted the seige in the
<pb facs="4"/>
night with a great confusion, leauing be hinde him a great many sick,
and hurt men, amunition, victuals, and other matterials. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quesse
<hi>Spinola</hi> then being Iealous of his honour, after <hi>Prince Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize</hi>
had putt into <hi>Breda</hi> 6000 choise Souldiers, namely, his owne
Guard, and most of the Coronels Companies, came and satt downe
before it, on the 28 of August. 1624. and hauing sustayned the losse
of a great many braue men before Bergin, feareing to attempt the
same by Approches, (cōmanding a mighty Armie) choose rather to
block it vp on all sides, and so knowing that many mouths, must eate
many victualls, sought rather to famish it out. Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
with the States Armie to the <hi>May,</hi> hauing a greater dessigne
in his head, to witt, an <hi>Enterprize</hi> vpon the Castle of <hi>Antwerpe,</hi>
which would haue fetch the Marquesse from <hi>Breda:</hi> failing for want
of Courage, and falling on (as it is reported) gaue the <hi>Marquesse</hi>
time to fortifie himself the stronger before <hi>Breda,</hi> and to that end,
made a double line of <hi>Circumvalation</hi> about it, with stronge Forts,
Horneworkes, halfemoones, Redoubts, and Spurrs, and cutting the
dike at <hi>Terhey,</hi> drownd all the lower grounds, and made a <hi>Steckado</hi>
ouer the drownd meddowes, to hinder and keepe vs from relieuing
it by water, and sloopes. Howsoeuer, his Highnesse the Prince of
<hi>Orange</hi> to see if he could possibly relieue yt, gaue command to <hi>Sir
Horace Vere</hi> of worthy Memory, Lord of <hi>Tylbery,</hi> and Coronell Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
of the English, with my <hi>Lord of Oxford,</hi> who commanded the
new English, on the 16 of May 1625 to fall on vpon the dike of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hey,</hi>
betweene the drownd lands; the dike being not a boue 20, or 30
foote broad at the most: the ennemie hauing two, or three strong Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubts
vpō it, ere you came to the <hi>Halfmoone</hi> before their quarter of
<hi>Terhey.</hi> An hower before day, the new English fell on, first tooke two
Redoubts vpō that Dike, &amp; an other vpō <hi>Seuenberks-Dike,</hi> beate the
Ennemie out of thē, slew many of thē, &amp; after a long fight the new &amp;
the old English fell vpō the half moone, &amp; disputed it a long with the
Ennemie, till such time as the Marquesse sent fresh forces, horse and
<pb facs="5"/>
foote to second them of Terhey, &amp; to defend that quarter: now after
Sun rising, finding it not feisible, our mē were driuē to retreate. Vpon
this seruice <hi>Sir Thomas Winne</hi> being a voluntier, Captaine <hi>Tubb,</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<hi>Dakers,</hi> Lieutenant Cheyney, Lieutenant Corbitt, and my
Lord of Oxfords Ensigne, with diuerse Gentlemen and souildiers
were slaine, &amp; Capt: <hi>Shippon</hi> shott, so that from that time forward,
this Citty by famine languished away, vntill the fifth of Iune 1625.
On which day it fell againe vnder the power, and obedience of the
King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and became a Receptacle for a great many Freeboo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
which did much annoy the States Countries, that lay next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
yt, bringing them vnder Contribution: Till that this present yeare,
his highnes the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> beseiged it, &amp; tooke it in againe, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
nation striuing at this seige, to doe the land seruice, besides the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
obligatiō they owed vnto his highnes, being his owne towne,
it gaue the more life &amp; courage vnto them. Now what memorable
peeces of seruice, &amp; actions haue bin performed during this Seige
from the 23 of Iuly, vntill the 10 of October 1637. This true and
briefe Relation (though I cannot remember all perticulars for want
of due information,) will giue the worthy Reader reasonable satisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
&amp; this as a preamble may serue to the matter it selfe following.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>