<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A BREEFE NOTE OF SOME OF THE CHIEFE generall poynts handled in this defence following.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104633_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16615</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3522</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104633</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A BREEFE NOTE OF SOME OF THE CHIEFE generall poynts handled in this defence following.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A myld and iust defence of certeyne arguments, at the last session of Parliament directed to that most Honorable High Court, in behalfe of the ministers suspended and deprived &amp;c: for not subscribing and conforming themselues etc : Against an intemperat and vniust consideration of them by M. Gabril Powell. The chiefe and generall contents wherof are breefely layd downe immediatly after the epistle</title>
                 <author>Bradshaw, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 163, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="abstract">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>
      <hi>A BREEFE NOTE OF SOME OF THE CHIEFE</hi> generall poynts handled in this defence following.</head>
   <p>THat the author of the Arguments is falsly accused to impute any dissembling or equivocating to the Kings most excellent Majesty, but that in all things he hath conceaved and written most reverently, Christiantly and duetifully of his Majestie.</p>
   <p n="2">2 That he is as vntruely charged with any vndutifull speeches against the Nobility, or any other that haue obeyed his Majesties procedings</p>
   <p n="3">3 That the Ministers pleaded for are not refractary, superstitious, or schismaticall: neyther confronters of the Magistrat, or troublers of the state, but that these and other the like imputations doe rather belong to their accusers</p>
   <p n="4">4 That our Churches of England are in nothing so glorious state as is pretended by <hi>M. Powel,</hi> and other prelaticall persons but rather in divers respects, and for divers parts <hi>thereof</hi> in lamentable condition.</p>
   <p n="5">5 That the late proceedings of the Prelats against such Ministers for not subscribing, conforming etc: &amp; that many of the late <hi>Canons</hi> or cōsti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutions are contrary to the word of God, &amp; the lawes of this Realme.</p>
   <p n="6">6 That the oth likewise <hi>Ex Officio</hi> is repugnant to the lawes of this Realme: yea abrogated by them, &amp; only inforced by forreyne Canons.</p>
   <p n="7">7 That the obedience &amp; loyaltie of the Ministers for conscience of Gods word not conforming themselues, is as good as of the greatest conformitans, yea that their not conforming thēselues in that respect, maketh more then conformity for the good &amp; safetie of his Majestie.</p>
   <p n="8">8 That the Considerer of the arguments, in his inconsiderat conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of them, hath most unreverently and undutifully censured the High Court of Parliament, for their late most religious indeavors in behalfe of the Ministers pleaded for in the sayd Arguments.</p>
   <p n="9">9 That the Ministers soe deprived, doe not forsake their callings.</p>
   <p n="10">10 That although the number of the Ministers so deprived be but smal in comparison of other, yet the deprivation of them &amp; the loss of their Ministery is dangerous for the whole Church in this kingdome.</p>
   <p n="11">11 That the Considerer of the arguments ofttimes offendeth in thos things which unjustly he objecteth unto the author of the arguments: viz: in sophistications in generall, and particularly in begging of the question: as also in equivocations, &amp; in vayne repetitions of the same things for encreasing of his volume: and lastly incontradicting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, yea sometyme in one and the same place.</p>
   <p n="12">12 That he and other the Prelats most striving for conformity, doe attribut more to conformitie, then to any more materiall &amp; principall duties of the Ministery expresly commanded by God.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>