<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A LETTER, written by a Gentleman, to the Author his friend.</title>
           <author>Philaretes, Assured</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104856_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17454</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4275</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104856</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A LETTER, written by a Gentleman, to the Author his friend.</title>
                 <author>Philaretes, Assured</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Alcilia : Philoparthens louing folly. Whereunto is added Pigmalions image. With the loue of Amos and Laura. And also epigrammes by Sir I.H. and others. Neuer before imprinted</title>
                 <author>I. C.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Hawkins, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, Roger.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Mattes, Edmund.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>100 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A LETTER, written by a Gentleman, to the Author his friend.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riend <hi>Philoparthens,</hi> in perusing your Louing-folly, and your declining from it, I doe behold Reason conquering Passion. The infirmitie of louing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you are a man; the firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse thereof discouereth a good wit, and the best nature; and the falling from it, true vertue, Beautie was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes of force to mislead the wisest, and men of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test perfection haue had no power to resist Loue. The best are accompanyed with Vices, to exercise their Vertues, whose glory shineth brightest in resisting motiues of pleasure, and in subduing affections. And though I cannot altogether excuse your <hi>Louing-folly</hi>; yet I doe the lesse blame you, in that you loued such a one as was more to be commended for her vertue then beautie; albeit euen for that too, shee was so well accomplished with the gifts of nature, as in mine owne conceit (which, for good cause, I must submit as inferiour to yours) there was nothing wanting, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the one or the other, that might adde more
<pb facs="3"/>
to her worth, except it were a more due and better regard of your loue, which <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hee requited not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your deserts, nor answerable to her selfe in her other parts of perfection: Yet herein it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth you haue made good vse of reason, that being heretofore lost in youthfull vanitie, haue now by timely discretion found your selfe. Let me intreate you to suffer these your passionate Sonnets to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, which may peraduenture make others, posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with the like humour of Louing, to follow your example in leauing, and moue other <hi>Alciliaes</hi> (if there be any) to imbrace deseruing loue while they may. Hereby also she shall know, and (it may be) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly repent the losse of your loue, and see how much her perfections are blemished by ingratitude, which will make your happinesse greater, by adding to your reputation, then your contentment could haue beene in inioying her loue: At the least wise the wiser sort, howsoeuer in censuring them, they may dislike of your errors; yet they cannot but commend and allow of your reformation; and all others that shall vvith indifferency reade them, may reape thereby some benefit or contentment: Thus much I haue written as a testimony of the good will I beare you, with whom I doe suffer or reioyce, according to the qualitie of good hap, or misfortune, and so I take my leaue, resting, as alwayes,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours most assured <hi>PHILARETES.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>