<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ Robert Norton to the courteous Readers.</title>
           <author>N., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104599_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12970</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23264</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104599</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ Robert Norton to the courteous Readers.</title>
                 <author>N., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Disme: the art of tenths, or, Decimall arithmetike : teaching how to perform all computations whatsoeuer, by whole numbers without fractions, by the foure principles of common arithmeticke: namely addition, subtraction, multiplication, and diuision. Inuented by the excellent mathematician, Simon Steuin. Published in English with some additions by Robert Norton, Gent</title>
                 <author>Stevin, Simon</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Astley, Hugh.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 1 leaf of plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>❧ Robert Norton to the courteous Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I haue too often been an vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling witnesse of the ouer-rash disposition of diuers vnaduised censurers, that would haue themselues estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med skilfull, and yet either will not, or rather cannot doe any thing of worth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, not sparing to cauill, detract, and iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously to burthen other mens well pretended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours, with vnworthy and vndeserued scoffes and scandalls: but in stead of reading to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, and then to examine their true validitie, that so with iudgement they might censure them, haue crittically plaid the right Momes: And though I hope not as Iacke alone, to escape that<pb facs="2"/>which few or none haue done before me: yet the respect I haue to the publike good, that you my Countrymen, such as either want leisure or lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, may become partakers of these excellent inuentions of that famous forraigne Authour, more preuailing with mee, then the carelesse re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard I haue of such iniuries could hinder, I haue, as you see, aduentured to prouide for this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy stranger, this English welcome, and haue preferred some few of mine owne friends (though vnworthy) to accompany him: And so commending him to your courteous entertainements, doe bid you hartily farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all courtesie, R. N.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>