<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READERS ON my second Booke.</title>
           <author>Austin, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104457_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23268</idno>
           <idno type="STC">971</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104457</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READERS ON my second Booke.</title>
                 <author>Austin, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Avstins Vrania, or, The heavenly mvse : in a poem fvll of most feeling meditations for the comfort of all soules, at all times: by S.A. B. of Arts of Ex. Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Austin, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                            <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 136 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="43"/>
   <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT TO THE READERS ON my second Booke.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Good Readers!</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I here come farre short of mine owne aymes, and your expectations, I shall intreate you to make this vse of it; the apprehension of that great Mystery of saluation (which I here treate of) is a matter of far greater difficulty, then at first I took it for: yea sure it is an Art so hard, and of so heauenly a nature, that <note n="*" place="margin">Math. 16.17. Iohn. 1.13.</note> flesh and blood can neuer attaine the knowledge of it, but it must be reuealed vnto vs from our Father which is in Heauen. Whence it came to passe, that whereas I thought presently to apprehend it vpon the first onset, without any further trouble, I was cast downe suddenly by mine owne sinnes and infirmities, euen to despaire of my selfe, and there lay for a long time in a speakelesse misery, till God of his free good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse at length restor'd me, and brought me to the happy sight hereof by the sweee helpe and aydance of his Word and Spirit. So that the readiest way to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this happy assurance, is to abandon all Papisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call presumings on selfe-abilities, and to annihilate ourselues as twere, by a faithfull humility, that so wee may<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> become the sonnes of God, by that sole power of Christ Iesus; and by a <note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 4.24.</note> new Creation be transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into his blessed likenesse, till in his good time,
<pb facs="44"/>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Philip. 3.9.</note> being found in him, not hauing our owne righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Christ, the righteousnesse which is of God by faith, we shall at length appeare vnspotted before the presence of our God in the highest heauens, and there enioy that eternall weight of glory which hee hath prepared for vs. Now, if you make this good vse of it, you shall doe well. Fare yee well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>S. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>