<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104826_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17282</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4125</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104826</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The practice of meditating with profit : The misteries of our Lord, the Blessed Vergin &amp; saints. Gathered out of diuers good authors, and published by the very Reuerend Master Iohn Alberto Buronzo, chanon of the cathedral church of Verselles. Reuiued and augmented by the same author, &amp; translated into English by a Father of the Societie of Iesus</title>
                 <author>Berzetti, Nicolas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaye (Jaey), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Mechelen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>11, 1, 371, 9 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="6" facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and different exercises of men in this life, the meditation of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and diuine thinges, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out al doubt is one of the most excellent. For by meanes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with our vnderstanding, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the light of Gods assisting grace, we doe search &amp; find out Gods holy wil, which is our sanctification; with our wil we desire &amp; loue the same; with our memory we cal it to mind, we apprehend it with our imagination, and in some sort do imbrace it with our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral senses and the faculties of our body, the better to put it in execution.</p>
   <pb n="7" facs="4"/>
   <p>Most iusty therfore may be said, that there remayneth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n man any one power either internal or external, which by meanes of this holy exercise is not wholy imployed in the praises of almighty God, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s a great part of that end for which mā was created, &amp; plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this world. Neither doth man only by meanes of medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iō attaine his proper end, &amp; the cause of his being in this presēt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ife, but also by a certain kind of participatiō, &amp; in some propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ion, doth vnite himself to that which is proper to the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ife, (which consisting, in see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng, louing, &amp; enioying the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ious maiesty of almighty God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ccording to the degree of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y ones merit, and that without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nterruption or desire of ought
<pb n="8" facs="5"/> els:) out of doubt, man giuing himself wholy in the exercise of meditation to seeke the most perfect knowledg of the most vnited loue, and the most swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test enioying of God, which this wretched life affords, he doth participat proportinally of that glorious happines in heauen, which is the last, and accomplished portion, and that happy end for which man was created,</p>
   <p>True it is, that through the vnhappy condition of this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome world, he being di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by other thoughts, and surprised by other affections cannot continually or withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> some violence, enioy this so great felicity: yet neuerthele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> he may with the help of God (from whom euery good medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="9" facs="5"/> proceedeeh, (as his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect gift) of whome therein he treateh, &amp; with whom he then conuerseth, and reasoneth) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his own diligence, and industry, attayn to such vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Gods diuine Maiesty, that he may, if not continually, at least for som time, enioy his creatour with some perfection. Therefore in this as in al other noble exercises, there must be vsed much diligence to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it wel, not only for the causes set down already, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so for that the nature of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation it self (as it is explicated by holy Doctors) doth exact no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esse. For meditation somtimes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s called a studious intention of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he mind, which diligently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>endeth to the finding out of some matter; sometime an espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial
<pb n="10" facs="6"/> application of our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing seriously imployed in searching out the truth; at other times an industrious inforcing of the mind, endeuouring to find out obscure things, and to vnfould the intricat and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed; as also it is described to be an earnest and vehement applicatiō of our mind to seeke, know, &amp; tast some diuine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; finally it hath other names, and definitions, al which doe playnly shew that great labour and industry is required on his part who intends to meditate. Wherefore it shal not be amisse to set down briefly the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal manner which is to be held in this so holy an exercise, to the intent it be not performed neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, or without the fruit which by it is pretended. I wil
<pb n="11" facs="6"/> therefore, for more facility, and cleerenes set down first what is to be done before me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, then what in the very time of meditation, and lastly what is meete to be obserued at the end thereof.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>