<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>What commodities and instructions may be eaped by diligent reading this Discourse.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104566_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09429</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1972</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104566</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>What commodities and instructions may be eaped by diligent reading this Discourse.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A trve discovrse of the late voyages of discouerie, for the finding of a passage to Cathaya, by the Northvveast, vnder the conduct of Martin Frobisher Generall : deuided into three bookes. In the first wherof is shewed, his first voyage. Wherein also by the vvay is sette out a geographicall description of the worlde, and what partes thereof haue bin discouered by the nauigations of the Englishmen. Also, there are annexed certayne reasons, to proue all partes of the worlde habitable, with a generall mappe adioyned. In the second, is set out his second voyage, vvith the aduentures and accidents thereof. In the thirde, is declared the strange fortunes which hapned in the third voyage, with a seuerall description of the countrey and the people there inhabiting. VVith a particular card therevnto adioyned of Meta Incognita, so farre forth as the secretes of hte voyage may permit</title>
                 <author>Best, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 52, 39, 1, 68 pages 2 folded leaves of plates, illustrations, 2 maps, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Arguments &amp; Summaries</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="summary">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>What commodities and instructions may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eaped by diligent reading this Discourse.</head>
   <list>
      <item>1 FIrst, by example may be gathered, how a Discouerer of new Countries, is to procéede in his first attempt of any Discouerie.</item>
      <item>2 Item, how he shoulde be prouided of shipping, victuals, munition, and choice of men.</item>
      <item>3 Howe to procéede and deale with straunge people, be the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> neuer so barbarous, cruell and fierce, eyther by lenitie or otherwise.</item>
      <item>4 Howe trade of Marchandize maye be made withoute money.</item>
      <item>5 How a Pilot may deale, being enuironed wyth moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Ise in the frosen Sea.</item>
      <item>6 How lengths of dayes, chaunge of seasons, Sommers and Winters, do differ in sundry regions.</item>
      <item>7 How dangerous it is to attempt new Discoueries, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the length of the voyage or the ignoraunce of the language, the want of Interpretors, newe and vnaccusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Elementes and ayres, straunge and vnsauery meats, daunger of théeues and robbers, fiercenesse of wilde beasts and fishes, hugenesse of wooddes, daungerousnesse of Seas, dreade of tempestes, feare of hidden rockes, stéepenesse of mountaines, darkenesse of sodaine falling fogges, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall paines taking withoute anye reste, and infinite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</item>
      <item>8 How pleasaunt and profitable it is, to attempt newe Discoueries, either for the sundry sights &amp; shapes of strāge beastes and fishes, the wonderful workes of nature, the different manners and fashions of diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rse nations, the sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> sortes of gouernemente, the sight of straunge trées, fruite, foules, and beastes, the infinite treasure of Pearle, Gold and Siluer, the newes of new found landes, the sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie positions of the Sphere, and many others.</item>
      <item>
         <pb facs="2"/>9 How valiaunt Captaines vse to deale vpon extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and otherwise.</item>
      <item>10 How trustie souldiers dutifully vse to serue.</item>
      <item>11 Also here may be seene a good exāple to be obserued of any priuate person, in taking notes, and making obserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of al such things as are requisite for a Discouerer of new Countries.</item>
      <item>12 Lastly, the Reader here maye sée a good paterne of a well gouerned seruice, sundrye instructions of matters of Cosmographie, Geographie, and Nauigation, as in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding more at large may be séene.</item>
   </list>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>