<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the Reader.</title>
           <author>M., B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104517_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05711</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1585</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104517</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>M., B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The trauayled pylgrime : bringing newes from all partes of the worlde, such like scarce harde of before. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed</title>
                 <author>La Marche, Olivier de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the matter (gentle Reader) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined
in this my simple treatise, be not
altogither fruitlesse, but that manye
things therein might verye vvell be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended,
yet notvvithstanding so farre I presume
of thy indifferent iudgement, that thou vvilt not
be according to the common sort of curious qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rellers,
a captious or a malipert correctour of
the labours or diligent studie of anye to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
although in some poyntes thou bee able to
correct: but fauourably consider the good vvill of
the wryter, and then if anye thing chaunce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie
to thy mind, show foorth thy friendly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations,
with such ordred corrections, as may
not onely encourage the Author, but also get to
thy selfe in lyke effect lyke cōmendation or praise.
It is hard for one to please many: therfore in fewe
wordes I haue thought good, to knit togither this
my simple vvorke, called the trauayled Pilgrime,
wherein is set foorth the state of man, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable
assaultes, that he is daylie and hourely
enuironed withall, not onely with outward or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily
enimies, as losse of goodes, or lyfe, of wyfe,
children, or familier friends, which eftsones hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens,
<pb facs="5"/>
as the losse of goodes by theft, or fyre, the
death of thy friende or familye, by slaunder and
murther, these and suche lyke distu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>bances, still
eyther in the one or other, man is alwayes subiect
vnto, yet better to be auoyded, then the inwarde
cogitations or thoughts, which daylie by Sathan,
man is vexed and moued, for the one may by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience,
in suffering vvrongful dealing, oftentimes
escape the doings, which otherwise myght else
happen to his or there great payne and grieuance:
the other must not onely be ouercome with paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
in suffering, but also fayth and good workes
must proceede, vvhich be tvvo chiefe causes, that
God by his sonne Iesus Christe beyng oure Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator,
doth continuallye heare, not the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard
prayers only, but also our invvard thoughts
so long as true hope vvyth these three doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne,
that is to say, pacience in suffring, fayth in
beleeuing, that God in Christ Iesus, is able, &amp; vvill
forgiue the sinnes &amp; offences of all true obedient
harts: good vvorks, doth and shall receyue hir re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard,
vvhich is euerlasting life. And hope then is
brought from calamities vvhich she long desired,
vnto iocundity &amp; triumphant glory. Thus much
<pb facs="5"/>
gentle Reader. I haue thought good to vvrite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the state of man, but vvhatsoeuer I haue
left vnvvritten in this my base and simple Epistle,
although not altogither it chaunce to please some
frovvarde braynes, yet as much as I haue thought
conuenient, so much haue I vvritten, not that I
knovve in my selfe, but that by the vvise and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
many things may be amended: impute ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the lacke of any thing which may chaunce to
discontent Tyme, not to ignorance, but only
the full minde and effect hereof to
the vvriter, vvho thinkes
this done suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
   <l>Read, but deride not, at merie things laugh not,</l>
   <l>After mirth cometh sorow, for Momus I care not</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>Farevvell in the Lorde.
S. B. M.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>