<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>FAVLTES ESCAPED, AND certaine observations.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104142_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03475</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13597</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104142</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>FAVLTES ESCAPED, AND certaine observations.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Panēguris D. Elizabethæ, Dei gratiâ Angliæ, Franciæ, &amp; Hiberniæ Reginæ : A sermon preached at Pauls in London the 17. of November ann. Dom. 1599. the one and fortieth yeare of her Maiesties raigne, and augmented in those places wherein, for the shortnes of the time, it could not there be then delivered. VVherevnto is adioyned an apologeticall discourse, whereby all such sclanderous accusations are fully and faithfully confuted, wherewith the honour of this realme hath beene vncharitably traduced by some of our adversaries in forraine nations, and at home, for observing the 17. of November yeerely in the forme of an holy-day, and for the ioifull exercises, and courtly triumphes on that day in the honour of her Maiestie exhibited. By Thomas Holland, Doctor of Divinity, &amp; her Highnes professor thereof in her Vniversity of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Holland, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Broome (Brome), Joan</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>164 pages, 1 leaf of folded plates, coat of arms, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <pb facs="14"/>
   <head>FAVLTES ESCAPED, AND certaine observations.</head>
   <p>B: 1: a: Two Benefactors to Oxford lefte out viz: HVMPH. Duke of Glocester and R. LICHFIELD Arch-deacon of Middlesex. B 3. a hāme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d, for broken B 4 a into Ireland for in Ireland L 3. a that watered for which watered ibid were only fructifying for that they were &amp;c. D 4 a. came proue him, to proue him ibid in hart, in her hart E 1: b. as, where E 3 b. not further, not intending further, b in that sort that, in that sort as the &amp;c. O. 2. a. where the day of the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is laid downe the 17. of November vid e 43. yeare, 41. l. 2. b. the 17. of September, the. 7 L. 2 b Ismolaus, Iohannes Molanus. L. 4 a. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this thing for after lothing. M. 1 a. The Collyridians: this word is vsed by Epiphanius in al the Greeke coppies that I haue seene, the greeke worde is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and it signifieth <hi>Panis Subcinericius</hi> a cake; baked vnder the ashes of this looke Antoni-Nebris: cap: 13: L: 1: bquing P 1. b. Since the greatest &amp; strongest nation now known in the world this day For: since the greatest nation knowne in the world this daie among the Heathen.</p>
   <p>Other faultes escaped by over-much hastening both to, and in the Printing, I desire thee (gentle Reader) to amend with thy pen, as thou seest cause.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>