<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authour his wordes farder to
king Philip, then at the time of
writing thereof, Prince of
Spayne.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104917_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18098</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4739</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104917</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authour his wordes farder to
king Philip, then at the time of
writing thereof, Prince of
Spayne.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Spanish colonie, or Briefe chronicle of the acts and gestes of the Spaniardes in the West Indies, called the newe world, for the space of xl. yeeres : written in the Castilian tongue by the reuerend Bishop Bartholomew de las Casas or Casaus, a friar of the order of S. Dominicke. And nowe first translated into english, by M.M.S</title>
                 <author>Casas, Bartolomé de las</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Broome (Brome, Browne), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>148 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="57"/>
   <head>The Authour his wordes farder to
king Philip, then at the time of
writing thereof, Prince of
Spayne.</head>
   <argument>
      <p>THat which followeth hereafter immediatly: is a part
of a Missiue or letter sent, written by one, who him selfe
was a partie in these voiages: recounting the works the
which a captayne did, and consented to the dooing in
the countrey, all the way as hee passed. And albeit so, that the
saide missiue being put to binding in one booke with other
papers, the binder eyther forgot, or lost a leafe or two: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding,
forasmuch as the said missiue contayned things
fearefull, euen to astonishement, the which one of them that
had done them had giuen me: and that I had them all in my
keeping: I thought good to present you therwithall, such as
it is nowe, though without beginning or ending. For that
this fragment remayning of the whole, is full of notable
pointes: and therefore being resolued that it shoulde bee so
printed, trusting that it will cause no lesse compass on and
horror in your highnesse minde, then the other matters afore
mentioned, with a desire forthwith to prouide for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse.</p>
   </argument>
   <head type="sub">The Missiue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ee gaue licence to put them to the Chaine and
in bondage: That which they did: and the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
led after him three or foure droues of these
persons enchayned: and in this doing, he procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
not y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the countrey shoulde bee inhabited and
peopled (as had been conuenient shoulde haue
<pb facs="57"/>
been done) but robbing from the Indians all their victuals they
had, the inbornes of the countrey were reduced to suche an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie,
that there were founde great numbers dead of famine
in the high wayes. And the Indians comming and going too
and fro the coast, laden with the carriage of the Spaniardes, hee
was the death by these meanes of about ten thousande. For not
one that arriued at the very coast escaped death: by reason of
the excessiue heate of the countrey.</p>
   <p>After this following the same tract and way, by the whiche
Iohn of Ampudia was gone, hee sent the Indians which hee
had purchased in Quito, a day before him, to the ende they should
discouer the bourges of the Indians, and shoulde pillage them,
that when hee came with his maynie, hee might finde his boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
readie.</p>
   <p>And those Indians were his owne mates: of the whiche
such a one had two hundred, such a one three hundred, and suche
a one a hundred: according to the haggage that euery one of
them had: which Indians came to yeelde them selues to their
maisters with all y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they had robbed. At dooing whereof they
committed great cruelties towarde young children and women:
and so had hee vsed before to doe in Quito, in burning the whole
countrey, and namely the garners where the Lordes kept their
Mahis in prouision.</p>
   <p>Hee suffered to bee done great outrages, in slaying the
sheepe with the which they nourished and entertayned for the
most part, both the Spanishe, and the naturall inhabitauntes of
the countrey. And onely to haue the braynes and the sewet hee
permitted that there shoulde bee killed two or three hundred
wethers, of the whiche the flesh was fayne to bee cast away.
And the Indians friendes to the Spaniardes, and the whiche
went with the Spaniardes, onely to eate the sheepes hearts, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
a great number, for as much as they eate none other thing.</p>
   <p>And two men in one prouince, named Purua, killed 25. we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
and sheep fit for carriage like our horse, &amp; the which were
worth amongst the Spaniardes twentie, and fiue and twentie
duckates a peece, only to haue to eate the braines, and the sewet.
So as by this disorder of exceeding slaughter of beastes, haue
<pb facs="58"/>
been lost aboue an hundred thousande head of cattell. By occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
whereof also, the countrey came into a great necessitie: the
natiue of the lande miserablie dying of famine. And Quito,
which was furnished of so great store of Mahis, that it can not
bee well spoken, was by this meanes so assaulted with famaine,
that a strike or bushell of Mahis, was raysed to the prise of 10.
duckets, and a sheepe to as muche.</p>
   <p>After that the sayde Captaine was returned from the coast,
hee determined to depart from Quito, and to goe seeke the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
Iohn de Ampudia, leauing thereto moe then two hundred
of foote men and horse men, amongst whome were a great many
inhabitauntes of the citie of Quito. Vnto those inhabitaunts the
captaine gaue licence to carrie with them the Cacikes, that were
escheated them in sharing, with as many Indians as they would.
That which they did: and Alfonso Sanches Nuita caried forth
with him his Cacike, with moe then an hundred Indians besids:
and in like maner Peter Cibo and his cousin: and they led out
more then an hundred and fiftie with their wiues: and sundrie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
sped out their children, because that in a maner euery one died
for hunger. Also Moran inhabitant of Popaian, caried out moe
then two hundred persons. And the like did all the rest, citizens
and souldiers, euery one after his abilitie: the souldiers crauing
that they might haue licence giuen them to captiue those Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
men and women, which they carried forth: the which was
graunted vnto them vntyll the death of the sayde captiues, and
those deceased, to take as many more: for if the Indians were
subiectes of his Maiestie, so likewise were the Spaniardes that
died in the warres as well as they.</p>
   <p>And after this maner departed the sayde Captayne of Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
going to a citie called Otaba, the which he held at that houre
for his share: and demanded of the Cacike, that there shoulde bee
giuen him fiue hundred men to lead to the warres: which were
giuen him with certayne principall persons of the Indians. Hee
departed some of those people amongst his souldiers, and ledde
forth the rest with him, some laden, and some chayned, and some
vnbounde to serue him, and to bring him meate.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="58"/>
Thus carried hee his souldiers some pinniond in chaynes,
and some in coardes. When they departed out of the Prouince
of Quito, they carried out moe then sixe thousande Indians, men
and women, and of al those there neuer returned home into their
countrey twentie persons. For they dyed all thorough the great
and excessiue trauell, which they made them endure in those br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
countreys contrary to their nature. It happened at that
tyme that one Alfonso Sanches, whom the saide Captayne sent
for chieftayne ouer a certayne number of men into a Prouince
there, met with a good company of women, and young boyes
laden with victuals: who stayed wayting for them without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
from the place to giue them of that which they had, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
so done, the captaine commaunded that they should bee put
to the sharpe of the sworde. There happened here a mayuailous
thing: which was, that a souldier striking an Indesse woman, his
sworde brake a two in the middest, at the first blowe, and at the
seconde blowe there remayned nought in his handes, but the
pomell hauft without that the woman was hurt. And an other
souldier, willing to strike another Indesse woman, with asquare
dagger he had, the dagger brake at the first choppe, the length of
foure fingers, and at the seconde, there remayned vnto him no
more saue the hauft.</p>
   <p>At the same tyme the sayde Captayne yeeded foorth of Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
and drewe out a great number of the naturall inbornes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marriyng
them, and giuing their young wiues vnto his Indians
whom hee ledde along, and the others wiues hee gaue to others
which remayned in the citie, for that they were too olde.</p>
   <p>There followed out of Quito a woman with a litle childe
in her armes, crying after him, and entreating him, that her
husbande might not bee forced to goe with him, for that shee
had three little children, the whiche shee coulde not nourishe
but were ready to dye for hunger:</p>
   <p>And as the Captayne gaue her a churlishe answere at her
first sute, shee returned the seconde time with greater cries, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
that her children dyed for hunger.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="59"/>
And seeing that the Captayne gaue her the repulse, and that
hee woulde not restore her, her husbande: shee beat the childes
head agaynst the stones, and slue it.</p>
   <p>It came to passe also, that at the tyme that the sayde
Captayne came into the prouice of Lili, to a towne called Palo
neere vnto the great riuer, where hee founde the Captayne
Iohn de Ampudia, which was gone before to discouer, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie
the countrey: the saide Ampudia kepte a citie by him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided
of a garrisō in the name of his maiesty, and of the marques
Frauncis of Pizarro: and had set ouer them for gouernours or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie,
one Petre Solano of Quennoues, and 8. counsellours,
&amp; all the rest of the countrey was in peace &amp; shared out amongst
them. And as he knew that the sayd captaine was in the said ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
he came to see him with a great number of the inhabitantes
of the countrey, and peaceful Indians, laden with victuals and
fruites. Shortly after also all the neighbour Indians came to
see him, bringing him food. There were the Indians of Xamun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,
and of Palo, and of Soliman, and of Bolo.</p>
   <p>Nowe because that they brought no Mahis which he would
haue, hee sent a great number of Spaniardes with their Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
to go search for Mahis: commaunding them to bring some
wheresoeuer they founde any. So went they to Bolo, and to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,
and founde the Indians men and women in their housen in
peace: and the sayd Spaniards with those that were with them,
tooke them and robbed their Mahis, their golde and couerings,
and all that they had, and bounde many.</p>
   <p>The Indians seeing that they entreated them so euill, went
to complaine vnto the sayde Captayne, requesting that all which
had been bereft them, might be restored them: But the Captain
woulde restore them none, and forbidde them to come at him any
more. Notwithstanding foure or fiue dayes after the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes
estsoones returne to fetche Mahis, and to pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladge
the Indians natiue of the soyle as before time.
Wherefore, they seeing that the Captayne kepte no faith with
them: all the Countrie arose and reuolted from the Spanishe,
whereof ensued greate dammage, and GOD and the
<pb facs="59"/>
kings maiestie offended: and by this meanes the countrie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained
dispeopled: for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the Olomas &amp; the Manipos their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
which are moūtaine people, &amp; warlike, descended dayly to
take and rob them, when they perceiued the citie and places of
their abode left destitute. And amongst them, hee who was the
stronger, did eate vp his fellowe, for all dyed for famine. This
done, the captaine came to the citie of Ampudia, where hee was
receiued for generall, and seuen dayes after from thence hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
to goe towards the harbour of Lili and Peti, with more
then two hundred horsmen and footemen. After this, that saide
is, the saide chiefe gouernour sent his captaines of one side and
other, to bid cruell battayle to the natiue Indiās: staying a great
number of them as wel men as women: burning also their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
and spoiling their goods. This indured a good many dayes.
And the saide captaine was gone towardes a citie named Yee,
withall the Indians whome they had taken in Lili, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leasing
any one: and beeing come to the saide Yee, hee sent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent
Spaniardes to pilladge, take and stay all the Indians
men and women, that they coulde take: thus they burned moe
then an hundred. From this place they goe to a Citie called
Tukilicui, from whence the Cacike of the place yeeded foorth
incontinent in peace, a number of Indians going before him.
The captaine demaunded golde of him and of his Indians. The
Cacik told him that hee had but a small deale, and that whiche
he had should be giuen him: &amp; immediatly al began to giue him
all that they had. Whereupon the sayde captaine gaue vnto
euery of them a ticket, with the name of the saide Indian for a
testimoniall that hee had giuen him golde: affirming that hee
which shoulde haue neuer a ticket, should bee cast to the dogs
to bee deuoured, because hee gaue him no golde. Whereupon
the Indians for feare y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they were put in, gaue him all the gold
that they were able: &amp; those which had none fled into the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
and other townes for feare to be slaine. By reason where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
perished a great number of the natiue inhabitants of the coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.
And shortly after the said captaine commanded the Cacike
to sende two Indians to another citie named Dagna, to will
them that they shoulde come in peace, and bring him golde in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance
<pb facs="60"/>
bundance. And comming to another citie, he sent that night ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Spaniardes to take the Indians, and namely of Tulilicui.
So as they brought the next morrow aboue an hundred persons:
and all those which could beare burdens, they tooke them for thē
selues, and for their souldiers, and put them to the chaine, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
they dyed all. And the saide captaine gaue the little children
vnto the said Cacik Tulilicui that hee should eate them: and in
truth the skinnes of those children are kept in the house of the
saide Cacik Tulilicui full of ashes: and so departed hee from
thence without an interpreter, and went towardes the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of Calile, where he ioyned himselfe vnto the captaine Iohn
de Ampudia, who had sent him to discouer another way, dooing
both of them great outrages, and much mischiefe vnto the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants
of the countrie where they became. And the said Iohn
de Ampudia came vnto a Citie, the Cacik and Lorde whereof
called Bitacur had caused to make certaine ditches to defende
himselfe, and there fell into the same two horses, the one of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie
Rodondos, the other of Marc Marquesis. That of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos
Marquis died, the other not. For which cause the said Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudia
commaunded to take all the Indians men and women
that might be: And therupon tooke &amp; laid together more then an
hundred persons, whome they cast aliue into those ditches and
slue them, and brent withal more then an hundred houses in the
said citie. And in that maner met in a great Citie, where with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
sommoning (the Indians being at peace, and without anye
spokesman to goe betweene them,) they slue with their speares
a great number of them, making on them mortall warre. And
as it is said, soone after they were met, the saide Ampudia tolde
the Captaine what hee had done in Bitaco, and howe hee cast so
many into the ditches: and the sayd captaine aunswered, that it
was well done, and that he for his part had done as much at the
riuer of Bamba when hee entred the same, which is in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince
of Quito, and that hee had flong into the ditches moe then
two hundred persons, and there they stayed warring on all the
countrie. Soone after hee entred into the Prouince of Bitu, or
Anzerma: in making cruell warre with fire and blood till they
<pb facs="60"/>
came as farre as vnto the salt houses. And from thence hee sent
Frauncis Garcia before him to pilladge, who made cruel warre
on the naturall inhabitants of the Countrie as hee had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
him. The Indians came vnto him two and two, making
signes, that they demaunded peace on the behalfe of the whole
Countrie: alleadging that they woulde afoord him, all that hee
coulde reasonably demaund, were it golde, or women, or victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als,
only that they woulde not kill them, as indeede it was a
troth. For themselues afterwardes confessed it to be so. But the
saide Frauncis Garcia, bid them get them packing: Telling
them moreouer that they were a sort of drunkardes, and that he
vnder stood them not, and so returned hee to the place where the
saide Captaine was, and they made a complot, to ouerrunne all
the Prouince, making cruell warre on all the Countrie, in spoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
robbing, and slaying all: and with the souldiers, which hee
brought with him drewe thence moe then two thousand soules,
and all those dyed in the chaine. Before departing the place
which he had peopled, they slue moe then fiue hundred persons.
And so returned to the Prouince of Calili. And by the way if
any Inde or Indesse were weary, in such sort that they could not
passe any further, they did incontinently head them, paring it off
from the shoulders euen with the chaine, to the ende not to take
the paines to open the locke thereof: and to the end that others
which went the same way shoulde not make wise to be sicke, and
by this meanes dyed they all: and in the high wayes were lefte
all those people which he made his purchase of out of Quito, &amp;
of Pasto, and of Quilla Cangua, and of Para, and of Popayan,
and of Lili, and of Cali, and of Anzerma, and a great number
of people dyed. Also immediately vpon theyr returne vnto
the great Citie, they entred into it, staying all that they could:
taking in that day moe then three hundreth persons.</p>
   <p>Hee sent from the Prouince of Lili, the saide Captaine
Iohn de Ampidia, with very manye souldiers vnto the lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynges
and peopled places of Lili: to the ende that they
shoulde take all the Indes and Indesses they coulde: And
that they shoulde bring them vnto him to serue for loadyng:
<pb facs="61"/>
for because that al those which he brought him before time from
Anzerma &amp; from Alli, were dead, whiche were great numbers.
And the saide Iohn de Ampudia brought moe then a thousande
persons, and siue very many. The captaine thus tooke as many
as he needed to serue his turne, and gaue the rest vnto the soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,
which confined them to the chayne in whiche they dyed.
So dispeopling the said citie of Spaniardes and inbornes of
the countrie, both in so great a number, as appeareth by the few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
of the folke, that are remanent: he departed thence to goe
to Popayan, &amp; left in the way a Spaniarde named Martine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guirr,
who was not able to follow the rest. And beeing come to
Popayan, he placed there a garrison, and began to root out and
rob those Indians there, in the order that he had kept elswhere.
And hee erected there a mynt royall, melting all the golde hee
coulde come by, with all that, that Iohn de Ampudia had before
he came vnto him, and without keeping any other audit or recko<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, and without giuing any part to any souldier, taking the
whole to his owne vse, except a little as came in his head to giue
vnto such as had lost theyr horses. And this done, bereauing the
kings Maiestie of his fift part, said he went to Custo, there to
giue in his account and audit vnto the gouernour. But in deede
he went to Quito, taking by the way very many Indians, men
and women, which all dyed by the way, or at the place at Quito.
Ouer and besides that, he altered the coyne royall of the mynt,
which he had made. Here is to be remembred a word, which this
man spake of himselfe, as one not ignorant of so many euils and
mischieues, which he wrought. Fiftie yeres hence, those the
which shall passe by this way, and heere speake of these things,
shall say, This way went a Tyrant</p>
   <p>Your highnes may know and be well assured, that these entries
and assaults made vnto these realmes, and this maner of visiting
the Indians, which liued in securitie in their regions, and the
vngraciousnesse which he did in those same, haue been practised
and executed by the Spaniards, which haue alwayes followed
the same traine and maner of doing, from the time that they first
began to discouer vnto this present day, throughout all the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>