<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL NOBLE AND BRAVE SPIRITED GENTLEMEN, WITH THE EXCELLENT AND VERTVOVSLY DISPOSED GENTLEWOMEN in generall.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104033_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03196</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13316</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104033</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL NOBLE AND BRAVE SPIRITED GENTLEMEN, WITH THE EXCELLENT AND VERTVOVSLY DISPOSED GENTLEWOMEN in generall.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The exemplary lives and memorable acts of nine the most worthy women of the vvorld : three Iewes. Three gentiles. Three Christians. Written by the author of the History of women</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Royston (Reston, Reyston, Roystore), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 212, 12 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO ALL NOBLE AND BRAVE SPIRITED GENTLEMEN, WITH THE EXCELLENT AND VERTVOVSLY DISPOSED GENTLEWOMEN in generall.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the most generous of both Sexes, I commend these few lines, devoted to the honour of all worthy women, of what qualitie or condition soever: come to their first creation; <hi>Adam</hi> was created from the dust of the earth, shee from the ribbe of man, <hi>Adam</hi> without she, within Paradise, and whether we take them nationall or singular, we shall finde them to parallell men, as well in the liberall Arts, as in high Facinorous Acts: For the nationall or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall, what braver resolutions then in the <hi>Troá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
the <hi>Phecides,</hi> the <hi>Chiae,</hi> the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>giuae,</hi> the <hi>Persides,</hi> the <hi>Salmanicae</hi> the <hi>Milasiae,</hi> the <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticae,</hi> the <hi>Melicae,</hi> the <hi>Tyrhenae,</hi> the <hi>Liciae,</hi> the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ae,</hi> or <hi>Cianae, &amp;c.</hi> Of all whose magnanimities there are l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st to us memorable Histories. Come to particulars, <hi>Valeria</hi> and <hi>Cloelia, Micca</hi> and <hi>Megisto, Pieria,</hi> and <hi>Policrita, Lampsace, Aretaphila, Camm Sratonica, Chiomara, Timoclea, Erixo, Xenocrita, Pithis, Lucretia Telesilla, &amp;c.</hi> and others without number.</p>
   <p>And therefore was the opinion of <hi>Gorgias</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived before that of <hi>Thucidades,</hi> who gave pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency and prioritie in place, to such as were least spoken of abroad, intimating that it was necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous in a good woman to keepe as well her fame as her body within doores, neither of them daring to be heard or seene beyond the threshold; alluding to the French proverbe, <hi>La Femme in La Maiscu, et La Jambe rompue,</hi> that is, let the woman be in her house and her legge broke, intimating shee ought to busie her selfe about houshold affaires onely, and not to goe abroad: But more approved was <hi>Gorgias,</hi> allowing both their features and fames a liberall freedome to undergoe any publicke cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
   <p>And therefore commendable was that law amongst the <hi>Romans,</hi> which admitted funerall orations to be openly delivered at the obsequies of any grave and modest matron, to animate and incourage the living, who by imitating their excellent indowments and departments, might be partakers with them in
<pb facs="5"/>
their obituall prayses and extolments: <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the eightie fift of his <hi>Roman</hi> questions, saith thus, <hi>Cur antiquitus mulieres neque sinebant mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere ne que coquere, &amp;c.</hi> that is, why in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times did they not suffer women eyther to grinde at the Mill, or to play the Cookes in the Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n? His answer is, it is in the memory of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made betwixt the <hi>Romans</hi> and the <hi>Sabines</hi>; for after their rape of the <hi>Sabine</hi> Virgins, a peace being concluded betwixt the two opposite nations: There was a Law written that not any of their wives should be put to such petty workes, nor any of their daughters to the like servile drudgeries.</p>
   <p>I spake at first of Arts and Armes, let a few in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances serve for many: Come to painting; <hi>Timarete</hi> the daughter of <hi>Micaon, Irene</hi> of <hi>Cratinus, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> of <hi>Varro, Aristarche</hi> the scholler of <hi>Nearchus,</hi> or <hi>Lala Cizizena, &amp;c.</hi> who might cōpare with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles, Zeuxis, Apollidorus Atheniensis, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stides, Thebanus</hi> or <hi>Nicomachus</hi> the sonne of <hi>Aristidamus</hi>; for musicke and songry <hi>Lamia,</hi> the beloved of King <hi>Demetreus,</hi> and <hi>Aglais</hi> the daughter of <hi>Megacles</hi> were no whit inferiour to <hi>Arion</hi> or <hi>Orpheus</hi>: In Poetry <hi>Sapho</hi> outshined <hi>Anacreon,</hi> and for learning what man was ever knowne to surpasse the <hi>Sibills</hi> and the <hi>Muses</hi>? and for masculine and heroicke spirits, though I could produce infinites to make this pocket booke rather voluminus then portable, let these nine serve to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the entire number.</p>
   <p>For whose greater honour and dignitie, the seven
<pb facs="6"/>
liberall sciences, the sences, all Cities and Countries. The Cardinall vertues, the foure parts of the world, the Muses, the Graces, the Charities are all figured and delivered in the portrackt of women, and even <hi>Sapientia,</hi> wisdome her selfe is of the same gender; who in her creation was not taken from the head of <hi>Adam,</hi> least she should presume to overtop him, nor from his soote, least she should be vilified by him, but from a ribbe neare unto his heart, that she might be ever deare and intire unto him; which showes the alternate love that ought to bee betwixt man and wife.</p>
   <p>In the composure of bodies Philosophers say some consist of parts sejunct (as an Army by Land or Navy by Sea) others of parts compact (as an house, a Shippe and the like) others of parts vnite, or in one nature concreate (as man, beast, and other Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals) so wedlocke consisting of naturall and recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call love, hath reference to that, composed of parts concreate: Children or issue to the compact, friends and alliance, to the sejunct, and as Physitians hold that humors in the body are totally in the totall, so in the true conjugall tie, the persons or bodies, riches, friends (or what else ought to preserve that unanimitie, consanguinitie and correspondencie, to be all in all, and wholly in the whole, which I wish to every one of that honorable order and consocietie, for, <hi>venare juvitis non facile est Canibus,</hi> Fare yee well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>