<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE CHARLES, By the Grace of GOD, King of GREAT BRITTAINE, FRANCE, and IRELAND, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. Sovereigne of the most Noble Order of St. GEORGE, called the Garter.</title>
           <author>Heylyn, Pet.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104019_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03144</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13272</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104019</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE CHARLES, By the Grace of GOD, King of GREAT BRITTAINE, FRANCE, and IRELAND, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. Sovereigne of the most Noble Order of St. GEORGE, called the Garter.</title>
                 <author>Heylyn, Pet.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of that most famous saint and souldier of Christ Iesus; St. George of Cappadocia : asserted from the fictions, of the middle ages of the Church; and opposition, of the present. The institution of the most noble Order of St. George, named the Garter. A catalogue of all the knights thereof untill this present. By Pet. Heylyn</title>
                 <author>Heylyn, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 50, 49-351, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE CHARLES, By the Grace of <hi>GOD,</hi> King of <hi>GREAT BRITTAINE, FRANCE,</hi> and IRELAND, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. <hi>Sovereigne</hi> of the most Noble <hi>Order</hi> of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>GEORGE,</hi> called the <hi>Garter.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>MOST DREAD SOVEREIGNE.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Sacred <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie</hi> being a KING, then, onely in the hopes and expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your people; vouchsafed to
<pb facs="4"/>
Grace me in the Infancie, and cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle as it were, of mine endeavours. Your <hi>Majestie</hi> was then my choise: and I was prompted to devote my selfe unto You, onely upon the true renowne of your Princely vertues. But now I am no longer left at my former liberty. For since your <hi>Maiestie</hi> hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, so graciously to admit of mee to your <hi>Service:</hi> it might be iust<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly accounted an <hi>Apostasie</hi> from Dutie, should I not consecrate my selfe, and all that I am able, unto your Maiesties acceptance. Yet were I, as a <hi>Subject,</hi> bound onely in alleigeance, to your <hi>Majestie</hi>; yea were I borne an <hi>Alien</hi> to your Maiesties Dominions: this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Worke, (which heere in all
<pb facs="4"/>
humilitie I prostrate at your Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious feet;) could not so fitly bee addressed to any other. It is (so please your Majestie) a Iustificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or <hi>Assertion of the Historie of St.</hi> GEORGE <hi>the Martyr:</hi> whom some have so farre quarrelled, as eyther not to grant him, hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, a being on the Earth; or now, an habitation only with the <hi>Feinds</hi> in <hi>Hell.</hi> St. <hi>GEORGE</hi> thus tainted in his Honour, and in a word, dethroned from all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer glories; to whom should hee referre the hearing of his cause, but to your Maiestie: the <hi>Sovereigne</hi> of that most Noble and Heroicke <hi>Order,</hi> which in the first Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, was entituled by his Name; and (as the times then
<pb facs="5"/>
were) committed to his <hi>Patronage.</hi> Which favour if your Maiestie vouchsafe him: this great and weighty cause, unfortunate in such an <hi>Advocate</hi>; will yet be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie in the <hi>Iudge. The onely Ruler of Princes, which hath set a Crowne of pure gold upon your Head; prevent You with the blessings of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse:</hi> and grant unto your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, a long and prosperous Life, <hi>here; and length of dayes for ever and ever.</hi> These the continuall prayers, of</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Majesties,</hi> Most humble Subject and faithfull Servant, PET. HEYLYN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>