<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The Printer to the Historie ensuing.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104310_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03886</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13999</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104310</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The Printer to the Historie ensuing.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The ancient, honorable, famous, and delighfull historie of Huon of Bourdeaux, one of the peeres of Fraunce, and Duke of Guyenne : Enterlaced with the loue of many ladies, as also the fortunes and aduentures of knights errant, their amorous seruants</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>672 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ The Printer to the Historie ensuing.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He foundation of all true fame and repute, which in this world is most to be reckoned of and esteemed, (according to the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Writers both ancient &amp; moderne) consisteth in bold, honourable, and heroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call resolution, which enflames the soule with a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thirsting desire, of pursuing braue and generous pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poses, perfourming of high and aduenturous ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ons, which (when their bodies are mantled vp in the ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>cure moulde of the earth) leaueth their names cannonized in Fames aeternall Calendar, and renownes them as rare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidents to all following Posterities. And from so perfect ground of good and laudable example, the young infant spirits of latter grow'th, raking vp the embers of their worthy proceedings, the sparke of glorious imitation cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth hold of their warme and forward desires, and so en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindling further till it breake foorth into a flame: burnes vp and consumes all conceits of cowardise, and as an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned Beacon on a Promontorie toppe, calles &amp; inuites them to the like honourable atchieuements. Hence en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued that desertfull and well worthy to bee remembred purpose, of Sir <hi>Iohn Bourchier</hi> Knight, Lord <hi>Berners,</hi> when not onely in this woorke of <hi>Huon</hi> of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> but many other famous Translations of like consequence by him perfourmed, he gaue witnesse to the world of so labouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous an endeauour, and (as it were) squared out an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb facs="3"/>
platfourme for generous imitation. But let me not herewithall forget, that the right noble Earle of <hi>Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Lord <hi>Hastings,</hi> was a continuall spurre to him in the pursuite of such paines, and likewise a cheerefull encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rager of me in the imprinting, assisting euer both with his purse and honourable countenance, the trauaile that sorted to so good example. Which being now fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished and made compleat, with better abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of will, then other perfourmance: we leaue to the gentle acceptance of such, as knowe how right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to iudge, and kindly to entertaine: to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers our paines are not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>