<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Authors Preface to the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104903_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12019</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4915</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104903</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Authors Preface to the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The history of the valorovs and vvittie knight-errant, Don-Qvixote of the Mancha. Translated out of the Spanish</title>
                 <author>Cervantes Saavedra, Miguel de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Barrett, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Blount (Blunt), Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>26, 594, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Authors Preface to the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOV maist beleeue mee (gentle Reader) without swearing, that I could willingly desire this booke (as a child of vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) to be the most beautifull, gallant, and discreet, that might possibly bee imagined. But I could not transgresse the order of Nature, wherein euery thing begets his like: which being so, what could my sterile and il-tild wit ingender, but the history of a dry to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, &amp; humorous son, full of various thoughts &amp; conceits neuer before imagined of any other: much like one who was ingendred within some noysome prison, where all discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiries haue taken possession, and all dolefull noyses made their habitation? seeing that rest, pleasant places, ameni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the fieldes, the cheerefulnesse of cleere skie, the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring noyse of the Cristall fountaines, and the quiet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of the spirit are great helpes for the most barren Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to shew themselues fruitful, and to bring forth into the world such births as may enrich it with admiration and delight. It oft times befals, that a father hath a child both by birth euil-fauoured and quite deuoide of all perfection, and yet the loue that hee beares him is such, as it casts a maske ouer his eies which hinders his discerning of the
<pb facs="5"/> faults and simplicities thereof, and makes him rather to deeme them discretions and beauty, and so tels them to his friends, for witty iests and conceites. But I (though in shew a Father yet in truth but a stepfather to <hi>Don-Quixote)</hi> will not be born away by the violent current of the modern custome now a daies, and therefore intreate thee, with the teares almost in mine eies as many others are wont to doe, (most deare Reader) to pardon and dissemble the faults which thou shalt discerne in this my sonne: for thou art neither his kinsman nor friend, and thou hast thy soule in thy body, and thy free wil therein as absolute as the best, and thou art in thine owne house wherein thou art as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute a Lord, as the King is of his subsidies and thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est well the common Prouerbe, that <hi>vnder my cloake a fig for the King,</hi> all which doth exempt thee and makes thee free from all respect and obligation; and so thou maist boldely say of this history whatsoeuer thou shalt think good without feare eyther to be controlled for the euil, or rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the good that thou shalt speake thereof.</p>
   <p>I would very faine haue presented it vnto thee pure &amp; naked, without the ornament of a Preface, or the rabble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Catalogue of the wonted Sonnets, Epigrams Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ems Elegies &amp;c, which are wont to bee put at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of bookes. For I dare say vnto thee that (although it cost me some paines to compose it) yet in no respect did it equalize that which I tooke to make this preface which thou dost now reade. I tooke oftentimes my pen in my hand to write it, and as often set it downe again, as not knowing what I should write, and being once in a muse with my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per before me, my pen in mine eare, mine elbow on the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and my hand on my cheeke, imagining what I might
<pb facs="5"/> write, there entred, a friend of mine vnexpectedly who was a very discret &amp; pleasantly witted man: who seeing me so pensatiue, demanded of me the reason of my musing: and not concealing it from him, said, that I bethought my selfe on my preface I was to make to <hi>Don-Quixotes</hi> history, which did so much trouble me, as I neither meane to make any at all, nor publishe the history of the acts of so noble a knight. For how can I chuse (quoth I) but bee much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded at that which the old legislator (the Vulgar) will saie, when it sees that after the end of so many yeeres (as are spent since I first slept in the bosome of obliuion) I come out loaden with my gray haires and bring with me a booke as dry as a kexe, void of inuention, barren of good phrase, poor of conceipts, and altogether empty both of learning &amp; eloquence: without quotations on the margents, or annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the end of the book, wherwith I see other books are still adorned be they neuer so idle, fabulous, and prophane: so full of sentences of <hi>Aristotle</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> and the other crew of the Philosophers, as admires the Readers, &amp; makes them beleeue that these Authors are very learned and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent. And after whē they cite <hi>Plutarch</hi> or <hi>Cicero,</hi> what can they say, but that they are the sayings of <hi>S. Thomas</hi> or other Doctors of the Church: obseruiug herein so ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Methode, as in one line they will paint you an ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured gull, and in the other will lay you downe a little see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming deuout sermon, so that it is a great pleasure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to reade or heare it, all which things must bee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in my booke, for neither haue I any thing to cite on the margent, or note in the end, and much lesse doe I know what Authors I follow, to put them at the beginning as the custome is, by the letter of the <hi>A. B. C.</hi> beginning with
<pb facs="6"/>
      <hi>Aristotle,</hi> and ending in <hi>Xenophon,</hi> or in <hi>Zoylus</hi> or <hi>Zeuxis.</hi> Although the one was a Railer, and the other a Painter. So likewise shall my booke want sonnets at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, at least such sonnets, whose Authors bee Dukes, Marquesses, Earles, Bishops, Ladies or famous Poets. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though if I would demand them of two or three Artificers of mine acquaintance I know they would make mee some such, as those of the most renowned in <hi>Spaine,</hi> would in no wise be able to equall or compare with them.</p>
   <p>Finally good sir, and my very deer friend, (quoth I) I do resolue that <hi>Sir Don-Quixote</hi> remain intombed among the old records of the <hi>Mancha,</hi> vntill heauen ordaine some one to adorne him with the many graces that are yet wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: for I finde my selfe wholy vnable to remedy them, through mine insufficiency and little learning: and also because I am naturally lazye and vnwilling to goe sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching for authors to say that, which I can say well enough without them. And hence proceeded the perplexity and extasie wherin you found me plunged. My friend hearing that, and striking himselfe on the fore head, after a long and lowd laughter said: In good faith friend, I haue now at last deliuered my selfe of a long and intricate error wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I was possessed all the time of our acquaintance, for hither to I accounted thee euer to be discreet and prudent in all thy actions, but now I see plainely that thou art as farre from that I tooke thee to bee, as Heauen is from the Earth.</p>
   <p>How is it possible, that things of so small moment, and so easie to bee redressed, can haue force to suspend and swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vp so ripe a wit as yours hath seemed to be, and so fitted to break vp and trample ouer the greatest difficulties that
<pb facs="6"/> can be propounded. This proceeds not in good sooth from defect of will, but from superfluity of slouth, and penury of discourse, wilt thou see whether that I say bee true or no? Listen then attentiuely a while, and thou shalt perceiue how in the twinkling of an eye, I will confound all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, and supply all the wants which do suspend, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright thee from publishing to the world <hi>the History of thy famous Don Qui-xote, the light and mirrour of all Knighthood Errant.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Say I pray thee quoth I (hearing what hee had said,) after what manner dost thou thinke to replenish the vacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity of my feare, and reduce the <hi>Chaos</hi> of my confusion to any cleerenesse and light? and he replied: the first thing whereat thou stopst, of Sonnets, Epigrams, Eglogues &amp;c. (which are wanting for the beginning, and ought to bee written by graue and noble persons) may bee remedied, if thou thy selfe wilt but take a little paine to compasse them, and thou maist after name thē thou pleasest, and father them on <hi>Prester Iohn</hi> of the <hi>Indians,</hi> or the Emperor of <hi>Trapisonde</hi> whom I know were held to be famous Poets, and suppose they were not, but that some pedantes &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous fellowes would backebite thee, and murmure against this truth, thou needst not waigh them two strawes for although they could proue it to be an vntruth, yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not they cut off thy hand for it.</p>
   <p>As touching Citations in the margent, and authors out of whom thou mayst collect sentences and sayings, to insert in thy history, there is nothing else to be done, but to bobbe into it some latine sentences, that thou knowest already by rote, or mayst get easily with a litle labour: as for example, when thou treatest of liberty and thraldome, thou mayst
<pb facs="7"/> cite that, <hi>non bene pro toto libertas venditur auro:</hi> &amp; presently quote <hi>Horace,</hi> or he whosoeuer els that said it on the margent! If thou shouldst speak of the power of death, haue presently recourse to that, of <hi>Pallida mors equo pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sat pede pauperum tabernas, Regumque turres.</hi> If of the instability of friends, thou hast at hand <hi>Cato</hi> freely offering his distichon. <hi>Donec eris foelix multos nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabis amicos. Tempora si fuerint nubila, solus eris.</hi> If of riches, <hi>quantum quisque sua nummorum seruat in arca tantum habet et fidei.</hi> If of loue, <hi>hei mihi quod nullis amor est medicabilis herbis.</hi> And so with these latine authorities and other such like, they will at least ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thee a good Grammarian, &amp; the being of such a one is of no little honour and profite in this our age. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the addition of annotations in the end of thy booke thou maist boldly obserue this course. If thou namest any Giant in thy booke procure that it bee the Giant Goliah, and with this alone (which almost will cost thee nothing) thou hast gotten a faire anotation, for thou maiest say, The Giant <hi>Golias</hi> or <hi>Goliat</hi> was a <hi>Philistine,</hi> whom the shepheard <hi>Dauid</hi> slew with the blow of a stone in the vale of <hi>Terebinitho,</hi> as is recounted in the booke of Kings, in the Chapter wherein thou shalt finde it written.</p>
   <p>After all this, to shew that thou art learned in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine letters and a Cosmographer, take some occasion to make mention of the riuer <hi>Tagus,</hi> and thou shalt present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finde thy selfe stored with an other notable notation, saying the riuer <hi>Tagus</hi> was so called of a king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> it takes it beginning from such a place, and dies in the <hi>Ocean</hi> Seas, kissing first the Walles of the famous Citie of <hi>Lisborne:</hi> And some are of opinion, that the sands
<pb facs="7"/> thereof are of gold, &amp;c. If thou wilt treate of theeues, I will recite the Historie of <hi>Cacus</hi> to thee, for I know it by memorie. If of whoores or Curtezans, there thou hast the Bishop of <hi>Mondonnedo,</hi> who will lend thee <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, Layda,</hi> and <hi>Flora,</hi> whose annotation will gaine thee no small credit. If of cruell persons, <hi>Ouid</hi> will tender <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea.</hi> If of Inchaunters or Witches, <hi>Homer</hi> hath <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipso,</hi> and <hi>Virgil Circe.</hi> If of valorous Captaines, <hi>Iulius Caesar</hi> shall lend himselfc in his commentaries to thee, and <hi>Plutarch</hi> shall giue thee a thousand <hi>Alexanders.</hi> If thou dost treate of loue, and hast but two ounces of the <hi>Thuscane</hi> language, thou shalt incounter with <hi>Lion</hi> the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> who will replenish thy vessels with store in that kind, but if thou wilt not trauaile for it into strange Countries, thou hast here at home in thy house <hi>Fonseca</hi> of the loue of God, wherein is deciphered all that either thou, or the most ingenious capacitie can desire to learne of that subiect. In conclusion, there is nothing else to be done but that thou only indeauour to name those names, or to touch those Histories in thine owne which I haue here related, and leaue the adding of Annotations &amp; citations vnto me, for I doe promise thee that I will both fill vp the margent, and also spend foure or fiue sheetes of aduantage at the end of the Booke.</p>
   <p>Now let vs come to the citation of Authors, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bookes haue, and thine wanteth, the remedie hereof is very easie, for thou needest doe nought else but seeke out a Booke that doth quote them all from the Letter <hi>A.</hi> vntill <hi>Z.</hi> as thou saidst thy selfe but euen now, and thou shalt set that very same Alphabet to thine own Booke. For although the little necessitie that thou hadst to vse their assistance
<pb facs="8"/> in thy work, will presently conuict thee of falshood, it maks no matter, and perhaps there may not a few bee found so simple, as to beleeue that thou hast holpe thy selfe in the Narration of thy most simple and sincere Historie, with all their authorities. And though that large Catalogue of Authors doe serue to none other purpose; yet will it at least giue some authoritie to the Booke at the first blush: and the rather, because none will bee so mad as to stand to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether thou dost follow them or no, seeing they can gaine nothing by the matter. Yet if I doe not erre in the consideration of so waightie an affaire, this Booke of thine needes none of all these things, for as much as it is onely an inuectiue against Bookes of Knighthood, a subiect whereof <hi>Aristotle</hi> neuer dreamed, Saint <hi>Basil</hi> said no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <hi>Cicero</hi> neuer heard any word. Nor doe the punc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualities of trueth, nor obseruations of <hi>Astrologie</hi> fall within the Spheare of such fabulous Iestings. Nor doe Geometricall dimensions impart it any thing, nor the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of arguments vsurped by Rhetoricke, nor ought it to Preach vnto any the mixture of holy matters with prophane, (a motley wherewith no <hi>Christian</hi> well should be attyred,) onely it hath neede to helpe it selfe with imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, for by how much the more it shall excell therein, by so much the more will the worke bee esteemed. And since that thy labour doth ayme at no more then to diminish the authoritie and acceptance that Bookes of Chiualrie haue in the world, and among the vulgar, there is no occasion why thou shouldest goe begging of sentences from Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, fables from Poets, Orations from Rhetoritians, or myracles from the Saints, but onely endeauour to deliuer with significant, plaine, honest, and welordered words thy
<pb facs="8"/> Iouiall and cheerefull discourse, expressing as neere as thou maiest possibly thy intention, making thy conceites cleare, and not intricate or darke; and labour also that the melancholy Mare by the reading thereof, may bee vrged to laughter, the pleasant disposition increased, the simple not cloyed; and that the iudicious may admire thy inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the graue not despise it, the prudent applaude it. In conclusion let thy proiect be to ouerthrow the ill compiled <hi>Machina</hi> and bulke of those Knightly Bookes, abhorred by many, but applauded by more. For if thou bring this to passe, thou hast not atchieued a small matter.</p>
   <p>I listned with very great atention to my friends speech, and his reasons are so firmely imprinted in my minde, as without making any replie vnto them, I approued them all for good, and framed my preface of them. Wherein (sweete Reader) thou maiest perceiue my friends discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, my happinesse to meete with so good a Councellour at such a pinch, and thine owne ease, in finding so plainely and sincerely related, the Historie of the famous <hi>Don Quixote</hi> of the <hi>Mancha,</hi> of whom it is the common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all the inhabitants bordring on the fields of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiel,</hi> that he was the most chaste enamoured, and valiant Knight, that hath beene seene, read, or heard of these many ages. I will not indeere the benefit and seruice I haue done thee by making thee acquainted with so Noble and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable a Knight, but onely doe desire that thou gratifie me for the notice of the famous <hi>Sancho Pancha</hi> his Squire, In whom in mine opinion are deciphered all the Squirelike graces dispersed throughout the vaine route of Knightly Bookes. And here withall I bid thee farewell, and doe not forget me. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>