<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE, SIR EDWARD COKE KNIGHT, LORD Chiefe Iustice of the Common Plea's, all health and happinesse in this world, and in the world to come.</title>
           <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1612</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104205_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03648</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13778</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104205</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE, SIR EDWARD COKE KNIGHT, LORD Chiefe Iustice of the Common Plea's, all health and happinesse in this world, and in the world to come.</title>
                 <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A concordancy of yeares : Containing a new, easie, and most exact computation of time, according to the English account. Also the vse of the English and Roman kalender, with briefe notes, rules, and tables, as well mathematicall and legal, as vulgar,for each priuate mans occasion. Newly composed and digested, by Arthur Hopton, Gentleman. The contents follow after the epistles</title>
                 <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1612</date>
                 <publisher>Moore (More), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 252, 2 pages, illustrations, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, SIR <hi>EDWARD COKE</hi> KNIGHT, LORD Chiefe Iustice of the <hi>Common Plea's,</hi> all health and happinesse in this world, and in the world <hi>to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING spent some time in my Art of <hi>Geodetia,</hi> &amp; Bookes of other matter, dedicated to the right honorable, the Lord <hi>Treasurer,</hi> and other times in my <hi>Topographicall Glasse,</hi> to the right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, the Lord <hi>Chancellor:</hi> After (as indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by complaint of some) I obserued the inconueniences that happened to the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar wits, and meane capacities in the calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the expiration of time, by such Rules and Computations as be now extant, occasioned chiefly thereunto by the part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of euery one <hi>Regnall</hi> yeare, with two <hi>Ecclesian</hi> yeares, because the yeare of
<pb facs="3"/>any Prince his reigne (as yet) began in one yeare of our Lord, taking part of the same, ending in the next, &amp; participating likewise therof; by which means, when a question is made by the <hi>Regnall</hi> yeare only, the cōmon doubt is to which yeare of our Lord it an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweres vnto: or a questiō being made by the yeare of our Lord, without mention of the <hi>Regnall</hi> yeare, to know if it answere to the yeare of the King that did take beginning or ending in the <hi>Eclesian</hi> yeere. All these, &amp; many other doubts (which to your Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are trifles) vnworthy the regard of such an ennobled spirit: yet to such, whose vnderstanding liues in a lower Region, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the mists and clouds of ignorance: to these, and the common sort, may this booke bring benefite; for whose sake I haue drawne new Tables and methods, which will be much auaileable to them, for whose sakes also I haue calculated perpetuall Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Termes and their Returnes, gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the same with a <hi>Decemnouenall</hi> circle, as the Paschall Tables bee. And lastly, haue made a <hi>Prognostication,</hi> exact, and <hi>ad minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> for 19. yeares, being referred to the Meridian of <hi>London,</hi> and is perpetually more true then any euer yet extant, with
<pb facs="3"/>other <hi>Astronomicall</hi> Rules, and new Tables, generall and necessary.</p>
   <p>It resteth then, that as your Lordship is <hi>Lex loquens,</hi> out of whose mouth like Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles proceed to posterities, that as you are a <hi>Lycurgus</hi> in prescribing Lawes for the Common-wealth, so you will be a <hi>Mecaenas</hi> in protecting literature for their necessary vse: That as you are a <hi>Cato</hi> in counselling for the good of all; so you will bee a <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi> in defending that which is for the gaine of all. Vpon presumption whereof, I am bold to craue your noble patronage of this little booke, intended for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good: and if time and health (to the pleasure of God) permit oportunity, I will hereafter present you with a worke better beseeming your reading. In the meane time let me not be troublesome. Although your Lordships minde bee continually busied in matters of State; yet sometimes let your eyes view trifles. We reade of a noble Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane that could both write, reade, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere petitions at once; which though he were an admired <hi>Phoenix</hi> for his time, yet such that daily obserue you vpon your Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall seate, reading Lawes to some, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing Iudgement to others, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="4"/>the complaints of all, haue beheld you with like admiration: insomuch that as we may wonder at the rarenesse of your gifts, so are we to pray for your Lordships con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in the place. But lest I proue troublesome, I end, euer praying for your Honours prosperity, resting,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours euer deuoted, <hi>ARTHVR HOPTON</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>