<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104037_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03205</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13325</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104037</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The golden age. Or The liues of Iupiter and Saturne : with the deifying of the heathen gods. As it hath beene sundry times acted at the Red Bull, by the Queenes Maiesties Seruants. Written by Thomas Heyvvood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 <publisher>Barrenger (Barringer), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Play comming accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Presse, and at length ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing notice thereof, I was loath (fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it mine owne) to see it thrust naked into the world, to abide the fury of all weathers, without either Title for acknowledgement, or the formality of an Epistle for orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therefore rather to keepe custome, then any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, I haue fixt these few lines in the front of my Booke: neither to approue it, as tastfull to euery palat, nor to disgrace it, as able to relish none, onely to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it freely to the generall censure of Readers, as it hath already past the approbation of Auditors. This is the <hi>Golden Age,</hi> the eldest brother of three Ages, that haue aduentured the Stage, but the onely yet, that hath beene iudged to the Presse. As this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, so you shall find the rest: either fearefull further to proceede, or encouraged boldly to follow.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Yours euer</hi>
   </p>
   <p>T. H.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>