<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTER TO the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1560</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104326_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03909</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14018</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104326</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTER TO the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A faithful declaration of Christes holy supper : comprehe [n] ded in thre sermo [n] s, preached at Eaton Colledge, by Roger Hutchinson. 1552. Whose contentes are in the other syde of the lefe</title>
                 <author>Hutchinson, Roger</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1560</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PRINTER TO the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ORASMVCH</hi> (gentle reader) as al felicitie helth, &amp; prosperitie of a christen man, stādeth &amp; consisteth in the perfecte knouledge of the true and liuing god and of himself, which knowledge euery faithfull man may plentifully and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly finde in the holy and sacred scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as it were in a moste pure &amp; cleare glasse or myrrour. In whiche all men ought to delight and exercise themselues both day and night, to the amendement of their owne lyues, and to the edifieng of their neighbours. And considering al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> there are many in these latter daies, (God amend them and sende them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grace) the which only study with hād and fote, toth and nayle (and yet would be counted good Christians, when in ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry deade thei ar nothing lesse) to impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the truth and to bury in perpetual ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuie and forgetfulnes the monumentes labours and trauailes of moste worthy men, who refused no paynes to aduaūce true religion and to ouerthrow the false


<pb facs="4"/>
religion superstitiō and idolatry. I haue therfore taken vpon me (through Gods helpe) to set forth &amp; bring to light these sermons which were geuen vnto me by maister <hi>Roger Hutchinson,</hi> to put into prynt, and that a litle before the death of the most Godly king, <hi>King Edward</hi> the sixt, and because immediatly after his death Gods true religiō was ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen and troden most shamefully vnder fote by the bloudy Papistes. I was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced and cōpelled, not only to surcesse from printing of these sermons but also of diuers others Godly mens workes. The author of these sermons liyng on his death bed. Whome (the Lord toke to his mercy) sent to me in my trouble, desi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring me, that whēsoeuer almighty God of his own mere mercy &amp; goodnes, wold loke no more vppon our wretchednes, (wherwith we had moste iustly prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him vnto wrath) but wipe awaiour sinnes, and hide them in the precious woundes of his sonne Iesus Christ, and turne once againe his mercifull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce towardes vs, and lighten oure heartes with the bright beames of his most glorious Gospel, that I would not


<pb facs="5"/>
only put these Sermons of his in print: But also his other boke, called the <hi>Image of God,</hi> the which he himselfe had newly corrected, declaring, that although God should take him vnto his mercy, yet he wold leaue behynd him som litle monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his good heart, mind, &amp; will, the which he bore towards y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> truth of Gods holy word, and furtheraunce &amp; profit of Christes church, for that diuers sectaries wer crept in vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> colour &amp; title of true religiō, who through y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> perswasiō of the deuill hath sowed their diuilish <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Ariās, Anabaptists, Pelagiās, Papists, &amp; dyuers others, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the flocke of Christes cōgregation, might haue som strong ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moure for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sure defēce of thēselues, and fitte weapons, whē thei shal haue at any time, any doing w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> those sectaries to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ouerthrowing of thē. Therfore as the authors good wil was (through y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> help of God) in setting forth y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> boke for thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: So accept &amp; take it in good parte, and geue the thankes vnto God. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching these sermons, iudge of them thy selfe as God shall geue the grace. Thus fare thou wel in him y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> liueth for euer. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <date>
            <hi>The</hi> .25. <hi>of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>