<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Earle of Oxenforde to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1573</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104794_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17947</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4607</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104794</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Earle of Oxenforde to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cardanus comforte translated into Englishe. And published by commaundement of the right honourable the Earle of Oxenford</title>
                 <author>Cardano, Girolamo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1573</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>216 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The Earle of Oxenforde to the Reader.</head>
   <l>THe labouring man, that tilles the fertile soyle,</l>
   <l>And reapes the haruest fruite, hath not in deede</l>
   <l>The gaine but payne, and if for all hys toyle</l>
   <l>He gets the strawe, the Lord wyll haue the seede.</l>
   <l>The Manchet fyne, falles not vnto his share</l>
   <l>On coursest cheat, his hungrye stomacke feedes</l>
   <l>The Landlord doth, possesse the fynest fare</l>
   <l>He pulles the flowers, the other pluckes but weedes.</l>
   <l>The Mason poore that buildes the Lordlye halles</l>
   <l>Dwelles not in them, they are for hye degree</l>
   <l>His Cotage is, compact in paper walles</l>
   <l>And not with bricke, or stone as others bee.</l>
   <l>The idle Drone, that labours not at all</l>
   <l>Suckes vp the sweete, of honnye from the Bee</l>
   <l>Who worketh most, to their share least doth fall,</l>
   <l>Wyth due desert, reward will neuer bee.</l>
   <l>The swiftest Hare, vnto the Mastiue slowe</l>
   <l>Oft times doth fall, to him as for a praye:</l>
   <l>The Greyhounde thereby, doth misse his game we know</l>
   <l>For which he made, such speedy hast awaye.</l>
   <l>So hee that takes, the payne to penne the booke</l>
   <l>Reapes not the giftes, of goodlye golden Muse</l>
   <l>But those gayne that, who on the worke shal looke</l>
   <l>And from the soure, the sweete by skill doth chuse.</l>
   <l>For hee that beates the bushe the byrde not gets.</l>
   <l>But who sittes still, and holdeth fast the nets.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>