<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A
PREFACE TO THE
GRAVE, LEARNED,
and religious Clergie of the
Diocesse of LINCOLN.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104010_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03139</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13267</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104010</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A
PREFACE TO THE
GRAVE, LEARNED,
and religious Clergie of the
Diocesse of LINCOLN.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Antidotum Lincolniense. Or An answer to a book entitvled, The holy table, name, &amp; thing, &amp;c : Said to be written long agoe by a minister in Lincolnshire, and printed for the diocese of Lincolne, ao. 1637. VVritten and inscribed to the grave, learned, and religious clergie of the diocese of Lincoln. By Pet: Heylyn Chapleine in Ordinary to his Matie</title>
                 <author>Heylyn, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Clarke, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32, 132, 132, 78, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>A
PREFACE TO THE
GRAVE, LEARNED,
and religious Clergie of the
Diocesse of LINCOLN.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is well noted by the Poet, that the<note n="a" place="margin">Serò medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cina paratur, Cum mala per long<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s invalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere moras. <hi>Ovid.</hi>
      </note> remedy
doth come too late, when once the mischiefe is
confirmed and setled by too long delayes. And
thereupon he hath advised us, <hi>Principiis obstare,</hi>
to crush a spreading evil even in the beginning,
before it gather head, and become incurable:
On this consideration I applyed my selfe to the present busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse;
and so applyed my selfe unto it, that it might come unto
your view with all speed convenient, before that any contrary
perswasion, by what great name so ever countenanced, should
take too deep a root in any of you, to be thēce easily rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ved.
In the beginning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>March</hi> last, there peeped into the world
a booke entituled <hi>The holy Table, Name and Thing,</hi> said to be
written <hi>long agoe</hi> by a <hi>Minister in Lincoln-shire, in answer to
D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      </hi> Coale, <hi>a judicious Divine of Queene</hi> Maries <hi>dayes; and
printed for the Diocese of Lincolne,</hi> An. 1637. So that being writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
by a Minister in <hi>Lincoln-shire,</hi> and printed for the Diocese
of <hi>Lincoln;</hi> who could conceive but that it was intended for
the private use of you, the Clergie of those parts, and not to
have beene scattered, as it was, over all the Kingdome: But
<pb facs="6"/>
being so faire a Babe, and borne in such a lucky houre, it would
not be restrained in so narrow a compasse, and therefore took
the libertie to range abroad; secretly, and by stealth at first, as
commonly such unlicenced Pamphlets doe, till it had gotten
confidence enough to bee seene in publick; and then, which
was not untill the first of <hi>Aprill,</hi> I had the happinesse to <hi>reade
and peruse it thorowly:</hi> So that as <hi>Florus</hi> said of the <hi>Ligurians</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>,
that it was <hi>aliquanto major labor invenire, quam vincere;</hi> the
like may bee a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>birmed of this and such like lawlesse, and <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>t</hi>
Pamphlets, that it is no less<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> labour to finde them but, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n
having found them, to confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> them.</p>
   <p>For having <hi>read, and thorowly perused</hi> the same, I found
forthwith, that the most part of all the businesse, was to detect
the extreme falshood of the man; which is so palpable, and
grosse, that I dare boldly sav it, and will make it good, such,
&amp; so many impostn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es of all sorts; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> thrust upon the
world in so small a Volume. For first, hee makes an Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of he knowes not whom, and then hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>▪ hee cares
not how; mangling the Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s words, whom hee would
confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, that so he may bee sure of the easier conquest; and
practising on those Authors whom he is to use, that they may
serve his turne the better, to procure the victory. A strange
and cruell kinde of <hi>Minister,</hi> equally unmercif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll to the dead,
as to the living; with both of which he deales, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> did<note n="c" place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
      <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crustes</hi>
with his captives, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
them fit unto his bed▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f they be longer than his measure,
then he cuts them sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>er; and if they bee too short, then hee
racks them longer: Hardly one testimony or authoritie in
the whole discourse that is any way mate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>all to the point in
hand, but is as true, and truely cited, as that the booke it selfe
was <hi>writ long agoe in answ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>r unto</hi> D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
      <hi>Coale</hi> of Queene <hi>Maris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi>
dayes: which, as it is the leading tale, &amp; stands in front of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
to make good the entrance; so doth it give a good essay
of those fine stories and inventions, which we are like to finde
within. One that conjectured of the house by the trimme or
dresse, would thinke it very richly furnished: The wals there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
that is, the <hi>Margin,</hi> richly set out with <hi>Antique</hi> Hangings;
<pb facs="6"/>
and whatsoever costly workmanship all Nations of these
times may bee thought to bragge of; and every part adorned
with flourishes, and pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ty pastimes, and gay devices of the
Painter: Nor is there any want at all of <hi>Ornaments</hi> or <hi>Vtensils</hi>
to set out the same; such specially as may serve for ostentation,
though of little use, many a fine and subtile <hi>Carpet,</hi> not a few
idle <hi>Couches</hi> for the credulous reader, and every where a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
for a <hi>Pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tans</hi> Elbow; all very pleasing to the eye, but
slight of substance; counterfeit stuffe most of it, and wrought
with so much fraud, and falshood, that there is hardly one
true stitch in all the Worke: From the beginning to the end,
our <hi>Minister</hi> is still the same, no Changeling:
<q>
         <l>
            <note n="d" place="margin">Hor. de Arte.</note> Servatur ad imum,</l>
         <l>Qualis ab incoepto processerit, et sibi constat.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <p>And yet if all these <hi>piae fraudes,</hi> (for so they must be thought
in so grave a <hi>Minister</hi>) did aime at nothing else, than to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
the reputation of his <hi>holy Table;</hi> the answering of his
worke were more proper for another Adversary. The <hi>holy
Table</hi> hath no enemies in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
he is faine to flie to <hi>Rome,</hi> to finde out some that are <hi>asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
of the name of the Lords Table.</hi> But so it is, that under the
pretence of setting up his <hi>holy Table,</hi> this Minister hath disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
throughout his booke, such principles of <hi>faction, schisme,</hi>
and <hi>disobedience,</hi> that even that <hi>Table</hi> also is <hi>made a snare</hi> to
those, who, either out of weaknesse, or too great a stomacke,
doe greedily devoure what ever is there set before them. So
venomous a discourse requires an <hi>Antidote,</hi> a timely and a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
<hi>Antidote,</hi> before the malignitie of the poyson bee diffused
too far; and therefore I thought fit to provide one for you▪ for
you the learned &amp; religious Clergie of the <hi>Diocesse</hi> of <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>nc.</hi> for
whō, &amp; for whose use alone, that worthy Work of his, whoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
hee bee, must be pretended to be printed, yet so, hat any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
may be made partakers of it, whose judgment and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
have been, or are distempered by so lewd a practiser, who
cares not if the Church were in a combustion, so hee may
<pb facs="7"/>
warme his hands by the flame thereof. The Author, what he
is, is not yet discovered; all that is openly revealed, is that
hee was a <hi>Minister in Lincoln-shire,</hi> as in the Title; <hi>some Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster
of the Diocese,</hi> as the <hi>Licence</hi> cals him. The booke, if wee
beleeve the Title-page, was writ long agoe, <hi>in answer unto Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi>
Coal, <hi>a judicious Divine of Queene</hi> Maries <hi>dayes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>:</hi> but
what the Author meanes by Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, is not so
easie to determine. If hee speakes <hi>properly, literally,</hi> and <hi>anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently,</hi>
as in the first part of the Title he would same be thought;
hee may perhaps meet with a<note n="e" place="margin">Doctor <hi>Coal</hi> was Deane of <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>. Paul,</hi> in Qu. <hi>Maries</hi> time, as in the Acts and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>on. <hi>part.</hi> 3.</note> Doctor <hi>Coal in Queene</hi> Maries
<hi>dayes;</hi> but then that Doctor <hi>Coal</hi> would not serve his turne,
because hee had no hand in the <hi>Coal from the Altar;</hi> but if he
meane the present times, and reckon them in the ranke of
Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, as if the light in which we live, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
not frō the cleer Sun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>shine
of the <hi>Gospell,</hi> but the fierce
fire of persecution; I would faine know what could bee said
more factiously, to inflame the people, whom he, and others of
that crew, have every were aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ighted with these dangerous
feares. Q. <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, we blesse God for it, were never fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
off, than now; religion never more assured, the <hi>Church</hi>
better setled, nor the Divines thereof more lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ned, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
than at this time under the most auspitious Raigne of our
Gracious Soveraigne. And therefore they that practise with
all art and cunning to cast such scandals on the State, and such
foule slanders on the Church, are utterly unworthy of those in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
blessings, which by the <hi>sword of God and Gideon,</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
of the Lord, and our religious Soveraigne, they enjoy in
both: So that the supposition of a booke <hi>written long agoe, in
answer to a Doctor of Queene</hi> Maries <hi>dayes,</hi> is at the best a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious
figment, and a <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rnicious Imposture,</hi> to abuse the people;
and onely for that cause invented.</p>
   <p>This factious figment thus rejected, all that is left us to find
out this Author, must bee collected by the style and argument,
though that perhaps will give us but a blinde discovery. The
argument, both in the maine, and on the by, shewes that hee is
a true descendant of those old <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>Lincoln shire,</hi> which
drew up the <hi>Abridgement</hi> in King <hi>Iames</hi> his time: in case hee
<pb facs="7"/>
bee not some remainder of that scattered company, which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
hath hid his head, and now thrusts out with <hi>Bastwick,
Prinne,</hi> and <hi>Burton,</hi> to disturbe the State. The stile composed
indifferently of <hi>Martin Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>e-Prelate,</hi> and <hi>Tom: Nash:</hi> as
s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>rillous and full of folly, as the one; as scandalous and full of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>action, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the other was: which, howsoever it may please
young heads, and such as are affected as the Writer is, yet it
gives just offence to the grave and learned, who would have
serious matters handled in a serious manner. They that can
finde him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ut by either of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>se <hi>Characters,</hi> must have▪ more
knowledge of the Diocesse, than I dare preten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to; who am
pronounced before-hand, and by way of challenge, to be none
of the <hi>Voisinage,</hi> and consequently no fit man to be returned of
the <hi>Inquest.</hi> Onely I have made bold out of my care and zeale
to the common<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>good, to give you this short notice of him;
that if by chance you should encounter with him any where
in his private<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, you may take heed lest hee seduce you
by his practi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es; and in the meane time be forwarned, lest he
misguide you by his writings: For comming in the habit of a
neighb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ur <hi>Minister,</hi> especially being recommended to you, for
one so <hi>Orthodox in doctrine, and cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nant in discipline to the
Church of England;</hi> you might perchance be apt to give cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit
to him, and lend too credulous an eare to his slie temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
Therefore to save that title which the Church hath in you,
and to preserve that interest which it claimes in your best affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
I have adventured to put in this <hi>Caveat,</hi> in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
name; which if you should neglect, as I hope you will
not, I must bee forced in maintenance of her right and interest,
to bring my <hi>double quarrell.</hi> Bookes of a popular argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and followed in a popular way, are commonly much
cherished by that race of men, who love to runne crosse to all
publick-order. And therefore it concernes all Churchmen,
and you especially of that <hi>Diocese,</hi> for which that worthy
Woke was printed, to have a wise and timely care, that those
which are committed to your severall charges, be rightly bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced,
and not inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>igled and abused by the neate subtleties of
those, who onely labour to deceive them.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>
And it concernes us all, the rather, because those factious
and schismaticall Pamphlets, that came out with, and since the
good <hi>Ministers</hi> Booke, seeme to indeavour nothing more,
than to possesse mens mindes, as before I said, with dangerous
and desperate, though most needlesse feares, that all things goe
not right amongst us. The placing of the <hi>holy Table</hi> in that
comly sort, as is most cōsonant to the practise of the <hi>Primitive</hi>
times, and to the generall usage of all <hi>Cathedrals</hi> in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
and his Majesties <hi>Chappels,</hi> given out by false and factious
men; onely to bee a preamble to a greater change: And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
in it selfe it bee a matter of <hi>indifferent nature,</hi> and so
acknowledged to bee both by the <hi>Minister</hi> himselfe, good
man, and by the writer of the letter to the <hi>Vicar</hi> of <hi>Grantham;</hi>
and that the <hi>Table</hi> be so placed in his Lordships Chappell, (by
whom the Ministers booke was allowed and licenced) as is
<note n="f" place="margin">Vide Sect. 2. ch. 4. in fine.</note> elsewhere said; this comes all to one: for place them▪ how
they will in Cathedrall Churches, his Majesties and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops
Chappels, and be the matter so indifferent, as no one
thing more; yet take we heed we doe not place them <hi>Altar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise</hi>
in <hi>Parochiall</hi> Churches; rather than so, poore people must
bee frighted with wee know not what, and told that there is
somewhat in it which is worth their feares; something that
mainly tends unto the alteration of religion here by law esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished.
As if the Table could not stand where the <hi>Altar</hi> did,
or be placed <hi>Altar-wise</hi> all along the wall; but it must needs
implie some <hi>Popish</hi> and prohibited sacrifice, to be intended for
the same, though not yet ready to be offered. In which most
false and scandalous imputations, as all the Pamphlets of these
times are extremely guilty; so there is none more positive in
it, than this <hi>Minister of Lincoln Diocesse.</hi>
      <q>These <hi>new Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi>
(I desire you to observe his words) though they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
and lay grounds for the same, dare not (for feare of so
many lawes and Canons) apparently professe this <hi>Eleusinian</hi>
doctrine. They are as yet busied in taking in the out-works,
and that being done, they may in time have a bout with
the Fort it selfe.</q> A speech of that schismaticall, facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
and seditious nature, that greater of that kinde was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb facs="8"/>
uttered by <hi>Bastwicke, Layton, Burton, Prynne,</hi> or any pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
Pasquill of the present, <hi>ne dum</hi> in any of the former times.
And though you may conjecture <hi>ex pede Herculem,</hi> what you
are like to finde by this, in the whole bulke of the discourse:
yet for your better satisfaction, I will lay before you, as by way
of Parallel, the harmony or agreement which is betweene him
in his <hi>holy Table,</hi> and <hi>H. Burton</hi> in his late seditious <hi>Sermon,</hi>
and <hi>Apologie.</hi> Not in the language onely, which is in both so
like, and so full of clamour, as if they had but one pen between
them; but in their factious and schismaticall positions, in which
they doe agree so sweetly. Which done, it shall be left to you
to consider of it, whether it may be possible that they should
jump so even, in so many passages, by meere inspiration, and
the enthusiasme of the same ill spirit, or that they rather fell
upon it, (as <hi>Iuglers</hi> sometimes doe their tricks) by combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and confederacy.</p>
   <p>
      <table>
         <row>
            <cell>The Minister of Lincoln.</cell>
            <cell>
               <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>.</hi> Burton of London.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>THese <hi>new reformers,</hi>
though they prepare and
lay grounds for the same, dare
not (for feare of so many laws
and Canons) apparently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse
this <hi>Eleusinian doctrine.</hi>
They are as yet busied in take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in the out-workes, and
that being done, they may in
time have a bout with the
fort it selfe. <hi>pag.</hi> 204.</cell>
            <cell>THey must first downe
with Tables, and up with
<hi>Altars,</hi> &amp;c. And what then?
Surely a <hi>Priest</hi> is not farre off.
But where is the <hi>sacrifice?</hi>
Stay a while; that service
comes last, and all these are
preparations unto it. So as all
these Preambles doe at last
usher in the great God of the
host, so soone as it is well ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked;
and the peoples stomacks
fitted to digest so hard a bit.
<hi>pag.</hi> 105.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>I appeale to any indifferent
men, that pretend to any
knowledge in divinity; if the
<pb facs="9"/>
               <hi>Reading Pew,</hi> the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> or
any <hi>other place</hi> in the Church;
be not as properly an Altar, as
is our holy Table, howsoever
situated. <hi>pag.</hi> 75, 76.</cell>
            <cell>Well, yet a raile must bee
made about it, to insinuate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
peoples mindes an opinion
of some extraordinary sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
in the <hi>Table,</hi> more than in
<hi>other places</hi> of the Church, as
the <hi>Pulpit, Pew,</hi> or <hi>Font. p.</hi> 33.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>A number of our Churches
have their Iles of such a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
crosse, that they cannot
possibly see either high <hi>Altar,</hi>
or so much as the Chancell.
<hi>pag.</hi> 224.</cell>
            <cell>When they must use no
prayer at all after the Sermon,
but come downe, and reade a
second or third service at the
<hi>Altar,</hi> where in great Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
halfe the people cannot
heare a word. <hi>pag.</hi> 150.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>Without which transpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
of the Table, the Minister,
were he that <hi>Stentor</hi> with the
sides of brasse, could never be
heard of his congregation. <hi>p.</hi>
204.</cell>
            <cell>Reading a second service at
the Altar, where even in lesser
Churches, the people cannot
possibly heare without a
<hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntorious voice</hi> of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.
In the Epistle to the
King.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>Our Communion shall bee
at the soonest our <hi>fourth,</hi> and
by no meanes our <hi>second</hi> ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.
<hi>pag.</hi> 174.</cell>
            <cell>And reade a second or
<hi>third</hi> service at the <hi>Altar. pag.</hi>
150.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>It seemes by you, wee are
bound onely to <hi>pray,</hi> but not
to speak the <hi>words</hi> of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons.
pag.</hi> 75.</cell>
            <cell>When they forbid Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
to use any <hi>prayer</hi> before
their Sermons, but the bare
and barren forme of <hi>words</hi> in
the <hi>Canon. pag.</hi> 150.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>God is aswell God of the
West, North, and South, as he
is of the East: and it is <hi>Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi>
to make him more propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
in any one corner of the
world, than hee is in another.
<hi>pag.</hi> 219.</cell>
            <cell>Praying with their faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the East, thus tying
God to a fixed place. <hi>pag.</hi> 129.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>Whereas S. <hi>Paul</hi> reckoneth
up a long Catalogue of graces,
to be <hi>blamelesse, vigilant, s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
modest, learned, hospitall,</hi>
and I know not what: the
man is content the <hi>Puritans</hi>
take all these for themselves,
&amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 191.</cell>
            <cell>The good Ministers of the
Land (<hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Puritan</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters)
are the Kings most loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
loving, dutifull, faithfull,
obedient, and peaceable sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.
<hi>pag.</hi> 48.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>He might also marke some
speciall differences which our
<hi>Canons</hi> themselves doe make
betweene <hi>Cathedrals</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochiall</hi>
Churches; and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly
in an observation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the point in hand <hi>pag.</hi>
182, 183.</cell>
            <cell>But let us examine a little
what force there is in this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument:
Cathedrals are so and
so: therefore all other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
must conforme to them.
I deny the Argument. <hi>Legibus
vivendum est, non exempl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. p.</hi>
160.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>I hope it will be no offence,
if I pluck out this <hi>Cumane</hi>
creature, (who like a saw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
Sycophant, thinkes to
take sanctuary in that holy
ground) from the shadow and
<hi>shelter</hi> of the <hi>Royall Chappell.
pag.</hi> 35.</cell>
            <cell>In the last place being pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
away from the hornes of
their <hi>Cathedrall Altars,</hi> as not
able to <hi>shelter</hi> thēselves from
their pursuers: they flye as
to their last refuge, and most
impregnable fort, to the <hi>Kings
Chappell. pag.</hi> 165.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>Every Parish Church is not
bound to imitate in all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="10"/>
circumstances, the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne
and forme, and outward
embellishment and adorning
of the <hi>Royall Chappell. pag.</hi> 33.</cell>
            <cell>Why should subjects think
to compare with the King, in
the state of his <hi>Royall</hi> family
or <hi>Chappell:</hi> there being many
things in the Kings Chappell,
which were presumption to
have in ordinary Churches.
<hi>pag.</hi> 165.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>It is not therefore his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties
Chappell, but his Lawes,
<hi>Canons, Rubricks,</hi> and Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations,
which we are to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
in these outward Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.
<hi>p.</hi> 34.</cell>
            <cell>The worship and service of
God and of Christ, is not to
be regulated by humane ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,
but by the divine rule
of the Scriptures. <hi>pag.</hi> 165.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>This Table, without some
new <hi>Canon,</hi> is not to stand
<hi>Altar-wise,</hi> and you at the
North-end thereof; but <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-wise,</hi>
and you must offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
at the North-side of the
same, by the <hi>Liturgie. pag.</hi> 20.</cell>
            <cell>The externall rites and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies
in the Church, are
limited by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi>
prefixed to the Communion
booke, and no more to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
or used in <hi>Churches. pag.</hi>
166.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <hi>Doctores legendi sunt cum
venia.</hi> The Doctors must bee
pardoned if they sometimes
slip in their expressions. <hi>p.</hi> 91.</cell>
            <cell>Their works are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
their <hi>naevi</hi> or spots, so as
they that reade them must
<hi>margaritas è coeno legere,</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
pearles out of the mud.
<hi>pag.</hi> 112.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>I should therefore reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
presume, that this good
worke in hand is but a second
part of <hi>Sancta Clara,</hi> and a
frothy speculation of some
few, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 85.</cell>
            <cell>The booke of <hi>Franciscus S.
Clara,</hi> which hath beene now
thrice printed, and that in
London as they say, and is
much applauded by our Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators,
&amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 117.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>And so the Bishop of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi>
must bee ever sending
forth letters of persecution:
because <hi>Iohn Fox</hi> observeth,
that one of them did so. <hi>p.</hi> 98.</cell>
            <cell>So hot is the persecution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
Gods faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters
&amp; people in those Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of <hi>Norfolke</hi> and <hi>Suffolke,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>pag.</hi> 25. that in all Queen
<hi>Maries</hi> time there was not so
great havo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke made of the
faithfull Ministers of God, &amp;c.
<hi>pag.</hi> 65.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> aggravates the
offence of these Testators, that
by making Church-men ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors
and over-seers of their
last wills, <hi>Ab altari sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi>
&amp; <hi>ministros volunt avoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi>
will needes withdraw mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters
from their <hi>Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
functions,</hi> with no lesse of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
than if under the law
they had with-drawne the
Priests from the holy <hi>Altar.
pag.</hi> 167.</cell>
            <cell>When Clergy men dare in
affront to Gods word, to
Christs doctrine and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
&amp;c. usurpe and take upon
them to meddle in the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
even of the highest and
weightiest affaires of Princes,
States, and temporall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,
which is incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
with the <hi>Ministeriall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
Epistle to the Nobility.
<hi>pag.</hi> 22.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>If the Ordinaries now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
where there is no law
or former <hi>Canon</hi> in force, it
layeth a grievance on the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
as a thing <hi>unjust,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently
of a nature where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
obedience is no way due.
<hi>pag.</hi> 66.</cell>
            <cell>And herein we have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ause
to blesse the name of God,
who hath raised up many zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
and couragious Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of his truth, I mean faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Ministers of his word, who
choose rather to lose all they
have, than submit themselves
to their <hi>unjust and base</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
<hi>pag.</hi> 83.</cell>
         </row>
         <row>
            <cell>
               <pb facs="11"/>
This fellow jumbles againe
the King and the Bishop, <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam
Regem cum Regulo,</hi> like
a <hi>Wren</hi> mounted upon the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
of an Eagle. <hi>pag.</hi> 91.</cell>
            <cell>Little Pope <hi>Regulus</hi> play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
such <hi>Rex</hi> in <hi>Norwich</hi> Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse.
And in the Margine. It
signifieth both a little <hi>King, a
Wren,</hi> &amp;c.</cell>
         </row>
      </table>
   </p>
   <p>So farre the Parallel holds betweene them in their words
and writings. And I pray God there be not a more unseene
Parallel at least in their ends and aimes, between this Lincoln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire
<hi>Minister,</hi> and <hi>Prinne,</hi> and <hi>Bastwicke,</hi> as well as betweene
him and <hi>Burton.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>What thinke you now of this consent and harmony be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
the <hi>Minister</hi> of <hi>Lincoln Diocesse,</hi> and <hi>H. B.</hi> of <hi>London?</hi>
Thinke, you not that they hold intelligence with one another,
and by their weekly packers give and receive advertisements,
both what they meane to write of, and how to follow it?
Certainly this must needes bee done by mutuall correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
and combination; at least <hi>non sine numine divûm,</hi> not
without speciall influence of the same ill spirit. Yet I must tell
you by the way, that of the two, the <hi>Minister of Lincoln</hi> is the
most adventurous: who befides all that here is said, hath a long
studied discourse in maintenance of sitting at the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
which good Master <hi>Burton</hi> never winched at. But now
upon the stating of the question by this man of <hi>Lincolnshire,</hi>
some of the latter libells (of which wee have had many since
the <hi>Ministers</hi> booke) have brought in that too; and made it
one of the disparities or <hi>Antitheses,</hi> betweene our Saviour and
the Prelates. And yet the brethren may doe well, not to give
too much credence to him. For howsoever hee hath strained
so much to gaine their favour; and set them out with a <hi>long Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue
of graces, as vigilant, sober, blamelesse, modest, learned,
hospitall,</hi> and <hi>I know not what.</hi> pag. 191. Yet at another time,
he flings them off, as if they had no reference to him. For if
they will expresse no reverence <hi>at their approach unto the holy
Table,</hi> as you know they will not; <hi>take them</hi> Donatus <hi>for him,</hi>
      <pb facs="11"/>
they shall be <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ever written in his Calendar for the children of this
Church.</hi> pag. 99. 100. Or if they doe dislike the callings of the
Reverend Ordinaries of this land, as you know they doe:
<q>He wisheth them presently with M. <hi>Cotton</hi> in the <hi>new,</hi> as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy
of that most happy government, which (by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
of God and the King) all the Laity and Clergy doe here
enjoy in the <hi>old England.</hi>
      </q> pag. 64, 65. And thus he deales
with <hi>Calvin</hi> also, whom he endeavoureth to save harmelesse
all he can, from having any hand in changing the <hi>English Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie:</hi>
yet saith, he was a <hi>Polypragmon.</hi> pag. 144. a man <hi>prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matically
zealous,</hi> pag. 145. And thus he feeds them, as you
see, with a bit and a knock, <hi>altera manu piscem ostendens, altera
lap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dem:</hi> and will be sure to keepe them under, how much so
ever he advance them.</p>
   <p>But <hi>O le quid ad te?</hi> What makes all this to me, may this <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister</hi>
say; who am nor named nor glanced at in his <hi>holy Table;</hi>
or at least named no otherwise, then amongst those Authors,
which were selected purposely to adorne his <hi>Margin?</hi> It is
true, the <hi>Minister,</hi> as if he knew not whom to pitch on for the
<hi>Coal from the Altar,</hi> layes about him blindefold: and like the
<note n="o" place="margin">Holy Table. <hi>pag.</hi> 232.</note>
      <hi>naughty boy</hi> he speaks of, he flings his stones abroad where
he sees most company; not caring whom hee hit, so hee hit at
some body. Yet generally the needle of his compasse points
unto the <hi>North,</hi> and he drives much at one or other, that was
not of the <hi>voisinage,</hi> but an <hi>inhabitant of a remote and another
province.</hi> pag. 3. who used to <hi>travaile Grantham Roade,</hi> p. 71.
and was a <hi>friend</hi> unto the <hi>Vicar,</hi> pag. 110. <hi>Iohn Coal,</hi> as hee is
called by name, pag. 88. <hi>New-castle Coal,</hi> as from the place
and parts of his habitation, pag. 114. A man <hi>whose learning lay
in unlearned Liturgies,</hi> pag. 85. and used to <hi>crack</hi> of somewhat
<hi>unto his Novices,</hi> pag. 122. but to be <hi>pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>yed</hi> for all that, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>married to a widdow,</hi> pag. 168. Who the man aimes at in
these casts, is not here considerable. It is possible hee aimes at
no body, but at <hi>have amongst you.</hi> However, all this while,
that I may keepe my selfe unto my Accidence<note n="p" place="margin">Had the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor kept himselfe unto his A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence▪ he could not have forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that <hi>Edwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> was his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per name. <hi>p.</hi> 23.</note>
      <hi>Petrus dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
securus,</hi> and may sleepe safely if he will; for none of all
these by-blowes doe reflect on him. Done with much cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="12"/>
I assure you, but with ill successe. For now he least of all
expects it, I must draw the Curtaine, and let him see his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary,
though he hide himself.<note n="q" place="margin">Virgil. Aeneid. 9.</note>
      <hi>Me, me, adsum qui feci,</hi>
in the Poets words. I am the man that never yet saw <hi>Grantham
Steeple;</hi> though for the Churches sake I undertooke the Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
of the poor dead <hi>Vicar.</hi> The letter to the <hi>Vicar</hi> being much
sought after, and by some factious hands <hi>spread abroad, of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose
to hinder that good worke of uniformity which is now in hand,</hi>
did first occasion me to write that answer to it, which passeth
by the name of <hi>A Coal from the Altar.</hi> Now a necessity is laid
upon me to defend my selfe, and with my selfe that answere
also, from the most insolent, though weake assaults of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine
certaine <hi>Minister</hi> of the Diocesse of <hi>Lincoln;</hi> who
comes into the field with no other weapons, than <hi>insolence, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi>
and <hi>falsehood.</hi> In my defence whereof, and all my refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences
thereunto, I am to give you notice here, that whereas
there were two Editions of it, one presently upon the other;
I relate onely in this <hi>Antidote</hi> to the first Edition: because the
<hi>Minister</hi> takes no notice but of that alone.</p>
   <p>The method which I use in this <hi>Antidotum,</hi> shall be shewn
you next, that you may know the better what you are to look
for. The whole discourse I have divided into three Sections.
Into the first wherof I have reduced the point in controversie,
as it relates to us of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> following the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister</hi>
at the heeles in his three first Chapters, touching the
<hi>state</hi> of the question, the <hi>Regall</hi> and <hi>Episcopall</hi> power in matter
of Ceremony; and in the fourth bringing unto the test, all that
he hath related in severall places of his booke, touching the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
downe of <hi>Altars,</hi> and alteration of the <hi>Liturgie</hi> in King
<hi>Edwards</hi> time. The second Section comprehends the tendries
of the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church, concerning <hi>Sacrifices, Priests,</hi> and
<hi>Altars;</hi> together with their generall usage in placing of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar</hi>
or <hi>holy Table:</hi> and that containes foure Chapters also. In
which we have not only assured our cause, both by the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and the usage of the purest Ages: but answered all those
Arguments (or Cavils rather) which by the <hi>Minister</hi> have been
studied to oppose the same. The third and last exhibites to
<pb facs="12"/>
you those <hi>Extravagancies,</hi> and <hi>Vagaries</hi> which every where
appeare in the <hi>Ministers</hi> booke; and are not any way reducible
to the point in hand: wherein wee have good store of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
ignorance, fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>fications farre more grosse, because more
unnecessary; and not a little of the old <hi>Lincolnshire Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
And in this wise I have di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>posed it for your ease, who
shall please to reade it: that as you are affected with it, you
may end the booke either at the first or second Section; or else
<hi>peruse and reade it thorowly,</hi> as your stomack serves you. In all
and every part of the whole discourse, as I have laid downe
nothing without good <hi>authority;</hi> so have I faithfully reported
those <hi>authorities</hi> which are there laid down: as one that cannot
but have learned by this very <hi>minister,</hi> that all fals dealing in that
kinde, however it may serve for a present shift; yet in the end,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> both shame to them that use it, and disadvantag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to
the cause, <hi>Great is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> the last, though
for a while suppressed by mens subtile practises. Nor would I
that the truth should fare the worse, or finde the lesse esteeme
amongst you; because the contrary opinion hath been under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken,
by one that calls himselfe a <hi>Minister of Lincoln Diocesse.</hi>
You are now made the Judges in the present controversie, and
therefore it concernes you in an high degree, to deale upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in the cause, without the least respect of persons: and having
heard both parties speake, to weigh their Arguments, and then
give sentence as you finde it. Or in the language of <hi>Minutius;
Quantum potestis singula ponderare, ea verò quae recta sunt, eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere,
suscipere, probare.</hi> And that you may so doe, and then
judge accordingly, the <hi>God of truth</hi> conduct you in the <hi>wayes of
truth,</hi> and <hi>leade you in the pathes of righteousnesse, for his owne
names sake.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>Westminster, <date>May 10.
1637.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>