<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Tomy VVorthy and much Respected Friend, Mr. Thomas Mannering Esquire.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104049_Fr2_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03223</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13340</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104049</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Tomy VVorthy and much Respected Friend, Mr. Thomas Mannering Esquire.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The iron age : contayning the rape of Hellen: the siege of Troy: the combate between Hector and Aiax: Hector and Troilus slayne by Achilles: Achilles slaine by Paris: Aiax and Vlisses contend for the armour of Achilles: the death of Aiax, &amp;c. Written by Thomas Heyvvood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>168 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="46"/>
   <head>Tomy VVorthy and much Respected Friend, Mr. <hi>Thomas Mannering</hi> Esquire.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd my much respected Friend: The Impression of your Loue, after so many yeares acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, inforceth me that I cannot chuse, but in my best re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection, to number you in the File and List of my best and cho ycest Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wishers. True it is, that my vnable merit hath euer come much short of your ample acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement: Howsoe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er, though you bee now absent in the Countrey, vppon a necessary retyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yet let this witnesse in my behalfe, that you are not altogether vnremembred in the Citty: Nor take it vnkindly at my hands that I hauere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued your name to the Catastrophe and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of this Worke: Since being <hi>Scoena nouissima,</hi>
      <pb facs="47"/>
It must be consequently the fresher in memory; as you haue had euer a charitable and indulgent censure of such poore peeces of mine, as haue come accedentally vnto your view. So <hi>I</hi> intreate you now, (as one better able to iudge, then <hi>I</hi> to determine) to receiue into your fauourable patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, this second part of the <hi>Iron Age. I</hi> much deceiue my selfe, if <hi>J</hi> heard you not once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it, when you saw it Acted; if you persist in the same opinion, when you shall spare some sorted houres to heare it read, in your paynes, <hi>I</hi> shal hold my selfe much pleased: ouer remaining</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours, not to be chang'd: Thomas Heywood.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>