<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104252_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07412</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17799</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104252</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A waying and considering of the Interim by the honourworthy and highly learned Phillip Melancthon. Tra [n] slated into Englyshe by Iohn Rogers</title>
                 <author>Melanchthon, Philipp</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Whitchurch (Whytchurch), Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecause I with great griefe haue nowe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten heard, (most dere Reader) that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learned and no lesse godly, ientle and louing man Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Melancthon is highlye belyed, in that a great sorte openlye saye that he hath denyed the trueth, or (that I maye vse their owne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des) recanted (whiche thyng they saye onelye to hyndre the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of Gods trueth) I coulde do no lesse, but turne into our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyshe speache, and also put out, this litle treatise of his: not so muche for the defence of his moste named and knowen fames sake (which he hath yet hitherto kepte vndefiled, so that euen the greatest enemyes of the gospell neither coulde nor haue saied otherwise of hym) as for the coūfortyng of many godly
<pb facs="3"/>
and christen hertes, whiche haue, bene not alytell dismayed and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged thorow suche lyes. And verely not without a cause, for his denying would do more harme to the trueth in these last and most pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relouse tymes, than any tongue or penne can expresse. And God of his goodnesse, bountefull mercye, and great power, graunt that that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer chaunce. At this tyme also, thā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be to god therfore, he hath not onely not denyed the trueth, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so after his olde accustomed christē manier, plainelye confessed and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged it: whiche thyng this his answere to the <hi>Interim,</hi> ynough witnesseth.</p>
   <p>And although this his writing be shorte, and answere not to al the poyntes of the <hi>Interim</hi> (for that would aske great labour, and long tyme) yet it playnely answereth to
<pb facs="3"/>
the greatest misuses and to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry senowes of the Rome bushops moste tryannouse kyngdome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in that boke.</p>
   <p>He also sheweth tokens ynoughe in the booke, that he will at leasure largelier write vpon manye poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes therof. I receiued also a letter with this treatise, from a nother godly and learned man, wherin is writen, that other and diuers lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men in Dutchlande, be in hand to shewe their meaning in writing, as touchyng the same, so that we maye be of muche better comforte then our papistes would gladly se, yea then manye of the good and faithfull christen be, that that <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim</hi> will be w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>standed, &amp; not so sone and easely receaued as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> papistes hope, &amp; many christen feare. This I saie chiefelye caused me to putte out this litle boke, at this time.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
But for that there be haply ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that know not what that <hi>Interim</hi> meaneth, for some. haue not seen it, and some haue not harde of it, ye and the moste vnderstande not the worde, as they that vnderstand no Latine, or not very well, neede dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me to shewe bothe what it is, and also the meanyng of the worde. <hi>Interim</hi> is a booke whiche was at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperoures Maiesties commaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demet, prynted and put forth about the begynnyng of June in this yere of our Sauiours birthe. 1548. wherein is commaunded that al the Cities in Dutchlande that haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued the worde of God and made a chaunge of Ceremonyes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the word, shal reforme their Churches agayne and turne to the olde popishe ordinaunces, as a dog dothe to that he hathe spued out, or a washen swyne to the myre.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
Thus haue ye harde what it is. Now heare what the worde signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth or betokeneth.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Interim</hi> is as muche to saye, as in the meane season, or, in the meane while. And therfore haue they chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened the childe and geuen him this name, because they wyll y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we kepe all the thynges commaunded and contayned in that booke, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meane while from this highedutche parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holden at Auszburg till there be a generall councell holden. There they thynke, (but God sitteth aboue in heauen, and thynketh happly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyse) to make y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> matter worsse. For because it had been an hastye worcke to haue chaunged all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at once, they of their great (I had almoste sayed) greuouse and mercilesse mercy haue borne with vs in two thynges, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is to saye, in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>▪ Maryage of priestes, &amp; receiuing of
<pb facs="5"/>
the communion in both the kindes. But how lōg? Forsoth <hi>Interim,</hi> that is, in the meane while till the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell come. And thynke then to beare no longer with vs, no nor with Christe himselfe, for then they thynke to be so strong, that neyther Christe himselfe nor all that wyll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde by hym, shall be able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande them. This is the meanyng of the worde in Englyshe.</p>
   <p>Unto this <hi>Interim</hi> and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof hathe thaboue named Phil. Melancthon answered, and written this present treatise, &amp; shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to what thinges a christen man maye agre, &amp; whiche thynges may be chaunged, &amp; whiche not: in which treatise y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> reader shall well perceaue, that he nether hath denied the trueth that he hathe thus longe taught and acknowledged, nor yet thinketh to doe: whiche vertu and high gyfte
<pb facs="5"/>
of God, the almighti father of our lord Jesus Christ increase in him and all the christen to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; glory of his holy name, increase of his knoweledge, and sauing of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny soules Amen. </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>At London in Edward whitchurch house by John Rogers. <date>1. Augusti. 1548</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>