<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Christen reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1537</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104610_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10570</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20840</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104610</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Christen reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A co [m] parison betwene the olde learnynge [and] the newe : translated out of latin in Englysh by Wyliam Turner</title>
                 <author>Rhegius, Urbanus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Nicholson (Nicolson, Nicolai, Nycolson), James</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London--Southwark</pubPlace>
                    <date>1537</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>120 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="56"/>
   <head>¶ To the Christen reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat thou mayest the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande (good reader) the arty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cles of Fre wyll, Fayth, Good workes, and of Merytes, which in this present boke be treated vpon I shall here brefely shew what God doth and hath done for vs, and what we agayne oughte to do for his sake as they that be thankfull of the benefites receaued of hym. And fyrste wyll I declare the maner of iustificacyon, remission of synnes, and saluacyon, whiche in scripture are all one thynge, of whom it doth come, and to how many thynges it is applyed.</p>
   <p>Fyrst it is applyed vnto God, for Paul sayeth Rom. viii. It is God that iustifyeth or maketh ryghteous. &amp;c. And Ro. iii. That he onely myght be ryghteous and the rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous maker of hym which is of the fayth on Iesus.</p>
   <p>Secondarely it is referred vnto Christ Actu. iiii. sayeth Peter: Ther is none other name geuen vnto men vnder heauen, in the which we shulde be saued. Roma. iii. sayeth Paul: Without deseruynge are they made ryghteous or iustifyed, euen by his grace thorow the redempcyon y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is done by Christ Iesu, whom God hath set forth for a mercy
<pb facs="57"/>
seate thorow fayth in his bloude, to shewe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ryghteousnesse y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> auayleth before hym. &amp;c.</p>
   <p>Thyrdly it is applyed vnto mercy. Tit. iii. Not of workes or dedes of ryghteousnes which we wrought, but after his mercy he saued vs. Roma. viii. Therfore whan God wolde shewe wrath, and to make his power knowen, he brought forth with great pacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the vessels of wrath, which are ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to damnacyon, that he myght declare y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ryches of his glory on the vessels of mercy, which he hath prepared vnto glory, whome he hath called. &amp;c. Item. i. Pet. i. Blessed be God and the father of oure Lorde Iesus Christ, which accordynge to his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hath begottē vs agayn to a lyuely hope.</p>
   <p>Fourthly it is attributed vnto his elec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon, Ephe. i. Accordynge as he hath chosen vs by hym, or euer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fundacyon of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worlde was layed, that we shulde be holy and with out blame before him in loue. Ioh. xv. I haue chosen you, and ordyned you, that ye go and brynge forth frute .ii. Timo. i. God hath sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs, and called vs wyth an holy callynge not accordynge to oure dedes, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to his owne purpose and grace.</p>
   <p>Fyfthly it is attributed vnto grace. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe. ii. By grace are ye saued thorow fayth,
<pb facs="57"/>
and that not of youre selues. Gala. i. I mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uayle that ye are so soone turned from hym that hath called you in the grace of Christ. Tit. ii. The grace of God that bryngeth sal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uacyon vnto all men, hath appeared.</p>
   <p>Syxtly it is assygned vnto the worde. Ioh. xv. Now are ye clene because of the word, which I haue spokē vnto you. Esa. lv. Lyke as the rayne and snow cōmeth downe from heauen, and returneth not thyther a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne but watereth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth, maketh it frut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full and grene that it maye geue corne and breade vnto the sower: So the worde also y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> commeth out of my mouth, shall not turne agayne voyde vnto me but shall accomplysh my wyll, and prosper in the thynge whervn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to I shall sende it.</p>
   <p>Seuēthly it is asscrybed vnto fayth, as Rom. iii. I speake of the ryghteousnesse be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, whiche cōmeth by fayth on Iesus Christ. And Roma. iiii. Vnto hym that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth on hym that iustifyeth the vngodly, is fayth counted for ryghteousnesse. Ro. v. Because that we are iustifyed by fayth, we haue peace with God thorow our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sus Christ.</p>
   <p>Eyghtly it is attribute vnto good workes as Iac. i. Ye se thē, how y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> of dedes a mā is iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stifyed
<pb facs="58"/>
&amp; not of fayth. The places are so ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifest (notwithstanding y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cōmune opiniō) y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> faith only iustifieth, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I am sure it troubleth no small nōbre of people: and peraduenture it may astōny euen them, which counte thē selues well learned. For it is a great thynge to bringe the olde and wylye foxe to a lease. Yee it is euen a new thynge vnto the proud Pharyses to saye, that good workes are not meritorious to obtayne heauen by: for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto haue they founded and vnderpropped theyr church with nothynge so greatly, as w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thys opinion. What hath abused fastynge more than thereby to obtayne heauen? For fastynge after theyr owne chosynge, they left the true fast, that God requyreth and cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maūdeth. Esa. lviii. &amp; zach. vii. What caused more abuse of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> supper of the Lorde, thē to vse it that is the remembraunce of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefyt and sacrifyce for our synnes, for a net &amp; hooke to gather &amp; catch mony w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>? sayeng y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it is a worke meritorious, &amp; a sacrifyce for redemyng of synnes. Somtyme were none chosen prestes but such as were endued w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> such gyftes as Paul requyreth in a byshop: now y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the B. of Ro. kyngdom requyreth ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny fauterers &amp; adherētes &amp; y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> purgatory may be swepte and kepte clene, the which is no
<pb facs="58"/>
office for such Lordes as byshops be, therfore syr Ihon lacklatyne shal suffise for that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice wel ynough, and masse shalbe made a sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice to pourge and clense pylgatory, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory shuld I haue sayd: Lord Lord opē once oure eyen, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we maye se y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> blasphemy done to thy holy bloude. Now wyll I go to youre cōsciences ye that boast so greatly of good &amp; meritorious workes: I require you by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swer, that we all shall geue at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great daye: Dyd Peter that was prince of the apostles (as ye saye) euer say nasse for the dead ether hym selfe or by other? shew here vpō ony au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenticall cronicle or hys owne wrytynge. Yf ye can not, than graunt that it is an inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of youre owne, ergo a lye and a thynge that shall perysh with your dayes. Yf Gods mercy shudle be bounde to sende soules to youre purgatory, and at youre massynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to release them, than were Christ no Iesus, and God no father but a seruaunt of yours, and contrary to hys owne wordes &amp; doctryne. Leaue therfore youre new erroni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous doctryne, and wyth the olde teachers geue God humbly glory. What caused more the abuse of honourynge of sayntes: whyche dyenge in charite, are ioyned with vs is cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryte, and therfore as true membres of one
<pb facs="59"/>
body, ceasse not to praye with vs, so that worshyppyng theyr pictures &amp; ymages, we rather blaspheme God, which hath forbiddē such maner of worshyppynge, than worshyp them. But leste I be to tedious vnto the (good reader) therfore wyll I do my dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to expresse the pyth of all thys matter in fewe wordes.</p>
   <p>God the father thorow the loue that he had to hys sonne Christ Iesu, dyd caste hys mercy vnto vs, which were sonken into the depth of synne and pytied vs, &amp; of his mercy and pitye he chose vs that we shulde be holy and wythout spotte in hys syghte. And to them that he chose, he instilled the grace of hys sprite, and sent them the word of health which they receaued thorow beleuynge it: &amp; than come they to the felynge of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of God, and of very loue are ready to fulfyll what soeuer God commaundeth thē: and loke how muche they beleue, euen so much they worke. And though it be true y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> we be iustifyed in Christ before the fundaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the worlde were layed, yet is y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> only knowe to God, and we haue no felynge of it vntyll fayth come. And euen as God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth downwarde, (for he thorow Christ had mercy on vs, and of mercy dyd chose vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="59"/>
we were, and than after we come into this world instilleth grace thorow his sprete and than sendeth vs hys worde, whiche the sprete causeth vs to beleue, &amp; worketh fayth in vs, from whence all good workes flowe) euē so do we go vpward, and by my fayth do know surely y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> God hath sent me hys word &amp; grace thorow his sprete to cause me beleue it &amp; therfore cōclud y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he hath chosen me, &amp; hath mercy vnto me thorow Christ hys only son which is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mage of the inuisible God, fyrst begottē before all creatures. Now is my dewtye agayne whā I haue &amp; perceaue this goodnesse of God the father and hys sonne Iesus Christ to me warde, that I stonde not styll and let hys grace be vacant and ydle in me: but (accordynge to the sprete y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> he hath poured in me, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> grace that is geuē me, to vse hys gyftes accordynge to hys wyll &amp; cōmaundement) to procede from vertue to vertue, as from steppe to steppe alwaye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochynge oure louynge fathers kyngdome nearer and nearer, where he sytteth &amp; ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth worlde without ende. To the which brynge vs he that wyll all mankynde to be saued.</p>
   <closer>AMEN.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>