<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104777_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16739</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3646</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104777</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A dialogue full of pithe and pleasure: betvveen three phylosophers: Antonio, Meandro, and Dinarco : vpon the dignitie, or indignitie of man. Partly translated out of Italian, and partly set downe by way of obseruation. By Nicholas Breton, Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Browne, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Cotton, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y your patience gentle Reader, giue mee leaue to laie before your eyes, a discourse vpon the Dignitie, or Indignitie of Man, handled in the maner of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, by two or three concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted companions: that though they were no great Graduates, yet it seemed by that they spake, they vnderstood what they learned; and though they exceed not in their knowledge, yet they went not to schoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e for nothing: two of them it should seeme were younger then the third, who, in his sullaine humour vsed speech that might giue cause of mirth; how euer they disagreed in their opinions touching the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had in talke, yet they parted, and liued such friends, as made good vse each of others company. So would I wish it to be with you that reade, what euer you thinke of my wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, yet so to conceiue of my labour, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not disdainfully spoken of in this, it may be
<pb facs="4"/>
better imployed hereafter: but least I should begge a liking of that which may seeme not worth the looking on, I will leaue my wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ke to the worlds curtesie, and my good wil to my friends kindnesse: and so rest to euery one as I haue reason.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>A friende, Nicho. Breton</hi>▪</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>