<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104267_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03779</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13898</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104267</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An apologie of infants : in a sermon: prouing, by the reuealed will of God, that children preuented by death of their baptisme, by Gods election, may be saued. By W.H. preacher in the Tower of London. Seene and allowed by authoritie</title>
                 <author>Hubbock, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 61, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the blessing of peace is great, <hi>Zach. 8.8.</hi> streets full of children playing, so among them to come sodainely the stroke of God,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.29.</note> as at midnight in Aegypt,<note place="margin">Virgil. Aeneid. lib 4. Si quis mihi paruulus aula Luderet AEneas. Act. 20.9. 1. King. 17.18. Ionas 4.7. 2 Sam. 12.17.</note> in euery house a dead childe, to fall dead from a windowe as <hi>Eutichus,</hi> to sicken in the field, and die at home presently, as the woman of <hi>Sareptaes</hi> childe: especially if it enioy not the next morning sunne, as <hi>Ionas</hi> shade, especially if it dye as <hi>Dauids</hi> child did before circūcisiō: so it before baptisme: &amp; the former ioy doubleth the grief, sillie leauened people lift vp their voice as <hi>Agar</hi> did for hers,<note place="margin">Gen. 21.19.</note> in a gentiles distrust as a people without hope,<note place="margin">1. Thess. 4.13.</note> (as though their babe were <hi>Ismael</hi> &amp; of Aegypt, &amp; not of the Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell of God: as though they were <hi>Agar</hi> of Sina engendring vnto bondage, &amp; not of Sion, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring childrē vnto God) moning there is no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: they blame not thēselues that they keep not
<pb facs="7"/>
houres with God and his Church, in regarde of gossips and outward complement, breaking out as the Sareptane:<note place="margin">1. King. 17.18.</note>
      <hi>O thou man of God, what haue I to doe with thee?</hi> Would to God they would thinke also with that good woman: God in my childe brings my sinnes to remembrance, that departure of children might cause departure from iniquitie. For many take on piteously with God and man if their children misse Baptisme: but take no care if they miscarie their owne Baptisme,<note place="margin">Math. 28.19.</note> forgetting the fellowship of the blessed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, into which they were baptized: so that the water of Baptisme is not the sweet water of life vnto life,<note place="margin">Act. 8.23.</note> but Marah, as in <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus:</hi> A gall of bitternes still in him. Christ should dissolue the workes of the diuell,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.8.</note> but a bond of iniquitie in him still. To such it should bee fearefull in their eares which is written: <hi>The children which yee sayd should bee a praye,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Deut. 1.19</note>
      <hi>and your sonnes &amp; daughters, which haue no knowledge between good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, they shall possesse mine inheritance:</hi> but as for you, <hi>Numb. 14.32.</hi> Your carkeises shall fall in the desart. Where is he that hath <hi>Dauids</hi> hart, a man after Gods owne hart? he moned for feare of death,<note place="margin">2. Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> but neuer moued to haue respite of life for circumcision, which no
<pb facs="7"/>
doubt he would if it had beene so daungerous to haue dyed without it: at least where is the mouth of <hi>Iob?</hi> Blessed be the Lord that gaue mee children: blessed bee the Lord that tooke away my children: blessed is he in giuing, bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in taking away, and blessed in the manner though strange: of him it is sayd,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.21.22.</note>
      <hi>Hee sinned not with his mouth, nor charged God foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishly.</hi> But thy child is thine Image, and thy shadow: and behold as <hi>Ionas</hi> shade, it vanish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thee in a night, it vanished before thou well lookedst vpon the face of it: &amp; howe pitifull a thing?<note place="margin">Ionas 4 11.</note> But the pitifull God telleth him and thee also: that hee pitieth little ones that cannot discerne betweene right hands and left, euen to the number of six score thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand in one citie: and that in Ashur, and Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niueh; and is his compassion shut vp from the seede of Christians? Yea but if it had beene sprinkled with water of Baptisme, <hi>Iohn 5.7.</hi> When the bedridden man for <hi>38.</hi> yeares had none to helpe him into the souereigne wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Christ healed him without water saying, vers. <hi>17.</hi> Though the Angell moue not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the water, vers. <hi>4.</hi> but at times, yet saith he, My Father still worketh and I also work. And though the spring of Baptisme should sometime be dammed vp: it followeth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants
<pb facs="8"/>
to bee damned: for as Christ said to his Disciples,<note place="margin">Gen. 21.19.</note>
      <hi>Ioh. 4.32. I haue meate that you know not of:</hi> so the Angell telleth <hi>Agar,</hi> and all mothers of water that she seeth not: and Christ here telleth of saluation, which the Angell and the water wrought not. Thou missest thy children in thine armes: beholde they are in the hand of God, they are pluckt from thy brests, but are in Abrahams bosome: not in thy cradle below, but in the throne of immortalitie aboue. How oft is it seene amōg men that friendes take a babe from a weake mother, a daughter, a nurse, and bring it vp for their owne:<note place="margin">Exod. 2.10.</note> as <hi>Pharaos</hi> daughter did <hi>Moses,</hi> so that the parents peraduenture ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer see it: or not till long after. What else doth God when he taketh the childe from the wombe, or breast, to haue it nursed in heauen lost it should haue ill bringing vp here? A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with such dispositions vpon a like sodaine accident, made mee gather against the next Lords day, these remembrances touching this argument, which nowe I haue more perfectly recognized. Then it bred such alteration in their apprehensions and opiniōs that heard it: that as once they who sayd of <hi>Paul,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 28.4.</note> hee was a murderer, (as if some should say, <hi>infancieida,</hi>) when they sawe the reuealed glorie of God:
<pb facs="8"/>
they changed their mindes. These also are a holy seede, <hi>Luk. 15.31.</hi> The childe that was dead to mee, is aliue: he that was lost is found: blaming themselues as <hi>Dauid, Psal. 73.23.</hi> so foolish were wee euen as beastes, vntill wee wēt into the sāctuary of God, where we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood the end euē of these little ones.<note place="margin">Math. 9.</note> The Lord of the haruest giue blessing to this, according to the riches of his glorious wisedome, and teach vs to abound not with captious know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which by scanninges, descantings, comparings puffeth vp, <hi>1. Cor 8.1.</hi> But to abounde with loue which buildeth vs vp to one heade ouer all, euen the Lord Jesus, to whom be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed saluation for euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>