<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the curteous Gentle∣men Readers.</title>
           <author>Barnefeild, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104851_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68287</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1484</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104851</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the curteous Gentle∣men Readers.</title>
                 <author>Barnefeild, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cynthia : VVith certaine sonnets, and the legend of Cassandra</title>
                 <author>Barnfield, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Humphrey 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the curteous Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Readers.</head>
   <p>GEntlemen; the last Terme there came forth a little toy of mine, intituled, <hi>The affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Shepheard:</hi> In the which, his Country <hi>Content</hi> found such friendly fauor, that it hath incouraged me to publish my second fruites. <hi>The affectionate Shepheard</hi> being the first: howsoeuer vndeseruedly (I protest) I haue beene thought (of some) to haue beene the authour of two Books here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore. I neede not to name them, because they are too-well knowne already: nor will I deny them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are dislik't; but because they are not mine. This protestation (I hope) will satisfie th'indifferent: and as for them that are maliciously enuious, as I cannot, so I care not to please. Some there were, that did interpret <hi>The affectionate Shepheard,</hi> otherwise then (in truth) I meant, touching the subiect therof▪ to wit, the loue of a Shepheard to a boy; a fault, the which I will not excuse, because I neuer made. Onely this, I will vnshaddow my conceit: being nothing else, but an imitation of <hi>Virgill,</hi> in the second Eglogue of <hi>Alexis.</hi> In one or two places (in this Booke) I vse
<pb facs="4"/>
the name of <hi>Eliza</hi> pastorally: wherein, lest any one should misconster my meaning (as I hope none will) I haue here briefly discouered my harmeles conceipt as concerning that name▪ whereof once (in a simple Shepheards deuice) I wrot this Epigramme.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>One name there is, which name aboue all other</l>
      <l>I most esteeme, as time and place shall proue:</l>
      <l>The one is <hi>Vesta,</hi> th other <hi>Cupids</hi> Mother,</l>
      <l>The first my Goddesse is, the last my loue;</l>
      <l>Subiect to Both I am: to that by berth;</l>
      <l>To this for beautie; fairest on the earth.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>Thus, hoping you will beare with my rude conceit of <hi>Cynthia,</hi> (if for no other cause, yet, for that it is the first imitation of the verse of that excellent Poet, Maister <hi>Spencer,</hi> in his <hi>Fayrie Queene)</hi> I leaue you to the reading of that, which I so much desire may breed your Delight.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Richard Barnefeild.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>