<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>I. C. To the Reader of the poore
Knight his Posies.</title>
           <author>C., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104857_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17462</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4283</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104857</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>I. C. To the Reader of the poore
Knight his Posies.</title>
                 <author>C., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A poore knight his pallace of priuate pleasures : Gallantly garnished, with goodly galleries of strang inuentio [n] s and prudently polished, with sundry pleasant posies, [et] other fine fancies of dainty deuices, and rare delightes. Written by a student in Ca [m] bridge. And published by I.C. Gent</title>
                 <author>Student in Cambridge</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>84 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>I. C. To the Reader of the poore
Knight his Posies.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, the feare of Ignomynie &amp; shamefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch,
hath caused the Author of these Posies to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
his name from the same, whom for this time I
haue thought not much amisse, to collour &amp; set forth
in the name of the poore Knight, &amp; I do duly protest vnto thee,
that without my great intreaty, these fewe Posies had not as yet
come vnto thy hand▪ VVherfore, if that any thing in the same be
acceptable, and worthy of commendacion, attribute the same vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the poore Knight, which shalbe both ioyfull vnto mee, and no
small incouragement to him. But if on the contrary, any thinge
demerit blame, I submit my selfe to beare the reproch, (which
was the publisher of the same,) desiring to quite him, and set him
free, which is the Author: least by his discouragement we should
lose that, which hereafter wee looke for. But by the way (gentle
Reader) I doo admonish thee, that in the first three Posies, thou
take Iudgement to thy reading, least with the Spyder thou finde
poyson, where the painfull Bee may gather Honny: For although
the name seeme somewhat vayne, (yet the outwarde apperance
doth not iudge the matter, according to the Prouerbe: <hi>Cuculus
non facit monachum:</hi> The matter is delectable, and requireth
to bee red with Iudgement. Thus I ende, desiring thee to accept
(my freend) the poore Knight his Posies in good worth.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my Chamber in <hi>Grayes Inne.</hi>
      </dateline>
      <signed>I. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>