<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Noble and Right worthy prince, Thomas Duke of Norfolke, Earle Marshall of Eng∣lande, and Knight of the honorable order of the Garter.</title>
           <author>Hill, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1571</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104092_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68187</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13482</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104092</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Noble and Right worthy prince, Thomas Duke of Norfolke, Earle Marshall of Eng∣lande, and Knight of the honorable order of the Garter.</title>
                 <author>Hill, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The contemplation of mankinde : contayning a singuler discourse after the art of phisiognomie, on all the members and partes of man, as from the heade to the foote, in a more ample maner than hytherto hath beene published of any. In the place next after the chapter of the forehead, hath the phisiognomer added a proper treatise of the signification of sundrie lines seene in most mens foreheads: which in sundrie disputations with a skilfull Iew, he at the last obtayned. ... In the ende is a little treatise added of the signification of moles ... written by a worthie Grecian named Melampus. All which, englished by Thomas Hyll. 1571</title>
                 <author>Hill, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seres, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1571</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 208, 109-132, 233-236, that is 244 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Noble and Right <hi>worthy prince, Thomas Duke</hi> of Norfolke, Earle Marshall of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and Knight of the honorable order of the Garter.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Man the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentest Creature, doth confesse the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie to be the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour and framer of the whole worlde, with all things contayned therein, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen so of duetie must hee faithfullye graunt, God to be the fountaine and spring of all wisedome and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, out of which, this science and Arte of Phisiognomie (as a part of Philosophie) hath hir proceeding, for if a man diligently beholde, not only the sundry and variable formes and shapes of liuing creatures, but also
<pb facs="5"/>
the forme &amp; fashion of man himself, shall wel perceyue such marueylous differences of countenances, such di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers lineaments of the body, &amp; they all greatly diffring one frō another, so that man maye not, nor ought to attribute it to hap, casualtie, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, but onelye to the great proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and will of almighty GOD, which extends it selfe vnto the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of the heares of mans heade, as our sauiour witnesseth in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelist S. <hi>Mathevve.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no absurde thing to affirme those small and little lineaments ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing on sundrye parts of mans bodye, by God to be appointed, for the great comfort and behoofe of mans nature, to thende he might enioy the perfite vse, and full know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them. And althoughe the weakenesse of mans nature be such, as it cannot redily attaine the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them, yet it is the part and
<pb facs="3"/>
dutie of euery good and well disposed minde to searche oute the excellent workes, and secretes of nature, so farre forth as the almightye power and heauenly gouernor doth permit and suffer him, and therein to note and consider the magnificencie and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>me of the highest workeman: the which very bright shall shine out, and as apparauntlye be seene in the least and smallest creatures, as in the greatest and largiest bodies. The learned <hi>Aristotle</hi> in his booke <hi>De ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malibus,</hi> diligentlye beholding and considering the two small beasts, the Bee and the Ante, doth not a little marueyle at their diuine workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and cunning. But to be briefe▪ there is nothing contained in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent frame and Theatre of this worlde, that requireth not great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, and the same of purpose appointed, for the only vse of nature▪ therefore in times past among▪ the
<pb facs="4"/>
auncient Philosophers, it was an vndoubted principle taught in their schooles, that all things were formed and made vnto some certaine ende and purpose. This mighty wisedom of God, although it doth most boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully shewe and expresse it selfe in euerye worke, yet in mans nature, which farre excelleth all other in dignitie and worthynesse, and in whiche the singular impressions of God are decerned, it doth offer all thinges to consideration and vewe more plainly, more cleare, and more abundaunt. This well vnderstoode and known to the auncient students of wisedome, did preferre mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be considered before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and in the same they asmuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arueised at the great diuersitie and disposition of minds, as at the linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the bodye. And they both carefully and diligently endeuoured to appoynt euery condicion and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,
<pb facs="6"/>
his proper body, and to ech body contrarywise, his proper qualities and condicions, thereby to obtayne and purchase the truth. The aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Poete <hi>Homere</hi> tooke vppon him liuely to describe that worthy <hi>Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sites,</hi> in comparing his maners and condicions to the notes seene on his body. The lyke also did <hi>Dares Phry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> in his long Catalogue of noble Piers, where he cunningly applyed their condicions with their formes and lineamentes seene. This <hi>Dares</hi> wrote that the valiant <hi>Aeneas</hi> was well coloured of body, tending vnto a rednesse, in personage square set, hauing cheerefull and smyling eyes, and these somewhat declining to a blacknesse, and therfore <hi>Dares</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him eloquent, gentle, friendlye of behauiour, wittye and politike in his counsels, pleasant at times, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant in his attempts, and vertuous. The iolly warrier <hi>Antenor,</hi> he descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth
<pb facs="7"/>
to be talle of stature, slender in bodye, in his members nimble and quicke, and therefore iudged to be warie, and craftie in his doinges. But the valiant <hi>Achylles</hi> is described to be bigge and large breasted, fayre spoken, gentle, strong membred, and with great strength of the armes; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a curled heade, a cheerefull or smyling countenance, and the heares of the heade of a browne Chest nut colour, by which notes, he was iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged not only fierce in armes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of great courage, mixed with cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesis &amp; liberalitie. Many moe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of antiquity might herebe alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, were it not that I thinke these sufficient for our turne, to note the antiquitie of comparisons, betweene the bodily formes &amp; lineaments, and betwene their dispositions, courage, and wit: Like to these, many may be read &amp; seene in <hi>Aristotle, Suctonius▪</hi> &amp; other of the Poets, who haue left in
<pb facs="5"/>
wryting to vs, sundry Pamphlets of this Art, extant in manye places, in which, it may euidently appeere, how much it hath bene accounted and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teemed in times past. For the skilfull <hi>Antenor</hi> (by the report of <hi>Homere</hi>) being a man expert in the Arte of Phisiognomie, tooke vppon him to consider, and diligently to vewe, the personages and formes both of the couragious <hi>Vlysses</hi> &amp; <hi>Menelaus,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the one in condicions &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, farre diffring from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelaus,</hi> sayth he, was a person of few wordes, yet graue &amp; wise in counsel, but the iolly <hi>Vlysses</hi> for his prowde shewe and boasting in words, did he pronounce like to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> winter snowes. Seeing this knowledge hath so long time bene obserued and exercised of so excellent and famous men, what shall it let or staye me, not to applye my study and penne thereto, and the rather for that it is lawfull for euery
<pb facs="6"/>
man to decerne, as farre as he can, the qualitie and condicions of the hart: seeing the secret matters lying deepe in the breast, are many times bewrayde by the outward gestures, what singular cōmoditie the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this Arte bringeth with it, may euidently appeare in this, that oftentimes men happening into ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintances and friendshippes, such as they suppose to be most friendly, most sounde, and most faythfull: for the more parte are founde dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers, vnfaithfull, turnecotes moste hurtfull, and most peruerse in their doinges. And without this Arte, a man can not so well detect their fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode and doings, as to find out and know <hi>Thersites</hi> from the mighty <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> or the effeminate <hi>Vlysses</hi> &amp; sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till <hi>Catiline,</hi> from the worthie <hi>Fabius</hi> and <hi>Camillus.</hi> If euer this were in any age a necessary science, then no doubt in this our time, being moste
<pb facs="8"/>
peruerse and wicked, it is most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and necessary. For who doth not see in our dayes, how the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Thersites,</hi> the subtill <hi>Vlysses,</hi> and the most seditious <hi>Catiline,</hi> do rage. For this cause most prudently were appoynted in times paste (as some report) in the Courtes of kings, and noble Princes, certain learned men able to discouer the facts and minds of their subiectes, souldiers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers conuersant about them. The learned <hi>Aristotle</hi> in his booke of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, willeth that comely men be chosen in office and made Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, and not mishapen and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. In another place he admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth men to beware of those per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, which are marked by nature, according to the common opinion of men: an euill fauoured and crabbed countenance, doth euermore yeelde vntoward condicions. For by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of all writers, the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb facs="9"/>
is euermore a bewrayer of the minde, and <hi>Martiall</hi> in his twelfth booke describeth by these signes and notes, his pieuish <hi>Zoilus</hi> and wicked backbyter, in two proper verses.</p>
   <q>Crine niger, ruber ore, breuis pede, lumine laesus, Rem magnam praestas Zoile, si bonus es.</q>
   <p>These englished, are thus much in effect.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>Thy heares are black, thy fete be short,</l>
      <l>purblinde to, vvith bearde readde,</l>
      <l>A good deede do (the Prouerbe sayth)</l>
      <l>and then cut of thy headde.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>The Greeke Poet <hi>Agadius,</hi> des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed also a certaine lymping or halting person in this sort, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>.</p>
   <p>Which may thus be translated.</p>
   <lg>
      <l>VVhy doste thou limpe and halt,</l>
      <l>thy minde is lame I see,</l>
      <l>These outvvard signes are tokens plain</l>
      <l>of secrete yll in thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>If <hi>Pompeius</hi> had vsed this dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in beholding and considering the countenance, hee woulde not so lightly haue credited, and bene sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by <hi>Achylles</hi> and <hi>Septimus,</hi> nor the valiant <hi>Caaesar</hi> had happened into the hands of <hi>Brutus</hi> and subtill <hi>Cas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius,</hi> by whome they and their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany were lamentably murthered, Further, this Art procureth no smal commoditie and profite to Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maysters, in searching out &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the aptnesse and pregnancie of their scholers vnto learning. For if they deale like honest and faythfull tutors, they ought to receyue none into their schoole to be instructed in learning and Arts, contrary to their capacitie, but rather followe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Apollonius Alabandensis,</hi> that deuine and rare Schoolemay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, of whom <hi>Cicero</hi> writeth in his booke <hi>De Oratore.</hi> This man (sayth he) although he customablye reade
<pb facs="8"/>
and taught schollers for a stipende and gayne, yet would he suffer none vnder him, to lose their tyme, if hee perceyued their wittes vnapt to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Oratorye: but rather wylled them to leaue of and cease that stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and to follow that skill and Arte that he knew and saw them inclyned vnto. Which example if our schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maysters and tutors would indeuor to practyse and followe, we shoulde then enioy and haue many more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent scholers, in all laudable stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies &amp; Artes, than at these daies are knowne to be. Here I thinke it good tyme to ende, not meaning to wade or proceede any further in the infinit prayses of so singular an Art, therby to hinder your honors graue &amp; seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous studies, with this my rud &amp; sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple worke, the which although it be not worthye to craue the protection of so Noble a personage, yet am I (the author thereof) bolde to intrude
<pb facs="9"/>
and thrust it vppon your Grace, to thintent that through your Graces fauorable protection, it may possesse a free passage, <hi>Zoilus</hi> be put to si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and I encouraged to shewe my simple skil and small iudgement hereafter in matters more pleasant and delectable. God preserue your Grace, and increase your meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and thoughtes, in all godlynesse and vertue, and sende you long helth, and the yeares of the mightye <hi>Nestor.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours most humble,
Thomas Hill.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>