<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader, and diligent traueyler, in the Arte of Phisiognomie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1571</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104092_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68187</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13482</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104092</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader, and diligent traueyler, in the Arte of Phisiognomie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The contemplation of mankinde : contayning a singuler discourse after the art of phisiognomie, on all the members and partes of man, as from the heade to the foote, in a more ample maner than hytherto hath beene published of any. In the place next after the chapter of the forehead, hath the phisiognomer added a proper treatise of the signification of sundrie lines seene in most mens foreheads: which in sundrie disputations with a skilfull Iew, he at the last obtayned. ... In the ende is a little treatise added of the signification of moles ... written by a worthie Grecian named Melampus. All which, englished by Thomas Hyll. 1571</title>
                 <author>Hill, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Seres, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1571</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 208, 109-132, 233-236, that is 244 leaves, illustrations (woodcuts), portraits, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>
      <hi>The Preface to the Reader,</hi> and diligent traueyler, in the Arte of Phisiognomie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeyng it is true (gentle Reader) that the first and principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest poynt of wisedome is to know God, the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to knowe our sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and the thirde to knowe our duties towardes our neighbors: it must néedes then be graunted and confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, that those meanes which leade vs to the nearest vnderstanding and perceyuing of them, are both good, profitable, and necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: wherefore great folly ruleth these men, who by their slender and faint arguments, woulde condemne and banish Philosophie. The which after the minde of S. Paule, doth force vs to the vnderstanding and knowledge of the seconde, and also by the agréement and consent of all the learned, doth throughly instruct vs in the last. The people of the world, lifting vp their mindes to the Elementes, beholding the motions, alterations, chaunges, the seuerall courses of the lightes, and Planets, with theyr infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb facs="10"/>
obseruations: looking downe againe vpon the earth, and there in séeing the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe, the situation, and magnificence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with the wonderfull working of nature, did acknowledge a God, the maker of them, and therein did confesse his power and om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie. The Philosopher <hi>Ariopagita,</hi> being without the swift hearing of thinges, done in Iewrie, when he sawe the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnnaturall darcknesse that sodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ranne ouer the face of the earth, durst af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the worlde to drawe to an ende, or else the maker and framer of it, to suffer violence. In <hi>Athens</hi> (the mother and nurse of learning) where the Philosophers had their long resting place, by learning ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged a greater God, then by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature they could attaine vnto: when by the witnesse of S. Paule, they erected an aultar (<hi>ignoto deo</hi>) to the vnknowne God. I haue read of a prowde king of Englande, whome the water (notwithstanding hys fierce, and thundering commaundement) woulde not obey, but still rose higher and higher, to the wetting of his féete, with shame ynough confessed a god, to whom the waters were obedient. By Philosophie we
<pb facs="11"/>
learne to know our selues, the diuersitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene Mankinde and other Creatures: the excellencie of the one ouer the other, in some pointes, and the excellencie of the other in other poyntes. Reason hath made man, to differ from the brutishe generation, and therefore more excellent, but by his disabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and weake ruling of himselfe, the other is his superiour. The beast doth all thinges, by the instinct and prouocation of nature: Man without reason, not able to bridle hys sensualitie, degenerates from that he ought to bée, and becommeth more monstruous with sinne, sensuality, lust, and all other wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vices, than any other monster in forme and shape. By Philosophie we learne, what is iust, honest, comely, profitable, decent, vertuous, and Godly: and againe what is dishonest, vnseemoly, vicious, and to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred. To make a perticuler prayse of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophie, the treatie woulde not be so long &amp; tedious, as the aduenture great, I should hasard a greater enterprise, than any here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore durst take in hande: but generally whatsoeuer procéedeth from reason, it is Philosophie. If reason procéedeth from a naturall disposition or inclination, if it come
<pb facs="11"/>
by experience, or forced by learned meanes, it is Philosophie. Peraduenture some there be (more curious a great deale, than theyr holye liuing requireth) that doe impugne some part of Philosophie, as a thing or Art not necessarie or méete to be knowne and studied. These men I suppose eyther neuer knewe, or else haue forgotten what maketh a man. Reason telleth, if a whole bodie or substaunce lacketh a part, it is become lame and vnperfite. If a man wanteth a member or ioynt, it cannot be said, there is the whole and perfite forme of a man: no more can Philosophie bée perfite, if anye one part bée plucked away. The Arte of diuination by the Starres, the face and hande, is a percell of Philosophie, and grounded vpon long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and reason: and therefore not so wicked and detestable as some men do take and repute these. Although it be an Arte wherewith many be deceyued (through the gréedie desire of gaine) yet it is no good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequent to say, that the Arte therefore is fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous &amp; naught. Diuinitie, being the words of God, perfit and most pure, where lurketh no deceyte nor leasing, suffereth abuse: for the deuill coulde alledge it agaynst Christ:
<pb facs="12"/>
and Antichrist therewith persecuteth hys members: bicause some men with wine be druncken, is wine therefore naught? Put a knife into a mad mans hande, he knoweth not how to vse it: but a wise, discreate, and sober man, will neuer hurt himselfe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly with it. Though some men do ghesse at randon, as touching the proper conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and qualities of persons, yet the Arte laudable and certaine is not to bée blamed: neyther is it to be condemned, though some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes he pronounceth cleane agaynst the persons maners, and conuersation. Tullie witnesseth (4. <hi>Tusculanarum</hi>) about the ende, of a certaine Phisiognomer named <hi>Zopirus,</hi> which tooke vpon him to beholde, and iudge the natures and dispositions of many persons, by the formes of their faces, and lineaments of the bodie: among which he was requested to beholde the forme of the learned <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and fayling in hys iudgement, for that he onely pronounced by the lineaments of the bodie, what by nature he was inclined vnto, and not what by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and vertue he was become, was of many laughed to scorne: although the wise <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> well allowed and confirmed
<pb facs="12"/>
his iudgement, saying by nature he was the lyke, that the Phisiognomer had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced of him. Therfore I admonish eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, that will rightlye pronounce and iudge in this Art, that they first consider and vew all the partes of man, and not to iudge rashly by any one member alone: so shall they be sure not to be deceyued, I meane to vnderstand and know the truth of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall disposition, and yet may they faile of the mans conditions, which <hi>Socrates</hi> well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in himselfe. For when he on a tyme (as vttereth <hi>Aristotle</hi>) sent two of his scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, with his table or Image liuely drawne and counterfeyted by a cunning workman, to that famous Phisiognomer <hi>Phylemon:</hi> who after he had diligentlye viewed, and considered one member with another, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced <hi>Socrates</hi> to be a leacherous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, subtill, a deceyuer, couetous, and giuen to wickednesse. This iudgement so much mooued the schollers, that they bitterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked the Phisiognomer. And in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, opening this iudgement to <hi>Socrates,</hi> confessed that <hi>Phylemon</hi> had truely repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of him in all poyntes, and swarued not one iotte from a truth after nature: but the
<pb facs="13"/>
studie of Philosophie, and honestie, had so brideled his desires and wicked nature, that he became a new man. By this a man may conclude, that our will to be subicct vnder the gouernement of reason and grace: and that through these we may bridle nature in vs, turning the prouocations of them vnto goodnesse. For the Chollerick or yrefull man may eyther by grace represse his furie and lust, or else alter the same in correcting of vices. The malicious man also may either by grace aswage his lust, or else turne the same agaynst the euill: and so lyke may be done, in all other naturall inclinations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting in vs. Experience teacheth how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny giuen to sundrie kind of vices, after they by Gods grace begin to haue a swéete taste of Gods worde, doe shake of their woonted nature, and become altered and chaunged fellowes. <hi>Saule</hi> by Gods spirite, of a perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor, became a Martyr, of a bloud sucker, an innocent and méeke Lambe. I might here recyte a number of Godly examples, it I wist these were not ynough, to prooue mine intent. It is not to be decyded, what Gods holy spirite can doe. It worketh my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, it worketh wonders contrarse to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="13"/>
it turneth olde <hi>Adam</hi> (in vs) into new <hi>Adam,</hi> contrary to all sence and vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of man: and then no marueyle, though the Phisiognomer doe faile, where nature fayleth. Much more (gentle Reader) I might say, but that I suppose this is sufficient, to shew vnto thée, the right vse of Phisiogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. I will leaue the whole commendation of the Arte, vnto thine owne iudgement, and experience. If by practise thou shalt find anye certaintie in it, then reiect it not as vaine and friuolous, but if thou canst not attaine vnto the certaine knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: yet let not thine yll fortune, condemne the iudgementes and experiences of a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber well learned and practised in this Arte: neyther thinke yll of me, who wisheth vnto thée verie well, and haue taken these paynes altogither for thy sake. Somewhat I haue séene by experience, all that thou hast here, gathered oute of the best wryters: muche more I haue reade, and the best of that, I also giue thée. So many as shall receyue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fruit or commoditie by me, let them giue thankes vnto the worshipfull and high lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man, Mayster Dée, by whose helpe and ayde at the beginning, I receyued such mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents
<pb facs="14"/>
and principles, as gaue me great light vnto this knowledge, and vnto whome also thou art greatly bound: for that he wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth well vnto his Countrie men, and hath taken great paynes to do his Countrie good. Thus leauing (gentle reader) to trouble you any longer: I commit you to God, wishing onely your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, in the furthering of thys my simple worke.</p>
   <closer>Et feliciter vale.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>