<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Wor∣shipfull, Sir Iohn Harper, Knight, all true prosperity.</title>
           <author>Brinsley, I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104368_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08375</idno>
           <idno type="STC">187.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104368</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Wor∣shipfull, Sir Iohn Harper, Knight, all true prosperity.</title>
                 <author>Brinsley, I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Esops eables [sic] translated grammatically, and also in propriety of our English phrase; and, euery way, in such sort as may bee most profitable for the grammar-schoole</title>
                 <author>Aesop</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Lownes, Humphrey 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Man, Jonas (Jonah)</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>5, 18, 18-35 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Classical authors</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, Sir <hi>Iohn Harper,</hi> Knight, all true prosperity.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worshipfull, I may not bee forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the loue which you haue shewed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of my indeuours, for the Grammar-schoole. Accept ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this small pledge of my thankefull acknowledgement. Though it be little in valew and in the esteem of the most, yet the b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nefit of it will (I trust) help to make amends, and further the perfecting of my desires. By the right vse heereof, may the little ones from their first yeares get much profitable vnderstanding &amp;
<pb facs="3"/>
wisdome, yea such, as whereof they may haue worthie vse, all their dayes, in what place soe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they shall be imployed; And may moreouer haue euery point &amp; part of the learning in it, so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in their memories as they shall neuer forget them, but haue them, as it were liuely before their faces: That so they may learne to embrace the vertues therein taught and to flee the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to foresee dangers and how to auoid them, to behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues wisely and discreetly in the whole course of their life. As for example, to giue a taste hereof; in the first fable of the cock estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a barley corne aboue a precious stone, to see the foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of men, especially of children preferring play before learning, a little pleasure and folly, before the most exellent and diuine wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:
<pb facs="3"/>
to teach them to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe after and to embrace lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and wisedome, euen from their tender yeares, and to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed of misspending their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious time in play and idle vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. So in the second fable of the wolfe and the lambe, to teach them to take heede all their life long how they haue to deale with or any way prouoke cruell men, that are too hard for them: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they, when they list, can take any occasion to prey vpon them, or to doe them a mischiefe, and that this is matter enough, If they bee not able to resist them. Thus likewise in the third fable of the mouse and the frog, being at war together, about the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the marish ground, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the kite snatch them both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and deuoure them, to teach children in all their time to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware
<pb facs="4"/>
of discord and dissension with others, especially contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for superiority &amp; preferment: Because such vsually as will goe to wa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>re, as it were, for euery tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle, make themselues a prey to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, especially to the common aduersary. And but onely to name the fourth, In the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of the dogge swimming o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the riuer, which through o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer much greediness, chopping at the shadowe of the flesh which he sawe in the water, lost the flesh it selfe which hee carried in his chops, to teach children alwaies to take heed of too much gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse, and euer to keep a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in their desi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es, lest that by ouer much earnestnesse in seeking more than is fit<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, they come to lose all &amp; to repent when it is too late. Now beside this sound wisedome, and besides all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="4"/>
helps concerning the more certaine, easie, and speedy means of attaining the Latine tongue (as happy experience hath taught very many, who haue giuen plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull testimony hereunto; for construing, pa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sing, making La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, getting phrase and the like, by such translations) they may learne hereby chiefly to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of a fable, or of any like nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or history in good sort &amp; fit wordes, which is no small commendation to any who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer. For the manner of effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hereof, I haue set it downe shortly in the Epistle to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and more fully in my <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar-schoole.</hi> And thus (that you may see my constant desire in creeping forwarde by little and little, for perfo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ming my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, in accomplishing my ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice for the perpetuall benefit of
<pb facs="5"/>
schools &amp; of all posterity, by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning still of all the learned to help the vnlearned, &amp; by propounding to all what I haue found by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that they may find the like and be partakers of al my trauels) haue I presumed vpon your loue to present this little translation vnto you. Which you accepting accordingly I shal be more incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to striue forward for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the whole, and to spend my last thoughts for the commō good. And thus with all thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acknowledgement vnto your self with your worthy Lady and all yours I humbly take my leaue, and rest</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships in the Lord, I. Brinsley.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>