<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Honourable and vertuous Lady, the Lady Sara Ha∣stings, Nicholas Breton wisheth all happinesse in this world, and eternall ioyes hereafter.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1602</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104703_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16794</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3699</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104703</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Honourable and vertuous Lady, the Lady Sara Ha∣stings, Nicholas Breton wisheth all happinesse in this world, and eternall ioyes hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The soules harmony. Written by Nicholas Breton</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bearkes (Barkes, Berke, Birks, Byrke), Randall</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1602</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Honourable and vertuous Lady, the Lady <hi>Sara Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stings,</hi> Nicholas Breton wisheth all happinesse in this world, and eternall ioyes hereafter.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, your zealous loue to diuine studies, hath made the Muses of that Nature, to present your fauour, with the best fruites of their delights, which in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of their spirituall Contemplations, haue brought sorth these comfortable Meditations: which bound vp in this little volume, they haue presumed with my seruice, to present to your good Ladyship, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching the same, with that good fauour to accept them, that may vnder heauen be the greatest grace, that they desire vnto them. It is intituled, <hi>The</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>Harmony of the Soule,</hi> who in the gracious thoughts of Gods blessing, and humble talke with his mercy, thinkes her selfe halfe in heauen ere shee come there: where, after that you haue passed a happy pilgrimage on this earth, God send you the eternall felicitie of the faithfull.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladyships in all humblenesse, Nicholas Breton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>