<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all gentle Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104551_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07648</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1804</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104551</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all gentle Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The honour of chiualrie : Set downe in the most famous historie of the magnanimious and heroike Prince Don Bellianis: sonne vnto the Emperour Don Bellaneo of Greece. Wherein are described, the straunge and dangerous aduentures that him befell. With his loue towards the Princesse Florisbella: daughter vnto the Souldan of Babylon. Englished out of Italian, by L.A</title>
                 <author>Fernández, Jerónimo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 286 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To all gentle Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as a yong child newly, (as I may say) crept frō his cradle, indeuouring to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noūce with perfection, his natural lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage for his future vse, is first instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to spell, before he be put to reading, &amp; to read, ere hee expound: So I, whose rough skill, and harsh vnfiled wit, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the practisse of continuing time, being disfurnis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t of Natures helpes, and Artes pollisht disciplines, must seeme to goe, before I may presume to flie, trusting to my owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fledged winges, leaste with rash asspiring <hi>Icarus,</hi> I ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme my helpes in the recordlesse Caue of euerlasting dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace. I speake this (most courteous and gentle Readers) for that I had some fewe monethes paste, onely for my pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate recreation, in idle houres, imitated in this Historie, the inuention of a forraine wit, whose conceit beeing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by diuers Gentles, of no meane desert, haue by their importunate intreaties, forced me (altogether vnwilling) to make known the rude excercise of my vacant leasure, which at length to satisfie their requestes (not my desires) I did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue to doe, onely thereby to make you sport, in the tedious passage of these winter nightes, if other pastimes doe not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbe it. For on this sole hope it onely leanes, that beeing the first sprigge of a young plant, set in a barren ground, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uergrowne with weeds, so it wil obtaine your general gentle
<pb facs="4"/>
acceptance, with a fauourable pardon for this rash presume. Defending it with the shield of your fauours, which will be a sufficient tower, wel armed against al scandalizing tongus, that but make an ecchoing noyse, with their ayrie wordes, to harme none saue themselues, by the rebounding backe of their reprochfull tauntes, euen on their barking selues. But walled with hope, that the gentlenesse of your vertues, will nothing derogate from your names, by kindly accepting my good-will, I end: praying, that all present and ensuing happinesse, and content, may euery way answere your owne wishes: requesting, that where you dislyke, there you would mildely amend, and not vtterly condemne.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>