<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the gentle Reader.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104696_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16804</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3705</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104696</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the gentle Reader.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvil of vvit, vvits vvill, or vvils wit, chuse you whether : Containing fiue discourses, the effects whereof follow. Read and iudge. Compiled by Nicholas Breton, Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 <publisher>Creede, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wright, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 33, 4+ 66-76, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the gentle Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> New Booke saies one, true, it came forth but tother day, good stuffe saies an other. Read, then iudge. I confesseit may seeme to a number, a bolde attempt, to set out a forme of wit, considering the witty discourses, of such fine wits as haue deserued such cōmēdation, as may driue this meane peece of woorke of mine into vtter disgrace, were it not that perfect courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie dooth beare with imperfect knowledge, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding more the good minde in the writer, then the matter written, and therefore the best will giue good woords, whatsoeuer they think, to incourage a forward will to doo better, when indeede it were a fantasticall heade that coulde doo worse. VVell when VVit is a wool-gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and VVill wandring, the worlde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out guide, what a case that manne is in, that is in such a taking I referre you to madde folkes, of whome you maye see examples sufficient, and so I beeing in a certaine melancholye moode, past all Gods forbod, tooke my Pen and Inke and paper, and somewhat I would goe doo, whatsoeuer it were, to put out one conceit, and bring in an other, at last, and at first, of a suddaine, vnwares, and at aduentures, by Gods
<pb facs="4"/>
good helpe, and good fortune, the litle wit that I had, meeting with good Will, I knew not how, fell to worke, (at first) I know not what, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing written a while, I made somewhat of it, which though litle to any great purpose, yet, if it please the readers, I am contented, &amp; if any man thinke it well done, then Wit shall thinke Will a good boy, and Will shall thinke he tooke Wit in a good vaine, and Will and Wit shall haue the more heart heereafter, to fall to further woorke, but if I haue bin more wilfull then wise, to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>tes, with a witlesse peece of worke, pardon me for this once, ye shall see I wil please you better heereafter, in the meane time desiring your courtesies to commend what you thinke worthie, and not to disdain without desert, I rest, wishing your content in what you wish well, as I pray you wish me as I doo you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your freend
Nicholas. Breton Gentleman.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>