<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, THOMAS Lord Ellesmere, Lord Chauncellor of ENGLAND.</title>
           <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104220_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03653</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13783</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104220</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, THOMAS Lord Ellesmere, Lord Chauncellor of ENGLAND.</title>
                 <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Speculum topographicum: or The topographicall glasse : Containing the vse of the topographicall glasse. Theodelitus. Plaine table, and circumferentor. With many rules of geometry, astronomy, topography perspectiue, and hydrography. Newly set forth by Arthur Hopton Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Hopton, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 203, 9 pages, 2 folded leaves of plates, illustrations, maps, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, THOMAS Lord Ellesmere, Lord Chauncellor of ENGLAND.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Priuiledge (Right Honorable) is common, and the custome commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, to dedicate bookes to Noble persons, to the end that what is effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by labour and study, may by their greatnesse be protected from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledictions and enuie; and therefore we select one, whose eminent vertues (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from Riuals) is of all admired, by all obserued, and with all beloued, and there the choicest wits shelter their chiefest workes: the habit of which wonderfull glories I finde most predominating in your Honour, which are powerful inducements to animate this presumption in cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing patronage for this worke: The Booke containes no nice or new controuersies, but matter of Art, verified with demonstrations <hi>Geometricall,</hi> as still ready to confirme the truth to the ignorant, or confute the malice of the arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, which though it be not fashioned out with beautifull lineaments, or painted ouer with golden phrases: yet is there dainties sufficient to delight the eye, and recreate the mind, choice of varieties to beguile the time with gaine of knowledge, and easie methods with facill documents to abiure the barbarous tyrant to vnderstanding. Things of greatest profit, require lest praise; the white silver is wrought in the blacke pitch; painting better beseemes rotten wals then pretious stones: the <hi>Mathematikes</hi> vse no conference with the sence-rauishing <hi>Rhetorique,</hi> their end is to instruct, not perswade; therefore superfluous eloquence besto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed
<pb facs="3"/>vpon a matter of sufficient excellence, is rather a testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a trifling wit, then a token of true wisedome.</p>
   <p>A chiefe cause wherefore I now proue troublesome, is, my loue to your Lordship, whom I euer honored, and the aduancement of the Art that I alwayes liked. By the one I shew my duty to a name emphasizing honor, and by the other my affection to an Art expressing wonders. <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> would be painted by none but <hi>Apelles,</hi> nor haue his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture cast in brasse by any but <hi>Lisippus. Appelles</hi> asked coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of none but <hi>Zeuxis,</hi> and <hi>Lisippus</hi> must onely censure <hi>Prisius:</hi> neither do I in this appeale to any but your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, which, as your selfe are honorable, so are your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings equitable, so that all <hi>England</hi> may boast of your great iustice, and all Europe reioyce of your good consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: amongst which, my selfe with the best will euer beare testimony; the great sonne of the <hi>Macedonian</hi> king honored <hi>Craterus,</hi> but most affected <hi>Hephestion,</hi> and I reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence all good wits, but here only appeale to your Honors wisdome, that as it is exceeding the grauest, so is it more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then the greatest; and therefore by the inferiors fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be admired then commended. But because your co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations cannot but be defessed and made weary, as well in priuate contemplating of his Maiesties serious affaires, as in publique negotiating for the good of the Comon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, I thinke it best to cease trouble, lest I offend your noble meditations, being leuelled at more weighty entend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: not doubting but the practizers in these Arts will yeeld your Honor perpetuall thankes, that for their good haue brought this <hi>Glasse</hi> to light, where they may see choise of delights to satisfie their aspiring wits.</p>
   <p>Thus committing this Booke to your Honorable patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, your Honor to the Almighties protection, and my selfe to your Honors command, I end, resting</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors in all humble duty, <hi>ARTHVR HOPTON.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>