<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Salutem in Christo Guliel∣mus Clowes.</title>
           <author>Clowes, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104460_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03456</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1358</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104460</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Salutem in Christo Guliel∣mus Clowes.</title>
                 <author>Clowes, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An antidotarie chyrurgicall : containing great varietie and choice of all sorts of medicines that commonly fal into the chyrurgions vse: partlie taken out of authors, olde and new, printed or written: partlie obtained by free gifte of sundrie worthie men of this profession within this land. By Iohn Banester master of chirurgerie</title>
                 <author>Banister, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 5, 1, 4, 359, 17 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_author">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>Salutem in Christo Guliel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Clowes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Read that <hi>Seneca</hi> the wise Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher demandeth, <hi>What man is he that would wish to liue in this transitorie worlde, so full of mischiefes, calamities and mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, without faithfull familiaritie and vnfeined friendship?</hi> It may be answered in a word, None, but the proud person, and the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and enuious man, whose words and deedes discouer the euill that is hatched in his heart. So that no firme friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship nor stedfast amitie can once so much as appeare in his life and conuersation: but frameth himselfe with euerie mocking Parasite to throw out the venime and poyson of his heart, to the discrediting of those that anie thing excell him, either in knowledge or practise. Such a vile person was one <hi>Antiphilos</hi> said to be, who professed great friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to <hi>Apelles,</hi> seeming both to reuerence him for his skill, and honour him for his Art: yet when he did see that he grew in fauor with all, so that his fame spred to the Court of <hi>Alexander,</hi> (who hearing of his skill in Painting, gaue foorth a commandement, that none should paint his Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture but onelie <hi>Apelles</hi>) this wicked <hi>Antiphilos</hi> (the verie shape of shame, and fellow to all dissemblers &amp; flatterers) with forged &amp; false accusations practised priuely to bring <hi>Apelles</hi> into displeasure and disgrace with King <hi>Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus,</hi> (who also deerelie loued <hi>Apelles,</hi> and had him in great estimation). Yet he could not bring to passe his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed practise: for the King through his deepe wisedome examined the thing by the rule of reason, and soone found out the secret purpose and vnhonest attempt of that peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Pick-thanke, which sought by vniust meanes to haue <hi>Apelles</hi> banished, and so to liue as a man defamed: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="2" facs="8"/>
vpon due consideration had of the innocencie of <hi>Apel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> cause, the King neither satisfied the leaud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>xpectation of <hi>Antiphilos,</hi> nor winked at his iniurious and wrongfull accusations, but perceiuing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ilthie liqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r that came forth of that stinking vessel, presently he tamed his tongue with the bridle of bondage, and beate downe his malicious proud heart with the sharpe scourge of continuall slauerie, condemning him iustlie, and command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ng him straightlie to serue as a bondslaue to <hi>Apelles</hi> all the daies of his life<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> In like manner, Master <hi>Banester</hi> my dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e and louing friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> it is not vnknowen vnto manie good men, how vnder the colour of faithful friendship<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> you haue been as it were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed about, and deepelie bitten with such like Antipholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, whom you haue nouseled in your bosome: whose ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour is such, that no good &amp; wholsome lawes can bridle or tame their piercing tongues. And one chief cause of their great impatience is for publishing of such like workes as is this your Antidotarie, saying forsooth, that onely their meere practise is sufficient without so manie bookes: as if amongst blind-men he that hath but one eie might bee a King. But contrariwise, to the good liking of the learned, and men of iudgement, you haue performed and publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>shed this your Antidotarie to your great fame and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is most certaine that the thing of it selfe deserueth praise: for they that read it with consideration shal finde in it varitie, breuitie, sound iudgement and varietie, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full fraught and s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uft with manie singular, good and approoued practises, so that you iustlie merit praise of al true and faithfull professors of this noble Arte of Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, yet you know full well, it will be hard for you to cast off the burthen and yoke of leawd reproaches. For no work can be so eloquentlie handled, but some <hi>Aristrachus</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (whose filthie stomackes, beeing inflamed with cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar) will improue the same: either for the slendernesse of the argument, impropernesse of the phrase, heauie and obscure reasons, false ortographie, faultes escaped, incke-horne
<pb n="3" facs="8"/>
tearmes, or some imperfection for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in tongues: yet you for your parte haue preuented such vaine pratlings, and I haue good hope that this your Antidotarie will yeelde a sufficient medicine to cure that olde vlcered maladie, which hath so farre infected their mouthes, and tainted their tongues: insomuch, that if now they finde faults, you and all may thinke, that either it is the vaine humours of certaine scoffing spirites, or els too much frequenting the hot-house, hath sweat out all their wittes. <hi>Themistocles</hi> a renowmed Captaine of the <hi>Greekes,</hi> beeing vpon a time verie pensiue and heauie, there came vnto him a verie familiar friend of his, and in secret manner demaunded of him, what might bee the cause that he was at that time so sorrowfull and sad? If you will needes know (said he) the cause of this my present sadnesse, it is, for that manie yeeres being past since I was borne, I perceiue not that I haue as yet done anie good thing worthie of memorie for the benefite of my Countrey and Common weale, beeing (by this reason) heereunto perswaded, that I know no man in all <hi>Athens</hi> that hateth or beareth me enuie. Now sith such a famous and most valiant Captaine supposed it better to be enuied and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the malicious, than to liue in idlenesse of life, and basenesse of minde, without dooing of some good thing, (woorthie of memorie) for the profite and benefite of his Countrey and Common wealth wherein hee liued: then let none of our proclaimers of infamie, (which are desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of truth and godli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>esse) once dismaie you with their iniurious vexations, which are neither pleasant in the hearing, nor yet profitable in the answering: for it is not the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r boorish or caluish bleatings, neither yet their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent facings vpon their rotten and confused Pamphlets, that so pleasantlie they sporte themselues withall, and which now shortlie shall come foorth like monsters with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out perfect shape, (at least if they proceede according to their boasting) can hurt any: for they are lanternes
<pb n="4" facs="9"/>
void of light, moued with malice and defame: and doo but decke their crowe with other birdes feathers. Although they counterfeit what they can, their long eares will discouer them to come of <hi>Midas</hi> progenie. And when their time ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth they will trie the dignitie of their wits therein: for they pretend we shal be shortl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e vtterlie drowned in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen whirlepoole. But let such idiots resemble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues: it skilleth not, sith manie of our ancients haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted of such slanderers furious rages. And therefore they shall walke with <hi>Antiphilos,</hi> as bondslaues all the daies of their life. And heere I protest my selfe an open enemie to all such your wicked aduersaries whatsoeuer: and I must confesse that I am bound manie waies so to doo, not onelie in respect of our olde acquaintance, or for that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d God to prosper &amp; blesse our labour, (being oftent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mes called to diuers great and dangerous cures: but chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>felie, for that we both do serue vnder the right Honorable Earle of <hi>Warwicke</hi> our verie good Lord &amp; Master, whom God long preserue in health to his good will &amp; pleasure. These causes aforesaid doo binde me in faithfull and vnfeined friendship vnto the vttermost of my power: the which I will performe, if it so please the Lord: who prosper al your lawfull proceedings in this our Arte of Chyrurgerie. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours:</hi>
         <hi>WILLIAM CLOVVES.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>