<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO AL FAITHFVL CHRISTIANS, &amp; true harted subiects that liue vnder the peace∣able and flourishing regiment of Q. ELIZABETH, by the grace of God Q. of England, France, &amp; Ireland: Grace mercy and peace in our Lord God everlasting.</title>
           <author>H., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104142_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03475</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13597</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104142</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO AL FAITHFVL CHRISTIANS, &amp; true harted subiects that liue vnder the peace∣able and flourishing regiment of Q. ELIZABETH, by the grace of God Q. of England, France, &amp; Ireland: Grace mercy and peace in our Lord God everlasting.</title>
                 <author>H., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Panēguris D. Elizabethæ, Dei gratiâ Angliæ, Franciæ, &amp; Hiberniæ Reginæ : A sermon preached at Pauls in London the 17. of November ann. Dom. 1599. the one and fortieth yeare of her Maiesties raigne, and augmented in those places wherein, for the shortnes of the time, it could not there be then delivered. VVherevnto is adioyned an apologeticall discourse, whereby all such sclanderous accusations are fully and faithfully confuted, wherewith the honour of this realme hath beene vncharitably traduced by some of our adversaries in forraine nations, and at home, for observing the 17. of November yeerely in the forme of an holy-day, and for the ioifull exercises, and courtly triumphes on that day in the honour of her Maiestie exhibited. By Thomas Holland, Doctor of Divinity, &amp; her Highnes professor thereof in her Vniversity of Oxford</title>
                 <author>Holland, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Barnes, Joseph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Broome (Brome), Joan</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>164 pages, 1 leaf of folded plates, coat of arms, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO AL FAITHFVL CHRISTIANS, &amp; true harted subiects that liue vnder the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> and flourishing regiment of Q. <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> by the grace of God Q. of England, France, &amp; Ireland: Grace mercy and peace in our Lord God everlasting.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE principal contents of this smal booke (loving friends and deere Country-men) compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hēdeth summarily, in one ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, a perspicuous narration of the holy, honorable, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious, peregrination, of the Queene of the South,<note place="margin">Mat: 12: 42<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 1: King: 10: 2. Chro: 9: Luke: 11:</note> who came from the vttermost parts of the earth, to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem to heare the wisedome of King Salomon. This history in the old Testament, is mentioned at large, by the sacred register thereof, inspired by the holy Ghost: and this history is briefly and perspicuouslie alleadged, by our Saviour Christ,<note place="margin">Ierusalē &amp;c How often wold I haue gathered thy childrē togither, as the hen ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth her chickēs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her wings, and yee woulde not. Mat. 24.37.</note> in the new Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by the way of comparison, and inferred most pertinently to that ende, where-vnto it was by him applied; namely, to convince the stiffe-necked Iewes of impious incredulity, and barbarous impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: who at that time, to their owne confusion, &amp; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal destructiō, refused the light of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ospel offered by our Saviors ministery vnto thē; preferring obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately darknesse before the sunne-shine of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, errour before trueth, foolishnesse before
<pb facs="4"/> wisedome, death before life.</p>
   <p>This peregrination of the Queene of the South in the words before I tearmed <hi>Holy, Honourable, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious. Holy,</hi> in consideration of the sacred mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and divine treasures, mystically wrapped vp in the letter of this History, recapitulated out of the old Testament by our Saviour in the New <hi>Honourable,</hi> in regard of the circumstance of the action, and the condition of those persons who are in my text men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned &amp; described. <hi>Laborious</hi> in regard of the longe, toilesome, daungerous, and chargeable iourney that this wise and holy Queene vndertaketh, and by Gods assistaunce and grace in al honour, discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, magnifical bounty, princely modesty, &amp; industry performeth.</p>
   <p>This Text, how it fitted the time, place, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; the mutual resemblance, by the way of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison, in the two persons, then spoken of in the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, evidently declared: the annual celebrities of the 17. of November, being in these times yearely the day wherin this whole Realme giueth thanks to God, by publike service, and sheweth great signes of ioy, in each parish, and general assemblies, for the happy regiment of our Q. Elizabeth, plainely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrateth.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Menander Plutarch <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>, &amp;c As God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ath fixed in heauē the Sunne and the Moone, excellent resemblan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of his glory so in a citty God hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the Prince to shine as a patterne &amp; a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>irror of his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesty.</note>The person in the Text by our Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iour commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded is a woman; by birth, vocatiō, descent a Queene, by consequente thereof, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, a liuing Image of God: And (as I haue by good reasō proved in the sermon) a Mayden Queene. The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb facs="4"/> for whom we doe the 17. of November accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rule of the B Apostle make supplication, praiers, intercessions, &amp; giuing of thankes is by sexe <hi>a woman</hi> by birth, auncient descent, vocation, title, right of inheritance, and regal investure <hi>a Queene;</hi> by honour, integrity of life, grace given by God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from aboue, <hi>a Mayden Queene.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The Queene of the South a woman of great wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, a woman endued with rare learning. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration and experience of the rare wisdome &amp; skil of tongues giuen by God to the Queene of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, hath not bin inclosed within the walles of her Courte, neither confined within the limits of her kingdome only, but hath beene sounded in forraine nations, to her everlasting honour, &amp; great admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō, not by the reference of her owne people chiefly, but by the testimony of many wise &amp; graue Embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadors sent from mighty Princes and great states to congratulate her Maiesty: with whom she hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred in several languages,<note place="margin">Learning is in poore mē, riches: in nobility, it shineth as gold: in Princes, like an o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent pearle and gliste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raud Mat. 12 42. 1 King 10 2 Chron. 9. Luke. 11.</note> answering them readily in those tongues, which they haue chosē of purpose to deliver their embassadge in.</p>
   <p>The Queene of the South enchronicled in the holy writte of the olde Testament, and honoured by the testimony of our Saviour in the New, for vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking so great and worthy a iourney, as is specified in the place marginally cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>: a iourney laborious, toilesome, perilous, chargeable, in regarde of the paines, place, persō, &amp;c. yet honourable in cause &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: a iourney laborious, in regard of the greate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
<pb facs="5"/> betweene Meroe &amp; Ierusalem,<note place="margin">Pomp. Mel. Africa incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, arena sterili ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducta, ob si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum coeli de serta, saepe multo ac mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>fico a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimaliū ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nere infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sta, &amp;c. Africa ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentibus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo faecūda est, vt mali meritò illi pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ssimum palma de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Solin. cap: 40. Serpentum largo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur fecū da veneno Africa. Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Strabo. lib. 2. Herod. 4. Diodor. l. 4. Virg. Egl: 1. Sitientes i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimus Afros Galust. bell: lug. desc. Afric.</note> the substance whereof is discoursed at lardge in the sermon: toile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, in regard of the extreame heate whereunto those countries, through the which she was to passe, were by nature of the clymates subiect vnto: peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, in respect of the danger of those viperous, vene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mous, and deadly vermine, which naturally each part of those countries ingendreth: Chargeable, in regard of the traine that she was attended and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with, and in regard of the great magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence wherewith King Salomon was by her in all regal bounty rewarded: Although the comparison heere wil not holde betweene the Queene of the South &amp; the Q of England for vndertaking a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney &amp;c. Yet neverthelesse how laborious, perilous, toilesome, chargeable the regiment of this mighty kingdome, in these daungerous daies, hath beene to Queene Elizabeth, al Christendome knoweth to her great honour, &amp; we her subiects doe acknowledge, glorifying God that hath wrought so great workes by her, for the establishment of religion, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold good of this Realme.</p>
   <p>The Queene of the South a daughter of peace; which appeareth partly by her learning, partly by her long peregrination: wherof the first is not so ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily obtained without peace and quietnesse: The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may be verefied to be true by the fruites of her peregrination. For it is to be presumed to be a thing infallibly true, that shee durst not haue vndertaken such a iourney, vnlesse her countries had beene set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled
<pb facs="5"/> in great peace at home. The Q. of England,<note place="margin">Cicer. pro Muren. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul ar{que} in crepuit sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picio tumul tus, artes il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licò omnes cōticescūt. Bach Lyri. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>. M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ham speaking of the Q in his School. master, fol. 19. Besides her perfitte redines, in Latine, French, &amp; Spanish, shee rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth heere nowe at Windsore more Greek every day, then some Prebenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of some churches do read la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine in a whol week.</note> a mirrour of peace in these troublesome daies, at her first cōming to the crowne, she came, like the doue to the Arke of Noah, with the oliue leafe, a signe of peace, in her mouth, as I haue mentioned in my tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atise adioined to the sermon: &amp; hath remained ever since, a continuer of that peace vvhich was first brought in by Gods goodnes vnder her regimēt. For her Maiesties: learning I refer you to M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Ascams te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonie marginallie coted, and speake the lesse of it, because it is contained in that parte of the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, wherein her skill in languages is mentioned.</p>
   <p>The Queene of the Souths holy wisdome thereby was ennobled, and deserved everlasting commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that shee was an embracer of true religion, and with an holy zeale endured extreame paines and peril of a long iourney, to come to Ierusalem, to bee resolued in such doubts by King Salomō, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the grounds of her salvation. The Q. of England, a zealous imbracer of his doctrine whom K. Salomō shaddowed and prefigured, a defender of that faith, which the blood of Iesus Christ hath sealed &amp; sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. For the which, although shee hath not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken any laborious peregrination, yet hath shee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, for the defence and maintenance therof, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bitter stormes, and escaped by Gods goodnes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great dangers, which for the defence of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell haue beene complotted against her. They that doubt of this, let them but call to memory the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full danger of the Northren rebellion in the yeare of
<pb facs="6"/> our Lorde,<note place="margin">Stowes Chron. An. 1569.</note> 1569. and the 12. yeare of her Maiesties raigne, blowne vp to a head by the bellowing of <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> bloody Bull, let them remember, I say, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingtons &amp; Ballards conspiracy, Hardings imagery, Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ies treasons, and vnnatural cruelty; let them put before their eies the attempts of the Spanish fleete, 1588. the Popish leagues, cruel, pollitike, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful confederacy, Lopez, &amp; Squires poisonable and venemous treachery. In the which doubtlesse, we had al perished, &amp; had bin swallowed vp quicke, if the Lord had not beene on our side,<note place="margin">Psalm. 124.</note> and God had not giuen wisedome to her, and her Counsell, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the drifts of our mighty adversaries.</p>
   <p>The Queene of the South a rare Phenix, and a bright starre eclipsing with the light of her vertue &amp; knowledge al the Princes before her and after her in Aethiopia, as farre-forth as by any record of the Aethiopians History it hath bin discovered vnto vs. How rare a Phenix the Q. of England hath beene, &amp; how bright a starre in these daies, our owne Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles can manifest, and the experience of her blessed regimēt this one &amp; forty yeares demōstrateth more evidently, then my pen can depaint. For in the fruits of her peace she wil shine as a star in the Catalogue of her honorable predecessours, and for her learning and wisedome wil be as a Phenix renowned by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny famous writers to the people of that age, which shal succeede her. Not meaning to presse this simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude or comparison any further, lest I should seeme to misdoubt the discreete iudgment of the intelligēt
<pb facs="6"/> Reader, to whom one word is sufficient to insinuate a matter of lardge discourse: and since it is a point in al learning obserued, that no comparison, reference,<note place="margin">Nulla simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor currit pedibus.</note> or resemblaunce similitudinary should hold in each part: and for that there are many things appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to the person of the Queene of the South, which cannot to any creature else be applied by any apt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: And since al know that wisedome,<note place="margin">I meane the faithful Iames 1.</note> learning knowledge, fortitude, mercy, &amp;c. and al good &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect giftes, as beames from the Sun, issue, and are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived and giuen from and by the Father of lights &amp;c. and that no good nor perfitte gifte shineth in man, but what he hath receiued from aboue, and for the which he is bound to be thankful to God the giuer:<note place="margin">Cirill: de recta fide ad pientiss. reginas.</note> &amp;c. I end this part with this sentence of Cyrill: <hi>Vbi fides recta et irreprehensibilis cum honorum operum honestate coniungitur, &amp; aquo cur su admittitur, illic omninò est in omni bono perfectio, &amp; sanctificationis integritas:</hi> Where a right and vnreprovable faith is conioined with the excellency of good workes, and entertained in one current with them, ther is a perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in al goodnesse, and there flourisheth the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of sanctification.</p>
   <p>I haue adioined to this Sermon (wherin I haue discoursed at lardge of each point of the Texte pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed to it) an Apologetical discourse not impertinēt to those thinges, wherunto the application of the sermon then tended wherein I haue fully and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully confuted al such slaunders, wherewith our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Country, and Gracious Prince hath beene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truely
<pb facs="7"/> and vncharitably charged &amp; traduced by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers malicious adversaries in the greatest cōsistories of Christendome, for that to the glory of God and honour of Q. Elizabeth the 17. of Novēber is yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly celebrated in festivall and ioyful manner by the subiects of this land in these times: our thankes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to God being grounded on the Apostles pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts the 1.<note place="margin">1: Tim: 2:</note> to Timothy and the 2. Chap. our other exercises of ioy being of that quality as by Christian people in most ages since Christs Incarnation haue beene vsed in the world,<note place="margin">Euseb: de vlt. pan. Const. 1.2.</note> at set times, in the honour of their soveraignes.</p>
   <p>The motiues that induced mee to vndertake the treatise of these matters were these. First for that this argument fitted the vse of the doctrine which I hād<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Paules the 17. of November Anno Domini, 1599. and was a necessary consequent in the Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Secondly for that by sundry things expressed in the contentes of the Apologie each indifferent Reader may palpably descipher the fruites of vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous malice, and malitious disloialty. Lastly, for that this Apology may serue as a Caveat for al good sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to beware of al seditious spirites, who, in such places where they may be bold, and hope to passe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way without controlement, cease not to set abroach sclaunders of this nature: hoping, by the intoxicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this venoum, to breede in many her Maiesties subiects a mislike of the present government, a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinesse of wel-doing, a loathing of the sincere and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolike religion, which by Gods blessing this flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing
<pb facs="7"/> Realme enioyeth in these times vnder the peaceable and bright sunne-shine of Queene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths Regiment.</p>
   <p>And although the Sermon runneth only in the general heades of discourse: yet I thought it most expedient to handle the things contained in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology scholastically, or after the maner of Schools, partly for that the truth or falshood of things of this quality wil easier appeare, and is sooner brought to head and issue by questional debatement truely and faithfully collected and alleadged, then by long dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursing. Offring with al to ioine issues in this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or any other now professed or defended in the Church of England with any learned or modest ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary, that shal vndertake to gainesay any thing that is laid downe either in the Sermon, or in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie. The learned and modest adversary only I provoke. For reviling and sclaunderous adversaries deserue no answer, but only that which Michael the Archangel in Saint Iude his Epistle giveth to Sathā <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi> And as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Zachary saith, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,<note place="margin">72. Interp. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>The Lord rebuke thee, O Satan,</hi> even the Lord that hath chosen Ierusalem reproue thee, &amp;c. Partly, I say, I haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into this manner of exercise, for that I hope by this forme of discussing, I shal provoke many of my sonnes, (whom I so tearme, for that by my Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical service in the Chaire of Divinity it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God that they should be invested in the titles of Theological degrees) to ioine with me in this kinde
<pb facs="8"/> of writing since (as the proverbe is) I haue begunne to breake the ice vnto them in this matter, and saie vnto them, not <hi>Ite,</hi> but <hi>Eamus,</hi> setting apart al ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuses, and shaking of al impediments. which vsuallie are suggested by Satans policie, and of purpose, to quench al good sparckles that may kindle flames of light, apte to discover the pathes of Gods glory.</p>
   <p>And although the vse of discoursiue Divinity bee profitable for the Church of God, and is question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse an holy, and a fruitful labour, if it be performed by men of learning and discretion: Yet neverthelesse in these times giue me leaue to thinke the Scholasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal manner of writing more convenient, for the Church of God. First for that in long discourses quarrels are very often piked in wordes by cavilling and vnconscionable adversaries, and yeelde many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasions to Sophistical wranglers, as appeareth by <hi>Stapletons Antidot:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Stap Antid Stap. Tripl.</note> and his <hi>Triplic:</hi> against <hi>Doctor VVhittakers Divers Tractes of Possevine</hi> a Iesuite, printed Ann. Dom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>87. at <hi>Collen,</hi> to the which we may adioine diuerse Pamphlets printed in High Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the defence of <hi>Vbiquity:</hi> many of which bookes and manie others entitled with monstrous names (as <hi>Calvinus Iudaïzans:<note place="margin">Calvinus Iudaiz us Asinus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis. Calvino-turcism.</note> Asinus Avis; Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino-turcismus)</hi> doe (in mine opinion) in most places resemble the dish that <hi>Prometheus</hi> in his banket en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained <hi>Iupiter</hi> with in derisiō, covering the bones with skinne and sinnowes, defrauding his guestes of the flesh and fat: Of al which bookes and treatises I say with <hi>Saint Austin,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug: conf. lib. 1. ca 15.</note>
      <hi>Vae tibi flumen moris humani,
<pb facs="8"/> quis refistet tibi? quamdiu non siccaberis? quous{que} vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves Evae filios in mare magnū &amp; formidolo sum, quod vix transeunt, qui ligna transcendunt?</hi> that is, Woe be to thee thou wicked woont or common custome of mankind, who shal crosse the tide with thee? how long shal the floating of thy waters not be drained? how long wilt thou role the sons of Eue to that great and troublesome sea, which they that passe them by ship can hardly escape:<note place="margin">Psal. 4.</note> and with the holy Prophet <hi>David</hi> in the 4. Psal. <hi>ô filij hominum &amp;c.</hi> O sonnes of men, how long wil ye turne my glory into shame? louing vanity, &amp; seeking lies.</p>
   <p>The second reason why I thinke it most conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, wherfore the most parte of controversies should be handled scholastically, is, for that long writing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes bringeth a great disadvantage to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, &amp; Readers, and serueth much the turne of the cavilling gainsayers. To the Author, for that longe discourses oftentimes enforce him to reiterate &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcat the same thing, and make him seeme tedious to the Readers: To the Readers, long discourse bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth incōveniēce. For the lēgth of the speech, &amp; the overmuch heaping of things consequently one vpō an others necke, causeth a forgetfulnes of that which hath beene said before: the memory and vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of man beeing not infinite, but faculties finite infused by God to the reasonable soule of man, and ordained to cōceiue knowledge &amp; learning <hi>nō per in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitum, sed per discur sum,</hi> not by the first insight, but by much discoursing and debating on all sides, as the
<pb facs="9"/> Schoolemen speake.<note place="margin">The School mēs distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitus and Discursus.</note> The gainsaiers only get advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage therby. For at their pleasures, Here they make an assaie, There they leaue,, Here they assault, There they relinquish, Here they wrest, There they depraue Here they inverte, There they perverte wordes invea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling thē vpō each smal quidditie to turne thēselues like changeable <hi>Proteus</hi> into al shapes:<note place="margin">Homer. Odyss. 4. Plyny. de nura Saep.</note> and in the end encourage them to play the partes of the fish <hi>Sapiae</hi> which (as <hi>Pliny</hi> saith) is accustomed to darcken the water, where hee is fished for, with an effusion as blacke as incke, attempting thereby to escape the handes of the skilful fisher-man, angle hee never so skilfully, and sufficiently. I am enforced in this vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie to vtter my minde, for that manie in these daies, I finde in writing rather to seeke glory of men then of God, and to dwel rather vpon wordes then matter: which course of writing (as the Apostle saith) rather breedeth strife,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1. c. v. 4.</note> then godly edifying, that is, by faith. Yet (deare sonnes and loving fellow-soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours in Christ) let not this my censure be a discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement vnto any one (that approveth this order of dealing with the Adversary) from his good labours, since no question, (if any incline this way) this kinde of writing is a gift given him from aboue. Assuring him that my wordes heerein are no causes of discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement vnto him, or anie others that shal labor in this course; but I wish in the Lord that these admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions may serue as caveats, and <hi>watchwordes,</hi> and <hi>wardwordes</hi> (as some of late haue written) to al such as preferre this kinde before anie other, and take this
<pb facs="9"/> the fittest field for them to bestowe their manuring of: and the best ground to til; &amp; the ground, which wil yeelde greatest blessing to their labours. For their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspectnesse herein wil doe great good both to the matter, and method. This advertisement I thoughte good here to inserte, as appertinent to the purpose, for that this kinde of writing vnlesse it bee managed in such sort, as I haue specified before, breedeth most inconvenience to the Author, troubleth most the Reader, and least disadvantageth the adversary. But whether long discourse, or scholastical method best serue your studies, and bee most fit for controversie writers, I wil not here further discusse, but refer each man in the Lord to his owne inclination, neither am I to prescribe to any one what course to take, only I speake therein mine opinion, as one that by Gods mercy haue long travailed in these exercises: and as one that hath <hi>obtained mercy of the Lorde to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi>
      <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note> Asserteining that these 2.<note place="margin">Plutarch. Virgil. Math. 25.</note> waies are not like the <hi>Bivium</hi> of <hi>Hercules,</hi> neither the letter of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> nor the right hād, nor the left in the day of iudgmēt. But, if they be wel handled, like the 2.<note place="margin">Apoc. 11. Nazian. Tetrast. 1.</note> oliue braūches and two cādelstickes which wil stand before the God of the Earth: And like those 2. goodly pearles of life whereof Nazianzene speaketh in his Tetrastikes, of which whosoever shal embrace either, he shal not loose his labour. <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: that is, both of them are fitte &amp; louely.</p>
   <p>But here I finde 2. sortes of people misliking my present exhortatiō. First some wil deeme that by this
<pb facs="10"/> discourse I meane to reduce againe into the Church the olde Dunsery of the Schoolmen, long agoe cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the world, &amp; by special verdit exiled out of the Church, reputed by al graue and learned di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines rather a trade of blinde Sophistry, then a right course of sound divinity; To these that obiect vnto me in this eager bitternes, I answere on this maner. If they meane the matters that the Schoole-mē de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate in their darke and cloudie affected obscurity, &amp; prophane mixture of Philosophie with divinity, let them assure themselues, this course I condemne as wel as they, and repute such schooles in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces worthy to be striken with that thunder-bolte of the Prophets:<note place="margin">Esaiae. 1. Ier. 2.</note>
      <hi>How is the faithfull city become an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lott? Thy silver is become drosse, thy wine is mixte with water, My people hath forsaken me the founteine of liuing waters, &amp; digg thē pittes evē, brokē pittes that can holde no water: VVhat hast thou to doe in the way of Aegypt to drinke vp the vvater of Nilus? or vvhat makest thou in the vvay of Assur to drinke the vva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the river?</hi> And that al that follow these courses in that forme with them, are no better thē those im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure <hi>Philistines</hi> that <hi>filled the welles vvith earth,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Gen. 28.</note> that <hi>Abrahā</hi> the holy Patriarch had digged. If otherwise, I say, that noe man of learning and iudgement can iustly condemne the scholastical method, Their manner of briefe distinguishing, Their short obiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Their art of summary and material aunswering, Their practise of short &amp; substātial concluding. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this mine opinion alone herein but also the
<pb facs="10"/> iudgment of <hi>Anthony Sadeele</hi> a man for knowledge of Divinity aboue al exceptions of any gainesayer,<note place="margin">Antonius Sadeele de vera me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodo The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ologicè si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul ac Scholasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cè disputā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di.</note> vnto whose censure I doe appeale heerein, to whose opinion I doe subscribe, &amp; to whose tract of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument I referre the Readers. Assuring al learned Schollers, that if the drosse &amp; tinne of Schoole-di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity be purged and burned away by the true fire of Gods word, that the method of Schoole-learning is not lightly to be reiected, neither vtterly to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
   <p>The secōd sort of people that wil take offēce at this treatise are many such as make supposal, that this per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>suasion of mine, if it should take effect, would great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinder the vnspeakeable benefitte vvhich godlie preaching worketh in the Church amongst Christiā people. To this I answere. God forbid that this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation or any other by me vttered should be anie impediment, or any waies a motion to hinder the gift of soule-saving preaching,<note place="margin">1. Thes. c. 5</note> cōcerning which the Apostle hath writtē to the Thessalonians in this mā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Quench not the Spirit, despise not prophecying:</hi> which, because it doth cōtaine these three benefits, namely, edification, exhortation, and cosnolation, the same Apostle preferreth before the miraculous giftes of tongues, which was the admirable trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure giuen to the Church after our Saviour Christ his ascension to be imploied to the gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Saints, and for the edification of Christs body. Yet I beseech them that are of this mind faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully &amp; iudicially to examine how I shal refel by Gods
<pb facs="11"/> grace this coniecturall supposal, and misconceiued imagination. True it is I must confesse that the gift of preaching, in our church, and in al the Churches vnder the cope of heaven, is a sacred and a most be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial gift, if it be sincerely ministred: that the true vse of it is farre to bee preferred before the vse of tongues, and many other giftes in the Church: that it was the summe of that cōmission, which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour gaue to his Apostles, both before and after his Ascension:<note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. v. 14.</note> that it is <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, or that worthy thing that P. commended to <hi>Timothy:</hi> and that thing which he was by the Apostle commaunded to deliver to faithfull men, which should be able al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to teach others: Yet this nothing impeacheth the true vnderstanding of the former proiect, as by the grace of God it shal appeare by this sequele.</p>
   <p>There may be numbred in this Realme at these times neere 5000. Preachers, Catechists, Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, God be praised, who increase the number of thē. The maine streame and tide of Students in Divinity is caried wholie this way, not without some secret influence of Gods spirite, I doubt not: In the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versities the greatest nūber of scholers desire to haue their names in the register of the sonnes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: Now of these 5000. if there were but 50. able men dedicated to this worke, men qualified in gifts, men which like <hi>Hur</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi> would hold vp <hi>Moses</hi> hands,<note place="margin">Exod. 17.</note> whilest <hi>Ioshua</hi> and <hi>Israel</hi> discomfite <hi>Amalecke:</hi> I dare boldly speak, that the studies of these 50. faith fully imploied, (so that they would not imitate the
<pb facs="11"/> children of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> who as it is said in the Psalme <hi>being armed and shooting with the bow, turned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues backe in the day of battell:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 78.</note>) would rather helpe preaching, then hinder it, increase it; then diminish it; multiply it, rather, then substract any thing from it. The master that sturreth at the healme, &amp; the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lottes that by their cards &amp; sea-markes discover the danger of shelues, sands; and rocks, hinder nothing either the sailers, or marriners: The scouts and tower-watchmen saue both Captaine and souldiour from many a danger. The kay-keepers of the little houses, the coverwel-heads, and spring-cleansers, (so that they keepe them free from poison &amp; corruption) are the causes why the streames of water that issue from the founteines, runne more purely; and why the rammes &amp; sheepe of Gods pasture may drinke of the liuing waters more delight<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>omely and safely. So in mine opinion if this or any other course of this qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity be in these daies put in practise in the church by them that are the great overseers therof: propheci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or preaching, Prophets and preachers wil bee more multiplied, the Adversary better aunswered, the glorie of God more advaunced.<note place="margin">Eight and thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sand 1 Chr 13. v 3. 1. Chr. 8 3 2. San<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 7. 1 King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>5. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tie 3. v. 7 8.</note> Lastly to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere al in one word there were in <hi>Israel</hi> in the raign of <hi>David</hi> nūbred aboue 30000. Levits, persōs ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical, Priests, musicions, singers: and in the time of <hi>Solomon</hi> his son, I thinke that they were augmented, since <hi>King Davids</hi> time was a time of bloode, but Salomons raigne flourished with peace: Yet the garding of the bed of <hi>Salomon,</hi> figuring the Arke
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="12"/>
      <pb facs="13"/> the testimony, (as it is expounded by the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee <hi>Thargum</hi> &amp; <hi>Lyra</hi> his cōmētaries) &amp; by cōsequēt therof a type of the church in the new Testament by three-score armed mē of the valiant of Israel,<note place="margin">Calde tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum. Lira com</note> mē ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perte in warre, of which every one had his sword v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pō his thigh, for the feare of the night. Was no impe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dimēt to the Priests, Levits, musitiās, singers, &amp; to thousāds of such as served in the ministery of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, &amp; taught Gods law to the people either in the Tēple at Ierusalē, or in the seueral Sinagogs in the lād of Israel. This seruing to cōclude, I boldly may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verre, as one that of the Lord hath obtained mercy, that 50. armed in the studies of Divinity, furnished with skil of toūgs, laboriously exercised in the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs, studiously cōversāt in the fathers, wel acquaīted with the history of times, practised in ready writing, will be no more hinderāce of the thousands of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of this land, following such a course, as I haue mencioned, then the 60. armed men, that garded &amp; warded the bed of Salomon for the terrors of the night were a scandal, or a clowd either to make Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el to fal, or to ecclipse the light of the blessed counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, of the Lord of hosts, that shined more bright then the light of the sun, vpon the congregations of Israel.<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.</note> God grant that my words may be goads vnto al the godly and good subiects of this Realme, for his Sonnes sake, to whom with the Holy Ghost be al ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, glory, and praise, world without end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>