<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his harty freind Master segraue Iohn Foxe the translatour, whyshyth grace and lyght of the ho∣ly spirit.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104178_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08463</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18787</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104178</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his harty freind Master segraue Iohn Foxe the translatour, whyshyth grace and lyght of the ho∣ly spirit.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sarmon, of Ihon Oecolampadius, to yong men, and maydens</title>
                 <author>Oecolampadius, Johann</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 <publisher>Powell, Humphrey.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Singleton (Syngleton), Hugh</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_translator">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To his harty freind Master segraue Iohn Foxe the translatour, whyshyth grace and lyght of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spirit.</head>
   <p>Sythen the tyme I fyrst perceiued in you, your desire to the word of God and hys holy institution, I haue not ceased to be sollycytus in mynd and prayers for you, desiring the father and sender of our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Chryst to encrease that thing in you whyche he hath begone. And that inwardly you myght be reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyshed wyth plentuous spyryt and knowledge of the great glory and ryches, which is geuen vs in Christ to thentent you myght be altered in the sence of your mind to a new mā, And profesly forsak the vaine frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thys earthly world, and to embrace y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> glorious vocatyon whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="3"/>
we called to in christe. The whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I thynk is hard for you and us all to do. The sence of our fleshe is so strong. The temptyng spyrytt is so ready. Neuerthelesse insomuche yet it is our partes wyth mutuall conferring one to exhorte an other. And also for the brotherly affection I beare to you warde, I cānot nor aught not I suppose, but some thyng I say as concernyng your spyrytuall eadyfycation. And by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause yow shall not take my exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyones whyche be but of feble weyght, for you to styk vnto, here I haue traunslated and sent to you a fruitfull adhortacion of a famose Chrystiane I, Oecolāpadius, desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng you to accepte well in worthe thys labore bestowed, and also to geue dilygent reding to his precep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis whose institutions yf you wyll attently mark and peruse, I doubt
<pb facs="3"/>
nothyng, but you shall receyue no smale fruyte thereatt, beyng suffycyently instructed in all thynges you shall desire. The liuing grace of chryst be with you. So be it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>