<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO MY LORD: THE
DVKE OF BVCKING∣HAMS
Grace: Whom God
Preserue.</title>
           <author>Holland, Hugh</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104140_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03469</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13591</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104140</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO MY LORD: THE
DVKE OF BVCKING∣HAMS
Grace: Whom God
Preserue.</title>
                 <author>Holland, Hugh</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A cypres garland : For the sacred forehead of our late soueraigne King Iames. By Hugh Holland</title>
                 <author>Holland, Hugh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Waterson, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>❧ TO MY LORD: THE
DVKE OF BVCKING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAMS
Grace: Whom God
Preserue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>RIVATE acknowledgment may not sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
for Publique curtesies. And what more
publique then a Kings presence? Very glad
therefore I should haue bin of the least opportunity to
expresse my thankfulnesse: and much more grieud at the
heart I am, that now I haue so iust occasion. But all the
Noble Fauours which I haue receiued at your Gracious
Hands, I haue layd vp in a gratefull Heart. It was you that
led me by the hand nor once, nor twice, to kisse that awful
Hand of his, to which I durst not haue else aspired▪ With
<pb facs="3"/>
what sweetenesse and brauery the Great Majesty of <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi>
imbraced then his meanest Vassal, and those my
humble Compositions, Our young Souereigne (then
Prince of my Country) your Grace and the Honourable
Lords then praesent, perhaps remember (sure I am, I can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
forget) And if I do, let my right hand forget her cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
But I will represse my selfe, least I may seeme to haue
pickt occasion, rather to boast my selfe, then to bewaile
him. And yet in spight of mine owne modesty, in spight
of others malignity, in the approbation of <hi>Iames the great,</hi>
I do, I must, I will euer triumph His Majesty to me did
much grace: and faine to his memory would I do some
Glory. Oft to my comfort I spake or wrot to Him, now to
my griefe I only write of him. This Elegy vents more
sorow then wit, For in wit the lesse I was to labour, in
whose roome matter had succeeded, If it be too longe,
thinke that my teares haue drouned my inke: if it bee too
<pb facs="3"/>
short, thinke that my sighes both inke at once▪ and teares
haue drayned▪ With his H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>hments, at Westminster I
also offer vp my Pen, consecrating the life thereof to Him,
and him to aeternity. I wil conclude with publique vowes.
With vowes <abbr>X</abbr> and with vowes <abbr>XX.</abbr> So with <abbr>X.</abbr> so with
<abbr>XX.</abbr> The God of <hi>Iacob</hi> proiect all his Elixar of blessings
vppon the Sonne and Seede of IACOB. That King
CHARLES may euer liue in the fauour of God, your
Grace in his, and I in yours.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Graces seruant
in much affection
HVGH HOLLAND.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>