<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ TO THE RIGHTE worshipfull Maister Ihon Fitz▪ williams Gouernour of the most fa∣mous societie of Marchauntes Aduenturers into Flaunders. And to the righte VVorshipfull the Consult, Assistens, and comminaltie of the same societie, Humfrey Baker wisheth health with continuall increase of commo∣ditie by their worthie trauaile.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104536_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01957</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1210</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104536</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ TO THE RIGHTE worshipfull Maister Ihon Fitz▪ williams Gouernour of the most fa∣mous societie of Marchauntes Aduenturers into Flaunders. And to the righte VVorshipfull the Consult, Assistens, and comminaltie of the same societie, Humfrey Baker wisheth health with continuall increase of commo∣ditie by their worthie trauaile.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvell spryng of sciences : whiche teacheth the perfecte woorke and practise of arithmeticke, bothe in whole nombers and fractions, with suche easie and compendious instruction into the said arte, as hath not heretofore been by any sette out nor laboured. Beautified with moste necessary rules and questions, not onely profitable for marchauntes, but also for all artificers, as in the table doeth partlie appere: set forthe by Humfrey Baker citezeine of Lo [n] don</title>
                 <author>Baker, Humfrey</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rowbotham (Robothum), James</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 162, 2 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ TO THE RIGHTE worshipfull Maister Ihon Fitz▪ <hi>williams Gouernour of the most fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous societie of Marchauntes Aduenturers into</hi> Flaunders. And to the righte VVorshipfull the Consult, Assistens, and comminaltie of the same societie, Humfrey Baker wisheth health with continuall increase of commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie by their worthie trauaile.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough heretofore (right worshipfull) diuers and sundrye wel skilled men in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> feate, and science of numbrynge, haue not spared their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, not onelie in beatifiyng, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so in augmentyng the same with such increase of witte, as hath excedinglye contained the studientes therein, and made them riper, in the exacte know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and redinesse of it. Yet because an arte can not haue to muche setting furthe, neither can be to muche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monded, I (amonge, and after so man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnaunt
<pb facs="3"/>
wittes) am bolde to putte forthe the fruicte of my blunt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng and trauaile, in the like sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, not correctyng or reprouyng any mans former edition, but makyng an attempte of my grosse, and meane stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die herein, to the entent that thys my enterprise maye (by other mennes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges (bee either gentlie amended, or frendlie receiued. And because I desire speciallie that it may bee gratfullie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, I haue chosen you (worshipful) to be as defendours of this little lucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration, to whom I knowe it shall bee welcome, not so muche for my sake, as for the science loue it selfe, wherin it is wel knowen you haue ripe iudgement and good vnderstandyng, as by youre daylie exercises it maie appeare. And although some folishe heades of fansie ouerthwart, thinke this Arithmetical art peculier onely to a fewe, vsyng the trade of marchaundise, as though it were not so necessarie for other men: yet I am sure, the wisest and best lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="3"/>
perceiuyng the wonderfull art, the depe diuises, and the cunnyng con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions that are comprised in it: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it (that of right) to bee the beste whetstone, or sharpnyng of the witte of euerie man that euer was inuented, &amp; thinke it most necessary to be taught vnto children, without the whiche, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge either priuate or common can bee well ordered. And true it is, that whosoeuer is ignorant of this science of numbring, he stepeth in all the reste and lacketh that promptitude of witt, whiche other haue in callynge and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptynge of greate summes. Yea, I saie he that hath the exact knowledge of it, hath a speciall gift of God, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth about hym a note and token of a good witte: and I doubt whether euer any was counted or estemed simple or folishe, that had this science in his head Nowe if some curiours braine would aske me this question: six you cōmende much your art of numbering, can you tell who was the firste inuentor of it, or
<pb facs="4"/>
what this worde <hi>Arithmetica</hi> doth si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie, I would answere hym that it is vncertaine who inuented it firste, but well I knowe, it is one of the seuen li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral sciences: which, if I say god gaue vnto man to adourne his life with all, I saie as it is, &amp; as wee ought to beleue of whom we acknowledge to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued them &amp; not of the Poetes, or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then gods, as some schole men wil say. Moreouer, I knowe that Abraham taught it first vnto the Egiptians, and no man wil denie but that he receiued all his knowledge of god for he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped no straunge gods neither recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued any giftes or sciences of them. And although many yeres after, Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras declared it to the Grekes, yet was not he the firste inuentor of it, but god. Plato also commended it as most ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie, willinge it to be taught to all youth before all other thinges. And thinkes be to god, it appeareth that his precept hath been very well folowed here in Englande, for I finde not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="4"/>
nation (I speake not flateryng my countrey men but commending them) more ready knowledge in this science, then there is in the moste parte of our youth here in Englande, and namely in London, whiche I séeyng it is in them, it is (out of question) in their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and tutours, whiche by their greate care ouer theim, haue trained theim vp vnto the practise thereof, to whom the greateste parte of the praise redoundeth. And nowe right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, when I consider how little profite my simple trauaill shall bryng, beyng but as it were an assaye of further at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, I am cōpelled to craue at your handes onely to accepte my good will with the worke: for will &amp; abilitie are somewhat vnequall in me, but if abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie were corespōdent to will, I would gladly pleasure you in greater thinges then this is, whiche is but a shadowe incomparison of other mēnes substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall labour and trauail in this art: yet I truste it is not altogether so vnpoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed,
<pb facs="5"/>
but it hath passed vnder the file of some workemanshippe, wherby some men maye take occasion of profit and furtherance herein, which is my chiefe desire, although I knowe many are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do better: for England is not so destitute of learned heades, but my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges may sone be folowed, yea rather amended. But yet forasmuche as I would thei should knowe, that knowe not▪ I thought it not good to hide that which hath been opened vnto me. And so casting with my self the sōme of all, I destre you eftsones, right worshipful (to whome I thought it moste mete to present the fruicte of my studie) than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kefullye to receiue it, as your wonted wisedomes doth all thinges well and vertuouslie purposed.</p>
   <p>Thus fare you well, destryng God to maintaine you in youre estate, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spere &amp; further all your traffickes and voyages, encrease you in vertue, and keepe you in good health.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>