<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶Vnto the Christen Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1530</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104932_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13748</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24045</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104932</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶Vnto the Christen Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The examinacion of Master William Thorpe : preste accused of heresye before Thomas Arundell, Archebishop of Ca [n] terbury, the yere of ower Lord .MCCCC. and seuen. The examinacion of the honorable knight syr Jho⁻n Oldcastell Lorde Cobham, burnt bi the said Archebisshop, in the fyrste yere of Kynge Henry the Fyfth</title>
                 <author>Thorpe, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hoochstraten (Hillenius Hoochstratanus), Joannes</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1530</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>136 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶Vnto the Christen Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Race and peace in oure lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Iesu Christe. Reade here with iudgemente goode rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the examinacion of the blssed man of god / and there thou shalt caselye perceyue wherfore oure holy chirch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the most on holy sorte of all the people wilbe cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led) make all their examinaciōs in darkenes / all the laye people cleane excluded from their coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cels. For yf their lies had ben openly confuted and also that the accused of heresye myghte as well haue ben admytted to reason their articles with councell / whether they were heresye or no as the accused of treason agenst the king / is ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mytted to his councell to confute his cause and articles whether they be treason or not / they shulde neuer haue murthered nor prisoned so many good christen men as they haue done. For their cloked lyes coulde neuer haue conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued so long in the lighte / as they haue done in corners. They good men when they / come in the pulpet and preache agenst the treuth / crye: Yf their lernynge were goode and trew / they wold neuer go in corners / but speke it openly. Where vnto I answere that besyde that Christe and his apostles were compelled (for because of the furyousnes of their fathers the bishoppes and preastes) whiche onely that tyme also wolde
<pb facs="2"/>
be called holy chyrche) often tymes for to walke secretly / and absent them self and geue place to their malice? yet we haue daylye examples off more then one or two / that haue not spared nor feared for to speake and also preache opnlye the trouthe whiche haue ben taken of them pryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and brent / besyde other that for feare of dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the haue abiured and caryed fagottes. Of whos articles and examinacion there ys no leye man that can shewe a worde. Who can tell wherfore (not many yeres paste) there we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re seuen burnt in conuentrye on one daye? Who can tell wherfore that good preaste and holye martyr Syr Thomas hitton was brente / now thys yere / at maydstone yn Kent? I am sure no man. For this is their caste euer when they haue put to deathe or punyshed any man / after their secrete examynacyon / to slaunder hym of soche thynges as he neuer thought. As they maye do well Inough: seynge there is no man to contrarye them. Wherfore I exhorte the good brother / who soeuer thou be that redest thys treatyse / marke hit well and consyder it seryouslye / and there thou shalt fynde not onelye what the chyrche ys / theyre doctryne of the Sacramente / the worshyppyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge off ymagyes / pylgremage / confessyon / Swerynge and payinge of tythes? But also thou mayst se what stronge and substan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall argumentes off scripture and doctou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / and what clerkely reasons / my lorde / the
<pb facs="3"/>
hedde and prymate of the holye chyrche in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland (as he wilbe taken) bryngeth agenst this pore / folysh / symple / and madde losell / knave / &amp; heretike as he calleth hym. And also the verye cause wherfore all their examynacions are ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de in darkenes. And the lorde of all lyght shall lighten the with the candle of his grace / for to se the trewth. Amen.</p>
   <p>¶This I haue corrected and put forth in the english that now is vsed in Englāde / for owe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> sothern men / nothynge therto addynge ne yet ther from mynysshyng. And I entende hereafter with the helpe of God to put it forthe in his owne olde english / which shal well serue / I dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te not / bothe for the northern men ād the faythfull brothern of scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lāde.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>