<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104788_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16746</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3654</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104788</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A floorish vpon fancie : As gallant a glose vpon so triflinge a text, as euer was written. Compiled by N.B. Gent. To which are annexed, manie pretie pamphlets, for pleasant heads to passe away idle time withal. By the same authour</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>132 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <pb facs="21"/>
   <head>¶The Preface.</head>
   <l>MY friend, who so thou bee, that faine wouldst buy this booke,</l>
   <l>so passe away the time thereon, in ydle times to looke:</l>
   <l>If so thou fyndste that like thee not, yet pardon graunt to mee,</l>
   <l>And wish me from thy harte no worse, then I wish vnto thee.</l>
   <l>Against my will it shall be much, if many I offende,</l>
   <l>With these rude rymes which I haue made, vnto none other ende</l>
   <l>But as I sayde before, for want of other glee,</l>
   <l>For pleasaunt heads to looke vpon, when they at leysure bee.</l>
   <l>But some there are I must confesse, gainst whom in great despight,</l>
   <l>Some running rymes which here you see, I chaunced to indight.</l>
   <l>But such I count my deadly foes: and such one if thou bee</l>
   <l>That bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>est my boke, then take the same in deepe despight of thee.</l>
   <l>But if you be my frien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, and take all in good parte</l>
   <l>That there you fynde: and thinke it is for want of better Arte.</l>
   <l>Then here with right good will, I offer it to thee,</l>
   <l>And doe but thanke me for my paynes, it is ynough for mee.</l>
   <l>Of troth I promise yee, t'is not for want of will,</l>
   <l>That rudely thus in rymes I run, but want of better skill.</l>
   <l>For if that I had Ouids pen, ech worde in printe to place,</l>
   <l>Or Homers excercyse I had, to giue my verse a grace.</l>
   <l>Or Tullies Eloquence to talke▪ as I in minde thought best,</l>
   <l>Or Aristotles pregnant wit, that passeth all the rest.</l>
   <l>Some prety peece of worke▪ perhaps then moughtst thou fynde,</l>
   <l>Among so many mery toyes, that mought content thy minde.</l>
   <l>But tush, my beetle brayne, can no such fruictes bring forth,</l>
   <l>My v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>es are but ragged rimes, and therefore little worth.</l>
   <l>My head vnhoodded yet, I ready am to flye,</l>
   <l>At euery little paltrye bird, that goeth whisking by,</l>
   <l>I neuer haue respect to any kinde of Game,</l>
   <l>Like to the hooded Hauke: that kepte a long while tame</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="22"/>When that her Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e doth spring, she knowes it by the whurre,</l>
   <l>And then to make a wing thereat, she gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>es offyst to st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rre.</l>
   <l>But till the Game be sprong, on fyst she pearcheth still,</l>
   <l>But I (God wot) to choose my game, haue no such kinde of skill.</l>
   <l>I stryke at what I may, and geue God thankes for all,</l>
   <l>And stande contented with the same till better doth befall.</l>
   <l>And glad I am sometime, to pray vpon a Byrde,</l>
   <l>I haue no wit to waye the best, but euery worthelesse worde</l>
   <l>I ready am in ryme to put, although my reason be</l>
   <l>But small (God wot,) and that too small, as you may plainly see.</l>
   <l>But since you see my simple head, vnhooded (as it is,)</l>
   <l>Accept the symple fruict therof, and be content with this.</l>
   <l>Vntill I haue the skill, to flye at better Game,</l>
   <l>Which when I kill, you shall be sure to taste some of the same.</l>
   <l>But if ye now disdayne these Byrdes, whereon I pray,</l>
   <l>With better game hereafter I, perhaps will flye away.</l>
   <l>And lyke a very Churle, then will I parte with none,</l>
   <l>But feede vpon the best thereof, vnto my selfe alone.</l>
   <l>Where few or none shall see, what foode I feede vpon,</l>
   <l>No▪ nor yet where I hyde the same, till all be spente and gone.</l>
   <l>Wherefore my friende I say, if so thou doest desyre,</l>
   <l>More of my workes, and wouldst not haue the rest throwne in the fyre.</l>
   <l>Skorne not these ragged rymes, but rather soone amend,</l>
   <l>What so thou fyndst that likes thee not, and so I make an ende.</l>
   <l>Wishing thee well to fare, if so thou be my friend,</l>
   <l>But if my foe, then ill and worse, and so agayne I end.</l>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>