<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The booke to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104710_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16791</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3695</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104710</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The booke to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A smale handfull of fragrant flowers : selected and gathered out of the louely garden of sacred scriptures, fit for any honorable or woorshipfull gentlewoman to smell vnto. Dedicated for a Newe-yeeres gyft, to the honorable and vertuous lady, the Lady Sheffeeld. By N.B</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ The booke to the Reader.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>SInce I poore booke am put into thy hand,</l>
      <l>although the tome or volume litle bee,</l>
      <l>Yet Reader deare that I be throughly scand</l>
      <l>with zelous minde I begge and craue of thée</l>
      <l>Ne séeme to iudge or sentence thyne to frame,</l>
      <l>Before throughout thou do peruse the same.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Reade not as though thou wouldst forget agayne,</l>
      <l>such fruitles fayth bringes profite none at all:</l>
      <l>But if thou wylt reape merite for thy payne,</l>
      <l>let not regarde from wonted custome fall,</l>
      <l>Which as I reade by wise men is defind,</l>
      <l>While time doth serue, to beare the fruits in mind.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If then I cast a iewell vnto thée,</l>
      <l>play not the Cocke that <hi>Esope</hi> speaketh on,</l>
      <l>Who rather craued a barlye corne to sée:</l>
      <l>then for to finde the costly precious stone,</l>
      <l>But if I might giue counsel with the rest,</l>
      <l>First reade, thē chuse such fruits as lyke thée
 best.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Holde me excused, and take my maisters <hi>Muse,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>in as good part as payne he doth bestowe,</l>
      <l>Let his good wyll his simple worke excuse,</l>
      <l>for were it much more better: to bestowe</l>
      <l>For thy delyght he woulde vouchsafe his toyle,</l>
      <l>And yeelde to thée the croppe of suche a soyle.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>