<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL
Sir HENRY APPLETON,
Knight Barronet, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1633</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104058_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03195</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13315</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104058</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL
Sir HENRY APPLETON,
Knight Barronet, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English traueller : As it hath beene publikely acted at the Cock-pit in Drury-lane: by Her Maiesties seruants. Written by Thomas Heyvvood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1633</date>
                 <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Raworth, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVLL
Sir HENRY APPLETON,
Knight Barronet, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>NOBLE SIR,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or many reason I am induced, to present
this Poem, to your fauourable acceptance; and
not the least of them that alternate Loue, and
those frequent curtesies which interchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
past, betwixt your selfe and that good
old Gentleman, mine vnkle (Master <hi>Edmund Heywood</hi>) whom
you pleased to grace by the Title of Father: I must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse,
I had altogether slept (my weaklines and bashfullnesse
discouraging mee) had they not bin waken'd and animated,
by that worthy Gentleman your friend, and my countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
Sir <hi>William Eluish,</hi> whom (for his vnmerited loue
many wayes extended towards me,) I much honour; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Sir, neede you to thinke it any vnderualuing of your
worth, to vndertake the patronage of a Poem in this nature,
since the like hath beene done by Roman <hi>Laelius, Scipio,
Mecaenas,</hi> and many other mighty Princes and Captaines,
Nay, euen by <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> himselfe, concerning whom
<hi>Ouid</hi> is thus read, <hi>Detristi: lib.</hi> 2.</p>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>
Inspice ludorum sumptus Auguste tuorum</l>
   <l>Empta tibimagno, talia multa leges.</l>
   <l>Haec tu spectasti, spectandaque saepe de desti</l>
   <l>Maiestas adeo comis vbique tua est.</l>
   <p>So highly were they respected in the most flourishing
estate of the Roman Empire; and if they haue beene vilefied
of late by any Separisticall humorist, (as in the now questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<hi>Histrio-mastix</hi>) I hope by the next Terme, (<hi>Minerua
assistente</hi>) to giue such satisfaction to the world, by vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating
many particulars in that worke maliciously exploded
and condemned, as that no Gentleman of qualitie and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
but shall therein receiue a reasonable satisfaction; I
am loth by tediousnesse to grow troublesome, therefore
conclude with a gratefull remembrance of my seruice inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixt
with Miriads of zealous wishes for your health of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
and peace of minde, with superabundance of Earths
blessings, and Heauens graces, euer remaining;</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours most obseruant,
<hi>Thomas Heywood.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>