<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Pasquill, </author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1600</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104765_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16773</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3679</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104765</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Pasquill, </author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Pasquils passe, and passeth not : Set downe in three pees. His passe, precession, and prognostication</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                    <distributor>Smethwick (Smithick, Smythicke), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1600</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Asquill commends him to all that loue him, to
whom he giues to vnderstand, that after his pains
taken in his Mad-cappe, and his Fooles-cappe,
laying them both aside, thinking to take alitle rest,
gat him his Night-cappe, vnder which, in steede
of sleep, many idle humors came in his head, which troubling
his little staied braine, would not let him be at quiet, till he had
committed them to the custodie of pen, and incke, and paper,
which hauing set downe somewhat to his owne contentment,
he hath in diuers Copies sent abroade to all such as will pay for
the writing, or els, I should rather say, for the printing which I
thinke be better cheape: to tell you what he doth intreate of,
were needeles, when it followeth neere at hand: and therefore
onely thus much I will tell you, hauing past through manie
strange courses, and finding little or nothing so pleasing, but
tasted like a bitter sweete, vpon a suddaine fell vpon, Good
Lord deliuer vs, and so continuing of his Precession as long as
he thought good, growing weary of his life, fell to dreame of
Doomes-day: but lest I prooue tedious, I will turne you to
that you shall reade if it shall please you, and consider of it as
it shall like you, and so for this time I leaue you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friend <hi>Pasquill.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>