<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The Prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1571</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104623_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69098</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5113</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104623</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The Prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A most excellent hystorie, of the institution and firste beginning of Christian princes, and the originall of kingdomes : wherunto is annexed a treatise of peace and warre, and another of the dignitie of mariage. Very necessarie to be red, not only of all nobilitie and gentlemen, but also of euery publike persone. First written in Latin by Chelidonius Tigurinus, after translated into French by Peter Bouaisteau of Naunts in Brittaine, and now englished by Iames Chillester, Londoner. Séen and allowed according to the order appointed</title>
                 <author>Chelidonius, tigurinus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1571</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 199, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>¶ The Prologue.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lutarch the renou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> Philosopher, hath lefte vnto vs in writing, that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius Phalerius</hi> an excellent Orator and Philosopher (vpō whome the <hi>Athenians</hi> as vpō a firm and strong piller repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them, for the gouernment of their Seigniories and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions) did accustome, amō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest his priuate exhortations, to persuade <hi>Ptholome</hi> king of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> to erect a Librarie, &amp; to furnishe the same with all manner of Bookes, and namely with such as did intreate of the Gouernment of Realmes and Kingdomes: and withall, did specially exhort him to employ certaine houres of the day in reading of them, that hée mighte therby the better he instructed how to rule and gouerne such a puissant Realme as <hi>Aegipt</hi> was: bicause Bookes do alwayes franckly &amp; with all libertie admonish vs of those things which our Friends (commonly giuing place to time) do suppresse and kéepe in silence. And in Bookes also, if wée wil diligently and with iudgement consider well such exhortations and councels as wée may reade in them, wée shall finde much comforte and commoditie:<note place="margin">Bookes bee Iudges with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare or affection.</note> for Bookes are as Iudges without feare, which neuer are ashamed to shewe the truth, nor neuer stay themsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues for the dyspleasure or indignation of any King, Prince, or Magistrate, but folowing their frée nature and condition, with sharp and nypping wordes do disclose mens corrupt manners, rebuking them so sharply, that there is no sworde more to bée feared than the Learned pen, which toucheth euil and wicked men euen to the inwarde partes of the soule, and neuer giueth any stroke, but it pierceth to the ende and memorie of mannes life: for if vpon purpose she wil describe the outrages and dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders
<pb n="5" facs="9"/> of any vicious Prince, shée maketh his doings appeare so odious (by hir eloquence) that those that reade thesame, shal bée in great dreade and feare to heare such things named: and such as haue committed any crime shall bée greately ashamed that euer they did offende. And againe, if shée do employ hir force to commende their vertues and well doings, shée wyll blaze and set them out so maruellously, that such as shal reade it, shall so honour and reuerence those (whose Heroicall ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues they heare so exalted) that euen as men rauished, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the fame and glorie therof, will enforce themselues by al meanes possible to resemble their doings so liuely repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented vnto them. But contrarywise, these flattering and mealy mouthed Friendes of the pleasaunt Court, thinking to lose the praie that they séeke for,<note place="margin">Fearefull friendes.</note> or to runne into the dysgrace and dyspleasure of their Lordes and Maisters, oftentymes do stoppe their eares, become mute and dumbe, and passe vnder consent the enormities and abuses they sée at the eie, and touch euen as it were with their fingers notwithstāding they know and sée very well, their Princes and Lordes want greatly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition and councell. There is yet an other kinde of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, but muche woorsse and more contagious by a thousande parts than the others, and be such as put the oyle to the match,<note place="margin">Those that doo flatter Princes and lead them to wickednesse.</note> that be the trumpettes to prouoke and stirre them to wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, the torches that inflame them to vice, and that with ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunt commendations oyle and annoynt their heads vntil they bée growne fat with their owne filthynesse: and these be they that the Prophet speaketh of, that do putte the pillowes vnder their heads and the cushions vnder their elbowes, and wyth pleasaunt and swéete flattering woordes bring them asléepe til they be drouned and buried in their owne abhominations And these kinde of monsters among men be of the nature of Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillers, which neuer cleaue but vnto the good fruites, or of the nature of Moatthes, that always follow good clothes: for yée shall neuer sée them at any poore mannes gate, but as the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe followeth the bodie, so shall you finde them in the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces
<pb n="6" facs="10"/> of Princes, Kings and great Lords, whose heartes they do so well know how to winne (by a certaine swéet and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious maner of flattering and vaine cōmendations which they ring vnto their eares) that in the ende they snare &amp; catch them by one meane or other. The entrie of this kinde of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is very gentle, they bée like vnto waxe, they melte and transforme thēselues into al fashions, but their end is woorsse than the byting of a Scorpion:<note place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> des<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the arte and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrie of the flatterers of the court.</note> their words bée washed wyth swéetnesse and perfumed with pleasant smelles, but in their hands they cary poison, &amp; do ruinate al such as giue eare vnto them. The dissimulation &amp; subtiltie of such persons did amaze and dyscomfort the <hi>Sicilians,</hi> when the tyrannie of <hi>Dennis</hi> &amp; <hi>Phalaris</hi> was by these flatterers called punishment &amp; due iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice for their wickednesse: such pestilent Vipers did infect &amp; defile Egipt, when the effeminate doings of <hi>Ptholome</hi> with other his fonde and foolish vanities, were called by them good deuotion and deuine seruice: and such corruptiō deceyued also the <hi>Romaines,</hi> when the deliciousnesse &amp; wantonnesse of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonie</hi> such flatterers made so smal accompt of,<note place="margin">Many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weales haue bene made ruinat by adultery.</note> that they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it humanitie and curtesie: Of which pestilent Serpents and such like, ought those that are Lords and possessioners of al, to haue good regard vnto, who want nothing but frank and discrete mouthes that should tel them the truth. And therfore to auoide such domesticall enormities (as wryteth <hi>Philostra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus) Titus</hi> the sonne of <hi>Vaspasianus,</hi> in the beginning of hys Empire, departing out of <hi>Iudea,</hi> prayed <hi>Appolonius</hi> that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Philosopher, that he woulde giue him some politique instructions for the better gouernment of his Empire and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his enimies. To whome <hi>Appolonius</hi> answered, that hée woulde giue him a scholler of his owne, which should al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes bée with him, a liberal, franke and iust man in all his woords, who for the feare of any man would not forbeare to say the truth.<note place="margin">Philosophers are rebukers of wickednes</note> I wil (sayd hée) giue you (at this your request) a dog, that shal bée capable of reason, and shall bark agaynst all men, yea euen against your owne selfe if ye shal do any thing
<pb n="7" facs="10"/> woorthy reprehensiō, and shal vse with al wisdom &amp; discretiō, and haue regard to the time &amp; season when and how he ought to do his office. I wil receiue him with a good heart (sayd the Emperor, &amp; not onely suffer him to bark but also to scratch &amp; bite if he sée me cōmit any iniustice, or any other act vnséemly for the maiestie of mine estate &amp; empire. And <hi>Alexander</hi> that gret Monarch,<note place="margin">Alexander for hys perfec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion desireth to bee like Diogenes.</note> did not disdaine the seuere answer of that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable &amp; abiect man <hi>Diogenes,</hi> but had him in so gret admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he cried out with loude voice, saying, that if he were not <hi>Alexander</hi> hée woulde not desire any other thing (for his perfection) but to be <hi>Diogenes.</hi> Likewise <hi>Dennis,</hi> although he was a tyran &amp; King of <hi>Sycilia</hi> by force, could neuer bée per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suaded by such flattering Courtiers, to put frō him that great number of wise and learned men that he had about him, who (although he was a man himself clene gone astray, wrapped and folded in al kinde of euil &amp; wickednesse) answered to those shamelesse flatterers and sayd: I do not mainteine these ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men about me that ye tell me off, for any loue I beare to them,<note place="margin">The tyrans themselues doe honour learning.</note> or for any accompt that I make of their knowledge and wisdome, but I do it (sayd he) for that I would be praised and cōmended rather of them than any others. So you may sée &amp; vnderstand hereby, that although he neither loued vertue nor iustice, yet alwayes he would eschue slander &amp; reproch aswel in his life time as after his death. For the like cause <hi>Lacydes Syreneus</hi> was cōmaunded of King <hi>Attalus</hi> by his letters, and also by his messangers to repaire to hys Court, and promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him great promotions with much fauour and good will in al his requests, whervnto he would not consent, but answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him that Philosophers were as pictures or images which did shew better far off than at hande. <hi>Craterus</hi> the Emperor also did oftentimes intreate <hi>Diogenes</hi> to remaine with him to bée an aide and helper vnto him to gouerne his Empire in good order, to whome he answered,<note place="margin">Nero a mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therer of hys dere frends.</note> he loued better to bée fed with salte at <hi>Athens,</hi> than to be with him in all pleasure &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licatenesse, fearing least hée would do with him, as <hi>Nero</hi> did,
<pb n="8" facs="11"/> with his, who put to death al his friendes bycause they should not admonishe him of his wickednesse, nor that they shoulde bée witnesses of his myssedemeanours: and to auoide this, he gaue great gifts and rewardes to <hi>Aurelius Cotta▪</hi> and to <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Anthonius,</hi> and retained them stil with him in al delicate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and plesure: but that holy and vertuous man <hi>Seneca</hi> his maister, in satisfaction of al his good exhortations and holy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumentes which hée from time to time had giuen him,<note place="margin">The cruell death of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca.</note> hée cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to bée put into a baine of luke warm water, and al the vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, of his body to bée opened, that hée might with bléeding die, and so hée entreated that poore olde man. And it was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good cause that <hi>Darius</hi> did so much commend his friend <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyrus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Zopyrus a deare friend to Darius.</note> who on a time holding in his hand a Pomegranade, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired among other things, to haue so many such like friends as <hi>Zopyrus</hi> was, as there were kernelles conteined in the same: and of good reason hée sayd it, for hée shewed him self so affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to him being his Prince and Maister, that hée spared not to cut his owne nose and eares, and to mangle and disgrace all his face to bring <hi>Babylon</hi> into his subiection. And <hi>Xerxes</hi> his sonne following therein his fathers good inclination, was not in that respect much inferiour to him: for in that great &amp; huge armie which he led into <hi>Grecia,</hi> hée had with him one <hi>Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rathus,</hi> who franckly and boldely did admonishe and reprooue him always of his disorders.<note place="margin">Philosophers gouerners of Princes.</note>
      <hi>Creses</hi> vsed the councel of <hi>Solon, Calisthenes</hi> the scholler of <hi>Aristotle</hi> shewed the way to <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander, Dyon</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> to <hi>Dionise</hi> of <hi>Syracusa.</hi> And therefore S. Hierome exhorteth al Princes, that when they find a wise and faythful man, they should kéepe him as their own hearts, For the comfort of this our miserable life (sayth hée) is to haue one to whom wée may commit our selues to open our mindes and to communicate our affaires in secrete, and vpon whome wée may repose and assure our selues in aduersitie, and to bée vnto vs as a firme rock in all troubles, and a reliefe among so many miseries and calamities with the which this oure care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full life is continually besieged. I haue bene the more willing
<pb n="9" facs="11"/> to bring forth these examples, bycause there bée some, whose eares bée so deintie that they cannot abide that any man (tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh it bée with modestie) shall reproue the euilles wherwith they are infected: but howe would they then suffer the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the scoffes, the bitter tauntes and sharpe dealings euen to the quicke, of the aunciente Comedies, as well in Gréeke as in Latine, that were made for the better destroying and pulling vppe by the rootes the wickednesse that did raigne in those dayes there.<note place="margin">Ieremie. 1. Esaie. 58.</note> And the Lorde God did not commaunde the Prophete that hée should onely plant and builde, but that hée shoulde first pull vp by the rootes and make all ruine, that hée might the better plant and builde afterwardes: and that hée shoulde crie out with a loude voice like a Trumpet to the people, not to pronounce or set forth their glorie, but their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and tel the house of Iacob their offences. In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Lorde our Sauiour Iesus Christ sayd vnto his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, speake openly that whiche I tell you in secrete, and preach vpon the toppes of the houses that I haue sayd in your eares.<note place="margin">The trueth ought freely with al liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly.</note> And the Lorde sayde also to Ezechiell that hée had gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his seruauntes a foreheade of Brasse and of harde stone, that they shoulde no more feare to tell the people their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, than they haue bene ashamed to offende, therefore sayde hée, go and speake to them, and say those things which I cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde thée: (who I knowe will not regarde thy woordes) yet I wil neuerthelesse thou shalt speak to them.<note place="margin">Ezechiel.</note> And to such manner of men as will not bée rebuked of their wickednesse openly, there is no medicine more méete for their dyseases,<note place="margin">A medicine for such as do offende, and wil not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly.</note> than the continuall reading of Bookes, which do the office of Iudges and refourmers, and giue them knoweledge of their offences. And further if wée mark wel, there are many other things that do sufficientely reproue and correcte vs of our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, for all our workes and actions serue as wytnesses of the same in our own consciences: for there is no man so fond or so farre out of his common sense, but alwayes knoweth whether hée doe well or euill: For as Chrysostome sayeth
<pb n="10" facs="12"/> wisely,<note place="margin">Tom. 6. Ho. 15 vpon .5. Luke.</note> that when a man hath committed any notable crime it is most certayne that hée tasteth his condemnation in hys owne conscience, and immediately after the offence done hée hath his conscience for an accuser, for witnesse, for iudge, and for an executer,<note place="margin">A maruelous puissaunce of the remorse of conscience</note> which doth strike such remorse into his heart and bite him so rigorously, that shee surmounteth the presence of a thousande witnesses: shée toucheth him so néere, shée vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and tormenteth him so cruelly, that if all the Aungels in heauen and all the men in the worlde shoulde persuade hym of any thing hée doth wickedly, to bée good &amp; iust, yet he could not satisfie himselfe, nor put from him the iudgement of hys own conscience: which is wel proued by that which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Deuteronomie,<note place="margin">Deuterono. 28.</note> that euell men do tremble and quake at the fall of the leafe of a trée, and that they are always euen as though their liues hung vpon a thréed. Wherfore the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Esay did not wryte without cause,<note place="margin">Wicked men be vexte and troubled as the waues of the Seas.</note> howe that euell men bée as the boyling of the seas, which can not bee pacified: as wée haue many examples therof in sundrie places of the scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and specially by <hi>Iudas</hi> and <hi>Caine,</hi> who féeling such an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish and troubles in their sprites, thought that their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were greater than the mercie of God. Wée haue the like examples in our prophane hystories of that cruell <hi>Nero,</hi> who after hee had killed his owne moother,<note place="margin">Nero &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula tormē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the night w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>th passions.</note> was reprooued and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended for his offences in his sléepe (as hée confessed hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe) for hee sayde hee had a vision of his moother, which did so trouble him, that often times hée was vexed and tormented with extreame furies, as though hée had beene burning wyth flaming Toarches. <hi>Caius Caesar,</hi> surnamed <hi>Caligula,</hi> was troubled in the night in his sléepe, and neuer coulde take hys rest quietly, but with terror and feare, was vexed and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with many passions and visions in his dreames (euen the very giltinesse of conscience for the life passed) the which would not suffer him to take rest.<note place="margin">God causeth euen the very reprobate too taste of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Iudgementes</note> And this violence of mans conscience procéedeth from God, which maketh his enimies so to féele his wrath and iudgement, that they can not beare
<pb n="11" facs="12"/> it quietly, but are constrayned to condemne themselues. And this is it that S. Iohn doth manifeste vnto vs, saying,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> if our heartes condemne vs, God is greater than our heartes: yea, and if there should wante sufficiente examples for these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the sacred Scriptures and prophane Authors, yet wée haue witnesse thereof by nature so well grauen and printed in our heartes,<note place="margin">The worm of the consciēce of the wicked neuer ceaseth gnawing and byting. <hi>Esay. 66.</hi>
      </note> that euen the same did constrayne the ancient Poets to inuent certaine torments and furies that should bee as reuengements and punnishments for our sinnes and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse: which in deede is nothing else but euen the tormē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and vexations of euell consciences This is the worme whereof Esay the Prophet speaketh, which neuer dieth, but gnaweth &amp; eateth without al mesure. And the remembrance of these mischeuous and wicked doings (as <hi>Cicero</hi> wryteth) bée as flames and toarches which burne and terrifie continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally our heartes,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Epicurus</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of the Athiests.</note> as is testified by <hi>Epicurus</hi> that great Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of the <hi>Epicurians</hi> (with whome all the worlde is infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) who althoughe hée neuer thought that there was eyther God, Diuell, Paradise, or Hell, yet alwayes hee doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse (as <hi>Seneca</hi> sayth) that the greatest paine of them that do sinne, is, that they haue sinned:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Epicurus</hi> cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strayned too confesse the remorse of conscience.</note> for the paine of sinne is the very sinne it selfe.</p>
   <p>But nowe to retourne to our first purpose, it is necessarie (Isay) following the councell of <hi>Demetrius,</hi> for all Kings, Princes, and other great Rulers, to haue refuge to Bookes which do contayne aswell instructions for their manners, as the order and dyscourse of their liues.<note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the woorke</note> Let no man therefore bée gréeued if hée féele him selfe a little touched or condemned in them, in some things, for that kinde of aduertisemente is not particular, but generall, as that is when any man doeth preach the word of God in any publike place, who searcheth and examineth gently all mens manners, and makes plaine their offences in generall, as Iesus Christ himselfe in many places of the Scriptures doth rebuke the people, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn their offences without touching any man particularly:
<pb n="12" facs="13"/> and yet for all this there can bée nothing so well and orderly sette foorth, whereof there wyll not bée made a peruerse and naughtie interpretation (if the Iudge bee wicked) nor anie thing so commendable or prayse worthy, which shall not bée brought into suspition or doubt by the malicious and corrupt iudgement of man. And thus much I say, bycause I woulde meete with certaine backbyters and slaunderers, that thinke I haue brought this woorke into lighte to deface or stayne the honour of those that are liuing, which is far from my intent, being for a long time conuersant in reading as well the holie Scriptures, as other prophane Authoures, wherein I haue learned in what regarde and reuerence we ought to haue our Superiours and Gouernours,<note place="margin">The reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence due too Superiours.</note> and howe that the kingdome of Heauen is shut from those that speake euell, and that there ought not to bée any backebyters or curssed speakers among the people,<note place="margin">Leuit. 19. Ecclesiast. 18.</note> for both be accursed of God, bycause they trouble those that bée in peace. To the ende therefore, I say, too shut vp the mouthes of such foolish babblers, and to take away the occasion of euell iudgement from those that followe the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Spiders, conuerting into poyson all that euer they doe touch, and as the Vipers infect al those with poyson that they may come vnto: I most certainely assure them I doe not by this treatise intende to hurte any liuing, no more than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the deade that repose themselues in the earth, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therin the precepte that Moses hath giuen vs in Exodus,<note place="margin">Exodus. 22.</note> not to backebite the Iudges, nor to speake euell of the Prince that gouerneth the people.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> Which also S. Peter doth confirm when hée sayth wée ought to giue them honor and reuerence. But if any man bée curious too know why I do make menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on héere in this booke of <hi>Nero, Roboam, Sardanapalus,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther suche like (the memorie of whome a man can not once name without note of infamie, bicause their liues haue bene so far out of order, bloudie and cruell, that the vertuous eares of those that shal heare them named can not but bée offended) I answere them that I will not, nor I do not intende by this
<pb n="13" facs="13"/> my discourse to make any comparison with oures and them, nor do not think neither that there is any cōformitie betwéen them: but this is the ende, that reading the Heroical vertues and excellent commendations of an infinit number of Kings, Princes and Lordes which haue bene before them, they shal be pricked and stirred vp by the brightnesse of their glorie, to make immortall and euerlasting their own renoumes, in fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing such good acts and doings as they haue done: and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to the contrary,<note place="margin">Jn reading the actes of the wicked, men are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</note> when they shal roade the discommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and euell reportes of many Tyrants that haue infected the earth, and haue giuen occasion of muche labour too those that write Hystories (to describe their euell and wicked li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues) it shall serue them as a glasse and a perpetuall example to guide their actions, and refourme the state of their liues, to the ende that in the worlde to come, their posteritie doe not the like to them. And to lette you knowe that these are not my woordes onely, hearken to the Lordes sayings (wrytten by the handes of the greate Secretarie Saincte Luke) who when hée will induce vs too humilitie,<note place="margin">Luke 10.</note> hée setteth before vs an example, howe Sathan fell from heauen as fire and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and all to the ende wée shoulde humble oure selues, and that wée should not thinke to bée exalted by those wayes and meanes whereby others are thruste downe. And when hée will exhorte vs to flée from euell and wickednesse, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seuer in good workes and well doings, hée recommendeth to our remembraunce the wife of <hi>Lot.</hi> And further, if thou doest marke well the order of the holie Hystories, thou shalt finde that after they haue rehearsed the vertuous acts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie good and holie men, they mingle and ioyne with thesame the doings of the euell and wicked men, to the intent the one may prouoke and carrie vs awaye by their good examples too all well doings, and the others by their euell actes and wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked demeaners might make vs forbeare to folowe their mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chéefe and wyckednesse.</p>
   <pb n="14" facs="14"/>
   <p>And nowe to make an ende of this my Prologue, I beséeche thee gentle Reader to construe wel and faythfully of this my labour and trauayle, according to my meaning: and so doing thou shalt giue me occasion hereafter to sette foorth one other woorke of mine owne inuention, entreating of the Original and beginning of Noblenesse: which, for that I haue consumed the most parte of my lyfe in the studie as well of the Gréeke as Latine ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, I will set forth the same in Latine, to the ende I may in something gratifie those that professe good Letters.</p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>