<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE, Sr. IOHN LEMMON Knight, Lord Maior of the most famous City of London, and to the Right Worshipfull Sr. William Crauen Knight, Alderman of London, and President of Christs Hospitall, with the Worshipfull Mr. Richard Heath TREASVRER, together with all the Right Worshipfull and Worshipfull Gouernours thereof, IOHN VICARS wisheth all externall happinesse, and internall peace of conscience in this life, and eternall be∣atitude in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Vicars, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104005_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03116</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13247</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104005</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NOVRABLE, Sr. IOHN LEMMON Knight, Lord Maior of the most famous City of London, and to the Right Worshipfull Sr. William Crauen Knight, Alderman of London, and President of Christs Hospitall, with the Worshipfull Mr. Richard Heath TREASVRER, together with all the Right Worshipfull and Worshipfull Gouernours thereof, IOHN VICARS wisheth all externall happinesse, and internall peace of conscience in this life, and eternall be∣atitude in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Vicars, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mischeefes mysterie: or, Treasons master-peece, the Powder-plot : Inuented by hellish malice, preuented by heauenly mercy: truely related. And from the Latine of the learned and reuerend Doctour Herring translated, and very much dilated. By Iohn Vicars</title>
                 <author>Herring, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Weaver (Wever), Edmund</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 109, that is 104, 115-121, 1 page, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. IOHN LEMMON</hi> Knight, Lord Maior of the most famous City of <hi>London, and to the Right Worshipfull S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>.</hi> William Crauen Knight, <hi>Alderman of London, and President of</hi> Christs Hospitall, <hi>with the Worshipfull M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>.</hi> Richard Heath <hi>TREASVRER, together with all the Right Worshipfull and Worshipfull Gouernours thereof, IOHN VICARS wisheth all</hi> externall <hi>happinesse, and</hi> internall <hi>peace of conscience in this life, and</hi> eternall <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitude in the life to come.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S diuers causes (Right Honourable, Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, &amp; my most worthy Patrones) do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce diuers effects: so diuers motiues do necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily incite &amp; stimulate all men to diuers actions &amp; inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Now therfore there be 3. especiall motiues which do at this time induce, nay compell mee to dedicate these my poore Labours rather to your Honour and Worships, then to any others, to whom indeed the History it selfe might seeme more peculiarly to appertaine. First, because as this deluge of destruction intended by the barbarous butchers of <hi>Rome,</hi> had beene (indeed <hi>Catholike</hi> and) vniuersall to the whole <hi>kingdom:</hi> So your <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Worships</hi> being the high-topt <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> chiefe <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates</hi> of this famous <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> especially beeing pious professors of <hi>Christs</hi> verity, should also haue had no small part, yea too too great and insupportable a portion
<pb facs="3"/>
and ponderous burthen of sorrow and lamentation in this vnparaleld proiect of the <hi>Pouder-treason.</hi> The second Motiue is that since I amongest many hundred poore <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes</hi> fostered in that blessed house of Piety, Pitty, and Charity, that Sanctuary of your Cities safeguard, yea that <hi>Blocke-house</hi> of defence (as so I may terme it) against Heauens iustly deserued iudgements, which but for the due and daily prayers elsewhere, and thence forcibly and (no doubt) effectually ascending, we might expect to fall vpon vs: I meane <hi>Christs Hospitall</hi> whereof your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> and <hi>Worships</hi> are principall <hi>Patrones,</hi> and most godly <hi>Gouernours, Et ô faelicia saecula, quae vos tales genuere Parentes.</hi> I, I say (as to Gods glory, your endles credit, and my no lesse comfort, I doe most thankefully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and ingenuously confesse) hauing suckt from the brests of your <hi>Charity, etiam ab origine prima,</hi> euen from mine infancy, the sweet milke of comfortable educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and pious institution, must thereby iustly also confesse that whatsoeuer is mine, is most properly yours, as being deriued from the ouer-flowing streames and radiant Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beames of your bounty and benignity to mee exhibited. Therefore as <hi>acceptam refero</hi> is the <hi>Moones</hi> motto: so <hi>Quod recepi retribui,</hi> must with no lesse reciprocall due be mine: <hi>At, at, ô si, dignas persoluere grates opis es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set meae,</hi> but alas, it is not (ô would to God it were) in my power condignely to remunerate your deserued merites. The third and last motiue or motion to this my dedication is, that since this translated <hi>Poeme</hi> is my first <hi>Essay</hi> and <hi>assay</hi> of what my weak faculty could effect, being indeed better meant then made, and finished with much defect &amp; feeblenesse, defect I say of Rhetoricall flourishes, and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes, in regard I haue beene but a meane proficient, if not a meere Trewant in the Schoole of the <hi>Muses,</hi> hauing e're cropt few or none of those odoriferous fragrant flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb facs="3"/>
which grow vpon, and most gorgeously doe garnish the pleasant banks of <hi>Parnassus,</hi> nor scarcely euer sipt of the aurifluous and mellifluous streames of <hi>Vrania's</hi> learned fountaine, hauing beene (oh too too soone) wained from the brests of my sacred <hi>Mother</hi> the most famous Vniuersity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and therefore like a weakling so feebly walking, as scarce able to goe alone without your <hi>Honourable</hi> and <hi>Worshipfull</hi> protection, yet in regard it is the <hi>Primitiae</hi> of that meane <hi>Talent</hi> which the <hi>Lord</hi> by you his most blessed instruments hath lent vnto mee, which (whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it is, as indeede it is but small) rather then I would hide it in the ground of ingratitude, I haue beene bould, embouldned by these considerations, but especially by the experimentall proofe of your <hi>Lordships</hi> and <hi>Worships</hi> wonted fauours, and most courteous dispositions in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility to offer the same to your <hi>Honours</hi> and <hi>Worships</hi> pious <hi>Patronage</hi> and pervse, most submissely intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting you <hi>(Right Honourable, Right Worshipfull,</hi> and my most worthy <hi>Mecaenaces)</hi> that as, <hi>ex paruis magna, ex vngue Leonem, &amp; ex pede Herculem:</hi> A man may see day light through a small creuice: so you would bee pleased fauourably to accept this small present as a pledge of mine obliged duty, and as a <hi>Symbole</hi> of my seruice, which is, and euer shall be wholly at your <hi>Lordships</hi> and <hi>Worships</hi> command. Which your courteous acceptation I desire, not so much for mine owne sake, as for the <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story</hi> it selfe, and that not so much for the manner as the matter, <hi>et res ipsa loquatur,</hi> let the matter it selfe speake for it selfe, <hi>num ruminari &amp; recordari cordibus piorū omniū per vniuersam Britannie regionem,</hi> Whether all true hearted English protestants haue not iust cause to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate &amp; record to all succeeding ages, the memory of this matchles Machination, &amp; plotted <hi>Pouder-treason,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of if I should heere enter into a copious discourse, it would
<pb facs="4"/>
administer such an <hi>Ocean</hi> of ouerflowing turbulent waues of destruction, such a world of wonder and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red accidents, and such a map of misery and mischiefe, yea such an endlesse boundlesse extent of greeuous aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, that I might with the sorrowfull <hi>Troian Prince, Infandos renouare dolores, &amp; totos vos in lachrymas resoluere,</hi> Tell you such a wofull tale as might with the <hi>Prophet Ieremy</hi> turne your heads into fountaines of teares: for <hi>Quis talia fando (nisi Papista crudelis) tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peret a lachrymis,</hi> none doubtlesse but the <hi>Pharaonicall</hi> hard-hearted <hi>Papist</hi> could choose but be exceedingly sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull thereat; yea and heereby I might rather write a large Volume, than a short <hi>Epistle,</hi> for my part I cannot but <hi>horrescere referens,</hi> euen tremble at the relation thereof. But not to wrong your Lordships and Worships patience with too much prolixity in this Epistle, lest there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I seem to set a great paire of Gates to a little City, I will conclude of it, as a certaine graue <hi>Senator</hi> did of a former ancient Treason, farre inferiour to this, <hi>Repertum esse facinus, quod nec Poetae fingere, nec Histrio sonare, nec mimus imitari poterit,</hi> that by Heauens prouidence such a trecherous villany is discouered, as neuer any <hi>Poet</hi> could faine the like, no <hi>Stage-player</hi> euer Act the like, nor <hi>Mimus</hi> euer imitate the like, which since it is so dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to describe, I will heerein imitate, though my selfe most vnskilfull, the skilfull Painter <hi>Timanthes</hi> of whom it is recorded, that being to describe and paint out the wofull Tragedy of <hi>Iphigema</hi> sacrificed to <hi>Diana,</hi> that when he was to portray &amp; set out her Father <hi>Agamem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> most compassionate passion, and wofull countenance for her, that he confessing his Art insufficient to set him out deseruedly in his liuely lamentation, was faine to paint a vaile couering <hi>Agamemnons</hi> face, that so hee might leaue the extremity of his sorrow to the iudgement and
<pb facs="4"/>
consideration of the behoulders: So I, vnskilfull I, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing my selfe (vnles I had the faculty of <hi>Maro</hi> or <hi>Meo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides)</hi> altogether vnable with hart or hand, with voice or vers to discouer the atrocrity &amp; ineffable horror of this <hi>Romish</hi> barbarity, yea more than Scythian, Thracian in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity; will couer the description therof with the vaile of <hi>Silence,</hi> and leaue it to the consideration of all that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer knew or heard of the endlesse extent thereof: Most humbly desiring your <hi>Lordship</hi> and <hi>Worships</hi> with wonted protecting paternall fauour and courteous disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to vouchsafe your gentle acceptance of this plaine <hi>Poeme,</hi> the poore mite which my thankefull heart and dutifull hand, doe with all obliged gratitude offer vnto you, most submissiuely commending and committing the same to your worthy name &amp; <hi>Patronage,</hi> your examples of Piety and charity, to the memory and imitation of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity, and your selues and soules to Gods all-sauing Grace, and all-sufficient Tuition in this life, neuer ceasing to pray for the blessing of <hi>Zaccheus</hi> on you and yours, euen eternall saluation in the life to come; which he grant that hath with the high price of his most precious bloud redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs, <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> the righteous, Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships and Worships most obsequious daily Orator duely and dutifully prest in all seruice to bee commanded: IOHN VICARS.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>