<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE CHRISTI∣AN
READER, GRACE,
MERCIE AND PEACE BE
multiplied in Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>Holland, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104153_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03468</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13590</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104153</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE CHRISTI∣AN
READER, GRACE,
MERCIE AND PEACE BE
multiplied in Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>Holland, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A treatise against vvitchcraft: or A dialogue, wherein the greatest doubts concerning that sinne, are briefly answered : a Sathanicall operation in the witchcraft of all times is truly prooued: the moste precious preseruatiues against such euils are shewed: very needful t be knowen of all men, but chiefly of the masters and fathers of families, that they may learn the best meanes to purge their houses of all vnclean spirits, and wisely to auoide the dreadfull impieties and greate daungers which come by such abhominations. Hereunto is also added a short discourse, containing the most certen meanes ordained of God, to discouer, expell, and to confound all the Sathanicall inuentions of witchcraft and sorcerie</title>
                 <author>Holland, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legat (Legate, Legatt), John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64, 24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE CHRISTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AN
READER, GRACE,
MERCIE AND PEACE BE
multiplied in Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE holy Apostle labouring<note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> to set foorth the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
maiestie and powerfull might of the ministerie
of the Gospel, sheweth how that a man must be,<note place="margin">Theoplilact.</note> as
it were conquered thereby, before he doe yeelde sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere
and sound obedience vnto Christ. And certen
it is, that before men be brought downe to that sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection,
they fall often into daungerous errours in
minde, and sundrie fearefull sinnes in life. In this question of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft,
some haue preferred the wicked folly of mā, before the holy wisdom
of God, &amp; would haue vs to credit their owne practise,<note place="margin">Discouery. 16. book. p. 478.</note> the <hi>knowledge
also and experience of Cornelius Agrippa, Iohn Wyerus, Nero, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian
Apostata, and such like:</hi> Their experience, to say no more, was
vnsufficient, most wicked and detestable. Let vs then humble our selues
before the wisdome of God, and see what direction wee haue in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie
by the holy Scripture. First for the being of this abhomination,
the holy word of god most clearely cōfirmeth it. For if there were no such
sinne, wherefore then are there so many kindes named and distinguished,
<hi>Deut. 18. 10, 11. Mecasephim, kozemim, &amp;c.</hi> Al which,<note place="margin">Com in Gal.</note>
      <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 20.
the Apostle comprehendeth (as <hi>Ierome</hi> saith) in that one word, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>,
<hi>Witchcraft?</hi> Secondly, wherfore haue we so many examples of the
practitioners of this profession, pointed at so often vnto vs? as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunters
<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 17.</note> of Egypt, the Witch of<note n="c" place="margin">Sam. 28.</note> Endor, the witches of<note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 2.</note> Persia, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Magus<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 8.</note> of Samaria, Elymas<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 13. 6.</note> the sorcerer at Paphus, the Pytho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 16. 16. Dialog. c. 2. P. 30.</note>
at Philippi? &amp;c. Thirdly, what meaneth the Lord to geue such
lawes against this sinne, as may be seene. <hi>Exod. 22. 18. Lev. 20. 27.
Deut.</hi> 18, 10, 11. For this is Maxime in Law, as <hi>Danaeus</hi> saith, and
the lawyers graunt it, <hi>De ijs rebus quae non sunt, leges non promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur,
There are no lawes made of things which haue no being:</hi>
If this be true of the lawes of men, how much more of the blessed Lawes
of God, wherein we must not imagine a want or superfluitie: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Hemingius</hi> saith,<note place="margin">De superstios. magic.</note>
      <hi>Sapientissimus Deus non potest leges ferre,
de rebus quae vel non sunt, vel esse non possunt: The moste wise
God can not geue lawes of things which haue no beeing, or can
haue no beeing.</hi> VVherefore I conclude that witchcraft is a sinne, &amp;
a filthie worke of the flesh, (as <hi>Paul</hi> speaketh) and therefore an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
worke of the devill, as <hi>Iohn</hi>
      <note n="b" place="margin">Iohn. 3. 8.</note> saith, and consequently, not so lightly
(as it is made of some) to be regarded. The adversaries here are glad to
betake the selues to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> first refuge:<note place="margin">Discov. p. 472.</note>
      <hi>Witchcraft is but coozening or
poisening arte, practised by humane industrie, whereunto Sathan
communicates no reall conference, or communication.</hi> What may
be said out of the booke of God, against this bold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>? what were
Pharaos coniurers in the court of Egipt, &amp; Nebuchadue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> wise men
in Babylon, but coozeners and porseners? poiseners of all others haue no
place nor free accesse vnto princes, and coozeners are most vnfit to be
their counsellers, so as all those Egiptian and Babilonian witches were,
as lerome writeth: <hi>Habuisse Babylonem omnem{que} Chaldaeam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantatorum,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ierom. Com. in Esay. 57.</note>
      <hi>&amp;c. studium, &amp;c. Danielis Prophetae lectio probat
qui ad eorum consilia, cunctareges Babilonios fecisse Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat:
The kings of Babilon, &amp;c. (saith he) did all things after the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise
and councels of there inchanters.</hi> Againe, what was the Pytho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist<note n="i" place="margin">Act. 16. 16.</note>
at Philippi, had not shee a reall conference with Sathan? for she got
her master great aduantage with her continuall practise of divination?
To be short,<note place="margin">Com. in 1. Sam. 28.</note> I can not see but hee that can doe the greater, may doe the
lesse: <hi>Non mirum est</hi> (saith <hi>P. Martyr) si exteriores hominum ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los
perstringat, cum antea occupauit oculos mentis. It is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile,
that he hold fast shut the eyes of the body, which so blindeth
the eyes of the minde.</hi> He that can worke so mightely by suggestion<note n="k" place="margin">1. King. 22. 22. Eph. 2. 2.</note> in
the children of disobedience, may also haue both a real possession of thē, &amp;
conference with thē.<note place="margin">Angelus pol. pan. epist. p. 473.</note> Lastly, wee must not so fondly confound diabolicall
&amp; naturall magicke, which so many learned men in al ages, haue cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
distinguished.<note place="margin">Ioh. Bap. Nea. ma. 1. l. 11. c. 1. Caelius Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignius. l. 9. c. 23. lectionum antiquarum. Discov. p. 317.</note> This shift beeing thus vncouered, they shelter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
vnder a second refuge, which is this: <hi>The witches of our time
can work at no hand, so as the witches mentioned in the Scripture
haue done.</hi> Against this conclusion, we may reason on this manner. If
our Witches, Coniurers, &amp;c. can not work the like as Iannes &amp; Iambres
did, the witch of Endor, &amp;c. the defect must be eyther in Sathan, or the
witch, or both: first for Sathan,<note place="margin">160. 162. 163.</note> bee wants at this day, neither will nor
<pb facs="4"/>
might, to doe the like. First, no will, for he see<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> his kingdome will not last
long, and therefore now towards the end of the world, he is, and will be
more and more enuious, and deceitfull, working all the wonders that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
he can, to blinde infidels, 2. <hi>Thes.</hi> 2. 9. 10. and to deceiue if it were
possible, the very elect, us our Sauiour hath forewarned vs. Secondly, no
strength: he is elder indeede but not weaker. The God,<note n="l" place="margin">Eph. 6. 12, 13.</note> the princes, and
gouernours of this world, with whome we wrestle, wax not weaker as we
doe, nor the red dragon wil<note n="m" place="margin">Rev. 12. 17.</note> not cease to make warre with the Saints, as
long as the world endureth. Againe, he is rather more wise in experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
and knowledge of all naturall causes, and therefore more readie in
his artes then euer he hath beene. And wherefore then Sathan for his
part, will not, or can not practise those former artes, it is impossible to be
prooued, and doe not we know, that Sathan hath multiplied, rather then
shortened the number of his artes? for we read and vnderstand, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
and since the Gospel was published, he hath had great varietie in
all ages, of false artes for the practises of his sciences.<note place="margin">See Bodin. de Daemonoani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia. l. 2. c. 1. 2. Cicero de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinat. lib. 1.</note> Secondly, for
his copartner the witch, Man or Woman, I would learne what wantes
they haue at this day, more then in former times, that by Sathans
helpe, they can not produce the like lying woonders. I am sure the
wicked also in the worlde, and the reprobates towardes the ende, waxe
worse and worse, and therefore in any wise ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> iudgement, are
more fitte for this sinne, for the more vncleane.<note n="n" place="margin">Matth. 12. 43. Discov. 13. book. p. 305. p. 302.</note> a man is, the more apt
is he for Sathans seruice. <hi>But they obiect, they can not haue at this
day, such knowledge in naturall causes as Iannes and Iambres
had, &amp;c.</hi> I answer, that Sathan as he regardes not characters, figures,
wordes, periapts, &amp;c. so doeth hee not a mans knowledge, to make
him his vassale to worke his woonders, vnlesse it be for this end, to vaile
and couer his delusions, as sundrie Sathanicall Astrologers in Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
and Egipt haue done. And in very truth there are in this age, as
wise in knowledge of all tongues, Philosophie, liberall artes, &amp;c. (as the
learned know) since the Gospell was preached, as euer was in any age
in Christendome. Wherefore if there was by meanes of naturall
knowledge, and humane industrie, a Sathanicall operation in witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft
in elder times, I say, there may be the like at this day, and vnto the
worldes end. The last, and most miserable refuge is this.<note place="margin">Disco. epist. to the Reader.</note>
      <hi>Our witches,
strigae, lamiae, our witches are not once mētioned in Scripture: our
<pb facs="5"/>
old woman, &amp;c. you shall not reade in the Bible of any such Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi>
      <note place="margin">P. 100.</note>
This if they could haue graunted, that God worde might not
fight against them, they know then, they might easilie triumph, for the
weapons of God are so mightie, to cast downe these holdes, that no arte
nor power of Sathan, or inuention of man, may withstand thē: but where
they strike, downe must all high proude things, the proud reason of man,
Sathan<note n="q" place="margin">2. Cor. 10. 5, 6. 2. 3. Law.</note> himselfe and al his kingdome. Albeit the Scripture giueth vs
no such historicall relations of the witches of our time: yet are they
mentioned there both in generall and speciall manner: in general, where
all the sinnes of idolatrie<note n="r" place="margin">Es. 47. 2. &amp; 21. 6. &amp; 23. 24.</note> and blasphemie are condemned; in speciall,
where the like sinnes are named. <hi>M. Cicero</hi> disputeth in his booke of
Divination, of the beeing of the old Auguries and magicall divinations
of his time: where after he hath distinguished them into two kindes: na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall,
and artificiall: (Vnto the naturall, belong all those divinations
which we may call meere diabolicall, as coniurations, and al the practise
of Pythonistes, which haue an expresse league and confederacie with
Sathan: vnto the artificiall appertaine all those artes, which men (saith
hee) haue learned by long obseruation, Astrologie, Palmistrie, and such
like: these we say, are mixt diabolicall, and belong vnto the secret coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
and confederacie, which Sathan hath with witches.) In the ende
he concludeth on this manner: <hi>Quid est igitur cur dubitandum sit,</hi>
      <note place="margin">De Divin. L. 1.</note>
      <hi>quin sint ea quae disputaui verissima, si ratio mecum facit, si even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,
si populi, si nationes, si graeci, si barbari, si maiores etiam nostri, si
deni{que} hoc semperita putatum est, si summi philosophi, si poetae, si
sapientissimi viri, qui res publicas constituerunt, qui vrbes condide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt?
an dum bestiae loquantur expectamus, hominum consentiente
authoritate contenti non sumus?</hi> If this Heathen could confirme by
such reasons this conclusion, how much more boldly may wee doe the
same, hauing not onely all these his arguments with vs: but also the
heauenly Oracles of God, the light, the lawes, the examples, and the
iudgements in Gods worde, denounced against these sinnes, which the
Scripture hath recorded for our instruction. Wherefore I conclude with
Master <hi>Calvine, Certè sacrilega esset Audacia negare vnquam in
vsu fuisse artes magicas,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Com. in Deut. 18.</note>
      <hi>quia hoc modo Deus incogitantiae argue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur,
ac silegem tulisset de rebus quae nullae sunt. Surely it were
gracelesse boldnes, to denie that the artes of magicke haue euer
beene practised, for so God might be argued to want iudgement,
as if he had giuen a Law of things which haue no beeing.</hi> Nowe
<pb facs="5"/>
to be short, concerning this treatise which here I offer thee (good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)
albeit I cannot teach thee, as I would, to discouer and to auoide the
Sathanicall delusions of witchcraft: so variable, so straunge, and so se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
are Sathans practises: yet that good which I purposed, I haue, I
trust, in some part performed. Whatsoeuer I haue written, in all hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
submission, I offer it to the Censure and iudgement of all the godly
learned in the Church of God. I was the more bolde to publish this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course,
for that but few haue written to any purpose any thing, which
may giue light in this argument, in the english tongue, master <hi>George
Gifford</hi> onely excepted vnto whom we are much bound in the Lorde.
An other cause which mooued me is the continuall trafficke and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket
which the rude people haue with witches. For like as the old heathen
(as Tulli saieth) de reb. maiorib, semper aut delphis oraculum,<note place="margin">De Divinat. Lib. 1.</note>
      <hi>aut ab Hammone, aut à Dodona petebant,</hi> that is, <hi>in their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
affaires sought alwaies after the master witches:</hi> and in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
affaires hid their common auguries: so likewise our blockish Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,
they haue their common base witches, and their master coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,
vnto whom they ride and goe in all their neede, some twentie, some
thirtie, some fortie miles, and what is moste lamentable, such is their
brutish ignorance, they thinke it not vnlawfull for them so to doe.
Wherefore I doe here also humbly request all those, whome God hath
blessed with knowledge and giftes to discerne, in any measure these hid
and horrible abhominations, that they would with all their might helpe
to vncouer them. The ministers of Christ must both in doctrine and
conuersation oppose themselues vnto the ministers of Antichrist. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
doctrine of the Gospell, which we professe, is flat contrarie (we knovv)
vnto all the principles of poperie: so let our conuersation also be vnto
the practise of all the Romish prelates. The monkes, the friers, and all
of the shauen ministerie, were not in any account for learning, which
made not an open profession of these sciences: and of the Popes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
sundry of them attained their popedome by these holy meanes: as
Sylvester the 2. Benedictus the 8. Geegorie the seuenth. Iohn. 20. 21.<note place="margin">Act. &amp; m. p. 167.</note>
Alexander the 6. if we may credit their ovvne Platina and others.
Our enimies then worshipping the beast and his image and bearing
these brandes of sorcery,<note n="s" place="margin">Rev. 21. 8.</note> vvitchcraft, idolatrie, and all impietie in
their handes and foreheads: let vs with all might avoide them, for
<pb facs="6"/>
without repentance, (the scripture hath forewarned) <hi>they shall drink
of the wine of the wrath of God, which is poured into the
cuppe of his wrath, and shall bee tormented in fire
and brim stone which is the second death.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
what I haue written (good reader) or
of thy curtesie giue it free passage
vnto others.</p>
   <closer>FAREWEL.
<signed>Thine in Christ Iesus.
<hi>HENRY HOLLAND.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>