<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VIRTVOVS AND WOR∣thily honoured Gentleman RI∣CHARD HVBERT, Esquire.</title>
           <author>Chapman, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104934_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18414</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4979</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104934</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VIRTVOVS AND WOR∣thily honoured Gentleman RI∣CHARD HVBERT, Esquire.</title>
                 <author>Chapman, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A iustification of a strange action of Nero; in burying with a solemne funerall, one of the cast hayres of his mistresse Poppæa. Also a iust reproofe of a Romane smell-feast, being the fifth satyre of Iuuenall. Translated by George Chapman</title>
                 <author>Chapman, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VIRTVOVS AND WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily honoured Gentleman RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARD HVBERT, Esquire.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, Greate workes get little regard; little and light are most affected with height: <hi>Omne le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vesursum; grave deor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum,</hi> you know; For which, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Custome or Fashion, is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nature, and that it is now the fashion to iustifie Strange Actions; I (vtterly against mine owne fashion) followed the vulgar, and assaid what
<pb facs="3"/>
might bee said, for iustification of a Strange Action of <hi>Nero</hi>; in bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a solemne Funerall one of the cast hayres of his Mistresse <hi>Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pea.</hi> And not to make little labours altogether vnworthy the sight of the great; I say with the great defender of little labours, <hi>In tenui labor est, at te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuis non gloria.</hi> Howsoeuer; As Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men seeing the aproches of Whales cast out empty vessells, to serue their harmeful pleasures, and diuert them from euerting their maine aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; (for in the vast and immane power of any thing, no thing is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguisht; great and precious things, basest and vilest serue alike their wild and vnwildy swinges) so my selfe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing yet once more some worthier worke then this Oration, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Translation, to passe this sea of
<pb facs="3"/>
the land; expose to the land and vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Leuiathan, these slight aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The rather, because the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation containing in two or three in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, a preparation to the iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of my ensuing intended Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slations, lest some should account them, as they haue my former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersions in some places; licenses, bold ones, and utterly redundant. Though your iudiciall selfe (as I haue heard) hath taken those liberall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundances, rather as the necessary o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowings of <hi>Nilus</hi>; then rude or harmefull torrents swolne with head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strong showers. To whose iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and merit, submits these and all his other seruices,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>GEORGE CHAPMAN.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>