<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Philosophie of the wise auncient Fathers. A worke first compiled in the Indian tongue, and aftervvardes transfer∣red into diuers and sundrie other lan∣guages: as the Persian, Arabian, Hebrue, Latine, Spanishe, and Italian: and now reduced into our vulgar speeche.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104622_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16131</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3053</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104622</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Philosophie of the wise auncient Fathers. A worke first compiled in the Indian tongue, and aftervvardes transfer∣red into diuers and sundrie other lan∣guages: as the Persian, Arabian, Hebrue, Latine, Spanishe, and Italian: and now reduced into our vulgar speeche.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The morall philosophie of Doni : drawne out of the auncient writers. A worke first compiled in the Indian tongue, and afterwardes reduced into diuers other languages: and now lastly englished out of Italian by Thomas North, brother to the right Honorable Sir Roger North Knight, Lorde North of Kyrtheling</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 111 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>The Philosophie of the wise auncient Fathers. A worke first compiled in the <hi>Indian</hi> tongue, and aftervvardes transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into diuers and sundrie other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages: as the Persian, Arabian, Hebrue, Latine, Spanishe, and Italian: and now reduced into our vulgar speeche.</head>
   <head>The Prologue</head>
   <div type="section">
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His precious Iewell (beloued Reader) was first founde written in the <hi>Indian</hi> tongue, entituled <hi>Morall vvisedome</hi>: and thence conueyed into <hi>Persia,</hi> and was coated wyth their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, naming it with them <hi>The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of good lyfe</hi>: and from the <hi>Persian</hi> spéech a long time after by the auncient Fathers (they knowing the woonderfull doctrine therof) brought into the natyue <hi>Arabian</hi>: &amp; from that translated into <hi>Hebrue</hi> by <hi>Ioel gran Rabi</hi> a Iewe: at length reduced into <hi>Latine</hi>: and passing through many lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages became a Spaniarde, with the tytle of <hi>Exemplario</hi>: and so in time brought to <hi>Venice,</hi> and there put into <hi>Italian</hi> by a company of Gentlemen associated togithers, entituling their Felowship <hi>Academia Peregrina</hi>: and nowe lastly out of <hi>Italian</hi> made vulgar to vs. What high doctrine is conteyned in thys Booke, the diligent and curious searche for the same of so many wise and famous men and of so sundrye nations doth
<pb facs="8"/>
witnesse. If therefore you desire the vnderstanding of Morall wisedome, spirituall doctrine, and infinite instructions and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples for man to liue well: reade I say this golden Volume. Surely reader, this booke shall be a looking glasse for thée, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou shalt most liuely beholde the daylie and present daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and deceytes of mans most miserable lyfe, and the eyes of thy vnderstanding shall be made open to discerne the flatteries of disceytfull men, and the wisedome of this moste guilefull worlde: by meanes whereof yée may easilye blotte out many malignant effects of this (alas) our crooked age. The style is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milier and pleasaunt, and wyll much delight thée. For the first and olde Authors hereof wrote it doubtlesse wyth great iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, trayned thereto with a feruent desire that their doctrine shoulde not onely remayne in perpetuitie for euer, but that it shoulde also be imprinted in the Readers minde, assuring them selues it shoulde profite all, and dislyke none. For it maye in maner be called an artificiall memorie, to benifite themselues at all times and seasons, and in all argumentes, with euerye perticuler thing that these wise and graue men haue inuented, shadowed with tales and parables, and wyth the examples of brute and dumme beastes.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>THE Sages of auncient nations, (expert in all the Sciences) desirous to publishe to those that came after them, their great knowledge and wisedome, euen with a determinate minde and counsell premeditate, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to set foorth a peece of woorke, adapted with diuers similitudes and sundrie comparisons of vnreasonable beasts &amp; birds, by which they might greatly beautifie their doctrine, and this they did for diuers respectes. First, to giue occasion that their wisedome and learning should be knowne to the worlde. Secondly, that men of iudgement and discretion reading the same might reape the benifite of their rules to direct this fraile lyfe. Thirdlye, that hee that vnderstandeth these examples, knowing little, shoulde by them knowe much. And fourthly, and last of all, if he were yong, and had small delight to reade much: yet he may with a short and</hi>
         <pb n="2" facs="8"/>
         <hi>pleasant waye be instructed with these delighting fayninges, and with those similitudes and examples taste the sweetenesse of the woordes, the pleasure of the sentences, accompanied with proper tales: and so (Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader) profite himselfe, and teache others. In this their treatise such wise Fathers haue hidden from vs woonderfull significations. For a treasure vndoubtedly of so high a misterye and doctrine as this is to be more estemed, than all the Iewelles of the worlde. This precious Iemme of knowledge, who so shall lodge it in the secresie of his memorie, shall neuer lose it, but shall rather augment and increase it with age in such sort, that he shall winne a marueylous commoditie to him: and of that plant shall taste the sauorie, pleasant, and profitable fruites, no lesse wonderfull then delectable. To reade such a Booke (worthy Reader) thou must call thy wittes togither, vniting them and thy vnderstanding with the due order of the woorke, to knowe why, and to what purpose the olde prudent Fathers framed it: least thou be lyke to the blinde man, that wanting his sight, taketh vpon him to go ouer Mountaines, Hilles, and Dales, through most daungerous and perillous wayes. He therefore that doth reade, must vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand what he readeth, and why he readeth it: and not to be so desirous to come to the ende, that he marke not the beginning, and forget the sense (full of knowledge) lincked with the middest and end. For he that readeth so, readeth without fruite, and rather troubleth the minde, and wearieth his body than otherwise, not forcing the benifite and knowledge of the truth. Folow therefore these graue preceps and ruled order, and let no vaine thoughts possesse your mindes to withdraw you from reading it. For to finde so riche a treasure, and not to know how to take and laye it vp: is rightly to folow him, that finding a Masse of Golde and Siluer, had not the wyt to take it, and cary it away.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <head>Of a Husbande man, and of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure he founde.</head>
      <p>A Husbandman of <hi>Persia</hi> going one daye to plough his lande, by chaunce stumbled of a marueylous treasure, fyndinge store of pottes of coyne, of Golde, and Siluer:
<pb facs="9"/>
and woondring at hys great fortune, began to think to lode him selfe, and to beare it home. But séeing the summes so great that scant twentie men coulde carie it awaye, it gréeued him much that hée alone coulde not conuey it, and thus hée sayde to himselfe. If I leaue it here, it is in daunger to be taken from
<figure>
</figure>
mée, and to watch it daylie, it woulde to much trouble mée: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, that that I coulde take with me, would doe mée but small pleasure. Well, hap what hap will, I will go fetch company to helpe me home withall, and they shall beare the burden, I will onely pay them, and take mine ease, tush I haue at will to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent them: and thus in one day I shal come home and finde my Cofers filled. With this minde resolued forth he goeth, &amp; calleth men togithers, bringing them with him to this Golden masse of coyne, where he giueth eche man his burden, and byddeth them
<pb n="3" facs="9"/>
hye them to his house. These bearers now departing with their burdens, ouercome with desire of the money, and gréedy of this praie, in steade of going to the house of this foolishe and vnluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie man, they went euery one to his owne house. The husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man after their departure commeth leysurely home wythout any burden, lyke a man of welth, as one that thought himselfe a Lorde at home, wéening to haue founde his richesse there. But when he was entered his house, and hearde nothing of the goodes nor bearers: then all to late hée knew his lack and folly, commending their iudgements that with the burden of theire shoulders had made themselues riche. So that for treasure he enioyed sorowe. For hée that might haue béene Lorde of all, discréetely gouerning that which good hap had layde on him, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruedly bought the price of hys folly, abyding the bitter smart of pouertie and myserie.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>THE discreete Reader that shall looke in this Booke must giue atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue eare, and note eche thing perticulerly he readeth, diligently mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the secret lessons. For alwayes the worke of these sage Fathers carieth two senses withall. The first, knowne and manifest. The second, hidden and secret. Of the first we sweetely enioy the taste: but of the second we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue small knowledge, if we deepely ponder not the wordes. And hereof we may take ensample of the Nut, which giueth no maner of taste to man if he doe not first breake and open the shell, and then comen to the wyshed kernell, he beginneth to taste the sauour therof, and to reape the fruit of so excellent a doctrine. Let vs not doe therefore as the vndiscreete and simple man that had a desire to seeme learned, and to bee counted eloquent in speach, as you shall heare.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <head>Of the simple ignorant man, desirous to seeme learned.</head>
      <p>ON a time one earnestly besought a Poet &amp; an excellent Rhetorician (his very friende) to giue him some thing written that might be learned and eloquent, which
<pb facs="10"/>
konning without booke he might recite at pleasure in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye of wise men, that he might at least séeme no lesse learned than they. His friende consented, and performed his desire, and gaue him in a written booke (faire bounde and lymned with golden letters) many goodly sentences, so that he began to learn by rote his written authorities, and laboring night and daye to commit them to memorie, he determined to show that he was also learned. And being one daye in argument, not vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the signification of the words he had learned, for that they were not in his owne tongue, hée began to alleadge them quite from the purpose: &amp; being taken with the maner they lawghed him to scorne. Hée being angrye at the matter, lyke an obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and ignorant foole, aunswered. What? thinke you I am deceyued, that haue learned that I alleage out of the booke of a woorthie learned man, yea, and the letters lymned with golde to? at which woordes they laughed him more to scorne then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to sée his ignorance.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>EVery man therfore must indeuor himselfe to vnderstand that he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and vnderstanding it well, he must diligently obserue that doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, marking to what end and purpose that was written that he hath red, to profit therby at any time. I knowe there will be wise men that will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue they can saye and doe more wonders than this commeth to: yet for all that, the more we reade, the more we knowe, and the quicker is our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, besides, there is obteined euen profounde knowledge. Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning bringeth with it a great priuiledge: for by that men are exalted, and to a man of knowledge and vnderstanding it giueth life. But to him that hath iudgement and vnderstanding, and that gouerneth not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and his actions according to the prescribed rule of reason: His knowledge I say dyeth in him without fruit. As by reading this example folowing you may easilye perceiue.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <pb n="4" facs="10"/>
      <head>A comparison of the slouthfull man for the Reader.</head>
      <p>AN honest man lying in his bedde hearde a Théefe going vp and downe in his house: and thinking to paye him home (to take the more aduantage of him) suffered him to take his pleasure and loding, that hauing in déede his packe at his backe, he might euen then as he thought take him with the maner, and iustly reward him with the swordes point
<figure>
</figure>
as he listed. Thus debating with him selfe, imagining to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his purpose, (the Théefe occupying all this while him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe taking what he woulde) this stelye good man fell a sléepe againe, and the Théefe with his fardell of the best things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any let at all quietly departeth his waye. This man when
<pb facs="11"/>
he awaked and sawe his house naked, hys chestes emptye and broken open, bitterly sighed and lamented, cursing himselfe, and blaming his folly: considering hée might easily haue saued all that he was robbed of (since hée knew it and heard the noyse) and for very sloth woulde not once rise and defend it, hauing as it were the théefe in his handes. Knowledge therefore is aptly compared to a trée, whose fruite are the works: and this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is that we al ought to desire, and to exercise our selues in. Were it not a mad part to leaue the brode beaten hie way, and to take the vnknowne and daungerous pathe? Euen so it may be sayde of him which followeth his owne appetite and lyking, gouerning himselfe thereby, (and not as he ought with reason and good order,) leaning to these worldlye experiences, which euer desireth that that is profitable, but follow alwayes in déede things that are hurtfull. A man of such life and gouernement we may compare to him that knoweth good meates light of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion, and the grosse ill and heauie: yet ouercome with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire taketh that that is most hurtfull, and so being hurt, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe alone is the cause of all his yll.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>EVen such a man is he whome affection subdueth. He vnderstandeth and is learned, and able to decerne troth from falshoode, and yet will not put in proofe the true profit, nor once follow and desire knowledge and wisedome. We might bring this man in thexample of him that hauing his sight good and perfite, shutting his eyes would needes be ledde by a blinde man, so that both they falling into a diche were drowned, and miserably died. Euery man will condemne him for a foole, and worse than mad, that hauing his sight good and without blemishe, that might haue seene the daunger and scaped it, and of mere foolishnesse would not. Therefore eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie wise and discrete person must continually labour to reade, and to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande that he readeth, and must then teache it to as many as desire to knowe it, and to doe the good workes of the knowledge he teacheth, that euery way he may showe the wonderfull profit of his doctrine: for in this case he may not be like vnto a Well or Spring, which without any profit to</hi>
         <pb n="5" facs="11"/>
         <hi>it selfe quencheth the thirst of all beastes. The wise man is afterwardes bounde (when he is growne to the perfection of learning) to teach and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct those that knowe not. Prouided euer that he can master himselfe, and subdue his affections. For to a wise man three things are pertinent: to wit, Knowledge, Richesse, and Mercie. And of all things a man must chiefly beware of reprouing his neighbour of that fault he himselfe is guiltie off. That he be not likened to him, which hauing a Perle in his eie, found fault with the element that it was alway clowdie, not considering the blemish of his eie. Yet greater doubtlesse is our offence when with our neighbours hurt or detriment we winne commoditie to our selues. As fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out many times, which this example following sheweth vs.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <head>The deceyt lighteth on the decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers necke.</head>
      <p>TWoo friends hauing a great mount of corne in a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner vndeuided, they fel to parting it, leauing to eche his portion a part (howbeit both in one Garner still) so that they could not erre to choose eyther heape. But bicause in déede the one heape was greater than the other, hée which had the lesser thought to steale the bigger, and so by deceit to be reuenged of Fortune that had allotted him the least part. Vpon this he went to the Garner determining to steale it that night, and bicause he would not misse of his purpose in taking the one for the other, he cast his cloke ouer his fellowes heape being the greater, that he might the easilier knowe his owne in the darke being vncouered. Not long after came to the Garner also the other honest partener to looke to his heape, &amp; to see his deuided part: and when he sawe the loue of his partener to him (sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing simply he had couered his heape of corne for good will he bare him, that it should receyue no dust) as one that would not be thought vnthankfull, nor come behinde his fellow in curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, thus he sayde to himselfe. Oh this man is to kinde to mée, that to couer mine leaueth his owne heape bare. And so taking the Cloke off his heape cast it on the others, and couered it as
<pb facs="12"/>
his was, requiting his curtesie with like good will, little sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the intended deceyte, but rather reputed his friende ciuile and full of humanitie. At night his false friende counselled with a théefe and tolde him his intent, saying: if thou wilt goe with mée this night I will bring thée to a
<figure>
</figure>
place where we shall haue a good bootie of Corne as much as we can both carie away with vs. And thus agréed togithers thervpon, they went both to the Garner where these two heaps of Corne laye, and this partener the théefe groping in the darke to finde the heape his Cloke laye on, laying handes on his Cloke (supposing he had met with his fellowes heape) hée gaue it in praye to the théefe hée had brought with him, labouringe both to loade themselues, and so betwéene them they conueyed the whole heape: and wéening they had
<pb n="6" facs="12"/>
stollen from the other honest man, founde at length he was théefe to himselfe. The next morning very earely the two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions (accordinge to appointment) went togithers to the Garner to carie away eche other his portion as it was deuided betwéene them. And he that had done this feate, séeing his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teners part whole and vntouched, and his owne gone: like a man halfe deade for sorrow he heauily departed thence to his house, and not a worde he spake, bewayling and lamenting his wretched pretenced craft, not daring once to open the theft to his friende, who so much did trust him.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>NO man therefore should deale so foolishly in thinges that haue no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ende, and that are hard to bring to passe: least that wearied with superfluous labor, he cannot afterwardes exercise himselfe in thinges certaine and needefull. All our workes and deedes ought rather to tende to profit vs in time to come, then to serue the time present. For if we abandon and forsake the insatiable and infinite desire we haue of this wretched worlde, doubtlesse in the other worlde to come we shall feele no paine. For who that serueth God deuoutly, and with pure conscience, and that desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth riches onely to supplie necessitie, and to doe good workes: him God doth prosper and guide in all his wayes. And let no man dispaire though he be visited with ill hap sometime, doing well notwithstanding. For God manye times sendeth his blessing and increase vnwares to man, and in an houre vnlooked for, which he neuer thought would happen. And heare in what maner.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="section">
      <head>The good and vertuous should neuer dispaire in aduersitie.</head>
      <p>THere dwelled in a certaine Citie a man of a godly life and disposition, who fallen into extréeme pouertie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ashamed to aske for Gods sake, determined to prooue his friends, and so he did. And bewraying his miserie, looking for reliefe and pittie, founde nothing but hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
<pb facs="13"/>
neither was there anye that once woulde looke vpon the necessitie of that honest conditioned man. And thus repleate with griefe, vexed in his minde, he sorrowfullye repaireth to hys poore mansion. And being layde at night in his bedde to take his rest, the anguishe of his minde, togither with famine, woulde not suffer him to rest but kept him waking. And by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce
<figure>
</figure>
hearing a noyse about the house, lystening diligently what it shoulde be: hée knewe straight it was some Théefe (hoping of a great bootie) that went thus ransacking vp and downe. So this poore man sayde vnto himselfe. Thou hadst néede looke narrowlye, if thou wéene to haue that thou séekest for: Surely I will sée yet what feates these théeues doe worke when they come into such places where they finde naught. The Théefe roming here and there, busily searching and groping in
<pb n="7" facs="13"/>
euery corner, founde nothing but a little pot with Meale: and bicause he would not lose hys labour, hée determined to drawe his string to ketch that little morsell, and began to poure it out into the lappe of his cloke, hauing in the cape therof great store of Iewelles and ready money which hée had stolen in an other house where he had béene. The good poore man which till nowe was whisht and quiet to sée the ende of the Théefe, perceyuing hys little discretion, his hart rose against him, considering the villanye of thys wretch that woulde not leaue him that sielye quantitie of Meale to sustaine him alyue withall: and thought with himselfe it were better defend it in time to kéepe him from famine, than to tarye looking for the late reliefe of his harde friends. So in a great fury he leapt out of his bed and tooke him to his sword, and hauing the same drawne in hys hande with a terrible noyse hée runneth to the Théefe. Which bicause hée would not both lose his honesty and life togither at one instant, leauing (for hast to saue himselfe) hys cloke in pawne with the Meale, hauing no leysure to cast it on his backe, he was forced to flye for life and let all alone. This honest poore man then at his pleasure poured out the Meale out of his cloke, and put it againe into hys earthen potte where it was before: and thus sayd to himselfe, a ha, by Sainct Marie this geare goeth well, I haue gotten a cloke to boote by the meanes, to defende mée from the colde at least, and putting his hande into the cape, hée met with great riches and Iewels, and happily lighted on those goods which he neuer hoped of: winning that frō his enimie by force, which his friends would neuer haue giuen him for loue.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>I Doe not like in such a case to say as the common people doe, that God prouideth liuing for euery bodie, and that he will not see me lacke that that shall be necessarie for me, so as I neede not to labor for my liuing: for sure it is but a foolish phrase and vaine speach. But rather I will conclude, that euery man is bound to labor to procure his liuing, &amp; he may not make any such cases presidents, in which it pleased GOD to sende great riches</hi>
         <pb facs="14"/>
         <hi>without labor, as in this. For these are only the secrets of God, &amp; we ought not to aske the cause of his diuine goodnesse. The wise man therefore must endeuour himselfe to gaine that he may, honestly and vprightly, trusting always in almightie God that he will prosper his doings and giue him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, seeking euer to keepe him selfe out of trouble and sorowe: and not to do as the Doue, which breeding hir Pigions about the house (making them familiar with the same) albeit they are monthly taken from hir and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, yet she leaueth not for that to returne to hir olde nest and breede yong againe, though she know they shalbe taken from hir. We finde it written, that God hath ordeined the end and terme of all things, and that they can not passe. Therefore say these wise men, that he that worketh respecting the worlde to come, lightneth the burthens and troubles of this frayle life: But he that reposeth his trust in these worldlye thinges and is wrapped in the same, doth waste and consume his yeares. A man ought to labour in these three things, bicause he hath neede of them, to wit. To knowe to keepe the lawe, and the good statutes thereof. The seconde, to procure things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie for mans life. And the thirde, that his woorkes be pure and cleane with himselfe and among others. Then he must beware and withdrawe himselfe from foure other mortall and damnable. The first, is to be negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in his art or science. The seconde, to contemne that the law commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. The third, to credit all things lightly. The fourth, to denie knowledge. For he that will be reputed wise in his doings, must first consider well what he taketh vpon him: and if he neede counsell, let him aske it of a faithfull friende. When he happeneth to haue great matters in hande, let him not goe about them rashly, but first way the importance thereof. That he be not likened to one which being out of his waye, and going on still, is the farther of the place he would go to. And also compared to another, which hath but a little hurt in his eye, and by continuall rubbing of it he maketh it incurable. A man must feare the diuine iustice, inclining him selfe to that that is good, and doing that to his neighbour he woulde haue done to himselfe, helping him in all daungers as he woulde be holpen him selfe. And to conclude this our worke, he that meaneth to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande it, must order his life according to the lawes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions of vertue: as showeth these wonderfull and learned examples, and sententious authorities.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>