<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the curteous Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104607_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16195</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3117</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104607</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the curteous Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Astrolabium vranicum generale : A necessary and pleasaunt solace and recreation for nauigators in their long iorneying, containing the vse of an instrument or generall astrolabe: newly for them deuised by the author, to bring them skilfully acquainted with all the planets starres, and constellacions of the heauens: and their courses, mouings, and apparences, called the (vranicall astrolabe.) In which, agreeable to the hipothesis of Nicolaus Copernicus, the starry firmament is appointed perpetually fixed and the earth and his horizons continually mouing from west towards the east once about euery 24 houres. Fraught also by new deuise with all such necessary supplements for iudiciall astrology, as Alkabitius &amp; Claudius Dariottus haue deliuered by their tables. Wherevnto for their further delight he hath anexed another inuention, expressing in one face the whole globe terrestriall; with the two great english voyages lately performed round about the world. Compyled by Iohn Blagraue of Reading Gentleman, the same wellwiller to the mathematicks. Anno. 1596</title>
                 <author>Blagrave, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <distributor>Mattes, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>68 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, the eares of my guilty conceit being continually troubled with such a noyse and clamor for my (Organum Vranicum,) and the second part of my Mathematicall Iewell, so long and largely promised, as the greedy Auditors are woont to make at a Stage-play: calling, Come away howe, with boyes thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing vollyes of stones ratling at the gates of my otherwise buisied imployments, for staying so long: Maketh me heere in haste (God graunt to your liking) to come vp the Stage, with a little, but rare piece of Mathematicke Musickly pleasure, not impertinent to the matter to be acted: to stay your langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing expectations, both woorth the acceptacion (which I dare boldly aduouch against the doggedst detractor that shall contradict) and sufficient to entertaine the time vntill Midsomer or Michelmas Terme at the farthest, when as (if God permit) the stately Comedy of Queene Vranya hir Pageants, shall abundantly offer themselues to your pleasant viewe, Sollace your selues I pray you heerewith the whiles, and be bold with me if in any thing you doubt. You shall haue me God willing once euery Terme in London ready to your wish, at a poore lodging within Maister Greenes Wharfe neere vnto Charing Crosse: and at Maister Ralfe Iacksons at the signe of the Swan in S. Paules Churchyard, or at Maister William Matts Stationer, at the signe of the Plough, ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst S Dunstons Church in Fleetestreete, who hath the Impression of this Booke, you shall euer know whether I be at any time in the Citty: With whome, I haue taken order to furnish with these In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments and their supplements any that shall want them.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>