<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the ryght excellent and honorable lorde Iohū Erle of Oxforde / and hygh chamberlayne of Englande Thomas Paynell gretynge.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1528</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104705_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11336</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21596</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104705</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the ryght excellent and honorable lorde Iohū Erle of Oxforde / and hygh chamberlayne of Englande Thomas Paynell gretynge.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Regimen sanitatis Salerni : This boke techyng al people to gouerne them in helthe, is translated out of the Latyne tonge in to englishe by Thomas Paynell. Whiche boke is as profitable [et] as nedefull to be had and redde as any can be to obserue corporall helthe</title>
                 <author>Joannes, de Mediolano</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1528</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>232 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="A ij" facs="2"/>
   <head>To the ryght excellent and honorable lorde Iohū Erle of Oxforde / and hygh chamberlayne of Englande Thomas Paynell gretynge.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Edynge of olde authors and stories my most honorable lorde / I fynde / that mē in tyme past were of lōger lyfe / and of more propsperous helthe / than they are nowe adayes. Whiche thynge as hit greued me / so in maner hit enforced me / to seke the cause of this sodeyne and strāge alteracion. For why / it is written / <note place="margin">Gen. v.</note> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Adam lyued .9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>0. yere. The Sibyls of Cumane liued .iii C. wynters: Nestor .iii.C. wynters: Arganton / kynge of Tartesses .iii.C. yeres: and Galen that famous doctor .C. and .xl. yeres: but nowe adays (alas) if a man may aproche to .xl. or .lx yeres / mē repute hym happy and fortunate. But yet howe many come therto? To serche &amp; gyue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very true reason herof passeth my small capacite: without I may say hit be / bicause we fulfyll nat the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandementes of almyghty god: whiche to well wyllyng {per}sones are very lyght / and of no burden. For our lorde sayth: My yocke is swete / <note place="margin">Mat. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Psal. 127</note> and my burden lyght to be borne. Sayth nat the prophet Dauid: that who so feareth god / and walketh in his wayes and preceptis / shal se his childers chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? And Salomon sayth: O my childrē / <note place="margin">Prouer. 3.</note> forget nat my preceptes &amp; lawes: for they shall kepe you &amp; {pro}lōge your days &amp; yeres. And I wyll (saith our
<pb facs="3"/>
lorde god by Dauid) lengthen his dayes.<note place="margin">Psal. 90.</note> Than may nat this be a reasonable cause of this our so shorte and wretched lyfe? Trewely I suppose hit be by our myslyuynge and fylthy synne? whiche beynge so abominable and so horrible / <note place="margin">Cap. quia infirmitas de peni et remis.</note> is at som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme the very cause of corporall infirmite / and of short lyfe. Sayd nat our lorde / the phisician of all phisicians / to the sicke man: Nowe I haue heled the / depart thou from hens: and loke thou syn no more / <note place="margin">Ioan. 5.</note> lest a worse harme happē vpō the? Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall I say / y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hit chanceth by our mys diete? and to moche surfettynge? Truely the prouerbe sayth / that there dye many mo by surfet / than by the sworde.<note place="margin">Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stici. 37.</note> Accordyng wherto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wyse mā sayth: Surfet sleeth many a one: and temperance pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth the life. Surfet and diuersites of meates and drynkes / lettyng and corruptyng the digestiō febleth man / and very oft causeth this shortnes of lyfe.<note place="margin">Plin. li. 7</note> What other thyng but mys diete caused Pto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lomeus Philadelphus to be so miserably &amp; peyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vexed with the goute: and so (as hit is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) that nothyng coude relesse his peyne / sauyng dethe? What caused Antipater / &amp; that noble man Mecenas / to be contynually vexed with the feuer but yll dite? What other thynge infected Aristar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus with the dropsy / but yl diete? Yll diete (as me thynketh) is chiefcause of all dangerous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable diseases: and of the shortenes of mans life. Than hit must nedes folowe / that a tēperate and a moderate diete / prolongeth mans lyfe: and saueth hym from all suche peynfull diseases. And
<pb n="A iij" facs="3"/>
therfore Asclepiades that noble phisiciā / <note place="margin">v. necessa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> thynges in regiment of helthe.</note> professed There are .v. necessarie thynges to conserue and prolonge mans prosperite and helthe: that is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinence from meate / abstinence from wyne / rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byng of the body / exercise / and digestiō. O howe holsome is hit than to vse good diete / to lyue tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratly / to eschewe excesse of meatis and drinkes?<note place="margin">Salerne.</note> Yea howe greatly are we Englishe men bounde to the maisters of the vnyuersite of Salerne (Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerne is in the realme of Naples) whiche vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed in our behalfe to compile thus necessari / and thus holsome a boke? But what auayleth hit / to haue golde or abundance of riches / if one can nat vse hit? What helpeth costely medicines / if one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue them nat? So what profiteth vs a boke / be hit neuer so expedient and frutefull / if we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande hit nat? Wherfore I / consydryng the frute y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> myght come of this boke / if hit were translated in to the englishe tonge (for why / euery mā vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standeth nat the latine) I thought hit very expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient at some tymes / for the welthe of vnlerned {per}<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones to busy my selfe ther in: For lerned {per}sones / and suche as haue great experiēce / nede no instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to diete them selfe / nor to conserue theyr helthe. Yet if suche other wyse and discrete par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sones / as is your lordeshippe / by chance rede this boke: they may {per}auenture fynde that shall please them: and that besides theyr owne diete and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of lyuynge / shall be for theyr corporall wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and good helthe. I wyll nat / nor it becometh me nat / to exhorte your lordshyp / with let of other
<pb facs="4"/>
your great busynesses / to rede this my powre trā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slacion: but if per chaunce at your leisure ye rede hit / I humbly desyre and praye your good lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyppe to rede hit with forgyuenes / and to accept the same as hit is worthy.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>