<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right worshipfull and his singuler good Master Siluester, But∣ler, George Bancrafte, Wishethe pro∣speritye and healthe, boeth of bo¦dye and soule.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1549</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104732_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11925</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22238</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104732</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right worshipfull and his singuler good Master Siluester, But∣ler, George Bancrafte, Wishethe pro∣speritye and healthe, boeth of bo¦dye and soule.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sermon declaringe hovv vue [sic] ar iustified by faith</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hill (Hyll), William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1549</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>118 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>¶ To the right worshipfull and his singuler good Master Siluester, But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, George Bancrafte, Wishethe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritye and healthe, boeth of bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye and soule.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I considered wyth my selfe the greate &amp; daū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, abuses in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministracion of such sacramentes as our sauiour Iesus Christe left to his misticall bodie the churche of the fayethfull, to be externe sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and tokens of suche giftes as God hath, and doth dailie worcke in vs, to his own glorie, and salua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of oure soules▪ I can fynde, perceiue, and proue none to be so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche abused, as the holy and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret supper of our Lord. For wher as he ordined, that holy sacramēt of his bodie, and bloud to be eaten and dronken in remembraunce of his passion whose frute they taste therin, which haue ther stedfaste fayth in hym. And thereby shewe
<pb facs="10"/> furth the Lordes death vntyll he come, and as brede is made, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny graines, &amp; wyne of many gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, so the membres of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion of Christes churche. Haue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge one God, one fayeth, and one Baptisme, are put in remēbraūce in eateinge and drinkinge y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they are one bodie, whereof Christe is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hed. The beally bishopes of Ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bilon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Romishe Antichrist, haue anullyd extripate, &amp; cleane abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ordinaunce of Christ and vse of thappostelles, in the admini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stracion therof. And haue of their owne brayne excogitated deuised and brought in to the churche a newe, and straynge ordinaunce for the same, whiche is as cōtrarie to christes wil and purpose, touch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing that blessed supper as heauē to earth, lyght to darknes, lyfe to death, and they call it the blessyd Masse but it maye be truely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd a diluesh Masking, for menes
<pb facs="10"/> eies, are masked there with y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thei cannot se the trueth, but through that detestable abominacion haue bene, brought to moste miserable perdiciō, for they applie it to soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyoures in war for faire weather and rayne for the plage pockes and suche other diseases for bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes sicke of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> morren for preserua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of health, and for remissiō of synnes, boeth for the quicke and deade I wyl not, speake how God is mocked therin and Christe had in derision they pley booe pepe, wyth seste me, or seste me not. My pene abhoreth to write what duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge knellenge lickinge kissing or Crossing and breathing these di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilles apes haue deuised in thys whorishe Masse ther desguisinge In apparell at Masse hath pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked manye a pore mannes purs and hath robbid theire soules of the true frutes of the spirite, for al suche somes of monie that men
<pb facs="11"/> shoulde haue bestowed on theire poure parentes, childrē and nedie neighbours was to litle for their vestimētes albes, stoles chalices, corporaces, aulter clothes, Mass<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bockes, and suche other, wherein Christe hath no delite for Christe and the Appostelles vsede none suche disguisynge in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistracion of thys blessid Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Christes bodie and bloud but were contendid with such ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente as they were accustomed daylye to were &amp; so these shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Idolaters, shewing them sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of what generacion they are, dare so bouldlye face out such ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeste lyes agaynste gods glorye y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> plaine truth, and ordinaunce of christ What shal I speake of these holi mumers (I would haue saied holy Masse mongers) that whan they here of any rich manes death they flocke together lyke rauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to a dead Carrē. Not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte
<pb facs="11"/> them that mourne for the deade wyth hope of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> resurrection of the fleshe, not to gyue thankes to God for them that are depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the fayeth of Christe nor to praye that we, departinge in the same fayeth maye wyth them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue like rewarde but to get mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney with Requiem eternā and pro quorum memoria corpus Christi sumitur with cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing dashing of holy water, &amp; such other lyke Iuglinges so that the ryght vse of it is cleane altered as thought christ had neuer ordeined it in remembraunce of his death and passion and for as much as in thys treatise folowinge the true vse of the Lordes supper and also the deuelishe patchinge of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pishe Masse is in fewe wordes li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely declared I haue thought it good to trāslate the same into the englishe tonge to the edifinge of my dere bretherne in Christ prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge God the father of oure saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb facs="12"/> Iesus Christ, that these thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges may shortlie be reformed that the pore flocke of Christ be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more deceyuede wyth suche craftye conueiaunce to kepe them in cōtenual blinded for lucres sake, to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great daunger of their soules and pernicious dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaciō of gods glorie to whome be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye for euer</p>
   <closer>AMEN</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>