<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right honorable &amp; my very singuler good Lord, the Earle of Huntingdon, Knight of the noble order of the Garter, Lord President of her Maiesties hono∣rable counsell established in the North partes, your Lordshippes daylie Oratour, and hum∣ble suppliant, Iohn Lyster, Clarke, late Cutate of Leedes, and nowe Vicar of Thorpeach, wisheth good health, long life, much encrease of honour, and after a godly and faith∣full ende.</title>
           <author>Lyster, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104942_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06667</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17122</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104942</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right honorable &amp; my very singuler good Lord, the Earle of Huntingdon, Knight of the noble order of the Garter, Lord President of her Maiesties hono∣rable counsell established in the North partes, your Lordshippes daylie Oratour, and hum∣ble suppliant, Iohn Lyster, Clarke, late Cutate of Leedes, and nowe Vicar of Thorpeach, wisheth good health, long life, much encrease of honour, and after a godly and faith∣full ende.</title>
                 <author>Lyster, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A rule how to bring vp children : A treatise wherein is declared, how the father apposeth his sonne in the holy Scripture, whereby all parents may be taught a rule how to bring vp their children, briefelie collected into a short volume</title>
                 <author>Lyster, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>5, 138, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the right honorable &amp; my very singuler good Lord, the Earle of <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> Knight of the noble order of the Garter, Lord President of her Maiesties hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable counsell established in the North partes, your Lordshippes daylie Oratour, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble suppliant, <hi>Iohn Lyster,</hi> Clarke, late Cutate of Leedes, and nowe Vicar of Thorpeach, wisheth good health, long life, much encrease of honour, and after a godly and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ende.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N most humble wise, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your good Lordshippe, that by your lordships good meanes I obtained the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice, whereof I am now resident, and remembring a saying of that worthie Philosopher SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NECA, that there be three degrees of thankefulnesse, one, recognoscere benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, an other, gratias et laudes agere, and the thirde, pro loco et tempore secundam suam facultatem retribuere, or rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the Samaritan in the Ghospel hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Christ of his Leprosie, returned and acknowledged Christes mercie towardes him, prostrate himselfe before him, and
<pb facs="3"/>
with a loud voice gaue him thanks, so like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise (good my Lord) I returning, doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your Lordships great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse vnto mee, render most hartie and humble thankes vnto your honour for the same, and not being able to make anye recompence vnto your Lordshippe, (as Seneca teacheth) although I haue medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated with my selfe sundrie times how to doe the same. Yet notwithstanding, that your Lordship may perceaue that I am not forgetfull or negligent of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipps great good will vnto mee, I haue drawen in Dialogue wise out of scripture, (which is able to make one learned to saluation) the dutie of all states and degrees of people, howe a Christian life is to bee ledde, what thinges are needefull to salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ende of manne, and the straight accompt in the day of iudgement, with the punishment of the wicked, and reward of the righteous, briefelie sette downe, and plaine for the capacitie of the ignoraunt, putting or adding nothing therevnto, which I doe present vnto your good Lordshippe, in remembrance of my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble duetie and obedient seruice vnto your Honour, beseeching your Lordshippe to
<pb facs="3"/>
accept of my good and simple meaning, and to beare with my boldnesse and small knowledge, to write any thing to such a Noble personage as your Lordship. And I shall incessauntlie entreate the eternall and euerliuing God till ATRAPOS shall cutte my fatall thred, for the preseruation of your good Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe, whome the King of glorie, Lord of hostes, and Father of all mercie, blesse, saue, and keepe for euer more, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordshipps poore suppliant, IOHN LYSTER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>