<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A Briefe Memorial of sundrye Unfortunate Englishe men. William Baldwin to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1559</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104522_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02342</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1247</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104522</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A Briefe Memorial of sundrye Unfortunate Englishe men. William Baldwin to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A myrroure for magistrates : Wherein may be seen by example of other, with howe greuous plages vices are punished: and howe frayle and vnstable worldly prosperitie is founde, even of those, whom fortune seemeth most highly to fauour. Anno. 1559</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsh (Marshe, Marche), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1559</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>5, lxxxv, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Discourses on government and political theory</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>¶ A Briefe Memorial of sundrye Unfortunate Englishe men. William Baldwin to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han the Printer had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed with hym selfe to printe L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates booke of the fall of Princes, and had made priuye thereto, many both honourable and worshipfull, he was counsailed by dyuers of theim, to procure to haue the storye conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed from where as Bochas lefte, vnto this presente time, chiefly of suche as Fortune had dalyed with here in this ylande: whiche might be as a myrrour for al men as well noble as others, to shewe the slyppery deceytes of the waueryng lady, and the due rewarde of all kinde of vices. Whiche aduyse lyked him so well, that he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me to take paynes therin: but because it was a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter passyng my wyt and skyll, and more thankles than gaineful to meddle in, I refused vtterly to vndertake it, excepte I might haue the helpe of suche, as in wyt were apte, in learning allowed, and in iudgemente a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d esty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion able to wield and furnysh so weighty an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryse, thinkyng euen so to shut my handes. But he ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest and diligent in his affayres, pr<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>iued A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o set
<pb facs="5"/>
vnder his shoulder: for shortly after, dyuers learned men whose many giftes nede fewe praises, consented to take vpon theym parte of the trauayle. And whan certayne of theym to the numbre of seuen, were throughe a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>all ass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt at a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> apoynted time a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d place gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to deuyse therupon, I resorted vnto them, bering with me the booke of Bochas, translated by Dan Lid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, for the better obseruacion of his order: whiche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we lyked well, yet woulde it not cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ly serue, seynge that both Bochas and Lidgate were dead, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were there any alyue that meddled with lyke arg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to whom the vnfortunat might make their moue.</p>
   <p>To make therfore a state mete for the matter, they al agreed that I shoulde vsurpe Bochas rowme, and the wretched princes complayne vnto me: and tooke vpon themselues euery man for his parte to be sundrye perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, and in theyr behalfes to bewayle vnto me theyr greuous chaunces, heuy destunes, &amp; wofull misfortunes.</p>
   <p>This doen, we opened suche bookes of Cronicles as we had there present, and maister Ferrers, after he had founde where Bochas left, whiche was about the ende of king Edwarde the thirdes raigne, to begin the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, sayde thus.</p>
   <p>I meruaile what Bochas meaneth to forget among his myserable princes, such as wer of our nacion, whose numbre is as great, as their aduentures wunderful: For to let passe all, both Britons, Danes, and Saxons, and to cum to the last Conquest, what a sorte are they, and sum euen in his owne tyme? As for example, king Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde the fyrste, slayne with a quarlle in his chiefe pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie,
<pb facs="5"/>
also king Iohn his brother as sum saye, poyso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: are not their histories rufull and of rare example? But as it shoulde appeare, he beynge an <hi>Italien,</hi> mynded most the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Italike</hi> story, orels perhaps he wan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted our countrey chronicles. It were therfore a goodlye and a notable matter to searche &amp; dyscourse oure whole storye from the fyrst beginning of the inhabitynge of the yle. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nge the printers mynde is to haue vs followe where <hi>Lidgate</hi> left, we wyll leaue that great laboure to other that maye intende it, and (as blinde bayarde is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way boldest) I wyll begin at the tyme of Rycharde the second, a tyme as vnfortunate as the ruler therein. And forasmuche frende <hi>Baldvvin,</hi> as it shalbe your charge to note, and pen orderly the whole proces, I wyll so far as my memorie and iudgement serueth, sumwhat further you in the truth of the story. And therefore omytting the ru<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>le made by Iacke Strawe and his meyny, and the mourder of many notable men which therby happened, for Iacke (as ye knowe) was but a poore prince: I will begin with a notable example whiche within a whyle after ensued. And althoughe he be no great prince, yet sythens he had a princelye offyce, I wyll take vpon me the miserable person of syr Robert Tresilian chiefe Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of Englande, and of other which suffred with him: thereby to warne all of his authorytie and profession, to take heed of wrong Iudgementes, mysconstruyng of lawes, or wrestyng the same to serue the princes tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nes, whiche ryghtfullye brought theym to a myserable ende, whiche they may iustly lament in maner ensuyng.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>