<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶A briefe note, taken out of M. Dees Mathematical Preface that goeth before Euclides Ele∣mentes nowe extant in our Inglish tongue, as touching what the Mathematical Sciences are, that is to say, all those Artes that order number, measure, or wayght, and tyme, without the which, in respect, we can doo nothing. For what can bee doone in any respect, but we must vse number, which is Arith∣meticke? or what can be doone, but we must vse measure or wayght, which is Geometrie? or what can there be doone, but that we must vse tyme, which dooth appertayne vnto Astro∣nomie? for by number we knowe howe many or fewe there are: and by measure we knowe whether it be ynches, feete, yardes, scores, myles, leagues, poundes, ounces, galloes, quartes, or tunnes: and by tyme, we knowe whether it be minutes, howres, dayes, weekes, monethes, yeeres. &amp;c. Whereof two are prynci∣pal, Arithmeticke and Geometrie, wherof al these compoun∣ded scientes are sprong of these two Simples.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104686_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16518</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3432</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104686</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶A briefe note, taken out of M. Dees Mathematical Preface that goeth before Euclides Ele∣mentes nowe extant in our Inglish tongue, as touching what the Mathematical Sciences are, that is to say, all those Artes that order number, measure, or wayght, and tyme, without the which, in respect, we can doo nothing. For what can bee doone in any respect, but we must vse number, which is Arith∣meticke? or what can be doone, but we must vse measure or wayght, which is Geometrie? or what can there be doone, but that we must vse tyme, which dooth appertayne vnto Astro∣nomie? for by number we knowe howe many or fewe there are: and by measure we knowe whether it be ynches, feete, yardes, scores, myles, leagues, poundes, ounces, galloes, quartes, or tunnes: and by tyme, we knowe whether it be minutes, howres, dayes, weekes, monethes, yeeres. &amp;c. Whereof two are prynci∣pal, Arithmeticke and Geometrie, wherof al these compoun∣ded scientes are sprong of these two Simples.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A booke called the treasure for traueilers : deuided into fiue bookes or partes, contaynyng very necessary matters, for all sortes of trauailers, eyther by sea or by lande, written by William Bourne</title>
                 <author>Bourne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 32, 1, 25, 1, 22, 2, 21, 3, 5-16, 4 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="note">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>¶A briefe note, taken out of M. Dees Mathematical Preface that goeth before <hi>Euclides Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes</hi> nowe extant in our Inglish tongue, as touching what the <hi>Mathematical</hi> Sciences are, that is to say, all those Artes that order number, measure, or wayght, and tyme, without the which, in respect, we can doo nothing. For what can bee doone in any respect, but we must vse number, which is <hi>Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticke</hi>? or what can be doone, but we must vse measure or wayght, which is <hi>Geometrie</hi>? or what can there be doone, but that we must vse tyme, which dooth appertayne vnto <hi>Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie</hi>? for by number we knowe howe many or fewe there are: and by measure we knowe whether it be ynches, feete, yardes, scores, myles, leagues, poundes, ounces, galloes, quartes, or tunnes: and by tyme, we knowe whether it be minutes, howres, dayes, weekes, monethes, yeeres. &amp;c. Whereof two are prynci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, <hi>Arithmeticke</hi> and <hi>Geometrie,</hi> wherof al these compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded scientes are sprong of these two Simples.</head>
   <div type="list_of_geometric_arts">
      <head>☞Thinges done by hand Geometricall.</head>
      <p n="1">1 <hi>Mecometrie.</hi> Is the measuring of <hi>the length</hi> anything whatsoeuer.</p>
      <p n="2">2 <hi>Embadometrie.</hi> Is the measuring the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes of all flat things, as Land, Boorde, Glasse.</p>
      <p n="3">3 <hi>Stereometrie.</hi> Is the measuring of all solid bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as Timber, Stone, Kaske, &amp; such lyke.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="list_of_things_measured">
      <head>☞Thinges measured that haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce from you.</head>
      <p n="4">4 <hi>Apomecometrie.</hi> Is how farre any thing is frō you, whether it be on lande or on water.</p>
      <p n="5">5 <hi>Hipsomettie.</hi> Is how high or deepe any thing seene, is from the leuell, whether it bee on
<pb facs="11"/>
Lande or water. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="6">6 <hi>Platometrie.</hi> How broade any thing is. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="7">7 <hi>Geodesie.</hi> Is the suruaying or measuring of landes, woods, or water, hauing distaunce from you by instrument or otherwise.</p>
      <p n="8">8 <hi>Geographie.</hi> Is the description of Countries, or Kingdomes.</p>
      <p n="9">9 <hi>Cherographie</hi> or <hi>Typographie.</hi> Is the descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a part of a Country or kingdome. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="10">10 <hi>Hydrographie.</hi> Is the discription of the Seas, with the Ilandes and rockes, and dangers and lynes, and Courses. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="11">11 <hi>Stratarithmetrie.</hi> Is the view or measuring of a battel of men, to know the number of them not comming neare them. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="12">12 <hi>Perspectiue.</hi> Demonstrateth the manner and propertie of all radiations directe, broken, and reflected.</p>
      <p n="13">13 <hi>Astronomie.</hi> Is the mouing of the lightes and Planets. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="14">14 <hi>Musike.</hi> Teacheth the diuersyty of sounds. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="15">15 <hi>Cosmographie.</hi> Is the descriptiō of the whole earth, and the Paralell of the heauens an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering thereunto &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="16">16 <hi>Astrologie.</hi> Is to geue iudgment by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> signes, lights and planets. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="17">17 <hi>Statick.</hi> Is an art that doth order and deale with heuines and lightnesse. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="18">18 <hi>Anthropographie.</hi> Is of thinges appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to the body of man, to shew them. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="19">19 <hi>Trochilike.</hi> Doth appertaine vnto the turning of wheels, this art is necessary for Clockma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,
<pb facs="11"/>
&amp; Crane makers, and Mylles, &amp; al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sciences, that doo deale with wheeles.</p>
      <p n="20">20 <hi>Helicosophie.</hi> Is an art to drawe hylical or Spheral or winding lines, and is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for Skrewe makers, &amp; diuers other things.</p>
      <p n="21">21 <hi>Pneumatithmie.</hi> This art is necessary for all them that doo make Pumpes or great Bellows, for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it teacheth al those thinges that goe by wynde and water. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="22">22 <hi>Menadrie.</hi> Is an art, that teacheth the making of al ingenes, as things to pull to, or thrust fro, or lyfting vp, or pressing downe. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="23">23 <hi>Hypogeiodie.</hi> Is that arte that dooth apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne vnto myners in the grounde. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="24">24 <hi>Hydrogogie.</hi> Is that art to bring water vnto any place assigned. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="25">25 <hi>Horometrie, or Horologiographie.</hi> Is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Dyals of al sortes. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="26">26 <hi>Zographie.</hi> Is the art of a cunning Painter. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="27">27 <hi>Althalmasat.</hi> The art of Grauing.</p>
      <p n="28">28 <hi>Archetectur.</hi> Is a cunning Mason or Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="29">29 <hi>Nauigation.</hi> Is sayling on the Sea. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="30">30 <hi>Thauruaturaike.</hi> Is that which dooth make strange workes, as those that made the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen head seeme to speake, the brasen Serpēt to hisse, the Doue of wood to flye, the Eagle made by art to flye. &amp;c.</p>
      <p n="31">31 <hi>Archemastrie.</hi> This art teacheth to bryng to actual experience sensible al worthy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions, by al the artes Mathematical, &amp;c.</p>
   </div>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>