<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right Worship∣full his speciall Patron, Maister Iohn Rotherham, Esquire, one of the sixe Clarkes of her Maiesties most Honourable Court of Chauncery.</title>
           <author>A., L.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104551_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07648</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1804</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104551</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right Worship∣full his speciall Patron, Maister Iohn Rotherham, Esquire, one of the sixe Clarkes of her Maiesties most Honourable Court of Chauncery.</title>
                 <author>A., L.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The honour of chiualrie : Set downe in the most famous historie of the magnanimious and heroike Prince Don Bellianis: sonne vnto the Emperour Don Bellaneo of Greece. Wherein are described, the straunge and dangerous aduentures that him befell. With his loue towards the Princesse Florisbella: daughter vnto the Souldan of Babylon. Englished out of Italian, by L.A</title>
                 <author>Fernández, Jerónimo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 286 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full his speciall Patron, Maister <hi>Iohn Rotherham,</hi> Esquire, one of the sixe Clarkes of her <hi>Maiesties most Honourable Court of Chauncery.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch, so great, and infinit are the fauors (Right Wo. Sir) that from the bounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liberallitie of your faire conditions, I haue without desert receiued: that by no meanes, in no respect nor in the least degree, my greatest duetie can no way satisfie by any actiue deede: Saue with a willing minde, alwayes acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging it selfe vnable to cancell the great bondes for the same. Which in my doubtfull thoughts reuoluing, beeing by perswasions wonne, to pubish the excercise of some vacant houres: &amp; remēbring that at your Wo. house at <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mars,</hi> I began the practise of the Italian tongue (as these fewe sheetes of paper there commenced, doe beare testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie) I cannot but in signe of my dutie, present this slender in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor to your Wo. kinde acceptance, crauing pardon for this audacious boldenesse; which confidently hoping to obtaine, I doe then beseech you, to patronage it, as the first token of my thankfull heart (beeing destitute of all other meanes to doe it:) Whose rude and harsh discourses, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in his infāt growth yet better please, through the myshe couert of grosse barbarisme, in an vnpolisht wit, onely sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting her weakenes, against al accidents of insuing harms,
<pb facs="3"/>
on the strongpiller of your fauourable lookes, which graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, my wandring desires shall triumph in the victorie of their owne wishes: and rest incouraged to labour in their second sowing, with more perfection, to your lasting praises. Whose continuing loue, I onely pray, may by no sinister oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, drowne mee in the obliuious center of forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, from your deare remēbrance, which is the anchorage of my hopes, that no longer in a mortall world doo wish may breath, then from your dutie they decline, or the grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful memorating (being al I craue) of your incomparable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. Whose life with many, many yeares increase, in all earthly happinesse, with augment of dignities in this terrene orbe, and in the future, the crowne of ioyes, infallible, the onely sole Ruler of them both, may grant you in all largesse.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your VVorships humblie deuoted.
L. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>