<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE IMPERIALL MAIESTY of GREAT BRITAINES Monarch JAMES &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Bainbridge, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1618</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104455_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01933</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1207</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104455</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE IMPERIALL MAIESTY of GREAT BRITAINES Monarch JAMES &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Bainbridge, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An astronomicall description of the late comet : from the 18. of Nouemb. 1618. to the 16. of December following. With certaine morall progosticks or applications drawne from the comets motion and irradiation amongst the celestiall hierglyphicks. By vigilant and diligent obseruations of Iohn Bainbridge Doctor of Physicke, and louer of the mathematicks</title>
                 <author>Bainbridge, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Fetherstone (Featherstone), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1618</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Parker, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 42, 2 pages, 1 folded leaf of plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE</hi> IMPERIALL MAIESTY of GREAT BRITAINES <hi>Monarch JAMES</hi> &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Most gracious Soueraigne,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of <hi>Aristides,</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. To wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship GOD with consecration of Temples, but to honour Noble
<pb facs="3"/>
personages with Dedication of bookes: following this aduice, I beganne not long since the descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of Great <hi>Britaines</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy in three Columnes, Histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, Panegyricall, and Prophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacticall; intending thereby to stir vp your leige people to a religious admiration of Gods wonderfull Prouidence in vniting these two famous Kingdomes into one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; to a iust acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our exceeding happinesse therein: as also to an vnanimous desire, and endeauour for the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Vnion and perpetuall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation thereof. In the meane time Heauen it selfe offered a faire occasion to manifest the feruent zeale long smothered in my loyall
<pb facs="3"/>
breast towards your MAIESTY, the late strange, and admirable Comet, which hath filled so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny eies with his rayes, and their thoughts with Meteors, or doubts. An Astronomicall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription whereof delineated in a celestiall Planisphere, with some briefe touches in the Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stickes, and Morall applications thereof, I humbly offer to your princely Excellence, beseeching you to proiect the beames of your sweete, and gracious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence both on it, and the Authour; that, as the glorious Sunne of Heauen with his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>splendence enlightned this (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise obscure) Comet: So your MAIESTIE our terresti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="4"/>
all <hi>Phaebus</hi> would vouchsafe to illustrate</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties most humble, and loyall Subiect.
IOHN BAINBRIDGE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>