<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO HIS WORSHIPFVL, WOR∣thy
and singular good friend Master
T. I. these faithfull com∣mendations.</title>
           <author>Barker, Andrew</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104493_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04099</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1417</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104493</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO HIS WORSHIPFVL, WOR∣thy
and singular good friend Master
T. I. these faithfull com∣mendations.</title>
                 <author>Barker, Andrew</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true and certaine report of the beginning, proceedings, ouerthrowes, and now present estate of Captaine Ward and Danseker, the two late famous pirates : from their first setting foorth to this present time. As also the firing of 25. saile of the Tunis, men of warre: together with the death of diuers of Wards chiefe captaines. Published by Andrew Barker master of a ship, who was taken by the confederates of Ward, and by them some time detained prisoner</title>
                 <author>Barker, Andrew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 <publisher>Busby, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hall, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Helme (Helmes), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 27, 1 page, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO HIS WORSHIPFVL, WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
and singular good friend Master
T. I. these faithfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, a farre greater happines then I of late
haue had, either leisure to hope for, or
means to expect; I commend to your
good selfe, &amp; the frends of our acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.
Being certified by my affection,
that your gentle nature, doth commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serat
the misfortunes hath befalne me, and therein as a
friend, doth share with mee in sorrow: I shall as soone
as occasion will suffer me, make hast to <hi>London,</hi> to bee
counselled by your aduise, touching those things in
particular, that mainly concerne my estate: Nor make
I any doubt, but before the receipt hereof, you haue
heard of my mishap, from the report of some of my men
who I hope, are ariued by passage, by the way of <hi>Holland:</hi>
therefore I omit herein to trouble you with the maner of
my first taking by the <hi>Turkes,</hi> whose gouernours, I
meane <hi>Masters</hi> &amp; <hi>Pilates,</hi> are all Englishmen, not onely
<hi>Pirates,</hi> but mearely reprobates, and whose successe at
Seas is so great, that it is most lamentable to report, how
many Ships of <hi>London,</hi> and other parts of England haue
beene taken and made prey vnto them: without the help
of which English, the <hi>Turks</hi> by no means could haue go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned
and conducted them through their vnskilfulnes
and insufficiencie in the art of <hi>Nauigation:</hi> yet of late to
my wofull experience, I can witnes, they haue beene so
readied by the instruction of our apostate countrimen,
[I meane of <hi>Ward</hi> and others, who haue beene their
commanders] to tackle their Ships, to man and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
a fight, that if it doe not please God to moue the
heart of his Maiestie, and other Christian Princes, and
<pb facs="4"/>
states, to ioyne together for their speedy suppression,
and the disiointing of their late strengthned forces,
which continually encreaseth by the Ships of <hi>England,</hi>
and <hi>Holland,</hi> which they daily surprise, It will be disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious
to the state, and so dangerous to the common
wealth, in succeeding times, that Christendome must
expect no Trafficke at Sea: for they are alreadie grown
to the number of fifteene saile of great ships belonging
to <hi>Tunis,</hi> some bearing 40. some 30. and some 20. pecces
of ordinance, with men accordingly, as 300. 250. and
200. men at the least, in euery Ship, so that I doubt, and
the cause it selfe may breed a generall feare, that if ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition
be not hastened against them, the state may
heareafter share a part in that sorrow, which wee poore
Sea-faring men haue already suffered. I haue sent you
a note by <hi>Leanard Crowder,</hi> of diuerse ships, both <hi>English</hi>
and <hi>Dutch,</hi> that haue been taken since <hi>Ianuary</hi> last, which
although it be a businesse not much pertinent to gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
of your profession; yet I doe assure my selfe, that
you are so faithfull a wel-willer to the good estate and
prosperitie of the common-wealth, of which the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant
and Marriners are not the least members, that in
pitie of our losses sustained, with vs you could wish, and
expect a reformation, since the infinite wealth that our
nation hath suffered ruine of, by the <hi>Turks</hi> this last yeer
it were without doubt, incredible to report, since hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily
you haue heard, and I doubt not to prooue that
<hi>Londons</hi> losses hath amounted to aboue 200000. pound.
Thus hauing presented you at this time, but with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish
and taste of that which heereafter shall bee stored to
your expectation in a more ample and fuller feast, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech
you receiue this with my loue, in good part.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Alwaies desirous to be
commanded yours
ANDREVV BARKER.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>