<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104076_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03253</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13369</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104076</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true discourse of the two infamous upstart prophets, Richard Farnham weaver of White-Chappell, and Iohn Bull weaver of Saint Butolphs Algate, now prisoners, the one in Newgate, and the other in Bridewell : with their examinations and opinions taken from their owne mouthes April 16. anno 1636. As also of Margaret Tennis now prisoner in Old Bridewell, with the hereticall opinions held by her, at the same time examined. Written by T.H</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Lambert, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 19, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous <hi>Reader,</hi> we have here exposed to thy view New Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and expounders of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> but I must tell thee, farre differing from those of Old: They were called by <hi>God,</hi> but these have called (or rather miscalled) themselves: These scorne the names of <hi>Doctors,</hi> or <hi>Schollers,</hi> yet being plaine <hi>Weavers,</hi> (as you may see them discovered in the Frontispeece) understanding nothing themselves, will undertake to teach others: Such is the stupidity of blind Simplicity and
<pb facs="3"/>
Ignorance, of which these shuttle-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fellows are too much guilty: Nor are they to be much wondred at; for as <hi>Salomon</hi> saith, <hi>There is no new thing under the Sunne:</hi> So the World produceth now no Prodigies, the like of which it bath not before tee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. As for example, that Pseudocbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ftus <hi>Hacket,</hi> who for his fearefull blaspbemies was executed in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side,</hi> and whose Associates dyed mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably: and <hi>Legat,</hi> who of more late daies for maintaining the Arrian He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie was burnt in <hi>Smithfield:</hi> Let the nominating of these serve for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. <hi>Gentle Reader,</hi> this onely I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat thee in the perusall hereof, that though thou wondrest at their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; thou withall pitty their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>