<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all Christian Readers, especially Londoners, Audi∣tours, and friends to the late Godly Preachers, master Greenham and master Holland.</title>
           <author>Man, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104152_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03465</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13587</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104152</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all Christian Readers, especially Londoners, Audi∣tours, and friends to the late Godly Preachers, master Greenham and master Holland.</title>
                 <author>Man, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of Adam, or the foure-fold state of man, vvell formed in his creation, deformed in his corruption, reformed in Grace, and perfected in glory. By Mr. Henry Holland, late preacher at Saint Brides Church in London</title>
                 <author>Holland, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Man, Thomas 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 182, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To all Christian Readers, especially Londoners, Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, and friends to the late Godly Preachers, master <hi>Greenham</hi> and master <hi>Holland.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S by God his prouidence master <hi>Greenham</hi> did not liue to publish his owne works, but left them at large, which so had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished, had not master <hi>Holland</hi> vndertaken with much care, trauell, &amp; paines, to collect and diuulge them to the world for your good: so by the same hand ouer ruling all things, master <hi>Holland</hi> also tilled another mans vineyard, and left his owne vntilled through vntimely death. But God forbid, but that the names of such iust men should be had in euerlasting remembrance: therefore to you I commend this booke as the voice of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> preaching out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> bosome, and if euer you lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued either master <hi>Greenham,</hi> or master <hi>Holland</hi> while they were liuing, and especially the later, I do require you in the name of Iesus Christ, as you will answere both him and me at the appearing of our Sauiour, that you shew it now after his death. For your sakes he spent his life, yea, and lost his life; for his diligence in keeping his flock, &amp; teaching you in greatest extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie brought him to that sicknes, that cut off his daies. And seeing he had such an ardent desire to promote religion, &amp; considered that one day death would close his eyes, and earth stop his mouth from preaching, in priuate he collected these instructions, with an intent to imprint them, for your bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, when he should be in his graue. Now you haue them, through the care of his poore widdow, and charitie of the Printer, whereinto I haue added a discourse of our ioyes, and estate after the later day. I assure you by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this booke you shall better know your Generation, Degeneration, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation and Glorification, then in any other of this quantitie. I preiudge no mans labours, I honour all, I desire that all learned men would do their endeauour to preach when they be dead, (for our haruest will be all eaten vp in a winter to come.) I wish readers to lay aside scorne and rash iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, especially such as are idle themselues (for a spirituall man must be the doer, and not the iudge of the Law.) I pray God encrease the number of good labourers in his vineyard (for good pastours will be precious soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours in another age) and continue our blessed liberty of preaching, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing, writing and hearing of the Gospell of Christ. Farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours while he is able to preach, <hi>Edw. Topsell.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>