<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Don Alexis to the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1558</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104380_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16068</idno>
           <idno type="STC">293</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104380</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Don Alexis to the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The secretes of the reuerende Maister Alexis of Piemount : Containyng excellente remedies against diuers diseases, woundes, and other accidents, with the manner to make distillations, parfumes, confitures, diynges, colours, fusions and meltynges. ... Translated out of Frenche into Englishe, by Wyllyam Warde</title>
                 <author>Ruscelli, Girolamo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>England (Ingland), Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1558</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 123, 11 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>Don Alexis to the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey that haue knowen me in
time past, or to speake plaine,
haue vsed me familierly all my
lyfe time, can peraduenture,
tel how God by his great good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes,
hath made me to be borne
of a noble house and bloude
(accordinge to the commune,
I will not saye vayne, perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion
of them, that stablish nobilitie more in the merites
of another man, than in our own) and that besides this
I haue alwaies had my pleasures, and great plentie of
richesse, yea farre passing the smalnes of my desertes. I
wil say yet more (not to boast or to auaunce my self, but
to the ende to refourme the gentill reader, and to geue
thankes vnto God) that there be many whiche knowe,
how I being geuen euen from my first youth vnto stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
haue gotten, not onely the knowledge of the Latin,
Greke, Ebrue, Caldei, and Arabic tonge, and also of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
other nations and countreis: But aboue al thinge
hauinge by a natural inclination, taken a singuler plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sure
in Philosophy, and in the secretes of nature, haue
wandered and trauailed abroad in the worlde the space
of .xxvii. yeares, to the intent to acquainte my self with
all sortes of learned and discrete men. By the which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
and curiositie, I haue learned many goodlye se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes,
not alonely of men of great knowledge and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
learning, and noble men, but also of poore w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mē
artificers, peysantes, and all sortes of men. Moreouer I
haue ben thre times in Leuant, and sondry times haue
traua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>led almost all other partes of the world, without
resting or seiourning at any time in one place aboue .v.
moneths. Now this my study and desire of knowledge,
as well of the vniuersall sciences, as of particuler secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,
and althoughe it was geuen vnto me by nature, as
to the most part of men (for euery man by an instincte of
nature desyreth to knowe thinges) yet haue I alwayes
<pb facs="6"/>
been noseled vp by a certain ambition and vainglorie,
to knowe that, whiche an other should bee ignoraunte
of: whiche thyng hath grafted in me, a continuall nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardnesse
or sparing, to distribute or communicate any
of my secretes, yea vnto my moste singuler frendes that
I had: saiyng, that if the secretes were knowen of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
man, thei should no more bee called secretes, but pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike
and common.</p>
   <p>Now, it chaunced these fewe daies past, being in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan:
in the fowerskore and twoo yere, and seuen mone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes
of myne age, that a poore artificer was maruelou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sly
tourmented with the stone, and had been twoo daies
without making his vrine. The Cyrurgen that dressed
hym, knowyng well that I had many secretes, and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulerly
for the stone, came to me, and requested me that
I would teache hym the receipte, or at the least to giue
hym the medecine, composed and ready made, for the
health of the patiente. But I perceiuyng that he would
vse other mennes thinges, for his owne profite and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
refused to giue it hym, but willed hym to bryng
me vnto the sicke man, and that I my self would mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster
the medecine vnto him <hi>gratis.</hi> The Phisition, either
fearyng blame if it should bee knowen, that he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course
to the aide of an other man, hauyng peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
bosted that he had the secrete hymself, or els in the
meane tyme, still to make his profite in dissembling the
matter, and differryng it yet twoo daies more, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse
excuses and colours, vntill he brought me to the
patiente, whom at my commyng I founde so nigh his
ende, that after he had a little lifted vp his iyes, castyng
them pitiously towarde me, he passed from this into a
better life: not hauyng any neede, neither of my secrete
nor any other receipt to recouer his health. With this
cace I was moued to soche a compassion and sorowe,
that not onely I wisshed my self euill, but also I desired
to die: seyng my ambition and vain glorie, to haue been
the cause that this poore man was not succoured with
the remedy, and gifte that God the father, and Lorde of
<pb facs="6"/>
vs all had giuen me. Wherefore, so greate was the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse
of conscience in me, that, desiryng to sequestrate
my self frō the worlde, and not findyng my self of soche
a disposition of mynde, that I could liue in a Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie
emong religious menne, better edified then I, I
was at the laste fully resolued with my self, to choose a
place separate from any Toune, where I haue a little
lande, some bookes, and a studie, for to auoide idlenes.
Here I liue a life, whiche I call a Monkes life, with one
seruaunte, whiche goeth to the toune, not to begge, but
to buie my prouision, and other thynges necessarie: for
to sustaine his poore life and myne, as long as it shall
please God.</p>
   <p>But yet not hauyng the power to put out of my fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasie,
but that I was a verie homicide and murtherer,
for refusing to giue the Phisition the receipt and reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,
for the healyng of this poore manne, I haue deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
to publishe and communicate to the worlde, all
that I haue, beyng assured that fewe other menne haue
so many as I. And mindyng to set forth none, but soche
as bee moste true and proued, I haue these daies paste
(taken partly out of my Bookes, and partly out of my
memorie, all those that came to hand) made a collection
of soche as I am certaine bee veritable, true, and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented,
not caryng if some of theim be written, or
printed in any other Bookes then this. For of this my
collection the reader, as touchyng those, maie at the
least take this vtilitee and profite, that whereas before
he mought haue doubted, whether soche remedies sette
foorthe by an other manne, were true or not, he shall
bee now assured, vnder the affirmaunce of my faithe:
For truely, I would not sette my selfe (beeyng in the
age, and disposition, bothe of bodie and mynde, that
I am nowe in) to write fables or lies, that should
continue alwaies. But of one poyncte I wille ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertise
the reader, and that is, that he dooe the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
with good diligence, and that in medecines concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge
<pb facs="7"/>
mannes body, he vse the ayde and helpe of phisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:
Although in dede many of theim, moued with a
certaine rustick, and euyll grounded enuie, with a passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Ialousy, are wont to blame and contempne thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
that come not of them selues. Wherefore, as wel in
this, as in euerye other pointe, if he that will vse these,
should perchaunce finde, that the thing would not take
effecte according to his contentation, lette him beware
that he abuse not him self in the confection of them, and
to beginne againe with more diligence. Assuringe him
selfe, that (as I haue sayd) there is nothing in this boke
but is true and experimented. And geuing alwayes
glory and praise vnto god onely for all, haue a
good hope, that, by meane of his diuine
grace, I will consequentlye make you
a present of the rest of all that I
haue gotten in so manye
trauayles, voyages,
costes, and
diligente studye.</p>
   <closer>Fare well.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>