<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Sq, W.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104451_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06793</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17229</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104451</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Sq, W.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Newes from Mamora, or, A summary relation sent to the king of Spaine of the good successe of a voyage : which it hath pleased God to giue in taking, and suprising, of Mamora, a port in Barbary. By the armado and hoast royall, of the ocean sea, whereof was captaine generall Don Luis Faxardo: assisted with three galleis [sic] of Portingall, vnder the command of the Conde de Elda, and fiue gallies of Spaine, vnder the Duke of Fernandina</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 <publisher>Archer, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Political tracts</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE Reader,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>of late there came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hands a Relation, written in Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish, of the surprising of <hi>Mamora,</hi> a Port in Barbary, by the Army of the King of Spaine, as by that which ensueth more at large appeareth, which at the request of some friends I Translated, and with all thought it necessary to aduertise thee, that heerein I respected not so much exactnesse in Translating word for word out of the Originall, (whereby the matter must perforce loose its garb and graine) as I haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuored to declare the precise truth of each passage, according to the authors methode and intention.</p>
   <p>I was the rather induced to giue thee notice, for that, happily, some that are curious, and intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, in that language, comparing this with some Copies, or Manuscripts of this businesse, might taxe my fidelity, or vnderstanding: which to preuent, I inserted this briefe aduertisment, which with the discourse it selfe, I referre to thy perusall, thy selfe to GOD, and my selfe to thy good opinion:</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>London <date>the 28. of September: 1614.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>W. Squ.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>