<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To all Gentlemen, Merchants, and Pilots.</title>
           <author>F., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104896_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18057</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4699</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104896</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To all Gentlemen, Merchants, and Pilots.</title>
                 <author>F., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A shorte and briefe narration of the two nauigations and discoueries to the northweast partes called Newe Fraunce: first translated out of French into Italian, by that famous learned man Gio: Bapt: Ramutius, and now turned into English by Iohn Florio; worthy the reading of all venturers, trauellers, and discouerers</title>
                 <author>Cartier, Jacques</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 78, 2 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶To all Gentlemen, Merchants, and Pilots.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had taken in hande to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate thys Treatise, which I did for the benefite and behoofe of those that shall attempt any newe disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie in the Northweast partes of <hi>America,</hi> I thought good brieflye to touch the vse of my translation, that the Reader may see and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the drift of my trauell. For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this Discourse may seeme very barraine, and not to containe suche matter as is pretended, as beyng a particular Relation of certaine Prouinces whyche haue beene hitherto of all men rather contemned than throughly knowen: yet if the Marchant Venturer, or skilfull Pilot, or whosoeuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous of newe Discoueries, haue the readyng and perusing thereof, for whome especially I haue done it into Englishe, they will find matter worthy the looking, and consequently, gratefully accept my paines herein. For here is the Descrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Countrey no lesse fruitful and pleasant in al respects than is <hi>England, Fraunce,</hi> or <hi>Germany,</hi> the people, though sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and rude in manners, and destitute of the knowledge of God or any good lawes, yet of nature gentle and tractable, and most apt to receiue the Christian Religion, and to subiect themselues to some good gouernement: the commodities of the Countrey not inferiour to the Marchandize of <hi>Moscouy, Danske,</hi> or many other frequented trades: the voyage verye shorte, being but three weekes sayling from <hi>Bristowe, Plym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> or any commodious Porte of the Weast Country, with
<pb facs="4"/>
a direct course to the coast of the Newe found land. Al which oportunities besides manye others, mighte suffice to induce oure Englishemen, not onely to fall to some traffique wyth the Inhabitants, but also to plant a Colonie in some conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent place, and so to possesse the Countrey without the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saying of any man, whiche was the iudgement and counsell of <hi>Iohn Baptista Ramusius,</hi> a learned and excellent Cosmogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, &amp; Secretary to the famous state of <hi>Venice,</hi> whose words, bicause they are not impertinēt to this purpose, I haue here set downe. Why doe not the Princes (saieth he) whyche are to deale in these affaires, sende forth two or three Colonies to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite the Country, &amp; to reduce this sauage natiō to some ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilitie? considering what a battle and fruitfull soyle it is, how replenished with all kinde of graine, how it is stored wyth al sortes of Byrdes and Beastes, wyth such faire and mighty Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, that Captaine <hi>Carthier</hi> and his company, in one of them sayled vppe a hundreth and foure score leagues, findyng the countrey peopled on both sides in greate abundaunce. And moreouer, to cause the Gouernors of those Colonies to send forth men to search and discouer the North lands about <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra del Lauorader,</hi> and toward Weast northweast to the Seas whiche are to saile to the Country of <hi>Cataya,</hi> and from thence to the Ilands of <hi>Molucke.</hi> These were enterprises to purchase immortall praise, which the Lord <hi>Anthony di Mendoza</hi> Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy of <hi>Mexico,</hi> willing to put in execution, sent forth his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains both by Sea and by Land vpon the Northweast of <hi>Nuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua Spagona,</hi> and discouered the Kingdome of the seauen Cities about <hi>Ciuola</hi>▪ And <hi>Franciscus Vasques de Coronada,</hi> passed from <hi>Mexico</hi> by lande towarde the Northweast 2850. miles, in so muche, that he came to the Sea, whyche lyeth betweene <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taya</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> where he met with the Catayan shyppes. And no doubt, if the French men in this their newe <hi>Fraunce,</hi> would haue discouered vp further into the land towards the Weast northweast partes, they shoulde haue founde the Sea, and might haue sayled to <hi>Cataya.</hi> Thus much out of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>musius,</hi> where you may see this learned mans iudgement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="4"/>
the planting of Colonies, and inhabiting these coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, whych might be a meane, not only to discouer the Sea on the backe-side, as he desireth, but also to come vnto the knowledge of the Countries adiacent: and namely of <hi>Sague<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay,</hi> whiche aboundeth with Golde and other Mettalles, as in the seconde Relation is to be seene. All whyche thyngs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte they builde and inhabite, can neuer be atchieued, for as <hi>Fraunciscus Lopez di Gomara,</hi> and dyuers other Spanishe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors affirme, the Spanyards neuer prospered or preuailed, but where they planted: whych of the Portingales maye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so be verifyed, as in the Histories of all theyr Conquests and Discoueries doth manifestly appeare. And as there is none, that of right may be more bolde in this enterprice than the Englishmen, the land being first found out by <hi>Iohn Gabot</hi> the Father, and <hi>Sebastian Gabot,</hi> one of hys three sonnes, in the yeare 1494. in the name and be halfe of King <hi>Henry</hi> the sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth, as both by the foresaide <hi>Ramusius</hi> in his first Volumes, and our owne Chronicles, and <hi>Sebastian Gabots</hi> letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents yet extant, and in his Mappe maye be seene: so there is no nation that hath so good righte, or is more fit for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, than they are, who trauayling yearely into those partes with 50. or 60. saile of shippes, might very commodiouslye transporte a sufficient number of men to plant a Colonie in some conuenient Hauen, and also might yeeld them yearly succour, and supply of al things necessary, receyuing againe such commodities as the country doth produce. And this the Frenchmen had done long since, if first their warres with the Spanyardes, and since their cruell dissentions at home, had not hindered them. And <hi>Iohannes Varrozzana</hi> a Florentine, if he had not beene preuented by death, purposed (as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayde <hi>Ramusius</hi> writeth) to perswade <hi>Francis</hi> the French King to send forth good store of people to inhabite certaine places of these coastes, where the aire is moste temperate, and the soyle moste fruitfull, with goodly Riuers and Hauens suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to harborough any nauie, the inhabitantes of which pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces might be occasiō to bring many good purposes to effecte,
<pb facs="5"/>
and amongest manye others, to reduce those poore rude and ignorant people to the true worship and seruice of God, and to teache them how to manure and till the ground, transpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ouer Beastes and Cattell of <hi>Europe</hi> into those large and champion countreys, and finally, in time they might discouer vp into the land, and search, whether among so many Ilands as are there, there be any passage to the Sea of <hi>Cataya.</hi> And thus much oute of the third Volume of Voyages and Naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, gathered into the Italian tongue by <hi>Ramusius:</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Bookes, if they were translated into English by the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of some noble Personage, ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Sea-men of <hi>England,</hi> and others, studious of Geographie, shoulde know many worthy secrets, whiche hitherto haue beene concealed. For, the beste Cosmographers of this age (as I am by the skilfull in those Sciences informed, and as to him that doth diligently consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Mappes, it shall plainely appeare) haue described <hi>Asia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> chiefly by the help of those bookes. But to returne to that from whence I did digresse, althoughe some attemptes of oure Countrey-men haue not had as yet suche successe as was wished, they ought not therefore to bee the slower in this enterprice, for if they were of late conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their voyage, to haue stayed al the Winter in those col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Countries, if their store of victualles had beene sufficient, howe muche rather ought we nowe in a farre more tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate clime, where <hi>Iames Carthier,</hi> accompanyed wyth <hi>120.</hi> men remained a whole Winter contrary to hys determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on when he set out of <hi>Fraunce?</hi> Thus beseeching God, that this my trauel may take that effect for the which it is meant, I commende the diligent consideration to al such Gentlemen, Merchants, and Pilots, as seeke Gods glory, the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Countrey, and the happy successe, to the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Almighty, who in my opinion hath not in vaine stirred vppe the mindes of so many Honourable and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull persons to the furtheraunce of these commendable and worthy Discoueries.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>In Oxford▪</hi>
      </dateline>
      <signed>I. F.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>