<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1625</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104038_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03149</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13277</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104038</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mikrokosmos : A little description of the great world. Augmented and reuised. By Peter Heylyn</title>
                 <author>Heylyn, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Oxford</pubPlace>
                    <date>1625</date>
                 <publisher>Huggins, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Lichfield, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Turner, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 380, 391-812, 2 pages, folded table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>RObora parentum liberi indicant.</hi> The growth of the children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the strength of the parent. For this cause the warlike nation of the <hi>Germans,</hi> ordained▪ that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage should be delaied in their young men, and not hastned in their Virgins. Had I obserued that due proportion of age, in begetting the issue of my bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e, which they did in the issue of their bodies: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it had not now needed a second generation, nor I a second de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery. The wants and weaknesses, with which this my <hi>First-borne</hi> came burdened into the world; I desire may be imputed to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age</hi> of his parent, and the <hi>vntimelinesse</hi> of his birth; either a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect sufficient to cause an <hi>abortion.</hi> I haue lately (good Reader) new-begotten him, and brought him to that strength and stature thou now soest. I am not the first of whom it was said, <hi>secundae co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitationes sunt meliores:</hi> neither is it a thing rare for children of this nature, to be as often perfected, as borne. Bookes haue an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality aboue their Authors. They, when they are full of age, and guiltinesse, can be re-taken into the wombe which bred them: and with a new life, receaue a greater portion of youth and glory. Every impression is to them another being: and that alwaies may, and often doth bring with it, a sweeter addition of strength &amp; loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse. Thus with them, age, &amp; each seuerall death, is but an vsher to a new birth: each severall birth the mother of a more vigorous perfection. The truth is, in my former Edition of this worke, I dealt with <hi>pettie chapmen,</hi> pedlers of <hi>History</hi> and <hi>Geography:</hi> wit i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> them I tooke vp my faults vpon trust; and had a happinesse which some want; autoritie for mine <hi>Errours.</hi> N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>w a three yeares addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of age, and a little of iudgement; hath brought me acquainted with elder reading, <hi>Marchants of the best sort:</hi> according to whose helps I haue <hi>augmented and reuised</hi> my former trauells.</p>
   <p>At the first, there went to the making vp of this <hi>Little world,</hi> these six integrall parts, <hi>History, Geography, Policie, Theology, Chronologie,</hi> and <hi>Heraldrie.</hi> It is now enlarged in all those parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, &amp; in nothing is deficient which the other did afford thee, but the faults. To these I haue vpon diuerse occasions added diuerse <hi>Philologicall</hi> discourses; not much impertinent to the places, wherein they are inferred. At the worst, thou canst but call them
<pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>Digressions;</hi> I am sure they are not <hi>Extrauagancies. Digred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> nos patimur, non diuagar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> saith <hi>Tully.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These additions and corrections haue swelled the volume big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then I expected: yet if to thee the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ngth of it be not offensiue; to me it shall n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t. It is now come to a iust growth, and hath recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued my last hand. Hereafter I will looke on it, only as a stranger. Thou needst not feare any future enlargements, which may make thee repent thy present markets. I haue now giuen ouer these youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger studies; and, beleeue me, 'twas more then time: for I gazed so long on the porch, that I had almost forgotten to goe into the house. If euer I am induced to look further into it, it shall be only to amend such crimes, whereof a cleerer iudgement then mine owne can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme me. For my part, I see not any: and when thou hast by the <hi>Errata</hi> corrected the Copy: I dare almost perswade my selfe, thou wilt (for materiall faults I meane) pronounce it, <hi>not guilty.</hi> Yet I exempt not my selfe from the common frailtie of nature; possibility of erring. Tis a misery from which <hi>his Holinesse,</hi> euen when he sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on his very <hi>Porphyry chaire,</hi> is not priuiledged. When by the strength of mine owne iudgement, or any ingenuous information, I am convicted: I will at once confesse my ouersight, and mend it.</p>
   <p>Thus haue I laid before thee, as in a Map, all that I haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, in this <hi>new creation</hi> of this <hi>Little world:</hi> in which I haue equally endeauoured thy good, and mine owne credit. To petition thy good opinion of my labours, is a thing infinitely below me. This were rather to extort commendation, then deserue it. Such re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests are punished in themselues; and need no wretchednesse with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them. The fauours they aime at, haue somewhat in them, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to ignoble quarrells, <hi>vbi &amp; vincere inglorium est; &amp; atteri, sordidum:</hi> and are not more infamous in the deniall, then the suit. A modest and voluntary acknowledgment of my industrie, I would gladly entertaine; but not invite. Guests of this qualitie, when they bid themselues, bring with them their owne welcome. When they come vpon entreatie, they come vnwillingly: and are not then receaued, but rauisht. Good Reader, iudge of me, as thou findest me worthie: for my selfe, I am neither ambitious of applause, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of censure. Giue me leaue so farre to be mine owne para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> as to flatter my paines, in the words and hope of <hi>Tacitus: hic inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim liber, aut laudatus erit, aut saltem excusatus.</hi> Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>