<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY EVER HONOVRED FRIENDS, THOSE MOST REFINED Wits and fauorers of most exquisite learning, Mr. M. Drayton, Mr. Will. Browne, and my ingenious Kinsman, Mr. Andrew Pol∣lexsen (all knowne vnto me) and to the rest (vn∣knowne) the Poets of these times, S. A. wisheth the accomplishment of all true happi∣nesse.</title>
           <author>Austin, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104457_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23268</idno>
           <idno type="STC">971</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104457</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY EVER HONOVRED FRIENDS, THOSE MOST REFINED Wits and fauorers of most exquisite learning, Mr. M. Drayton, Mr. Will. Browne, and my ingenious Kinsman, Mr. Andrew Pol∣lexsen (all knowne vnto me) and to the rest (vn∣knowne) the Poets of these times, S. A. wisheth the accomplishment of all true happi∣nesse.</title>
                 <author>Austin, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Avstins Vrania, or, The heavenly mvse : in a poem fvll of most feeling meditations for the comfort of all soules, at all times: by S.A. B. of Arts of Ex. Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Austin, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                            <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 136 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>TO MY EVER HONOVRED FRIENDS, THOSE MOST REFINED Wits and fauorers of most exquisite learning, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>M. Drayton,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Will. Browne,</hi> and my ingenious Kinsman, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Andrew Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexsen</hi> (all knowne vnto me) and to the rest (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne) the Poets of these times, <hi>S. A.</hi> wisheth the accomplishment of all true happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</head>
   <head type="sub">
      <hi>Austins</hi> aduertisement.</head>
   <l>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Noblest Friends! you that deriue your birth</l>
   <l>From some thing that's more excellent then earth,</l>
   <l>From some sweet influence, or some Deitie</l>
   <l>That liues aboue the base capacitie</l>
   <l>Of ignorant Spheares (those rude vntutor'd braines,</l>
   <l>That neuer trauell'd farther then their Plaines</l>
   <l>To learne of ought, but Heards, and Flocks, or how</l>
   <l>They might dispose a Cart, or guide a Plow:)</l>
   <l>To you alone I write, what I of late</l>
   <l>Haue scene and heard; the lamentable state</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="9"/>Of these our latter iron times; and hence</l>
   <l>It is I speake from sad experience:</l>
   <l>The matter's this: Occasion did inuite</l>
   <l>Me hence of late to take a Summers-sight</l>
   <l>Of our farre-famouz'd London, where when I</l>
   <l>Was come, I tooke an opportunitie</l>
   <l>For venting of these plaints of mine, which here</l>
   <l>My <hi>Vran</hi> 'hath brought forth with many a teare,</l>
   <l>And speakelesse pang of griefe, with losse of time</l>
   <l>Most precious to my soule: (O that a rime</l>
   <l>So poore as this should cost so deare!) but lo,</l>
   <l>When I would faine haue let these waters flow</l>
   <l>Abroad vnto my Countrimen, I went</l>
   <l>To see how well our Stationers were bent</l>
   <l>To further me herein: but they reply,</l>
   <l>Sure 'twill not take, for 'tis Diuinitie:</l>
   <l>Poems diuine are nothing worth; but if</l>
   <l>I had portray'd a pretty Sea of griefe</l>
   <l>For some lost Mistresse; or compos' a toy</l>
   <l>Of loue in verse, this would haue been a Boy</l>
   <l>Worth the conception, each would take it vp</l>
   <l>And play with it: or had I but a cup</l>
   <l>Of strong-breath'd Satyres mixt with spleene &amp; gall,</l>
   <l>And could but powre it handsomely to fall</l>
   <l>Vpon some high-mans head, Oh, this would take</l>
   <l>Eu'n like Tobacco, each Barbours shop would make</l>
   <l>A sale of it: or had I but the time</l>
   <l>Neately to weaue some loose-lasciuious rime,</l>
   <l>Stuft with conceits of wantonnesse, Oh then</l>
   <l>I had been call'd one of the Wits; for men</l>
   <l>Must haue their humours, now they say; but this</l>
   <l>Is quite against them; euery one will hisse</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="9"/>It off the Stage. And is it so, thought I?</l>
   <l>Why then, 'tis time for our Diuinitie</l>
   <l>To stirre her selfe, and speake in Ʋerse if she</l>
   <l>Can ought perswade; O what a miserie</l>
   <l>Is like to fall vpon this age! when men</l>
   <l>Shall so forget themselues, as turne agen</l>
   <l>To their first veines of childishnesse, and will</l>
   <l>Giue any price to buy each toy of ill;</l>
   <l>But will not giue a straw for good, altho</l>
   <l>It be to saue their very soules? What wo</l>
   <l>And horror's this, when men grow desperate,</l>
   <l>To buy damnation at so deare a rate,</l>
   <l>To pay a price for hell, but will not giue</l>
   <l>A pin for heau'n? O that my soule should liue</l>
   <l>To see such drearie dayes as these! But now,</l>
   <l>Since things are so, what shall I say, or vow,</l>
   <l>Or doe to make them otherwise? Why sure,</l>
   <l>Great friends! my present suit's to you, whose pure</l>
   <l>And heau'nly essences doe plainely say,</l>
   <l>You are Diuine: let me presume to pray,</l>
   <l>And challenge you on all those bonds that be</l>
   <l>'Twixt God and you; 'twixt heau'ns eternitie</l>
   <l>In blissefulnesse, and your deare soules, that hence</l>
   <l>You aide me on with your high eloquence,</l>
   <l>And heau'n-commanding tenors, to reuerse</l>
   <l>(If our Diuinitie can ought in Ʋerse)</l>
   <l>Those strong opposing humours of this age,</l>
   <l>This wayward madnesse, this prepostrous rage</l>
   <l>Of humane hearts which gape so greedily</l>
   <l>To swallow sinne, and drinke iniquitie</l>
   <l>Like water (as the <note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 15.16.</note> Scripture speakes) but good</l>
   <l>They will not taste so much, lest their ill blood</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="10"/>Should be <note n="b" place="margin">Infected, I say, because wicked men account goodnesse as grieuous a plague to them, as the godly doe wickednesse, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to be shunned, for feare it should dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbe their former course of cursed merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and put them to the paines of blessed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, whereby they might liue anew vnto God, and be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> infected by't, and so perchance</l>
   <l>They might be drawne from hellish ignorance</l>
   <l>Into the glorious light of Grace, whereby</l>
   <l>They might be brought to heauens felicity,</l>
   <l>Before they were aware of't. O my soule!</l>
   <l>What fury's this? How should we not controle</l>
   <l>Such stupid waywardnesse, when now aday</l>
   <l>Men labour more (it seemes) to finde the way</l>
   <l>That leades to hell, then euer heretofore</l>
   <l>The Saints for heauen? O, how should I deplore</l>
   <l>This wretched hum'rousnesse? How should I chide</l>
   <l>My Countrimen for this, that they'le abide</l>
   <l>This cursed <hi>Achan</hi> to remaine so long</l>
   <l>Within their tents, which hath done all the wrong,</l>
   <l>Our Countrey hath of late endur'd, how-ere</l>
   <l>Some ignorant braines thinke otherwise. But here,</l>
   <l>O that I might obtaine but this of them,</l>
   <l>Which is, that these my deare-wise-Countrimen</l>
   <l>Would onely duly thinke vpon, and wey</l>
   <l>The way wherein they goe, knowing when they</l>
   <l>Haue had their filles of vanitie, at last</l>
   <l>They must expect a change, that fearefull blast</l>
   <l>Of the last Trumpe will one day <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 24.31. 1. Cor. 15.52.</note> sound, and then</l>
   <l>That dreary doome also will fall on them,</l>
   <l>
      <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 25.41.</note> Depart from me yee curst, and they must goe</l>
   <l>Into those prisons of eternall woe,</l>
   <l>The deepes of euerlasting hell, where they</l>
   <l>Shall be in paine beyond conceite; no day</l>
   <l>Or instant shall giue ease to them, but still</l>
   <l>They shall drinke vp those poys'nous drugs of ill,</l>
   <l>Hells most reuengefull torturings, if they</l>
   <l>Doe not repent themselues while 'tis to day;</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="10"/>I meane, ere deaths blacke night approach. O then</l>
   <l>Thinke you on this, my dearest Countrimen.</l>
   <l>And thou, deare <hi>Drayton!</hi> let thy aged Muse</l>
   <l>Turne now diuine; let her forget the vse</l>
   <l>Of thy earst pleasing tunes of loue, (which were</l>
   <l>But fruits of witty youth:) let her forbeare</l>
   <l>These toyes, I say, and let her now breake forth</l>
   <l>Thy latest gaspe in heau'nly sighes, more worth</l>
   <l>Then is a world of all the rest; for this</l>
   <l>Will vsher thee to heau'ns eternall blisse:</l>
   <l>And let thy strong-perswasiue straines enforce</l>
   <l>These times into a penitent remorce</l>
   <l>For this their sinfull frowardnesse; and then</l>
   <l>Heau'n shall reward thee, neuer care for <note n="e" place="margin">That is, the esteeme, or respects of meere car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall men.</note> men.</l>
   <l>And honour'd <hi>Willy,</hi> thou whose maiden straines</l>
   <l>Haue sung so sweetly of the Vales and Plaines</l>
   <l>Of this our Ile, that all the men that be</l>
   <l>Thy hearers, are enforc'd to honour thee,</l>
   <l>Yea, and to fall in loue with thee; I say,</l>
   <l>Let me intreate thee to transport thy Lay</l>
   <l>From earth to heau'n: for sure thy Muses bee</l>
   <l>So good, the Gods will fall in loue with thee,</l>
   <l>As well as men: besides, 'tis fit thy Layes</l>
   <l>Should scorne all Crowns, saue heau'ns eternal Bayes.</l>
   <l>Then bid the world farewell with <note n="f" place="margin">
         <hi>vid. Sydneys</hi> last Sonnet at the end of his Arcadia.</note>
      <hi>Sydney,</hi> (he</l>
   <l>That was the Prince of English Poesie,)</l>
   <l>And ioyne with me (the worst of all thy traine)</l>
   <l>To bring these times into a better straine.</l>
   <l>And dearest <hi>Pol'sfen,</hi> last of all the three,</l>
   <l>Which should be first by that affinitie</l>
   <l>And int'rest that thou hast in me; I here</l>
   <l>Intreate thy helpe amongst the rest, whose deare</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="11"/>And precious apprehensions reach so high,</l>
   <l>As nought but heau'n, or pure Diuinitie</l>
   <l>Should be the subiect of thy straines: for they</l>
   <l>Are farre too good e're to be cast away</l>
   <l>On earth's base worthlesse vanities, which be</l>
   <l>At best but emblems of mortalitie,</l>
   <l>So soone they die, and quaile away: but thine,</l>
   <l>Thy wits, I meane, are heau'nly and diuine</l>
   <l>Emblems of Euerlastingnesse, and can</l>
   <l>Create conceits were neuer form'd by man,</l>
   <l>No, nor so much as thought vpon, ere thou</l>
   <l>Thy selfe gan'st being vnto them: but now,</l>
   <l>Since things are thus proportion'd out, I pray</l>
   <l>Come aide me with that heau'n-commanding sway</l>
   <l>Of thy high Ʋerse, which rather will compell</l>
   <l>Men to be mad, then let them goe to hell</l>
   <l>In such a childish hum'rousnesse; nay, will</l>
   <l>Enforce them to be good against their will,</l>
   <l>If they can be so dull, or voide of sense,</l>
   <l>As not loue goodnesse for selfe-excellence;</l>
   <l>Whose sweet and louely fairenesse at first sight</l>
   <l>Without gaine-say obtaines a soueraigne right</l>
   <l>Ore all ingenious hearts, at least if Grace</l>
   <l>Reside in them; then nothing else takes place.</l>
   <l>Come then, I say, deare <hi>Drayton, Browne</hi> and thou,</l>
   <l>And all the rest that euer made a Vow</l>
   <l>To keepe the Muses sacred Lawes, come here</l>
   <l>And ioyne with me, let neither loue, nor feare</l>
   <l>Make you proue partiall, till this <note n="g" place="margin">The ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour which preferre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> before goodnesse, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> vpon any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ly re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>spect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> hum'rous rage</l>
   <l>Be banisht quite from off our Englands Stage:</l>
   <l>What shall I vrge you more? or why intreate?</l>
   <l>Your Wisdomes see the cause is wondrous great,</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="11"/>That craues your helpe; nay more, it craues the Pen</l>
   <l>And tongue of our best <note n="h" place="margin">Preachers, diuinest Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors.</note> Angels too: for men</l>
   <l>Must not be humour'd thus in ill: or if</l>
   <l>It should be so, sure, goodnesse then for griefe</l>
   <l>Would run away, or hide her selfe, when she</l>
   <l>Should be discourag'd thus, alas! and we</l>
   <l>That honour her, should not once dare to speake,</l>
   <l>O, 'twere enough to make our hearts to breake.</l>
   <l>Be valiant then, my friends, and let all those</l>
   <l>That wish our England well, and hate her foes;</l>
   <l>Be of like minde with vs, yea, those that bee</l>
   <l>The <note n="i" place="margin">Chiefe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, who can do most in this case.</note> Princes of our Ile; so shall we see</l>
   <l>Our England flourish spight of Pope, and all</l>
   <l>That thirst with bloody hearts to see her fall.</l>
   <l>So Goodnesse shall proue Conquerour, but ill</l>
   <l>Shall not dare shew it selfe within this Hill</l>
   <l>And holy Mountaine of our God, which he</l>
   <l>Preserues by speciall prouidence; and we</l>
   <l>To see it thus, with gladsome hearts shall sing</l>
   <l>Our thanks to God, who rays'd so good a King</l>
   <l>To sit on our late <hi>Dauids</hi> Throne; and may</l>
   <l>He grow as great, as good, still let vs pray:</l>
   <l>Yea, Peeres, and all, ioyne with my humble Pen,</l>
   <l>And so let all the people say, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </l>
   <closer>
      <signed>The true well-willer and seruant of you all in the Lord Iesus, <hi>S. A.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>