<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right VVorshipfull and worthy Fauourer of Learning and nourisher of vertue: Sir Iohn Linwraye Knight, Master Surueyer of all his Maiesties Ordinance within his Highnes Realmes of England &amp; Ireland: Nich. Bre∣ton wisheth encrease of all happi∣nesse on earth, and the ioyes of heauen heere∣after.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104769_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16767</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3674</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104769</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right VVorshipfull and worthy Fauourer of Learning and nourisher of vertue: Sir Iohn Linwraye Knight, Master Surueyer of all his Maiesties Ordinance within his Highnes Realmes of England &amp; Ireland: Nich. Bre∣ton wisheth encrease of all happi∣nesse on earth, and the ioyes of heauen heere∣after.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An olde mans lesson, and a young mans loue. By Nicholas Breton</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right VVorshipfull and worthy Fauourer of Learning and nourisher of vertue: Sir <hi>Iohn Linwraye</hi> Knight, Master Surueyer of all his Maiesties Ordinance within his Highnes Realmes of <hi>England &amp; Ireland: Nich. Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> wisheth encrease of all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse on earth, and the ioyes of heauen heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue often noted, that the wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of experience, hath bene the Schoole of a good wit, where youth giuing eare to age, may the better determine of his courses: And againe, that nature weying loue with reason, worketh the best effectes of vnderstanding. The truth of this you may finde made good in this little Dialogue, where the Father kindely deales with the Sonnes duetie, and the Sonnes loue, with the Fathers discretion: many prettie tractes haue passed among them, where each was so pleased in the Summarie of their discourse, that, if all Fathers would be as kinde, and all Children as wise, there would be a blessed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth: but the world is to be weyed as it is, and their rules to bee made examples of much good: the discourse is Diagolicall, and the varietie not vnpleasant:
<pb facs="3"/>
where nature with wit, wit with learning, and learning with iudgement, may prooue some paines in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and worthie patience in the reading. Such as it is (with my better seruice) I cōmēd to your good fauour, hoping that as in this little you may see my loue, so in a greater seruice, you will commaund the bonds of my affection: in which, with hearts thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse▪ for your euer vndeserued kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: I take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours Deuoted and obliged</hi>: Nich. Breton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>