<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the friendlie and Chri∣stian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104468_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23383</idno>
           <idno type="STC">981</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104468</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the friendlie and Chri∣stian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A meruailous combat of contrarieties : Malignantlie striuing in the me [m] bers of mans bodie, allegoricallie representing vnto vs the enuied state of our florishing common wealth: wherin dialogue-wise by the way, are touched the extreame vices of this present time. VVith a earnest and vehement exhortation to all true English harts, couragiously to be readie prepared against the enemie. by W.A</title>
                 <author>Averell, W. (William)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>54 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the friendlie and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HREE sorts of people (courteous Reader) I
knowe there are, that will dislike, and discommend
that which I shall write, the first are our proude
<hi>Dares,</hi> that are as farre in loue with themselues as
<hi>Narcissus,</hi> and our wanton wiues and mincing
minions, that all day pranke themselues at the Glasse, like daintie
Misteris <hi>Acco.</hi> The second are our gluttonous <hi>Sanctrae</hi> that
for their feeding and vnmeasurable drinking, may better be called
<hi>Beotians</hi> then Englishmen: and the third are our couchant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists
that priuilie lurke in corners, to bring euery thing in disgrace,
that is not for their purpose, nor serues (as we say) for their tooth.
These peraduenture beeing gauled, cannot abide to haue their sore
rubbed, like to <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> that because he had but one
eye himselfe, was angry when any man talked of a <hi>Cyclop,</hi> or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
a gogle eye, or spake of any that had but one of his eyes: Or
like <hi>Hyrmeas,</hi> that beeing himselfe an Eunuch, coulde not abide
to heare of a Raser, or a knife, or anie man that was cutte, because
he was himselfe a gelding. Wherfore if we touch these men, it must
be <hi>figurate</hi> but not <hi>aperte,</hi> closelie and cunninglie, not openly nor
plainely, for if we doe, we vtterly lose their good wil, but as for these
I count not, onely I wish them better mindes, with a sound amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of their liues.</p>
   <p>The rest that are well disposed, I earnestlie desire to beare
with whatsoeuer faultes haue eyther hastilie scaped my handes in
wryting, or the Printers presse in printing.</p>
   <p>I am not <hi>Roscius in Scena,</hi> I knowe manie coulde better
haue handled this Theame, yet I friendly request thy patience,
<pb facs="4"/>
and gentle acceptance of that I haue written, knowing that if thou
haue iudgment, thou wilt not be a <hi>Lynx,</hi> in prying too narrowlie
into my ouer-sights, but rather a <hi>Mole,</hi> in not seeing mine infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.
That I haue written hath beene for thy profit and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,
my selfe in labouring haue felt the payne, all the reward I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde
is thy good worde, which if I may haue I am satisfied,
and so reposing my selfe thereon I ende, wyshing thee health
and long life, with the fruition of heauenlie
ioyes. Farewell.
(∴)</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>