<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Hono∣rable
Mister George Bonde, Lord
Maior of London, much health,
and happy successe through out hys
whole gouernment.</title>
           <author>Averell, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104468_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23383</idno>
           <idno type="STC">981</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104468</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Hono∣rable
Mister George Bonde, Lord
Maior of London, much health,
and happy successe through out hys
whole gouernment.</title>
                 <author>Averell, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A meruailous combat of contrarieties : Malignantlie striuing in the me [m] bers of mans bodie, allegoricallie representing vnto vs the enuied state of our florishing common wealth: wherin dialogue-wise by the way, are touched the extreame vices of this present time. VVith a earnest and vehement exhortation to all true English harts, couragiously to be readie prepared against the enemie. by W.A</title>
                 <author>Averell, W. (William)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>54 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ister George Bonde, Lord
Maior of London, much health,
and happy successe through out hys
whole gouernment.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue reade right Honourable,
<hi>Ʋirtutem esse bonum commune pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triac,</hi>
that virtue is the common
profit of our Countrie, and that
he is not to bee honoured with
the noble name of virtue, which
doth not wholy apply his mind
freely to profit manie, and to
seeke the cōmoditie of others:
which made <hi>Cicero</hi> to say, that if
there were a question, or comparison, to whom wee ought
to shew most duetie, our Countrey &amp; Parents ought chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
to be regarded, vnto whom we are bound by many bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits:
And <hi>Cicero</hi> did not alone say it, but by his owne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
confirmed it, when beeing Consul of <hi>Rome,</hi> through his
singular diligence, and painfull watchfulnes, he both preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
the Cittie from the secret conspiracies of <hi>Catiline,</hi> and
also repressed his violent attempts, that fully purposed the
ouerthrow of his Countrey: so that hee might iustly say of
himselfe as hee did, <hi>O fortunatam natam me Consule Roma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>;</hi>
O happie <hi>Rome</hi> in the time that I was Consul. Your selfe
(right Honorable) may in these dangerous daies, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
times, worthily deserue <hi>Ciceros</hi> praise, that are so careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
occupied, painfully busied, and watchfully prepared, not
onlie to preuent by warie foresight all priuie attempts that
noisome vipers, and hurtful Traytors, either by night or day
<pb facs="3"/>
shall practise against this honorable and famous Cittie, but
are ready bent valiantly to defende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t, though with losse of
your owne life, rather then it should in the least part bee
harmed, or the inhabitants thereof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> wayes iniuried.</p>
   <p>The valour of your antique predecessors, are yet to bee
seene in the armes of your honorable Cittie, and shall for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
remaine in the minds of all posteritie, whose glorie wee
see you emulate, and to which, your watchfulnes and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
diligence will make you equiualent, if in these stormie
tempesteous times, you shall (like a warie and heedfull Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot)
skilfully (as you haue begunne) continue to holde the
helme in this Ship of your gouernment, and happily guide
it from blustering vvindes, and wallovving vvaues of secret
malicious enemies: which the more they are, dooth make
you more carefull, and the more secret, farre more watchful.</p>
   <p>The time wherein you gouerne, may wel be compared to
the time of <hi>Catiline,</hi> but that in this point it is far more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous,
for that we haue not one <hi>Catiline</hi> that purposeth the
ruine of our Cittie, but manie: &amp; as <hi>Cicero</hi> sayd at that time,
<hi>Crescit in dics singulos hostium numerus,</hi> so may we say, the nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of our enemies doo still encrease, yet vvill not we stande
vppon that vvhich he did, neither doe I thinke you of his
mind, that either our nightly watches (vvhich God knowes
are but slender) the garrison of our Cittie, the strength of
our people, the vnitie of our mindes, the counsels of your
Senate, or such like can preserue vs, but that our God, euen
for the glory of his name, and for his mercy sake will defend
vs, that neither their counsels or conspiracies shall euer bee
able to hurt vs. And albeit they doe <hi>intestinam aliquam quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
perniciem reipublicae moliri,</hi> deuise dailie some secret and
deadlie destruction of our common vvealth, yet I doubt not
but first by Gods mercie, and then through the prouident
care of you and our Magistrates, not alone this Cittie, but
the whole land shalbe preserued from their malice, and they
thēselues fall into the pit that they haue digged for others,
<pb facs="3"/>
as <hi>Catiline</hi> did, with his conspiratours.</p>
   <p>I haue printed your Honors name in the forehead of this
my Booke, not because I wanted patrons to defend it, (for
vvho in this time will not esteeme the faithfull good vvill of
a louing Subiect, that zealously seeketh the profit of hys
Countrey) but for that I heare and see your honors care, &amp;
vvatchfulnes deserues it, &amp; to depriue the vertuous of their
praise, vvere nothing els but meere enuie and secret malice.
Wherefore as I vvillinglie dedicate this vnto your Honor:
so I beseech you gratefully accept it, and defend it against all
the malitious tongues of enuious and slaunderous Papists,
vvhose mouthes either I desire the Lorde God to stop, and
conuert their harts, or els confound them, that they may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
see their desires.</p>
   <p>And so wishing your Honour to prosper in all your
counselles and that you take in hand. I
cease to trouble you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
further.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all duety to
commaunde,
William Auerell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>