<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>
To the Right Honorable, and most noble-minded Lorde, VVilliam Stanley, Earle of Darby, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Barnefeild, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104851_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68287</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1484</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104851</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>
To the Right Honorable, and most noble-minded Lorde, VVilliam Stanley, Earle of Darby, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Barnefeild, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cynthia : VVith certaine sonnets, and the legend of Cassandra</title>
                 <author>Barnfield, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Humphrey 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <pb facs="2"/>
To the Right Honorable, and most noble-minded Lorde, VVilliam Stanley, Earle of Darby, &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Honorable, the dutifull affection I beare to your manie vertues, is cause, that to manifest my loue to your Lordship, I am constrained to shew my simplenes to the world. Many are they that admire your worth, of the which number, I (though the meanest in abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie▪ yet with the formost in affection) am one that most desire to serue, and onely to serue your Honour.</p>
   <p>Small is the gift, but great is my good-will; the which, by how much the lesse I am able to expresse it, by so much the more it is infinite. Liue long▪ and inherit your Predecessors ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
<pb facs="3"/>
as you doe their dignitie and estate. This is my wish: the which your honorable excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent giftes doe promise me to obtaine: and whereof these few rude and vnpollished lines, are a true (though an vndeseruing) testimony. If my ability were better, the signes should be greater; but being as it is, your honour must take me as I am, not as I should be. My yeares being so young, my perfection cannot be great: But howsoeuer it is, yours it is; and I my selfe am yours; in all humble seruice, most ready to be commaunded.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Richard Barnefeilde.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>