<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Poem touching the credit of
this Newes, with an item to them,
that takes felicitie in publishing
Lies.</title>
           <author>B., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S1049_Bo1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00234</idno>
           <idno type="STC">1030.7</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S1049</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Poem touching the credit of
this Newes, with an item to them,
that takes felicitie in publishing
Lies.</title>
                 <author>B., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nevves out of France for the gentlemen of England : A stratagem most ventrously attempted, and valiantly atchiued by the French King, the 27. day of Iuly. anno Domini 1591. Wherein is desciphered, what trust his royall Maiestie reposeth on the valour of the English, and their duetifull seruice vnto him at all assayes. Newes also touching 16. shippes taken nigh the hauen of Deepe, and the discomfiture of the Popes forces transported into France towards the ayde of the Leaguers, both concurring on the 28. of Iuly last past. VVith a report of the princely meeting, and honorable conioyning of the whole power of the French King the sixt day of this present moneth of August, consisting of English, Germane, and his owne people</title>
                 <author>G. B.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Kid (Kyd), John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>A Poem touching the credit of
this Newes, with an item to them,
that takes felicitie in publishing
Lies.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Othing (saith <hi>Quintilian</hi>)
so much commēdeth the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
of the writer, as the truth
of the subiect, he proposeth to
write: And certes nothing
aduaunced so highly <hi>Iulius
Caesars</hi> historie, as truth po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished
with Eloquence dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetely:
for as in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the wise the one without the other had argued
great imperfection: so both intermingled sauour of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
discretion, and so much the rather, because the
Author seemeth estranged from Philautie, &amp; Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
I cannot but praise them of ancient time, &amp; touch
some in these dayes, who either for that they know not, or
care not for truth, or wil not inquire after the truth, wil
be sure to publish nothing but vntruth, mispending their
time, misdemeaning their braine, and misusing their
pen, no lesse foes to themselues, then back friends to the
welminded. I speake this (Gentlemen) for that this
Pamphlet had many dayes sithence come to your view,
had not these apish Pamphleters neither left waie for
themselues, nor other, any further to thrust out their
heads: But whereas this obortiue Pygmey dare peepe
out, and shew his face to the world, vnderstand that it
is but vnder sureties, on conditiō, that he neither mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="4"/>
speake, nor write any thing but truth, or at the least
that whereof he can alleadge sufficient authoritie: who
although hee hath been staied, but not brought to a
blancke, therein taketh so much the more heartie grace,
because he knoweth some of these counterfeites will bee
driuen to a Nonplus: And thus much I will saye, and
and in saying truly auouch (being priuie to all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings)
that at this time he will not, (nay if he would
he may not) neither would hee if hee might speake any
more than truth, or that hath been credibly informed,
or that commonly among the best passeth for truth,
wherein if peraduenture hee speake not so much, as
some of you knowe; or write so much, as others heare,
thinke, that neither his eares, nor his eyes are so large, as
to heare and see all things done in his owne countrey,
much lesse ouer Sea in a forrayne climate: but accept
his Newes fauourably, as he giues it friendly, and if in
any iot hee shall offend you, hee most humbly
craues your pardon, euer remayning
courteously at your commande.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>G. B.</signed>
Magna' est veritas, ét preualet.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>