<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all VVomen in gene∣nerall, and gentle Reader whatsoeuer.</title>
           <author>Anger, Jane</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104402_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B11194</idno>
           <idno type="STC">644</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104402</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all VVomen in gene∣nerall, and gentle Reader whatsoeuer.</title>
                 <author>Anger, Jane</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iane Anger her protection for vvomen : To defend them against the scandalous reportes of a late surfeiting louer, and all otherlike Venerians that complaine so to bee ouercloyed with womens kindnesse. Written by Ia: A. Gent</title>
                 <author>Anger, Jane</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To all VVomen in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and gentle Reader whatsoeuer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IE on the falshoode of men, whose minds goe oft a madding, &amp; whose tongues can not so soone bee wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, but straight they fal a railing Was there euer any so abused, so slaundered, so railed vpō, or so wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly handeled vndeseruedly, as are we women? Will the Gods permit it, the Goddesses stay theyr punishing iudgments, and we ourselues not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue their vndoinges for such diuelish practises? O <hi>Paules steeple</hi> and <hi>Charing Crosse.</hi> A halter hold al such persons. Let the streames of the channels in <hi>London</hi> streates run so swiftly, as they may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alone to carrie them from that sanctuarie. Let the stones be as Ice, the soales of their shooes as Glasse, the waies steep like <hi>Aetna,</hi> &amp; euery blast a Whyrl-wind puffed out of <hi>Boreas</hi> his long throat, that these may hasten their passage to the Deuils hauen. Shal Surfeiters raile on our kindnes, you stand stil &amp; say nought, and shall not <hi>Anger</hi> stretch the vaines of her braines, the stringes of her sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and the listes of her modestie, to answere their Surfeitings? Yes truely. And herein I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure all you to aide and assist me in defence of my willingnes, which shall make me rest at your com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundes. Fare you well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your friend. Ia. A.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>