<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104535_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08691</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18999</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104535</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The copie of a letter sent from Paris to the reverend fathers of the Society of Iesus, who liue in England : Containing an answere to the calumniations of the Anti-Coton against the same Society in generall, and Fa. Coton in particular</title>
                 <author>Owen, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>English College Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>93, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING had this Copy imparted vnto me by a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good friend, I would not (gentle Reader) depriue thee of the pleasure &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, which thou mayst reap thereby; especially since that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents therof be no other, but such, as are already published in print. For which cause also I doubt not, but that the Reuerend Fathers, to whom it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, will take this my labour in good part: hoping that it will be no lesse pleasing to them, then to others. And <pb n="4" facs="3"/> it may be, that this printed Copy may come sooner to their handes, then the Letter it selfe; at least it will saue them some labour, which otherwise they could not easily haue excused, for the satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of such, as no doubt would be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to haue a sight of this discourse; which as thou wilt see by the perusing therof, is an exact and complete confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the
<hi>Anti-Coton.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>And that nothing may be wanting, I haue thought good to follow my friends aduise, and to tell thee briefly in this my Preface, that the Translator of the <hi>Anti-Coton</hi> into English hath shewed himselfe no lesse false &amp; foolish, then the French Author thereof. For he will needes take vpon him to adde <hi>Fa. Becanus</hi> to those which the other alledgeth in proofe, that the <hi>Society</hi> teacheth it to be lawfull for particuler men to kill Princes, because he nameth <hi>Fa. Mariana</hi> among the rest; vvhereas it is manifest, that <hi>Fa. Beca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> expressely affirmeth in that place, that a Tyrant in respect of his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <pb n="5" facs="3"/> onely, cannot be flayne by any. And this he affirmeth to be the doctrine of the vvhole Society, yea and of <hi>Fa. Mariana</hi> also; though he aftervvard va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth from the rest in the explication of some particuler poyntes, as thou maist see in this Letter, which I present vnto thee.</p>
   <p>That likewise, which the same Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slator produceth out of
<hi>Fa. Gregory de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia</hi> is no better, since that this Father expressely affirmeth, that only the Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth may restrayne and impugne such a Tyrant: vvhich is not to range him as the Translatour saith, in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of common murtherers &amp; theeues whome not onely the Common-wealth it selfe, but euery particuler Magistrate &amp; officer may apprehend and punish.</p>
   <p>And this shall suffice at this time: for I will not enter into that other discourse, vpon vvhat occasion the Canon of the Councell of
<hi>Constance</hi> against <hi>Tyrannides</hi> was enacted. Certaine it is,<note place="margin">Art. 15. &amp; 17. Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff. in fine Cōcil. Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant.</note> that <hi>VVickliffe</hi> and <hi>Husse</hi> affirmed,
<hi>That there was no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie <pb n="6" facs="4"/> in ciuill Lords and Princes, when they were in mortall sinne:</hi> &amp;, <hi>that the people might at their pleasure, and according to their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, correct and punish them, if they did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend.</hi> But I will detayne thee no longer from the Letter it selfe.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>