<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader, health and peace in Iesus Christ.</title>
           <author>C., B.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104953_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18431</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4999</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104953</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader, health and peace in Iesus Christ.</title>
                 <author>C., B.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The garden of prudence : Wherein is contained, a patheticall discourse, and godly meditation, most brieflie touching the vanities of the world, the calamities of hell, and the felicities of heauen. You shal also find planted in the same, diuers sweet and pleasant flowers, most necessarie and comfortable both for body and soule</title>
                 <author>Chappell, Bartholomew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Reader, health and peace in Iesus Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">X</seg>Erxes,</hi> that mightie Monarch and Emperour of the
Persians, (gentle Reader) beholding from an high the hugenesse of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,
which was in strength inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, in qualitie diuerse, in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber infinite,
and in euerie degree surmounting all that euer were before or since, yea
couering the whole face of the earth: in whose courage, force, &amp;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ight, he reposed the strength of
his kingdome the safegard of his person, and the glorie of his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, could
not but gush out most bitter teares, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>idering that of all the woonderfull multitude that he saw, after one
hundred yeares there should not a man be left. And shall not we that be
Christians at least wise in name, viewing from the depth of our conceits, our
selues, our pompe, our honour, our glorie, our magnificencie and renowne, our 
<pb facs="4"/> wealth, our substance, our beautie our friendes, our strength, our
great possessiont, and territories, our knowledge, our witte, our brauerie and
poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique dealinges, wherein we repose all our felicitie and happines, be
nothing mooued with due consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that this world and all things therin
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, are but fickle and vaine, and that our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e they neuer so faire, be they
neuer so high, be they neuer so strong &amp; valiant, can not escape the dart
of death, but must be resolued to earth, wherof they were framed, and know not
when, how soone or how suddenly, for this is the indgment of all flesh, thou
shalt die the death, and the couenant of the graue is not reuealed to any, for
our life appeare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> as a bubble of
water, and suddenly passeth, it va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth into the ayre, as smoke, it slideth
as a ship, that s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yleth with a full
winde, or as a bird swift of flight, yea swifter then an arrow, mightilie
shott<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> out of a strong bowe: for as
soone as wee are borne, foorthwith we decay, our first entrance into this life,
is our first step to death, and draweth vs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an end, shewing nothing,
but the frailtie and ficklenesse of our estate the weaknesse and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of
our flesh, whose impietie dayly draweth vs from vertue to vice, from carefulnes
to carelesnes from the chaire of godly studie, to the cradle of <pb facs="5"/>
vaine securitie: but the rewarde hereof is nothing but death and damnation in
vtter darkenesse for euer, where our drinke shall be turned to sharpe
vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, and our bread to bitter
gall: Wherefore view and with al diligence marke (most curteous reader) the
sweet and comfortable flowers which thou shalt finde to adorne this little
Garden, and regarde not the slender workmanship of the vnskilfull Garde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
but weigh in the ballance of thy deep discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the singular vertues, and
most diuine operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both of the plants, hearbs and flowers inserted in the
same, for so maist thou eschue the vaine va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this wicked world, so
shalt thou escape the miserable calamities of that fyerie lake, the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
of Satan, and finallie, most happily attaine the ioyfull felicitie of most
gladsome Paradice in the blessed kingdome of God. Thus desiring
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nelie thy loue for my labours, I
bid thee hartily farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord. B. C.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>