<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HO∣norable, and my much worthy honored, truly learned, and Iudicious Knight, Sr Francis Bacon, his Maties Attourney Generall, Increase of honor, health, and eternall happinesse.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104709_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16733</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3635</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104709</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HO∣norable, and my much worthy honored, truly learned, and Iudicious Knight, Sr Francis Bacon, his Maties Attourney Generall, Increase of honor, health, and eternall happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Characters vpon essaies morall, and diuine : written for those good spirits, that will take them in good part, and make vse of them to good purpose</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Edward 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Gwillim, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>62 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, and my much worthy honored, truly learned, and Iudicious Knight, Sr Francis Bacon, his Ma<seg rend="sup">ties</seg> Attourney Generall, Increase of honor, health, and eternall happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ORTHY Knight, I haue read of many Essaies, and a kinde of
<pb facs="4"/>
Charactering of them, by such, as when I lookt into the forme, or nature of their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I haue beene of the conceit, that they were but Imitators of your breaking the ice to their inuentions; which, how short they fall of your worth, I had rather thinke then speake, though Truth neede not blush at her
<pb facs="4"/>
blame: Now, for my selfe vnworthy to touch neere the Rocke of those Diamonds, or to speake in their praise, who so farre exceede the power of my capacitie, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe me leaue yet, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech you, among those Apes that would counterfet the actions of men, to play the like part with learning, and
<pb facs="5"/>
as a Monkey, that would make a face like a Man, and cannot, so to write like a Scholler, and am not: and thus not daring to aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Print, vnder your Patronage, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your fauourable allowance, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted seruice of my bounden duty, I leaue these poore Trauells of my Spirit, to the
<pb facs="5"/>
perusing of your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing leasure, with the further fruites of my humble affection, to the happie employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pleasure.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>At your seruice in all humblenesse</hi> NICH: BRETON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>