<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO ALL MY LOVING Friends and well-willers, both in and without the Liberties of this City of LONDON, Grace and Peace bee multiplied.</title>
           <author>Lawrence, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1624</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104883_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05191</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15325</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104883</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO ALL MY LOVING Friends and well-willers, both in and without the Liberties of this City of LONDON, Grace and Peace bee multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Lawrence, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A golden trumpet, to rowse vp a drowsie magistrate: or, A patterne for a governors practise : drawne from Christs comming to, beholding of, and weeping ouer Hierusalem. As it was founded at Pauls Crosse the 11. of Aprill, 1624. By Iohn Lawrence preacher of the word of God in the citie of London</title>
                 <author>Lawrence, John, preacher of the word of God in London</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1624</date>
                 <publisher>Griffin, Anne.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 104, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO ALL MY LOVING Friends and well-willers, both in and without the Liberties of this City of LONDON, Grace and Peace bee multiplied.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian friends, some known, all desired in the Lord; I cannot more fitly salute you, then in the phrase of that diuine Apostle:<note place="margin">2 Ep. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. v.</note>
      <hi>Grace be with you, mercy and peace from God the Father, and from the Lord Iesus Christ.</hi> Beloued, I wish aboue all things that your soules may prosper as your bodies doe, for I haue <hi>no greater ioy then to heare that my children walke in the truth:</hi> as I haue laboured to doe you good,<note place="margin">3 Ep. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. v.</note> doe not you requite me with euill; censure me not too rashly for this my forwardnesse to the Presse, nor for my slender iudgement in prosecution of my matter. I must confesse, that in regard of the small number of my yeeres, I may iustly incurre the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of presumption, in that I should bee so forward; first to preach in such an honourable Assembly, next to send my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to the worlds view; had I not to the former beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned by authority, and to the latter pressed by importunity, the place of birth had beene the place of buriall, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of many the graues where I would haue left it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so earnestly pressed thereunto, with the perswading how much good might come thereby, not onely to the City in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but to euery mans house and family in particular; at last condescended, not for <hi>affection</hi> or <hi>ostentation,</hi> but for the glory of my God, and the good of Church and City: It was plaine in preaching, but more plaine in printing, to the end it might not be obscure to any: if any thing be amisse, as sure it
<pb facs="6"/>
cannot be perfect, let me request you to mend the fault with a good conceit, and to cure my failing with my good meaning; remember it is an easier thing to plucke downe a house then to build one: If my stile be too homely, then thinke wise men desire rather a carefull then an eloquent <hi>Physician;</hi> if wee might not make bookes, wherefore were letters first inuented? shall the <hi>Epicure</hi> be tolerated to write dishonest things, and shall not a Minister much more good and needfull things? O yes: accept therefore of this small mite, which at this time I haue cast into <hi>Gods Treasury.</hi> Scorne not to reade it because I am young, for the least <hi>starre</hi> hath his light and influence, and there may be some vse of <hi>Goats-haire</hi> to the finishing of the <hi>Tabernacle:</hi> I haue many friends to remember in this my iourney, but if I call at euery mans doore, I shall be lated, therefore I craue leaue to passe by most, not for want of any affection (for I loue you all in Iesus Christ) but that in due time I may arriue at my hoped hauen, entring my lodging at a lawfull houre.</p>
   <p>The first friend which dwelleth in the way I trauell, is the <hi>Minories</hi> which in times past vsed me very kindly, for she en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained me when I was destitute of outward comfort, affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding both me and mine meat, drinke, and lodging, almost two yeeres together, and still would, had not the principall corne beene <hi>blasted</hi> with the <hi>Easterly wind of vaine reports,</hi> and the <hi>mil-dew of euill imaginations;</hi> yet for the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse once receiued, I cannot forget them, for hauing lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them, I cannot chuse but still loue them: Can the mother forget that Childe which indangered her life most? if she could, yet cannot I forget you, I speake it not for any vaine glory, but the more to stirre mee vp to returne praise to him to whom all praise belongeth, that gaue me such an heart to seeke the good of your soules: my God (and you, if you will but speake the truth) can testifie with me, how that I thought not my life deare for your sakes. This is my comfort, so long as I was with you, I omitted no time, wherein I might doe good to your soules, but <hi>in season, out of season,</hi> morning, euening, publike, priuate, in Gods
<pb facs="6"/>
house, in my house, or in your houses, was I neuer backward to afford you the <hi>milke of the word,</hi> if I were desired there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: when you were asleepe, I was awake; when you were a bed, I was at study; when you little thought of me, many times was I praying for you, that the Lord would make my Ministery <hi>the sauour of life vnto life, and not the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of death vnto death</hi> to any one of you. But alas, my paines were not noted, but my failings strictly obserued, and pried into, nay blazed abroad <hi>to the wounding of my soule.</hi> It was not you, but <hi>Satan,</hi> who sought to sow <hi>tares</hi> where God sowed <hi>wheat,</hi> and the Lord brought this thing to passe for my greater humiliation, yea I know it shall worke for my good if the fault be not in my selfe: but I cease, desiring you to esteeme of me as I of you, my hoped, louing and faithfull friends, saluting the worshipfull Master <hi>Mulis,</hi> Master <hi>Tice,</hi> Master <hi>Vphill,</hi> Master <hi>Hauercampe,</hi> with their wiues and families, and all the rest of that parish, wishing health and happinesse to attend you in this life, and eternall glory to be conferd vpon you in the life to come, <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Before I had quite taken leaue of the <hi>Minories</hi> (for I was preuented of that intended curtesie) through the mercy of the Lord my God, I met with another harbor, namely Saint <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garets Fish-street,</hi> where I was louingly receiued, kindly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained and friendly welcommed, but a ruffe Sea of a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging discontented minde soone wrought my departure from my faithfull friends, for such is the nature of enuy, that both eies shall be ventured to extinguish one of the parties not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, and <hi>Viper</hi>-like will not sticke to teare the belly where once it was cherished, but I remember my promise was vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to forget, and absolutely to forgiue in my farewell: since my continuance was so short, my discourse cannot bee long, therefore I kindly take my leaue of all my louing friends there remaining, euer resting your poore <hi>Orator</hi> at the throne of grace for your ioy in this life, and euerlasting happinesse in the life to come.</p>
   <p>At this time I was like the distressed traueller, remaining in the wild fields, in the midst of a tempestuous storme, farre
<pb facs="7"/>
from company, destitute of mony, beaten with raine, terrified with thunder, stiffe with cold, yet not brought to despaire for all these miseries, but still trusted in God who was able to helpe me. Neither was I deceiued in whom I relied, for hee that is called <hi>faithfull,</hi> shewed himselfe most <hi>mercifull,</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his countenance angry to his wonted clemency, giuing me entrance after seuen daies absence, into his Sanctuary at Saint <hi>Margaret Pattens,</hi> alias <hi>Rood-Church,</hi> where recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a most free <hi>Election,</hi> I comfortably spent my labours al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most two yeeres, reaping the profit of my studies with much ioy; I hope the conuersion of many soules vnto God: but <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> that subtill enemy of mankinde, who euer sought my sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersion and ouerthrow, would not suffer my foot long to rest in any place, but by his malicious minde I was soone dispossessed of my harbour, where had I not found one faithfull friend,<note n="*" place="margin">Saint <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolphs.</hi>
      </note> my habitation had beene like <hi>Dauids</hi> in the <hi>Wildernesse;</hi> farre be it from me I should lay any thing <hi>to the charge of Gods chosen,</hi> my sinnes deserued my punishments had they beene greater, and I pray with Saint <hi>Augustine, Hic vre, hic seca, vt in aeternum parcas Domine,</hi> id est, <hi>Here burne mee, here slay me, to spare me hereafter,</hi> q.d. Lord doe what thou wilt with my body, so that thou wilt but saue my soule. Nay further, I pray with Saint <hi>Ierome, Vtinam ob Domini mei nomen, atque iustitiam, cuncta gentilium turba me persequatur &amp; tribulet: vtinam in opprobrium meum, stolidus hic mundus exurgat, tantum vt ego mercedem Iesu consequar;</hi> id est, <hi>I would to God that the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Gentiles, Pagans, and Infidels, would for the name of my God, and for the glory of his Gospell, perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute me and trouble me: I would to God this mad and foolish world would rise vp against me for the profession of Gods blessed truth, only that I may obtaine Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus for my reward.</hi> For the loue I found generally amongst you all, I haue nothing wherewith to requite it, therefore I onely praise my God, and heartily thanke you, amongst which Louers I cannot chuse but particularize some of the best, for where most kindnesse hath beene receiued, most thankefulnesse
<pb facs="7"/>
should be returned; and though I am not able worthily or suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently to returne thankes vnto you, yet I hope you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of what I am able, receiuing these few lines as a testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of further seruice.</p>
   <p>First therefore, I salute the worshipfull Mistris <hi>Moore,</hi> with whom though my acquaintance be but small, yet for the good I haue both heard and seene, cannot chuse but mention as one of my friends, if my iudgement faile not: they are to be counted the best friends that prouoke a man to cleane clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest to God.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.5.</note>
      <hi>Iosephs</hi> brethren out of enuy sold him to bee a bond-slaue, but God that sits aboue turned the wheele so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, that enuy brought glory; debasement, aduancement; for this the Lord suffered them to doe for his and their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation. Mistake me not, I doe not tax you with any iniury, but thanke you for your courtesie, for this be farre from me to grieue any of the Saints, of which I am perswaded you are one, for the world hath crowned you for <hi>religion, piety</hi> and <hi>bounty,</hi> for <hi>wisdome, honesty</hi> and <hi>ciuility,</hi> for <hi>kindnesse, courtesie</hi> and <hi>modesty,</hi> and which is most of all, for a tender conscience, ready to releeue the poore members of Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, affording succour to his Ministers, which are destitute of outward comfort. <hi>Helen</hi> Queene of <hi>Adiabene,</hi> when shee left her owne Country and came to dwell at <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> shee filled the bellies of the poore with the Cornes of <hi>Aegypt,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Eus. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi> Ioseph. antiquet. lib. <hi>20.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
      </note> and the Fruits of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> sparing for no cost to doe good to the Saints that were at <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> by which your selfe hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a very famous report, and I hope the Lord will still make you a beneficiall instrument, both to <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> The rarer this vertue is, the more I reuerence it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending you and your houshold to <hi>God,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 20.32.</note>
      <hi>and to the word of his grace, which is able to build further, and to giue you an inheritance among all them which are sanctified.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Master Freeman,</hi> you I must not forget, vnlesse I forget my selfe, and though I should forget my selfe, yet can I not chuse but remember you, the affection of your heart I haue found by the act of your hand, and your willingnesse to doe me good hath beene seene by your forwardnesse to speake and
<pb facs="8"/>
write in my behalfe, vpon any occasion that hath beene offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto you; a requitall I cannot make, vnlesse it please you to accept of my heartiest prayers, which I cease not to poure out at the throne of grace for you, your wife and family, and for my vnknowne friend, who desiring them, hath not forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten me.</p>
   <p>Master <hi>Goodwin,</hi> my loue is great to your soule, though my familiarity be small with your bodily presence and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly association. I wish (if it might not be offensiue) to liue to requite some part of your courtesies, for beyond my desert I haue found you forward to subscribe to any good motion for my good, for which I shall euer rest at your command for any seruice.</p>
   <p>Mistris <hi>Glouer,</hi> much wrong I should doe you, if I neglect to number you amongst my friends, you were the tree that yeelded me the first fruit in this City; though it was but small, yet it was comfortable, by reason of my necessity, since you haue watered my studies with your beneficence, that euen my barrennesse hath (through your drops) yeelded some fruit, I trust to the comfort of many, your loue to Gods Saints and zeale to the Word doth crowne you; for as women delight not onely to see faire Iewels, and curious needle-workes, but to take them out and we are them, so I dare boldly say, that your care is not onely to know, but to expresse and weare the good things you know in your conuersation. I beseech God to increase his fatherly blessings vpon you, and vpon your sonne, Master <hi>Richard Glouer,</hi> and vpon all the rest of your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and family, to his owne glorie and your endlesse com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts.</p>
   <p>Master <hi>Alkin,</hi> you are the fauour of my heart, and the Father of my being in some kinde, if euer I was obliged to any, in a double and treble manner to you. Your care both for me and ouer me, hath beene more fatherlike then friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and not onely to me, but to many more of my Brethren, which if pride doe not too much puffe vp their minds, cannot chuse but acknowledge: forwith <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodome,</hi> you haue receiued the <hi>Angels and Messengers of God;</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.2, 3.</note> with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca,</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
you haue courteously entertained the seruants of <hi>Abraham;</hi> with beleeuing <hi>Rahab,</hi> receiued the <hi>Spies;</hi> nay,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.25. <hi>Iosh.</hi> 2.1.</note> with <hi>Publius in the Ile of Malta,</hi> you haue receiued <hi>Paul;</hi> and with <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> you haue receiued, if not Christ himselfe, yet Christ in his members: nay, with <hi>Lydia,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 28.7. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.38.</note> you haue constrained the <hi>Apostles</hi> to staie in your house; and with <hi>Tabitha</hi> you are full of <hi>good works</hi> and <hi>almes deeds,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 16.15.</note> according to your abilitie. This I know, therefore cannot chuse but speake, not to the end you should bee puft vp with vaine glorie, but to encourage you in this godly course, that at the latter end of your daies, you may with comfort say: <hi>I haue fought a good fight, I haue finished my course,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8.</note>
      <hi>I haue kept the faith, from henceforth is laid vp for me a crowne of righteousnesse, which the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> I seale vp my loue with my heartiest praiers; for you, your Wife, and all the rest of your Family, euer resting your true friend.</p>
   <p>Time calls away, the euening requires haste, I dare not call to any more friends, lest darknesse ouertake me, and preuent me of my hoped hauen: Generally therefore, I salute <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Camden, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Parker, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Whitbread, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Milsop, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Smith,</hi> with the rest of my friends in <hi>Rood Parish;</hi> wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all happinesse to attend you in this life, and eternall glory to be conferred vpon you in the life to come.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>To Master</hi> Gifford, <hi>and all his louing Parishioners now dwelling in</hi> Saint Buttolphs Billingsgate, <hi>Iohn Lawrence</hi> wisheth health and happinesse.</p>
   <p>Louing friends, yet not more louing then beloued, though you are the last in this action, yet not the least in my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: If I owe a thankefull acknowledgment to any, much more to you; for aboue many you haue comforted my bowels both in word and deed. In health you were ioyfull to receiue me, in sicknesse you often came to visit me: my rising was your desire, my falling you did not require. This, and more then this I haue found, which enforceth my pen (because my tongue cannot) to set forth the thankefulnesse of my heart to you for it. I was your Preacher two yeares together, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time I trauelled in paine, that <hi>Christ Iesus
<pb facs="9"/>
might be formed in you.</hi> All my desire was your good, not your goods: your saluation was the end of my studie, and by submitting to the word, though meanly deliuered by me, you did much encourage my holy entended labours. My de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire was still to haue beene amongst you, but sithence it might not, my praier was, and still is, that the Lord would giue you a <hi>Pastor according to his owne heart,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iere.</hi> 3.14.</note> whereby you may be <hi>fed with knowledge and vnderstanding.</hi> And further, I pray that euery good Minister may finde as much comfort from his people as I haue found by you. I know you take no pleasure to haue your goodnesse published, because you account vertues fairest Theater to be a good conscience, yet it becomes an ingenious minde to professe by whom he proficeth. I would that euery Parish in London vnderstood your godly disposition and Christian cariage, both in publike and priuate, that they might be prouoked by your vertuous example. I will not dull your eares with too large a discourse: therefore to conclude. I commend this Treatise to your diligent reading, and not onely to yours, but to all theirs that loue the truth, and my selfe to your Christian praiers, and all of vs to the good grace of God. Thus crauing your pardon, and the continuance of your fauour to him who acknowledgeth himselfe</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Bound vnto you in all dutie, IOHN LAVVRENCE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>