<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A BRIEF, PLAYN, AND effectuall instruction concerning Pur∣gatory, and Prayer for the dead.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104083_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03334</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13454</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104083</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A BRIEF, PLAYN, AND effectuall instruction concerning Pur∣gatory, and Prayer for the dead.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The first motiue of T.H. Maister of Arts, and lately minister, to suspect the integrity of his religion : which was detection of falsehood in D. Humfrey, D. Field, &amp; other learned protestants, touching the question of purgatory, and prayer for the dead. VVith his particular considerations perswading him to embrace the Catholick doctrine in theis, and other points. An appendix intituled, try before you trust. Wherein some notable vntruths of D. Field, and D. Morton are discouered</title>
                 <author>Higgons, Theophilus</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Auroi (Ouroy), Pierre</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 172, 4, 8, 70, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="treatise">
   <pb facs="97"/>
   <head>A BRIEF, PLAYN, AND effectuall instruction concerning <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> and <hi>Prayer for the dead.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>COurteous Reader; the intended breuity of my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course did not permitt me so to inforce,<note place="margin">Booke 1. Part. 1. Cha. 2. §. 4. nū. 16.</note> and to illustra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te the testimony of S. AVGVSTINE in this matter, as I had conceiued, nor as the dignity thereof doth justly require; and especially for their sake, who either in regard of their weaknesse cannot, or in regard of their negligence care not, or in regard of their peruersenesse will not see the cleare, and irrefragable truth. VVherefore, hauing a little remnant of vacant paper, I haue thought good to employ it vnto this profitable end; assuring my self that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Reader may informe his vnderstanding, and settle his conscience herein, by the waight, and euidence of theis THREE ensuing propositions.</p>
   <div n="1" type="proposition">
      <head>The <hi>FIRST</hi> proposition.</head>
      <p n="1">1 <hi>THere was alwayes, and now is, and euer shall be a CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THOLICK Church, which is free from any</hi>
         <note n="†" place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt this doctrine of <hi>Purgatory</hi> &amp;c. to be <hi>damnable.</hi>
         </note>
         <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable errour.</hi> This assertion is very often deliuered by <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> and the very same (though not precisely in theis words) is yealded by <note n="*" place="margin">
            <hi>Pag.</hi> 203.</note> D. <hi>Field</hi> in the name of his Church.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="2" type="proposition">
      <head>The <hi>SECOND</hi> proposition.</head>
      <p n="2">2. <hi>THe instruction of this Church is the last, and finall judgement, wherein all men may, and must rely, as in the PROPOVNDER of truth.</hi> This assertion is streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened by sondry testimonies of the Fathers, and <note n="†" place="margin">In his ep. dedic.</note>
         <hi>D. Field</hi> approoueth it, saying, that men desirous of satisfaction must diligently search out the true Church, and <note n="*" place="margin">Therefore it must be knowen; &amp; therefo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it must be visible.</note>
         <hi>rest in hir judgement</hi> &amp;c. In which respect he sayeth, that, <note n="†" place="margin">
            <hi>Pag.</hi> 193.</note>
         <hi>if the reprehension of Aërius</hi> [touching <hi>PRAYER FOR THE DEAD] be vnderstood to extend vnto the generall practise, &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="98"/> of the Church, it is not, nor may not be iustified.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reas he sayeth, <hi>it is not iustified</hi> [by Protestants] that is not true; whereas he sayeth, <hi>it may not be iustified,</hi> that is very certayn. Wherefore I desire you to stand constantly vnto this position, and not to flye your ground.</p>
   </div>
   <div n="3" type="proposition">
      <head>The <hi>THIRD</hi> proposition.</head>
      <p n="3">3. <hi>THe iudgement, and purpose of the ancient CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LICK Church is discouerable vnto us by two meae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes;</hi> viz. <hi>the perpetuall succession of PRACTISE, and the conforme testimony of the FATHERS.</hi> For where we find no substantiall mutation of <hi>PRACTISE,</hi>
         <note place="margin">All men know, that the practise of <hi>praying for the dead</hi> is the same now <hi>sustā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially,</hi> as in <hi>S. August.</hi> time: and, I hope, it was not <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne</hi> then but <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued.</hi> See before; pag. 25.</note> but see it perpetuated in all descents, and deriued vnto vs by <hi>the long hand of time,</hi> we may infallibly conclude, that the later ages of the Church conspiring with the former, are free from just reproof. Agayn; the testimony of the <hi>FATHERS</hi> conuaigheth vs vnto the knowledge of the Churches jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement; so that we require fidelity in them, authority in it; they are the witnesses, she the judge; they relate hir voyce, she pronounceth the sentence.</p>
      <p>
         <hi>Theis propositions as they are very perspicuous, &amp; ponderous, so they will excellently, and forcibly apply themselues in decision of this controuersy, touching</hi> PVRGATORY, <hi>and</hi> PRAYER FOR THE DEAD.</p>
      <q>
         <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="testimony">
                  <head>The testimony of <hi>S. AVGVSTINE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The faithfull do know, according to the instruction of the Church, that, when MARTYRS are recited at the Altar of God, this is not done with intention to pray for them (it being an injury to pray for a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, vnto whose prayers we ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended) but we pray for other decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed men, whose commemoration is there made.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </floatingText>
      </q>
      <p>Now, for your full satisfaction in this poynt, you must here obserue three things; viz. the quality of the <hi>WIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESSE,</hi>
         <pb facs="98"/> the competency of the IVDGE, the resolution of the MATTER.</p>
      <p n="1">1. Concerning the FIRST; it importeth the witnesse onely to expresse, what was the intentiō of the Church in this practise. And as <hi>S. Augustine is a most faithfull witnesse of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity</hi> (in M. <note n="*" place="margin">Inst. l. 3. c. 3. §. 10. &amp;c.</note>
         <hi>Caluins</hi> opinion) so <hi>it goeth hard, if for a MATTER OF HISTORY, the Fathers can not find creditt at your hands; they should know, as well as you, what was then in FACT.</hi> Which sentence being very justly deliuered against the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> by the <note n="†" place="margin">
            <hi>Suruay</hi> pag. 338.</note> L. of <hi>Cant</hi> (in the question of <hi>BISHOPPS</hi> &amp;c.) ought to be considered exactly in this issue.</p>
      <p n="2">2. Concerning the SECOND; you see that the Churches <hi>instruction</hi> touching this matter, was knowen familiarly vnto all the <hi>faithfull:</hi> so that you must either vnnaturally, and impiously (as <hi>Aërian</hi> hereticks) reiect your Mothers instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or els as dutifull, and obsequious children, you must submitt your selues vnto hir doctrine. Which least you should intemperately renounce, I pray you to remember that famous sentence of <hi>S. Augustine;</hi> viz.<note place="margin">
            <hi>Ep.</hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>18.</note>
         <q>to call any thing in question, which is frequented by the VNIVERSALL CHVRCH, it is the part of most INSOLENT MADNESSE.</q>
      </p>
      <p n="3">3. Concerning the THIRD; you can not but perceiue the clearnesse thereof expressed in this distinction; <hi>VVe do not pray for Martyrs:</hi> and, <hi>VVe do pray for other men,</hi> By which manifest difference, <hi>S. Augustine</hi> doth sufficiently declare, that the memory of Martyrs was celebrated at the Altar, by way of <hi>THANSKGIVING,</hi> and gladnesse: but the names of other men were remembred by way of <hi>PETI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION,</hi> and desire. The reason whereof ariseth out of their estate. <hi>VVe pray not for a Martyr;</hi> and, <hi>it were an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury to pray for him:</hi> Why? Because we know that he is in heauen; and to haue any diffidence of his beatitude, it were injurious vnto his cause, and derogatory from his passion; therefore <hi>we pray not FOR him,</hi> as though he wanted our relief, but <hi>VNTO</hi> him rather, that he may assist vs with his charitable intercession.</p>
      <p>But <hi>we pray for others;</hi> that is to say, for all them, of whose actuall felicity the Church hath not yet attayned a secure, and infallible perswasion; otherwise, if she knew that
<pb facs="99"/> they were in present possession of ioy, it were as great as injury to pray for them also, as for the Martyrs themselues, since the reason, why she prayeth not for Martyrs, is, because she is confidently resolued that they, being in heauen, stand not in any exigence of hir deuotion.</p>
      <p>Wherefore, since the <hi>CATHOLICK</hi> Church prayed for other mē, as not being in heauen (or not certainly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to be there) she did conceiue that they were, or might be (for ought she knew to the contrary) in <hi>some third place,</hi> and consequently <hi>in some temporall payn:</hi> and so (necessarily) she did belieue, that there is a <hi>PVRGATORY</hi> after this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> life. To contend about <hi>WORDS,</hi> and <hi>NAMES,</hi> it is a vanity; for it is sufficient to haue a sure apprehension of the <hi>THING</hi> it self. To litigate about things <hi>ACCI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DENTALL,</hi>
         <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> it is a folly; for it is inough to be certayn of the <hi>SVBSTANTIALL</hi> point: the rest haue their probability in their seuerall degrees, and are permitted vnto <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> free dispute. Finally; later ages may amplify, not alter the doctrine of the former; fayth hath an augmentation, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitt hir progresse, not innouation to chandge hir purenesse. <hi>IESVS proficiebat sapientiâ,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <hi>Luca.</hi> 2.53.</note>
         <hi>&amp; aetate, &amp;c.</hi> Now since he, that is <hi>WISEDOME</hi> it self did profitt in <hi>sapience;</hi> and he, that is <hi>ETERNITY,</hi> did increase in <hi>age,</hi> it may well become the Church to shew a conformity vnto hir head, and Lord.</p>
      <q>
         <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="petition">
                  <head>The petition of S. AVGVSTINE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Confess. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. c. 13.</note>Inspire, o Lord my God, inspire thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, &amp; my brethren, that, at thy Altar, they may remēber <hi>Monica</hi> thy handmayd, with <hi>Patricius</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hir husband.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </floatingText>
      </q>
   </div>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>