<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104023_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03146</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13274</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104023</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The history of the Sabbath : In two bookes. By Pet. Heylyn</title>
                 <author>Heylyn, Peter</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 <publisher>Cotes, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, Elizabeth</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>38, 179, 7, 31, 36-192, 209-271, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="115"/>
   <pb facs="115"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd such I hope to meet with, in this
point especially: which treating of
the affaires of the <hi>Christian</hi>
Church, cannot but be displeasing
unto t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>em, which are not <hi>Christianly</hi> affected.
Our former Book wee destinated to the <hi>Iewish</hi>
part of this enquiry: wherein, though long it
was before we found it, yet at the last we found
a <hi>Sabbath.</hi> A <hi>Sabbath</hi> which began with that
state and Church, and ended also when they
were no longer to be called a Nation; but a
dispersed and scattered ruine of what once they
were. In that which followeth, our enquirie must
be more diffused, of the same latitude with the
<hi>Church;</hi> a <hi>Church</hi> not limited and confined to
some Tribes and Kindreds, but generally sprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
over all the world. We may affirme it of the
<hi>Gospel,</hi> what <hi>Florus</hi> somtimes said of the state
of <hi>Rome. Ita late per orbem terrarum arma
circumtulit, ut quires ejus legunt, non u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius
populi, sed generis humani facta dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt.</hi>
The historie of the <hi>Church,</hi> and of the
<hi>World,</hi> are of like extent. So that the search
<pb facs="116"/>
herein, as unto me it was more painf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ll in the
doing▪ so unto thee will it be more pleasing being
done; because of that varietie which it will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford
thee. And this Part wee have called the
<hi>History</hi> of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> too: although the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution
of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the same in all times and Ages since that
insti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ution, be the chiefe thing whereof it trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.
For being it is said by some that the <hi>Lords
Day</hi> succeeded, by the <hi>Lords</hi> appointment, into
the place and rights of the <hi>Iewish Sabbath;</hi> so
to be ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ed, and so to be observed, as the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
was: this booke was wholy to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> spent
in the search thereof, whether in all, or any
Ages of the Church, either such doctrine had bin
preached, or such practice pressed upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science
of Gods people. And search indeed we did
with all care and diligence, to see if wee could
finde a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> in any evidence of Scripture, or
writings of the holy Fathers, or Edicts of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours,
or Decrees of Councels: or finally in any
of the publick Acts &amp; Monuments of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
Church.</hi> But after serverall searches made
upon the <hi>alias,</hi> and the <hi>pluries,</hi> wee still re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,
<hi>Non est inventus:</hi> and thereupon re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>solve
in the Poets language, <hi>Et quod invenis
<pb facs="116"/>
usquam, esse putes nusquam;</hi> that which is no
where to be found, may very strongly be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
not to be at all <hi>Buxdorfius</hi> in the 11. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of his <hi>Synagoga Iudaica,</hi> out of <hi>Antonius
Margarita,</hi> tels us of the <hi>Iews, quod</hi> die sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batino,
<hi>praeter animam consu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tam, praediti
sunt</hi> &amp; <hi>alia;</hi> that on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, they have
an extraordinary soule infused into them, which
doth enlarge their hearts, and rowze up their
spirits, <hi>Vt Sabbatum multo honorabilius
peragere possint,</hi> that they may celebrate the
<hi>Sabbath</hi> with the greater honour. And though
this <hi>sabbatarie</hi> soule, may by a <hi>Pythagoricall</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, seeme to have transmigrated from
the <hi>Iewes,</hi> into the bodies of some <hi>Christians</hi>
in these later dayes: yet I am apt to give my selfe
good hopes, that by presenting to their view, the
constant practise of Gods Church in all times
before, and the consent of all Gods Churches at
this present; they may be dispossessed thereof
without great difficulty. It is but <hi>anima super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flua,</hi>
as <hi>Buxdorfius</hi> cals it; and may be better
spared, then kept, because <hi>superfluous.</hi> Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<hi>I</hi> shall easily perswade my selfe, that by this
generall representation of the estate and practise
of the Church of Christ, <hi>I</hi> may confirme the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering,
<pb facs="117"/>
in a right perswasion; and assure such
as are already well affected, by shewing them the
perfect harmonie and agreement, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
this Church and the purest times. It is
our constant prayer to almighty God, aswell that
he would <hi>strengthen such as do stand,</hi> and
<hi>confirme the weake,</hi> as to <hi>raise up</hi> those men
which are <hi>fallen</hi> into sinne and errour. As are
our prayers, such should be also our endeavours;
as universall to all sorts of men, as charitable to
them in their severall cases and distresses. Happy
those men, who do aright discharge their duties,
both in their prayers, and their performance.
The blessing of our labours we must leave to him,
who is <hi>all</hi> in <hi>all:</hi> without whom all <hi>Pauls plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
and <hi>Apollos watering,</hi> will yeeld poore <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease.</hi>
In which of these three states soever thou
art, good Christian Reader, let me be seech thee
kindly to accept his pains; which for thy sake
were undertaken: that so be might, in some poore
measure, be an instrument, to <hi>strengthen</hi> or
<hi>confirme,</hi> or <hi>raise</hi> thee, as thy case requires.
This is the most that I desire, and lesse then this
thou couldst not do, did I not desire it. And so
fare thee well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>