<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The copie of a letter sent by Wil∣liam Blandy, before the imprinting of his booke, to his assured and worshipfull good friend, EDWARD MORRIS, Captayne.</title>
           <author>Blandy, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104609_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16206</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3128</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104609</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The copie of a letter sent by Wil∣liam Blandy, before the imprinting of his booke, to his assured and worshipfull good friend, EDWARD MORRIS, Captayne.</title>
                 <author>Blandy, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The castle, or picture of pollicy : shewing forth most liuely, the face, body and partes of a commonwealth, the duety quality, profession of a perfect and absolute souldiar, the martiall feates encounters and skirmishes lately done by our English nation, vnder the conduct of the most noble and famous Gentleman M. Iohn Noris Generall of the Army of the states in Friseland. The names of many worthy and famous gentlemen which liue and haue this present yeare. 1580. ended theyr liues in that land most honorably. Handled in manner of a dialogue betwixt Gefferay Gate, and William Blandy, souldiars. Anno 1581</title>
                 <author>Blandie, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 30 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>Military handbooks</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ The copie of a letter sent by Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Blandy, before the imprinting of his booke, to his assured and worshipfull good friend, <hi>EDWARD MORRIS,</hi> Captayne.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ANIBALL</hi> exiled <hi>Carthage,</hi> sought the supportance of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus</hi> king of Ephesus. <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> embracing Chiualrye, would <hi>Haniball</hi> to be honored of all his people: as one whose worthye actes, and noble en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises, filled at that tyme the world with fame and glorye. This king, whether he did therein respect his owne profite and wonted ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise, or pleasure and recreation of this valiant and famous warriour, brought him to heare <hi>Phormio</hi> reade, appoynted at that tyme to discourse of some high poynt, and difficult question of Philosophie. <hi>Antiochus</hi> and <hi>Haniball</hi> accompaned with many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and braue courtiers of his nation, entred the place of audience: <hi>Phormio</hi> laboring then no lesse in the waightynes of his Argument, then a tall shipp richly and heauely laden, tossed in the middest of the Ocean. Whether the Maiestye of his king, the coūtenaunce of so great, &amp; honorable a person as <hi>Haniball</hi> was, rushing in of so glittering and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a troupe, or a vaine conceite of poore prayse should moue in a deepe and approued Philosopher, such chaungeablenes or no: <hi>Phormio</hi> suddaynely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined from his intent and purpose, conuerting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
<pb facs="4"/>
to the speach of warres. After whose oration made and finished, <hi>Antiochus</hi> demaunded of <hi>Haniball</hi> what he thought of <hi>Phormio.</hi> I haue heard (sayd <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball</hi>) many a Doter speake, but a more dreamer then <hi>Phormio</hi> is, shall I neuer heare agayne. Which history my good Captayne, is a president to me, (sith I write of the Martial affaires of our Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) to stand in doubt, how this attempt of mine may be taken: for that there are emong our nation many <hi>Haniballs,</hi> but few of <hi>Phormios</hi> minde, &amp; I, least able of all other, to sustayne on my part, the waight of this cōparison. My drift and desier therefore is, it would please you to peruse these papers, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially viewe that part, wherein is disclosed the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertye, nature, and qualitye, of a good, and perfect Souldiar. Your will, or nill, shall cause me to follow or forsake my purpose intended. My busines, and being here in this land (as you know right well) is such, that I haue no long tarying. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore returne I most hartely pray you, as speedely as you may an Aunswere. Fare you well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Most ready and willing to pleasure you.
William Blandy.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>