<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all Ministers &amp; fellow labourers in the Lords vine-yarde, salutations in Iesu Christ.</title>
           <author>Lyster, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104942_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06667</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17122</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104942</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all Ministers &amp; fellow labourers in the Lords vine-yarde, salutations in Iesu Christ.</title>
                 <author>Lyster, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A rule how to bring vp children : A treatise wherein is declared, how the father apposeth his sonne in the holy Scripture, whereby all parents may be taught a rule how to bring vp their children, briefelie collected into a short volume</title>
                 <author>Lyster, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>5, 138, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To all Ministers &amp; fellow labourers in the Lords vine-yarde, salutations in Iesu Christ.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowen vnto you (my brethern) that the Lord hath elected vs before we were fashioned in our mothers wombe, sanctified vs or euer we were borne, ordained vs to be stewards of his secrets, watchmen ouer his people, shepperds of the sheepe of his pasture, to the edifiyng of the saincts, to the worke and ministra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, euen to the edifiyng of the bodie of Christ, till we all come to the vnitie of faith and knowledge of the sonne of God, vnto a perfect man, euen vnto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of the full perfect age of Christ. And knowing my selfe to be the meanest a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, in respect of my knowledge, not worthie to be of that calling, although the grace of God hath otherwise dealt with mee in calling me to that function, and hath giuen one talent vnto mee, for the instructing a little number of his flocke which he hath bought with his bloud, of
<pb facs="5"/>
whome he hath made me an ouerseer, and therefore it is not meete for me to passe ouer the sum of this life with the singing Grashopper, till the stormie nightes and Boriall blastes of winter come vpon mee, neither to let the cleare day passe idlelie, till the darke night come, when none can trauell, neither to followe the drone Bee, eating the labours of others, but rather to studie to discharge (in some measure) my selfe, according to my function, and to profite others. Seeing that I perceaue the greatest number of you my brethren, to followe the example of the Emmit, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the day, and busie as the Bees in the spring of the yeere, to gather their home, so you to accomplish the worke where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto you are called, the Lord prosper you and continue your proceedings. I haue therefore for my parte drawen a shorte treatise in Dialogue manner betwixt the Father and the Sonne out of Scripture, wherein may fullie and perfectlye be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued the duties of all sortes of people, how a Christian life is to be ledde, what thinges are needefull to saluation, the ende of man, and straite accompt in the fearefull iudgement, with a punishment of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb facs="5"/>
and reward of the righteous, not seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any prayse for the same, but Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, which all men ought to doe, seeing we are oftentimes tryed by our cheife Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocesan (according to our gracious Princesse commaundement) how we profet Gods people cōmitted vnto vs within his graces prouince, but especyally seeing we shall appeare before the great shepperd and Bishop of our soules Iesus Christ, to giue accompts of the bestowing of our Talents, that wee may receiue an incorruptable crowne of glorie, where they that haue taught others shall bee as the shining of heauen, and they that haue instructed the multitude vnto Godlynesse shall bee lyke the starres world without ende, and thus not doubting of your great care and dyli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in your functions, I beseech the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God from whome all good gruiftes doe proceede, encrease you with wisdome and knowledge in this life, and with eternal happinesse in the world to come. Thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearche, within the ancienty or lyberties of Yorke, the 12. day of Iunne. 1587.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your faithfull yokefellow in the Lord Iohn Lyster.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>