<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right worshipfull my good Lady the Lady Paulet, who was wife to the ho∣norable sir Hugh Paule Knight.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104961_Bo1_14_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18722</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5220</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104961</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right worshipfull my good Lady the Lady Paulet, who was wife to the ho∣norable sir Hugh Paule Knight.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Churchyards challenge</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 135, 126-170, 175-198, 209-232, 231-278 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <head>To the right worshipfull my good Lady the Lady Paulet, who was wife to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable sir <hi>Hugh Paule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Knight.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the manifold works in print, pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phelets, bookes, volumes, and deuises, I neuer addressed my pen to your Ladiship till now, though bound for many courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies better to consider of so good a Lady, and now worst able to redeeme duty forgotten, I bring my selfe backeward to behold my great ouersight, but presing forward to win ground, I leese the keeping of a writers credit, for no one thing is left worthy your view and looking on, such hast haue I had in the spoiling of my selfe &amp; inuentions: a prodicall point of bountie ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the part of a wise bountiful writer, especially to bestowe the best matters on others, and present but a dreame to your Ladiship, shewing thereby the shallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of my iudgement: but yet some such substaunce of matter as I trust is more delightfull than dainty. For my Dreame hauing many significations, may grow on ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny causes, and hit on a nomber of Accidents fit for my humour, but skarse meet for your graue consideration, yet such fancies as a dreame brings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>orth, I of necessitie must offer (because my store is not great) and such fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies as I haue, I hope your Lad. amongst the rest of my friends wil stand pleased with, til better matter fall out. So in heart, seruice, and goodwill, I betake you to the sweet blessing of the Almightie.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>