<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the vertuous, courteous, and worship∣full
Gentleman, Master Robert Greenewood of
Westerton, health, with the happinesse of both worlds.</title>
           <author>Fowldes, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104175_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03504</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13626</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104175</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the vertuous, courteous, and worship∣full
Gentleman, Master Robert Greenewood of
Westerton, health, with the happinesse of both worlds.</title>
                 <author>Fowldes, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The strange, vvonderfull, and bloudy battell betweene frogs and mise : the occasion of their falling out: their preparation, munition, and resolution for the warres: the seuerall combats of euery person of worth; with many other memorable accidents. Interlaced with diuers pithy and morall sentences, no lesse pleasant to be read, then profitable to be obserued. Couertly decyphering the estate of these times. Paraphrastically done into English heroycall verse by W.F. C.C.C</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Bailey, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <epigraph>
      <q>Perlege Maeonio cantatas carmine Ranas,
Et frontem nugis soluere disce meis.</q>
      <bibl>Martialis in Xenia, 183.</bibl>
   </epigraph>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the vertuous, courteous, and worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
Gentleman, Master Robert Greenewood of
Westerton, health, with the happinesse of both worlds.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch louing fauours from your sonne I found,</l>
      <l>So kind affection at your Worships hand,</l>
      <l>Though vndeserued, that I still am bound,</l>
      <l>And vnto you and yours obliged stand:</l>
      <l>And though that <hi>Greene</hi> braunch, which ay-springing stood,</l>
      <l>As chiefest crowne or garland to your <hi>wood,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Be by the stroke of Fate quite cut away,</l>
      <l>Ne're shall a thanklesse nature in me sway.</l>
      <l>No loftie Cedar, though in height he passe</l>
      <l>Eche seu'rall plant which desert forrests yeeld;</l>
      <l>No Laurell, though <hi>Apollo's</hi> tree it was;</l>
      <l>No Pine for shippes, no Oke ordayn'd to build,</l>
      <l>Nor any shrub was halfe so deare to me,</l>
      <l>As was that braunch falne from the <hi>Greenewoods</hi> tree:</l>
      <l>Which though, as dead, entomb'd in earth it lyes,</l>
      <l>A day will come, we hope, to see it rise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Here (worthy Sir) doe I present to you.</l>
      <l>The timely Buds of my frost-bitten Spring,</l>
      <l>And though this trifle not deserue your view,</l>
      <l>Yet such a trifle once did <hi>Homer</hi> sing,</l>
      <l>Adorn'd with robes, spun from the wooll of <hi>Greece,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Homely by me now clad in <hi>English</hi> fleece:</l>
      <l>Albeit no pleasure in this toy you take,</l>
      <l>Yet deigne a kind aspect for <hi>Hargreues</hi> sake,</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>The vnworthy wel-willer of your Worships
wel-fare, William Fowldes.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>