<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE OF THE translator.</title>
           <author>P., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104922_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18250</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4868</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104922</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE OF THE translator.</title>
                 <author>P., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The firme foundation of Catholike religion, against the bottomles pitt of heresies : wherin is shewed that only Catholiks shalbe saued, &amp; that all heretikes of what sect so euer are excluded from the kingdome of heauen. Compyled by Iohn Caumont of Champany: and translated out of French into English, by Iohn Pauncefote the elder Esquyre, in the tyme of his banishement</title>
                 <author>Caumont, Jean de</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Conincx, Arnout</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 115, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translators_preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE OF THE translator.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it hath bene often a great greef vnto me to consider hovv many of you (my deer frends and good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey men) not al of malice but some of blynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, some other of a folyshe feare, others also for lak of instructions and trevv infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiō of the holy Catholike Church the true spouse of Christ, do daylie erre and lyue in scisme &amp; heresie, diuiding yor selues by that meanes from Christ his mysticall bodie, &amp; hazarding your soules to perishe eternally: Euen so of late I did not a litle reioyce vvhē I hitt by chance on a litle frenche treatise, vvhich doth lyuelie expresse, &amp; as it vveare in a table sett furth such sufficient, true, &amp; infallible tokens of Christ his Church, that none can be ignorant that is vvilling to learne, nor no man lefte in blyndnes that vvil open his eyes to see. And albeit my skylin the french tonge is but small, yet the loue vvhich I beare to you my deare frendes hath supplied that vvant, and giueth me corage to attempt somthing aboue my strēgth
<pb facs="3"/> in translating the sayd treates as vvell as I could, vvhich I haue put to the print, that you may be partakers of it, trusting that you vvil accept the same as a token of my good vvill. And if it shall please God to send my labeur so good successe, as that any of you all receiue benefit therby: after due thankes to him that is author of all goodnes, I pray you remember me in your deuout prayers, vvho haue not bene vnmyndfull of you here in this my poore banishement. And so ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping you vvill excuse or amend such faultes as you may find eyther in the translation or printyng. I beseche God send you so much light, as to find the vvay home again to the Catholike Church. Fare you vvell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your louing frinde. I. P.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>