<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104049_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03223</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13340</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104049</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The iron age : contayning the rape of Hellen: the siege of Troy: the combate between Hector and Aiax: Hector and Troilus slayne by Achilles: Achilles slaine by Paris: Aiax and Vlisses contend for the armour of Achilles: the death of Aiax, &amp;c. Written by Thomas Heyvvood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>168 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="45"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader:</hi> I commend vnto thee an intire History, from <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturne,</hi> to the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ter subuersion of <hi>Troy▪</hi> with a faithfull account of the Deathes of all these Princes of <hi>Greece,</hi> who had hand in the Fate thereof, <hi>(Vlisses</hi> only excepted, to whom belongeth a further <hi>History.)</hi> Reade freely, and censure fauourably. These Ages haue beene long since Writ, and suited with the Time then: I know not how they may beereceiued in this Age, where nothing but <hi>Satirica Dictaeria,</hi> and <hi>Comica Scommata</hi> are now inrequest: For mine owne part, I neuer affected either▪ when they stret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the abuse of any person publicke, or priuate. If the three former Ages (now out of Print,) bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to these (as I am promised) to make vp an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Volumne; I purpose <hi>(Deo Assistente,)</hi> to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate
<pb facs="46"/>
the whole Worke, with an Explanation of all he difficulties, and an Historicall Comment of euery hard name, which may appeare obscure or intricate to such as are not frequent in Poetry: Which (as the rest) I shall freely deuote to thy fauorable perusall, in this as all the rest industrious to thy pleasure and profit:</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Heywood</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>