<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader, in what calling soeuer, Grace, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Arthington, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104408_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21674</idno>
           <idno type="STC">798</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104408</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader, in what calling soeuer, Grace, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Arthington, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Prouision for the poore, novv in penurie : Out of the store-house of Gods plentie: which they shall be sure to find in all places, that are indued with his graces, to thinke seriously on this sentence following. Explaned by H.A</title>
                 <author>H. A. (Henry Arthington)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>38 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader, in what calling soeuer, <hi>Grace, &amp;c.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He complaint of the poore through penurie in Englande, hath continued long, (good Christian reader) and yet it appeareth their want groweth greater. What should this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port? but either they cry not aright them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, to him that is able &amp; willing to help, or else the bowels of tender compassion are shut vp in such as should relieue them. Touching the poore that crie hard for foode, and finde small supply: the reason is, for that they doe not complaine vnto God of their grieuous sinnes (the verie maine cause of all their calamities:) which if they looke to haue released, and no further increased, they must confesse in maner following. First, that they haue misspent much good time in idle roging vp and downe, and woulde not worke: therefore the Lord doth iustly requite them, that now when they would, they shall not eate (or verie little.) Second, that in the time of abundance, they haue beene great wasters in bibbing and belly cheare: therefore nowe iustly they feele the want thereof. Thirdly, That when God by his messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, called vpon them to leaue their euill wayes, and serue him better, they would not heare to follow the same: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth God nowe shut vp his eares, and others also, when they cry for foode. If they would gladly then finde sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, they must resolue to turne to God quickly, to confesse all their sinnes, to aske him pardon, to promise amendment,
<pb facs="3"/>
and to pray dayly for increase of his grace, that they may performe the same, then will he shorly send them releefe. To come to those that should relieue the poore, whom God hath indued with wealth and abilitie, whereof some are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to supply their wants, and do it in some places to Gods glorie and their owne comfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, but others (alas) are too hard hearted, vnwilling almost to part with any thing (albeit they richly abound with all things, (and they may bee proued to haue bin makers of poore) vnto whō I speak in the name of the Lord,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Prou.</hi> 21.13</note>
      <hi>That if they still refuse to heare and helpe the needie when they crie for succour, they shall crie themselues and not bee heard when they would fainest speed.</hi> I wish thē therfore in time to shewe mercie (as this booke informeth them) least when they looke not for it, they finde strict iudgement without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mercie:<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.13.</note> for shall the Lord Iesus stand at the doore (in his needfull members) and will they not releeue him that came to saue them?<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>25.</hi> ch.</note> Then shall they bee reiected at the last great day into eternall torments. Lay this to your hearts ye rich men of the world, and open your eares and purses to the poore,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>41.</hi> ch.</note> whilst God giueth space and offereth you grace, least when you would haue it, you cannot finde it. If I could my selfe as well remoue their wants (as <hi>Ioseph</hi> preuented the like in Egypt) I should not thus sue for succor at your hands. The Lord open your hearts to extende com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion, that in the ende you may find consolation. So be it.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your poore welwiller,</hi> Hen. Arth.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="3"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>