<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104618_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16209</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3132</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104618</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A reuelation of the true Minerua : The effect of this booke. Who on earth be gods: and by what meanes mortall men may bee made immortall</title>
                 <author>Blenerhasset, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Printer to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle reader, the intricate sence of some things contayned in this smal treatise, may induce thy doubtfull minde into diuers iudgementes: therefore by obseruing the Alphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beticall order set down in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and so conferring the notes which I haue heare prefixed with the authours discourse, thou shalt (I doubt not,) finde a light sufficient to leade thee tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe that darknesse, and thou vnderstanding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his intent wilt (I hope) remaine sufficiently satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, which thing I hartily wishe.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>BEcause that diuers verie good Philosophers haue inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prited <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> this worde * <hi>Saturne</hi> to signifie the plentifull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundaunce of a minde endued with true vnderstanding, deriuing it from the greeke woorde <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: because also in his time the golden worlde was in the most flourishing estate: therefore hee is here brought in, as one indued with the true vnderstanding how to gouerne and rule a common weale: and so generally throughout this treatise, when any one whom the heathen for his woorthinesse woorshipped as a god is rehearsed, not the man, but the vertue which made him of so great estimation is to be regarded, and in this place the author with great admiration, finding all vertue, goodnes and godlinesse, to concurre in a woman, because he thinketh it no herisie to affirme that euery good man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the place of a Maiestrate is a god: therefore his intent
<pb facs="4"/> is, that they whom vertue made goddes, shoulde create this goddesse, the very beloued of God, on whom God hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly bestowed his great and best blessinges without measure, and thus he taketh his exordium from the <hi>Psal. 82</hi> God standeth in the congregation of the gods, &amp;c.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Pallas</hi> and <hi>Minerua</hi> by the authoritie of many Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> woulde seeme both to bee but one: because <hi>Pallas</hi> the daughter of <hi>Iupiter</hi> is called by the name of <hi>Minerua:</hi> yet this is most certayn, we reade but of one <hi>Pallas</hi> whose name is deriued of <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: shee is of some called <hi>Bellona</hi> the goddesse of warre, of other <hi>Tritonia,</hi> taking that name of the Fenne in which she was first founde: shee was compted the goddesse of humaine knowledge, and <hi>Aristotle</hi> calleth her <hi>Scientiarum &amp; prudentiae dea:</hi> but we read of <hi>5. Miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uae:</hi> all the Philosophers, and especially <hi>Tully</hi> (contrary to the opinion of manie Poets) do call one of them <hi>Disciplina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; Sapientiae dea,</hi> the great and greatest goddesse, euen shee who had the knowledge of heauenly wisedome: but howe so euer it was his intent is to showe that worldly wit is of none effect without heauenly wisedome, and for that cause <hi>Pallas</hi> doth here lament the losse of <hi>Mineruae,</hi> thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it not possible that the pollitike lawes of any common weale can bee of sufficient force to beate downe sinne, and to bridle the ranging desires of mans disposition with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diuinitie, and that the bodie cānot be brought to obey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie lawe, except that the working of the conscience bee the chiefe cause thereof: and so he proceedeth to his purpose, to prooue that heauenly wisedome is the knowledge and feare of God, and shee which is indued therewith, doth well deserue to be called <hi>Minerua,</hi> the very true goddesse of wisedome.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Alecto</hi> that spitefull furiesse of hell (for so haue the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> Auncients tearmed hatred and malice) doth vpon no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion deuise to hurt the happie, and such as by vertue doe as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende vnto the toppe of fortunes wheele, &amp; to aduaunce the vnworthie: therfore here he bringeth in <hi>Galathea,</hi> a light &amp;
<pb facs="5"/> very wanton woman, and thereby may be seene howe blind spite and hatred are: whose desire is alwayes to destroy the vertuous, and to aduaunce the wicked.</p>
   <p>
      <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> There is nothing else contayned in this verse but a Poeticall description of a deuise, such as the Popes holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is full of, especially when he woulde extinguishe the light of the Gospel, and as this verse seemeth to haue no sence, so his deuises haue no force, therefore it obserueth a certayne <hi>Decorum.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Farewell.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>