<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY BEST ESTEEMED
AND WORTHELY HONORED
LADY, THE LADY WALSINGHAM,
one of the Ladies of her Maiesties
Bed-chamber.</title>
           <author>Chapman, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104949_Bo1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06993</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17414</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104949</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY BEST ESTEEMED
AND WORTHELY HONORED
LADY, THE LADY WALSINGHAM,
one of the Ladies of her Maiesties
Bed-chamber.</title>
                 <author>Chapman, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Hero and Leander: begun by Christopher Marloe; and finished by George Chapman</title>
                 <author>Marlowe, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <distributor>Linley, Paul</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="24"/>
   <head>TO MY BEST ESTEEMED
AND WORTHELY HONORED
LADY, THE LADY WALSINGHAM,
one of the Ladies of her Maiesties
Bed-chamber.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Present your Ladiship with the last affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
of the first two Louers that euer
<hi>Muse</hi> shrinde in the Temple of <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie;</hi>
being drawne by strange instigation
to employ some of my serious time in so
trifeling a subiect, which yet made the
first Author, diuine <hi>Musaeus,</hi> eternall. And were it not that
wee must subiect our accounts of these common receiued con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits
to seruile custome; it goes much against my hand to
signe that for a trifling subiect, on which more worthines of
soule hath been shewed, and weight of diuine wit, than can
vouchsafe residence in the leaden grauitie of any <hi>Mony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Monger;</hi>
in whose profession all serious subiects are conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
But he that shuns trifles must shun the world; out of
whose reuerend heapes of substance and austeritie, I can, and
will, ere long, single, or tumble out as brainles and passionate
fooleries, as euer panted in the bosome of the most ridiculous
<pb facs="24"/>
Louer. Accept it therfore (good Madam) though as a trifle,
yet as a serious argument of my affection: for to bee thought
thankefull for all free and honourable fauours, is a great summe
of that riches my whole thrift intendeth.</p>
   <p>Such vncourtly and sillie dispositions as mine, whose con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment
hath other obiects than profit or glorie; are as glad,
simply for the naked merit of vertue, to honour such as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance
her, as others that are hired to commend with deepeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
politique bountie.</p>
   <p>It hath therefore adioynde much contentment to my
desire of your true honour to heare men of desert in Court,
adde to mine owne knowledge of your noble disposition, how
gladly you doe your best to preferre their desires; and haue as
absolute respect to their meere good parts, as if they came per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed
and charmed with golden incitements. And this most
sweet inclination, that flowes from the truth and eternitie of
Nobles; assure your Ladiship doth more suite your other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments,
and makes more to the aduancement of your Name,
and happines of your proceedings, then if (like others)
you displaied Ensignes of state and sowrenes in your fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head;
made smooth with nothing but sensualitie and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents.</p>
   <p>This poore Dedication (in figure of the other vnitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> and your selfe) hath reioynd you with
him, my honoured best friend; whose continuance of ancient
<pb facs="25"/>
kindnes to my still-obscured estate, though it cannot encrease
my loue to him, which hath euer been entirely circulare; yet
shall it encourage my deserts to their vtmost requitall,
and make my hartie gratitude speake; to which
the vnhappines of my life hath hetherto
been vncomfortable and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
dumbnes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>By your Ladiships vowd in
most wished seruice:
<hi>George Chapman.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>