<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GENERALL READER.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104033_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03196</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13316</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104033</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GENERALL READER.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The exemplary lives and memorable acts of nine the most worthy women of the vvorld : three Iewes. Three gentiles. Three Christians. Written by the author of the History of women</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Royston (Reston, Reyston, Roystore), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 212, 12 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>TO THE GENERALL READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Enerous Reader (for all the Iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are so) know, that <hi>History</hi> in generall,<note place="margin">A distinction of History.</note> is either <hi>Nugatory</hi> as in all comicall Drammae's; or <hi>adhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatory,</hi> as in the Fables of <hi>Aesop, Poggius, &amp;c.</hi> or <hi>fictionary,</hi> as in poeticall nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; or <hi>Relatory,</hi> such as soly adheare to truth without deviation or digression; of which onely the ancient Gramarians admitted, as worthy the name, and in which ranke I intreate thee to receive this following tractate.</p>
   <p>Of History there be foure <hi>species,</hi>
      <note place="margin">The species.</note> either taken from place, as <hi>Geography</hi>; from time, as <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologie</hi>; from Generation as <hi>Geneologie; or</hi> from gests really done, which (not altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly) may be called <hi>Annologie:</hi>
      <note place="margin">The Elemens</note> The Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of which it consisteth are person, place, time,<note place="margin">The defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> manner, instrument, matter, and thing: It is defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb facs="7"/>
      <hi>Rerum gestarum expositio,</hi> a declaration of such things as have beene done:<note place="margin">
         <hi>The derivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Budaeus</hi> in his Greeke commentaries derives Historia from <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, that is, I narrate, I looke, I see, I inquire, aske, know, seeke, learne, dictate, &amp;c. besides what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is gravely explicated, my goe under the name of History.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The profit that comes by reading of history.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Simon Grinaeus</hi> speaking of the utilitie that ariseth unto us from the reading of History hath words to this purpose. What can be thought more pleasing or profitable then in this spatious Theater of humane life, for a man to instruct his understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, by searching to know whatsoever is marve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously carried in all the parts thereof? To view the danger of others without any perill to himselfe, thereby to make him the more wise and cau<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>elous? to make happy use of forreigne presidents and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples by applying them to his owne perticulars? to be as it mere private with the greatest men, in their gravest counsells, and not onely privie to the purpose, but partaker of the event? To be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all the passages of state, the qualitie of times, the succession of Ages the vicessitude of both? The situation of countries, the originall of nations? the rare lives of good Princes, the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ends of Cruell Tirants? To make all that hath beene precedent, as familiar with us as the present, forreigne lands as well knowne unto us as that wherein we live: The acts of our fore fathers as visible unto our eyes as were they now in being: As ours (if we shall doe ought worthy remembrance)
<pb facs="7"/>
commended to all the posteritie: briefly such is the benefit of History, that comparing what is past with the present, we may better prepare our selves for the future.</p>
   <p>Further to the exact composure of History, there belongs such an accurate curiositie, that whosoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver shall atta<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne to the true method and manner, may boast he hath transcended <hi>Herodatus, Xiphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line, Dio, Trogus Pompeius, Justine, Livy, Curtius, Tacitus, Swetonius,</hi> and even <hi>Caesar</hi> in his Commentaries: To all which I must inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niously confesse I am so many degrees inferiour that I dare not list my selfe in the number of the History<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers being now rather a remembrancer or collector of some passages concerning the persons now in agitation.</p>
   <p>But my discourse at this present is of women, and women onely, intimating to my selfe, that it is a kinde of duty in all that have had mothers, as far as they can to dignifie the Sex, which in my <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: or History of Women, I have strived to doe with my utmost minerva; but that was a meare misce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine of all ages, sexes, qualities, complexions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions dispositions, of rich, poore, learned, unlearned, faire, foule, well featured, deformed, barraine, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, matron, meretrix, and all in generall, from the Scepter to the sheepe booke. From the Court to the Cottage. But in this tractate I have onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorated the lives and memorable Acts of nine <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>alluding to the number of the Muses.) Three <hi>Iewes,</hi> three <hi>Gentiles,</hi> three <hi>Christians.</hi>
      <pb facs="8"/>
Courteous Reader, what is here proposed to thy view, peruse without prejudice. What thou fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest worthy just taxation, correct without mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice: which granted, the Nine worthy Women go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before, it may bee presumed that the Nine worthy Men may at some small distance follow.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Constantly devoted to thy content, THO. HEYVVOOD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>