<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A preface of the Author to the reader</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1540</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104539_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10769</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21038</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104539</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A preface of the Author to the reader</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A commentary in Englyshe vpon Sayncte Paules Epystle to the Ephesyans : for the instruccyon of them that be vnlerned in tonges, gathered out of the holy scriptures and of the olde catholyke doctours of the churche, and of the beste authors that nowe a dayes do wryte. Anno D. 1540 Per Lancelotum Ridleum Cantabrigensem</title>
                 <author>Ridley, Lancelot</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Redman, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1540</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>258 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>A preface of the Author to the reader</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>RACE MERCYE</hi> and peace from God the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther and from our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sus Chryst / be vnto al them that loueth / fauoureth / and promotethe the truthe of Goddes worde. Amen.</p>
   <p>♣Many and dyuers causes moued me to wryte this Commentary in Englyshe / O gentyle reader for theyr sakes whiche do nat vnderstāde Latyn but onely rede En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glysshe / to helpe the rude and ignoraunce people to more knowlege of God and of his holy worde. Because I perceyue fewe or none to go about to open by commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries or exposicions in Englyshe to the vnlearned to declare the holy Scriptures nowe suffered to all people of this realme to rede &amp; to study at their pleasure to their edifyenge and comforte in god by the kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges gracyous lycence / for the whiche thīg bye thankes is to be gyuen to God and laud &amp; praise to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kīges highnes y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> so tēde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth the helth &amp; saluacyon of h{is} subiectes
<pb facs="3"/>
that wylleth they shal lacke nothyng that may be to their comforte and soules helth and specyally that they shall nat lacke the worde of God / whiche is the foode of the soule. Math. 4. that saueth the soule. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi. 1. the armour onely wherby the deuil and all hys temtacyons is withstande / re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>systed &amp; ouercommen. Ephesyans .6. the meane wherby God doth saue them that beleue. 1. Corin. 1. ye the spyryte and the lyfe .1. that bryngeth the spyryte of God and lyfe euerlastynge. Because I could percayue fewe or none to go aboute to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and declare thys worde of lyfe to the Englysshe people vnlearned in tonges that it myghte be lyfe in dede / whyche nowe vndeclared to them but onelye had in the bare Lettre do appere to many rather deathe then lyfe / rather to brynge men in to errours and heresyes / then into the truethe and veryte of Goddes worde / whiche nowe vndeclared bryngeth not so muche the symple / rude / and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunte people frome theyre ignoraunte / blyndnes / corrupte and backewarde iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes / false trustes / euyll beleues / vayne superstycyousnes and fayned holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / in the whyche the people haue bene
<pb facs="3"/>
in blyndnes longe tyme for lacke of know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of holye Scripture. which the man of Rome kepte vnder the hatche &amp; wolde nat suffer to com to lyght to delyuer the seruaūtes of God from ignoraunce and blyndnes / but wolde haue kepte them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in darkenes / that his vsurped power shulde nat haue ben espied / his worldely glorye menysshed and his profyte decayed Bycause I dyd se none go aboute to dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the rude people frome theyr blyndnes ignoraunce or errours by any exposicion in Englishe vpon the Scriptures but ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny to study rather to continewe them styl in errours and in blynde ignoraunce ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I as one of the least lerned of al hath set forth and expocision to this Epystel of Saynt Paule to the Ephesyans as afore this in the Epystel of Iude the Apostle of Chrest y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the people y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> can but onely rede Englishe may y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> better know part of the holsome doctryne of saynt Paule may be delyuered from theyr ignoraunce and blin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>denes / corrupte and backewarde iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes / euyll oppynions / rooted in theyr hartes / false trustes and vayne supersticy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes / whiche the holy Ghoste here spea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge in Saynt Paule reproueth and cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demneth
<pb facs="4"/>
/ and teacheth nessysarye thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for mannes saluacyon as you maye here se and reade in thys exposicyon whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein I haue as it hathe pleased God to gyue his grace opened the holy scriptures shewynge the true vse of them / and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they serue. And in this thynge to be done I haue vsed the helpe of tonges as of the Greke / Hebrewe and the Latyne tonges / and the helpe of the olde Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke Doctours approued by the Churche and also of the beste authors that in these dayes nowe do wryte / and of them al ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out that after my iudgement shuld declare the Scripture beste and moste for the glory of God and / and for the edyfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge of the chrystians vnlearned in ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / as maye be sene throughout all thys Exposycyon.</p>
   <p>☞ The seconde cause that moued me to this was to dyscharge my conscience kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wynge the gyftes of God gyuen to be dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse / gyuen to euery man nat to be idle / but to exercyse hym selfe in hys talentes gyuen / to the glory of God and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyte of other. In this my talente gyuen of God / al thought I knowe it is the leaste of all it is my deutye nat to be idle / but to
<pb facs="4"/>
exercise my talente in all maner of wayes to promote and set forthe Goddes worde to edifie other / to do this thing I thought no waye more to Goddes glorye and to the edyfyenge of other / then to set fourthe an exposycyon of some parte of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pture to brynge men vnlearned to the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue and desyre of holye Scrypture whyche is the true worde of the spyryte of God to the whiche thynge the vnlearned shall be broughte to when they shall se and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely perceyue so muche holsome doctryne / so many godly vertues shewed in one litle Epystle of Saynt Paule / what godly les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and Spyrytuall teachynges shulde they haue in the hole Byble. yf it were in like maner declared vnto them? syth there is so muche heauenly teachynges in one lytle Epystle of Saynte Paule.</p>
   <p>❧The thyrde cause was to exhorte o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that be muche better learned than I that can do muche better to set fourth so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me parte of the holy Scripture in Engly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>she or in Latyne to shewe the goodnes of God to vs Englyshemen / to shewe that God is the God of Englande as well as of Fraunce / Italye / Germanye / or other countrees. And that he hathe shewed hys
<pb facs="5"/>
truethe as well in Englande as in these countreys. For God is not the acceptor of personnes or of countres. In Englande be men of no lesse wytte / wysedome / lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge / eloquence / then be in Fraunce / I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talye / Germanye / or other countres. ye I wyl not speake of more wysedome and learnynge / leaste I shulde be counted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy all to my countre. Ye I doubte not but Englyshe men shulde gyue as greate light to the worde of God as euer dyd these countres / yf they wolde applye theyr stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye wyttes and myndes to wryte vpon the holy Scrypture and in wrytynge de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare it. Which thynge many learned men wolde do / yf hye rulers whome God hath set in authoryte to be defenders and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters of hys worde / wolde excyte and prouoke learned men ther vnto. And whē a Commentary of the holy scrypture were wryten approued of learned men worthye pryntynge / it myghte be prynted and set fourth with pryuylege. So God shulde be more gloryfyed / his worde better knowen and beleued / greate glory and commenda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion come to Englande / whiche shulde gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue greate lyght in the true vnderstanding of the scriptures to all the worlde.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="5"/>☞These and many other causes moued me to wryte thys playne Exposy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon in thys Epystle of Sayncte Paule to the Ephesians. Wherfore gentle reader I praye the accepte in good worthe thys my rude dylygence and laboures / whyche was to set fourth openly before euery man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes eyes the mynde of the Apostle Saynte Paule in this Epistle / to shewe what thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge he wolde haue vs to knowe and to do / and what thynge not to do / and howe he seketh alwaye Goddes glorye and the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacyon of other to teache vs to do suche lyke. yf thys Epystle be declared accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the mynde of Sayncte Paule gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue all thankes and prayse to God onely of whome it commethe / and none to the wryter whose mynde is to teache or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende no errour nor heresye / but to teache the truethe of Goddes worde symply and playnely / more regardynge the truethe / then the eloquence of wordes / and by the truethe of the Gospell to profyte euery man yf he can. Yf thys Exposycyon do agree wyth the holye Scryptures / as I truste it dothe / take it / yf it do not / re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuse it / I wolde not haue my wrytyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or sayenges no farther to be taken
<pb facs="6"/>
then they do agree with the holy Scryp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures of God and by them maye be prouyd / and by the holy Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res onely to be iudged. I am a man and maye erre as well as other hathe done / but I wyll nat be obsty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nat / yf I shall be gently admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyshed and instruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted better by the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures of god to whome be all honoure and glorye / worlde without ende. A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men.</p>
   <trailer>❧ ¶ Here endeth the preface of the author.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>