<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧To the courteous and freendly Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104464_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23370</idno>
           <idno type="STC">980</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104464</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧To the courteous and freendly Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An excellent historie bothe pithy and pleasant, discoursing on the life and death of Charles and Iulia, two Brittish, or rather Welshe louers : No lesse delightfull for varietie, then tragicall in their miserie, not hurtfull to youthe, nor vnprofitable to age, but commodious to bothe. By W.A</title>
                 <author>Averell, W. (William)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>❧To the courteous and freendly Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle reader, I shall not neede with superfluous prayses to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto thée, either the pleasure or profit thou maist take in perusing this straunge and lamentable Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story, let the meate be seene in the man, the Trée in his fruite, the Flower in his sent, the cloth in his wool, and the Wine in his taste, <hi>Nam vino vendibili nihill opus est suspensa haedera,</hi> which béeing saleable, néedes no Iuie Garlande, yet herein mayst thou see the vanitie of youthe, the corruption of nature, the vnstedfastnesse of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, the faithfulnesse of fréendship: but especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the punishment, that God sheweth vpon those wanton childrē, which without consent of their Parents mindes, from whom they had their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, doo stubernely, or at least wise foolishly knit that knot, which the aduise of their Parentes should moste fyrmelye fasten, running rashlye vpon the Rockes of theyr owne ruine, and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the Sandes of their owne séeking, to the auoydinge of which inconueniences I haue penned for thy delight this Historye, of two Brittish or rather Welsh loouers, whose amorous affections I haue somewhat louer lyke depaynted, not that I bringe Oyle
<pb facs="4"/>
to maintaine the light of <hi>Venus</hi> lampe, but with the saciety therof quight to extinguish her flame, that Loouers perusing the wanton contracts of these two <hi>Venus</hi> darlings, may by the fulsome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of theyr straunge euents, be driuen into disliking of so vaine a pastime, or rather a mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, which altereth the minde, chaungeth the body, peruerteth reason, subuerteth wisdom, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelleth ioye, and bringeth with it more poundes of paine, then drams of delight, these affections, or otherwise infections, mayst thou (curteous Reader) perceaue bothe one and other in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell of this discourse, which may peraduenture in the eies of some, séeme ouerwanton, and more worthye a Fagot to burne it, then a Candell to reade it, but the garment is not to be cast away, that is fretted with some Mothes, the Rose is not to be reiected for his sharpe prickelles: nor the Tree to be rooted vp, whose fruite is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what wormeaten, séeing they all may serue bothe for pleasure and commoditie, neyther is this discourse to be discommended, eyther for the grosenesse of the Theame being loue, or for the effeminacy of the personnes being louers, séeing bothe the one and the other are esteemed and practised among those whose heaires are not so graye with age, but theyr harts are as gréene in luste, that drawing euen againe to theyr former Childehood, yet can spell <hi>A. M. O.</hi> when they
<pb facs="4"/>
haue one foote on the ground, and the other in their graue. But wishing vnto such more grace, and to the younger sorte more grauity: I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, referring thy iudgement to the view of this my rude discription, crauing thee to suspend thy verdyt, tyll thou hast considered the end, and then not despise my labor, which I haue attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for thy onely pleasure, least I may say iuste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of thée. <hi>Ego volens laboraui, et tu improbe sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophantaris,</hi> and thus desiring thée to beare both with the Printers faults and mine, which he hath committed by vnwarinesse, and I by wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynesse, I end, excusing my selfe with that olde Verse of the Poet, <hi>In opere longo fas est obre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere somnum,</hi> and so I commit this treatise to thy learned correction, and thy selfe to the almighties protection, whom I beseeche to guyde thée.</p>
   <closer>Farewell.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>