<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Praeface.</title>
           <author>Wynchester, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104234_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03691</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13818</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104234</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Praeface.</title>
                 <author>Wynchester, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An ansvveare made by Rob. Bishoppe of VVynchester, to a booke entituled, The declaration of suche scruples, and staies of conscience, touchinge the Othe of the Supremacy, as M. Iohn Fekenham, by vvrytinge did deliuer vnto the L. Bishop of VVinchester : vvith his resolutions made thereunto</title>
                 <author>Horne, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wykes (Wekes), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>2, 130 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Praeface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is nowe an whole yéere paste, since I herde of a booke secretely scattered abroade by M. Fekenham emonge his fréendes: And in April laste I came by a copie therof. When I had redde the booke, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued bothe the matter and the maner of the mannes doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges therein: I sawe his proofes so sclendre: and his maner of dealinge so shameles: that I stoode in doubte what to doo, whether to discouer the man by writinge, or to shake him of with silence. If I had not séene a further meaninge in his settinge foorth and publishinge the booke, then he durste plainely vtter, or then his cunninge coulde by any meanes Answeare vnto: or then, that I with a good conscience mought haue neglected: I woulde haue paste it ouer with silence, as a péece of woorke not woorthie of Answeare. But séeing the chiefe ende and principall purpose intended, as may be iustly gathered in publishyng the booke, was, to ingrafte in the mindes of the subiectes a mislikyng of the Quéenes Maiestie, as though she vsurped a power, and authoritie in Ecclesiasticall matters, whereto she hath no righte: to sclandre the whole Realme, as though it were stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and directly against the Catholike Churche, renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinge and refusinge to haue Communion therewith: And vndre my name to deface the mynisters of Christes Churche: I coulde not choose, oneles I woulde wilfully ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect my duetie to her Maiestie, shewe my selfe ouermuch vnkinde vnto my natiue Countrey, and altogeather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb facs="3"/>
carelesse of the Churche Mynisterie, but take penne in hande, and shape him a ful and plaine answeare, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any curiositie. Wherein I folowe the order of M. Fekenhams booke: I make the proofes accordyng to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest: and besides my proofes foorth of the Scriptures, the auncient Doctours, the Generall councelles and Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: I make proofe by the continuall practice of the Churche, in like gouernement as the Quéenes Maiestie taketh vpon her, and that, by suche Authors, for a great sort of them, as are the more to be credited in this matter, for that they were moste earnest fautours of the Romishe sea, infected as the times weare, with muche superstition, and did attribute vnto the sea of Rome, and so to the whole Cleargie so muche authoritie in Churche matters, as they mighte, and muche more then they ought to haue done. Their iudgementes and sentences shall appeare in readinge by the forme of letter: for leuinge foorth the Latine to auoide tediousnes, I haue put into English the Authours mindes and sentences, and caused them, for the moste parte, to be Printed in Latine letters, that the English reader may know and decerne the Authours say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges from mine.</p>
   <p>If this that I haue done, woorke that effect in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishe Reader whiche he ought to séeke, and I doo wishe, I haue wonne that I wrought for: but otherwise, let men saie and iudge what they liste, I haue discharged my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science and shewed the trueth. <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1565. <hi>Feb.</hi> 25.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Rob. Wynchester.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>