<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the hy∣ghe excellent and most gracious Prynce Edward Duke of Somerset, Erle of Hertforthe viscounte Beane Campe. Lorde Semer, Gouerner of the Kynges Maiesteis person, and Protector of al hys realmes, hys leauetenaū te general of al hys armyes, boht by lande &amp; by sea, treasoroure and Erle marshall of En∣gland, Gouernour of the Ylles of Gern¦sey &amp; Iersey and knight of the most noble order of y• gar¦ter</title>
           <author>Mardeley, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104366_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06886</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17317</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104366</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the hy∣ghe excellent and most gracious Prynce Edward Duke of Somerset, Erle of Hertforthe viscounte Beane Campe. Lorde Semer, Gouerner of the Kynges Maiesteis person, and Protector of al hys realmes, hys leauetenaū te general of al hys armyes, boht by lande &amp; by sea, treasoroure and Erle marshall of En∣gland, Gouernour of the Ylles of Gern¦sey &amp; Iersey and knight of the most noble order of y• gar¦ter</title>
                 <author>Mardeley, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A declaration of thee power of Gods worde : concerning the holy supper of the Lord, confutynge all lyers and fals teachers, whych mayntayne theyr maskynge masse inuented agaynst the woorde of God, and the Kynges Maiesties most godly proceadynge compyled anno d [omi] ni M.D.XLVIII</title>
                 <author>Mardeley, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raynald, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe excellent and most gracious Prynce Edward Duke of Somerset, Erle of Hertforthe viscounte Beane Campe. Lorde Semer, Gouerner of the Kynges Maiesteis person, and Protector of al hys realmes, hys leauetenaū te general of al hys armyes, boht by lande &amp; by sea, treasoroure and Erle marshall of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, Gouernour of the Ylles of Gern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sey &amp; Iersey and knight of the most noble order of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter</head>
   <head type="sub">¶ Ihon Mardeley wysheth grace peace &amp; abundaunce of knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in gods truthe securitie of body wyth long lyfe in the lyuinge God. Thorowe Christe Iesus oure onely sauioure.</head>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
COnsyderynge redup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and moost noble prynce, howe prone and ready the malig ners of gods veritie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all theyr exacte diligence, to depraue and say yll, aswel of the true doctrine of that infallable and syncier truth, as al so of thee teachers &amp; preachers of the same, it hath in manner cōpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oundering the great dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceatfulnesse and sturdynesse of the se wycked wordlinges whych bee so pernyscyously bent to blynde y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people of god wyth lyes &amp; old wy fe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ables to depresse &amp; holde dow ne the gospel of christe, and styl to vpholde and mayntayne mannes inuencyons, dreames &amp; tradiciōs. Thus moste gracious lord hath in maner coharted me, to set fourthe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s symple worke, touchyng the most holy body and bloud of christ whyche is the food of oure soules and confortable pledge of our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, sertyfyenge the true bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers to be made heyres of eternal lyfe, and the partakers of all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes
<pb facs="4"/>
merytes. Death and resurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the whych moste sacred my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterie, hathe bene bothe learnedly and pythely, by soundrye notable clerckes, and learned menne, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulgated vnto the congregacyon as well in theyr Sermoones as in wrytynges therein confutyng all errours and false opynyons why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the vngodlye malygners ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue seduced thee people in, and yet doo bothe by wryt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nge and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge, contrarye vnto the insty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Christe the symple mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges of the Scriptures and the Kynges Maiesties mooste godlye<note place="margin">beholdoye chyldrē of Syō and reioyce in the Lorde you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> god for he hath geuen you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> teacher of ryghtes ousnes Io. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> proceadynges, where of youre gra ce is a fortherer of the same I haue most redoupted lord as one moste vnworthy and indynge, wythout profound knowledge of learning confes me far vnhable to enter in the discussing of so hygh a matter yet albeyt I haue according vnto the talente whych I haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not hydyng it in the grounde as dyd that euel seruaunte, but to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
      <pb facs="5"/>
measure and vnderstāding which I haue receaued of god by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gyfte of hys spyryte I wyll lyke vnto ruthe the mohabite, grayne some parte aswell vpō the land of scrip ture as vpon auncient Doctours approued, and thē so gathered as it were in a bundell together, the true vnderstanding of this mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal meate of christes body &amp; bloud Declaring the right vse therof as by the worde of God shalbe playn lye approue, and for bycause as yet this holy misterie hangeth as it were in a ballaunce, and not the true weyghe therof as yet recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the multitude I haue dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated this symple worke into you re noble grace, vnto whome God hath not onely cōmytted the gard and defence of thys polytyke and ciuile realme, But also the setting furth and ratifycacion of Goddes moste infalable word whych hath many yeres sustayued open &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfest wronge, in thys holy myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. And bycause I cannot so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly prefer this vrgent matter to so prudent and myhhty a Prynce as youre grace is, yet I truste my good wyll and dyligence is accep
<pb facs="5"/>
ted of God, and thoughe it be but very litle that I can do, yet I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe lykewyse that for the declarati on of thys symple and manifest ve ritie▪ your grace woll pardon my bolde euterpryse and accept thys powre worke of my s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>are houres in good parte, whych shall encora ge youre prayerman, to the more continuaunce of study here after. Thus god the eternall father for the death and bloud sheddynge of hys onely sonne Iesus Christ our sauiour preserue the Kinges Ma iestie, your most noble grace with all hys mooste honourable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayle, and the hole realme to gods glorye.</p>
   <closer>Amen.</closer>
   <closer>
      <signed>¶ Your most humble oratour Ihon Mardeley Clerc of the Kynges Maiesties mynte called suffol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke house.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>