<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The BOOKE to the sober and discreet Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104068_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03239</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13356</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104068</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The BOOKE to the sober and discreet Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Philocothonista, or, The drunkard, opened, dissected, and anatomized</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Crouch (Crowch), John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Raworth, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 91, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>❧</hi> The BOOKE to the sober and discreet Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Enerous Reader, thou hear'st my charge, and I come to present my selfe to thy viewe, like a Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Bill, pitifully complaining. The reason is, because I am turn'd out, like a masterles man, without Patron, or Mecaenas to counta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance mee, much misery I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, meerely for my names-sake: For is he that hath a bad name is said to be halfe hang'd, what may I hope for then, when mine is so abominable; Notwithstanding, if my condition had accorded with my Title. I might have had Incouragers enough, and too many; but when they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood my nature and my name were directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sites (For many who were loath to have me follow them publikly in the streetes, would have beene glad to have hugg'd me in their private Chambers) I then was left de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute, both of pitty and patronage: For instance; I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented my service to a great Favourite in the Court, who when hee apprehended that my comming was, rather to plucke up, then plant the Vine, and to condemne, not countenance the vice, he bit the lip, contracted the brow, and made me this answere: <hi>And would'st thou barre me from drinking healths to the Prince whom I serue? the Lords whom I honour? and my Mistris whom I love?</hi> So with a looke able to sowre the next draught before he swallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, left me.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>From the Court I tooke my progresse into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, where hearing of a Noble house-keeper, who kept liberall hospitalitie (not common in these dayes) I ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred my seruice to him, who generously excused himselfe thus. <hi>Friend, would'st thou have mee now close-handed, and to set a pad-locke upon my Buttery hatch; If my seruants bee freely entertained in other great mens Sellers? Shall I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid their followers to drinke drunke in mine?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>From him I went to an old Country Lawyer, his next Neighbour, who presently clapt his spectacles on his nose, and reading my inside, with my Title (in a great chollar, which swell'd up his ruffe as hie, as his veluet cap) said, <hi>Hence from my doores thou imposture, which art not what thou seemest, were it not for such of thy name, who quarrell in their cups, how should I doe for clients to maintaine my estate?</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Neere unto the Lawyer, dwelt a Farmer: I descended so low, as to offer my selfe to him, telling him my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and qualitie, he replied in a furie, <hi>How then shall I pay my Land-lord? were it not for Drunkards, I should sow no more Barley, so might the Malt-men starue, and I perish.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Having such cold comfort in the Countrey, I then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to come up to <hi>London</hi> with the Carryer. The first Inne wee came unto, I open'd my selfe to mine Host (a Iollie Corpulent fellow, and a boone Companion) who at the very motion, first stamped, then staring, he began at length to be starke mad, saying aloud; <hi>Who then shall keepe my guests vp all night? call in for drinke? and put them to unnecessary charges? how shall my Tapster live? or I main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine fire in thy Kitchin? As good perswade me to cut downe my signe-post: For thinkest thou, that I can eate and drinke hay and water, with the Horses?</hi> Much adoe I had to get lodging there that night, but with condition, to be gone thence by the day breake in the morning. At length I came to the Citie, and hoping to have beene entertain'd by one of the Sheriffes, I found the Seargeants and Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ready to beate their siluer Flagons about mine eares.
<pb facs="4"/>
Their Sellers were open for all commers, and I onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and extruded, for by no intreaty, they would shew me to their Masters. The <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spanish</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, that trade in Wines, rejected me, <hi>as one who had laid some project to undermine, and blow up their trafficke.</hi> I then thought good to find some reliefe at Vintners Hall, but there I was more churlishly repulsed, then at any time before. They call'd mee Innovator, and told mee, <hi>I had laid a plot to begger them, who had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> so many.</hi> I went thence to the Fraternitie of the Brewers, and finding them assembled, I had no sooner petitioned to them; but they presently open'd so many stale bottles mouthes against mee, that I was afraid either to be drown'd in their frothy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> (which powr'd upon me like a deluge) or to be shot to death with their corkes, which peal'd against mee like so many Pot-guns: For which injury, I complained to a Iustice, desiring his warrant; and withall, besought him of entertainement. But hee gave me this short answere. <hi>I prethee friend, how then dost thou thinke my Clerke should live?</hi> I then was in dispaire, but thus comforted my selfe, surely one Schollar will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the worke of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and so put my selfe upon a Poet, who looking first stedfastly upon mee, after a small pause, gave mee this short answere, and so left mee.</p>
   <p>
      <q>Ennius <hi>ipse pater num nisi potus ad Arma prosiluit.</hi>
      </q>
   </p>
   <lg>
      <l>Old father <hi>Ennius</hi> never durst aspire</l>
      <l>To write strong line, till <hi>Bacchus</hi> lent him fire.</l>
   </lg>
   <p>I have now no refuge; but to thee (oh temperate and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>screete Reader) under whose wings I hope at length to be shadowed, if not supported; For which favour, I shall protest me thine in all sober s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>dnesse,</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Philocothonista</hi> Anatomized.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>