<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE REDERS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1536</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104591_Bo1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12945</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23236</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104591</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE REDERS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A preface to the Kynges hyghnes</title>
                 <author>Starkey, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1536</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6+ 88, that is 98 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="1" facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE REDERS.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR BICAVSE I HAVE here</hi>
folowynge somwhat more brefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
than the nature of the thynge
dothe well suffre, comprised and
gathered vnto the people a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
instruction, whereby they
myghte the better be induced to suche vnitie and
obedience as is of theym mooste iustely requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:
I shall mooste Christen reders, here in this
prologue, open vnto you a lyttel more at large,
what is the nature of this obedience and vnitie,
to the whiche we be so straytly bounde bothe by
goddis lawe and all good ciuilitie: and touche
also somwhat the cause whiche hath chiefly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
me to the conceyuynge of this mattier and
purpose. But here in the begynnynge to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
the thyng may the better be perceyued, I do
you require a lyttelle to lyfte vp your eies with
som consideration, to wey with your selfe in som
part the diuine power, wysedome, &amp; prouidence,
thoughe the thynge fully to conceyue farre sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth
all mannes witte and imagination.
And fyrst this is open and manifest,<note place="margin">The prouy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of god.</note> that al this
sensible worlde, wherin is conteyned this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
varietie and nature of thingis,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> is nothing
els but as a certayne shadowe of goddis good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
and diuinitie, or rather a glasse of the diuine
maiestie, wherby to mans iudgement and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie
is opened, the infinite power,<note place="margin">Psa. 18.</note> and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="6"/>
wisedome of hym, who by his hyghe prouy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
gouerneth and ruleth all. For whither so
euer you cast your eies, other aboue vnto heuen,
there beholdynge that heuenly body in his syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie,
other here benethe vnto the erthe, there
considerynge of nature the wonderfull varietie,
you shall euer see, of that power and prouidence
in euery thinge mooste certayne argumente and
sure testimony. Wherof I thynke no man canne
doubte, who wyth any consyderation, lokynge
into this glasse, there standeth in meruayle and
admyration. For fyrst there shall he see the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte
nombre &amp; multitude of sterres euer kepyng
their certayn course and mouyng without al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stabilitie,
there shal he se the son, the mone, with
all the other planettes waueryng abrode, nowe
to this parte of the worlde, nowe to the other,
to the comforte and creation of all mortal thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
subiecte to corruption: there shall he see the
wonderful vertue and influence of the same, by
the whiche as by chiefe instrumentes the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
of god worketh al thinges. Here in the lower
worlde garnyshyng it with this varietie, wherin
standeth all naturall beautie. ye, &amp; yet ferther, yf
he into this glasse diligently loke, there shall he
see, of the foure elementes, of the fyre, the ayre,
the water, and of the erthe, the mooste meruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
nature, so knytte by dewe proportion in a
certaine equalitie, that though they be by nature
mooste dyuers and full of contrarietie, yet they
<pb n="2" facs="6"/>
are cowpled and ioyned togyther, as it were in
a natural concorde and vnitie: there shall he see
the erth, as foundation and ground, susteyning
the reste, hangynge in the myddes after a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
maner, and about the same the see conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
rollynge, with his certayne and sure eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bynge
and flowynge after a strange fashion, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge
to mans wytte no smal cause of meruayle
and great admyration: and fynally to say, there
shall he see of all beastes, fyshes, and fowles, the
meruaylous nature and propretie, by the which
all, the diuine power spredeth her goodnes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng
to the nature of thinges and their capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie:
so that to hym who so euer into this glasse
diligently dothe loke, may remayne no doubt of
this heuenly wysedome and prouydence, wherof
in euery thinge here in this worlde sette forth to
goodis honour and glorye, appereth so sure tokē
and so certayne signe, for in euery thyng shyneth
the image therof, euery thing here is a glasse of
the same. And to me this thinge, considerynge &amp;
reasonynge with my selfe of the goodnes of god
and of his prouidēce, though the thinges before
touched mynister therof sure profe and sufficient
argument, yet it appereth, that nothynge more
clerely declareth the same, than mans actis and
fashion of lyuynge here in policie, all be it many
men haue taken thereby greate argument to the
contrary, in so moche, that whan they haue sene
many men longe to contynue in worldly ioy and
<pb facs="7"/>
prosperitie, whome they haue iudged most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
of al aduersitie: and contrary, other of great
perfection &amp; vertue to be oppressed with al wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chednes
and myserie. This I say, whā they haue
sene, they haue playnly thought, no prouidence
to be nor gouernance of god, but all to be lefte to
mans wyl and tyranny: To the whiche opinion
they slypped, for lacke of iugement and good cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syderation:
for who so euer weyeth mans actes
groundly,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> and of his lyfe the hole proces, he shal
fynde moste manifestly, and by reasone shall be
constrayned playnly to confesse, that this highe
prouydence is not onely declared by suche dedes
and actes of man, as appere to the worlde to be
good and vertuous, but also moche more by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
whiche seme pestilent and pernicious, and
to all vertue contrarye. For this semeth to be a
certayne truthe and sure, that euen lyke as god
by his infinite goodnes, these erthequakes and
general fluddes, by the whiche many cities and
hole nations oft tymes be ouerflowē and sonke,
euer tourneth to the good order of the reste, and
conseruation of the holle in a naturall tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite:
so vice reygning in mans lyfe for a tyme, ye
open warre and sedition, his goodnes cōuerteth
to the settyng forthe of vertue and to his honour
and glory. For such is the nature of that infinite
goodnes, that nothinge it wyll suffre vtterly to
be yll, but out of al imperfection and vicious ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes,
or more truly to say, vicious defectes, his
<pb n="3" facs="7"/>
goodnes pyketh out euer some good. As by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
this thinge to declare, this dyuelyshe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
of the dyuell, who aboue al other thinges is
moste pestilent and pernicious, the goodnes of
god vseth to good, as to driue man by fere at the
lest to flee from synne and wretchednes, and his
crueltie and malyce he vseth also to declare his
iustyce and ryghtwysenes, as by the miserye of
vice he driueth man oft to the loue of vertue, and
to conceyue the felicitie therof: lyke as he dothe
many tymes, by sycknes of body and aduersitie,
brynge man to helth and prosperitie, and by the
tyranny and wretchednes therof, he induceth mā
to perceyue the nature of good polycie, and of al
quietnes and tranquillitie restynge in the same.
Euen lyke as by blynde and folyshe superstition
he styreth ofte tymes man to folowe syncere and
trewe religyon. And thus all thyng, whiche ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth
in mās lyfe to be playn yll, &amp; viciouse, his
infinite goodnes turneth to good: and out of all
thing he pyketh som good.<note place="margin">Gen. 11.</note> For if there were any
thing which by nature were yl, than were not he
infinyte goodnes, the which without cōtradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
can suffre no ylle. Wherfore playnely to saye
euen as I thynke, these thynges whiche to the
worlde, and to the common iugement of manne
seme ylle and moste pestylent, of the goodnes of
god, and of his highe prouidence, minister vnto
men most sure argument. The whiche thyng I
haue here nowe touched to this purpose &amp; ende,
<pb facs="8"/>
that where as many men nowe adayes, conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng
the state of the Christen polycie vexed with
so moche sedition and heresie, feare moche to see
shortly therof great ruine and decaye, I wolde
haue them to alter that opinion: And to stande
fully in this perswasion, that this diuysion by
sectes and contrary opinion, reignynge amonge
christen nations, the goodnes of god shall turne
to his honour and glorie, and to the setting forth
of his true religion, the whiche longe and many
a day hath ben by simple superstition moche ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scured
and hydde: ye and though it were so that
in folyshely fleinge this superstition, we shuld a
whyle slyppe into the contrary, that is to say, the
contempte of religion, yet I doubte not but the
goodnes of god in tyme conuenient, wolde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
vs at the laste to the meane, and bring vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
lyght the knowlege of his true religion, as he
hath done in al tymes from the beginning of the
world vnto this day, by lyttel and lytell euer dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng
mans wekenes to the true waye. And this
maner with vs I dout not but that his goodnes
wyll vse nowe in these dayes, and so inspire and
gyue lyght to the hartis of his christē flock, that
they all with concorde and vnitie shal to his wyl
be obedient moste mekely. This hope and truste
I haue fyxed in my harte, wherwith I moche
comforte my selfe. And though there be here in
our nation growynge in, a certayne diuision, by
corrupt iugement and false opynion, yet I trust
<pb n="4" facs="8"/>
we shall not so farre slyppe from gooddis proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
that it may take among vs any such rote,
whereby shall sprynge any sedition, or of good
and ciuile order any ruine or distruction: but cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
if we as membres of one body, runne all
togyther after one fashion, I trust at lēgth sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
it shall minister a great occasion, to the setting
forthe of Christis trewe religion. For the which
cause nowe, I haue conceyued this lyttel instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
exhortynge our people to vnitie and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,
the lacke wherof in the state of Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
hath bene a great cause of moche diuision,
and specially in the coūtrey of Germany, where
as by the folyshe auoydyng of superstition they
haue slipped into greatte discorde and sedition,
whose example I trust shall be to vs a spectacle,
ministringe vnto vs no small instruction, speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
if we consyder groundly the cause and fū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
of all their controuersie and sedition, the
whiche doutles, rose of thinges in no poynt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary
to mās saluation, but about ceremonies
and traditions, to the which many men blynded
by superstition, leaned none other wyse, thanne
to Christis worde and gospel, they dydde not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scerne
with ryght iugement, betwixt thinges of
themself good &amp; necessary, &amp; other, which ar only
for the time conuenient to a certayne policie, but
all thinges of longe tyme receyued, by custome,
&amp; generall decree, some of them toke as goodis
lawe indifferently, &amp; som all turned vp so downe
<pb facs="9"/>
vndiscretely. Wherfore suche persons as by the
examination of them to goddis worde, founde
therin moche abusion, fyrste the reste coude not
well beare, but noted them of herisie, and as mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers
of sedition: by the reson wherof, sprange y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
great diuision, wherby the coūtrey was deuided
into many &amp; dyuers sectes, but now by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence
of god eche one spyeng the foly of other,
they begynne to fall vnto the meane, that is to
say to Christis true religion, gyuinge to goddis
worde the full authoritie, that preachinge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
abrogation. And as for ceremonies and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,
they suffre as thynges conueniente to
maynteyne vnitie, where as they repugne no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to goddis worde, nor to good ciuilitie: the
which thyng if they had done at the begynning,
they shulde not by their blyndnes haue fallen to
suche confusion, nor by their folyshe correction
of the abuses of the churche haue brought in su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
a diuision. Howe be it I doubt not, but that
the prouidence of god hath suffered this thinge
for the institution of other, for we may as I ofte
reherse, take example of that foly, and runne to
gyther in one course with obedience and vnitie,
the whiche if we do, we shall doubtles shortly se
the prouidence of god, so worke, that out of our
church &amp; congregation, we shal se plucked vp al
superstitious abusions: as contrary, if we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede
in our corrupt iugement and lately growen
in diuision, we shall without fayle slippe to like
<pb n="5" facs="9"/>
confusion. For the auoydynge wherof, I haue
directed to the people this rude instruction, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge
them to obedience and vnitie, whose na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
nowe sommewhat to touche, remayneth in
the seconde place.</p>
   <p>¶Wherin brefely to say, this you shall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande,
that obedience in all tymes,<note place="margin">The nature of obediēce.</note> and with all
nations hath euer ben reputed, the chiefe bonde
and knotte of all vertue and good ciuilitie, and
not onely amonge vs, whiche be of the chrysten
flocke, lighted with the spirite of god, but also a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge
the gentyl philosophers, ladde onely by
the course and power of nature, with whome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience
was euer noted to be as the mother of
al vertue and honestie. For whan the affectes in
mans mynd sensuall drawinge hym to pleasure
and vanitie, be so obediēt to reson, that betwixt
them is no repugnancye nor rebellion, but reson
euer hath dominion, leadynge man to his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralle
dignitie, than is he sette in hyghe felicitie,
than lyueth he in perfyte quietnes and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,
as farre as man may optayne in this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
lyfe full of frailtie. Lyke as contrary, whan
reason beinge ouer runne, affection dothe reule
by disobedience, then man, as he were fallynge
downe out of goddis order and prouidence, who
appoynteth reason to his gouernance, slyppeth
into infinite misery and wretchydnes, and neuer
enioyeth tranquillitie and quietnes, but dyuers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
torne by dyuers desires,<note place="margin">Roman. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> lacketh all comforte
<pb facs="10"/>
and swetenes of this lyfe. So that by this, hit
is euidente and playne, what power obedience
hadde with the gentylitie: but of vs, whiche be
lyghted with Christis doctrine obedience of an
nother sorte is required. For our obedyence is
not reuled by suche a sklender reule, as man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
reasone is, whiche is for the mooste parte
soo blynded with corruption, that seldome it se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
the clere truthe withoute affection: but the
lyne of our obedience is reasone it selfe, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
worde and sonne of God by Christe to vs<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oman. 1.</note>
declared, the wylle of god in his scriptures ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.
By this lyne and rule we must square our
affection, to this al, reason and affection of man
set apart, we muste be obedient, to this we must
gyue faythe, sure truste, and also confydence.
To stable this obedience Christ was made man,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>b. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note>
the whiche bothe by doctrine and dede he moste
playnely toughte, the whiche to confyrme with
many wordes, here is no place, speciallye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syderynge
that all holy scripture is fulle of the
same, as it is to all men open and playn. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
here perauenture you wyl say, that obediēce
to goddis word is required: no man douteth, no
man is ignoraunt therof, but whiche is goddis
worde, and the trewe sense therof, vnto the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
we ougthe for to be obediente, here lyeth the
double, this is not vnto all menne playne: for
somme menne herein saye one thynge, and some
saye an nother, in so moche, that we knowe not
<pb n="6" facs="10"/>
to whiche sense &amp; to what thyng we shulde gyue
our obedience, and whether we shulde rather be
obediente to generall counsaylle, or to our prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis
authoritie. This perauenture you wyll say.
For the answere wherof, thoughe in the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
folowynge, I haue at large handeled the
thinge, as the chiefe mattier thereof, yet here in
this place somewhat I wyll touche, bothe howe
you shall comme vnto the trewe sense of goddis
worde, and also what obedience you oughte for
to gyue bothe to generall counsayle and princis
authoritie. And fyrste this you shal vnderstand,
as a sure grounde to the resolution hereof, that
suche thynges, to the whiche we owe our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
and are bounden vnto, other by goddis
worde, generall counsaylle, or princis authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
be of .iii. sortes, and of .iii. dyuers kyndes,
for other they be of theyr owne nature, good
and profytable: or contrarye, by nature ylle and
dampnable, or elles indifferente, whyche of
theym selfe be nother good nor ylle. As by an
exaumple, suche thynges are good,<note place="margin">Thynges good of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> selfe.</note> not as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth
to mannes corrupte reason, but suche
as be by goddis owne worde defyned, by the
whiche rule only we muste examyne what thing
is good with ryghte iudgemente: as to truste
in god and in his onely goodnesse, to loue hym
aboue all thynges, and thy brother as thy selfe,
these with such other, expressed by goddis word,
<pb facs="11"/>
are by nature good, and Profytable. As con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hinge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> yf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>f them self.</note>
suche thinges as by the same worde are
prohibyte and forbydde, are by nature ylle and
damnable, as to distrust the mercye of god, and
doubte of his goodnes, to haue thy brother in
hate, or wrongfully to couete worldly riches.
Thynges indifferent I calle all suche thynges,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>hinge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of them selfe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>fferent.</note>
whiche by goddis worde are nother pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>bthyted
nor commaunded, but lefte to worldly polycie,
wherof they take their ful authoritie, by the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che
as tyme and place requireth, they are some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes
good, and somtymes yll: As to eate fleshe
the fridaye, &amp; after the customed maner to kepe
the holy day, to go a pylgremage, and pray vnto
saynctis, these and other lyke, I calle thynges
indifferent, and nothynge necessarie to mannes
saluation, though they may be well vsed and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
a good fashyon, as I shall hereafter more at
large open and declare. Amonge the which also
I nombre this great matter of the popes supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
whiche so troubleth many weake cōsci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.
For as I iuge it not so yll and damnable,
that all our forefathers, whiche haue ben obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
therto this .vii. C. yeres therfore be damned,
so I iuge it not so good, that obediēce therto shal
be necessarie to them whiche shulde be saued, as
I haue at large declared in the mater folowing,
and opened therin fully myn opinion. But nowe
to the purpose, this and all other lyke, whiche be
not in scripture expressed by commaundement,
<pb n="7" facs="11"/>
I note to be thynges indifferent, the nature of
whome is of this sorte, whiche is highly here to
be obserued, that thoughe of theym selfe, they
be nother good nor yll, nor to them we owe none
obedience, yet whan they be set out with autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
by them which haue hole rule in any kynd
of policie, whether it be in the state of a prince or
populare: than the people are to them bounde, ye
by the vertue of goddis owne worde, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth
expressely his disciples to be obedient
to commune policie, whan so euer therby is cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded
any thinge, whiche is not repugnant
to his preceptes and doctrine, ye and though hit
were contrarye to their owne priuate profytte,
plesure, and quietnes, ye or contrary to a world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
right wisenes: yet wolde he haue his disciples,<note place="margin">Iuce. 20.</note>
and the professours of his name euer to be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
with humilitie and mekenes, wherwith as
with a peculiar mark, he hath marked his flock.<note place="margin">Marc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. Iuce. 18.</note>
And so nowe this grounde presupposed, I shall
make answere to the doubtes before moued: and
fyrste to them that be vnlerned, to whom I haue
directed chiefly this instruction, this I wyl say,
that scrupulous and exact knowlege of thinges
conteyned in goddis scriptures, is nothinge so
necessary to iduce them to obediēce, as is meke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
and humilitie, whiche is among many other
thinges to them whiche be rude, the chiefe way,
wherby they maye attayne to the trewe sense of
goddis worde and doctrine. For the which cause
<pb facs="12"/>
as I thynke in the counsayle of Nece, the sūme
of our feythe, conteynynge suche poyntis as be
necessary to euery mannes saluation, was redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
vnto certayne artycles, and so propowned in
Symbalo,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> in the common Crede to all chrysten
nations, as a thynge sufficient to be had in hart
and mynde of all men, without ferther enserche
or inquisition, in the reste euer gyuynge obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
to the order and custome in euery countrey
receyued with concorde and vnitie. So that we
maye iudge, as hit appereth to me,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> that to the
vnlerned people and bodye of euerye commy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie,
withoute ferther knowledge, sufficiente
hit is, euery manne doynge his office and dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
as he is called, and by goddis prouysion
therto appoynted, here in this worldly polycie,
stedfastely to hange vppon the commune or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
leanyng therto constantely, euer comforted
with the same feythe and expectation of the euer
lastynge lyfe, hereafter to be hadde in immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,
&amp; not by our owne merites, but by the mere
benefytte and onely goodnesse of god,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> who to
vs soo trustynge in hym, hath made suche pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys
of his benignitie. This is the mooste sure
knotte, as I thynke, of all christen cyuilitie, this
generalle knowledge of thynges necessary ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
with mekenes, I thynke sufficiente to the
v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>lerned people: in all other thynges, whiche
be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="5 letters">
         <desc>•••••</desc>
      </gap>fferente, euer gyuynge obedyence to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n
authoritie, and gladdely herynge theym
<pb n="8" facs="12"/>
whyche are directed and appoynted for to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
Christis doctryne, wherby they may bothe
confyrme and increase dayely theyr faythe. And
where as somme of theym preache <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>one cleane
contrarye to annother, by the reasone whereof
somme of you maye be perauenture brought in
to somme doubte, this you shall vnderstande,
that theyr controuersies and contrarietie, for the
moste parte be, concernynge thinges indifferent,
and seldome of suche, whiche be necessarye to
mannes saluation. Wherefore their controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syes
therin oughte to trouble you nothinge atte
all. For menne, the whiche are of lernynge and
letters, in suche mattiers neuer dydde yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde
nor agree in vnitie, it is ynough that they
accorde in the artycles of our feythe: and as for
the reste, lette theym proue theyr wyttes after
theyr owne pleasure, mynde, and lybertie.
Wherfore their folye therin and controuersies
nedeth not to mynyster any occasyon of scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lositie
to the vnlerned people and rude, but euer
they takynge the generalle poyntes and arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
of Christis faythe, with mekenes and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mylitie,
muste in the reste gyue theyr obedience
vnto suche thynges, whiche be decreed &amp; made
in the common policie.</p>
   <p>¶But nowe I wyll speke somwhat of the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
that you shall gyue vnto the common au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorytie,
and also what to generall counsaylle,
<pb facs="13"/>
here brefely I wyll touche. And first this is sure,
that in all kynde of polycies among christen na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note place="margin">The order of obedience<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
the worde of god must be of chiefe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
that muste haue therin the firste place and
preeminēce. Wherfore if any thynge be decreed
contrary to that, by any worldly policie, it must
be vtterly abrogate and boldely disobeyed with
al constancy. For suche barbarous tyranny may
not be suffred in christen ciuilitie: But contrary,
what so euer is decreed in any policie, nothynge
repugnant to Christis doctrine, and to his sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie,
to that euer obedience is required, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
resteth a great grounde of christen ciuilitie, to
the whiche poynt, if any priuate person repugne
seditiousely, moued by any scrupule of consciēce
conceyued folishely, if he may nother be brought
to knowlege by good instruction, nor yet to iuste
obedience with dewe admonition, he is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
to lyue in that cōmen policie, nor to be a mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre
therof, as one that abhorreth frome all good
order and ciuilitie. For to the obedience of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis
and of all other commen orders and politike
we are bounde, after they be ones receyued, by
goddis owne worde and commaundement. And
suche thinges as by their own nature be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,
are made therby to our saluation necessary,
so that this remayneth a sure truth, that to al su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
thinges as be decreed by princely authoritie,
to goddis worde nothynge contrarye, we are by
goodis worde bound, after they be receyued and
<pb n="9" facs="13"/>
stablyshed: to the whiche we muste gladdely be
obedient with humilitie, ye though they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
to suche thynges, as be propowned by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
counsell and assemble.<note place="margin">The nature of generalle counsayse.</note> For the which this
is to be obserued, that though counsell generall
and vniuersall assemble of all chrysten nations,
be a thynge not necessary to the conseruation of
Christes fayth and doctrine, for as moche as it
was conserued in his most purytie almoste .v. C.
yere, withoute any suche congregation: yet for
bycause it was of wise men and politike brought
in, to the auoydyng of schisme and heresie, and
stablynge of christen vnitie, I thinke it not to be
reiected. For as it is gret superstition and playn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>foly,
to iudge it necessarie to mans saluation, ye
and a great token of infidelitie and of dystruste
in the goodnes of god, who hath promysed to al
men in al places, and at al tymes, eternal salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Matt. 7.</note>
when so euer &amp; where so euer with faythful
trust they cal for the same: so it is a tokē of great
arrogancye, and lacke of christen humilitie, hit
vtterly to refuse, whan so euer hit is taken as a
collation, and a conferrynge to gether of lerned
men for the inuention and trialle of the truthe,
concernynge suche thinges as pertayne to rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
as hit was at the fyrste institution, at the
whiche tyme the thinges driuen out by counsell
generall, were of none authoritie, vnto the time
that princis in euery nation dyd receyue and sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyshe
them in their countreys, by the consent of
<pb facs="14"/>
the same, as it is euidēt by diuers lawes imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,
by the which such thinges as were conceyued
in coūsel generall, were authorised &amp; confyrmed.
Wherfore to cōpare these authorities to gyther,
with boute of preemynēce of the same, it is small
reson. For as moch as such thīges as be propou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
by general coūsell &amp; assēble, be of none autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie
among the people in any coūtrey, tyl they be
confirmed by princely power and cōmon coūsell.
Wherfore this foloweth surely, that the same au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoritie
may suche thynges reiecte, whan tyme
place and other occasion, that doth require with
good reason: This therfore semeth to me a sure
conclusion, that rather we ought to gyue obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
to that thynge, whiche is decreed by comon
authoritie in euery nation, then to such as is pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>powned
by generall assemble &amp; vniuersall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell.
For suche thinges are but counsels in dede,
and bynde no man, tyll they be by common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent
receyued, the whiche euer by the same maye
be also dissolued, and specially touchynge suche
thynges that are indifferente, the whiche at the
fyrste counsels were euer omytted and left to the
order of worldly policie: but after that the see of
Rome toke this heed ouer al christen nations, by
lytle &amp; litel in general assēbles, they began to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine
&amp; hādle thinges {per}taining to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> worldly poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
for the mainteining of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pompe &amp; arrogancy,
the which they atteyned to by p̄tense of religion.
Wherfore the coūsels succeding the same heed,
<pb n="10" facs="14"/>
smellid therof, &amp; sauorid moch of worldly vanite,
but if they had cōtinued after y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> firste institution,
only medlyng with y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> interpretation of scripture
&amp; thinges {per}tayning by necessite to mās saluatiō,
I thinke to this day no christē prince nor nation
wold in any point haue made to thē any cōtrary
cōstitution: but nowe sith that popes in general
coūsels, cōtrary to the order of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> same, haue med
led with maters {per}taining to worldly policy, mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uayl
it is not to se, princis decre cōtrary, to whose
order touchinge thinges indifferēt, the people in
euery natiō, are more boūde, thā to such thinges
which ar but only {pro}pouned as coūselsi general
coūsels, &amp; vniuersal cōgregation, as shal appere
more largely herafter: &amp; this cōcerning obediēce
here in this preface to be obserued, to thē y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> be vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lerned
I think sufficiēt, &amp; as for thē y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> ar lerned,
they knowe how to answer to this matter better
thā do I. How be it I wold coūsel euery man ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned
in scripture, whose cōsciēce is troubled with
any scruplosite cōceiued by any thing decreed by
cōmen authorite, here in our coūtrey, wel to wey
the thing, wherwith he is troubled, with diligēt
exaīation therof, whether it be vpon a groūd ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary
to mās saluation, or els vpon a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differēt:
&amp; aboue al to be ware, &amp; diligētly to take
hede, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> nother by authorite of mā, {pro}cesse of time,
nor cōtrary custom, he suffre not him self so to be
blinded, nor deceiued by siplicite, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> he with right
iugemēt cā not pōder goddis word indifferētly:
<pb facs="15"/>
and where as he fyndeth cōtrouersie or gret dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie,
to trye out the true sense of goddis word
and doctrine, in his scripture tought: lette hym
with a meke harte come to hym, of whom com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
all heuenly lyght,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 11.</note> who hathe promysed to
all men neuer them to fayle, whiche mekely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande
of hym the knowledge of truthe with ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
affecte inserchynge the same: for mekenes
is the only way and the strayt gate of the entree
to Christis misteries. For except we base our sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makes
full of arrogancie, we can not conceyue
the swetenes of that heuenly simplicitie, wherof
make hartes onely and humble are part takers.
For as to pride &amp; arrogancy Christ euer resistith,
so to lowlynes and humilitie, his grace euer he
communeth,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>. 11.</note> that he exalteth and setteth in high
dignitie, euen as pride, he euer depresseth and
putteth vnder foote. Soo that by this gate we
must entre, whiche fewe men fynde, yf we wyll
folowe hym, and to the mysteries of his doctrine
take the true way: for excepte we be as chyldren
lowely and meke,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note> without all corrupt affection,
there shall to vs be no gate open, to brynge vs to
his kyngdome and heuenly perfection. This is
the trewe trace, wherin he muste treade, who so
euer fruitefully wyl seke the true sense of goddis
worde, the whiche who so entreth, doutlesse shall
fynde, to suche scrupule of conscience a synguler
remedy, without ferther expectation of general
counsel and decree: &amp; neuer shal fere to giue obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="11" facs="15"/>
to suche thynges as be decreed by cōmon
authoritie, specially seing they touche only thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
indifferent, nothyng necessary to our salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō:
as I thinke it shalbe euidēt vnto al thē, who
wyl throughly rede and indifferently weye suche
thynges, as I haue gathered in this lyttell In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction:
and than I shal not dout, but that we
shall runne all togyther in one course in christen
vnitie,<note place="margin">Christen vnitie.</note> whiche shortly to touche standeth in this
poynte chiefely. We must conceyue if we wyl be
true professours of Christs doctrine, a certayne
brotherly loue eche one towarde other, iugynge
our selfes to be borne of one father,<note place="margin">Iohan. 13. Galatas. 3.</note> nouryshed of
one mother, membres of one body, hangynge of
one heed, lokynge for one reward, promysed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
vs, lyuyng to gyther in this vnitie. We must
thinke that our mayster Christe discended down
from the bosome of his father, to stablyshe this
concorde and vnitie, in the hartis of all theym,<note place="margin">Iohan. 17.</note>
which purpose to be inheritours with him in his
kyngedome of heuen euerlastyngely. We muste
thynke, that by this onely is the way to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talytie,
the whiche if we doo, I doubte not, but
that all suche diuision as hangeth ouer our hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,
whiche myght bringe in confusion into this
our countrey &amp; polycie, we shal ryght wel auoyd
and eschewe, lyuinge together in due obedience
and perfyt vnitie. For the which I shal not cesse
to pray vnto hym, who hath promysed surely to
gyue the lyght of truthe to all them, whiche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande
<pb facs="16"/>
it mekely. And the same I shall require
of you all, to whom it shall chaunce to rede this
instructiō, and of this to make a sure cōclusion,
that if we with mekenes and humilitie, faythful
loue and charitie, seke out the true sense of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis
worde diligently,<note place="margin">Matt▪ 21.</note> we shal surely it fynde, and
suche lyght therof receiue, that though we neuer
here of pope nor cardynall, nor yet of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell
generall, yet shall not we be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute
of suche truthe and lyght
as is necessary to our salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
But here I wylle
make an ende, and
trouble you with
no longer
preface,
remyttynge you to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction,
for ferther
declaration.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>