<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the knowing Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104636_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16657</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3563</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104636</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the knowing Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The English gentleman : containing sundry excellent rules or exquisite observations, tending to direction of every gentleman, of selecter ranke and qualitie; how to demeane or accommodate himselfe in the manage of publike or private affaires. By Richard Brathwait Esq</title>
                 <author>Brathwait, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Bostock, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 456, 10, 459-487, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the knowing Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E</hi> that provides not for his <hi>Family</hi> is worse than an <hi>Infidell:</hi> yet he who prefers the care of his family, before the advācement of Gods glory, may seeme to be of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Bourbons</hi> minde, who would not lose his part in <hi>Paris,</hi> for his part in <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise,</hi> Each mans private <hi>Oeconomie</hi> ought to be a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Academie,</hi> wherein all sacred and morall knowledge is to be taught. For that master of a family, who only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends his care in providing how to get, making the <hi>Object</hi> of his providence <hi>gaine,</hi> will experimentally crie out, when his <hi>mouth shall be filled with gravell: O Death, how bitter is the remembrance of thee to that man, whose peace is in his substance!</hi> To prevent which immoderate care, and that every one may cloze with <hi>Cicero: Virtute qui praediti sunt, soli sunt divites,</hi> I have proposed some especiall <hi>rules</hi> of <hi>direction,</hi> right worthy (if my judgement doe not deceive mee) the observation of every publike or private family: though principally tending to the making up of an <hi>Accomplish'd Gentleman.</hi> For who knowes not, (if he know any thing) how the <hi>Gentry</hi> of this age, through a depraved effeminacie, must be in custome with the fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to purchase him the title of <hi>Gentleman?</hi> Where he is to enter cōmerce with Taylor, Haberdasher, Millener, Semp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, and sundry other appertinences of a <hi>Gentleman:</hi> which in time, worke <hi>Gentility</hi> out of love with <hi>Hospita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> engaging him so deeply to vanity, as by a strange <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tastrophe,</hi> he ever ends with misery. To rectifie these obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, I have brought a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> who professeth the true and new Art of <hi>Gentilizing:</hi> yet not like your begging pedanticall <hi>Artist,</hi> who by a mercenary <hi>Bill</hi> pasted on some
<pb facs="5"/>
frequented gate, gives notice to the itching Passenger, that if any one be minded to learne the rare and mysterious Art of <hi>Brachygraphie, Stenographie, Logarisme,</hi> or any Art (indeed) whatsoever, (though he be a meere stranger to any) upon resort to such a Signe in such a Lane, he shall find a most illiterate <hi>Anacharsis,</hi> ready to bray his braines in a <hi>Morter</hi> to give him content. But this <hi>Gentleman,</hi> as the <hi>Science</hi> which he professeth is free, so doth he teach it free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: craving no other reward for his fruitfull Observance, than thy friendly acceptance.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Vpon the <hi>Volume</hi> and <hi>Title.</hi>
      </head>
      <p>I Had purposed that this Worke should have beene digested in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>portible Volume,</hi> to the end it might be more familiar with a <hi>Gentlemans</hi> pocket, not to picke it, but that he might pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some good f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>om it: But since the <hi>Volume</hi> would not beare it, you must with patience beare with it, and with more trouble beare it: by enlarging your pocket to containe it.</p>
      <p>Now for the <hi>Title,</hi> I am not wholly ignorant, how a Subject inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled <hi>The Complete Gentleman,</hi> was heretofore published; which (I can assure you <hi>Gentlemen</hi>) consorts with this rather in <hi>Title</hi> than <hi>Tenour, Name</hi> than <hi>Nature</hi>; the proofe whereof I referre to the generous and judicious Reader.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>The Subjects whereof this Booke principally trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and insisteth.</head>
      <list>
         <item>Youth.</item>
         <item>Disposition.</item>
         <item>Education.</item>
         <item>Vocation.</item>
         <item>Recreation.</item>
         <item>Acquaintance.</item>
         <item>Moderation.</item>
         <item>Perfection.</item>
      </list>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>