<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶A Chapter to the Reader, towchynge the order obserued in this booke: verye necessarye to be read and well conside∣red before he enter anye further.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104611_Fr3_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16229</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3152</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104611</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶A Chapter to the Reader, towchynge the order obserued in this booke: verye necessarye to be read and well conside∣red before he enter anye further.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fower chiefyst offices belongyng to horsemanshippe : that is to saye. The office of the breeder, of the rider, of the keper, and of the ferrer. In the firste parte wherof is declared the order of breding of horses. In the seconde howe to breake them, and to make theym horses of seruyce, conteyninge the whole arte of ridynge lately set forth, and nowe newly corrected and amended of manye faultes escaped in the fyrste printynge, as well touchyng the bittes as other wyse. Thirdely howe to dyet them, aswell when they reste as when they trauell by the way. Fourthly to what diseases they be subiecte, together with the causes of such diseases, the sygnes howe to knowe them, and finally howe to cure the same. Whyche bookes are not onely paynfully collected out of a nomber of aucthours, but also orderly dysposed and applyed to the vse of thys oure cou [n] trey. By Tho. Blundeuill of Newton Flotman in Norff</title>
                 <author>Blundeville, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 <publisher>Seres, William 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 33, 9, 79, 26, 4, 32, 4, 120, 120-123, 14 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <head>¶A Chapter to the Reader, towchynge the order obserued in this booke: verye necessarye to be read and well conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before he enter anye further.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ndeuoring my selfe gentle reader for your better vnderstandinge to reduce Grysons boke, whiche in the Italion tounge dothe treate of the arte of rydynge, and of breakynge greate Horses, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a more briefe and compendious waye of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge, then hee to my Iudgemente hathe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in obserued: I soughte firste to what ende suche laboure was chiefly to be employed vpon great horses. And I founde that eyther it was to make them horses of seruice, or els horses of pleasure, called Stirers. Then I cōsidered what things were incident to an horse of seruice, and what to a horse of pleasure or Stirer. And of those thinges which were common to them both, and which were appertayning to eche one perticulerly. And firste I founde that to a horse of seruice belonged these chiefe poyntes here folowinge. That is to say, to trot cleane &amp;
<pb facs="39"/>
lustely, to stop lightly, to turne on both handes redely, to gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loppe stronglye, to maneg with single turne surelye, and laste of all to passe a carire swiftly. And in all his doinges from the beginning to the ending, to reane well, and to beare his head steddely. Al which things are also cōmon to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> stirrer, but then it is requisite that the stirrer besides all this, learne to bounde alofte with all foure, &amp; to yarke withall, to gallop the gallop galliarde, to fetch the Capriole, to doe the Coruetti, and such like kind of saltes. But yet this sufficeth not, vnles I mighte also know the nighest meanes for a horse to attayne to these feates, &amp; what order was therin to be obserued, which whilest I sought, behold the riders office wholy discouered, wherby I mighte well perceiue that vnles the rider were first instructed in all those thinges that appertayned vnto his office: the horse coulde neuer be well broken. Wherefore minding to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende all thinges in iii. bokes, I thought it most mete to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the ryder in teaching him first howe to know a good horse, and apt to be taught, aswell by hys coulour &amp; markes, as shape, to thintent he bestowe not his laboure vpon a Iade, or Roile. Then howe to tame him, and to make him so gentle as he may suffer to be ridden. After that, how to sit him and to behaue him selfe in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> poynt like a horseman. Then I proceded further, declaring the iii. chiefe pointes, wherin the perfection of a horseman consisteth. That is to say, in knowing how to helpe, to correct, and to cherishe his horse, and with what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strumentes, and generally how and when to vse them, and so I ende the first boke. That done I come to the horses lessons, which he hath to learne for his parte, declaring what order is to be kepte therin: to which soeuer of those ii. endes beforesaid. he be broken. And to euery lesson I ioyne such helpes and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, as are mete to be vsed for redresse of such faultes, as most cōmonly chaunce therin: whych faultes for the most part I call errors making a distinction betwene errors and vices, attributing errors to the lacke of knowledge, and vices to na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, or euil custome. As these be vices, to be restif, to be ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mege, to lye downe in the water, to be skittishe, which for dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction sake I do otherwise cal general faultes, because they may chaūce in euery lesson. Of the most part, of which faults I do treat seuerally in the third boke, declaring therewith the
<pb facs="40"/>
corrections of the same. For otherwise I shoulbe be driuen to make many digressions, and to interrupte the tenoure of my talke which I loue not to do. And I say here of the most part, because ther be some vices so peculier &amp; so incident to certayne of the horses lessons, as I am forced to myngle the correctiō of the same, euen amongst the errors, as occasion requireth, and yet therby no order broken at all, as any man of iudgemente, I am sure will easely confesse. Then the horse being through<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly broken in all poyntes, mete for him to learne: be he horse of seruice or styrrer: I finallye teach you how to ryde him to the best shewe before a prince. And there endeth the second booke. In the third booke I treate onely of the corrections of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall vices aforesaid, and of the diuersity of bits, and to what purpose euery one serueth. The order of all which three boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes shall more playnely appeare vnto you, by the contentes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chapters hereafter folowing. And though Gryson semeth to vse the like order, that I do in the very beginnyng: yet he doth not continew the same, but immediately maketh so many dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions, and interlaceth so many and dyuers matters toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as were ynough to confounde the memory of a very dys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete reader. And yet Gryson not to be blamed, for not obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that order or Metheode in wrytynge, whiche perhaps he neuer had learned: But rather muche to be praysed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended of almen, for vttering in the best maner he could, that his assured knowledge which he had gotten with great labour and contynuall exercisyng him selfe in ryding, the space of xl. yeares and aboue. Of which knowledge what lacke we Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishmen haue had, &amp; specially haue at this present, is best sene at a mustre, when the Queenes Maiesty hath nede of hors and horsemen, where ofttimes you shall see some that sit on their horses like winde shaken reedes, handlinge their handes and legs like weauers. Or if the horseman be good; then the horse for hys parte shall be so broken, as when he is suffred to go forwarde, he will go backewarde. And when hys ryder wolde haue him to turne on the right hand, he wil turne cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. And when he should stoppe, he will arme him selfe, and runne away, or els stoppe sooner then his ryder woulde haue hym or vse such lyke toyes. For redresse of which faultes, both in man and beast, this booke is chiefly set forthe, with the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.
<pb facs="40"/>
wherof, if you that lack knoweledge shall vouchsafe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainte your selues, not onely by reading, but also by exercise of rydynge, I doubt not but by your spedye profityng therein, you shall haue iust occasion to be thankefull, both to Gryson for the first inuention of the matter, and also to me for dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing and reducing the same into a playne forme and order of teaching. And you shal haue very good cause also to be thank<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful vnto my deare frende M. Iohn Asheley M. of the Queenes Maiesties Iewel house. For by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dayly practising of the rules of Gryson his booke, I sawe him without the helpe of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther teacher, bryng two of hys horses, and specially that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he calleth his Balle, vnto such perfection, as I beleue few gentlemen in this realme haue the lyke. Which euident profe together with his encouraging me vnto it, made me the more willing to take the matter in hande. In hope that other men woulde with lyke diligence vse the lyke exercise, wishinge all gentelmen lackyng hys qualityes, to be his lyke indede. And that not onely in this exercise, but also in many other his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous exercyses, as well of mynd as of bodye. To thintent they may deserue as he doth the loue, fauour, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendacion of all men, whereof I haue no doubte at all, because I my selfe do knowe a number of yonge gentlemen that be geuen in these oure dayes, to suche cyuill, and commendable exercyses, (as God geuinge theim grace to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue therin,) in tyme to come they will be no small ornament vnto this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme. Whiche I pray God to graunte, and there I end bidding you well to fare.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>