<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104854_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69037</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4271</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104854</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Epistle to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The forrest of fancy : Wherein is conteined very prety apothegmes, and pleasaunt histories, both in meeter and prose, songes, sonets, epigrams and epistles, of diuerse matter and in diuerse manner. VVith sundry other deuises, no lesse pithye then pleasaunt and profytable</title>
                 <author>H. C.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purfoot, Thomas 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>160 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O variable are the minds of men (gentle Reader) and so diuerse their opinions, that amongste twenty, it is hard to fynd twaine that agree all in one thing. For commonly that which one man lyketh, another loatheth, that which one man praiseth, another reproueth, that which one desy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, another disdayneth, and whatsoeuer pleaseth one, doth as much displease another. The yong man taketh pleasure in all youthfull excersises, as Daunsing, Synging, playing on instruments, dallying with daynty dames, and such like, whereby his pleasure may be procured, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased, without respecting any perrill that maye insue thereof. The aunciente Syre, whome experience hath taught to be more wise and wary of such vaine vanities, hath an eye to his profit, and reiecteth pleasure as a thing vnprofytable. The couragious Captayne accompteth it for his greatest glory to be in the field, marching among his men of warre, or skirmishing with his enemies, to trie his strength and courage, with the hazarde of his life, for the furtheraunce of his fame, and increase of his commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity. The man likewise that is inclyned to learning, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes best at ease when he is setled in his study, there to tosse and turne his bokes, perusing the workes of aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent wrighters, whereby he may in tyme be able both to profite his countrey, and purchase such prayse to himself as is due to his good desyres. But as these great clarkes doe not all delight to study one onely science, but some apply themselues to deuinity, some to Philosophie, some to phisicke, some to Astronomy, and some to euery one of them alike, not making any speciall choyse of eyther of
<pb facs="5"/>
them. So likewise the common sorte whose learning nor capacity cannot attaine to the full perfection or perfecte vnderstanding of such deepe misteries, haue their seueral delightes, as well in reading such workes, as are in theire vulgare tongue, as in any thing else. For one will peruse pleasant Histories, and other poeticall deuises, this man merry tales, and other like toyes: that man deuine and morrall matter, euery one seuerally, according to his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall affection, and naturall inclination, and there is no man be he neuer so well stayed, that will adict himselfe to one thing onely, and refuse all other. For as the stomacke is quickly cloyed with feeding continuallye vppon one kinde of meate, so is the mind greatly greeued, to bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes musing vppon one matter, and therefore desyreth chaunge.</p>
   <p>Which considered, after I had gathered togither in one small volume diuerse deuises, as well in prose as meeter, of sundry sortes, and seuerall matter, which at idle times (as wel to sharpen my wits, and shake of sloth, as to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye my friendes, that had occasion to craue my helpe in that behalfe) I haue heretofore as occasion serued, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersly framed, supposing the same to be fitte for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent time, and agreable with the mindes of moste men, I haue (as well for the disordered placing of euery perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler parcel thereof, being rudely and dispersedly deuided, as also for the seuerall fancies therin contained, fit for eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry degree, &amp; agreable to their diuerse affections) thought good to name it <hi>The Forrest of Fancy,</hi> and so causing it to be imprinted, I doe here friendly Reader, present it vnto thee as a gift, of my good will, desiring thee to accept it. And though my yong yeares and small experience, will not permit me to wryghte so pithily as some haue done heretofore, whose worthy works are extant, and in great estimation, yet considering that I haue not done it either for gaine or glory, but partly to make my selfe more apte in other matters of more importaunce wherein <hi>I</hi> maye
<pb facs="5"/>
happen hereafter to be imployed, and partly to procure thy pleasure and profite (which may easilye be obtained) if thou doe duely consider, and rightly conceiue of that which shall be offered to thy view, I beseech thee conster my doinges to the best, take this my small labour in good parte, amend the faultes escaped. Let my good meaning serue to excuse my rashnes, in presuming thus boldly to publish a thing of so small valew, and vouchsafe me thy friendly assistaunce against the slaundrous reportes of enuious <hi>Zoylus</hi> and his mallicious mates, and in so doing, thou shalt incourage me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to search my wits, and apply my trauaile to contriue some thing more worthy thy reading.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>