<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the freendly Reader.</title>
           <author>Hichcock, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104130_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03408</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13531</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104130</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the freendly Reader.</title>
                 <author>Hichcock, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A pollitique platt for the honour of the Prince, the greate profite of the publique state, relief of the poore, preseruation of the riche, reformation of roges and idle persones, and the wealthe of thousandes that knowes not howe to liue. Written for an Newyeres gift to Englande, and the inhabitantes thereof: by Robert Hitchcok late of Cauersfeelde in the countie of Buckyngham Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Hitchcock, Robert, captain</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, 3 folded leaves of plates, maps, table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the freendly <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR asmutche as the</hi> Almightie God hath blessed and enriched this noble king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, with the sweete dewe of his heauely goodnesse, and stored therein many rich hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and pleasaunte treasures for our benefites, to reueale vnto vs whē his good pleasure is. I thinke therefore, euery man is rather borne to profite his natiue soile and common weale, in reuealyng the same secretes, and hidden treasure to his countrey, (if thei be shewed hym) then to seke after his owne priuate gaine, and glorie thereby. So I haue taken vppon me good gentle Reader, to vnfolde some of the same hidden treasures to my Countrey, whiche I suppose is manifested vnto me: Albeeit there be a great nomber, that can more sweetly and with pleasanter wordes and sugred stile (then I) set out the matter to thee (if thei knewe it) in farre better Methode and order. Yet the zeale and duetie I
<pb facs="6"/>
beare to my countrey, beyng partly fed with hope of thy good paciece (gentill reader) &amp; partly enbol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with the fore warnyng that <hi>Eccle. ca. II.</hi> giueth, which is, <hi>That no man shalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempned before his tale be tolde, and inquitision thereof made:</hi> whereby righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Iudgemente maie thereof followe, Least he (as Salomon saieth) <hi>Procure to hym selfe follie and shame, in giuyng sentence of a matter before he heare it.</hi> These thin ges I saie haus moued me, to putte forthe my sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple mynde in writyng to my Countrey, and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng thee of thy good courtesie to peruse it, and throughly waie the depthes thereof, in the ballance of thy graue Iudgemente. And if thou finde the pithe and carnell of my labor, frutefull to thee and thy Countrey (as I doubte nothyng thereof but thou shalte) then maie it bee, that it hath pleased God to powre out his knowledge as well vppon a Soldiour, as vppon a greate Clarke, for now and then wisedome maie bee shrouded vnder an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane Cloke. And I doubte not also, but the same reasons and duetie that bounde me this many ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,
<pb facs="6"/>
to trauell in this action, to my greate coste and charge, to finde out the waie and perfection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, shall also binde thee, and moue thee effectually, to fauour it, to further it in the Parliament house, and to defende my imperfection, against a sorte of Momus fecte, and Zoilus bande, that can rather finde fault with the man, then with the matter, be it neuer so well, or any waie putte to their helpyng handes to amende the same (if it bee not orderly.) My care hath been to please my Countrey▪ and the honest and graue sorte thereof: whiche if this my trauell shall doe &amp; content, I haue cause to thanke almightie God for it, and thinke my tyme well spēt For in this little booke (gentill Reader) thou shalt finde (if the same be executed accordyng to lawe) it importeth mutche matter, bryngeth greate plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and mutche wealthe, and benefite, to all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes of this Realme. It prouideth for the poore, in honest and decent maner, brynging them to a good and a Godly vocation of life: with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other speciall benefites, to this Kyngdome and common wealth, whiche for tediousnesse sake, least I wearie thee, I referre thee to the booke it self, where thou maiest at large see them, with thy eye,
<pb facs="7"/>
Iudge them by thy good discretion, wisedome, and fauour, and further them by thy good helpe and assistaunce at conuenient tyme. So fare thee hartly well.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Robert Hitchcocke.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>