<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Encomium]</title>
           <author>I., L.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104924_Fr1_8</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18097</idno>
           <idno type="STC">4738</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104924</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Encomium]</title>
                 <author>I., L.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Galateo of Maister Iohn Della Casa, Archebishop of Beneuenta. Or rather, A treatise of the ma [n] ners and behauiours, it behoueth a man to vse and eschewe, in his familiar conuersation : A worke very necessary &amp; profitable for all gentlemen, or other. First written in the Italian tongue, and now done into English by Robert Peterson, of Lincolnes Inne Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Della Casa, Giovanni</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 <publisher>Middleton, Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 122 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <lg>
      <l>THe vine is praisde, that daintie grape doth giue</l>
      <l>Although the fruite more please then holsome be.</l>
      <l>Each fertil tree is fauord for the fruite,</l>
      <l>So is the hearb that gallant is to see.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If this be trueth, he needes must merit well,</l>
      <l>That giues vs groundes to guide our erring wayes,</l>
      <l>And trades vs truely in the golden maze,</l>
      <l>Where vertu growes and courtlike manners stayes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Galateo</hi> first did frame this golden booke</l>
      <l>In Ital land. From thence it went to Spaine.</l>
      <l>And after came into the coasts of Fraunce.</l>
      <l>And nowe at last in England doth remaine.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The Authour sure deserueth more renoume,</l>
      <l>That so could spend his time for our behoofe,</l>
      <l>Then my poore wit or cunning can recite,</l>
      <l>As thou thy selfe by reading shalt finde proofe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And as the Authour merits passing well,</l>
      <l>So doth my friend deserue as greate a meede:</l>
      <l>That make a worke so hard to vnderstand,</l>
      <l>So easie that each simple may it reede.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I say no more: for (lo) it were in vaine</l>
      <l>To praise good wine by hanging vp a bushe,</l>
      <l>The best will giue (I hope) my friende his due,</l>
      <l>As for the bad, I way them not a rushe.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Browne
of L. I. Gent.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>