<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the worshipfull and his moste approoued freend, Maister Henry Campyon: W. A. vvisheth health and wealth of body, quietnesse and contentation of minde, in this life fulnesse of felicitie, and in the life eternall true tranquillitie.</title>
           <author>Averell, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104464_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23370</idno>
           <idno type="STC">980</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104464</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the worshipfull and his moste approoued freend, Maister Henry Campyon: W. A. vvisheth health and wealth of body, quietnesse and contentation of minde, in this life fulnesse of felicitie, and in the life eternall true tranquillitie.</title>
                 <author>Averell, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An excellent historie bothe pithy and pleasant, discoursing on the life and death of Charles and Iulia, two Brittish, or rather Welshe louers : No lesse delightfull for varietie, then tragicall in their miserie, not hurtfull to youthe, nor vnprofitable to age, but commodious to bothe. By W.A</title>
                 <author>Averell, W. (William)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>White, Edward 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the worshipfull and his moste approoued freend, Maister <hi>Henry Campyon</hi>: W. A. vvisheth health and wealth of body, quietnesse and contentation of minde, in this life fulnesse of felicitie, and in the life eternall true tranquillitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing taken some paynes (Woorshipfull Syr) to reduce this Historie into sauorie verse, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Pen in hand to present you with the simple Dedication of the same, the grauity of your person, suddenly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred my rash attempt, with such a hot assault of misdoubte, that I was forced to make a hasty retire into the Castell of deeper consyderation, and hauing pondered with my self that the wise and painefull Bee, sucketh Honny sometimes out of the wastefull weede, I gathered your Worship to haue the like discresiō in reading, that the Bee hath in choosing, and therefore I thought it not amisse, imitating the Phisition, to mingle some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times poyson amidde the pure Treackle, thereby to driue out one Naile with another, so that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, my young braine do yeelde greene fruite, to the taste of your mellowed yeares: yet beeing vsed well, it may redound bothe to your pleasure and profit. Though the greene Apple
<pb facs="3"/>
being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, breedes crude and rotten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> well rosted, it hurteth not the stomack, your Worship hauing now passed the fierie heate of youthe, may in the happy state, of your luckie age, syt and smile at the vaine baight of affectiōs, which ouer ruleth the sway of youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mindes, and sighe at the synnes which you were subiect to, in the vnstedfast state of that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constant age, which you shall aptly beholde in these two louers, by reading the contents of this my simple verse. Esteeme the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me I beseech you not as a requitall of your desarts (which are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;) but as a remembraunce of my good will (which is great) though my abillity be small, who being so deepely and diuersly indetted to your worship, thought euery day a yeere, till some fruite of thankfulnes did appeare to spring, from the groūd of my well willing minde. Thus committing you to the taste of these my simple Cates, which I wish as much to please your appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite in reading, as they did disease me in writing, I leaue you to the tuition of the almightie, who graunt to you and yours, more ioyes then I can wish, and yet my wishes more then I can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours in all freendely sort to commaunde.</hi> W. Auerell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>