<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Preface]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1546</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104350_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06511</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16984</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104350</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Preface]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The last wil and last confession of martyn luthers faith co [n] cerming [sic] the [principal articles of religion which are in controuersy, which he wil defend &amp; mai [n] teine vntil his death, agaynst the pope and the gates of hell drawe [n] furth by him at the request of the princes of germany which haue reformed theier [sic] churches after the gospel, to be offred vp at the next general councel in all their names &amp; now published before that all the world may haue an euydent testimony of his faith if it shal fortune him to dye before there be any such cou [n] cel, tra [n] slated out of latyn beware of the pope &amp; of his false prophetes and bissopes for thei wil come in shepys clothing and in angels facys but yet inwardly thei are ravening wolnys [sic] ]</title>
                 <author>Luther, Martin</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Straten, Derick van der (Theodoricus Plateanus)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Wesel</pubPlace>
                    <date>1546</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han Paul bisshop of ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me the third of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me did
proclame &amp; appo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynt a general councell to be holden at mantua in the yere.
1537. at the fest of pētecost which within a while after he wold ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue had
at some other pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and not at mantua / in so moch that it was vncetten
where he wold or might best appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te it / in the meane tyme we thought
surely ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be called vnto the councel to gether with other / or els to
be condemned there vncalled / wherfor this labor was required at that time of
me that shuld gather our whole doctrine in to certen specyal chapters and
principal arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles / that if the councel schuld goo forward in ernest / 
all men might haue a sure knoulege wherin and how farre we wold or colud gyue
place to the papistes / and againe in what sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tēce and mynd we haue
determyned fully with our selues to abyde and remaine constantly for euer.
And vp on this request I dyd gather the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se prīcipal articles. set forth
ī this boke / which I delyuered to the whole nomber of them that haue receiued
our doctrine. And thei all with one cōsent did receiue and approue them / in
so moch as it was determyned among them that <pb facs="3"/>if the pope with his
part shuld ones dare be so bold as to hold a right free / and lauful
councel without any false fraude disceite or dissimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / that than
these articles with the confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syon of our faith shuldbe offred vp vnto
them. But the court of rome abhorreth so sore from a fre councel / and
auoydeth from the light so shamefully / that it hath made euē them which
stond on theer syde / vtterly to despaire of any general assemble / 
not only that this court of ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me wil neuer call any free coūcel / but also
that it wil neuer be content to suffer gladly any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ūcel / to be had / with
the which thing euē thei thē selues are offended &amp; discontent / as
thei ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue a good cause / and are sore greued therwith / for as moch as
thei perceyue that the pope had rather all christen men to perissh and go
to the deuel / and that al theer sowles sschuld perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually be danned / 
than to suffer him selfe / his carnals / bisshopys and shauelings to
be refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med broght in to a right way or to oues cease his tyranny. But I not
with stōding thought it best to publyssh &amp; set fort these
principal arti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cles of our doctrine for this cause / that if it shu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> fortune death to peruent me before any
co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>sel shuld be gathered as I
both hope and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> / for as moch as
these wretches / abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> the
perfit lyght like owels / cōtendand
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> so besyly both night and
day to hynder ād <pb facs="3"/>prolōg al mauer of cōsellesyit the peple
my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glit haue deuer more in time to come my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessyon and the testymony
of my faith at hand to vse reade and loke vpon wherin as I haue continewed
vntyl this day so wil I stil remayne so long as I lyue by the grace of
god. for what shuld I say / or how shuld I complaime? I am yet alyue / I
wryte I teach / I reade &amp; preach dayly / and yet the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re be certen venemos
serpentes not only amōg our aduersarys but also among our false
coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terfet brethern which wil seme to hold withus which do vtter &amp;
betray them selues studying maliciosly &amp; falsely to wrest myne
own writīg myne own doctrine / against my self / euen befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re my face / I
my self loking vp on them &amp; also hearing them / and yet the
themselues knowe welinough that I teache the contrary. Thus li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke false
theues thei abuse the labors &amp; swet of my browes to the maintenans of
eher venom &amp; poison. What wil they doo (thīke yow) whā I am dead? It is
my part and duty therforto resist / withstand &amp; confound them whils I
ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue. But how can I alone stoppe all the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of the deuel? of them
specyally which (as they are all poisoned and infect) wil neither he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>are
nor considre or marke such things as we write / but applye theer mīdes an
study to this thing only. most shamefully to wrest / corrupt 
<pb facs="4"/>mistake / and peruert our wordes in euery ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne The deuel of hell
/ or at the least the wrath of god confute such wretches as thei are
wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. I do often tymes remember the saing of good gersō / which douteth
whether any good boke ought to be publisshed in writing or no? If nothing
shuld be writne thā are the soules of many one neglect and not regarded
which by such writings might haue moch help and remedy. And agayne on
contrary part whan any thing is written / than the deuel with an infinyte
nomber of most spiteful &amp; pestilēt tun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges is redy at hād / to
īfect / poison ād peruert all thīgs that no mā can receiue &amp; take any
pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fi therof. And yet not witstonding all the world seyth what thei wynne:
for after thei be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gan ones to forge lyes vp on us / and wēt abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ut to
withdrawe mēs hartes from us and to wīne them to thē selues with lyīg / 
god hath done and wrought his worke and wil effectu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>osly. and hath brought to
passe that many do daily swarue frō thē andi oncline to us ād thus by
their lyes thei haue procured thē selues {per}<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual shame and
dishonor / which thīg god do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th yet daily also. I must nedes shewe
&amp; vtter a certī story that cometh now to my mid There was at wittenberg
a certē do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tor sent hether frō
frāce which said opēly before our faces th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the king his master did surely bileue that there was no maner
of church or cōgregacion with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>us / no maner of rulars nor officers. And that there shuld be no
maner of matrimony but that euery mā shuld rūne at large now to one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mā
now to a nother euē aftir the maner of bru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te beastes / and agaime that it
shuld be lauful for euery priuate mā to vse or misuse / do or vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do
all maner of thīghs after his own wil &amp; iust &amp;c. Now tel me I pray
yow with what face shal these men dare loke vp on us at the latter day
before the iudgement seate of christ which haue tolder persuaded bi their
letters &amp; wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tīgs / this Fig &amp; other peple &amp; noble mē such
mō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stros &amp; abhominable lyes / for tru tales? Christ all our lorde / 
&amp; the most rightful iudge, is our witnesse that thei lye shamefully
vp on us and haue euer done: whose sentēce and iudgemēt cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demnīg them
to euerlastīg dānacion thei shal not chose but heare &amp; abide. This
am I sure of Now god turn &amp; cōuert thē to repētāce which cā by any
possible meanes be cōuerted / as for o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther euerlastīg and most cruel
ponischment &amp; dānaciō doth remaine for thē. But now to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to my
putpose agaī / I wold wissh surely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to see a true coūcel
wherby many cōtrouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sys might be takē a way ād many mē might re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue
profi: not that we our selues haue nede o any such coūcel or plamēt for
our churches are so lighned &amp; cōfirmed ī the pure word / of god ī rhe
true vse of sacramētes / ād in the knoulege of all good order &amp; all
good workes that for our <pb facs="5"/>cause we desire no maner of perlament
or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uncel / for we cannot think that any councel can teach vs a more perfight
order than we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue. But we see with depe sorow &amp; lamentaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our
hartes mani parisshes miserably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute / forsakē &amp;
vnregarded both of bisshops and of prebendarys: we see in theer
diocyses &amp; parisshes after what sort the sely miserable pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple
do lyue and dye for whose saluacion Christ him self suffred death vp
on the crosse: and yet thei cā not be suffred to heare nether him their
tru shepard &amp; pastor / nor yet none of his spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aking and preaching
vnto them for the which cause tremble &amp; feare vehemently lesse god
wil shortly call &amp; bring all the world to a councel by some angel / 
which shal vtterley destroy us all / as he did ones Sodom &amp; Gomor / for
as moch as we contemne &amp; mocke him so lightly thorow our councels. And
beside those thīgs which are necessary to be reformed in the
spiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tualty / (as thei cal it) there be an infinite nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of abuses in
the temporal regiment to be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dressed. for there is vncharitable grudgd
and dissensyon betwene princes and other nobles: and vsury &amp;
couetosnes haue so farre preua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yled &amp; hath so drowned the temporalty
euen ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke a flode or a see) that now in the place of the lawe are crept in / 
ryot / vnmesurable excesse / wantones / pryde in apparel / glotony
banker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting / <pb facs="5"/> dise / cardes and pompe / withal kindes of vices
&amp; mischefe / disobedience of subiectes and housoldes toward theer
heades / pestilent enhansing of all maner of marchandise in bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng &amp;
seiling / these I say / with an infinyte sort such life / haue so
preuailed that thei can not be reformed in X. councels nor in XX.
as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembles. These principal matters both of the temporalty &amp; of the
spiritualty / if thei shuld be entreated of in a general coūcel / thei
shuld ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke us to haue so moch labor and besines / that we shuld sone
forget &amp; litle regard the folissh triflyng about long gownes &amp;
brode shauyn crownes / fryres girdels / bisshops forked cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes / carnal
hattes / ād croser staues with such other trifyls. for it were time
inough to entre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate of the choise of meates / the differēce of gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meetes
short or lōg of the shauīg of crounes &amp; of cloisters / after that
the prīcipal articles of the faith with a godly politike ordre for the
co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monwelth were determined &amp; cōcluded by the word of god. But if we wil
swalow op Vho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le camels / and strayne gnaties / if we wil recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue &amp;
suffer gret beames in our eys &amp; pluck out the smal motys / if we wil
stomble at a strane &amp; leape at a block / we nede not be so gretly
ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riful for any councels. wherfor I haue made but a very fewe chapters &amp;
principal articles for els we haue so many cōmandmēts geuē vs <pb facs="6"/>of god to be obserued in his church / in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynalty / and in
euery particular house &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rissh / that we are neuer able to perform
them. wherfor what nede is it to make many actes decreys and tradicions
beside? specially if the principal articles and cōmandments enioined us bi
god himselfe be neglect and nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded / as though god must geue
place to our folissh trifles because we treade his special
cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandmenas / vnder our fete like swyne. But our sinnes do so sore
vexe oppresse &amp; lade us that thei wil not suffer god to haue mercy
vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on ue / because we do not repēt nor amend / but rather study and labor
to stablissh &amp; maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne all maner of wickednes. O merciful lord
Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>su christ / were saue then thy self to celebrate a councel &amp; to
redeme thi elect thorow thy own glorios presens for of the pope and of his
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents ther is no hope at all. thei wil in no wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>se receiue the. wherfor
help thou us pore mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable creatures / crieng &amp; calling vnto the / 
se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ernestly / for the abowndant mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cys safe that thou hast
geuen tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row thi holy spirite which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth &amp; reigneth with the &amp;
with the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to be prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed &amp; glorified for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>