<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
           <author>L., H.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104588_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06202</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16696</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104588</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader.</title>
                 <author>L., H.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ecclesiastes, othervvise called The preacher : Containing Salomons sermons or commentaries (as it may probably be collected) vpon the 49. Psalme of Dauid his father. Compendiously abridged, and also paraphrastically dilated in English poesie, according to the analogie of Scripture, and consent of the most approued writer thereof. Composed by H.L. Gentleman. Whereunto are annexed sundrie sonets of Christian passions heretofore printed, and now corrected and augmented, with other affectionate sonets of a feeling conscience of the same authors</title>
                 <author>Lok, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 117, 15, 79, 82-170, 36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
   <p>IT is the most fit subiect for the nobility of mans spirit to meditate of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie:
and a true saying of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> that <hi>Omnia appetunt bonum.</hi> Yea the
common practise of our high minded age, is to striue for the same in the
superlatiue degree. But so foolish and new-fangled are our desires, that
wishing we wot not what, and seeking it we know not how nor where: we
come all farre short of the same, and some runne headlong to the despised
contrary (looking for it on earth) and therby groping for it to their graues,
they are there cut off of their hopes, and die discontented with their haps.
Whereas if they acknowledged it to be the tree of life, planted in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
paradise, they wold lesse labor their bodies for attaining these transi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie
shadowes of pleasure, and more exercise the faculties of the soule for
atchiuing the same, so much the more despising these instable &amp; imperfect
happinesses of this life, as they found their foolish affections of the flesh
(doting on thē) to worke neglect of the nutriment of their soule: &amp; slacknes
in the constant trauell in religion and vertue (which is requisit for the long
iorney we haue to passe through life and death thereunto.) But this hauing
bin the sicknes of all ages, &amp; specially of the Iewes in <hi>Salomons</hi> time, (which
induced him, as it should appeare, to take so great paines in remouing thē
from that error,) I the lesse maruell, that our age florishing in the pride of
like long peace and plentie, vnder her Maiesties most happie raigne, be also
sotted with the world as they were, dreaming of that perfection and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity
here, which God by nature hath denied vnto vs, &amp; but by her Highnes
raigne we could hope for. And since it is the dutie of euery part and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of the body, to ioyne in the assistance &amp; cure of the whole, if any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
of it shold suffer: I haue in a dutiful compassiō of this cōmon calamity
endeuored to seeke forth some mithridate for this poyson: by which so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
perish, and haue here brought thee a Doses of the wisest Physitions cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position,
that euer had practise of that cure: who did not (for th' experimēt
of his potions qualitie, first kill many patients in triall thereof) but apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
it to his owne wound first, dares confidently write <hi>probatum est,</hi> and by
the seale of the holy spirit and consent of the Church, doth warrant thee to
tast of the same. It is a receipt so oldly composed perhaps, that thou respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctest
it the lesse, or of so small price, that thou shamest to take it, or perhaps
knowing the bitternesse of the tast, thou hadst as liue continue sicke, as to
trie it. But deceiue not thy selfe, it is of the nature of the perfectest drogs,
which with age increase in strength: of the kind of <hi>Sibillaes</hi> works, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused,
grow higher prized: and of the herbe called woodroofe. which onely
handled hath an euill smell, but more forcibly rubbed, yeeldeth a sweet sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.
Receiue it therefore as confidently as he assureth it, and as kindly as
I intend it: who in respect that the obscuritie of many places, the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie
(as at first would appeare) of some points, and strange dependancie
of the whole together: haue done my carefull &amp; studious iudeuor (by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration
&amp; imitation of the best interpreters hereof) to explane the true
<pb facs="5"/>
sense, accord the different places: to ioine by probable cōnexion the whole
discourse together: which aswel to distinguish the seuerall arguments, as to
varie the verse, and pawse the reader) I haue not altogether vnfitly distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
into three Sermons, each one containing foure Chapters a peece. The
first especially shewing the vaine opinion of felicitie, which is not in earth
to be found. The second pointing more directly (by the lawfull vse of this
life) the true way vnto her. The last, teaching her residence to be in heauen,
and perswading the speedie pursute of her fauor. And that you might truly
consider of the cariage of the matter, according to the scope of the Text, I
haue caused the same to be quoted in the margent, reducing for memorie
sake into two abstract lines of verse set in the top of euerie leafe: the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance
of euery pages content, which afterward as thou seest, is paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stically
dilated page by page, in the plainest forme I can deuise. Who in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
of the grauitie of the argument did restraine my pen frō the helpes of
much profane learning, and in consideration of the antiquity of the worke,
and maiestie of the author, could not (without great indecencie) haue vsed
the authorities of men, or of so late times (as since the learnings florished,
whence we now receiue our common light.) Like naked truth therefore I
pray thee receiue it, for it owne, if not for my sake: &amp; if in any thing I seeme
to swarne from thy conceit of many points, I pray thee confer farther ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
with <hi>D. Gregorius, Neocerasiensis Epis. Olimpioderus, D. Salonius Epis. Viennēsis,
Theod. Beza, Ioh. Serranus, Anth. Corranus, Tremelius,</hi> all interpreters and para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrasers
in prose vpon this worke, and <hi>I. Lectius, Ro. Lemmannus, I. Viuianus,</hi>
reducers thereof into Latin poesie, or any other thou likest better of, so shal
my errors be couered or excused, whilst their different formes, distributiōs
of method, &amp; interpretatiōs, wil leaue thee (I am perswaded) in some points
as litle satisfied as this my labor shall do: who in some things was forced to
digresse from them all, when either too much in one place, or too litle in an
other, they followed the forme of a Paraphrasis, which they vndertooke: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
which error also it is not vnlike but I haue sometimes fallen my selfe, and
I doubt not but many things more might haue bin said, &amp; perhaps to more
purpose then I haue done, but <hi>non omnia possumus omnes.</hi> According to my suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie
I haue discharged my self faithfully vnto thee, and therfore I trust
(in these dayes wherein some pernitious, many vnciuil, and a swarme of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous
and vnprofitable books passe from the presse) it shall not be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
for me to vse great insinuation for thy fauour; since it lyeth not in the
bounds of a Preface, to prepare a peruerse mind, or in the nature of such a
worke, to go a begging for a grace. I will therfore cut off that labor, &amp; only
signifie vnto thee the excellency of this worke, compiled by the wisest man,
and mightiest king of Israell, euen <hi>Salomon</hi> the king of peace: <hi>Ydida:</hi> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued
of God: <hi>Ecclesiastes</hi> the preacher: who in his Prouerbs instructeth thee
as a child, to a ciuill and honest life: in this worke, instituteth thy manly
thoughts to the inquisition of the highest good. To the end, that by his last
song of heauenly loue, thy ripened thoughts might be inflamed with that
glorious bride Christ Iesus: to whose holy direction I hartily cōmend thee.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>H. L.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>