<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Square plainely set downe.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1597</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104588_Fr2_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A06202</idno>
           <idno type="STC">16696</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104588</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Square plainely set downe.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ecclesiastes, othervvise called The preacher : Containing Salomons sermons or commentaries (as it may probably be collected) vpon the 49. Psalme of Dauid his father. Compendiously abridged, and also paraphrastically dilated in English poesie, according to the analogie of Scripture, and consent of the most approued writer thereof. Composed by H.L. Gentleman. Whereunto are annexed sundrie sonets of Christian passions heretofore printed, and now corrected and augmented, with other affectionate sonets of a feeling conscience of the same authors</title>
                 <author>Lok, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1597</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 117, 15, 79, 82-170, 36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <head>The Square plainely set downe.</head>
   <l>GOd hath powr'd forth rare grace on this Ile, and</l>
   <l>Makes crown'd your rule, Queene in the same so still,</l>
   <l>Kings laud this Saint faire, that with truth doth stand,</l>
   <l>Rule so long time mild Prince, ioy land it will.</l>
   <l>For proofe you showes, wise of earths race whom there</l>
   <l>Heauens haue vpheld▪ lust choyce whom God thus shields,</l>
   <l>Your stocke of kings (worlds rich ofspring and feare,</l>
   <l>States fame knowne farre) praise Ile which all blisse yeelds.</l>
   <l>Hold God therefore sure stay, and port the best;</l>
   <l>Blest is your raigne, here builds sweet peace, true rest.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>