<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the captious company of carping
Readers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104175_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03504</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13626</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104175</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the captious company of carping
Readers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The strange, vvonderfull, and bloudy battell betweene frogs and mise : the occasion of their falling out: their preparation, munition, and resolution for the warres: the seuerall combats of euery person of worth; with many other memorable accidents. Interlaced with diuers pithy and morall sentences, no lesse pleasant to be read, then profitable to be obserued. Couertly decyphering the estate of these times. Paraphrastically done into English heroycall verse by W.F. C.C.C</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 <publisher>Bailey, John 2.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_carping_readers">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the captious company of carping
Readers.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Purne not the study of my nouice Muse,</l>
      <l>though but a toy;</l>
      <l>Who scornes to reade this trifle, let him chuse,</l>
      <l>though ne're so coy:</l>
      <l>Yet no base trifle: for by <hi>Homers</hi> quill</l>
      <l>The subiect was contriu'd, if good or ill.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If then the subiect was of <hi>Homers</hi> worth,</l>
      <l>from <hi>Homers</hi> brayne,</l>
      <l>What should affray my Muse to set this forth,</l>
      <l>and scorne disdayne?</l>
      <l>For he which scoffes this Poeme in his pride,</l>
      <l>If that he durst, great <hi>Homer</hi> would deride.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Let addle heads by idle humours guise,</l>
      <l>ybent to stray,</l>
      <l>Iest at this battell of the <hi>Frogs</hi> and <hi>Mise,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Ile not dismay,</l>
      <l>Since <hi>Homer</hi> stands as bulwarke on my part,</l>
      <l>T' award the scornfull termes that fooles will dart.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>The babbling prayses of the vulgar vayne</l>
      <l>I nought esteeme,</l>
      <l>Nor how the curious, through fantastick braine,</l>
      <l>my labours deeme.</l>
      <l>As one to eu'ry trifle giues applause,</l>
      <l>So th' other, all condemnes, without iust cause.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And yet the censure of the meanest wit</l>
      <l>I nill refuse:</l>
      <l>For slender iudgements best I thinke befit</l>
      <l>my simple Muse:</l>
      <l>Onely I wish, that he which reads this booke,</l>
      <l>His praise or dispraise may to reason looke.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Nil moror vlterius.</hi>
      </l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>