<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, WILLIAM, LORD HERBERT EARLE OF Pembrooke, Baron of Cardiffe, Marmion, and Saint Quintin, one of his Maiesties most honourable priuie Counsell, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter. Robert Anton wisheth a happy life militant and trium∣phant.</title>
           <author>Anton, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104412_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20460</idno>
           <idno type="STC">686</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104412</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, WILLIAM, LORD HERBERT EARLE OF Pembrooke, Baron of Cardiffe, Marmion, and Saint Quintin, one of his Maiesties most honourable priuie Counsell, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter. Robert Anton wisheth a happy life militant and trium∣phant.</title>
                 <author>Anton, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The philosophers satyrs, written by M. Robert Anton, of Magdelen Colledge in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Anton, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 76 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, WILLIAM, LORD HERBERT EARLE OF Pembrooke, Baron of Cardiffe, Marmion, and Saint <hi>Quintin, one of his Maiesties most honourable priuie</hi> Counsell, and Knight of the most noble order of the Garter. <hi>Robert Anton</hi> wisheth a happy life militant and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
      </hi> Remember (Right Honourable, the whining complaint of the Poet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning vertue: <hi>Credo pudicitiam Saturno: rege moratam delapsum in coelis:</hi> 'Tis the iron age, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue must haue Estredge like concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or else die in an Hospitall for want of a Patron. Tis well she is stellified in heauen: for earth is her locall place of torment: I haue been a sad spectator of her iniuries, and deplore her miserable exile; yet her ecclipse by the interposition of vice is not a totall defect of her heauenly light, but partiall and limited, yet how prodigious it is, the tragicall changes of this age can truly prophesie. Some Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon might haue begd a dead body from the fanges of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, whose Anotomy might haue taught the age the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of vice, impostumated with murder and hot raind affections. My prayer is more charitable, then Cynicall to wish any plants of such an vnfortunate tree, I haue seene vice adored with her superstitious Imagerie, and I wish all true Protestants to vertue rather to die Martyrs, then
<pb facs="3"/>
reuolt from her profession, in whose faith your honour is held a most religious professor, the sects of vice are more then in Amsterdam, to whose errors I oppose my booke, as an eager disputant. The motions of this planitarie satire are regular and presented in a maske of a seuenfold vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity. Appeare Philosopher in thy vndaunted humor of grauity, &amp; spit defiance in the face of scurrile satirrisme: lend heauenly whipcord, and borrow correction from the Sunne: fetch blood from the whole body of Nature, and the sixe planets lay on load on the stigmatick shoulders of vice. This book was conceiued in dog-daies, and must bite, the signe is in Scorpio, and the planets in their most criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call mansion. Be as the world thinkes you, vertuous, and reade this booke with a more then laurell resolution. The thunder hath no power ouer a consecrated and vertuous mind, it smites onely strong timbred villanies. Kings haue accepted rootes from a Philosopher: the gift is small: yet it calls you Lord, and me master. A satire is musicke worthie of Pithagor as his opinion, especially, when the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets dance a heauenly lauolto, they are nimble spirited and actiue, and onely hope for the passiue part of your noble patronage.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours obliged Robert Anton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>