<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE HONORABLE AND EMINENTLY VERTVOVS, THE EX∣cellent Lady THEOPHILA, the Learned Consort of the right wor∣thy Sir ROBERT COOKE, Knight, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104033_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03196</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13316</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104033</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE HONORABLE AND EMINENTLY VERTVOVS, THE EX∣cellent Lady THEOPHILA, the Learned Consort of the right wor∣thy Sir ROBERT COOKE, Knight, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The exemplary lives and memorable acts of nine the most worthy women of the vvorld : three Iewes. Three gentiles. Three Christians. Written by the author of the History of women</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Cotes, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Royston (Reston, Reyston, Roystore), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 212, 12 pages, 1 leaf of plates, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE HONORABLE AND EMINENTLY VERTVOVS, THE EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Lady THEOPHILA, the Learned Consort of the right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Sir ROBERT COOKE, Knight, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Excellent Madam,</salute>
   </opener>
   <l>SHould I present you with your merited praise,</l>
   <l>What Muse should I invoke? what rapture raise?</l>
   <l>For my <hi>minerva,</hi> tis too high a straine,</l>
   <l>As farre surpassing both my pen and braine.</l>
   <l>When I shall say, the Lilly doth excell</l>
   <l>For whitenesse, or the Violet for the smell;</l>
   <l>Or for a modest blush, the Garden Rose;</l>
   <l>What speake I more in this then each man knowes?</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>Or if I shall proclaime the Turtle chast;</l>
   <l>Or praise the ripe fruits for their pleasing taste,</l>
   <l>The Nightingale commend for many a tune,</l>
   <l>And say shee farre excells the Bird of <hi>Iune.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>If in their grace I strive to doe my best,</l>
   <l>What write I more, then is by all confest?</l>
   <l>If I shall say y'are beautifull and faire,</l>
   <l>Matchlesse, unparalleld, in all parts rare;</l>
   <l>And to those outward should I then annex</l>
   <l>The inward vertues, that most grace your Sex!</l>
   <l>To name which, would exceede number, or to tell</l>
   <l>The severall tongues, in which you so excell,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Greeke, Roman, French, Castillian,</hi> and with those,</l>
   <l>
      <hi>Tuscan, Teutonick,</hi> in all which you pose</l>
   <l>The forreigne Linguist: in the most select</l>
   <l>Both native <hi>Ideom,</hi> and choise dalect.</l>
   <l>Or, for all learning Morrall or Divine,</l>
   <l>To list you a tenth Muse amongst the nine?</l>
   <l>When to the height of all these I am growne,</l>
   <l>I shall adde nothing to you save your owne.</l>
   <l>Nor can my praise the least advantage win you</l>
   <l>Since all that know you know these to be in you.</l>
   <l>If to your honours, both of <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Booke,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>You shall but daine an animating looke,</l>
   <l>To' inlifen these dull papers; they shall strive,</l>
   <l>Alternatly to make your name survive.</l>
   <l>Acknowledging, in a submisse surrender</l>
   <l>They had dy'd blind, not lightned by your splendor.</l>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours absequiously devoted.</hi> THO. HEYVVOOd▪</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>