<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THOMAS, Lord HOVVARD, Earle of Arundell and
Surrey, Primier Earle, and Earle Marshall of England, Baron HOVVARD, Mowbray,
Segrave, Brus of Gower, Fitz-Alan, Clun, Oswaldestre, Maltravers,
and Graystocke, Knight of the most Noble Order of the GARTER, and one of his Ma∣jesties most Honourable Privie Councell.</title>
           <author>Howard, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1634</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104244_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03751</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13871</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104244</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THOMAS, Lord HOVVARD, Earle of Arundell and
Surrey, Primier Earle, and Earle Marshall of England, Baron HOVVARD, Mowbray,
Segrave, Brus of Gower, Fitz-Alan, Clun, Oswaldestre, Maltravers,
and Graystocke, Knight of the most Noble Order of the GARTER, and one of his Ma∣jesties most Honourable Privie Councell.</title>
                 <author>Howard, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A patterne of Christian loyaltie : vvhereby any prudent man may clearely perceive, in what manner the new Oath of Allegiance, and every clause thereof, may in a true, and catholike sense, without danger of perjury, be taken by Roman Catholikes. And all the chiefe objections, which are usually made against the said Oath, either in particular, or in generall, may according to the grounds of Catholike religion bee easily answered. Collected out of authours, who have handled the whole matter more largely. By William Hovvard an English Catholike</title>
                 <author>Preston, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Badger, Richard 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1634</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 61, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THOMAS, <hi>Lord</hi> HOVVARD, <hi>Earle of</hi> Arundell and
<hi>Surrey,</hi> Primier Earle, and Earle Marshall <hi>of England, Baron</hi> HOVVARD, Mowbray,
<hi>Segrave, Brus</hi> of <hi>Gower, Fitz-Alan, Clun,</hi> Oswaldestre, Maltravers,
<hi>and</hi> Graystocke, <hi>Knight of the most Noble Order of the</hi> GARTER, <hi>and one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties most Honourable Privie Councell.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>
         <hi>My very good</hi> LORD;</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Titles on which this Dedication is grounded have prooved stronger then my bashfulnesse, or feare; for your singular candor of minde, makes mee hope an
<pb facs="4"/>acceptance of my good intentions, though joyned with weake abillities, and (besides the honour of my relation to your <hi>Lordship</hi> in bloud) the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience I have had of your Noble and gracious favour to my selfe in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, gives me assurance, that you will not bee displeased, if for protection in an undertaking exposed to much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, I addresse my selfe to your <hi>Lordship.</hi> For so earnest have they been in this controversy, as now at last (even since this little Treatise was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der presse) they have objected to me; that wee are bound to beleeve as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of faith, the generalities delivered by the <hi>Popes Holinesse,</hi> though the wisedome (say they) of the See
<hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolike</hi> for bearing to irritate Christian <hi>Princes,</hi> descendes not to particulars.
<pb facs="4"/>Thus indeavour they to beare us in hand, that wee are bound to professe what they conceale from us, and that <hi>Catholike</hi> faith must bee all one with mysterie of
<hi>State,</hi> and consequently every good <hi>Christian</hi> being bound to professe his
<hi>faith,</hi> with the losse of his life and living, we must in this questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bee tyed to no lesse, for a secret in policie, thought fitting to bee kept from us out of reason of
<hi>State.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>The very laying downe of this their last refuge, sufficiently dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covereth the weakenesse thereof: so it onely resteth that I crave your <hi>Lordships</hi> pardon for presenting it out of due place to your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>View; to whom as Chiefe, both by nature and merit, I am obliged to professe my selfe,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>A faithfull and humble servant,</hi> WILLIAM HOVVARD.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>