<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right VVorshipfull my singuler good friend Sir William Hatton knight.</title>
           <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104961_Bo1_9_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18722</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5220</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104961</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right VVorshipfull my singuler good friend Sir William Hatton knight.</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Churchyards challenge</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 135, 126-170, 175-198, 209-232, 231-278 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <head>To the right VVorshipfull my singuler good friend Sir William Hatton knight.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the remembrance of a sorrowful losse I had by the death of the last Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celor, (good Sir William Hatton) and considering your great countenance partly declined by that soddaine acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, besides the great soms of money you were left to pay. For the parting from such an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable friend, I thought (euery peece of cause well waied) you knowe as well what calamitie is as a meaner man, and feeling the smart and weight of that burthen, before you were ready to support it, your care and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie could not be little. First for the losse of so great a comfort, &amp; next for the sorrow &amp; trobles that belongs to such a losse, though lands or liuings helps to beare of a peece of the vexasion of mind, yet the body shall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes beare to the death a sorrowfull imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that hastie mishap, the impression therof shal neuer goe out of your memory, so long as life lasteth. So good sir, in signe of some consolation, I present you a discourse of Calamity, the right path to come to quietnesse, and the very hie way that leades a good mind to thinke of the immortality of the soule, thus presuming your fauorable acception of the same, I passe to the discourse of Calamity, wishing you much worship, hartes ease &amp; health.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>T. Churchyard.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>