<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honorable Sr. Maurice
Abbot, Knight, the Lord Maior of this
renowned Metropolis, London.</title>
           <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1638</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104071_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03242</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13359</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104071</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honorable Sr. Maurice
Abbot, Knight, the Lord Maior of this
renowned Metropolis, London.</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Porta pietatis, or, The port or harbour of piety : Exprest in sundry triumphes, pageants, and showes, at the initiation of the Right Honourable Sir Maurice Abbot Knight, into the Majoralty of the famous and farre renowned city London. All the charge and expence of the laborious projects both by water and land, being the sole undertaking of the Right Worshipfull Company of the Drapers. Written by Thomas Heywood</title>
                 <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes (Oakes), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1638</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honorable S<seg rend="sup">r.</seg>
      <hi>Maurice
Abbot,</hi> Knight, the Lord Maior of this
renowned Metropolis, <hi>London.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ntiquity informes us, in the most
flourishing state of <hi>Rome,</hi> of an
Order of the <hi>Candidati,</hi> so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
because habited in white ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture,
betokning <hi>Innocence,</hi> and
those of the noblest Citizens, who in that garbe wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
the streets with humble lookes, and submisse ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture,
thereby to insinuate themselves into the
grace of the people, being ambitious after honour and
Office. Great Lord, it fareth not so with You, who
though for inward Candor and sincerity, You may
compare with the best of them, yet have beene so far
from affecting such popularity, that though You in
Your great Modesty would willingly have evaded
it; yet some places by importunity, and this Your
present Praetorship hath by a generall suffrage, and
the unanimous harmony of a free Election, beene
conferd upon You.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>Neither can I omit the happinesse of Your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased
Father, remarkable in three most fortunate
Sonnes: the one, for many yeares together, Arch-Bishop
of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Metropolitane of all
<hi>England:</hi> another, a reverend Father in God,
Bishop of <hi>Salisbury:</hi> as memorable for his learned
Workes and Writings, as the other for his Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall
government in the Church, and Counsell in
State. And now lately Your Honour'd selfe, the
Lord Maior of this Metropolis, the famous City
<hi>London:</hi> In which, and of which, as you are now
<hi>Maximus,</hi> so it is expected you shall prove <hi>Opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi>
Grave Sir, it is a knowne Maxime, that the
honour which is acquired by Vertue, hath a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
assurance: nor blame my boldnesse, if I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume
to prompt Your memory in what You have long
studied: The life of a Magistrate is the rule and
square whereby inferior persons frame their carriage
and deportment, who sooner assimulate themselves to
their Lives than their Lawes, which Lawes if not
executed are of no estimation. But I cease further to
trouble Your Lordship, leaving you to Your Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
charge, with that of the Poet,
<q>Qui sua metitur pondera, ferre potest.</q>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships in all observance
<hi>Thomas Heywood.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>