<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Praeface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104387_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21975</idno>
           <idno type="STC">832</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104387</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Praeface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The scholemaster or plaine and perfite way of teachyng children, to vnderstand, write, and speake, the Latin tong : but specially purposed for the priuate brynging vp of youth in ientlemen and noble mens houses, and commodious also for all such, as haue forgot the Latin tonge, and would,by themselues, without à scholemaster, in short tyme, and with small paines, recouer à sufficient habilitie, to vnderstand, write, and speake Latin. By Roger Ascham</title>
                 <author>Ascham, Roger</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 67, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>A Praeface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the great plage was at London, the yeare 1563. the Quenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> lay at her Castle of Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sore: Where, vpon the 10. day of December, it fortuned, that in Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Cicells</hi> chamber, hir Highnesse Principall Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretarie, there dined to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither these personages, M. Secretarie him selfe, Syr <hi>William Peter,</hi> Syr <hi>I. Mason,</hi> D. <hi>Wotton,</hi> Syr <hi>Richard Sackuille</hi> Treasurer of the Exchecker, Syr <hi>Walter Mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maye</hi> Chauncellor of the Exchecker, M. <hi>Haddon</hi> Master of Requestes, M. <hi>Iohn Astely</hi> Master of the Iewell house, M. <hi>Bernard Hampton,</hi> M. <hi>Nicasius,</hi> and <hi>I.</hi> Of which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the most part were of hir Maiesties most honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble priuie Counsell, and the reast seruing hir in verie good place. I was glad than, and do reioice yet to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that my chance was so happie, to be there that day, in the companie of so manie wise &amp; good men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, as hardly than could haue bene piked out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, out of all England beside.</p>
   <p>M. Secretarie hath this accustomed maner, though his head be neuer so full of most weightie affaires of the Realme, yet, at diner time he doth seeme to lay them alwaies aside: and findeth euer fitte occasion to taulke pleasantlie of other matters, but most gladlie of some matter of learning: wherein, he will curteslie heare the minde of the meanest at his Table.</p>
   <p>Not long after our sitting doune, I haue strange newes brought me, sayth M. Secretarie, this morning,
<pb facs="5"/>
that diuerse Scholers of Eaton, be runne àwaie from the Schole,<note place="margin">M. <hi>Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi>
      </note> for feare of beating. Whereupon, M. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretarie tooke occasion, to wishe, that some more dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dretion were in many Scholemasters, in vsing correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than commonlie there is. Who many times, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe rather, the weakenes of nature, than the fault of the Scholer. Whereby, many Scholers, that might else proue well, be driuen to hate learning, before they knowe, what learning meaneth: and so, are made wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to forsake their booke, and be glad to be put to any other kinde of liuing.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">M. <hi>Peter.</hi>
      </note>M. <hi>Peter,</hi> as one somewhat seuere of nature, said plainlie, that the Rodde onelie, was the sworde, that must keepe, the Schole in obedience, and the Scholer in good order. M. <hi>Wotton,</hi>
      <note place="margin">M. <hi>Wotton.</hi>
      </note> à man milde of nature, with soft voice, and fewe wordes, inclined to M. Secretaries iudgement,<note place="margin">Ludus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terarum.</note> and said, in mine opinion, the Scholehouse should be in deede, as it is called by name, the house of playe and pleasure, and not of feare and bondage: and as I do remember, so saith <hi>Socrates</hi> in one place of <hi>Plato.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Plato</hi> de Rep. 7.</note> And therefore, if à Rodde carie the feare of à Sworde, it is no maruell, if those that be fearefull of nature, chose rather to forsake the Plaie, than to stand alwaies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the feare of à Sworde in à fonde mans handling. M. <hi>Mason,</hi>
      <note place="margin">M. <hi>Mason.</hi>
      </note> after his maner, was verie merie with both parties, pleasantlie playing, both, with the shrew de touches of many courste boyes, and with the small dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of many leude Scholemasters.<note place="margin">M. <hi>Haddon.</hi>
      </note> M. <hi>Haddon</hi> was fullie of M. <hi>Peters</hi> opinion, and said, that the best Scholemaster of our time, was the greatest beater, and named the Person.<note place="margin">
         <hi>The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this booke.</hi>
      </note> Though, quoth I, it was his good fortune, to send from his Schole, vnto the Vniuersitie, one of the best Scholers in deede of all our time, yet wise men do thinke, that that came so to passe, rather, by the great towardnes of the Scholer, than by the great beating of the Master: and whether this be true or no, you your selfe are best witnes. I said somewhat farder
<pb facs="5"/>
in the matter, how, and whie, yong children, were soner allured by loue, than driuen by beating, to atteyne good learning: wherein I was the bolder to say my minde, bicause M. Secretarie curteslie prouoked me thereunto: or else, in such à companie, and namelie in his praesence, my wonte is, to be more willing, to vse mine eares, than to occupie my tonge.</p>
   <p>Syr <hi>Walter Mildmaye,</hi> M. <hi>Astley,</hi> and the rest, said verie litle: onelie Syr <hi>Rich. Sackuill,</hi> said nothing at all. After dinner I went vp to read with the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie. We red than togither in the Greke tonge,<note place="margin">Demost. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> as I well remember, that noble Oration of <hi>Demosthenes</hi> against <hi>Aeschines,</hi> for his false dealing in his Ambassage to king <hi>Philip</hi> of Macedonie.<note place="margin">Syr <hi>R. Sackuiles communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with the Author of this booke.</hi>
      </note> Syr <hi>Rich. Sackuile</hi> came vp sone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and finding me in hir Maiesties priuie chamber, he tooke me by the hand, &amp; carying me to à windoe, said, M. <hi>Ascham,</hi> I would not for à good deale of monie, haue bene, this daie, absent from diner. Where, though I said nothing, yet I gaue as good eare, and do consider as well the taulke, that passed, as any one did there. M. Secretarie said very wisely, and most truely, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yong wittes be driuen to hate learninge, before they know what learninge is. I can be good witnes to this my selfe: For a fond Scholemaster, before I was fullie fourtene yeare olde, draue me so, with feare of beating, from all loue of learninge, as nowe, when I know, what difference it is, to haue learninge, and to haue litle, or none at all, I feele it my greatest greife, and finde it my greatest hurte, that euer came to me, that it was my so ill chance, to light vpon so lewde à Scholemaster. But seing it is but in vain, to lament thinges paste, and also wisdome to looke to thinges to cum, surely, God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge, if God lend me life, I will make this my mishap, some occasion of good hap, to litle <hi>Robert Sackuile</hi> my sonnes sonne. For whose bringinge vp, I would gladlie, if it so please you, vse speciallie your good aduice. I heare saie, you haue à sonne, moch of his age: we wil
<pb facs="6"/>
deale thus togither. Point you out à Scholemaster, who by your order, shall teache my sonne and yours, and for all the rest, I will prouide, yea though they three do cost me à couple of hundred poundes by yeare: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side, you shall finde me as fast à Frend to you and yours, as perchance any you haue. Which promise, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Ientleman surelie kept with me, vntill his dying daye.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>The cheife pointes of this booke.</hi>
      </note>We had than farther taulke togither, of bringing vp of children: of the nature, of quicke, and hard wittes: of the right choice of à good witte: of Feare, and loue in teachinge children. We passed from children and came to yonge men, namely, Ientlemen: we taulked of their to moch libertie, to liue as they lust: of their let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting louse to sone, to ouermoch experience of ill, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the good order of many good olde common welthes of the Persians and Grekes: of witte gathered, and good fortune gotten, by some, onely by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, without learning. And lastlie, he required of me verie earnestlie, to shewe, what I thought of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon goinge of Englishe men into Italie. But, sayth he, bicause this place, and this tyme, will not suffer so long taulke, as these good matters require, therefore I pray you, at my request, and at your leysure, put in some or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of writing, the cheife pointes of this our taulke, concerning, the right order of teachinge, and honestie of liuing, for the good bringing vp of children &amp; yong men. And surelie, beside contentinge me, you shall both please and profit verie many others. I made some excuse by lacke of habilitie, and weakenes of bodie: well, sayth he, I am not now to learne, what you can do. Our deare frende, good M. <hi>Goodricke,</hi> whose iudgement I could well beleue, did once for all, satisfie me fullie therein. Againe, I heard you say, not long agoe, that you may thanke Syr <hi>Iohn Cheke,</hi> for all the learninge you haue: And I know verie well my selfe, that you did teach the Quene. And therefore seing God did so blesse you,
<pb facs="6"/>
to make you the Scholer of the best Master, and also the Scholemaster of the best Scholer, that euer were in our tyme, surelie, you should please God, benefite your countrie, &amp; honest your owne name, if you would take the paines, to impart to others, what you learned of soch à Master, and how ye taught soch à scholer. And, in vttering the stuffe ye receiued of the one, in decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the order ye tooke with the other, ye shall neuer lacke, neither matter, nor maner, what to write, nor how to write in this kinde of Argument.</p>
   <p>I beginning some farther excuse, sodeinlie was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to cum to the Queene. The night following, I slept litle, my head was so full of this our former taulke, and I so mindefull, somewhat to satisfie the honest request of so deare à frend. I thought to praepare some litle trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise for à Newyeares gift that Christmas. But, as it chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to busie builders, so, in building thys my poore Scholehouse (the rather bicause the forme of it is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what new, and differing from others) the worke rose dailie higher and wider, than I thought it would at the beginninge.</p>
   <p>And though it appeare now, and be in verie deede, but à small cotage, poore for the stuffe, and rude for the workemanship, yet in going forward, I found the site so good, as I was lothe to giue it ouer, but the making so costlie, outreaching my habilitie, as many tymes I wished, that some one of those three, my deare frendes, with full pursses, Syr <hi>Tho. Smithe,</hi>
      <note place="margin">M. <hi>Smith.</hi> M. <hi>Haddō.</hi> M. <hi>Watson.</hi>
      </note> M. <hi>Haddon,</hi> or M. <hi>Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> had had the doing of it. Yet, neuerthelesse, I my selfe, spending gladlie that litle, that I gatte at home by good Syr <hi>Iohn Cheke,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Syr <hi>I. Checke. I. Sturmius.</hi>
      </note> and that that I borrowed abroad of my frend <hi>Sturmius,</hi> beside somewhat that was left me in Reuersion by my olde Masters, <hi>Plato, Aristotle,</hi> and <hi>Cicero,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Plato.</hi>
      </note> I haue at last patched it vp, as I could, and as you see. If the matter be meane, and meanly handled, I pray you beare,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Aristotle.</hi>
      </note> both with me, and it: for neuer worke went vp in worse wether,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Cicero.</hi>
      </note> with mo lettes and stoppes,
<pb facs="7"/>
than this poore Scholehouse of mine. Westminster Hall can beare some witnesse, beside moch weakenes of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, but more trouble of minde, by some soch sores, as greue me to toche them my selfe, and therefore I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose not to open them to others. And, in middes of outward iniuries, and inward cares, to encrease them withall, good Syr <hi>Rich. Sackuile</hi> dieth,<note place="margin">Syr <hi>R. Sackuill.</hi>
      </note> that worthie Ien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman: That earnest fauorer and furtherer of Gods true Religion: That faithfull Seruitor to his Prince and Countrie: A louer of learning, &amp; all learned men: Wise in all doinges: Curtesse to all persons: shewing spite to none: doing good to many: and as I well found, to me so fast à frend, as I neuer lost the like before. Whan he was gone, my hart was dead. There was not one, that woare à blacke gowne for him, who caried à heuier hart for him, than I. Whan he was gone, I cast this booke àwaie: I could not looke vpon it, but with weping eyes, in remembring him, who was the onelie setter on, to do it, and would haue bene, not onelie à glad commender of it, but also à sure and certaine comfort, to me and mine, for it. Almost two yeares togither, this booke lay scattered, and neglected, and had bene quite giuen ouer of me, if the goodnesse of one had not giuen me some life and spirite againe. God, the mouer of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, prosper alwaies him &amp; his, as he hath many times comforted me and mine, and, I trust to God, shall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort more and more. Of whom, most iustlie I may saie, and verie oft, and alwaies gladlie, I am wont to say, that sweete verse of <hi>Sophocles,</hi> spoken by <hi>Oedipus</hi> to worthie <hi>Theseus.</hi>
      <q>
         <l>
            <note place="margin">Soph. in Oed. Col.</note>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>.</l>
      </q>
Thys hope hath helped me to end this booke: which, if he allowe, I shall thinke my labours well imployed, and shall not moch aesteme the misliking of any others. And I trust, he shall thinke the better of it, bicause he shall finde the best part thereof, to cum out of his Schole,
<pb facs="7"/>
whom he, of all men loued and liked best.</p>
   <p>Yet some men, frendly enough of nature, but of small iudgement in learninge, do thinke, I take to moch paines, and spend to moch time, in settinge forth these childrens affaires.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Plato,</hi> in initio Theagis. <gap reason="foreign">
            <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
         </gap>.</note> But those good men were neuer brought vp in <hi>Socrates</hi> Schole, who saith plainlie, that no man goeth àbout à more godlie purpose, than he that is mindfull of the good bringing vp, both of hys owne, and other mens children.</p>
   <p>Therefore, I trust, good and wise men, will thinke well of this my doing. And of other, that thinke otherwise, I will thinke my selfe, they are but men, to be pardoned for their follie, and pitied for their ignoraunce.</p>
   <p>In writing this booke, I haue had earnest respecte to three speciall pointes, trothe of Religion, honestie in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, right order in learning. In which three waies, I praie God, my poore children may diligently waulke: for whose sake, as nature moued, and reason required, and necessitie also somewhat compelled, I was the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger to take these paines.</p>
   <p>For, seing at my death, I am not like to leaue them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great store of liuing, therefore in my life time, I thought good to bequeath vnto thē, in this litle booke, as in my Will and Testament, the right waie to good learning: which if they followe, with the feare of God, they shall verie well cum to sufficiencie of liuinge.</p>
   <p>I wishe also, with all my hart, that yong M. <hi>Rob. Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uille,</hi> may take that fructe of this labor, that his worthie Grauntfather purposed he should haue done: And if any other do take, either proffet, or pleasure hereby, they haue cause to thanke M. <hi>Robert Sackuille,</hi> for whom speciallie this my Scholemaster was prouided.</p>
   <p>And one thing I would haue the Reader consider in readinge this booke, that bicause, no Scholemaster hath charge of any childe, before he enter into hys Schole, therefore I leauing all former care, of their good bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp, to wise and good Parentes, as à matter not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
<pb facs="8"/>
to the Scholemaster, I do appoynt thys▪ my Scholemaster, than, and there to begin, where his office and charge beginneth. Which charge lasteth not long, but vntill the Scholer be made hable to go to the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie, to procede in Logike, Rhetoricke, and other kindes of learning.</p>
   <p>Yet if my Scholemaster, for loue he beareth to hys Scholer, shall teach hym somewhat for hys furtherance, and better iudgement in learning, that may serue him seuen yeare after in the Vniuersitie, he doth hys Scholer no more wrong, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth no worse name therby, than he doth in London, who selling silke or cloth vnto his frend, doth giue hym better measure, than either hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise or bargaine was.</p>
   <closer>Farewell in Christ.</closer>
   <pb facs="8"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>