<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104788_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16746</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3654</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104788</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A floorish vpon fancie : As gallant a glose vpon so triflinge a text, as euer was written. Compiled by N.B. Gent. To which are annexed, manie pretie pamphlets, for pleasant heads to passe away idle time withal. By the same authour</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>How (Howe, Haw), William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>132 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Prouerbe olde, and therewith trewe there is,</l>
      <l>That, <hi>haste makes waste,</hi> ech thing must haue his time:</l>
      <l>Who high aspiers, must euer looke to this,</l>
      <l>To marke his steppes, before he ginne to clime:</l>
      <l>For who in climing takes no care at all,</l>
      <l>Ere hee get vp, is like to catch a fall.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Who doth desire, to <hi>Honor</hi> hie to clime,</l>
      <l>By due desart, must worshippe first attaine:</l>
      <l>Then for to seeke, in farther tract of time,</l>
      <l>The meane, whereby to <hi>Honor</hi> to attaine:</l>
      <l>For hee that thinckes, to bee a Lorde first day,</l>
      <l>Will misse a Lorde, and proue a Loute streight way.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Who doth assault, the huge high <hi>Fort of Fame,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Must first beginne, to scale the outwarde walles:</l>
      <l>Longe is the Ladder that doth reach the same,</l>
      <l>And happie he that gets vp without falles:</l>
      <l>Tedious the time, the labour nothing short,</l>
      <l>To take in hande to scale so high a Forte.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>This prouerbe olde, my selfe obserued well,</l>
      <l>Who not assault, the gallant <hi>Fort of Fame</hi>:</l>
      <l>But <hi>Fancies Forte,</hi> not minding there to dwell,</l>
      <l>But for to see the secretes of the same:</l>
      <l>And many times, I thought to make retire,</l>
      <l>But in the ende, obtained my desire.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I scalde the walles, and got into the Fort</l>
      <l>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>h ease inough, short time and little fight▪</l>
      <l>And there I sawe, whereof I make report,</l>
      <l>Ech thinge, that was for to be seene worth sight:</l>
      <l>And when that I some time therin had past,</l>
      <l>How by good hap, I got away at last.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <l>Now farre from this, I see <hi>The Fort of Fame</hi>
      </l>
      <l>A harder thinge, to giue assault vnto:</l>
      <l>I dare not seeke the meane, to scale the same,</l>
      <l>And if I durst, I know not what to doe:</l>
      <l>In scalinge Fortes, my skill is too too small,</l>
      <l>Then if I clime, I needes must catch a fall.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>By lying still, I can but little gaine,</l>
      <l>By clyminge too the feare is but a fall:</l>
      <l>No praise in deede, is gotten without paine,</l>
      <l>Smale hurte by falles, if bruze growe not withall:</l>
      <l>No bruze nor fall, takes hee that takes good heede,</l>
      <l>No takinge heede, great haste, and little speede.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Then when I clime, my selfe am warnde to learne</l>
      <l>The way to scale, ere ought I take in hande,</l>
      <l>To set my <hi>Ladder,</hi> wisely to discerne</l>
      <l>To choose a place, where it may surely stande:</l>
      <l>Then for to make my <hi>Ladder</hi> of such stuffe,</l>
      <l>As I may trust, to treade on sure ynouffe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But then the <hi>Roundes,</hi> must not be made of <hi>Ryme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi>▪</l>
      <l>My feete will slippe, in treading on the same:</l>
      <l>And <hi>Reason</hi> sayes, that who so fondly clymes,</l>
      <l>Falles downe into the ditch of foule <hi>Defame,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>God keepe me thence, and helpe me so to clyme,</l>
      <l>That <hi>Reason</hi> yet, may rayse me vp in tyme.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>