<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The preface to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104540_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10770</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21039</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104540</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The preface to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An exposicion in Englishe vpon the Epistle of .S. Paule, to the Colossians : wherin the letter is purely declared, with many good exhortacions to flee vice, and to take vertue, as shall appere clerely to the faithfull reader throughout all this epistle: written by Lancelo Ridley of Cantorbury. Anno salutis humanæ M.D.XLVIII</title>
                 <author>Ridley, Lancelot</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>280 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶The preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Race, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and peace, from GOD oure father of heauē, bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all thē that loueth
<hi>GOD</hi> and his worde, and bee true set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters furth &amp; promoters of Gods holy Gospell.
Amen.</p>
   <p>Because the worde of God is the spirituall foode of our soule <hi>Matth. iiii.</hi> and as
necessary for the soule to feede it, as corporall food is to fede the body, ye more
necessarie, because it feedeth the soule, a more plenteous thyng then is the body, and
geueth life eternall with GOD the father, whereas the foode of the body
<pb facs="3"/> feedeth the body for a short time and bryngeth not eternall life with God the
father. And this spirituall foode for the mooste part lieth hid, in the letter of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
scripture, vnknowen to many that readeth scripture, because thei dooe not vnderstande that
thyng thei reade, although thei doo vnderstande Englishe, and the scripture in many plain
pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet there bee in the holy scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, many darke places and hard sentences to be
vnderstād, whiche requireth more help then the bare texte in Englishe, either by diligente
searchyng oute the true trāslacion of that place, out of that toungue that it was first
written in, that is, out of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew or the Greke tongue, in the whiche the holy scriptures
was
<pb facs="3"/> first written: either by cōparyng of one place of holy Scripture with another, and
expoundyng one place by another, or by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent obseruyng the circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and sentences,
goyng before and commyng after, or by helpe of some learned aucthor, or god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learned man in
holy scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, to whom more knowlege was geuen of GOD, bothe by great studie, and also by
humble praier, made in faith for the same to God the aucthor of all wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and diuine
knowlege, by whiche meanes, the misteries of holy scripture, bee knowen and shewed to man of
God.</p>
   <p>That the spirituall foode of this Epistle to the Collossians should not be hid, but
parte of it made more opē and plain to the
<pb facs="4"/> simple, not learned in the Latin toungue, I as one of the least in learnyng
<hi>(quid em̄ musca cum E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephantis)</hi> haue sette furthe this rude exposiciō in this
Epistle of sainct Paule to the Collossians as it hath pleased God to geue me grace and
knowledge, as I did before in the Epistle of sācte Paule to the Ephesians, and to the
Philippiās, studiyng alway to profite all menne (if I could) and to hurt no man, as knoweth God
the iudge of consciēce, and of all secrete thoughtes: And to excite other better learned then
I, and of more health of body then I haue, to applie their stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die &amp; wit, to set furth in
English some part of holy scripture, that the symple people might be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued more to read
the holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="4"/> and take more profite of theim, then thei doo now by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng onely of the letter, and
not vnderstāding the true meanyng of that thei read, but rather rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to take it amisse,
then after the true sence of the holy ghost: &amp; so by taking y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> scriptures amisse,
commeth greate error and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, euil and preposterous iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemētes, false trustes and
vain hopes, and all for lacke of true knowlege of holy scriptures, as Christe saied to the
Sadduces <hi>Mat. xxii. Erratis, ignorantes scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturas,</hi> you erre, not knowyng the
scriptures: So ignoraunce hath been and yet is, the cause of many errors and heresies, and
that men runne into dampnaciō iudgyng euill good, and good euil, swete soure, and soure
swete
<pb facs="5"/> lighte darkenes, and darkenes light, to whō the Prophete Esai did threate woo
euerlastyng sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng. <hi>Esaie .v.</hi> Woo bee to theim that call good euil, &amp; euill
good lighte darkenes, and darkenes lighte. &amp;c. So ignoraunce is yet y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cause of these
euils, although the Bible bee in Englishe, suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to euery man and woman to reade at their
pleasures, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor GOD, to edifie theimselfes and other with all, ye, commaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to bee
reade euery daie at Matins, Masse, and Euensong, yet there remaineth great igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce,
corrupt iudgementes, blindzeales, not after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of God, and will remayne still (excepte
I bee deceiued) and excepte the holy scriptures bee made more plainer to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lay peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="5"/> vnlearned, by some commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, exposicion, or annotacion, that the laie people
maie vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande the holy scriptures better and knowe the wil and pleasure of GOD, by theim
opened and plainly declared.</p>
   <p>Therefore let ignoraunce the mother of al errors and heresies supersticion and Idolatrie,
bee clerely putte a waie, by knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods holy sacred word truely opened and declared, by
some exposicion made by sobre, sadde and discrete learned men, that of holy scriptures
truly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, nothyng maie bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, but spirituall foode to feede the soule, or elles
I feare greatly, that many will gather poyson for meate, and errors for truth, interpretyng the
holy scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
<pb facs="6"/> after their awne mynde and affecciō, and not accordyng to the mynde of the holy
ghoste, by whom it was written: But now I truste that all ignoraūce Idolatrie, and
supersticion, and blynde zeale, shall fall awaie by litle and litle, the causes of them
take awaie, and the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Gods woorde had, and such Godly Homilies, shewyng so
muche Godly wisedome, and true knowlege of necessary ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities for our saluacion, as was
neuer shewed before our daies, to the people of this realme: for the whiche, glory is to be geuen
to GOD, laude and praise to the kynges Maiestie, and to his mooste prudent and honorable
counsaill, that so tendereth the health and the saluacion of the
<pb facs="6"/> people of this realme, that thei would haue al Idolatrie, super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticion, and
feined religion takē awaie, and Christes true honor and glory set furthe and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that
all men mighte honor and worshippe God truly, with that honor that he would be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored,
appoynted not of manne but of God, in his holy scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res geuen to vs, to knowe God, to loue
God, and to feare God, to know our duetie to God, and to our neighbor, and to do it in deede the
better, accordyng to the will and pleasure of God, to whom with the sonne, and the holy
ghoste be all honor and glory nowe and euer. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>