<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian and courteous Reader.</title>
           <author>Hoard, Sa.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104116_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03409</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13533</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104116</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian and courteous Reader.</title>
                 <author>Hoard, Sa.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Churches authority asserted : in a sermon preached at Chelmsford, at the metropoliticall visitation of the most Reverend Father in God, VVilliam, Lord Arch-bishop of Canterbury his Grace, &amp;c. March 1. 1636. By Samuel Hoard B.D. and Parson of Morton in Essex</title>
                 <author>Hoard, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles</publisher>
                    <distributor>Clarke, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian and courteous Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O Sweet a thing is <hi>Peace,</hi> that God is pleased to put it into his owne <hi>title,</hi> and to style him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Peace:</hi> 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.23. Nay, <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Love it selfe,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.16. and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him that <hi>seekes</hi> and <hi>makes</hi> peace, a <hi>blessed man; Blessed are the Peace-makers, Mat</hi> 5.9. But much more amiable is the peace of the <hi>Church;</hi> being the principall thing that our blessed <hi>Sauiour,</hi> next to mans peace with <hi>God,</hi> came into the world to procure, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.15. and that which makes Gods <hi>family</hi> on earth like to the State of innocency in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise, and of <hi>glory</hi> in heaven. This peace therefore should every <hi>sonne</hi> of <hi>peace</hi> pray for, <hi>Pray for the peace of Jerusalem, Psal.</hi> 112. and pursue with all endeavour possible, as men doe their <hi>game,</hi> for so the word may signifie, <hi>Hob.</hi> 12.16. Follow peace with all men. But what <hi>peace</hi> can be expected without <hi>unity?</hi> like <hi>Hypocrates</hi> twins they decay and thrive, live and die together.</p>
   <p>And therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> puts them both together, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.3. <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace:</hi> and for the procuring of agreement in affections, he conjures the <hi>Philippians</hi> by all the arguments enforcing <hi>concord</hi> among Christians, to a <hi>consent</hi> of judgement, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>To be of one minde, Phil.</hi> 2.2. to beleeve and think the same thing. And therefore it should be every mans care (contrary to the custome of too many <hi>turbulent</hi> dispositions, who can fish best in <hi>troubled</hi> waters, and gaine most <hi>profit</hi> or <hi>respect</hi> to themselves by kindling <hi>contentions</hi> among brethren: not only to <hi>marke them that cause divisions, and avoide them, Rom.</hi> 16.17. but <hi>fix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> pede,</hi> with a s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led resolution and courage to <hi>oppose</hi> them, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did S. <hi>Peter, Gal.</hi> 2. when he saw that he did not <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, <hi>walk with a right foot,</hi> and take a right course for the uniting of the <hi>mindes,</hi> and by consequent, the <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi> As therefore it hath alwayes been my <hi>desire,</hi> that we who are of the same <hi>saith,</hi> might be (if possible) in all things of the same <hi>opinion,</hi> so I thought it my <hi>duty</hi> at this time, having so faire an occasion, by the command of my superiours, to preach the <hi>Visitation</hi> Sermon, put into my hands, to cast in my <hi>mite</hi> toward the purchasing of this <hi>pearle,</hi> and to set one small <hi>prop</hi> under the house and <hi>Church</hi> of God in our Israel, too much <hi>tottering</hi> by our mutuall dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and for that end to <hi>justifie</hi> the <hi>authority</hi> of our Church, in requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="3"/> an <hi>uniforme</hi> subjection in <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>practise</hi> at the hands of her children to the comely and good <hi>orders</hi> therein established, and to <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade</hi> a generall <hi>good opinion</hi> of, and <hi>obedience</hi> to her just authority in these things. Some there be so <hi>obstinate</hi> in their error and undutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, that like <hi>Solomons</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le, though they be brayed in a <hi>morter,</hi> and sufficiently convinced of their false and disorderly opinions and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises, will not leave their folly: others there be, I hope, of more <hi>tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable</hi> and <hi>tractable</hi> tempers, and willing, if better informed, to frame their courses to more <hi>moderation</hi> and subjection. Now, <hi>sermons</hi> of this <hi>nature</hi> may be of use to both these: to the <hi>first,</hi> to take off their <hi>fig-leaves,</hi> and present them naked (as troublers of <hi>Israel</hi>) to the deserved <hi>stroke</hi> of justice: to the rest, to make them <hi>peaceable</hi> members of the <hi>body</hi> wherein they live, and obedient children to the <hi>heads</hi> by whom they are governed. Whether I shall effect this <hi>last</hi> and <hi>best</hi> end of such discourses by preaching or printing this small peece, I know not: I doe not altogether despaire: the <hi>former</hi> (I doubt not) I shall in some measure compasse: at least <hi>liberabo animam meam,</hi> I shall hereby dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge mine owne <hi>conscience,</hi> and <hi>famam meam,</hi> redeeme (in some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) my <hi>reputation</hi> too: Words being then most liable to envious mistakes and mis-reports, when they are but taken in by the <hi>eares</hi> of some few <hi>partiall</hi> and prejudging hearers, not exposed to the <hi>eyes</hi> and <hi>view</hi> of more <hi>indifferent</hi> and charitably minded <hi>Readers.</hi> Bring an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and <hi>peaceable</hi> spirit with thee, and then <hi>reade,</hi> and <hi>censure</hi> as thou seest cause.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Sa: Hoard.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>