<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In Lectores prorsus indignos.</title>
           <author>Udall, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1598</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104629_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07078</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17485</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104629</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In Lectores prorsus indignos.</title>
                 <author>Udall, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The scourge of villanie : Three bookes of satyres</title>
                 <author>Marston, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1598</date>
                 <publisher>Busby, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>124 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>In Lectores prorsus indignos.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>FY Satyre fie, shall each mechanick slaue,</l>
      <l>Each dunghill pesant, free perusall haue</l>
      <l>Of thy well labor'd lines? Shal each sattin sute,</l>
      <l>Each quaint fashiō-monger, whose sole repute</l>
      <l>Rests in his trim gay clothes, lye slauering</l>
      <l>Taynting thy lines with his lewd censuring?</l>
      <l>Shall each odd puisne of the Lawyers Inne,</l>
      <l>Each barmy-froth, that last day did beginne</l>
      <l>To reade his little, or his <hi>nere a whit,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Or shall some greater auncient, of lesse wit,</l>
      <l>(That neuer turnd but browne Tobacco leaues</l>
      <l>Whose sences some damn'd <hi>Occupant</hi> bereaues.</l>
      <l>Lye gnawing on thy vacant times expence?</l>
      <l>Tearing thy rimes, quite altering the sence?</l>
      <l>Or shall perfum'd <hi>Castilio</hi> censure thee?</l>
      <l>Shall he oreview thy sharpe-fang'd poesie?</l>
      <l>(Who nere read farther then his Mistris lips,</l>
      <l>Nere practiz'd ought, but som spruce capring skips</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>Nere in his life did other language vse,</l>
      <l>But, <hi>Sweete Lady, faire Mistres, kind hart, deare couse,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Shall this <hi>Fantasma,</hi> this <hi>Colosse</hi> peruse</l>
      <l>And blast with stinking breath, thy budding Muse?</l>
      <l>Fye, wilt thou make thy wit a Curtezan</l>
      <l>For euery broking hand-crafts artizan?</l>
      <l>Shall brainles Cyterne heads, each iubernole,</l>
      <l>Poket the very <hi>Genius</hi> of thy soule?</l>
      <l>I <hi>Phylo,</hi> I, I'le keepe an open hall,</l>
      <l>A common, and a sumptuous festiuall,</l>
      <l>Welcome all eyes, all eares, all tongues to me,</l>
      <l>Gnaw pesants on my scraps of poesie.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Castilios, Cyprians,</hi> court-boyes, spanish blocks,</l>
      <l>Ribanded eares, granado-netherstocks,</l>
      <l>Fidles, Scriueners, pedlers, tynkering knaues,</l>
      <l>Base blew-coats, tapsters, brod-cloth minded slaues,</l>
      <l>Welcome I-fayth, but may you nere depart,</l>
      <l>Till I haue made your gauled hides to smart.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="4"/>Your gauled hides? avaunt base muddy scum.</l>
      <l>Thinke you a Satyres dreadfull sounding drum</l>
      <l>Will brace it selfe? and daine to terrefie,</l>
      <l>Such abiect pesants basest rogary?</l>
      <l>No, no, passe on ye vaine fantasticke troupe</l>
      <l>Of puffie youthes; Know I doe scorne to stoupe</l>
      <l>To rip your liues. Then hence lewd nags, away,</l>
      <l>Goe read each post, view what is plaid to day.</l>
      <l>Then to <hi>Priapus</hi> gardens. You <hi>Castilio,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>I pray thee let my lines in freedome goe,</l>
      <l>Let me alone, the Madams call for thee</l>
      <l>Longing to laugh at thy wits pouertie.</l>
      <l>Sirra, liuorie cloake, you lazie slipper slaue,</l>
      <l>Thou fawning drudge, what would'st thou Satyres haue?</l>
      <l>Base mind away, thy master calls, begon,</l>
      <l>Sweet <hi>Gnato</hi> let my poesie alone.</l>
      <l>Goe buy some ballad of the Faiery King,</l>
      <l>And of the begger wench, some rogie thing</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>Which thou maist chaunt vnto the chamber-maid</l>
      <l>To some vile tune, when that thy Maister's laid.</l>
      <l>But will you needs stay? am I forc'd to beare,</l>
      <l>The blasting breath of each lewd Censurer?</l>
      <l>Must naught but clothes, and images of men</l>
      <l>But sprightles truncks, be Iudges of thy pen?</l>
      <l>Nay then come all, I prostitute my Muse,</l>
      <l>For all the swarme of Idiots to abuse.</l>
      <l>Reade all, view all, euen with my full consent,</l>
      <l>So you will know that which I neuer meant;</l>
      <l>So you will nere conceiue, and yet dispraise,</l>
      <l>That which you nere conceiu'd, &amp; laughter raise:</l>
      <l>Where I but striue in honest seriousnes,</l>
      <l>To scourge some soule-poluting beastlines.</l>
      <l>So you will raile, and finde huge errors lurke</l>
      <l>In euery corner of my Cynick worke.</l>
      <l>Proface, reade on, for your extreamst dislikes</l>
      <l>Will add a pineon, to my praises flights.</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="5"/>O, how I bristle vp my plumes of pride,</l>
      <l>O, how I thinke my Satyres dignifi'd,</l>
      <l>When I once heare some quaint <hi>Castilio,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Some supple mouth'd slaue some lewd <hi>Tubrio,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Some spruce pedant, or some span-new come fry</l>
      <l>Of Innes a-court, striuing to vilefie</l>
      <l>My darke reproofes. Then doe but raile at me,</l>
      <l>No greater honor craues my poesie.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg n="1">
      <head>1.</head>
      <l>But yee diuiner wits, celestiall soules,</l>
      <l>Whose free-borne mindes no kennel thought contoules,</l>
      <l>Ye sacred spirits, <hi>Mayas</hi> eldest sonnes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg n="2">
      <head>2.</head>
      <l>Yee substance of the shadowes of our age,</l>
      <l>In whom all graces linke in marriage,</l>
      <l>To you how cheerfully my poeme runnes.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg n="3">
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <head>3.</head>
      <l>True iudging eyes, quick sighted censurers,</l>
      <l>Heauens best beauties, wisedoms treasurers,</l>
      <l>O how my loue embraceth your great worth.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg n="4">
      <head>4.</head>
      <l>Yee Idols of my soule, yee blessed spirits,</l>
      <l>How shold I giue true honor to your merrits,</l>
      <l>Which I can better thinke, then here paint forth.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>You sacred spirits, <hi>Maias</hi> eldest sonnes,</l>
      <l>To you how cheerfully my poeme runnes.</l>
      <l>O how my loue, embraceth your great worth,</l>
      <l>Which I can better think, then here paint forth.</l>
      <l>O rare!</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>