<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHTE HONORABLE AND HIS SINGVLER GOOD LORDE, THE Lorde Roberte Dudley, Erle of Leycester, Bar∣ron of Denbighe, Knight of the honorable order of the Garter, Maister of the Queenes ma∣iesties horses, and one of her highnes pryuie councell. Thomas Blundeuil wissheth perfect felicitie.</title>
           <author>Blundeville, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104611_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16229</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3152</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104611</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHTE HONORABLE AND HIS SINGVLER GOOD LORDE, THE Lorde Roberte Dudley, Erle of Leycester, Bar∣ron of Denbighe, Knight of the honorable order of the Garter, Maister of the Queenes ma∣iesties horses, and one of her highnes pryuie councell. Thomas Blundeuil wissheth perfect felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Blundeville, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fower chiefyst offices belongyng to horsemanshippe : that is to saye. The office of the breeder, of the rider, of the keper, and of the ferrer. In the firste parte wherof is declared the order of breding of horses. In the seconde howe to breake them, and to make theym horses of seruyce, conteyninge the whole arte of ridynge lately set forth, and nowe newly corrected and amended of manye faultes escaped in the fyrste printynge, as well touchyng the bittes as other wyse. Thirdely howe to dyet them, aswell when they reste as when they trauell by the way. Fourthly to what diseases they be subiecte, together with the causes of such diseases, the sygnes howe to knowe them, and finally howe to cure the same. Whyche bookes are not onely paynfully collected out of a nomber of aucthours, but also orderly dysposed and applyed to the vse of thys oure cou [n] trey. By Tho. Blundeuill of Newton Flotman in Norff</title>
                 <author>Blundeville, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 <publisher>Seres, William 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 33, 9, 79, 26, 4, 32, 4, 120, 120-123, 14 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHTE HONORABLE AND HIS SINGVLER GOOD LORDE, THE Lorde Roberte Dudley, Erle of Leycester, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of Denbighe, Knight of the honorable order of the Garter, Maister of the Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties horses, and one of her highnes pryuie councell. Thomas Blundeuil wissheth perfect felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>FTER THAT</hi> I had put foorthe the Arte of Riding, and sawe how thāk<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully it pleased not only your Honoure, but also the moste part of the Ientlemē of this Realme, to accept the same: I was so muche encoraged therby as I sought to make the saide boke more periecte, by addinge therevnto three other bookes, wherof the first should treate of the bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of Horses, the seconde of their dyet, to preserue them longe in healthe, and the thirde of their diseases: declarynge therewithall the causes, sygnes, and cures of the same, whiche bokes how necessarye they be, and how meete they are to accompany the Arte of Riding, the matter it selfe (being well handled) would euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shewe. For then it should be a perfecte worke, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the foure chiefyst Offices belonging to Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manshyppe, that is to say: The office of the Breeder, of the Ryder or Breaker, of the Keeper, and of the Ferrer. For as towchinge the Bitmaker &amp; Saddler their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the first is indifferently wel declared alredy in the
<pb facs="3"/>
Arte of Riding: &amp; the Sadler his office, shalbe taught herafter in another litle boke of additions, which I en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tende God wyllynge to ioyne to this volume, briefelye cōprehendyng all the good preceptes of a later Writer, nowe being your Honors most excellente Ryder, called maister <hi>Claudio Corte</hi>: Not onely touching that office, but also touchynge diuerse of the other Offices before recited. Whiche Booke shall supply to all the wants of suche necessarye thynges, as eyther Gryson in his boke or I perhappes haue neclygently omytted. And truely, your Honour deserueth no litle prayse, for procuryng so synguler a man into this Realme: For besydes his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in riding, he is so wel learned, wyse, courteouse, and modest withall, as his acquaintaunce, company, &amp; frendship ought to be right deare vnto al ciuill Ientle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and specially to those that delyght in Horseman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyppe. But now to retourne vnto my purpose, for that I sawe it lay not in me to perfourme this worke, so as it might answere euery mans expectacion, and special<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of such as are more readie to finde faultes, then to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende them, I did almost repent me of mine enterprise and good desire: and the rather, for that I had no one certayne Author to followe, that eyther wrote of these matters to the full, or in suche order as did satisfye my minde, but should be driuen to deale w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a great nombre of Authors, whose sayinges and experiences, together with mine owne small knowledge gotten by traueling in forreine countreies: I must not onely orderly dispose: but also apply the same to the vse of this our countrey. Which thing being more laborious (thē some perhaps take it,) I had cleane geuen it ouer if your good Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp had not ben, by whom I was so much harted, as
<pb facs="3"/>
I could not chose but to take the same in hand, and to go thoroughe withall so well as I coulde: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any man receyueth any commodity therby (as I doubte not but he shall, if he wyll vouchsafe to rede al that I haue wrytten frō the beginning to the ending) he shall haue most cause to be thankefull to youre Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for the same. And I beleeue your thankes and prayse shoulde be so muche the more, if it would please your Honour to be a meane that the Quenes highnes may not onely cause such statutes as were made in her noble Father and deare Brothers time, (bothe of good Memory) touchyng the breedinge of horses vpon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to be put in executiō: but also that all such parkes within this realme, as be in her highnesse handes, and mete for that purpose, might not wholly be imployed to the keping of Dere, (which is altogether a pleasure without profyt) but partly to the necessary breeding of Horses for seruice, wherof, this realme of all others at this instant hath greatest nede. The lacke of whiche, if any inuasion shuld chaunce (which God defend) wold quickly appere (I feare me) to the great perill &amp; danger of this her highnes realme. And her Maiestye geuyng this good example, I doubt not but that the most part of the noble men and Ientlemen of this realm hauing parks or groūds impaled mete for such vse: wold folow the same. And to the intēt that no couetousnes might hinder so good an act: I wold wish the couetous mind &amp; desyre of all men to be brideled by a lawe &amp; discipline. Wherby it wold be prouided that not onely a sufficiēt nombre of able Horses maye be bred within this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme: but also that the same horses may be broken, kept mainteyned, and exercysed accordyngly. <hi>Monsieur de l'
<pb facs="4"/>
Angeay</hi> in his boke of war, wold haue no man to keepe a hackney or easye horse to ride on him selfe: vnlesse he kepte also a horse mete for seruice in the fielde. Whiche thing I feare me wold not please vs English men at al, which of late daies are more geuen to priuat ease &amp; sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler cōmoditie, then to a welth publique or cōmon pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite. Notwithstanding, if a good law (as I said before) were made aswel for the breding, as exercising of great horses, and Gueldinges meete for seruice: and the same straightly executed by vncorrupted officers, whiche in mine opinion wold be skylful Surueiours for the bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and expert muster masters for the horses of seruice. And also that such Surueies be made twise a yeare at the least, and that the Musters of the horses of seruice be taken throughout the whole realme foure times in a yere, that is to say quarterly, and al in one day, for the auoyding of false Musters: I beleue that in short space we shold not only haue plenty of good horses, but also that the Ientlemen of this realme would so farre passe the Frenchmen and al other nations in this exercise, as they now excel vs: wherby this realme shuld be of such force, as our enemies would alwayes be afrayde to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any enterprise against vs. Wherfore me thinkes your honour cānot by any one way deserue more praise or better gratify al true English hartes, then by seking to bryng to passe so nedeful a thing as this is: whervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to because I know your Lordshyp to be of your owne good nature &amp; disposicion so redy and prone, as no man more: I leaue therfore to trouble your Honour any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, prayenge God long to prosper the same.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>AlWayes prest to serue your Lordship. Th. Blundouill.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>