<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104167_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08444</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18766</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104167</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Certayne sermons of the ryghte famous and excellente clerk master Barnardine Ochine, borne within the famous vniuersitie of Siena in Italy, now also an exyle in thys lyfe, for the faithful testimony of Iesus Christe. Faythfully translated into Englyshe</title>
                 <author>Ochino, Bernardino</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>208 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho wel considereth where vnto we are created (good Christen Reader) shall find that of al our trauailes ther resteth no fruite, as proueth the holy spirite of prophecy by the mouthe of Salomon sayinge. I haue looked vpon al the thynges vnder the sunne, and haue founde none other but vanity. Onely reserued the Image of God in vs, beyng the spirit that sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth not the natural lyfe alone, but also al the holy and vertuous thoughts, which God hath created immortal vnto his own likenes, as thou maiest wel par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue, if thou consider the substaunce of the natural body, that hauyng the spirit is al liuely, &amp; not only moueth ech finger hand, foote, eye &amp; toung materially, but also wyth the thoughte penetrateth the heauens, and in maner conceiueth a sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stance in the immortality of Gods euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lastyng kyngdom, and wanting the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, resteth dead priuate of al those ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, though wel thou shalt se that it lac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth nether hand, foote, eye, tunge nor other member. Thys I saye vnto thee (gentle reader) to the entent that thou shouldest know that the almyghty crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour is serued not of vanities, that is to
<pb facs="3"/> say, of bodely or worldlye exercises, but of spirituall thoughtes, whyche are the iuste and true sacrifyces vnto God. And therby to draw the to remember the mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaile of hys workes, and to thinke more vnto thine end thē to thy life. Disposing thy selfe to learne the sciences that this lytle boke shal teach the, which treateth of none other but of the spiritual thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and beareth in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> the substaunce of the holy scripture wyth so vehemēt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and so good perswacions, that it suffiseth to draw frō the thy stony hart, and to reneu in the a carnal hart, if thou be one of them, to whom God hath deter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mined to gyue hys grace. One of thē (I say) y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> wyth lyuely fayth confesse Christ the son of god, to haue suffered for their synnes. As the Authour hereof sufficiēt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perswadeth the, who (being a man of great yeares, and wonderful reputaciō) for the loue of Christe and of the truthe, hath rather chosen exyle and persecuci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then contynuaunce of wealthe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and frendshyp. A man of profoūd learnyng. The most notable preacher of al Itali. Famous for the great example of hys good lyfe. Estemed and honored of all Princes, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>or hys age onely (be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng a man of .lxx. yeares, or therabouts)
<pb facs="3"/> but also for hys infinite vertues and mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>desty. And fynally so beloued of al peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that in what place so euer he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, ther hath euer bene founde greate prease of audyence. All thys notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standyng at length<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>because he syncere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly folowed the true Gospel, and did not forbeare to reprehend the publyke abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the Romish church) he was perse<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuted of Paul the thyrde, and constray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to forsake Italy, &amp; to flee into Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani. Wher he hath not ceased with his penne to folow the vertuous exhortacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, that before tyme wyth hys mouthe he preached. And now God of his merci hath brought hym hither vnto vs, &amp; prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth in the Italyan toung, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yche all men vnderstand not, I haue translated v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. of hys Sermons out of hys toung in to Englysh. Intending to translate the rest very shortely if these shal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e thanke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully receiued) to the entent that hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyue toung therby may be ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e oures: and that the glory of God may the better be set forth. Vnto whō al honour is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue worlde wythout end.</p>
   <closer>So be it.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>