<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right Honorable and vertuous Lady, the Lady
Sheffeeld, N. B. wisheth conti∣nuall health, with encrease of
Honour.</title>
           <author>B., N.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104710_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16791</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3695</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104710</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right Honorable and vertuous Lady, the Lady
Sheffeeld, N. B. wisheth conti∣nuall health, with encrease of
Honour.</title>
                 <author>B., N.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A smale handfull of fragrant flowers : selected and gathered out of the louely garden of sacred scriptures, fit for any honorable or woorshipfull gentlewoman to smell vnto. Dedicated for a Newe-yeeres gyft, to the honorable and vertuous lady, the Lady Sheffeeld. By N.B</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the right Honorable and vertuous Lady, the Lady
<hi>Sheffeeld, N. B.</hi> wisheth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall health, with encrease of
Honour.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I must of necessitie</hi> (<hi>right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> and
vertuous Lady) geue leaue, licence and libertie vnto such as altogeather search
out the straunge operations of thinges wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh incredible to the rude and
ignorant sort: So reposing a confidence in your noble degree, redy prest to
accept the simple gift of a yong and vnskilful hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, I am the more bolde
to present your Ladyship with this litle <hi>handful of Flowers,</hi> the sent
wherof I trust, being gathered in so fruitful a time, wil so reuiue your
senses, that your godly industrie wil vouchsafe to plant the roote therof in
the <hi>Gardē of nobilitie,</hi> which I am assured, being watered with the
due vnderstāding of the founten of knowledge, cannot chuse but encrese to a
defens<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> modest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor. As therfore on
th'other side, your vertuous life is such as rather alloweth the godly worke of
a simple scholler, willing by dayly practise to grow vnto more &amp; exacter
ripenes of vnderstā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. And on the other part is redy to prefer the base
&amp; coūtrey mās pen, to the end that I m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ght hereafter take the more hart of grace, to attempt a more
substantial peece of worke. And then if it shal please the almighty to be my
guide, in future time I wil not be forgetfull of your Honors clemencie, which
the almighty G<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d garde and furnish plentifully
with increase &amp; mayntenance of renowne for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your most humble to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde</hi> N.
 B.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>