<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶THE PROHEME OF the historie of Herodian, trea∣ting of the Romayne Em∣perours, after Marcus.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1556</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104002_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A03094</idno>
           <idno type="STC">13221</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104002</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶THE PROHEME OF the historie of Herodian, trea∣ting of the Romayne Em∣perours, after Marcus.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The history of Herodian, a Greeke authour : treating of the Romayne emperors, after Marcus, translated oute of Greeke into Latin, by Angelus Politianus, and out of Latin into Englyshe, by Nicholas Smyth. Whereunto are annexed, the argumentes of euery booke, at the begynnyng thereof, with annotacions for the better vnderstandynge of the same historye</title>
                 <author>Herodian</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Copland, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1556</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, xlvii, xlvii-lxxxv, lxxxv-lxxxvii, 1, lxxxviii-lxxxix, c-cvi, 17 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="proem">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶THE PROHEME OF the historie of Herodian, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Romayne Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, after Marcus.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey whiche haue delyuered vnto theyr posteritie auncient tradici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and endeuored to renewe by writyng the olde memorye of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stories: They I saye, earnestly affecting the renowne of erudici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and learning: and busyly stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyeng to preserue theyr names from thiniurie of obliuion, did employ moche lesse laboure in searching oute the truthe, then in trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge the style of their Histories. Knowinge pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisely, that althoughe they falsefyed any thing longe before theyr time passed, the same coulde not be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendid, and yet neuertheles them selfes shold (through the pleasaunt eloquence, of their finely penned talke) obtayne very muche commoditie, of their paynefull trauayle. Other some beyng moued, with perticuler enmityes and hatred of Tyrauntes, or elles fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vnmeasurable flaterye, with praysyng of Princes, Cyties, &amp; priuate persons, dyd through skylfull know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of wryting, blase and extoll farre aboue truthe, thinges that by them selues were symple &amp; of no esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion. But I in contrarie wyse, haue enterprysed to wryte an historye, not receyued of others, vnkno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, or elles wanting witnesses, but at this present, fixed and remaining in the memories of the Readers, and collected with synguler trueth and diligence. Trustyng, that the knowledge of those thinges, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many and great, and not longe agone happened) wyll not be vnpleasaunt to the posterite. For yf a mā wyll well ponder al the ages synce the time of Augus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, (when the Romayne superioritie was commyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the arbitrement of one man) he shall not fynde in all those .ii.c. yeres (so many almost perdy are recke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="4"/>
betwene Augustus, and Marcus) so diuers suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessions in thempire, so variable chaunces and happes in the warres either Ciuyle or foreyn, so manie naci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons raised vp, or so many of our owne and barbarous Cities destroyed, besides earthquakes and plagues, the liues also of Princes, and Tiraunts so straunge and incredible, that none or at the lest verie few like examples can be founde amongs our elders. Of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che princes, some of longe tyme remayned in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, other some a shorte while enioyed the dominion yea many of them scarcelie entered into honour, and being onlie named Emperours, lost thempire the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie same daye they tooke it vpon them. And when by the space of .lx. yeres, the Citie of Rome had sustained more gouernours then for the time sufficed, it came to passe, that many straunge thinges and worthy admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion chaunced. For the Princes somewhat striken in age, as men expert in sundry affayres, did pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently gouerne themselues and their charge. On thother side the yonge men ledinge their liues in voluptuousnes, inuented and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded new thinges dayly. wherbie it happened, that the yonge princes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of vnlike age and licence, did also folow vnlike studie &amp; maners. How these thinges were done, in obser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinge a iust order of the trew tyme and prynces, we will now declare.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>