<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull Edmund Arscot, Esquire, High Sheriffe of the County of De∣von, Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplied.</title>
           <author>Pecke, Richard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1632</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104988_Fr2_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A73009</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19522.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104988</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣shipfull Edmund Arscot, Esquire, High Sheriffe of the County of De∣von, Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplied.</title>
                 <author>Pecke, Richard</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo sermons delivered at St. Peters in Exeter. By Rychard Peck, Master of Arts, and minister of Gods word, at Columpton in Devon</title>
                 <author>Pecke, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1632</date>
                 <publisher>Harper, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ritherdon, Ambrose</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 38, 4, 35, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull <hi>Edmund Arscot,</hi> Esquire, High Sheriffe of the County of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>von,</hi> Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplied.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right VVorshipfull,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T befell this Sermon in its deliuery, what some pregnant <hi>animals</hi> doth sometime in <hi>theirs</hi> Times orifice was so strait, affaires of publique Iudicature, like impatient Midwiues, so violent to haue all soone out, that limbs not a few were left behind. This after birth (extorted by friends importunity) hath brought out all, and presents you the whole <hi>Foetus</hi> with its intended inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grals, though weake I confesse, and very feeble. My humblest intreaty now is but the hire of a roome or two vnder the roofe of your Affections
<pb facs="4"/>
for shelter a little, or if I may presume it) edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Perhaps (so the Lord giue life and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to it) it may become, if no instrument of much good abroad, yet (like King <hi>Philips</hi> Seruitour with his dead-mans skull) as a domestique Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitor to serue in daily to your thoughts some <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> or timely watchword for preparation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the great Iudge his comming. Wee are all too apt by Satans guiles, the deceits of sinne, and bewitching cares and profits of this life, as by some <hi>Mercuries</hi> pipe, <hi>Argos-</hi>like to bee sung asleepe, and so like foolish Virgins out-sleeping seasons of getting oyle in our lamps, to bee cast behinde hand: How seasonable then some thorn at securities breast to keep it waking, that when the Iudge appeares, our lamps bee trimm'd, our loynes girt vp, our lights burning. Worthy Sir, if this Infant-attempt may proue auayl-some to such an end, either on your owne or any others soule, take it, tis yours, vse it. Here will bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for me. My Master shall haue glory, you boldnesse in the day of the Lord Iesus.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships very obseruant Chaplayn,
Rychard Peck.</signed>
      <dateline>Columpton <date>April 30. 1632.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>