<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument of the thyrde Booke, of the treasure for Trauailers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104686_Fr3_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16518</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3432</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104686</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument of the thyrde Booke, of the treasure for Trauailers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A booke called the treasure for traueilers : deuided into fiue bookes or partes, contaynyng very necessary matters, for all sortes of trauailers, eyther by sea or by lande, written by William Bourne</title>
                 <author>Bourne, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 32, 1, 25, 1, 22, 2, 21, 3, 5-16, 4 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Science and mathematics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <div type="argument">
      <pb n="1" facs="72"/>
      <head>The Argument of the thyrde Booke, of the treasure for Trauailers.</head>
      <p>¶The thirde Booke of the Treasure for Trauailers, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning some matters for the measuring of superfycialles, as Lande, Borde, Pauement, or Glasse, and also some matters as touching Solled bodyes, as Tymber, Stone, or such otherlyke: and also howe to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Tonnage, burthen, or bygnesse of shippes, and to keepe that moulde and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther necessary thinges belonging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. &amp;c. Being very necessary for all sortes of people that trauaile eyther by Sea or Land, written by <hi>William Bourne.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="to_the_reader">
      <pb facs="73"/>
      <head>To the Reader of this third Booke.</head>
      <p>GEntle Reader, although Maister Leonard Dygges in hys Booke called Tictonicon, and also Maister Thomas Dygges his Sonne in another Booke, called Pantometry, hath shewed how for to measure al Superfycialles, as Land, Borde, Glasse, Pauement or any such other lyke, &amp; also how to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure al maner of Solled bodies, as Timber, Stone, &amp; such other lyke, yet notwithstandyng I haue written in this third Booke, a lyttle briefe note as touching those causes, and also how to buylde shippes for to make them of what tonnage or bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then that you lyst, and to keepe any forme in the mould or proportion that you lyste, whereby that any Mechanicall workemen by following the order in the Booke prescribed, may make any shippe the one lyke the other, and to make them of what bygnesse or smalnesse he lyst, and to keepe that forme and fashion in an poyntes, both in the moulde that is vnder the water, and also in the fashion aloft, aboue the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And also there is conteyned in this third part, howe for to know the bygnesse of Ropes, whether that it be as byg agayne, or three tymes so bygge more or lesse, at your discretion, which in my opinion is very neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to be knowne, both vnto Naupegers or shippe Carpenters, and also vnto all sortes of Sea men: and also there is other necessarie matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in this third Booke.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>