<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THAT HONO∣RABLE GENTLEMAN, Mr. IOHN ROBARTS, Sonne to my Lord Robarts, Baron of Truro in Cornwall, the accomplishment of all true happinesse both in Grace and Glory, &amp;c.</title>
           <author>Austin, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S104457_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23268</idno>
           <idno type="STC">971</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S104457</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THAT HONO∣RABLE GENTLEMAN, Mr. IOHN ROBARTS, Sonne to my Lord Robarts, Baron of Truro in Cornwall, the accomplishment of all true happinesse both in Grace and Glory, &amp;c.</title>
                 <author>Austin, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Avstins Vrania, or, The heavenly mvse : in a poem fvll of most feeling meditations for the comfort of all soules, at all times: by S.A. B. of Arts of Ex. Colledge in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Austin, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, Felix</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 <distributor>Allott, Robert</distributor>
                            <distributor>Seile (Seale, Seely, Seyle), Henry</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>22, 136 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="42"/>
   <pb facs="42"/>
   <head>TO THAT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE GENTLEMAN, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. IOHN ROBARTS, Sonne to my Lord <hi>Robarts,</hi> Baron of <hi>Truro</hi> in Cornwall, the accomplishment of all true happinesse both in Grace and Glory, &amp;c.</head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Noble Sir!</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue here emboldned my selfe to intreate you also (since you came hither so seasonably) to be the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond God-father of these my low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceptions: and my hopes are, that you will bee the easier wonne hereto, because you haue so good a Compartner, as (my great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourer) your diuine Tutor. Neither is this all, but I had many other most vrgent incitements, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward these my lawfull presumings: first, in that it was my happines to be your Countryman; whence I thought it no meane disparagement, both to my selfe and Country, especially to your Honour; that our Cornwalls Muses should not finde a Patron within their owne limits. Secondly, your happy growth in all vertuous perfections within these late yeeres, (as my selfe also amongst others haue seriously obseru'd, to the great comfort of my soule) with your extraordinary zeale, and primarie deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to all diuine exercises, hath been inough to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite,
<pb facs="43"/>
if not enforce mee, to the humble presentment of these my desires, and vtmost seruices to forward you. If my Muse had here play'd the wanton, I should haue thought her too toyish, and altogether vnworthy your more serious, and iudicious aspect: but shee has been somewhat affected with those passions, that were sometimes yours; shee hath been bath'd in the teares of a deare mothers death; but especially, she hath desir'd to bee in all things heauenly, and to please you euen in diuine contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations; and therefore cannot despaire of your good patronage. I will no longer stand in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, either on your vertues, or mine owne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauourings; only I shall intreate you to know, that there is none more sincerely desires your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in goodnesse then my selfe, though haply you may haue many far better furtherers: and in confirmation of this, I haue heere humbly presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you this deare (though poore) conception of mine, who, like a weeping infant, new brought into the world, beseeches you with teares for its Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage; which if you but please to blesse it with, and so make it liue famous in the world by being yours, you shall not faile of his continuing prayers and thankfulnesse; who desires to be euer</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your true seruant in the Lord Iesus, <hi>Samuel Austin.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my Study in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Colledge in Oxford,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>this</hi> 11. <hi>of Aprill,</hi> 1628.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>