<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ERRATA.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1613</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105599_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01202</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11316.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105599</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ERRATA.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An introduction to a deuoute life : composed in Frenche by the R. Father in God Francis Sales, Bishop of Geneua. And translated into Englisg [sic], by I.Y</title>
                 <author>Francis, de Sales, Saint</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Patte, Gerard</publisher>
                    <distributor>Heigham, John (Roger)</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>France--Douai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1613</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>487, 1, 135, 11 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Errata</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="errata">
   <head>THE ERRATA.</head>
   <p>Pag. 14 line 13. Picaustes, reade, Piraustes. p 17. l. 24. many soules, reade, of many soules. p. 37. l. 23. of riches, reade, of the rich. p. 39. l. 26. foules, reade, soules. p. 68. l. 3. were created, reade, we were created. p. 91 l. 17. infinitle, reade, infinite, p 91, l. 19 Certefie, reade, Terrefie. p. 95. l. 11. pight, reade, right. p. 120 l. 18. of, reade, or. p. 135 l. 22. forces, reade, species. p. 139. l. 2. thy, reade, the. p. 141. l. 20. of, reade, or. p. 172. l. 12. this, reade, his. p. 191. l. 22. Consiliat, reade, Conflict. p. 235. l. 19. perfections, reade, thinges. p. 277. l. 20. king, reade, kinde. p. 337. l. 12. and, reade, it. &amp; l. 13. it, and. p. 344. trade, reade, trace. p. 365. l. 22. cordes, reade, the cordes. l. 376. l. 16. back, reade, lack. p 377. l. 4. turne, reade, tame. p. 405. l. 26. word, reade, world. p. 21. l. 6. part the fourth, fore, reade, fire.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>If there be any other faultes escaped, I pray the gētle reader of his curtesie to correct them.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>