<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right excellent, and most honorable
Ladie, the Ladie Marie, Countesse
of Pembroke.</title>
           <author>Fraunce, Abraham</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105635_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01227</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11340</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105635</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right excellent, and most honorable
Ladie, the Ladie Marie, Countesse
of Pembroke.</title>
                 <author>Fraunce, Abraham</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Countesse of Pembrokes Yuychurch : Conteining the affectionate life, and vnfortunate death of Phillis and Amyntas: that in a pastorall; this in a funerall; both in English hexameters. By Abraham Fraunce</title>
                 <author>Fraunce, Abraham</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Ponsonby, William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right excellent, and most honorable
Ladie, the Ladie Marie, Countesse
of Pembroke.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F <hi>Amyntas</hi> found fauour in your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
eyes, let <hi>Phillis</hi> bee accepted for
<hi>Amyntas</hi> sake. I haue somewhat al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<hi>S. Tassoes</hi> Italian, &amp; M. <hi>vvat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi>
Latine <hi>Amyntas,</hi> to make them
both one English. But <hi>Tassoes</hi> is Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall,
therefore this verse vnvsual: yet it is also Pastoral,
and in effect nothing els but a continuation of <hi>aeglogues,</hi>
therefore no verse fitter than this. For such as generally mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slike
this reformed kinde of verse, as I spake before, so
I say stil, I neuer heard better argument of them than this;
Such an one hath doone but ill, therefore no man can doo wel:
which reason is much like their owne rymes, in condemning
the arte, for the fault of some artificers. For others, that like
well of the thing, but not of my peculier labour herein,
mine aunswere is the same it was: if there were anie penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
appointed for him that would not read, hee might well
complaine of mee that publish it to bee read: But if it bee in
euerie mans choyce to reade it, or not to reade; why then not
in mine also to publish or not to publish it? Hee that will,
let him see and reade; hee that will neither reade nor see, is
<pb facs="3"/>
neither bound to see nor reade. If anie begin to reade, when
hee beginneth to take no delight, let him leaue off, and go no
further. If he folowe on in reading without pleasure, let
him neither blame mee, that did what I could; nor bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie
with the thing, which hath no sense; but reprehend him
selfe, who would continue in reading, without anie plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
taking.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours
<hi>most affectionate,</hi>
Abraham Fraunce.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>