<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In praise of the Author.</title>
           <author>Percy, Ed.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105886_Fr1_3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02073</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12216</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105886</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In praise of the Author.</title>
                 <author>Percy, Ed.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Alcida : Greenes metamorphosis, vvherein is discouered, a pleasant transformation of bodies into sundrie shapes, shewing that as vertues beautifie the mind, so vanities giue greater staines, than the perfection of any quality can rase out: the discourse confirmed with diuers merry and delightfull histories; full of graue principles to content age, and sawsed with pleasant parlees, and witty answeres, to satisfie youth: profitable for both, and not offensiue to any. By R.G</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Pindley, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <head>In praise of the Author.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>THe busie Bee, that riseth with the Sunne,</l>
      <l>Hies forth her hiue, to end her daily taske:</l>
      <l>With weary wings she plies into the fields,</l>
      <l>And Natures secrets searcheth by her skill,</l>
      <l>From flower to flower her carefull way doth flie:</l>
      <l>To sucke her hony from her natiue sweet;</l>
      <l>Loden, she rich bestirres her to her home,</l>
      <l>And there she workes and tilles within her hiue:</l>
      <l>Not for her selfe thus busily she romes,</l>
      <l>But for vs men, that feed vpon her combes.</l>
      <l>So GREENE hath sought into the depth of Art,</l>
      <l>With weary labours toyling at his bookes</l>
      <l>For fruits, such as the learned Authors yeeld;</l>
      <l>Searching the secrets that their wits haue pen'd,</l>
      <l>Tossing amongst their learned principles</l>
      <l>Their Rhethoricke and deepe Phylosophy:</l>
      <l>Gathering the sweet that euery Science giues,</l>
      <l>To carry pleasant hony to his hiue.</l>
      <l>Not for himselfe alone the Author lookes,</l>
      <l>But for such men as daigne to read his bookes.</l>
   </lg>
   <q>Sic vos non vobis melli ficatis apes.</q>
   <closer>
      <signed>Ed. Percy.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>