<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface.</title>
           <author>Robinson, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1614</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105158_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10843</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21115</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105158</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface.</title>
                 <author>Robinson, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of religious communion private, &amp; publique : With the silenceing of the clamours raysed by Mr Thomas Helvvisse agaynst our reteyning the baptism receaved in Engl: &amp; administering of Bapt: vnto infants. As also a survey of the confession of fayth published in certayn conclusions by the remaynders of Mr Smithes company. ... By Iohn Robinson</title>
                 <author>Robinson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Marsce (Maersche), Joris Abrahamsz van der</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1614</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 131, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Preface.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here passed out, some while since, a defamatory libell vnder
the names of <hi>Charles Lawn,</hi> &amp; three other his <hi>brethren
in evill;</hi> but certainly penned by some other persons, whose
greater knowledg did arm their cruell hatred the more to
hurt: makeing them fathers of that <hi>generation, whose
teeth are as swordes, &amp; their iawteeth as knives to</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prov. 30. 14▪</note>
      <hi>devour the afflicted from of the earth, &amp; the pore
from among men.</hi> Agaynst whom, &amp; whose freinds
durst I vse the same liberty, in publishing to the world their
personall corruptions, which I know, &amp; could soon learn by
the testimony of honester men, then these informers, they who have written of others,
what hath pleased them, should read that which would not please them, of their own,
if not of themselves. But God forbid. My desire is rather to pacify, then further to
alienate affections: remembring Christs instruction vnto his Disciples, to <hi>blesse those</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 44.</note>
      <hi>that curse them: to do good to those that harm them: &amp; to pray for those
that persequute them.</hi> Besides, in following their course, I should for the faults of a
few corrupter persons, wrong the credits of many honest, &amp; innocent men: for whose sakes
I would rayther cover the others faylings, then for them, blemish the credit of the rest.
But herein speciall respect is to be had to the common truthes of the Lord Iesus by them
&amp; vs, acknowledged: vppon the honour whereof had they been but half so bent, as vppon
our disgrace, they would not thus have gratifyed the common adversaryes thereof, even
theirs, &amp; ours: &amp; with them, the Atheists &amp; Epicures in the land; by whom their
book is most affected: blessing themselves in their professed contempt of God, &amp; of all
religion, by the faylings of those (whether truely, or falsely suggested, they regarde not)
who professe his more speciall fear, &amp; service: &amp; concludeing, that all others are as ill
as themselves, though more covertly. It is the spiders disposition, so she may entangle the
silly flyes in her web, to weav out her own bowels.</p>
   <p>This libell it hath pleased divers persons of note for learning, &amp; Zeal, to countenance
with their wryteings of divers kyndes. Amongst the rest, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> W: Ames, fearing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
lest eyther it should want credit, or I discredit by the accusations in it against the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
of other men in other Churches (which though they were all true, as I know some of
them to be wholy false, &amp; others impudently published by such as were themselves cheif
agents in them, yet did no more concern me, &amp; the Church with me, then did the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
in the Ch: of Corinth, the Ch: at Rome; or those in some of the 7 Churches in Asia,
the rest, which were free from them) hath published to the world, in the body of that
book, without my consent, privity, or least suspition of such dealing, certayn private 
<pb facs="3"/>
letters passing between him, and me, about private communion betwixt the members of
the true visible Ch: and others, though he take advantage, and occasion by certain gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
wordes of myne to alter the state ef the question. The occasion of which passages if I
should also publish, I am sure he would not like it, nor had cause.</p>
   <p>Now as I neyther am, nor would he thought in sensible of this vnchristian enmity, and<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
violent opposition by them against vs in the practise of those things, which themselves, as
their wryteings testify, do so far approve; so think I it a Preface very convenions for my
present purpose, to communicate with others such grounds, as vppon which they seem to
rayse the same.</p>
   <p>And first, all oppositions in religion are caryed vsually with violence, as wherein men
have speciall perswasion they please God, in that their speciall work of Conscience and
Zeal for him, and his truth. And as men are in daunger to mistake errour for truth, so
to prosequute the same with wrath, and indignation, instead of true Zeal of God. And I do
much entreat, &amp; warn those men in the fear of the Lord, to beware that in-stead of Zeal
against our supposed errours, they nourish not in their hearts, wrath, and hatred against<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
our persons. Which is a great iniquity where it is found, and most contrary vnto love, and
so vnto <hi>God who is love;</hi> &amp; the breaking of <hi>the whole law,</hi> which <hi>love fulfilleth.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But besides this generall, they take more speciall occasion of offence at vs, &amp; our sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
by which we cary our differences; as wherein we do not onely in word, but even
really &amp; indeed reprove their state, &amp; standing, as vnlawfull: &amp; such, as we rayther
chuse all calamityes, by losse of country, freinds, riches, credit, liberty, yea &amp; life is
self, then by continuance therein, to <hi>withould the truth of God in vnrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi>
&amp; vphould the chayr of Apostacy, and so to pull down wrath from heaven vppon
our heades. Which our sequestration is yet the more offensive vnto them, by how much
the nearer we were, &amp; yet are, in many things, vnited: the <hi>contentions of brethren
being as the barres of a castle:</hi> as also for that their party for the reformation of<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ov. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 19.</note>
their pretended nationall <hi>Iudah</hi> is thereby weakened. And as any (accordeing to the
proverb) may easily fynde a staffe, to beat a dog withall, so do men easily take occasion to
lay load vppon vs, who are for our fewnes in number, &amp; mean-nes of condition, so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible
in their eyes: &amp; against whom they have all advantages for treading vppon
vs (save the truth) which they can desire. But the L: Iesus in teaching, that <hi>the way
to life is narrow, which few fynde:</hi> &amp; that to <hi>the pore the gospell is preached,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ath. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.</note>
&amp; therevppon, that <hi>he is blessed who is not offended at him,</hi> doth plainly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn
all his servants of this offence. Others there are also, who whatsoever they boast of
the Scriptures, have for the most parte, a traditionall faith, &amp; religion: &amp; as <hi>Naaman
the Assirian</hi> would not beleev that there could be any <hi>better</hi> waters then <hi>the rivers</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>King. 12.</note>
      <hi>of Damascus,</hi> so neyther do they think it possible, that there should be any purer man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of worshipping God, then that, to which they have been alwaies vsed: vnto which
they are so superstitiously addicted, as they are ready to think it an hereticall way for any
man to step out of the beaten trod of their teachers traditionary religion.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>
There are also beside all these, that have their politique ends, &amp; respects, for which
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hey affect vpposition against vs. Some, (of the Prelats faction) to gratify their Lords.
and Maisters, at whose devotion they stand, and against whom we principally witnes:
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>thers, though they like not the Byshops, yet think it a point of their wisdom to take, and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ould vp professed opposition against vs, that vnder it as a buckler they may cover their
own irregularity, and make their iealouse Maisters beleev, that they cannot but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e
indifferently well affected towards them, being so vehemently bent against vs. Yea,
others perceaving that their own grounds do in the iudgmēt of others wise, &amp; vnpartiall,
directly lead to the way, in which we walk, and yet seing it not to be for their purposes
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o have the world so to esteem of them, do vndoubtedly, streyn, &amp; wring the neck of theyr
Consciences, and courses, to look the coutrary way, that they may not be thought to have
their faces towards vs.</p>
   <p>Lastly, there are, who fearing belike to be overcome of the truth we professe, if with
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uiet, &amp; calm thoughtes they come to consider of it, &amp; not haveing hearts to embrace it,
do set themself against it tumultuously; like those cowards, who fearing the force of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>heir adversaries, do think by debaseing, &amp; revileing of them, to encourage their own
faint, &amp; feeble hearts against them.</p>
   <p>But good had it been for the truth, if at it offences had onely been taken by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaryes
thereof, and not also given by them, who have professed it: and those both
so publique, as they cannot be concealed, and so great, as they can receav no suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
excuse. Yet are there notwithstanding divers things (and those such as will
seem, I doubt not, of weight, to the wise in heart) which both iustly may, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>essarily
must be observed about those matters: whether offensive contentions, or
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ther personall evilles, layd to our charge, and published to the world against
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s.</p>
   <p>First then, and in the generall; the publishers of those accusations cannot be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suspected
of any reasonable man: being such generally, as are both enemyes to our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ession,
and have eyther for their vnfaythfull Apostacy, or other scandalous sins, or
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oth, been cast out of the Church and excommunicated. Now as, for the former,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> is truely, and commonly sayd, that <hi>no person running away from his May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,
will easily speak well of him:</hi> So doth experience confirm it, for the latter,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hat scarce any condemned in any court (how iustly soever) but will complayn
eyther of the mallice of the evidence, or ignorance of the Iury, or iniustice of the
Iudg. Condemned persons must repayr their own, by ruinateing the credits of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>heir iudges.</p>
   <p>More specially: and first, of the contentions which have faln out amongst the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessours
of this way. As <hi>Paul</hi> complayneth, that <hi>sin takeing occasion by the law,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Rom. 7 8.</note>
      <hi>wrought in him all manner of concupiscence:</hi> so indeed hath the mallice of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>han,
and mans corruption taken occasion to work much evill of this kynde, by sundry
good things specially found in the professours of this truth: as 1. by their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudg,
<pb facs="4"/>
2. Zeal, &amp; 3. liberty of the Gospelly.<note n="†" place="margin">1. Cor. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>dg,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> 3. 1. Ch. 1. 5. 7. 11. Ch. 3. 3.</note>
      <hi>Knowledg,</hi> saith the Apostle, puffeth
vp: &amp; hence was it, that the same Church to which he so wrytes, exceeding other
Churches in <hi>knowledg,</hi> did also passe them in <hi>contentions, &amp; strifes:</hi> So the
Churches this way (which I may truely speak, &amp; without boasting) goeing before other
ordinary assemblyes in knowledg, are the more in daunger of contentions, without special<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
modesty, &amp; watchfulnes. Ignorant persons, &amp; peoples, are for the most parte, easily ruled,
as being content to trust other men with their faith, &amp; religion: neyther was there eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
so great peace in the Christian world (as it is called) as in the deepest darknes of popery.
2<hi>
         <seg rend="sup">dly</seg>,</hi> as the greatest Zeal for God is rightly found amongst Gods people, so is peace, &amp;
agreement greatly endaungered thereby, if it be not tempered with much wisdom, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
&amp; brotherly forbearance: &amp; that they consider not aright, that both themselves
&amp; others, are frayl men, &amp; compassed about with much ignorance, &amp; infirmity other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise:
who are therefore to study not onely how to have that which they like, but also
how to bear that in other men (if not intollerable) which they like not: otherwise, whilst
men think by their Zeal to warm the house, they will burn in over their own, &amp; other
mens heades. <hi>3<seg rend="sup">ly</seg>,</hi> &amp; lastly, they onely, who enioy liberty, know how hard a thing it is
to vse it aright. And when I see them in Engl: wondering at the dissentions in this way,
methinkes I see two prisoners (being themselves fast chayned &amp; manicled together by
feet, &amp; handes) wondering to see that other men (at liberty) walk not closer together
thē they do. Theyr thraldome makes them vnequall Censurers of the abuse of our liberty.
How many thousands are there, whose very hearts are fretted with the chaynes of their
spirituall bondage? Yea how many severall factions of ministers are there, whose diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences,
if by servile fear they were not nipped in the bud, would bring forth no small both
dissensions &amp; divisions: as at this day wofull experiēce teacheth in the reformed Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,
whose dissentions do infinitely exceed all that ever haue been amongst is? As igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
begot, so tyranny mainteyned the greatest peace, &amp; vnity, when pope: sh iniquity
most prevayled.</p>
   <p>Now for personall offences; as we professe, &amp; avow before all men, that, for our selves,
we neyther receav, nor keep amongst vs any persons not sanctifyed in their measure (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
our discerning:) so do we not think our selves any way priveledged, eyther from the
common infirmityes of Gods more worthy servants in all ages, or from the mallice of Sa
than in thrusting vppon vs <hi>false brethren vnawares:</hi> whose hypocrisy, &amp; prophan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ude 4.</note>
vsurpation of the Lords Covenant, &amp; holy things, vnto which they have no right, he
often punisheth with scandalous sins, &amp; so <hi>leadeth them out amongst the workers
of iniquity.</hi> Which scandalles we could yet cover from the eyes of the world in a great
measure, if we durst (as others do) eyther let <hi>sin rest vppon our brethren:</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <note place="margin">Lev. 19. 7.</note>
sm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ther in a Consistory such offences, as are eyther publique, of their own nature, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
made by the offenders private impenitency: which because we dare not do, nor but <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. 20.</note>
      <hi>him openly, which so sinneth,</hi> &amp; so iudg both his sin, &amp; person (in which
our pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dings, &amp; dealings, new offences are also added often tymes) we do thereby
<pb facs="4"/>
lay open our own shame in the eyes of the world: &amp; so walking in our simplicity, because
we dare not be wise against the Lord Iesus Christ his order, &amp; ordinances, we have in
so great a measure our faults written in our foreheads, &amp; are a wonder, &amp; offence vnto
others, who are far better acquaynted with our faylings, then with their own.</p>
   <p>But besides, if not above the rest, great offence hath been taken by many at our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream
streytnes in respect of the order wherein we walk: &amp; more specially for refuseing
communion in the private, &amp; personall exercises of religion with the better sorte in the
assemblyes; as wherein we have not onely made a separation from the wicked, &amp; from
the godly also in things vnlawfull, or vnlawfully performed, but even in their lawfull
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>actions. This <hi>Mr Ames</hi> calles <hi>the bitternes of separation:</hi> &amp; for it, as it seems,
thinkes it lawfull to cast vppon me the reproach of the sins of other Churches &amp; persons,
whether truely, or falsly layd to their charg, he knoweth not; as also to insinuate against
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, that <hi>I despise</hi> the wryteings of <hi>Iunius,</hi> &amp; so of other learned men: as iustly as<note place="margin">
         <hi>Grot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> agayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> the <hi>Eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap> Puritan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> as he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les thē.</note>
others have layd to his charg the contempt of all antient wryters: wherein if men deal
vniustly with him, &amp; his freinds, let him see whether God deal not iustly, in rewarde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
him as he hath served others.</p>
   <p>For the matter of his letters, if I would strive with him about the Arguments, with
whom I agree in the question, I could manifest (I doubt not) how he hath not dealt
sufficiciētly in it. Whither or no there were in the assemblyes faythfull, &amp; godly persons,
&amp; the same so appearing vnto men, I never called into question, nor could without sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
greatly against myne own Conscience: the thing I feared, was the violation, &amp;<note place="margin">See fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> this <hi>A Iustific<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> Pag. 432. 433.</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>reach of <hi>order</hi> in the communion between the members of the true visible Church, &amp;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>hers out of that <hi>order,</hi> or in the contrary. Myne obiection hereabout M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> A: an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swereth
not, but onely makes light account of it, as <hi>a straung order, which is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
by saying Amen to a godly mans prayer.</hi> But all men know, that to set light
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> an Argument is no sufficient answer vnto it. And many cases may be put in which
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rder may be sinfully broken in communicateing even with a godly mans prayers; eyther
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rivately, as if he will professedly offer vp the prayers of an excommunicate, detected
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eretique, or other vngodly person: or publiquely if he perform the same, without a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue, or by a false calling. Here was vse of a distinction of <hi>religious actions,</hi> into
<hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ersonall, &amp; Church</hi> actions: which if eyther M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> A: had observed vnto me, or<note place="margin">See pag 1.</note>
my self then conceaved of, would have cleared the question to my conscience: &amp; with
which I did wholy satisfy my self in this matter, when God gave me once to observ it.</p>
   <p>My iudgment therein, &amp; the reasons of it, I have set down in the first parte of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ook: vnto which I bynde no man further to assent, then he sees ground from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>es.
In it I oppose no <hi>Article of</hi> our <hi>confession:</hi> neyther was it the Authours
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eaning, as it seemeth, further to conclude &amp; professe separation then from communion<note place="margin">Art. 31</note>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the <hi>publique worship, &amp; administrations</hi> there: neyther do I herein oppose any
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t order of any Church this way, to my knowledg. I my self, &amp; the people with me
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>enerally, did separate from the formall state of the parrish assemblyes, in this persw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,
<pb facs="5"/>
&amp; so practised all the while we abode in Engl: as some there continuing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
done to this day: there haveing been also sundry passages between <hi>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Smith,</hi> &amp; me
about it: with whom I also refused to ioyn because I would vse my liberty in this point:
&amp; for which I was by some of the people with him excepted against, when I was chosen
into office in this Church. Indeed afterwardes fyndeing them of other Churches, with
whom I was most nearly ioyned, otherwise mynded for the most parte, I did thorough
my vehement desire of peace, &amp; weaknes withall, remit &amp; loose of my former resolutions
&amp; did (to speak as the truth is) forget some of my former grounds; &amp; so have passed
out, vppon occasion, some Arguments against this practise. Which yet notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
I have in the same place so set down, as all may see I was therein far from that, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynty
of perswasion, which I had &amp; have of the common grounds of our separation: of
which I think this no parte at all. But had my perswasion in it been fuller, then ever it
was, I professe my self alwayes one of them, who still desire to learn further, or better,
what the good will of God is. And I beseech the Lord from myne heart, that there
may be in the men, (towards whom I desire in all things lawfull to enlarg my self) the
like readines of mynde to forsake every evill way, &amp; faythfully to embrace &amp; walk in
the truth they do, or may see, as by the mercy of God, there is in me; which as I trust
it shalbe myne, so do I wish it may be their comfort also in the day of the Lord Iesus.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>IOHN ROBINSON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>