<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1562</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105152_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19788</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6214</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105152</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pleasaunt and vvittie playe of the cheasts renewed : with instructions both to learne it easely, and to play it well. Lately translated out of Italian into French: and now set furth in Englishe by Iames Rowbothum</title>
                 <author>Damiano, da Odemira</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hall, Rowland</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rowbotham (Robothum), James</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1562</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may peraduenture seeme straunge vnto some that anye man should bestow his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and tyme in set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out such kynd of bookes as this is, whereby men may learne to playe, when in dede most men are geuen rather to play then to studye. And because there may be alledged some reasons, why no man ought to allure anye vnto games: some more curious then wise wyll by and by catch occasion if not to condempne yet to disproue the trauayle and paynes that hath ben taken in this, &amp; so thinke that either the authour or the transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour might haue bene much better occupied. Whose opinion and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement I graunt were true &amp; good if it were a booke cōteinig any art of dise plaie, of cogging, or setting dyce, of falshod in carde play, or any
<pb facs="6"/>
other like sleights for the deceiuing one another or for sturring men to anger as suche games do often ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. But for asmuch as this game or rather kingly pastime is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly voyde of all crafte, gyle, fraude, deceyt, colour, swearing, staring, impacience, fretting, or falling out: but also it breadeth in playes a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine studye, pollicie, wit, forcast, memorie, with other properties, to make men circumspect not onelye in playing this game, but also com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paring it to a publick gouernemēt, or more properly a batttel, all men as well Captaines as souldiours, may pike out of these woddē pieces some pretie pollicie how to lead or conduct liuely men in the field. For this game hath a certaine allusion or similitude of a ranged battel, as by order in placing the men and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them forth in their marche, it maye easely appeare. The kinge is here as a king in the field placed in the middle of his armie, and hathe his welbeloued queene nexte vnto
<pb facs="6"/>
him, and his nobilitie aboute him, with the souldiours in the forfront orderly set. And although this bee but a briefe instruction to teache to playe, yet the onset beinge geuen, some other will folowe to amplifie or to finishe this ingenious and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie deuise, that thereby the subtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and hidden gyles of this game maye be more discouered, with the maner how to play without bourd or men walking or riding on horse backe with as great delite and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentation as if thei had the cheste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourde and men in their handes, which thing is done by diligent no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the place and houses wherein eche man standeth, and whither or into what house he marcheth or may marche, euery one hauing his way appoynted him to go. And in the meane tyme content your selfe with this, for I assure you the diffi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cultie to expresse or set out the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes and figures of the men is so muche and the chardges so greate, that as yet no man woulde euer
<pb facs="7"/>
gladly take in hand to prynt them. Albeit <hi>Hieronimus Cardan'</hi> in his boke <hi>de varietate rerum,</hi> geueth a certayne forme and maner, how to set out in print the cheste bourd and the men vpon it, according to the diuersitie of the colours blacke and whyte. But he that would folow him shuld cut as many bourdes and diuers fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of men as the playe hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers wayes to bee played, whiche woulde be intollerable charges. And therefore (curiositie set a part) take in good worth these types and figures here presented vntyll some better inuention be founde. For I doubt not but there be in England as good heades as either Italians or Spaniards, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> can if thei woulde inuent as fine a way to plai at this game as this is: but yet when a thing is begon, it is the easier and the soner made an end of. Now thei that will playe well at this game, muste beware that they talke not with any other standinge by, nor geue eare to anye that talketh by,
<pb facs="7"/>
for then shal his senses be occupied so with other matters that his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie that playeth against him will with his diligēce giue him y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> foyle: for this game (as the best players say) requireth the whole man, and consequently all the senses. Take hede also that the by standers (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che commonlye see more then the plaiers) do neither by signe or word admonishe your aduerse partie of any good or gaynfull draughte: for that is one thing amonge many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that causeth choler, and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth one of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> plaiers, but it is such a kind of choler that passeth awaye lightly, farre vnlike y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dyse plaiers anger, for he fretteth, he fumeth, be curseth, and banneth the dyse, &amp; despyteth his ill lucke, and you at the chest, blame not your men but your selfe, so that yf you haue a mate you saye commonly, yf I had played thus or thus I had saued the mate, herein is no offence to anye but vnto your selfe, and anone it is gone. Suche and other lyke plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure
<pb facs="8"/>
is there in this game, beynge a moste princely exercise, and full of good pollicie, and quickenynge of a mans witte. These things con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sidered, I thoughte it no labour e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill bestowed to occupie me selfe in the translation hereof, at tymes extraordinarie, when my more earnest studies and busy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes were done: Thus fare well gentell Reader.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>