<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honorable and vertuous Lady, the Lady Mary Talbot, wife to the Right honou∣rable Gilbert, Lord Talbot: Robert Greene wisheth increase of honour and vertue.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105892_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02074</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12219</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105892</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honorable and vertuous Lady, the Lady Mary Talbot, wife to the Right honou∣rable Gilbert, Lord Talbot: Robert Greene wisheth increase of honour and vertue.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Arbasto : The anatomie of fortune. Wherein is discoursed by a pithie and pleasant discourse, that the highest state of prosperitie, is oft times the first steppe to mishappe, and that to stay vpon fortunes lotte, is to treade on brittle glasse. VVherein also gentlemen may finde pleasant conceits to purge melancholie, and perfit counsell to preuent misfortune. By Robert Greene Master of Arte</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Hugh</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedicatory_letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right honorable and vertuous Lady, the Lady <hi>Mary Talbot,</hi> wife to the Right honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Gilbert, Lord Talbot: Robert Greene wisheth increase of honour and vertue.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>YRON</hi> that vnskilfull Painter of Greece, neuer drewe anie picture, but the counterfaite of <hi>Iupiter</hi>: saying, that if it were ill wrought, his woorthines should countenance out the meanenes of his worke, if well, commend the perfection of his arte.</p>
   <p>In like maner fareth it with me (right Honourable) who hauing vnskilfully shadowed with bad colors, the counterfait of Fortune, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume boldly to shroud it vnder your Ladiships patronage, as able to defend it, be it neuer so meane, and to countenaunce it, were it neuer so good, beeing of <hi>Decius</hi> minde, who thought himselfe safe vnder the shielde of Caesar.</p>
   <p>Poore <hi>Irus</hi> comming into the Temple of <hi>Pallas,</hi> seeing hir pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied with a Speare in the one hand, and a Booke in the other, noting thereby as well her inward vertue, as her outward valor: sayde, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spightfull pouertie, thou shalt not keepe me from honouring <hi>Pallas,</hi> though from giuing her presents.</p>
   <p>So hearing of your Ladiships exquisite perfection, as well in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde shape, as in vertuous qualities, drawne with a deepe desire, to shewe what a dutifull affection I owe to such noble and vertuous personages: although want sought to hinder my will, yet I thought rather to fault in the defect of abilitie, then not to shewe in effect the forwardnes of my desire, which wishing to bring forth a Mountain, haue scarce performed a Moul-hill, and willing to shew your honour <hi>Alexanders</hi> Picture, is far vnable to present you with <hi>Agrippas</hi> shaddowes.</p>
   <p>But I hope your Ladiship will deale with me as <hi>Caesar</hi> did with his yong Souldiers, who accepted of their seruice, not onelie when they performed what they should, but when they practised what they could. Thus resting assured of your Ladiships curtesie, praying conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie for the increase of your honor, with all things that you would wish or imagin, I end.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Ladiships most dutifull to commaund, <hi>Robert Greene.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>