<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen Readers, health.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105841_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02157</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12299</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105841</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen Readers, health.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Planetomachia: or the first parte of the generall opposition of the seuen planets : wherein is astronomically described their essence, nature, and influence: diuersly discouering in their pleasaunt and tragicall histories, the inward affections of the mindes ... Conteyning also a briefe apologie of the sacred and misticall science of astronomie: by Robert Greene, Master of Arts and student in phisicke. 1585</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 <publisher>Cadman, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Dawson, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 8, 32, 9-22 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen Readers, health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Present here (Gentlemen) vnto your woonted courtesies, a ciuill conflict be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the seuen Planets: not discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in this Pamphlet any straunge or myraculous newes of the opposition or aspect of the Starres, but onely shewing their nature and essence, and what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per qualities their celestiall configuration and influence doth infu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e into humaine bodies: so that their proper dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions once knowne, it shall bee easie by their outward affects to iudge what Planet is chiefly predominant in his naturall constitution: But that I might not be to tedious to young mindes, I haue interlaced my Astronomicall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course with pleasaunt Tragedies, that your profitable Haruest may be gleaned together with delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full paines. And thus committing my selfe and my labours to your courtesie, I most hartely and humbly bid you farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to vse, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Greene.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>