<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vnto The ryght Honourable LORDE Edward / Duke of Somerset mooste deare vncle vnto the Kinges Maiesté / ād Gouuernour of hys Royall Parson / and of his Realmes / Dominiōs ād subiectes Protectour. Hys graces mooste humble Seruaunt Rychard Argentyne wissheth the increa∣se of honour and grace.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105735_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08443</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18765</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105735</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Vnto The ryght Honourable LORDE Edward / Duke of Somerset mooste deare vncle vnto the Kinges Maiesté / ād Gouuernour of hys Royall Parson / and of his Realmes / Dominiōs ād subiectes Protectour. Hys graces mooste humble Seruaunt Rychard Argentyne wissheth the increa∣se of honour and grace.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons of the ryght famous a [n] d excellent clerke Master Bernardine Ochine, borne within the famous vniversyte of Siena in Italy, nowe also an exyle in this life, for the faythfull testimony of Jesus Christ</title>
                 <author>Ochino, Bernardino</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Scoloker, Anthony</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Ipswich</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>62 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Vnto The ryght Honourable LORDE Edward / Duke of Somerset mooste deare vncle vnto the Kinges Maiesté / ād Gouuernour of hys Royall Parson / and of his Realmes / Dominiōs ād subiectes Protectour. Hys graces mooste humble Seruaunt Rychard Argentyne wissheth the increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se of honour and grace.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>yke as in the beginig (moost Gracyous Lorde) it maye appere by the propre names of men / that the same were appoynted vnto them by a synguler reason.
<note place="margin">Genes. 4.</note> So by Seth also it maye be manifest that Kings are geuen vnto the Worlde of God.
<note place="margin">Genes. 1.</note> For after the time that the infinite Lorde / had created the vniuersall worlde / ād reserued the supremité of it vnto him selfe / he made man Prince and Lorde / and a Kynge im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly vnder hiouer all / whych myght
<pb facs="3"/>exercise his office / him selfe not being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonaly present before our eyes / to the intēt that we shulde alwayes elevate the same vnto Heauen there to seke him. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of iust cause Kynges / Prynces ande Gouuernours that moost lyuely and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably represēt vnto vs the diuine maiesté of God / being indued with a large porciō of the same / are called Goddes in the scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture.
<note place="margin">Genes. 6.</note>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 82.</note> And of the prophane poete Homere are named to come from God.</p>
   <p>These Princes ād Kinges / as it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the register of thíges done in time / were in moost places accustumed euē frō theyr tender age / to be brought vp vnder iiij. gouuernours. Iustice / Prudēce / For<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude and continency / amōgest the which vertues. Iustice beīg the highest of power albeit that wyth her manyfold benefittes / necessary vnto the vse of mā / she goeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ground / yet that notwithstāding wyth hyr shulders she reacheth vnto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. For as moche as she couereth nothig to hyr selfe nor craueth anye thynge / but geueth vnto euery man hys owne / ande restoreth euery thynge vnto hys ryght or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre
<pb facs="3"/>ād kynde.
<note place="margin">Paral. 16.</note> Where therfore the people of God made greate ioye ande feasted for their true religion restored / and were ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the confyrmyng of theyr Kynge / the which dyd minister vnto them onely externally iudgement ande iustice / what ipye / ought all thys realme to be in / vnto whome it hath fortuned the right ordre of the supper of the LORD to be restored / through the studye of suche a Prynce as walketh in all the waies of God in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ād fayth / ledde by a Gouuernour that moost parfectly hath trayned hym to the same?
<note place="margin">2. Reg. 6.</note>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 25.</note> In whome the spirit of Iesu christ that was ones onely offred / manifestlye produceth hys effectes.
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> And where as in our daies manye that of right ought to be called martirs / lyke vnto Paule / intendig that Chryst shuld be magnyfyed in theyr bodyes or by theyr death / with theyr blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / dyd not sticke to gyue a testimony vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worlde of the internal goodnes pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared vnto the sayntes hereafter / ād fedde the rauening wolues with their carcases. Now (God be blessed) by our so gracyous a Prynce / their teth are blunted and theyr
<pb facs="4"/>mouthes musseled. For those that shuld ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve bene the lyght / that the frute of rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnes that commeth by Iesu Christ on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / might have been planted in manye / ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto the Phariseys that had miracles comune vnto them with the fathers / and the presence also of the moost mekest lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be of God / the which dyd illustrate them wyth hys doctryne ande miracles / wolde in no case come to any amendement. And yet they glorye that theyr name was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied to be exercised in iustice by the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete Esay.
<note place="margin">Esay. 60.</note> Where the ixx. interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have (if it be theyr text ād not others) I shall gyue thy Princes in peace / ād thy Bysshoppes in iustice. But the Hebrewe text (yf they wyll that place to be ment of them and not of other publyke officyers) calleth them more (accordyngly vnto the trueth) exactours or cursitours / nothyng seking for the founteine of all saturité lac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king the frugalité that Paule willeth thē to vse. The which thinge they wolde not if they had in them the carefull mynde of the iust executiō of thinges to be done vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Gods honour. Lyke as by the shauing
<pb facs="4"/>of theyr beardes and of theyr heades (the whiche were in the olde tyme tokens of a pensyve ande sadde minde) they appere to have.
<note place="margin">Esay. 15.</note> But treuth it is / that lyke as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde (that was accounted to be the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the man) is hatefull vnto them / and is not to be found amongest them / so is the studye of all good vertue amongest others and not amongest them. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the migtye LORD hath appointed your grare vnto the same office for the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of all the faithful / as the necessary hā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of a Kynge gyvē vnto vs by God. And to that purpose these syx Sermons of the famous clerke Bernardinus Ochinus are translated out of the Italyan tongue. The fyrst declaring what thynge GOD is. The second / Howe to knowe GOD by hys creatures. The thyrd yf Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophye serue to true theologye and in wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at maner. Fourthely / Howe we ought to vse the Scryptures in attayninge the knowledge of GOD. Fyfthly / Of thinconue mences that are happened and dayly happē by the abuse of the holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Syxtly and finally / If to be good
<pb facs="5"/>diuines it behoue vs to have the humaine sciences or not / and gevē vnto your grace as a moost vnworthye gifte / that by your graces fauour the frute of all the oher ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons maye be brought vnto your graces louinge servauntes of the whole bodye of this Realme / vnto whose cōfort the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de IESV Chryst preserue your grace. At Ippeswych the xiiij. daye of February. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. M.D. xlviij.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>