<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>A Madrigale to wanton Louers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105832_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02111</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12253</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105832</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>A Madrigale to wanton Louers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Greenes neuer too late. Or, A powder of experience: sent to all youthfull gentlemen : to roote out the infectious follies, that ouer-reaching conceits foster in the spring time of their youth. Decyphering in a true English historie, those particular vanities, that with thei frostie vapours nip the blossoms of euery ripe braine, from atteining to his intended perfection. As pleasant, as profitable, being a right pumice stone, apt to race out idlenesse with delight, and follie with admonition. Rob. Greene in artibus Magister</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 <distributor>Busby, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 56, 49-62, 2, 84 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>A Madrigale to wanton Louers.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>YOu that by <hi>Alcidalions</hi> siluer brookes</l>
      <l>Sit and sigh out the passions of your loues,</l>
      <l>That on your Goddesse beauties feede your lookes,</l>
      <l>And pamper vp sweete <hi>Venus</hi> wanton Doues,</l>
      <l>That seeke to sit by <hi>Cupids</hi> scorching fire,</l>
      <l>And dally in the fountaines of desire.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>You that accompt no heauen like <hi>Venus</hi> spheare,</l>
      <l>That thinke each dimple in your Mistresse chin</l>
      <l>Earths paradice, that deeme her golden haire</l>
      <l>Tresses of blisse wherein to wander in:</l>
      <l>That sigh and court suppliant all to proue,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Cupid</hi> is God, and theres no heauen but Loue.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Come see the worke that <hi>Greene</hi> hath s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ilie wrought,</l>
      <l>Take but his <hi>Nunquam sera</hi> in your view,</l>
      <l>As in a myrrour there is deeply taught</l>
      <l>The wanton vices of prowd fancies crew,</l>
      <l>There is depainted by most curious art,</l>
      <l>How loue and follie iumpe in euery part.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>There may you see repentance all in blacke,</l>
      <l>Scourging the forward passions of fond youth,</l>
      <l>How fad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ng pleasures end in dismall wracke,</l>
      <l>How louers ioyes are tempred all with ruth,</l>
      <l>Sith then his <hi>Nunquam sera</hi> yeeldes such gaines,</l>
      <l>Reade it, and thanke the Author for his paines.</l>
   </lg>
   <byline>Ralph Sidley.</byline>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>