<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the very Woorthy, Learned, Iuditious, and Noble Gentleman, Syr Iohn Harrington Knight.</title>
           <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1608</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105243_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20054</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6496</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105243</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the very Woorthy, Learned, Iuditious, and Noble Gentleman, Syr Iohn Harrington Knight.</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The dead tearme. Or, VVestminsters complaint for long vacations and short termes : Written in manner of a dialogue betweene the two cityes London and Westminster. The contentes of this discourse is in the page following. By T. Dekker</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1608</date>
                 <publisher>Hodgets, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jaggard, William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Trundle, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>54 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the very Woorthy, Learned, Iuditious, and Noble Gentleman, Syr Iohn Harrington Knight.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, the Loue (which your immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall <hi>Ariosto</hi> tels to the world) that you really beare to <hi>Diuine,</hi> (but now <hi>Poore</hi> and <hi>Contemned</hi>) <hi>Poesie,</hi> hath a long time made me an <hi>Honorer</hi> of those bright ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Vertues</hi> in you, which those <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Pure Flames</hi> of <hi>Her</hi> haue kindled in your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some. <hi>Happy</hi> you are by <hi>Birth,</hi> Happy, by your bringing vp, but most happy in that the <hi>Muses</hi> were your <hi>Nurses,</hi> to whome you haue beene so tender, that they make you an <hi>Elder</hi> sonne and <hi>Heyre</hi> of their <hi>Goodliest Possessions.</hi> So that your <hi>Loue</hi> to <hi>Them,</hi> hath drawne from <hi>Others,</hi> an <hi>Honourable Loue</hi> and <hi>Regarde</hi> of you. The <hi>Path</hi> which <hi>True Noblenesse</hi> had wont (and ought) to tread, lyes directly before you: you haue beene euer, and are now in the way, which emboldens me to presume, that as our <hi>Greatest Commanders</hi> will not disdaine to instruct e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Fresh-water souldiers</hi> in the Schoole-poynts of war, so (out of your Noble disposition) you will vouchsafe to viewe the labours of so dull a <hi>Pen,</hi> as <hi>This</hi> that writes, vnto you. Two <hi>Citties</hi> haue I summoned to a <hi>Parley,</hi> and of their great <hi>Enter-view</hi> haue I chosen you to be <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> It is <hi>Boldnes</hi> in me, I confesse, but it is the <hi>Boldnes,</hi> of my <hi>Loue,</hi> referring which (and my selfe) to your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Censure, I Rest.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Deuoted to you in all seruice,</hi> Thomas Dekker.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>