<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right wor∣thie and right worship∣full Gentleman, Sir Iohn Scot, knight: a prosperous increase of honour in this world, and a perfect inioy∣ing of glorie in the world to come.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105249_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20057</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6499</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105249</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right wor∣thie and right worship∣full Gentleman, Sir Iohn Scot, knight: a prosperous increase of honour in this world, and a perfect inioy∣ing of glorie in the world to come.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Foure birds of Noahs arke : viz. 1. The dove. 2. The eagle. 3. The pellican. 4. The phoenix</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Ballard, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 65, 10, 58, 6, 71, 16, 29, 1, 14 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="47"/>
   <pb facs="47"/>
   <head>To the right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie and right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Gentleman, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> Scot, knight: a prosperous increase of honour in this world, and a perfect inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of glorie in the world to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, after I had builded vp these foure al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars of deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to present the first of thē to your worshipful brother in Law (Sir <hi>Thomas Smith</hi>;) I knew not where to find a man that did more truely parallell him in goodnesse then you your selfe; aswell for the ornaments of mind, as for that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie, pietie, zeale, and other ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the soule, wherewith the world taketh especiall note, that you are (both) abundantly stored.
<pb facs="48"/>
For that cause thefore, (as also in regard that Affinitie hath knit you together in a strong and holy league of loue) am I bold to reare vp this my second altar to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of your name. Vpon it are offered vp Prayers onely, whose incense are as sweet odours in the nostrils of God. They are in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of Princes and Rulers (who are the highest vpō earth) &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doeth an Eagle carie them vp to heauen. Shee flieth now to your bosome, there to build her nest: esteeming it a happie place for her to abide in, sithence shee foreseeth (or at least with me prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) that all your thoughts, words and actions which are bred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, doe shew themselues, and so may proue still true Eagles, by being able to looke stedfastly on the sunne of righteousnesse. And thus crauing pardon for bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, I rest:</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Deuoted</hi> yours</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>