<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
           <author>Foxe, Luke</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1635</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105645_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01108</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11221</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105645</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Foxe, Luke</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>North-vvest Fox, or, Fox from the North-west passage : Beginning vvith King Arthur, Malga, Octhur, the two Zeni's of Iseland, Estotiland, and Dorgia; following with briefe abstracts of the voyages of Cabot, Frobisher, Davis, Waymouth, Knight, Hudson, Button, Gibbons, Bylot, Baffin, Hawkridge: ... Mr. Iames Hall's three voyages to Groynland, with a topographicall description of the countries, the salvages lives and treacheries, how our men have beene slayne by them there, with the commodities of all those parts; ... demonstrated in a polar card, wherein are all the maines, seas, and ilands, herein mentioned. With the author his owne voyage, being the XVIth. with the opinions and collections of the most famous mathematicians, and cosmographers; ... By Captaine Luke Foxe of Kingstone vpon Hull, capt. and pylot for the voyage, in his Majesties Pinnace the Charles. Printed by his Majesties command</title>
                 <author>Foxe, Luke</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Sparke (Sparkes, Wreichionen), Michael 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1635</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 79, 100-171, 1, 169-269, 3 pages, folded plates, illustrations, map, table, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE READER,</hi> expect not heere any florishing Phrases or Floquent tearmes, for this Child of mine begot in the North-wests cold Clime, (where they breed no Schollers,) is not able to digest the sweet milke of Retho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, that's food for them▪ the Parent not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to maintaine it any longer, it being now past the Cradle, hopes, the Publike will willingly bestow Education of the Infant for his better breeding; for which the Father prayeth, and the rather because the Midwife perswades him that the Child lookes like himselfe, there were some desired to have had him come abroad like the Lapwing, before the shell was from over his head, but the Nurse more carefull of the tenderly borne Infant procrastinated the time, supposing that after birth it would strengthen apace in this temporate Clime, and in time be the better able to Iourney; but in Conclusion its turned to Discoverie, not of a Passage but of the way to find one, to come to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>le <hi>Iapon, China,</hi> and the Orient all <hi>India;</hi> of which, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that divers inquired after; (for who would not share in such Treasures as there's to be had) as what hath <hi>Fox</hi> done, others how farre farre hath hee beene, hath he beene as farre as any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>an, If there be a Passage how chance hee hath not found it, if not, why doe they search after it; and in fine, hath hee made a Voyage or no, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this last I know not, nor I thinke they neither; but for that the most desire to know what I have done, and how farre I have bin; I answer as the Old women tells tales, <hi>Further and further than</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <hi>I can tell;</hi> and for the rest I referre them to mine owne Iournall: For I hope it may satisfie those that are indifferent, and that stand well affected to those Discovering enterprises, for whose cause and the good or content of others it was chiefly compiled. I doe confesse, that they have not done me much amisse in causing me to show my selfe; for hereby they shall know, that before this vndertaking I was not ignorant of what my predecessors had done before I came, which was no small helpe both to my safety and proceeding. For some will Calumniate out of malice, some for that they dislike all things but what themselves or friends doth; but I hope the judiciall Sea-man will stand in my defence: For amongst those inquisitors, especially the never-satisfied-curious, I finde few that doth or will know what they inquire after, other having other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments rests content with the verball Report of their owne Times, rather than looke after the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> and Experiences of so vnpleasant, and as it is held vnprofitable a Voyage. For these and others, I leave to peruse what shall follow, wherein the desirous may bee satisfied, how every Successour (as his fancy, direction, or opinion guided) thought to rectifie himselfe by others mistaking, or to finde the Passage in those places left vnsearched or perfectly discovered: For no question, but this Voyage might long since have attained his full perfection; if the first beginners had beene yearely continued, which since Captaine <hi>DAVIS</hi> was not, but sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wayes (after some yeares of breathing) by Greene men, or those who (in that time) had forgot their experience; nay, I may avo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ch, that if this course had beene taken, and private ends had beene wanting, that since Mr. <hi>HVDSON</hi> his first Voyage 1610. the Passage had been sayled through before 1618. and done at one quarter of the Charge; and howsoever it was not my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to finde, yet I praise GOD for that I have brought home the newes thereof, though I have left it for him whose time God shall be pleased to ripen for the same; For it is a wonder that a Voyage of such Consequence as this, wherein all the parts of Navigation may be practised, should so longlye raked in the embers and no
<pb facs="4"/>
further search made thereinto, (conside-ring that within these few yeares, there hath bin more excellent Secrets in Navigation found out then hath beene in all the former Ages) it being (no questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) but more then the difficultest halfe Discovered; to incourage which thou shalt reade h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>w great Princes have taken plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to increase their Dominions (in Person) by Navigation, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so that our Ancestors were not so simple as we make them; and that this Hunting of the Whale (which as yet wee make rare) was in practice in King <hi>ALFREDS</hi> time related by <hi>OCTHER,</hi> who cald him Lord, as King <hi>ARTHVRS</hi> Successour; which <hi>OCTHER</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led about the North Cape of <hi>Finm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rke,</hi> as appeareth by his owne Narration, and this was long before <hi>RICHARD CHANCELOR,</hi> whom wee make <hi>Prima.</hi> I begin with those Princes, to show the Honour and Renowne of our Nation, and so proceed to all that went before me North-Westwards, out of a coniecturall necessity which I conceive them to bee as Appendices to the Iournals of these mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne times.</p>
   <p>It will be obiected, that many of these Abstracts are taken out of other Bookes, and that those are the Voyages of other men; I answer it is true, the most of them are. For what are all those of Mr. <hi>Hac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>its,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Purchas,</hi> but the Collections and preservations of other mens labours; For who can speake or write that which was never done before, and I doe confesse my selfe to be infinitly bound vnto them and others for their paines; for if they had not bin thus carefully stored vp, these had beene wanting as are divers others. For in searching thou shalt finde, that the workes of many brave men are buried in oblivion, whose Names are devolved and but something brought vnto vs through the succession of Ages, and though part of those workes have escaped, the wracke of the rest have perished in the Gulfe of time, which hath swallowed the best of many mens endeavors, and for those extant▪ thou canst not come vnto without labour and charge, all which I have brought to thy hands almost for nothing, considering the charge of Bookes of great prise, the labour in search and Quotations; besides, heere
<pb facs="5"/>
is much that never came in Print as yet, being very difficult to be had. And though I have abstracted those Workes of my Predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, yet I have interlaced my owne experience, and beene curious not to leave out any thing of theirs or my owne, wherein I could thinke my remembrance might avayle thee. And although wee all have sometimes stumbled, yet wee may bee excused, considering the long and strange Iourney wee had to goe, and who followeth doth but persevere by our example, nor have I like the Poet feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a Storme where I had none: Nor doe I hold that man fit to take charge of Voyages remote, especially Northeast or Westward, and be Ignorant of those Abstracts and Iournals following. For I know, knowledge will conceive them to be good Preparatives. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever in them I have done my best, and whosoever will amend them, I shall take him for my friend, I have restored all the names of Capes, Headlands, and Ilands formerly given by Captaine <hi>DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIS,</hi> Mr <hi>HVDSON,</hi> and Sir <hi>THOMAS BVTTON,</hi> (which since have beene infringed vpon) vnto their first appellations, both in my Booke and Map. I doe confesse, that there be many who might more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>itly have vndertaken this labour then my selfe, if they had been so well acquainted with the action; For we have many Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners, whom we call Mathematicall Sea-men, who that after a little practice in Art, purposeth then to goe to Sea and Travell; therefore carefully busying themselves about perusing the Cosino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphicall Maps, and with great industry studied the bookes of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, and to better their knowledge, have enquired of many excellent Mariners for their better satisfaction, in the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test parts thereof, thinking that they are now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>it to set sayle and launch foorth to Sea, conceiting of themselves to bee farre more able then the Sea-man; yet when they have taken the charge of the Ship vpon them, and is hoyst forth of the quiet port into the ruffe and boisterous Ocean, where they shall behold many hideous moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of high threatning billowes, and raging waves, tempestuous gusts, with hayle, raine and thunder, Shifts of windes, and counter Seas, Currents, Races, Sets, and Over-fals, being deprived of Sun,
<pb facs="5"/>
Moone and Starres for long season, they will then thinke that they onely dreamed before, when they imagined of the Course of the Seas, and that their Bookes were but weake Schoolemasters, that the talke of Art were farre short of the Practice, when at beholding the Starres which they thought to have vsed as guides and directions▪ seeme now as they threatned their ruine and destruction; nay, when you shall looke forth and tremble at the rising of every wave, and shall be agast with feare to refraine those Rockes and dangers which lye hid within the Seas fairest bosome, together with the greatnesse of the Ocean, and smalnesse of their Ship; for want of experience to handle, not knowing how to shun, they will then thinke that the least gale is of force to overthrow them, and know that Art must be taught to practice by long and industrious vse. For it is not enough to be a Sea-man, but to be a painefull Sea-man; for a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred man of reasonable Capacity, may attaine to so much Art as may serve to Circle the Earths Globe about, but the other wanting the experimentall part cannot▪ for I doe not allow any to be a good Sea man, that hath not vndergone the most Offices about a Ship, and that his youth hath bin both taught and inured to all labours; for to keepe a warme Cabbin &amp; lye in sheets, is the most ignoble part of a Sea man, but to endure and suffer; as a hard Cabbin, cold and salt Meate, broken sleepes, mould bread, dead beere, wet Cloathes, want of fire, all these are within board; besides Boate, Lead, Top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yardes, Anchor-morings and the like. For as Oyle Paper layd vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the obiect, makes it more transparant, so doth Experience show Art to see without spectacles; and concluding this point in starling for I have no other Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne and but small store of that, to those who saith, that I am but a North-Countrey Coaster, and hath but been brought vp in small Vessels. I wish their pride to know, that Gods mercy is over all his Creatures, and hath created as good men in the North as in the South, let no man bee disdained, misprised or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalued for his wants (except in Vertues.) For I doe not thinke, but litle M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>IEFFERY</hi> that pretty Courtier, can pitch his eye-sight as high into the Firmament, as M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>EVANS</hi> his Maiesties great
<pb facs="6"/>
Porter. And for Sea-men, where have you better than the <hi>Scotsh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> are, and yet North-Countrey men. It was also cast into my dish, that I was an Officer of the Admiralty; a poore conceit to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect against me for this vndertaking, and as much as to say; as the greatest Civilian held to be in Christendome, cannot be capable of higher Promotion, if hee belong to the Admiraltie.</p>
   <p>I have also placed a Polar Map or Card, that this Discoverie may be the better vnderstood, and for that I did desire to give sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction by Demonstration of all treated of in the Booke, for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, another proiection could not have contained it but at vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable diversity; and because I cannot describe all the Names in <hi>Fretum Hudson,</hi> of Capes, Ilands, and Bayes at length in Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in respect of the smalnesse of the Degrees of Longitude, I have inserted them in a table by the letters of the Alphabet, as thou shalt find, beginning with <hi>A, b, c, d,</hi> and tracted my owne way and discovery foorth and home, in small prickes.</p>
   <p>I acknowledge it to be but rough-hewen like Ship wrights <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but what it wants in smoothnesse or forme, let thy good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port licke it into. I trust I shall not need to vse the fashion of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, to make any doubt of carping <hi>Momus</hi> or rayling <hi>Zoilus,</hi> seeing I have intended thy Good without any Reservation to my selfe. But I feare mee I have held thee too long in this place, like him who purposeth to take a long Iourney stumbles vpon his owne threshold, but have Patience, for I had rather be in fault then want, I have here prostrated my duty to my King, and my service to my Countrey, craving thy favourable acceptance, I rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From <hi>Kingston</hi> upon <hi>Hull,</hi>
         <date>this first of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 1635.</date>
      </dateline>
Thine, in all welwilling,
<signed>Luke Foxe.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>