<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Worshipful Thomas Burnabie Esquier Robert Greene wisheth hartes ease, and heauens blisse.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105865_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02160</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12301a.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105865</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Worshipful Thomas Burnabie Esquier Robert Greene wisheth hartes ease, and heauens blisse.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A quip for an vpstart courtier: or, A quaint dispute betvveen veluet breeches and cloth-breeches : Wherein is plainely set downe the disorders in all estates and trades</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Worshipful Thomas Burnabie Esquier Robert Greene wisheth hartes ease, and heauens blisse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, after I had ended this Quippe for an vpstart Courtier, contayning a quaint dispute betweene Clothbreeches and Veluet breeches, wherein vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a dreame I shadowed the abuses that Pride had bred in <hi>Englande,</hi> how it had infected the Court with aspiring Enuie, the Citie with griping couetousnesse, and the countrye with contempte and disdaine. How since men placed theit delights in proud lookes and braue atyre, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spitality was left off, Neighbourhood was exciled, Conscience was skoft at, and charitie lay frozen in the streets: how vpstart Gentlemen for the maintainance of that their fathers neuer lookt after, raised rents, rackte their tenants, and imposed greate fines, I stoode in a mase to whome I shoulde dedicate my labours, knowing I should bee bitten by many, sithens I had toucht many, and therefore neede some woorthye Patrone vnder whose winges I might shroud my selfe from goodman finde fault. At last I cald to mind your Worship, and thought you the fittest of al my frends, both for the duetie that I owe, and the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull qualities you are indued withall, as also for that all Northam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>hire reports how you are a father of the poore, a supporter of aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Hospitalitie, an enimie to Pride, and to be short, a maintayner of Cloth breeches (I meane of the old and worthie customes of the Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and yeomanrie of <hi>England.</hi>) Induced by these reasons, I humbly present this phamplet to your Worship, only crauing you wil accept it as courtiously as I present it dutifully, and then I haue the end of my desire and foresting in hope of your fauourable acceptance, I humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your duetifull adopted sonne, Robert Greene.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>