<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO M. IOHN IEVVEL THOMAS STAPLETON vvissheth the loue of Truthe.</title>
           <author>Stapleton, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1566</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105218_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12943</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23234</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105218</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO M. IOHN IEVVEL THOMAS STAPLETON vvissheth the loue of Truthe.</title>
                 <author>Stapleton, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A retur [ne of vn] truthes vpon [M. Jewel] les replie : Partly of such, as he hath slaunderously charg [...] Harding withal: partly of such other, as he h [...] committed about the triall thereof, in the text of the foure first articles of his Replie. VVith a reioyndre vpon th principall matters of the Replie, treated in the thirde and fourthe articles. By Thomas Stapleton student in Diuinitie</title>
                 <author>Stapleton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Laet (Latius), Hans (Jan) de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1566</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 134, 196 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prefatory_letter">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO M. IOHN IEVVEL THOMAS STAPLETON vvissheth the loue of Truthe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F you are, M. Ievvell, the Man that you pretēd to be, desirous of Gods honour, a Zelatour in the House of God, and a Boulter out off that Truthe, vvhich you haue vaunted, and many doe thinke, can not be founde: it shall not seme straunge vnto you, much lesse it shal of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fende you, if I amonge the rest, though a Man to you vnknovven, yet a Christen Man and your Countreman, do put my helping hande to this your Zelous enterprise, and as if it vvere shevve you some parte of the vvaye that may leade you thereunto. For as betvvene the Flynt and Yron, being striken together, fyre doth Flye out, so Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes and VVittes contending, the Light off right knovvleadge must nedes appeare. Suche Lighte ones appearing, the Truthe is soone had. You M. Ievvel, to haue this Truthe tryed, haue proposed your Questions, and haue Challenged all that vvill, to ioyne issue vvith you in a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Articles. To that your Challenge it hathe bene Ansvvered Copiously and Lernedly. And
<pb facs="5"/>
the Truthe hathe bene proued, not only in the Termes of your Challenge vvhich is lesse mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, but much more in the Matter, comprised in those Termes. To that Ansvver you haue Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied largely also and painefully.</p>
   <p>In this your Replie as you haue spared no Rhetorike, multiplyed Allegatyons, hunted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Common places, entred in to Digressyons, al to make a Shevve of lerning, and a Countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of a Iuste and Full Replie to the Matter it sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe: so haue you for the Disgracing of your Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, and for Discredityng the Author him selfe, vsed much Arte and taken great Paynes. Novve vvith Scoffes and Tauntes, Novve dissembling a great vvhile his Meaning, and reasoning sadly against that no man saied, coming in after vvith your, <hi>But M. Harding will saie,</hi> Then altering quite his text in your Replie, and so confuting at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure your ovvne Inuentyon. At other times not Replying to him at all, but Opposing off your ovvne store. But one Caste you haue inuented, vvhich I remembre not that any other vvriter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Vsed before. A Caste I saie sufficient alone, if it vvere clenly conuayed, and vprightlye practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, not only to discredit the Author and to Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde the Aduersary, but also to ouerthrovve his Doctrine, and to satisfie the Matter. VVhat is
<pb facs="5"/>
that trovve vve? Forsothe you haue scored all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe the Ansvver of D. Harding, euen from the beginning to the ending, <hi>Vntruthes,</hi> as you call them, <hi>Slaunders,</hi> in dede they be.</p>
   <p>In these <hi>Vntruthes,</hi> you note to the Reader, not only the presumed faultes, errours or escapes of the Author, in penning and treating his Matter, but much more you note euery Principall poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of Doctrine, euery Proued Proposition, and Matter treated, that semed to you and your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, Vntrue. In this Inuentyon you take great pleasure. Of it you make great Vaūtes. By it you thinke to vvinne the Credit and Persuasion of al men. For, this point you note to your Reader of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes not only in the text of your Replie, but in your Preface, in your Conclusyon, and in the Table of your booke. In your Text, tovvard the ende of your first Article, hauing thē charged D. Harding vvith .44. Vntruthes, you Crie out, and saie. <hi>O M. Harding,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Ievvell. pag. 91.</note>
      <hi>is it not possible your doctrine maye stande without lies? So many Vntruthes, in so litle roome, without the shame of the worlde, without feare of God?</hi> In an other place you put the Reader in minde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of this matter, and you saie of <hi>D.</hi> Harding. <hi>This man coulde neuer vtter so many Vntruthes together without some speciall priuilege.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Pag. 195.</note> In your Preface you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire these Vntruthes, first and especially to be
<pb facs="6"/>
discharged, or amended, for thus you saie. <hi>Before he addresse him selfe to his Second Booke, I woulde counsel him to consider better the ouersightes and scapes of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Booke.</hi> And a litle after. <hi>But before all thinges lett him write no moe Vntruthes. For thereof he hath sent vs enough already. Let him no more wreast and racke the Scri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptures: let him nomore neither misalleage, nor mysconstrue, nor corrupte, nor alter the holy Fathers.</hi> Thus many vvaies you presume D. Harding to haue dealed Vntruly. And this you vvil not haue your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to forgette. In your Cōclusion you put agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the Reader in minde of them, as a Matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other to be boren avvaye. For amonge other thinges thus there you speake to D. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. <hi>Your Vntruthes be so notorious, and so many, that it pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap>th me in your behalfe to remembre them. But the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be euident, and Crie Corruptiō, and maye by no shifte be denied.</hi> The like you doe in your Table, vpon the Name of M. Harding noting very sadly and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely the totall summe off <hi>Vntruthes,</hi> vvhiche by your good Audit ariseth in the vvhole An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svver of D. Harding, to the number of 255. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that they are <hi>with better aduise to be redressed.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Novve verely M. Ievvel, vvere your Audit he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein good, and your Notes true, that so many Vntruthes in that ansvver vvere in dede cōmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, partly by the Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s faulte and ouersight
<pb facs="6"/>
(to speake the leste) partly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd Vntrue Doctrine therein con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>yned▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> the booke vvorthy to be reproued, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> greatly to be blamed. Yea I vvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> you M. Ievvell, then vvere his doctrine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> tolerated, and his Person neuer to be cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap>ed. Then vvas it bothe vvisely done of you to disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it, and charitably done to expresse it, to note it, and to open it vnto all the vvorlde. For more Charite it is, that one false Teacher abide the Shame, Blame, and Reproche, then that a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand ignorant and innocent soules be induced to Errour, False doctrine, and Heresy.</p>
   <p>But if on the Contrary parte, these are no Vntruthes, vvhich for such you haue Noted, M. Ievvell, if neither the Doctrine neither the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of D. Harding is founde Vntrue, if all these Vntruthes, (as farre as I haue yet entred vvithe you, vvhich is to the one halfe thereof) be Retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned euery one vpon you (One Only excepted, vvhich yet is no Vntruth in doctrine, but a mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>setaking of the Author) if they be proued to be your ovvne Vntruthes and that Slaunderous: vvhat can remaine but that bothe the Ansvver of D. Harding, is so farre, good and perfect, and voide of Vntruthe, and yovv for your part are founde to be a greate Slaunderer of your Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary,
<pb facs="7"/>
and an Open enemy to the Truthe, vvhich you vvil seme to defende?</p>
   <p>I vvill saie farder M. Ievvell. VVhat if you, not through your vvhole Replie, nor yet through out the former Halfe thereof, vvhich at this time I haue only taken in hande, but through those places only of this Halfe, in vvhiche you labour in the text to Iustifie the Vntruthe noted in the Margin, vvhat I saie if in these small Parcelles of halfe your Replie, (though in dede the Principal and most Important Parcelles thereof) you haue beside of your ovvne parte, vvhat vvith false Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, vvhat vvith extreme Levvde Dealing, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted certain Hundreds of Vntruthes your sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe: then vvhat shal vve saie vnto you, or of vvhat Credit ought you hereafter to be, vvith all men, that loue the Truthe, and are not Fastned to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
   <p>Maye vve not then saie to you vvith the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esa.</hi> 5.</note>
      <hi>Veh qui dicitis malum bonum, bonum malum?</hi> Accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed be you that call euill, good, and good, euill? vvhich call Truthe, Vntruthe, and persuade Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes for Truthe? Maye vve not truly take you for one of them, vvhich the Apostle saieth, shall come in the later dayes, <hi>In hypocrisi loquentiū mendaciū,</hi> Vttering lyes in Hypocrysy?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> For vvhat greater Hypocrysy is there, then to Charge Vntruthes,
<pb facs="7"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> Vntruly, and to impugne the Truthe vvith the coulour of Truthe? Maye you not vvorthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be thought to be one of them, vvhom the Prophet describeth saying,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esa.</hi> 28.</note>
      <hi>Posuimus mendacium spem nostram, &amp; m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ndacio pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>tecti sumus.</hi> VVe haue put our Confidence in Lying, and Lies haue bene oure Sauegarde▪ Are you not truly like to those false prophets of the Ievves, vvho (as the prophet sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieth) <hi>Docue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="4 letters">
            <desc>••••</desc>
         </gap> ling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>am suam loqui mendacium,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ierem.</hi> 9.</note>
      <hi>vt inique age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint laborau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>t.</hi> Framed their tounges to Vtter Lies and toke great paynes to Deale Falsely: For so Manifolde and so Thicke are your Vntru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes that it maye seme, you haue Laboured your selfe to Vtter them. Yea maye vve not then thinke, that S. Peter, as it vvere pointed to you M. Ievvel, vvhen he saied, <hi>As there were false prophets amonge the people</hi> (of Israël) <hi>so there shall be ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Masters amonge you,</hi>
      <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note>
      <hi>which shall bringe in wicked and damnable sectes</hi>? Verely M. Ievvell vve maie saye al this and much more most truly of you, and that therefore (your excessiue lying and Vntrue dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling being so euident) neither your doctrine is to be tolerated, neither your Person euer more to be credited.</p>
   <p>For vvhat kinde is there of Authors, that you haue not Corrupted, Misalleaged, False Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by one meanes or other Abused? VVhat
<pb facs="8"/>
Faulte in vvriting is there that you haue not in this your Replie committed? I speake not off your VVhole Replie, but of that Parte only vvhich I at this present haue taken in hande to examine, that is, the Effect and Principall Poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of your foure first Articles.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">A briefe Summary of M. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvelles Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyons.</note>As touching your Authors and Allegatyons, vvhich you haue so Ambitiously Multiplyed through out your booke, and vvhereby the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are much abused, beholding therein a Coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of Lerning, but not able to descrie the Couered Falshood, you haue Falsifyed and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salleaged the Doctours and holy Fathers of Christes Church, the Decrees of Councelles, the lavves of Emperours, the Ecclesiasticall Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the Schoolemen, and other good VVriters a numbre. You haue falsifyed and mangled the very Text of holy Scripture, namely of S. Paule ☞*in one Chapter ix. times as the Reader maye see in the thirde Article fol. 107. and in certaine lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues folovving.<note place="margin">The Text of D. Hard. fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sified.</note> You haue Altered the Text of D. Harding, not vvhen you alleage his vvhole text alonge in the diuisions, as you cal them (for that you savve vvell, vvere to much open a legerde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine) but in the Text of your Ovvne Replie, vvhen you Repete his vvordes pecemele, to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute them. For there lo, sometime you adde a
<pb facs="8"/>
vvorde, and then dispute against your ovvne Addition (as Art. 3. fol. 62. b. 63. a) at other times you quite Alter his vvordes and meaning, and so you Replie against that vvhiche he neuer saied. This levvdenesse you haue committed in many and sondry places of this parte of your Replie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially in the .3. Article. Namely fol. 117. fiue ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in one place.<note place="margin">In the Letter I.</note> Other particularites of this your dealing are noted to the Reader in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of this booke. But brefely to geue you a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vve thereof, beholde M. Ievvell vvhat Authors and of hovve diuerse sortes you haue in so thicke Allegatyons Missealleaged, and Abused. I note you vvithall the leafe and page of this Booke, vvhere you shall finde them eche one so decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and proued to the eye.</p>
   <p>The holy Fathers by you thus vsed or rather misuded are.<note place="margin">Doctours Stories, and other good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors mis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sealleaged by M. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvell.</note>
   </p>
   <list>
      <label>S. Ciprian.</label>
      <item>Articulo. 3. fo. 70. b. Art. 4. fo. 76. a. 127. a. &amp;. b</item>
      <label>S. Basill.</label>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 122. b</item>
      <label>S. Ambrose.</label>
      <item>Art. 3. fol. 95. a</item>
      <label>S. Hierom.</label>
      <item>Art. 3. fol. 84.</item>
      <label>S. Chrysostom.</label>
      <item>Art. 1. fol. 39. Art. 3. fol. 90. Art. 4. fo. 83. a</item>
      <label>S. Augustin.</label>
      <item>Art. 3. fol. 70. a. Art. 4. fol. 57. a.</item>
      <label>Athanasius.</label>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 27.</item>
      <label>Leo.</label>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 152. b. 163. b. 176. a.</item>
      <label>S. Gregory.</label>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 3. a. fol. 141. a.</item>
      <label>S. Bernarde.</label>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 80. b.</item>
   </list>
   <p>The Historiographers, with whom also you haue so dealed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> are</p>
   <list>
      <pb facs="9"/>
      <label>Ruffinus.</label>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 121. a</item>
      <label>Socrates.</label>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 28. a</item>
      <label>Sozomenus.</label>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 131. a. 153. b</item>
      <label>Theodoretus.</label>
      <item>Art. 3. fol. 124. b. Art. 4. fol. 139. a. 160. b</item>
      <label>Cassiodorus.</label>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 159. a</item>
      <label>Beda.</label>
      <item>Art. 3. fol. 133. a</item>
      <label>Galfridus Monemuth.</label>
      <item>Art. 3. fol. 130. b</item>
   </list>
   <p>Other good Authors bothe olde and newe, whom you haue in like maner and with the like Sincerite alleaged, are.</p>
   <list>
      <item>
         <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Art. 3. fol. 90. a</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Liberatus.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 142. a. 155. a.</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Sulpitius</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Art. 3. fol. 100. a</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Gelasius</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 175. a</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Gennadius.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Art. 4. fol. 120. b</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Innocentius.</hi> 3.</item>
      <item>Art. 3. fol. 97. &amp; 98. a</item>
      <item>
         <hi>Eckius.</hi>
      </item>
      <item>Art. 3. fol. 87. a</item>
   </list>
   <p>VVhat Councells you haue in like maner falsified and Misalleaged, it maye be sene, Art. 1. fol. 28. b. 37. a. Art. 4. fol. 37. a. 40. b. 71. b. 74. b. In alleaging your Ciuill Lavves and decrees of the Canon lavve hovve you haue partly to a vvron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge vnderstanding dravven them,<note place="margin">Councels and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vves mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seallea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</note> either of your ovvne ignorance, or of lavvyers misse informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, partly quite mangled them and falsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied them, you maye beholde M. Ievvell, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the first, our Ansvver to your Replie cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Iustinians Constitution Art. 3. fol· 77. &amp; seq. and touching Appeales Art. 4. fol. 103. &amp; 104.
<pb facs="9"/>
concerning the later point, the lavves of Iustiniā Art. 4. fo. 51. a. 52. b. 53. b. of Honorious fo. 79. a. &amp; b. and the decrees Artic. 4. fol. 115. and. 176. b.</p>
   <p>The Schoolemen likevvise, Durandus,<note place="margin">Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused The Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se of M. Ievvelles so many and thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatyon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.</note> Art. 3. fo. 87. b. Thomas Aquinas. fol. 88. b. and Lyra. fo. 103. b. you haue Alleaged for your purpose, but falsely and Corruptely. By such falshood and Sleighte, you haue Multiplied your Allegatiōs, and furnished your booke vvith Quotations, not caring hovve or vvhat you brought, so that the Margyn vvere stuffed. These Quotatyons you vsed as a Call for birdes. VVith them you Tolled and Bayted your Reader. VVho taketh in gladly the Bayte of Authorite, but seeth not the Hooke of Falshood and Vntruthe vvherevvith you Choke him. For this purpose you haue a knacke to macke sundry Allegations vvhich are but one. As in the fourthe Article. fol. 6. a. you doe most Ambitiously. Also Artic. 1. fol. 27. and Art. 3. fol. 105. b. By such shevve of lerning you thought to vvinne credit. And vnder the Visarde of the Fathers and Coūcels, of Histories and Lavves, of Authors bothe olde and nevve, you thought to plaie the part of a Lerned VVriter and of a true Teacher. But the visarde being novv plucked of, your Vntrue Alleagatyons discouered, your Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novved Fethers pilled avvaye, you vvil remaine
<pb facs="10"/>
not only for opinion of good lerning as pilde as AEsops davve, but also for farder Credit off your VVorde, you vvill stande (I feare) for yanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keroute. Verely if Truthe maye preuaile, as she euer hath and vvill preuaile, you for your Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes (except you redresse them) are no more to be acompted for a Teacher of Truthe, but to be taken for (as S. Peter termeth suche) a Lying Master.</p>
   <p>Of your other yehauyour and Dealing M. Ievvel, if I should put you particularly in minde, vvhat faulte is there of an honest, discrete, and vpright vvriter to be auoyded, that you haue not incurred, and either Ignorantly or vvilfully committed? Your Ouersightes touching the Storie, Time, and Practise of the Churche are Greate and Many.<note place="margin">The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fightes of M. Ievvel.</note> I reporte you and the Reader to these places for example thereof Art. 3. fol. 82.83. b. Art. 4. fol. 39. b. 42. a. 44. b. 94. a. 140. b. 160. b. 162. b. 164. b. 174. b. Hovvbeit this maye procede of Ignorance, and is Excusable.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">He clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by heretikes.</note>But that you should Claime by Open Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Heretikes, and Builde your Proufes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their sayinges and doinges, vvhat Ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce can you here pretende, or vvhat Coulour off Excuse can you deuise? If you remembre you haue done no such thing, Cōsider I beseche you
<pb facs="10"/>
hovve Often and hovve Boldely you alleage the Arrians, their sayinges and doinges, in the fourthe Article against the lavvfull and devve Obedience, (practised by the Carholike bishops vvhom those Arrians persecuted) to Christes Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caire here in earthe, the bishop of Rome. For the readyer vevve hereof, and hovve also you Claime by the late Grekes, by Eutychiās and by Donatistes, these places noted may pointe vnto you. Art. 1. fol. 13. a. Art. 4. fol. 75. b. 97. b. 109.110.119. b. 120. a. &amp; b. 126. a. 130. b. 162. b. 163. a. 169. a. If suche Plea maye commende your Action, then must you seeke for an other Benche, and an other Courte. The Catholike Churche admitteth no such vvitnesses to speake or to geue euidence. VVe haue not so Lerned Christ, M. Ievvell. This point verely of all levvdenesse, is the levvdest.</p>
   <p>An other sleight or Crafte you haue to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroye a Truthe by telling a Truthe. Example vvhereof you maye beholde. Art. 4. fo. 160. a. and 161. a. By that meanes you make many longe Processes, to very shorte Purposes.</p>
   <p>Your maner of vvriting is beside so Dissolut Loose and Negligent,<note place="margin">His loose Maner of vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> or els your selfe so Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, in contradiction, that many times you are founde <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Contrary to your selfe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> sometime in plaine vvordes to Confute your selfe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> at other
<pb facs="11"/>
times by the force of your ovvne reasoning to be Cast in your ovvne Turne. For a vievve of particular examples in eche one of these faultes, I remitt you to these places. For the first, Art. 1. fo. 11, b. 31. b. Art. 2. fo. 50. b. Art. 4. fo. 62. a. 158. a. For the seconde, Art. 1. fol. 19. a. 25. a. 32. a. Art. 4. fol. 149. b. 150. a. For the thirde and laste. Art. 2. fo. 45. a. Art. 3. fol. 85. b. 111. b.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">His vvrō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and levvde maner of Reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note>Your maner of Reasoning, is so beside al Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and so Squarre from the Purpose, that the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof arise a huge and mayne Number of levvde and Fonde Argumentes, vvhich by the Force of your talke must nedes be Concluded. Verely no lesse fonde and foolish, then those vvhiche you made and framed your selfe also in your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie vnder the name of D. Hard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nges Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Only this is the difference. Those in your Replie vvere fathered of you vpon D. Harding vntruly (as it hath bene othervvhere declared vnto you) and vvere your ovvne,<note place="margin">By M. Ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stel .li. 2. cap. 4.</note> but made in sporte, or els to make sporte: These vvhich are to be founde in this Booke, are rightly youres, and of your selfe made in good earnest. I haue only brought them in to their Forme, and exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed them by the like. VVherein hovve vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I haue dealed, I make euery Indifferent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, yea your selfe M. Ievvell, if any Indifferency
<pb facs="11"/>
be in you, the Iudge. VVhere and in vvhat places these your levvde and fonde Argumentes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye be founde, bicause the number is not conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to be noted in this place, I remitt you to the Table of this Booke, and to the first letter of your ovvne Name therein. Other generall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of your levvde Dealing, or rather VVrā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling, you maye consider M. Ievvell (not to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you vvith longe serche thereof) Art. 1. fo. 4. b. 17. b. Art. 2. fol. 46. b. Art. 3. fol. 62. b. 121. b. Art. 4. fol. 3. a. 30. a. 56. b. 133. b. 185. a. 186. b.<note place="margin">His levv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de dealing and vvran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gling.</note> Many particular faultes might yet more be noted. But for a shorte vievve thereof, I remitt you M. Ievvell, or any other the Reader hereof to the Table of this booke, and the place, of it aboue saied. All vvhich layed together, euery Indifferent Reader and your selfe also shall see, except in suche thinges you can see and not see, that bothe for your Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true Allegatyons of the Fathers, the Councelles, the very text of holy Scripture, the Ecclesiastical histories, the Lavves and Decrees, and of other good Authors bothe Olde and Nevve, as also for your vnhonest and levvde dealing through your vvhole maner of vvriting, neither your Person is to be Credited, and muche lesse your doctrine to be tolerated.</p>
   <p>By this also it may appeare, that I haue right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="12"/>
Returned Vntruthes vpon you,<note place="margin">The Tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le of this booke.</note> and haue therefore not vvithout good Cause Intitled this my small labour. <hi>A Returne of Vntruthes vpon M. Iewell &amp;c.</hi> vvhich yet I haue so Intitled not only for this Cause, but also and that Principally bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Vntruthes vvhich in these Foure Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, to the Number of a Hundred tvventy and fyve, you haue charged and turned vpō D. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I haue discharged him thereof, and Rechar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged or Returned them vpon you againe. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nevvly Charged vpon you to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of certain hundreds, are suche as you haue committed in your Replie, in such places as you labour to Iustifie and to proue, that thinge, vvhich in the Margin of D. Hardinges text you noted for Vntruth. VVhich paynes you take not allvvaies, and therefore allvvaies I enter not to your Replie, but shortly do Iustifie the vntruthe, and so Returne it vpon you for a Slaunder. Only you take that paynes, vvhen the Vntruthe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth such a proufe or declaration: As vvhen it contayneth a Matter of Doctrine. And at suche times I enter your Replie, and vvhat I finde tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that vntruthe, I goe thourough vvith it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially in the thirde and fourthe Articles. In the other tvvo vvhy I do not so, the reason shall be geuen in my Preface to the Reader.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>But touching these Vntruthes,<note place="margin">Vpon vvhat groundes, M. Ievvell hath No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted D. Harding vvith Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes.</note> vvhich it hath liked you M. Ievvell in these foure first Articles to charge D. Harding vvithall, if vve shoulde Consider a litle your maner of Dealing therein, and somevvhat specifie the same, vvoulde it, trovve you, thereby appeare, that you did it, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Loue and Zele of Truthe it selfe, or els vpon good and substantial groundes moued thereunto? No truly. But directly the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For (as touching the first) vvhat Loue or Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le of Truthe can be presumed to haue bene he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein (I appeale but to all indifferent Readers) vvhen you note that for Vntruthe, vvhiche you coulde not be ignorant, vvas not the saying of D. Harding him selfe, but of his Author allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged then presently? Examples of this your Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Diligent Reader maye espie. Art. 1. fo. 10.26. and 29. Also Art. 3. fol. 120. b. Art. 4. fo. 48. b. For in these places, you note for vntruthes those vvordes vvhich are the very vvordes of S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom, of S. Augustin. Of Leontius, of Origen,<note place="margin">The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours ovvne sayinges are made D. Hardin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes.</note> and of the Nicene Councell out of Franciscus Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianus. All vvhich Authors being by D. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in those places alleaged, are noted by M. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvell to speake vntruly. If you vvoulde nedes note the matter for vntrue, you shoulde haue noted the vntruth M. Ievvel vpon such and such
<pb facs="13"/>
Authors, not vpon D. Harding. Novve vvhat shall I call that in you, grosse ignorance or vvill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dissimulation, vvhen you note those sayin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of D. Harding for Vntrue, vvhich are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry saiynges of other good Authors though not alleaged then presently? So you Note that for Vntruthe, yea and for a foule deprauation or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li scripture, vvhich is the very saying and doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of S. Hilary. Art. 2. fol. 48. b. The like you doe Art. 4. folio. 170. a. by a saying of Innocentius the first, defended also by S. Augustin. In these poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes M. Ievvell either you loued not the Truthe, or els you must confesse, you missed of the grounde thereof.</p>
   <p>
      <note place="margin">Vntruthes noted vpō a vvronge dissembled meaning of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</note>Againe vvhen you dissemble the Course of D. Hardinges treatyse, and vpon that Dissimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation do score vp Vntruthes, bicause that is not Concluded, vvhich in dede vvas not of him in that place Intended, can this your dissimulation procede of the zele and loue of Truthe? In the first Article, vvhen D. Hardinge alleaged Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, S. Dyonise, Iustinus Martyr and Ireneus, S. Basill and Chrysostom and last of all Cyrillus for proufe of the Sacrifice of the masse, you note vpon al these Allegatyons a number off vntru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, bicause (you saie there) <hi>those Doctours do speake of a Communion and not of Priuat Masse,</hi> vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reas
<pb facs="13"/>
yet (as I saied) they vvere expressely brought to proue the Sacrifice of the Masse not to proue priuat Masse. Of this your leude dealing you maye reade more particularly in this <hi>Returne</hi> Art. 1. fol. 4. b. But this your open and manifest dissimulation, can it (I appeale to your ovvne Conscience) procede of any Zele or loue of the Truthe? Did the Truth, I saie, moue you to note those Vntruthes? The like dissimulatyon you vse in a number of other Vntruthes, vvhich you haue scored vpon D. Harding, as the diligent Reader maye consider Art. 1. fol. 5. &amp; 6. a. folio. 9. b. 10. b. 17. b. Art. 2. fo. 53. a. Art. 3. folio. 117. b. 119. a. 121. a. 123. a. Artic. 4. fol. 185. a. 186. b. but especially in the same Article. fol. 2 b. and .3. a. vvhere you charge D. Harding though not with Vntruthe in the Margin, yet vvith a great Vntruthe in your text, as if he had nipped a saying of S. Gregory quite in the middest, scoffing also there at him, as if he had (you saie) the Choynecyngh &amp;c. and all that bicause (you saie in that place) <hi>D. Harding alleaged those wordes of S. Gregory to proue that the B. of Rome was called the Vniuersall bishop.</hi> vvhich thing in that place vvas not of him at all Intended, but an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Matter expressely taken in hande, as in that place (Art. 4. fol 2. b. and .3. a.) you maye beholde and see to the eye M. Ievvell. Novve this so open
<pb facs="14"/>
and greate dissimulation of youres, in scoring and charging of Vntruthes vpon D. Harding, hath it I saie on your part any Colour or Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, of any loue or zele of the Truthe? All the vvorlde seeth you did it to Deface, to Shame, and to discredit your Aduersary, vvhom other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvise you coulde not vvith any force of good Reason, any lerning, truth, probabilite or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite ouerthrovve.</p>
   <p>Other your Vntruthes scored vpon D. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding are such sayinges and Assertions, as not only D. Harding but all the Catholike Churche affirmeth and holdeth for assured verites of the Catholike Faithe.<note place="margin">Commō Verites of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, noted for spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes of D. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> You coulde not then iustly note them as speciall Vntruthes of D. Harding, as if they had bene of his ovvne Inuentyon, but if you vvoulde nedes score them vp for vntru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, you shoulde haue scored them vpon the vvhole Church of Christ, or (as you esteme that Churche,) vpon all Papistes in generall. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vve as you haue ordred the Matter, your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern do vaunte (as I haue heard some of them my selfe) that D. Harding hath committed this great number of vntruthes, him selfe by his ovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne negligence or vvilfulnesse. Such your vntru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes so noted maye shortly be sene. Art. 1. fol. 1. b. touching the name of Masse. fol. 6. b. 7. b. 8. a. 11.
<pb facs="14"/>
b. 20. a. and. b. 32. a. Art. 2. fol. 41. a. 43. a. 44. a. 54. b. 57. a. Art. 4. fol. 1. a. 58. b. 71. a. 111. a. 116.126. b. 134. a. 165. a. 170. a. &amp;c. By this vvaie you might note M. Ievvel a number of Vntruthes not only vpon all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike vvriters of these dayes, but also in the Olde Fathers and Doctours of Christes Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, vvho saie herein no lesse then vve saye, as v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon these your Vntruthes it hath bene here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. Againe these matters being betvvene you and vs in question and controuersy, you to proclaime them for vntruthes, it is to blovve the Triumphe before the Victory.</p>
   <p>But that in this your Singular Deuise of Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp Vntruthes, you rather sought meanes to fill vp the Score, then to boulte out the Truthe,<note place="margin">Vntruthes repeted to make vp the Score.</note> it maye vvel appeare by the repeting of one selfe Vntruthe, so often times. For some you repete foure times in one Article, as Art. 1. fol. 32. a. some other three times, as in the same Article fol. 40. b. and Art. 4. fol. 172. but many there are vvhiche you repete tvvise, only to make vp the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. As Art. 1. fol. 8. a. Art. 2. fol. 53. b. 54. b. Art. 3. fol. 123. b. Art. 4. fol. 19. By vvhich your dealing it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye easely appeare to any Indifferent Reader that in the great Number of these Vntruthes, you sought more the Number then the Truthe.</p>
   <p>To you therefore M. Ievvell that thus vntru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="15"/>
haue dealed, that so many vvaies haue betra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed your corrupted Affectyon, and Blotted your selfe so much, intending to Blemish your Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, I maye vvell ansvver vvith the vvise and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete saying of that Noble Philosopher Plato, vvherevvith he touched that Rude Reprocher Diogenes. <hi>Calcasti fastum Platonis, sed maiore fastu.</hi> Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I maye tell you, as in the Grand Senat off Rome it vvas tolde ones to a dissolut and ryo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous younge Man declayming sadly off Vertu, <hi>Quis te ferat cenantem vt Crassus,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Plutarchus in Catone Vticensi.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>aedificantem vt Lucullus, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentem vt Cato?</hi> VVho can abide thee, to lauish in sumptuous building as Lucullus, to ryot in bā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketyng as Crassus, and yet to talke sadly as an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cato? VVhich Reproche as he had right vvorthely before that Honourable Senat, for his extreme dissimulation and vvretched Hypocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se: so deserue you M. Ievvell in the estimation of all men to be taken, for a dissembler and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, you (I saie) that vvith such and so manifol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Vntruthes do charge other of vntruthe, and dealing your selfe most vntruly pretende to be a Singular proctour of Truthe. For vvho may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde you M. Ievvell, to Corrupt the Fathers as haue done olde heretikes, to scoffe like an other Lucyan, to lie as faste as an other Sinon, and yet to talke like a Teacher of Truthe, to preache like
<pb facs="15"/>
an other Paule, and to be a Comptroller of other mens Vntruthes? Blamers shoulde allvvaie be Blamelesse, and Fault finders ought of all right to be Faultelesse. Remembre the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Master Ievvell, that speaketh thus vnto you. <hi>Hypocrita, eijce primum trabem do oculo tuo,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.</note>
      <hi>&amp; tunc videbis eijcere festucam de oculo fratris.</hi> Thou Hypocrite, cast out first the beame out of thy ovvne eye, and then thou shalt see to pike out the mote of thy brothers eye. You M. Ievvell that note your brother of vntruthe, deale first your selfe Truly. Then shall you see better, vvhat is Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthe, and then maye you more boldely tell the other his faulte. Remoue avvaye first the mighty beame of your so many, so Notorious, and so Open Vntruthes. Then may you vvith a better face, pike avvaye the motes, the small er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and escapes, vvhich your brothers eye se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to haue.</p>
   <p>For like as the Sonne or Moone at their ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing or going dovvne,<note place="margin">
         <hi>A Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude.</hi>
      </note> vvhen either the Misty Morning vapours, or the euening falling devve dimmeth our sight betvvene, do seme to our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes much greater, then tovvarde none time or midnight vvhen mounting on highe they haue passed all such lettes: or like as the shining sonne beames yelde not their light so clere, vvhere a
<pb facs="16"/>
spotted glasse vvindovve standeth betvvene, as in the open fielde: so verely M. Ievvell your Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement being partly dimmed vvith a vvronge persuasyon of many Vntruthes, partly blinded vvith a corrupted Affection of Singularite, desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of Contradiction, or some other vvorse pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, can not so clerely Pearce to the true trial of the Truthe, and to descrie Vntruthe in others, as if your Iudgemēt vvere Vpright, and your Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction Clere. For novve the Case in you stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as vve see it dothe, euery light escape in D. Harding semeth a <hi>wilfull and Manifest Falsifying of the Author,</hi> euery true and Catholike propositiō, contrary to the humour of your Affection se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a <hi>Notorious and wilfull Vntruthe.</hi> Yea and of this it falleth out, that many times either you misse the true meaning of your Aduersary for vvante of Iudgement, or els dissemble it vtterly for no vvante of euil Affection, so to take Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and Matter of Vntruthe. Of this also it ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, that the Fathers ovvne saiynges, are D. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges Vntruthes. And to make matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, D. Harding is made to saie, that vvich he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer saied.</p>
   <p>Correct therefore your selfe M. Ievvell, and Amende that is amisse: Your greate Faultes I meane, vvhich in this preface you see Opened
<pb facs="16"/>
vnto you. VVhich for your ovvne sake I haue so Opened, that beholding them at the first so Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly layed for the, you might thinke either that you are in dede (vvhiche I promised at the first) brought somevvhat in the vvaie, to finde out the Truthe, vvhich so earnestly you pretend to seke after: or els that you are shortly admonis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed to Clere your selfe, and to teache vs the Truthe, if vve haue missed thereof. God sende you M. Ievvell, I hartely vvishe, a harty and earnest loue of the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, at perfect knovvledge the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof, and Grace from Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to teache other the same. Farre you vvel in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Stapleton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>