<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prefac to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105738_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01792</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11927</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105738</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prefac to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A discourse of the great crueltie of a widowe towardes a yong gentleman, and by what meanes he requited the same. Set forth in English verse by Iohn God</title>
                 <author>God, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Prefac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ark gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> in this little tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>atis, both fonde and affectionate loue, the one proceeding from a loyall and gentle hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther decked with ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tue, than follie, I say ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r adorned, &amp; beautified with <hi>Venus</hi> mild and gentle behauiour, than enuironned with the deadly and spitefull rage of <hi>uno</hi>: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from a disdainefull and loths<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>me sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke puffed vp with too muche superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vnder the coloure of mecke humilitie. with vainglorie, vnder the shadowe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie: with disdaine, vnder the pretence of perfect and sounde chastitie. They that haue passed the most part of their time in humaine follies, and haue rather foll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>wed the vanities of fooles and insensuate louers in matters of loue (and the contemplation of heau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nlie things, or else of those that here on earth may giue some entrie for man to attaine glory and honour of his name) they I say shall serue mee
<pb facs="3"/>
for witnesses to confirme the opinion of long time rooted in the fansies of men, which is, that the beautie &amp; comely fauour of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is the most true and natural Adaman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that can be found, sith the same stone (for a certaine attractiue power and agreable qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie therin enclosed) doth not better draw the iron, than a woman doth by a certaine hidden force, whiche rysing vnder the allurement of hir, draweth vnto it the heartes and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, which hath made manie beleeue, that the same only essence was sent to vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe to serue bothe for mennes torment and ioy togither. But yet there is another thing of greater wonder, it is not to heare tell that <hi>Paris</hi> forsooke, <hi>Troy</hi> to go visite <hi>Helena</hi> in <hi>Grece,</hi> that <hi>Hercules</hi> had giuē ouer his mace to handle the distaffe at the commaundement of a woman, or that <hi>Salomon</hi> was s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tted in his wisdome to dallie with those which made him a voluntarie slaue. But that a woman of whom a man had receiued no fauour nor curtesie, had forgotten hir duetie to hir seruaunt, if it seeme not straunge, I knowe not what to call wonderfull or maruellous. If defence of speeche for loue, is not deemed suche whereby man is different from brute beastes: (for reason is altogither r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>fuse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ers) and notwithstā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="3"/>
our Fathers haue seene the example of that vertue no long time paste in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of a Gentleman, verie wise and wel trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in other thinges, a case so straunge, as declaring the singular force of nature in that matter, wherein shee seemeth to haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the preferment aboue all things in the earth. Examples hereof is the effemination of <hi>Hercules,</hi> the depriuation of <hi>Sampsons</hi> force, the losse of sense, and the Idelatrie of the famous and wise King <hi>Salomon,</hi> and the simplicitie of a warelesse &amp; vncircumspecte Gentleman, of whome yee shall reade in the Historie following. Marke I say, (gentle Reader) howe fortune dealeth with them, which trusting in their force, despise (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of that whiche they doe them selues) the little portion whiche they iudged to bee in others. If the vaineglorie and arrogant presumption of a chastitie impregnable, had not deceiued the Gentlewomanne fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in this Treatise, if the sugred hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of golde had not blinded hir, it coulde not haue bin knowne wherein hir incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie consisted, not in the minion delites and alluring toyes of a passionate Louer, but in the couetous desire of filling hir purse, and hypocriticall glorye of praise a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ngs
<pb facs="4"/>
menne: Notwithstanding, you shall see the gaine whiche shee made; to serue hir turne nothing at all, but to the perpetuall reproche of hir name, and raysed a slaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, suche as ill speakers and enimies of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menkinde do burden that sex withall. But the fault of one whiche by hir owne presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion disceiued hir selfe, ought not to obscure the glorie of so manye vertuous, faire, and honest dames, who by their chastitie, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie and curtesie, bee able too deface the blot of follie, couetousnesse, and crueltie of this Gentlewoman heere, and of all other that doe resemble hir: notwithstanding in the ende reconciling hir selfe, and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the foolishe fantasie of hir former life, with an ordinarie greefe of him whiche ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued hir for a spurre too hir conscience, and continually forced hir too thinke, that the force of a man is lesse than nothing where God work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th not by his grace, who failing in vs, our wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>kes can sauor but of the stenche and corruption of our nature, wherein it tumbleth and tosseth as the sow in the pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles of dirt and mire. This breefe discourse giueth lessons vnto Louers to auoide the imm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>derate pangues of loue, it doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> the indiscretion of promised pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce,
<pb facs="4"/>
it warneth to beware all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> heastes, least the penalties of couetous<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="4 letters">
         <desc>••••</desc>
      </gap> and vaineglory be incurred, whiche shall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest it selfe, if you marke the sense thereof in Reading. And that the same might the more delighte thee, I haue turned it into simple verse, according as my capacitie woulde serue, but notwithstanding take it in worth, which I know to be full of errors, and not so eloquent as you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, nor so dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable as I wold desire. Thus greeting thee, I bid thee farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>