<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ The true Coipe of a letter which the faith∣full in suffolke made &amp; gaue it vnto Ni∣colas Shaxton when he had recā∣ted in London and came to Hadley to declare the same.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105139_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19657</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6083</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105139</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ The true Coipe of a letter which the faith∣full in suffolke made &amp; gaue it vnto Ni∣colas Shaxton when he had recā∣ted in London and came to Hadley to declare the same.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The confutation of. xiii. articles, wherunto Nicolas Shaxton, late byshop of Salilburye [sic] subscribed and caused to be set forth in print the yere of our Lorde. M.C.xlvi [sic] : whe [n] he recanted in Smithfielde at London at the burning of mestres Anne Askue, which is liuely set forth in the figure folowynge. In the nexte page shalt thou finde the contentes of thys little boke</title>
                 <author>Crowley, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mierdman (Mierdmans, Nuyts), Steven</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 <distributor>Day, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Seres, William 1</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>160 pages, folded woodcut plates, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>❧ The true Coipe of a letter which the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in suffolke made &amp; gaue it vnto Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas Shaxton when he had recā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in London and came to Hadley to declare the same.</head>
   <p>A Wonderfull dreade maie be vnto the cōscience, of those which are in daunger of the threateninge that Christe speaketh in the Gospel of Luke the .xvii. chap. that sayth. It is vnpossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that offences should not come, but vnto hym by whom they come, it were better for hym: that a mylstone were hāged about his necke, &amp; be caste into the sea, thē that he shold ossend one of these littleons, Oh Shaxton, shaxtō, take hede to your self now, although you haue in your recātation saied you were not perfectly sene in the scripture. Yet howe can you excuse your selfe but that you be the offêder of many a pore soule. But now you saye, ye are better learned thê you were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Well seyng that you haue bene so wel scholled sithence you went to Lōdon, it may be well gathered that you were simply lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned afore. And yet to saye the trueth, youre learninge is not greatly augmented sithēce.
<pb facs="8"/> For these be the doctrines of men, and not of the holy Gost that ye haue now set forth in your recātatiō which ye wold that we shold earnestly beleue and folowe, not one title of the lyuelye worde of God, haue ye authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed your dreaming articles withal vnto the whiche blessed. S. Paule, woulde that we should gyue no credite althonghe you were an Angell of heauen and had spoken them. Oh merciful Lord thou that hast all grace, it is thou that canst &amp; maist illumine the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of all menne. So that they shall not deny the trueth. We besech the, O Lord euē for the trueth sake, graunte that thys loste shepe may come home agayne to thy graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouse folde not fearinge the worldly punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of princes &amp; rulers, but boldelye to cōfesse with al the holy prophetes and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles thy eternal wysdome whiche thou hast cōmaunded thy son the bishop &amp; onely saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of our soules Iesu Christ to declare. And that with thy sernaunte Peter he maye weepe bitterlye for that he hathe denied the, which art our gratiouse God. Oh Shaxtō Shaxton praye to oure mercifull God that he may geue the hys grace againe. For ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by the are offended whose cōscience be so assured in Gods trueth, that nother fyre, nor h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>er can plucke it oute of theyr hertes. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in scilēce they do mourne, yet thinke
<pb facs="9"/> not but those newe vessels whiche are fille<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> with new wine must nedes haue hys vente. You know that if we should hold our peace the stones in the streate, wyl speke to declare the glorye of oure eternal god. Yea ye haue brought your self in such case, that none wil trust you, which is illuminate with christes veritie. Oh Shaxton weye in your cōsciēce And marke well to thend what glory to our Lord god thou shouldest haue offred, if thou haddest stād strong in the vndoubted trueth of God &amp; ended thy life in that thou tokeste in hāde, thou stodest manfully to cōdēnatiō. Alas whi didest thou not perceiner, thou sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest at thy departing frō vs, whē thou were sēt for to London, that either thou wouldest burne, or els forsake Gods trueth. In dede thou prophesiedest truly, but it was more to preserue thy fleshe, thē to honour the eternal god with thy deth, thou fearedest thē the vn quēchable fire that iseuerlasting. Thou stō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleist at the stone, wher other wyth a strōge fayth wēt ouer. Thou forsokest this, but we pray God that for it thou findest not death euerlastinge. Thou laideste thy hande vnto Gods plough, but thou lokedest backward Thou deniedest thy onelye sauioure before mē, yea thou waste ashamed of him &amp; of his word. Thou haste vtterly forsakē the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corner stone, whiche thy fayeth should haue
<pb facs="9"/> bent coupled wholy to it, it is to be thought that sit hence your laste scholyng at London thou hast betrayed the innocent bloud.</p>
   <p>Alas Shaxton remembre that our sauioure Christ in al the holy scriptures, nor yet none of hys Apostles hathe promised vs in thys life to lyue wythoute anye trouble in thys worlde, but for his wordes sake to be called a reprobat, a seditious persō, an heritike one that goeth aboute to make insurrection these with such other names must hys elect suffer, so to be called of the worlde for the settinge forth of Christes doctrine, you knowe what S. Paul sayth. Al that is writtē is writtē for our learnyng &amp; cōfort. The wyse man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth his sonne, to prepare him selfe vn to tribulatiō when he shoulde enter into the waie of the Lord, you shold haue sate downe as Christe geueth coūsaile and haue cast the accomptes what the buildinge woulde haue cost. But Oh Shaxton thon walkest on the water wyth Peter a little tyme, trustynge to much to thine owne strengthe, ye had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gottē the counsaile of. S. Iames. which say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Who that lacketh wisdome let him axe it of God. The thinge that was not in you that ye thought that ye had had. But blessed is our mercifull God that hath euidētly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his manifeste trueth of his worde ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge the knoweledge of it to the vnlearned
<pb facs="10"/> and very babes, &amp; hath hid these thinges frō the prudent &amp; wise of this world, yea youre doctors, bishops or what name so euer they haue, are manie tymes wythout this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Euē as those doctors, lawiers, which disputed with Christ, not knowyng what to say to him, so far were they of frō his know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge. So do ye whiche are of that religion tomble &amp; tosse the scriptures, loking to your liyng prophetes, fātasies &amp; dreames, &amp; what ye imagin in your deuillish braynes cōtrary to Gods holy worde, that same are we pore subiectes cōpelled to beleue in paine of hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; fyre. But as the true prophete of God sayeth. Ye grope in the daye &amp; will fynde no light, ye walke not circūspectly as mē wise. Ye wāder after vanities to put Gods word to silence. Ye compasse with your flatteryng kynges &amp; gouernours to your diabolical lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, ye are those that cri peace, peace, &amp; make al the strife, &amp; with your subtil inuentiōs ye do asmuche as lyeth in you to frustrate the glory of God. But this we say: do make, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe what ye can: yet is Gods trueth graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in our hertes, &amp; faythfully we do beleue it that the Lorde whiche onelye hath died for our sinnes, &amp; as touching his māhode sitteth on the right hād of God our father in he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, this Lord we say, is able to defende hys owne cause, whoe wyl at his pleasure beate
<pb facs="10"/> you to powder, &amp; in the meane time we shall be cōtent to beare the words of the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle in our hertes. Nos autem gloriari o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet in cruce domini nostri Iesu Christi.</p>
   <p>And we remēbre his godly lessōs, that those which wil liue deuoutly in Iesu Christ, must suffer persecutiō. Well Shaxton the liuinge God that sitteth in heauē geue the hys holy spirite in the knowledge of hys worde, and strōglye as a champiō of Christe to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto the battaile fyghtyng vnder hys baner. If thou lose this temporal life (which is but vaine pleasures) yet a better is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the which neuer shall faile. Oh Shaxtō, lette these sayinges of Christ perse into thy conscience, and doubte not but that erroure which is in the brought in by the deuyll and his ministers shall be to quietnes &amp; reste.</p>
   <p>Take hede that thy housse be cleane swepte Thy own cōscience shal beare the recorde.</p>
   <p>Thus art thou writtē vnto, for great care is taken for thy fall, yet rise vp againe &amp; be of good confort there is mercy with the Lorde. The game shal go on thy side, Christ hathe promised he is true therfore beleue him. We besech the Oh Shaxtō, do this much for vs euē for Christes sake: Let it be knowē to the magestrates &amp; to al those that be in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnder the kynges magestie hauing suche vrgēt matters cōmitted vnto theyr wisdome
<pb facs="11"/> how the cōsciēces of manie as yet be vnstai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, seynge the commaundemētes, Articles, &amp; actes be void of gods holy word. We se my Lord of Winchesters boke very feble &amp; yōg to cōfute Gods trueth withal. It is no fyne threde of holy scripture, but rather bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ble twine in make torches to honoure his Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or idols withal. We do not doubt but it is thought (amōg such as he is) that with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue brought to pas a pleasan̄t sacrifice to God the burning of Christes testamētes with other Godly new bokes whiche as yet they were neuer able to answer by the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. This O Shaxtō thou knowest aswell as we. But after this &amp; suche other meanes they stop y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> swet springes that lead vs to the head foūtaine Iesu Christ. In this they play the Philistiās parte that stopt vp Abrahams wels. But we pray daily vnto our merctfull God which hath al mens hertes in his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, to reueile to the kinges magestie more of their subtile inuētiōs that he mai perceiue theyr crafty iuglinges. As king Darius did thorow the worckynge of God by hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Daniell. Thus the lyuynge Lorde by whom all mercy cometh sende hys maiestye longe lyfe and quietnes boeth of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and soule.</p>
   <trailer>Finis,</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>