<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105079_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12220</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5778</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105079</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Essayes or rather, Encomions : prayses of sadnesse: and of the emperour Iulian the Apostata. By Sir William Cornewallis, the younger knight</title>
                 <author>Cornwallis, William, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Purslowe, George</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hawkins, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Classical authors</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F those precepts that aduise the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting of the infirmities of the mind, haue bin euer more safe and sweet, thē theirs that like laws hold their peace vntil they haue them in their power, and then plucke them vp by the roots: is he that prescribes temperance be the best Physicion: hee the best Pilot that foresees a storme: he the best States-man, that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stands the dangers of his Countrey in their bud and greennesse: and in a word they the happiest Counsellors, that seeke to keep vs out of the contingency of perill: it is not impossible (Reader) but I may be of some vse to thee: But I prayse <hi>Sadnesse,</hi> so doth the Physicion his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, which howsoeuer thy taste abhorres, thy reason desires, and being once downe, thou art content to forget the lothsomnesse, and regard the operation. I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my prescription to thee no further, then that it cannot hurt; what good it may doe, let thy experience resolue thee; which the warranty of the safety may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite thee to: If it wants those graces and embellish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that he hath need of, that aduentures on an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouation; let a plaine true tale be accepted better then a
<pb facs="3"/> filed falshood; especially since through the cloud of mine Ignorance truth shewes thee light enough, to direct thy way, though not to delight thee in thy iourney: I seeke not honour from thee, nor am I the subiect of thine opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; thy censure shall onely concerne thy selfe: for mee, though I should hold my cloake the faster for the winde; yet shall I neuer yeeld it to the Sunne; he that feeles not their present power, needes not feare the future, and I am armed against both, either with a knowledge or a dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of proofe: And so I leaue thee to thine owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment if thou hast one; or if thou hast not, to liue like the Moale by hearing: <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>