<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Thomas Brabine Gent. in praise of the Author.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105808_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02133</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12272</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Thomas Brabine Gent. in praise of the Author.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Menaphon : Camillas alarum to slumbering Euphues, in his melancholie cell at Silexedra. VVherein are deciphered the variable effects of fortune, the wonders of loue, the triumphes of inconstant time. Displaying in sundrie conceipted passions (figured in a continuate historie the trophees that vertue carrieth triumphant, maugre the wrath of enuie, or the resolution of fortune. A worke worthie the youngest eares for pleasure, or the grauest censures for principles. Robertus Greene in Artibus Magister)</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, Sampson.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>Thomas Brabine Gent. <hi>in praise of the Author.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>COme foorth you witts that vaunt the pompe of speach,</l>
      <l>And striue to thunder from a Stage-mans throate:</l>
      <l>Uiew <hi>Menaphon</hi> a note beyond your reach;</l>
      <l>Whose sight will make your drumming descant doate:</l>
      <l>Players auant, you know not to delight;</l>
      <l>Welcome sweete Shepheard, worth a Schollers sight.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <hi>Smirna</hi> is drie, and <hi>Helicon</hi> exhal'd,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Caballian</hi> founts haue left their springing sourse,</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Parnassus</hi> with his Lawrell stands appal'd;</l>
      <l>And yet <hi>His</hi> Muse keepes on her wonted course:</l>
      <l>Wonted said I? I wrong his paines too much,</l>
      <l>Since that his pen before brought foorth none such.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>One writes of loue, and wanders in the aire;</l>
      <l>Another stands on tearmes of trees and stones:</l>
      <l>When heauens compare yeeldes but the praise of faire,</l>
      <l>And christ all can describe but flesh and bones:</l>
      <l>Yet countrey swaynes, whose thoughts are faith and troth,</l>
      <l>Will shape sweete words of wooll and russet cloth.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Mongst whom if I my <hi>Tityrus</hi> should chuse,</l>
      <l>Whose warbling tunes might wanton out my woes;</l>
      <l>To none more oftner would my solace vse,</l>
      <l>Than to his Pastoralls their mortall foes.</l>
      <l>Sweete verse, sweete prose, how haue you pleasde my vaine?</l>
      <l>Be thou still <hi>Greene,</hi> whiles others glorie waine.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>