<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶Robert Copland the translatour herof to the Reders.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1542</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105904_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02340</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12468</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105904</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶Robert Copland the translatour herof to the Reders.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The questyonary of cyrurgyens : with the formulary of lytell Guydo in cyrurgie, with the spectacles of cyrurgyens newly added, with the fourth boke of the Terapentyke [sic], or methode curatyfe of Claude Galyen prynce of physyciens, with a synguler treaty of the cure of vlceres, newely enprynted at London, by me Robert wyer, and be for to sell in Poules Churcheyarde, at the sygne of Judyth. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum</title>
                 <author>Guy, de Chauliac</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyer (Wyre), Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1542</date>
                 <distributor>Bankes, Richard</distributor>
                            <distributor>Tab (Dabbe), Henry</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>240 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶Robert Copland the translatour herof to the Reders.</head>
   <p>GEntyll reders in consydera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion that euery scyence, arte, and faculte that are speculate &amp; practysed by Phylosophers, nat one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ought to be shewed and taught vnto suche as be present with them in theyr dayes, but also for a {per}petuall benefyte to be set forth by wrytynges vulgarily in euery tongue, for the more eredines and erudycyon of all yonge and pregnaunt practycyens, as fayne wolde attayne to the perfytenes of euery suche scyence, arte, and fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culte. And nat withstandynge that there be ryght many and sondry sortes, aswell of very good and scyentyke bokes, as of ryght expert men within this Realme in the scyentycall arte of Cyrurgery. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles this lytell questyonary &amp; formulary with the other bokes added therto haue ben often requyred and soughte for, to be had in englysshe (aswell of me as of other) by dyuers and many persones of the sayde scyence. In consyderacyon aforesayd, and that it is cōmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyous, vtyle, behouefull, and benefycyall to the cōmon welth of the sayde scyence and arte. A certayne yonge gentyll man enured in the sayd scyence haue a boke of the same in frenche moued the ryght ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nest {per}sone Henry Dabbe bybliopolyst &amp; stacyoner to haue it transla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in to englysshe. At whose instigacyon meanynge the help of God (though moste rudely) with the symplenes of a good wyllyng herte I haue enterprysed to do it in folowynge dyrectly my copy. For I knowlege myne enernyte in pronoūcyng the englysshe of the names and termes naturally expressed in the sayde boke, aswel in greke, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne, &amp; other, whiche myne aucthour hath nat reduced in to frenche, which names and termes I cōmyt to the dyscrecyon, emendacyon, and grauyte of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>em that haue the perfytenesse of the sayde scyence and facultie. For as Phylyatros sayeth, many termes and names that are symply spoken in one language and scyence is harde to be spoken in an other, except they be expressed, and what they signyfye. wherfore curteys and gentyll reders take this in worth, and desyst myne ygnoraunce in the same with your scyentycall beneuolence, aud clere fronysate intellygence. And Iesus preserue you. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>