<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105170_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09745</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20005</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105170</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Ten sermons preached by that eloquent divine of famous memorie, Th. Playfere Doctor in Divinitie</title>
                 <author>Playfere, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Legge (Legg), Cantrell</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 270 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat a losse the Church of God had by the death of <hi>D. Playfere,</hi> I had rather the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world should determine, then my slender penne attempt to expresse. If euer those combinations of Vertue and Learning, of Knowledge and Vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance, of Wit and Memorie, of Reading and Vse, of Holesome and Delightfull, of Schoole and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>lpit, of Old and New, or in one word to say, of Nature and Ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>strie, of hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ne felicite and heauenly grace, concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make a Scribe perfect and absolute to the kingdome of God; we may not be so much our own back-friends (though we detract not from the fortune os places further off) nay w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> may not so impeach the honour of the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>er, nor disparage the worth of our friend
<pb facs="4"/>
departed, as to doubt but this was principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifested in <hi>M. Playfere.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Who b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>cause he was but lent the world for a time, nay because he was redemaunded soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then his time, (if it were lawfull to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll the heauenly w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>sedome with that word <hi>Sooner,</hi> but I meane in regard of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vse, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>t same <hi>propter vos,</hi> which<note place="margin">Phil. 1. 24.</note> made the Apostle to demur) I say since he was to be returned back againe to his maker, and ouer-ripe perfection not to continue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, it had beene to be wished, he had left behind him some more monuments of his trauails, as wel comfortable to the suru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>uers, as honourable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>o himselfe. Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ch whether he in his discretion, and because he had so resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, was nice to doe, after the example of them that would write nothing, though verie able, or was then a doing most when God cal'd him, I cannot say. This which the good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will be loath perhaps to heare, I may not conceale, that these are the last of all his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours which are like to be divulged. Into so small a compasse is that spirit now ranged, as to be as she sayes,<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ud Proper. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>. 12.</note>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>En sum quod digitis quinque leuatur onus,</hi> or indeede not so much as a iust handfull,
<pb facs="4"/>
which lately was not cōfinable with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n bounds too great for me to speake of.</p>
   <p>But the summe is this: (For I list not to defend his method of preach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ng against the Method-masters of our age, who me thinkes should knowe either that of the Apostle, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitas donorum est, sed vnus spiritus:</hi> or that of the Prophet, <hi>Laudate eum in tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, laudate in cithara:</hi> or if nothing will please them but what they doe themselues, we must be faine to say as Crassus did to Scevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>nium igitur conciones tu confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies vnus, omnes ad te sub tempus veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emus, &amp;c.</hi>) I say the summe is this: that as the Sun-light is pleasantest toward the set, &amp; the skilfull eare finds most store os musike in the close: so this Sunne, this Swan, this sweet singer of Israel, (for what lesser tearmes can our loue affoard him? if any bring more we will not refuse them) his last monuments, and his last labours, that the world may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hope for, shall finde we trust the dearer intertainment.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>