<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A tutti i Gentilhvomini Inglesi che si di lettano de la lingva Italiana, Salute e pace in Christo.</title>
           <author>F., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1578</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105629_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00990</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11096</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105629</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A tutti i Gentilhvomini Inglesi che si di lettano de la lingva Italiana, Salute e pace in Christo.</title>
                 <author>F., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Florio his firste fruites : which yeelde familiar speech, merie prouerbes, wittie sentences, and golden sayings. Also a perfect induction to the Italian, and English tongues, as in the table appeareth. The like heretofore, neuer by any man published</title>
                 <author>Florio, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1578</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 163, 1 leave, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="it">Italian</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dictionaries, vocabularies, phrase books, instruction in foreign languages</term>
                    <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_English_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <div xml:lang="ita" type="version">
      <head>¶ A tutti i Gentilhvomini Inglesi che si di lettano de la lingva Italiana, Salute e pace in Christo.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ar<seg rend="sup">mi</seg> mjèi Signori, qvantunqve che molti per l'adje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro habbino cerco, (con longo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po, e grā fatica) di demostrar la vera e grande Eccelentia de la lingva Italiana (veramente degna di èsser da ciascadun amata.) Io credo, e so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no persvaso, che à pochi sia dato qvel dono, &amp; qvella gratia di farlo, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piutamente come merita. Peróse in tutto non hó compjuto il vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stro desiderio, io spero che leggjèrmente mi perdonerete, non ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gvardādo alla mia basezza. Ma al mio bvon volere, il qvale è<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stato, e sarámentre che vivo, pronto a servirvi in ogni cosa che io possa: tutta via esort ando tutti qvelli che si dilettano de la No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billingva Italiana, á perseverar constantemènte in essa, e cercar diligentementè, con il tempo, &amp; con la fatica, di condur la vostra navicèlla in porto salvo, con superar tutte le onde contrarje à es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa, e non straccarsi, &amp; restar per strada, come fanno molti hoggi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, che comincjano, è vogliono far il bravo, che è, che non é, indue, ó tre di sono lenti, e strachi, &amp; se hanno due parole di spagnivolo, tre di franzese, è qvantro di Italiano pensano d'aver assai. Ma io vi prego che tutta via vogliate perseverare in essa, arricordan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovi che molte sono le comodità che ne rjéscono à qvelli che la hanno perfettamente, voi troverete qvi in qvesta operetta delle bèlle sentènze, gentili proverbij, varij detti, con certe domande con le loro risposte, necessarie, è profittevole, per il gentil scolare di essa con certe regole à modo di Gramatica con le qvali in bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve tèmpo potete imparar la lingva benissimo. M ricordatevi se hò errato di perdonarmi perche nō è la mia professione, &amp; qvel
<pb facs="6"/>
ch'io ho fatto, lo feci solamente in principjo per compjacèr a vno amico mio privato perche s'io hauessi saputo che doveva venir in stampa aréi tenuto altro modo, ma ora non ci é rimédjo pero pregovi a pardonarmi. Ecosicésso di pjù darvi fasti dio humilmente bacjandovi le mani, vi lascjo con Dio il qval da mal vi gvardi Restate sani, <hi>V.</hi> per Sempre.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>G. F.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
   <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <head>¶ Ʋnto the friendly, curteous, and indifferent Reader.</head>
      <p>
         <hi>
            <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost curteous Reader,</hi> at the request of sundrie my friendes: I here present to thee my first fruites, although not altogether ripe: The which I pray thee to accept in good and friendly parte, &amp; weigh my good will. It is done very simply and that is because I haue no lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I haue kept no order because I did not thinke it should haue come to light: As for the pronoūcing of it, with little labour maist thou attaine to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of it. Therefore remember my good wyll which if I see it be well accepted I aske no more, if it be not, I am the more sorie, if you profit any thing by it, I promise thee a better, and that shortly, if not here I end, and so committing thee to God, I bid thee farewell. From his lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in Woster place.</p>
      <closer>
         <signed>Thine to commaund. I. F.</signed>
      </closer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>