<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Publisher's Advertisement to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1636</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105167_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10378</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20652</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105167</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Publisher's Advertisement to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tubus historicus : an historicall perspective; discovering all the empires and kingdomes of the vvorld, as they flourisht respectively under the foure imperiall monarchies. Faithfully composed out of the most approved authours, and exactly digested according to the supputation of the best chronologers. (With a catalogue of the kings and emperours of the chiefe nations of the world.) By the late famous and learned knight Sir Walter Raleigh</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Harper, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Fisher, Benjamin</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1636</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28 pages, portraits, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The Publisher's Advertisement to the Reader.</head>
   <p>THis excellent Piece (modell to that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Worke, <hi>The History of the World</hi>) being an exquisite Abstract and Summary of all the famous Kingdomes and Empires that ever were; how worthy it is of publick view, will soon appeare to a discerning judgement. In this suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct Recollection is contrived (by a <hi>Daedalean</hi>
      <note n="*" place="margin">Autor opus laudat. Ovid. de Ponto lib. 4 Eleg. 9.</note> Hand) the <hi>Apotelesma</hi> and effect of infinite Volumes; the
<pb facs="4"/>
Originall, Progresse, and Duration of the most Glorious Monarchies &amp; flourishing States of the World. A Synopsis so mainly conducent and essentially necessary to the right understanding of all Sacred and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Histories, as without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct thereof (the like being never yet extant in English) small benefit can accrew to ordinary Readers. To reduce such a World of Matter, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to so compendious Forme, can be adiudg'd no lesse then an <hi>Herculean</hi> taske. But of This, vulgar Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities are as incompetent Iudges, as blinde Men of Colours. This Perspective is not fitted to the dull sight of Self-opinionate Ignaroês. To the intelligent and judicious Peruser, if it prove a gratefull worke
<pb facs="4"/>
(as to such, undoubtedly it will) the Publication may be justly reputed <hi>Operae pretium. Ave (mi Lector) &amp; fave huic Opellulae:</hi> cui intùs Ambrosia.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>