<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the VVorshipfull and worthy Captaine, Martin Pring, Commander of the Sea Nauy of the East-India Com∣pany in India.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105066_Ba1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19313</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5727</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105066</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the VVorshipfull and worthy Captaine, Martin Pring, Commander of the Sea Nauy of the East-India Com∣pany in India.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Virginia's God be thanked, or A sermon of thanksgiving for the happie successe of the affayres in Virginia this last yeare. Preached by Patrick Copland at Bow-Church in Cheapside, before the Honorable Virginia Company, on Thursday, the 18. of Aprill 1622. And now published by the commandement of the said honorable Company. Hereunto are adjoyned some epistles, written first in Latine (and now Englished) in the East Indies by Peter Pope, an Indian youth, borne in the bay of Bengala, who was first taught and converted by the said P.C. And after baptized by Master Iohn Wood, Dr in Divinitie, in a famous assembly before the Right Worshipfull, the East India Company, at S. Denis in Fan-Church streete in London, December 22. 1616</title>
                 <author>Copland, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                            <distributor>Sheffard, William</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 36, 8 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="23"/>
   <head>To the VVorshipfull and worthy Captaine, <hi>Martin Pring,</hi> Commander of the Sea Nauy of the East-India Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in <hi>India.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>I Shal peraduenture seeme bold (most Illustrious <hi>Mecoenas</hi>) daring to trouble your learned eares with this rude Epistle, but your humanity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all, and beneuolent loue toward the learned incouraged me, though the least of the learned, yet most desirous of learning, and a louer of learned men, to present vnto you these first fruits of my wit, and first tryall in the latine tongue; to the end I may testifie how much I loue both you and the excellent gifts and graces of God bestowed vpon you. Now if you will bee pleased to take in good part, and haue respect to these vnpolished lines, you may perhaps ore it bee long, expect from the some more learned and better digested Letters. Farewell Worshipfull Sir.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From the <hi>Iames</hi> Royall <date>.22. Ianuary 1619.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>