<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In laudem Authoris, Distichon amoris.</title>
           <author>Uchear, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105808_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02133</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12272</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In laudem Authoris, Distichon amoris.</title>
                 <author>Uchear, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Menaphon : Camillas alarum to slumbering Euphues, in his melancholie cell at Silexedra. VVherein are deciphered the variable effects of fortune, the wonders of loue, the triumphes of inconstant time. Displaying in sundrie conceipted passions (figured in a continuate historie the trophees that vertue carrieth triumphant, maugre the wrath of enuie, or the resolution of fortune. A worke worthie the youngest eares for pleasure, or the grauest censures for principles. Robertus Greene in Artibus Magister)</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, Sampson.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>In laudem Authoris, <hi>Distichon amoris.</hi>
   </head>
   <lg>
      <l>DElicious words, the life of want on wit,</l>
      <l>That doo enspire our soules with sweete content;</l>
      <l>Why haue your father <hi>Hermes</hi> thought it fit</l>
      <l>My eyes should surfet by my hearts consent?</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Full twentie Summers haue I fading seene,</l>
      <l>And twentie <hi>Floras</hi> in their golden guise:</l>
      <l>Yet neuer viewd I such a pleasant <hi>Greene</hi>
      </l>
      <l>As this, whose garnisht gleades, compare denies.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Of all the flowers a <hi>Lillie</hi> once I lou'd,</l>
      <l>Whose labouring beautie brancht it selfe abroade;</l>
      <l>But now old age his glorie hath remoud,</l>
      <l>And Greener obiectes are my eyes aboade.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>No countrey to the downes of <hi>Arcadie,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Where <hi>Aganippes</hi> euer springing wells</l>
      <l>Doo moyst the meades with bubling melodie;</l>
      <l>And makes me muse, what more in <hi>Delos</hi> dwelles;</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>There feedes our <hi>Menaphons</hi> celestiall Mus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>,</l>
      <l>There makes his pipe his pastorall reporte;</l>
      <l>Which strained now a note aboue his vse,</l>
      <l>Foretels, he'le nere more chaunt of <hi>Choas</hi> sporte.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Reade all that list, and reade till you mislike;</l>
      <l>Condemne who can, so enuie be no iudge:</l>
      <l>Noreede can swell more higher, lesse it shrike.</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Robin</hi> thou hast done well, care not who grudge.</l>
   </lg>
   <signed>HENRIE V<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>CHEAR Gentleman.</signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>