<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, vertuous and Christian Lady, the Lady Mar∣garet, Barronnesse Dacres of the South, grace, mercie and peace, be multiplied, in this life pre∣sent and eternall felici∣tie in the life to come.</title>
           <author>Topsell, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105980_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13823</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24127</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105980</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, vertuous and Christian Lady, the Lady Mar∣garet, Barronnesse Dacres of the South, grace, mercie and peace, be multiplied, in this life pre∣sent and eternall felici∣tie in the life to come.</title>
                 <author>Topsell, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The revvard of religion : Deliuered in sundrie lectures vpon the booke of Ruth, wherein the godly may see their daily and outwarde tryals, with the presence of God to assist them, and his mercies to recompence them: verie profitable for this present time of dearth, wherei manye are most pittifully tormented with want; and also worthie to bee considered in this golden age of the preaching of the word, when some vomit vp the loathsomnes therof, and others fall away to damnable securitie</title>
                 <author>Topsell, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 311, 1 page, 1 leaf of plates, table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, vertuous and Christian Lady, the Lady Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet, Barronnesse Dacres of the South, grace, mercie and peace, be multiplied, in this life pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent and eternall felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the life to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: it is reported that the inhabitants of the mountaine Cassius by <hi>Seleucia,</hi> at the third watch of the night doe behold the Globe of the Sunne: so that on the one side they see our accustomed darkenesse, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the face of the whole earth; on the other side the glistering beames of the shining light,
<pb facs="3"/>
displaying the shadow of the nightly darkenes. In my opinion this hill doth verie fitly resemble the excellencie of the word of God, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof, the professors of Religion: for long since the Sun of righteousnesse, the Sonne of God, departed from the sight of the world; and declined like the Sunne of the firmament; hath left the vniuersall Orbe of the whole earth in palpable darknes. Yet to vs liuing in this world, the beames of his brightnesse, the light of his spirit, the power of his person, and the glorie of his godhead, is most euidently manifested, by the Scriptures and preaching of his holy word: so that there we behold infinite thousands walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in darkenesse, and standing on the left hand of God ready for damnation: but here wee see a few persons, professors of Religion, like the men of Cassius, liuing in the sight and presence of our Sauiour, (whom they behold shining in the Scriptures) and standing on the right hande waiting for saluation. For this cause, the voice of the eternall God soundeth so often vnto vs in the Scriptures, that wee were vnder the prince of darkenesse, that wee were darkned in our cogitation, that it was night, but now the day starre from on high hath visited vs, and therefore we must cast away the deedes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and put on the armour of light: and the
<pb facs="3"/>
Scriptures euery where testifie, that the Church of God is in the toppe of the mountaines, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that the dignitie of our calling, as farre excelleth the fancies of the world, as the hils a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise aboue the vallies of the earth. This is the infallible word of life: and all the writings of men, are but the Apes hereof▪: from hence they heard of their Golden ages, their feareful won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, their strange inuentions, and their incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible fictions which they haue broched concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heauen and earth. When <hi>Ptolomeus Philadelphus</hi> king of Egypt, builded his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Librarie, and had furnished it with al the writings of the heathen, hee also by Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours to the high Priest in Iudah, obtained the olde Testament, and sixe men of euery Tribe, to Translate it out of Hebrewe into Greeke: then <hi>Demetrius Phalerius,</hi> one of the Schollers of <hi>Theophrastus,</hi> certified the King, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the writings of their learned Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, they onely were Diuine, and the Caelesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Oracles of the euerlasting God. For their truth the secrete nature of euerie hart is forced to confesse; for their substance, it is altogether occupied on heauenly things; for their sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, it is established in the promise of him, who neuer changeth for their stile, neither the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Plato,</hi> the demonstrations of <hi>Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi>
      <pb facs="4"/>
the inuentions of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> the sleights of <hi>Carneades,</hi> the exclamations of <hi>Cicero,</hi> or the conceipts of <hi>Seneca,</hi> were vttered in so plaine eloquence or commendable phrases, as the Scriptures of our saluation. Also if your Ho. consider the often changes of the lawes of godlesse Gentiles, you shall perceiue that they haue had as many Religions as generations: but you shall finde that we haue now the Religion of <hi>Adam,</hi> the faith of <hi>Enoch,</hi> the Arke of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> the sacrifice of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and all the true worship of God, as the Church possessed it▪ many thousand yeares agoe: and all because the rule hereof, the heauenly word of God remaineth for euer. <hi>Lycurgus</hi> the best law-maker that euer was among the Gentiles, when he saw his lawes to be amended of the <hi>Spartanes,</hi> for very griefe thereof famished himselfe at Crissa. The lawes which <hi>Papius</hi> &amp; <hi>Iulius</hi> gaue to the Romanes, were disanulled by <hi>Seuerus</hi> the Emperour: all the world erreth, some one way, and some ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, mutually condemning each others super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition; onely the Church of God, in euerie age retained one God, one faith, one Baptisme, and one substance of Religion, because it followeth one voice of the holye Ghost speaking in the Scriptures. It were infinite to set downe all the commoditie we receiue by this heauenly wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="4"/>
By it our manners are mollified, our minds instructed, our liues blessed, and we deliuered from Atheisme, Paganisme and Papisme: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme denieth all things, Paganisme corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all thinges, and Papisme confoundeth all things, therefore by the word of God, wee are freed from doubting the truth, deceiuing our owne soules, and confounding Religion. And because this requireth some proofe, I beseech your Ho. to beare with my tediousnesse, while I manifest my minde so briefely as I may; omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Atheisme fitter for dogges to beleeue, then men to professe, I will briefely declare, how the Gentiles, (such as wee were before the worde wrought our calling,) haue falsified the whole Scripture and corrupted the tradition thereof, with the inuentions of their owne Poets; and how the Papists are but confounders of Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme, heresie and Christianitie. First to begin with the Gentiles, while reason and nature en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced them to confesse a God, (which is onely and truely learned in the scriptures,) they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined a multitude of goddes and goddesses; in the Scripture we finde the mention hereof, that euerie nation had a peculiar God. The Zidoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Sirians had <hi>Astaroth,</hi> or as some call him <hi>Astartes</hi>: the Moabites had <hi>Chemosh</hi>: the Ammonites had <hi>Milcom</hi> or <hi>Moloch</hi>;
<pb facs="5"/>
the Babilonians <hi>Bel,</hi> the Philistins <hi>Dagon,</hi> the Egyptians worshipped many beastes, but especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally a sheepe: among other writers, we find that the Athenians, had <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Minerua</hi>; the Boetian Thebes, <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Hercules</hi>; Carthage had <hi>Iuno</hi>; Cyprus and Paphus, <hi>Venus</hi>; Rhodes, <hi>Apollo</hi>; Taenarus, <hi>Neptune</hi>; the Creetes, and Ephesians, <hi>Diana</hi>; the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines <hi>Mars,</hi> the Italians, <hi>Ianus,</hi> the Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>Diasares</hi>; The Germaines <hi>Tibilenus,</hi> the men of Affrique <hi>Caelestus</hi>; and the Moores haue worshipped the gouernours of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Thus they turned the glorie of the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible God, into the similitude of corruptible creatures, as birds, beasts, fishes and Serpentes, and wandered without God while they framed to themselues a multitude of goddes: and the best they coulde inuent, were sinfull and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable wretches, such as exceeded all others in notorious crimes, as I could easily shew, if it were to my purpose: and moreouer they haue forsaken not onelye the true God, but haue blotted the names of their most famous men, leauing the worthiest in hell, and lifting the worst into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. For might not they as well made <hi>Socrates</hi> a God for his wisedome, whom <hi>Apollo</hi> himself honoured with this Oracle: <hi>Pantoon An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droon Socrates sophotatos,</hi> of all men <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>
was the wisest: <hi>Aristides</hi> excelled them all in iustice, <hi>Themistocles</hi> for warre, <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> in honour, <hi>Polycrates</hi> in felicitie, and <hi>Demosthenes</hi> in eloquence: Who was more graue then <hi>Cato,</hi> more valiant then <hi>Scipio,</hi> more affable then <hi>Camillus,</hi> more excellent then <hi>Iul. Caesar,</hi> more happy then <hi>Sylla,</hi> more wealthie then <hi>Crassus,</hi> or more religious then <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi>; truely none among all their Deuils, I would say goddes, with whom all the nations of the earth haue committed forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. In latter times the Romaines had onely power to consecrate goddes, as now the Pope &amp; his Cardinals doe challenge the same to Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize Saints. But would not the hearts of the godly breake in sunder, to consider that euerie Cittie inuented a new God, yea euerie familie had their housholde goddes, committed Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie with birdes of the ayre, and beastes of the earth, men and women, Moone and Starres, Sunne and Angels, euen to the Asses head, as commonly as the Serpent liueth on the dust, or as greedily as the Lyon raueneth when hee fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a pray. The studie of Astronomie verifieth this, for they haue imagined signes from the Eagle to the little birde, from the Lyon to the little dogge, from the Whale to the litle fish, and from reasonable creatures to vnreasonable
<pb facs="6"/>
monsters: because they would haue some colour for their impietie, they translated their Idols to be signes in heauen. But now when the light of the word of life once shined in the world, they perceiued their owne follies, renounced their olde errours and receiued the wholesome doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of the onely true and eternall God: for as the Lyons runne at the sight of a fire brand, as the Cockatrise flyeth when shee sauoureth the Weasill, and the clouds flie away when the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren winde bloweth; so these subtilties of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than being once discouered, thorough the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of the Scriptures, they fall againe into the brest of the first Author, and I would to God they were for euer buried in his bottomles king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Also that which we finde in the word of God, concerning the creation, the floud, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenishing of the earth, the beginning or confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of tongues, the destruction of Sodom and Gomorhe, the deliuerie of the Isralites from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, the myracles of Moses and Aaron, the ouerthrow of the Cananites whome they call <hi>Phoenicians,</hi> the building of Salomons Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the scattering of the Tribes of Israell, the birth of Christ, the darkenesse at his death, and the preaching of the Apostles: they haue cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with fond additions, wilfull deuises, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable blasphemies, ignorant relations, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="6"/>
substractions, and accursed deprauations, which if I should follow, I might make a large volume: onely thus much I will be bolde to say, that all the wisedom of the Gentiles was nothing but the doctrine of Deuils, &amp; that all the world before the comming of Christ, was without the true knowledge of God, the Iewes onely excepted. The learned haue noted these fower as the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall heads of auncient impietie, the first is Barbarisme, wherin men liued vnder no guide, preserued no peace, followed no commendable kinde of life, but euerie one did that which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him, to the disgrace of mankind, refusing onely that which was good, and altogether em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing that which was accursed. Then one sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied another with bloudy reuenge, making no more accompt of the life of a man thē the bloud of a beast; then they mingled themselues like brutish creatures in generation, brother with sister, father with daughter, and mother with her sonne, then their strength was their lawe, their desire was their counsellour, their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons pleaded, their will gaue iudgement, &amp; their mallice was the meanes to execute their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The second head or fountaine of falsehoode among the Gentiles, is called Schythisme, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was first practised among the Scythians a barbarous and cruell people, differing in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="7"/>
from the former, saue onely because they had one gouernour or ruler, to whom they were subiect, being at his commandement, to execute right or wrong, to saue or kil, keeping peace with none, but manie times setting the children to drinke the bloud of their owne parents, and the parents to eate the flesh of their owne children. The third kind of falsehoode which raigned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles for want of the word of God, is called Hellenisme, which consisteth in the worship of Idols, this began among the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who are called in their owne tongue <hi>Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> and therefore was the superstition called Hellenisme, this detestable canker so preuailed, that not onely the Grecians, Babilonians, Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Sirians, Phaenicians, Phrygians, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other nations were infected therewith, but the Israelites the people of God, were poysoned therewith, which in the ende was their vtter subuersion, and this hath raigned a long time in the Church of Rome, and in all those king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, where she could plant her chaire, which all the godly doe perceiue will be her euerlasting destruction. But this Hellenisme preuailed mightilie, for the space of two thousand yeares, vnder which time sprang vp all the sects of the Philosophers: as the Pythagoreans, which taught that men might not sacrifice to the gods,
<pb facs="7"/>
that the soules of men departed do go into other men, and also into bruite beasts, that whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was aboue the Moone was immortal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, with such like fantasies, and in the ende this <hi>Phytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> would be called a God. Next vnto him arose the Platonistes, who affirmed that the world was created of the Angels and little god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that of one God there came many other god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that all women ought to bee common, and that no man ought to haue a wife peculiar to himselfe, in a wel ordered common-wealth. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter these succeeded the <hi>Stoickes</hi> who affirmed this world to be God, that all flesh shall perish, and that the soules departed from one into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. Then also began the Epicures to growe like Serpents, borne onely to destroy other, they would haue all things to ende in pleasure, that there is no God or prouidence, that none are bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed but in this present life. And thus your Ho. may perceiue how miserable were those dayes, when men ranne headlong into so great extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, that their profession of wisedome was the cōfession of folly, &amp; for al their light of lerning, they groped in a Cimmerian darknes, being sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with ignorance like the Countrie Odessae in Greece, which by reason of mightie hils ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to adioyning, neuer felt the beames of the Sun. The fourth head or fountaine of vngodlinesse is
<pb facs="8"/>
called Samaritanisme, of the Samarians which mingled themselues with the profession of the Iewes, and receiued some parte of the Bible; yet like the Anabaptistes of our daies, without any difference or conscience, kept companie with Iewes and Gentiles. Of these came many accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed sects, from whom sprang many detestable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and thus the world laboured with dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable deuises, while the Deuill laughed at their dayly destruction; whereby this is euident, that Philosophie or Paganisme is the corruption of our Religion. But some peraduenture will obiect vnto me, that they had very excellent and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men, who Crowned their Countrie and kindred with endlesse memorie. <hi>Mutius</hi> left his right hand on the Altar. <hi>Empedocles</hi> willingly cast himselfe into the burning flames of the mountaine. <hi>Aetna</hi> one of the builders of Carthage, to auoide a second marriage, cast her selfe into the burning graue. <hi>Regulus</hi> being freed from the Carthaginians, chused rather to suffer death himselfe in most cruel torments, then to discharge their prisoners at Rome. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocaeus,</hi> seeing his Cittie of the <hi>Thebes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieged by the Grecians, which they threatned to destroie, except one of them would giue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe for all, did ascend to the wall of the Citie, and there pearcing his body with a sword, fell
<pb facs="8"/>
downe dead among his enemies, wherewith they contented, departed. <hi>Alcestis</hi> the wife of <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> seeing (as she supposed) the fiendes come for her husband, who lay sicke, slew her selfe, bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them to take her shaddow and spare her husbands life. To speake nothing of <hi>Lucretia; Dyrachia, Aria, Cyane</hi> and many others, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let this suffice. <hi>Eleates</hi> being asked of <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisius</hi> the tyraunt, what was better then Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophie, answered, death, whereupon hee was commaunded to be scourged to death, which for the defence of his speach, and contempt of death he most patiently endured. Yet <hi>Tertullian,</hi> a Christian father speaking of such like actions, hath these wordes, O lawfull commendation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause humaine, to whome neither wilfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption, nor desperate perswasion is imputed, to whome it is permitted to die in contempt of death, and all manner of crueltie: to whome is giuen more libertie to suffer for his countrie, kingdome or friends then for God. Who is hee that cannot with one eye espie the meaning of this father? Improuing this kinde of death, as presumption or desperation which may neuer haue any harbour in the hearts of the faithfull, what shall wee then say of all these worthie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons? Surely whatsoeuer is not of faith is sinne, and without faith it is impossible to please God.
<pb facs="9"/>
We must not regard what man doth, but what God commaundeth, as the Emperour <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> once said, it is not death but the cause of death that deserueth commendation; as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesilaus</hi> the best Grecian Prince that euer was was wont to say, The purest Adamant is not worne with yron, nor wasted with fire, yet a little Goates bloud will consume it: euen so if one man could suffer al the tryals in the world, and abide many thousand deathes by fire and torture, yet it shall no whit profit him, except the bloud of Iesus Christ loose the fetters of sin, and breake the chaines of the Deuill; now the mercies of God in Christ, are not communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any, but to such as know them, and who can know them without the word of God? This is the fountaine of water of life, and all other are but poysoned puddles, stinking more filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the presence of God, then the Lake of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marina in the nostrels of men. They reporte that in Sycilia there are two springs, whereof one will make a fruitfull woman barren, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a barren woman fruitfull: if this were so, I thinke all the world would haue recourse vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. Yet in this word of God, there is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter commoditie declared vnto vs, for here wee learne the true cause of barrennesse; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knowne, the disease is the more easily remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="9"/>
here wee learne the meanes whereby it is cured, as in <hi>Rebecca, Annah, Elizabeth</hi> and others, which might as easily bee practised, as true Religion vnfainedly professed. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they tell vs, that in Epirus at the foote of the hill Tomarus, there is a holy Well, which of it selfe will kindle a Torch, being put vnto it, &amp; quench it being brought burning therto; graunt this to be true, &amp; it will represent vnto vs the nature of this holy Wel the word of God, which with the water of our Baptisme doth fire our hearts by the holy Ghost, but comming vnto it burning in the heate of our owne lust, quencheth the flame of our owne concupiscence. Also wee finde in <hi>Varro,</hi> that there are two streames in Boeotia, whereof if sheepe drinke, the one burneth their coulour in Russet, and the other maketh them while againe, if this be possible as al things are possible to the creatour of the world, what maruaile though we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, not (new couloured) by the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall seede of his heauenly word. Which are his sheepe, and the corruptions of our nature so washed in the same, that our garments of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse are as white as snow in his presence. <hi>Solinus</hi> telleth that at the Cittie Debris a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Garamantes, there is a spring which at the rysing of the sunne congealeth to Yce,
<pb facs="10"/>
but at the setting thereof resolueth to water a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, which is contrarie to all the world beside freezing with heate, and thawing with colde: yet we may make this vse thereof, that it is no wonder to see our heauenly Well to worke these contraries, to be the sauour of life vnto life, or else the sauour of death vnto death, that vnto some it is a two edged sword to giue them mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall wounds, vnto other, a broad Target to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them from danger, that it wrought so ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually in the daies of persecution, when it was oppressed in darkenesse, but now freezeth and hardneth in these daies of peace, when the sunne of prosperitie shineth to all. Surely as the Albeste stone once set on fire, can neuer be quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, so if we could but once burn in loue vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly with the Gospel, our profession should not be so luke warme, nor our deuotiō so smal in the cause of religiō. And thus I haue bene bold with your Ho. to proue my first assertion, wherein if I haue beene too long, let me craue pardon, and I will promise greater breuitie in my seconde proposition, which is this, that Poperie is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion of Heathenisme, Heresie and Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. And that I may methodically proceede, I will begin at their highest degree, and so in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der lightly touch so many things as may certifie your Ho. of the truth of their Religion. <hi>Numa</hi>
      <pb facs="10"/>
appointed one to bee a high Priest, at whose iudgement all temporall and spirituall thinges were administred, the same is retained in the Church of Rome, for the Pope obtained of <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas</hi> the Emperour and murderer of <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> that the Bishoppe of Rome might bee the heade of all Churches, to whose iudgement all the world in spirituall matters must be subiect: by which in time it came to this, that hee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the whole Church of Christ, that hee got both swords into his hand, and made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a triple Crowne, after the manner of the late Roman Emperors, who had three Crownes at their inauguration; and as the triple light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was the auncient of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> so the triple Crowne is the badge of the Pope▪ thourough the honour or terrour thereof, he threatneth what thunder-bolts he pleaseth in the world. The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balists imagined two Keyes, whereby Paradise was opened and shutte; from hence the Pope hath in his banner the crosse Keyes, telling vs that he hath power, to open and shut Paradise, for, &amp; against whō he pleaseth. Being thus exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the highest place, as it was reported, the God <hi>Termines</hi> would not giue place to <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> standing both in the Capitoll, no more the Pope giueth place to Christ although hee stand in the middest of his Church, and sit at
<pb facs="11"/>
the right hand of his Father in heauen. For this cause, as the Emperours had their senate, so he hath his Cardinals: as the Egyptians bound the Priests of Isis or Apis to liue in perpetuall virginitie; so hee forceth the sacred shauelings of his vnholy seate, with the vowe of perpetuall chastitie, and that he might helpe their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in this behalfe, as <hi>Caligula</hi> suffered the whoores of Rome in his daies, so the Popes haue graunted the tolleration of a Stewes, builded by a Pope, <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth, which in shorte time so preuailed, that the Pope receiued for Rents thereof fourtie thousand Duccats by the yeare. And <hi>Paule</hi> the thirde had the names of fourtie &amp; fiue thousand Tennants belonging to that most filthie and damnable kinde of life. Furthermore hee furnished, or rather poysoned the Church of Christ, with Friers, Munkes, Nunnes. The Friers and Munkes are the suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors of the <hi>Essaean, Dosithaean, Nasachae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and <hi>Cynicall</hi> heretickes, which like these take vpon them the vowes of wilfull pouertie, and perpetuall chastitie, placing their Religion in abstinence from meates, in outward and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall fasting, affirming that they are the successors and followers of the Apostles, like the heretiques called by <hi>Augustine</hi> Apostoliques, defending that the Apostles leade a single life,
<pb facs="11"/>
and had no wiues, so these Romish heretiques accompt Marriage but filthines, like the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionites, Tacians, Adamites, Platonists, and Valesian heretiques, and are not ashamed to make the holy Apostles of Christ breakers of wedlocke, and wilfull departers from their own wiues, contrarie to the writings of the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists and Saint Paul. The Nunnes or women-Munks are the naturall successors of the vestall Virgins instituted by <hi>Numa,</hi> &amp; as these were Dedicated to <hi>Vesta, Apollo; Iuno, Argiua, Diana &amp; Minerua,</hi> so are the Romish Nunns to <hi>Marie</hi> the mother of Christ, and other holy women. Then also did he begin to dresse and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne the Temples with Images, which he lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Gentiles, as I haue already declared, and herein hee ioyned with the Gnostickes and Basilidian heretiques, who defended Images to be lawfull for Christian people; and as the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles had their sacrifices for the dead, called <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriae,</hi> so he instituted praiers for the dead, least he should seeme to want any thing, which hee should not haue. Then also hee tooke the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from the common people, least they should espie his lewdnesse, and as <hi>Lysis</hi> the Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rean blamed one of his fellowes for making knowne abroade their Masters precepts, so hee blameth all those that shall open the misteries
<pb facs="12"/>
of the Gospell to the common people: and as the Magicians of Persia were wont to sing to their Idols in a strange tongue, so the Pope comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all things to bee done in the Church in an vnknowne language, wherein they also ioyne with the Basilidian heretiques, who gaue this as a principle, that their misteries must be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed and reuealed onely to a few, being worse then the Pythagoreans, who commaunded but fiue yeares silence to their Disciples, but the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistes keepe men all their liues from reading, speaking and conferring on the Scriptures. By this meanes he deceiued the world with iugling like the heretiques called <hi>Mirabiliarii,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that faith commeth by nature, like the Basilidians and Gnosticks; they taught that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one that would be saued must be annoyled in their sickenesse; like the Heracleonite here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques; that it is lawfull for women to Baptise like the Marcionites; that children vnbapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed are not vnder the couenant, and that grace is giuen with the outward signe, like the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians and Heracleonites; that children must be annoynted with Oyle in Baptisme, like the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques <hi>Marcus</hi> and <hi>Marcosus</hi>; that Baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me washeth away originall sinnes, and such ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall as are committed before, like the Nouati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Messalian heretiques; that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb facs="12"/>
of the Supper of the Lord, after the words of Consecration spoken, is the verie body and bloud of Christ, so the heretiques called <hi>Marcites,</hi> said, they made by coniuration, and for this cause the Pepuzian heretiques baked the bloud of man with the bread ordained for this supper; that wine must bee mingled with water, as the <hi>Artotyrites</hi> said, they must offer Cheese with the bread in the Sacrament; that good workes merite eternall life, like the Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians, Catharites, and Mahumetistes; that a man since the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> hath free will, and that God hath▪ Predestinated none, like the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagians, that it is lawfull for vs to sweare by creatures, as the Virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> Saints and Angels, so doe the Manichaeans and Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metistes; that some sinnes be mortall and some veniall, so doth <hi>Mahomet</hi> affirme: with a thousand like, most vaine, wicked, wretched, blasphemous and damnable assertions, which were most easie to bee proued if there were any question of it. By this your Ho. may perceiue, that their Religion is but patched of many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned heresies, defended by vnwritten tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and maintained by violent and forcible dealing: like the Chamelaeon they haue often changed and poysoned the world, but the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are as a Baye lease, to cure the contagion
<pb facs="13"/>
of such mortall confusion; and thus in some sort I haue perfourmed my promise, in deliuering the vanity of the world which hath refused the wisedome of the eternall word of God. The end of this my speech is to shew the wonderfull and incomparable treasure of the holy Scriptures; for as the Golde hath the brightest beames, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laide to the Copper: as the Adamante is of greatest force, when the loade stone is beside it, and the purest colour hath the best hiewe, when the countersaite is compared with it; so the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of God in his word, doth most magnificent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare, when wee behold before our eyes the counterfaite colours of superstitious conceipts, the crooked deuises and cursed opinions of the condemned Crue, which haue refused the waye of life declared herein, and chused the path of damnation for the hire of their superstition. The Scriptures are not only a Castle to keepe vs from heresie, but also a salue or remedie, if wee haue been poysoned by falshoode. The sting of the Scorpion is cured by applying the Achates stone, the grasse Alimos preserueth the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed person from death, The Baare hauing eaten Mandragora saueth his life by the little Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, and the poyson of the Chamelaeon is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by a Baye leafe: euen so the word of God, cureth the heresies of Poperie, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb facs="13"/>
to the stinging of the Scorpions in the Scriptures, it is the fruite of the tree of life, and whosoeuer eateth and disgesteth in shall neuer die, it is a preseruatiue against all poyson, and the leaues thereof shall cure the nations. By this alone the Lord hath wrought the calling of his children, the confusion of his enemies, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his Saintes, and the replenishing of his kingdome. All the Kings of the earth haue beene in armes against it: yet the ministers thereof, who neuer bore armes against them, by their onely preaching haue wonne a glorious fielde. All Egypt coulde not resist <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> because they came on the Lordes message: no more shall all the world ouercome the preachers of peace, so long as they faithfully performe their heauenly Ambassage. Wordes haue wrought more then weapons; the spirite hath pearced more then the Speare; the wals of Paper and the ordinaunce of Fathers haue bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered downe the stately kingdome of the whoore of Babilon, learning hath done better seruice then Launces, Gownes haue conquered moe then Gunnes; Bookes haue done more good then Bullets; and the prayers of the faithfull haue preuailed more then the Pikes of horsemen; the stone which the builders refused, is become the
<pb facs="14"/>
head of the corner, this is the Lordes doing, &amp; it is maruailous in our eyes, the bloude of the dead Martyrs hath giuē greater wounds in this quarrell, then the swords of the liuing souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. But thus I haue too long troubled your Hon. with that which you knewe before, and haue presumed on your fauour for the accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of these my slender labours vpon one parte of Scripture, the booke of Ruth; which as the holy Ghost hath vouchsafed to call by the name of a woman, to the praise of the whole sexe, and euerlasting commendation of her Religion: so am I emboldned to Dedicate it to so Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ourable a Lady, as your selfe, whome I know to be a Ruth by Religion, though a Noble woman by birth. For many witnesses can testifie this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so if I should be silent, and the ordinarie exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cises at <hi>Seuenoke,</hi> will sound your name, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause your presence and diligence at them, hath stirred vp manye meaner persons, comforted some godly people thereabout, and much euery way countenanced, and encouraged the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the same. There are many causes which might compell me, (though vnwilling) to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my labours to the Presse, yet willingly to present them to the world vnder the name of your Honour. For I am assured of the accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="14"/>
of any small thing that shall bee offered in the name of Religion, much more of this which comprehendeth the recompence and rewarde of our profession. Your Honour knoweth that better is it to see the smoke of ones owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, then the fire of another: so I trust my slen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der studies, which are but as smoke, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the burning coales of others know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, such as dayly you heare, shall be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter accepted, because there I had my being, where your Honour hath your dwelling. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so I am hereunto moued, that I might haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occasion, to testifie my bounden dutie, which I owe vnto that Noble and worthie Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Sir <hi>Henrie Leonard</hi> your Sonne, of whome I haue receiued especiall encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in the course of my studies, and to whom I must remaine a debtour to the ende of my dayes, being no wayes able to recompence his wonted kindnesse, but onely by this, daylye to praye for the life and prosperitie, that hee may be as the heyre of your Honour, so an orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Noble house of the <hi>Dacres.</hi> And the God of all peace blesse your owne person, with such blessings as you daylye desire, that you may still liue to the comfort of the godlye in this present life, to the enlarging of your
<pb facs="15"/>
owne Honour, to the reioysing of your whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and to the endlesse saluation of your owne soule with Iesus Christ the Sauiour of all them, which haue vnfainedly embraced true religion. Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don this first of October. 1596.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honours to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in the Lord.</hi> Edward Topsell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>