<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the excellent and most accomplish'd Ladie, Lucie Countesse of Bedford.</title>
           <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105390_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20829</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7208</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105390</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the excellent and most accomplish'd Ladie, Lucie Countesse of Bedford.</title>
                 <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Mortimeriados : The lamentable ciuell vvarres of Edward the second and the barrons</title>
                 <author>Drayton, Michael</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <distributor>Lownes, Humphrey 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>148 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the excellent and most accomplish'd Ladie, <hi>Lucie</hi> Countesse of Bedford.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Arest of Ladies, all, of all I haue,</l>
      <l>Anchor of my poore Tempest-beaten state,</l>
      <l>Which giuest life, to that life Nature gaue,</l>
      <l>And to thy selfe, doest onely consecrate:</l>
      <l>My hopes true Goddesse, guider of my fate,</l>
      <l>Vouchsafe to grace what here to light is brought,</l>
      <l>Begot by thy sweet hand, borne of my thought.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And though I sing of this tumultuous rage,</l>
      <l>Still paynting passions in these Tragedies,</l>
      <l>Thy milder lookes, this furie can aswage,</l>
      <l>Such is the vertue of thy sacred eyes,</l>
      <l>Which doe contayne a thousand purities;</l>
      <l>And lyke them selues, can make their obiect such,</l>
      <l>As doth Th'elixar all things it doth tuch.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Sweet fruite, sprong from that euer sacred tree,</l>
      <l>That happie wombe from whom thou lyfe do'st take,</l>
      <l>And with that lyfe, giues vertue vnto thee,</l>
      <l>Thus made of her, her lyke of thee to make,</l>
      <l>Shee lou'd for thee, thou honour'd for her sake;</l>
      <l>And eithers good, from other so deriued,</l>
      <l>Yet shee, nor thou, of any due depriued.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>The <hi>Harringtons,</hi> whose house thy byrth hath blest,</l>
      <l>Adding such honour to theyr familie,</l>
      <l>And famous <hi>Bedfords</hi> greatnes still increast,</l>
      <l>Raysing the height of theyr Nobilitie,</l>
      <l>That Earledomes tytle more to dignifie?</l>
      <l>That Vertue lyuely pictur'd forth in thee,</l>
      <l>May truly be discernd, what shee should be.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And Lawrell-crowned <hi>Sidney,</hi> Natures pride,</l>
      <l>Whom heauen to earth, but onely shew'd this good,</l>
      <l>Betwixt the world, and thee did then deuide,</l>
      <l>His fame, and vertues, which both equall stood,</l>
      <l>The world his fame, to thee of her owne blood</l>
      <l>Hee gaue his vertues, that in his owne kind,</l>
      <l>His neuer-matched worth might be enshrin'd.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>That whilst they boast but of their sun-burnt brayns,</l>
      <l>Which <hi>Tramontani</hi> long haue termd vs so,</l>
      <l>With all their <hi>Po's,</hi> their <hi>Tyburs,</hi> and their <hi>Rheyn's,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Greeuing to see how tidefull <hi>Thames</hi> shall flowe,</l>
      <l>Our Groues which for the gracefull Muses growe:</l>
      <l>Thy name shall be the glorie of the North,</l>
      <l>The fayrest fruit that euer shee brought forth.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And in despight of tyranizing times,</l>
      <l>This hope great Lady yet to thee is left,</l>
      <l>Thy name shall lyue in steele-out-during rimes,</l>
      <l>Still scorning ages sacraligious theft,</l>
      <l>What fame doth keepe, can neuer be bereft:</l>
      <l>Nor can thy past-priz'd honour euer die,</l>
      <l>If lynes can gyue thee immortalitie.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <l>Leauing vnto succeeding times to see,</l>
      <l>How much thy sacred gyfts I did adore.</l>
      <l>What power thy vertues euer had in mee,</l>
      <l>And what thou wer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> compar'd with those before,</l>
      <l>Which shall in age, thy youth againe restore:</l>
      <l>And still shall ad more vigor to thy fame,</l>
      <l>Then earthly honors, or a Countesse name.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Proclayming vnto ages yet to come,</l>
      <l>Whilst <hi>Bedford</hi> lyu'd, what lyuing <hi>Bedford</hi> was,</l>
      <l>Enclosing thee in this immortall toombe,</l>
      <l>More durable then letter-grauen brasse,</l>
      <l>To shewe what thy great power could bring to passe,</l>
      <l>And other hopes I vtterly refuse,</l>
      <l>And thou my hope, my Lady, and my Muse.</l>
   </lg>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors euer deuoted seruaunt <hi>Michaell Drayton.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>