<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen Rea∣ders, health.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1589</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105808_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02133</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12272</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105808</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen Rea∣ders, health.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Menaphon : Camillas alarum to slumbering Euphues, in his melancholie cell at Silexedra. VVherein are deciphered the variable effects of fortune, the wonders of loue, the triumphes of inconstant time. Displaying in sundrie conceipted passions (figured in a continuate historie the trophees that vertue carrieth triumphant, maugre the wrath of enuie, or the resolution of fortune. A worke worthie the youngest eares for pleasure, or the grauest censures for principles. Robertus Greene in Artibus Magister)</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1589</date>
                 <publisher>Clarke, Sampson.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Orwin, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, health.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T fareth with mee Gentlemen, as with <hi>Batillus</hi> the ouer bold poet of <hi>Rome,</hi> that at euerie winke of <hi>Caesar</hi> would deliuer vp an hundred verses, though neuer a one plausible, thinking the Emperours smile a priuiledge for his ignorance: so I hauing your fauor in letting passe my Pamphlets, feare not to trouble your patience with many works, and such as if <hi>Batillus</hi> had liued, hee might well haue subscribed his name to. But resting vpon your fauors I haue thus farre ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured to let you see <hi>Camillas alarum to Euphues,</hi> who thought it necessarie not to let <hi>Euphues censure to Philautus,</hi> passe without requitall. If Gentlemen you finde my stile either <hi>magis humile</hi> in some place, or more <hi>sublime</hi> in another, if you finde darke Aenigmaes or strange conceipts as if <hi>Sphinx</hi> on the one side, and <hi>Roscius</hi> on the other were playing the wagges; thinke the metaphors are well ment, and that I did it for your pleasures, whereunto I euer aymed my thoughts: and desire you to take a little paines to prie into my imagination. Wherein if you shall rest inine, I shall euer as I haue done rest yours; and so I bid you farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>