<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Epilogus.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1575</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105718_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01520</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11643a</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105718</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Epilogus.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The glasse of gouernement : A tragicall comedie so entituled, bycause therein are handled aswell the rewardes for vertues, as also the punishment for vices. Done by George Gascoigne Esquier. 1575. Seen and allowed, according to the order appointed in the Queenes maiesties iniunctions</title>
                 <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Barker, Christopher</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1575</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>106 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="epilogue">
   <head>Epilogus.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>WE liue to learne, for so Sainct Paule doth teach,<note place="margin">VVhat soeuer is written is written for our learning.</note>
      </l>
      <l>and all that is, is doone for our auaile:</l>
      <l>Both good and bad, may be the wisemans leach,</l>
      <l>The good may serue, to make him beare like sayle,</l>
      <l>The bad to shun, the faults wherin they fayle.</l>
      <l>Good wyndes and bad, may serue in sundry sorte,</l>
      <l>To bring our barkes, into some pleasant porte.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Who liste to learne, what dilligence may do,</l>
      <l>what humble minds, by studies may attayne,</l>
      <l>Let him behold, these younger brethren two,</l>
      <l>Whose wits at first, did séeme to bee but playne,</l>
      <l>Yet as you see, at last they got with payne,</l>
      <l>The golden fléese, of grace and cunning Skyll,</l>
      <l>Before the rest which folowed wanton will.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And such as brag, of quicke capacitie,</l>
      <l>Or thinke the field, is woone withouten blowes,</l>
      <l>Let them behold, the youthfull vanitie:</l>
      <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap> th'elder twayne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ncies lightly chose,</l>
      <l>To séeke delight, in garish grounde that growes.</l>
      <l>Yet had by hart, their masters wordes in hast:</l>
      <l>But thinges sone got, are lost againe as fast.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>For proofe whereof, behold how soone they fell,</l>
      <l>From vertues path, to treade in vices tracks,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="54"/>And therwithall, (I pray you marke it well)</l>
      <l>Their falles were foule, they fell vpon their backs.</l>
      <l>Which gaue their bones, so many brusing cracks:</l>
      <l>That afterwardes, they neuer rose again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>,</l>
      <l>Till shamefull death, did ende their greuous payne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Who falles on face, hath elbowes hands and all,</l>
      <l>To saue himselfe, and therwith eke to rise:</l>
      <l>To fall on backe, betokens such a fall,</l>
      <l>As cannot rise againe in any wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e▪</l>
      <l>For when he falls, his face wide open lies,</l>
      <l>To euery blowe: and cannot fend the same,</l>
      <l>Such falles found they, which brought them sone to shame</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And in meane while, their Brethren rose as fast,</l>
      <l>Much like the snaile, which clymes the Castle wall,</l>
      <l>With easie steppes▪ when souldiers do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>ne be cast,</l>
      <l>With furious force, and many a hedlong fall.</l>
      <l>Assaultes are hotte, but yet if therewithall,</l>
      <l>Some temperance, and pollyey be vsed,</l>
      <l>They winne those fortes, which hotter heades refused.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I meane but this: you sée the younger twaine,</l>
      <l>(Because they did in vertue take delight)</l>
      <l>They clombe at last (and that with pleasaunt paine,)</l>
      <l>To honours Court, wherein their place was pight.</l>
      <l>You sée againe, their Brethren (by delight,</l>
      <l>In fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>thy lust, selfe loue, and such like nio)</l>
      <l>Did fall as fast, to shamefull death and wo.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>You sée the bend, for faithfulnesse made frée,</l>
      <l>You sée the frée, for doublenesse disdaind:</l>
      <l>You sée the whippe, the cucke stoole, and the trée,</l>
      <l>Are thought rewardes, for such as vice hath staind:</l>
      <l>You s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>e that right, which euer more hath raignd,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="55"/>And iustice both: do kéepe their places still,</l>
      <l>To cherish good, and eke to punish ill.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>These thinges my muse, did meane to make you knowe.</l>
      <l>By proofe in acte, of that which you haue séene</l>
      <l>These thinges my muse, thought méete to set in showe,</l>
      <l>But otherwyse, then common wont hath bene.</l>
      <l>This christall glasse I polisht faire and cléene,</l>
      <l>For euery man, that list his faultes to mend,</l>
      <l>This was my mind, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>s I make an end.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>