<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The contents of this Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1585</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105109_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18998</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5415</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105109</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The contents of this Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The schoole of horsmanship : VVherein is discouered vvhat skill and knowledge is required in a good horseman, practised by perfect experience. And also how to reforme anie restie horse, of what nature and disposition so euer. Briefely touching the knowledge of the breeder sadler, smith, and the horseleach. With a strange and rare inuention how to make a new kinde of racke, and how to teach a horse to lie vpon his bellie vntill the rider take his backe. By Christ. Clifford, Gent</title>
                 <author>Clifford, Christopher</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Cadman, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1585</date>
                 <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Potter, George</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 24, 29-99 leaves, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Agriculture, viticulture, texts on hunting, veterinary science</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_note">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>The contents of this Booke.</head>
   <p>AL the principall points belonging to a good horsman, most plainly taught, according to my true experience, which I haue wel approoued and tried by the space of 30. years, that is to saie, of the Breeder, the Rider, Keeper, and the Sadler, of the Horseleach and Smith. Where, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning you shall finde certaine briefe notes necessarie to be obserued of the Breeder. In the first Booke you shal find the Art of Riding, with a treatise how to vse your hand vpon the bridle and cauison, so plainly taught, that it is not possible for anie man of reason that is willing to learne this Art, but that he may make any horse readie, of what nature or disposition soeuer he be, and after an easier maner than hath beene here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore taught by any man. The second Booke sheweth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme al kinds of restie horses, or hard mouthed runawaies, both easly and plainely. The third Booke intreateth of the Kepers office, how to make your stable with a standing rack, that there may no dust fall, neither on the horses mane, nor on his head, a most rare inuention: Also it teacheth you how to diet your horse, both when you trauell and exercise him: And how to maister all those horses that will bite their Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, or leape on them with their forefeet, at such time as they leade them in their hands, or that the Rider would take their backes. The fourth Booke intreateth of the Sadlers office, how he should make his saddle, and what kinde of saddle is best, both for seruice and trauell: And also how euerie soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dior may carrie both his headpeece, and pistoll, in such sort as it shall not trouble him any more than if he had nothing at al at his saddle: Also it teacheth how to make your headstall, to serue in steede of a collar, when you trauell anie iourney, or that you are in seruice, a thing verie necessarie to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of al souldiers: It teacheth you also <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ow to make your ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uison, curb, &amp; diuers other necessarie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>tions very needful to be vsed of the Rider. The fift Booke teacheth how to cure your horse of so many diseases as I haue in al my life had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of. The sixt and last Booke sheweth howe you should shoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> your horse: and how to make that horse that hath euil feet, to haue good hoofes in very short space.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>