<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE PRAISE of the Dead, and the ANATOMY.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105367_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20619</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7022</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105367</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE PRAISE of the Dead, and the ANATOMY.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An anatomy of the vvorld : Wherein, by occasion of the vntimely death of Mistris Elizabeth Drury the frailty and the decay of this whole world is represented</title>
                 <author>Donne, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Macham, Samuel 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE PRAISE of the Dead, and the ANATOMY.</head>
   <l>WEl dy'de the world, that we might liue to see</l>
   <l>This world of wit, in his Anatomee:</l>
   <l>No euill wants his good: so wilder heyres</l>
   <l>Bedew their fathers Toombs with forced teares,</l>
   <l>Who<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e state requites their los: whils thus we gain</l>
   <l>Well may we walk in blacks, but not complaine.</l>
   <l>Yet, how can I consent the world is dead</l>
   <l>While this Muse liues? which in his spirits stead</l>
   <l>Seemes to informe a world: and bids it bee,</l>
   <l>In spight of losse, or fraile mortalitee?</l>
   <l>And thou the subiect of this wel-borne thought,</l>
   <l>Thrise noble maid; couldst not haue found nor sought</l>
   <l>A fitter time to yeeld to thy sad Fate,</l>
   <l>Then whiles this spirit liues; that can relate</l>
   <l>Thy worth so well to our last nephews eyne,</l>
   <l>That they shall wonder both at his, and thine:</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>Admired match! where striues in mutuall grace</l>
   <l>The cunning Pencill, and the comely face:</l>
   <l>A taske, which thy faire goodnes made too much</l>
   <l>For the bold pride of vulgar pens to tuch;</l>
   <l>Enough is vs to praise them that praise thee,</l>
   <l>And say that but enough those praises bee,</l>
   <l>Which had'st thou liu'd, had hid their fearefull head</l>
   <l>From th'angry checkings of thy modest red:</l>
   <l>Death bars reward &amp; shame: when enuy's gone,</l>
   <l>And gaine; 'tis safe to giue the dead their owne.</l>
   <l>As then the wise Egyptians wont to lay</l>
   <l>More on their Tombs, then houses: these of clay,</l>
   <l>But those of brasse, or marble were; so wee</l>
   <l>Giue more vnto thy Ghost, then vnto thee.</l>
   <l>Yet what we giue to thee, thou gau'st to vs,</l>
   <l>And maist but thanke thy selfe, for being thus:</l>
   <l>Yet what thou gau'st, and wert, O happy maid,</l>
   <l>Thy grace profest all due, where 'tis repayd.</l>
   <l>So these high songs that to thee suited bine,</l>
   <l>Serue but to sound thy makers praise, in thine,</l>
   <l>Which thy deare soule as sweetly sings to him</l>
   <l>Amid the Quire of Saints and Seraphim,</l>
   <l>As any Angels tongue can sing of thee;</l>
   <l>The subiects differ, tho the skill agree:</l>
   <l>For as by infant-yeares men iudge of age,</l>
   <l>Thy early loue, thy vertues, did presage</l>
   <l>
      <pb facs="3"/>What an hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> part thou bear'st in those best songs</l>
   <l>VVhereto no burden, nor no end belongs.</l>
   <l>Sing on, thou Virgin soule, whose lossefull gaine</l>
   <l>Thy loue-sicke Parents haue bewayl'd in vaine;</l>
   <l>Neuer may thy name be in our songs forgot</l>
   <l>Till we shall sing thy ditty, and thy note.</l>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>