<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface or rather an aduertisment
to the Reader before he read this Poem of some
spetiail points to be obserued in the
whole worke with the vse
of some partes see∣ming
Fabolus
therein.</title>
           <author>G., P.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1615</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105764_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01929</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12066</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105764</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface or rather an aduertisment
to the Reader before he read this Poem of some
spetiail points to be obserued in the
whole worke with the vse
of some partes see∣ming
Fabolus
therein.</title>
                 <author>G., P.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The famous historie of the renouned and valiant Prince Robert surnamed the Bruce King of Scotland e&amp; [sic] : &amp; of sundrie other valiant knights both Scots and English. Enlarged with an addition of the Scottishe kinges lineallie discended from him to Charles now Prince, together with a note of the beginninges of the most parte of the antie [n] t and famous nobilitie of Scotland. A historye both pleasant and profitable set forthe and done in heroik verse by Patrick Gordon Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Gordon, Patrick</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Waters (Walters), Joris (George)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Dordrecht</pubPlace>
                    <date>1615</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>192 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>The preface or rather an aduertisment
to the Reader before he read this Poem of some
spetiail points to be obserued in the
whole worke with the vse
of some partes see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
Fabolus
therein.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Earing to be taxt of ambitious arragance for daring to
midle with so rare a work I am onlie armd with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
dewtie which I owe to my countrey the vant of good
wil in the more excellēt <hi>Spreits</hi> but aboue al the neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough
praised verteus of that most admirable Prince <hi>Robert
Bruce</hi> ambitiously desiring to immitat him, whose vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quensable
loue &amp; burning zeale towards his Contrey was such, as he being
a Prince Roialy discended delicately brought vp, beloued and honoured of
all men, of larlge and great reueneues both in England and scotland: so that
it was thoght he had more contentment of mynd and more blisings-heaped
on him by heavens then any liveing in his dayes: Yet such was his loue to the
libertie of his countrey, as forseaking his reveneues, leaveing his wyf &amp; chel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
abandoning al his royel delicasies, plesurs, and delights, he betook him
self to armes wherein when fortune hade crosd him so far as it is sead he
lost thertin Battels before he wan one, so that heauens seemd to threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin
wengence for the wilfull refusall of thees former blisings and
first was he crosd with mis-fortun in warr, the lose of his brotheren, his wife
and daughter being taken presoners, at which tyme his brotheren was crual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
execute his freinds become al his enameis and being persueit both of scots
and English was forsd in great miserie and powertie the speace of thrie yeare
to keip the montains wher herbs was his dentiest meaits and watter his
strongest wyne not withstanding that he might still haue bene restored to
al his former digniteis and much more, if he could haue suffered to behold
his countreyes miserie, as they saw his, but such was his meachles loue to
them althogh they hatted him that still he lamented their caus more then
his owin, &amp; in his manie soroufull discourses wold alwayes repeat these wers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
following.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Ni me Scotorum Libertas prisca moveret</l>
      <l>Non mala tot paterer orbis ob Imperium</l>
      <p>Robertus Brusius.</p>
   </q>
   <p>THeis verses written and subscribed with his owin hand in his Manuall
book which he alwayes careed about with him was extent within thes
feew years, but to sett downe all his workes and fortitude of mynd ware to
redious, seing you shal find manie of them in the historie following and
altho the old printid book besyds the owtworne barborous speiches was so
euill composd that I culd bring it to no good method till my loveing freind
<hi>Donald farchersone</hi> (a worthie gentil man whoes name I am not asham'd
to expres for that he was a restles suter to me to taik this work in hand)
broght me a book of virgine parchement which he hade found amongst
the rest of his books is was old &amp; torne almost inlegeable in manie pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="3"/>
vanting leaves yet hade it the beginning and hade bein sett doune by a
monk in the abey of melros called <hi>Piter fenton</hi> in the year of god (one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand
th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ie hundreth sixtie nyne, which was a year before the death of King
<hi>Dauid Bruce,</hi> it was in old ryme like to Chaucer but vanting in manie
parts and in special from the field of <hi>Bannochburne</hi> fourth It wanted all the
rest almost, so that it could not be gotten to the pres, yet such as I could reid
thereof hade manie remarkable taillis worthie to be noted, and al so proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
agreing with the trewth of the historie as I haue foloued it alsweil as
the other theris onlie two partes seeming sabolous the first is the <hi>Baliols</hi>
Visioune which as it is of small consequence &amp; doth no euil,<note place="margin">The balio his vision not vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessare for the Histo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie,</note> so doth it chek
and forbid a base mind to aspire showing that a mightie &amp; generous sperit
onlie ought to be ambitious the secound is the historie of the Kingis which
after I hade fullie accomplisd with the rest of the book, fearing it should be
too tedius for the reader I haue taken it out &amp; in the place therof insert thoes
princes discended of the <hi>Bruce</hi> nether would I be offenceive for the adding
of theis fragments for I know that sume curious heads wil alege I wrong
the vnione but farr be it from me to think,<note place="margin">The Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Bruce cheanged for thoes succeding after him. This Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie not offē siue to anie</note> muche les to doo anie thing
that may offend his <hi>Royall maiestie</hi> or seeme to hinder so blessed a pace of
the which it seameth that the heauins has called him to be the happie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument, my intensione is onlie to eternize his predicessors &amp; his own glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
being bound both by naturall love and dewtie to imploy my whole In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuors
theirto: nether doo I their in wrong the <hi>English</hi> but rather to my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
exstolle their valour and with more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>mildnes modifie that which
our wryters most sharplie haue wretin Therby to extinguish (if it be posibill)
the euil opinion that hath bein so long ingreftid in the hearts of manie by
reading of thoes old historeis hoping yat this my work may haply mak thois
that tretith of the sam mater to be forgotin by tyme being onlie desirous to
steir vp euerie manes mind to the following of glorious actions: with that
most praise worthie and admirable wonder of mankind that heauen ordea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<hi>Sidnie</hi> who sayeth that the hearing of the <hi>Martiall</hi> feats of arms betuixt
the <hi>Perfie</hi> and the <hi>Douglas</hi> stierd vp his spierit to the search of glorious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis:
and as for the Kinges discendit of the <hi>Bruce,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Sir Phillip Sidnie his saying.</note> comparing them with the
constellations I haue foloued <hi>Bartas</hi> who cheangeth not onlie theis por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traits
names, from names of <hi>Gentils</hi> giuen them by old <hi>Philosophers</hi> to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
of holie men in the <hi>Scripture,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Why the Kings dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended of the Bruce are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard to the constellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> but also concludeth with a libertie to anie
christian to name them after sume good christian princes and yet that I
should not seeme without reasone to aluede to theis princes more then to
anie other I haue sundrie good arguments moveing me theirto. First then
I say if thoes portraits must neids be designed by their names, without the
which <hi>Astronomers</hi> can not proceid in the cours of <hi>Astronomie,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Resones why they at so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</note> it is les fault
that they be named after such christian princes as haue leiued in the light of
the <hi>Gospell,</hi> acknowligeing the <hi>creator</hi> of all things <hi>Trinitie</hi> in <hi>Vnitee,</hi> then
after theis <hi>Gentils</hi> to whome god did not reveil him self and from whom
the misterie of Saluatioune was hid; secoundlie the height of their royall
station, the blessednes of their calling the excellencie of their actions yea and
cuin their werie forme seemeth too haue a correspondence with them Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathesing
them so neirlie, as they seemd to be the verie same Whom the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<hi>Maiestie</hi> hath meand by these portraits Thirdlie their is but the portraits
of eleuin men and one woman and the twelf man some <hi>Astrologsans</hi> afer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mith
to be an the schipe <hi>Argus</hi> this agreable with the number of the Kings
discendit from the <hi>Bruce,</hi> for counting him the first and prince <hi>Charles</hi> the
<pb facs="4"/>
last their is lust twelf and one woman <hi>Queene Marie:</hi> As for anie other
poetik floures I haue presumde on <hi>Aristotill</hi> his opinioune, who saieth that
how trew soeuer the historie be, it ought not to be formed in Poesi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> without
invention, wharin that excellent and wise <hi>Philosopher</hi> hath said must trew
for with invention the <hi>Poet</hi> must bew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>isie his work of invention he fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
the curious winding knots of his Garding of invention he composeth
his colours: of invention buddeth his diuersitie of odo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>iferous flouris, as the
onlie ornaments of his whole framm, of invention he forgeth links to make
as it wer a chaine of his work, theirby making euerie parte to depend and
hang vpon vther, and so winding the reader in his laborinth delighteth the
mynd without paine, which vtherwaises should be a vallaie full of diches
wheer the traveller shold be forceed to leap from on banck to an vther hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing
no bridges to go ouer at his pleasiur &amp; those are the things wherof thou
courtous reader should be aduertest; wishing the alwayes to reed my work
to an end before thou take offence &amp; the if nether the willingnes to pleas nor
onwillingnes to displeas can satisfie let my first fault be forginen for Ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
sake and I never shall intend a second, So shall I euer rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy silent Friend
P. G.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>