<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable THOMAS, Lord RIDGEWAY, Baron of GALTEN-RIDGEWAY: And to the right Vertuous and Religious LADY his WIFE, all grace and happinesse in Earth, accompanyed with all glorie and renowne in Heauen.</title>
           <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105958_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07287</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17682</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105958</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable THOMAS, Lord RIDGEWAY, Baron of GALTEN-RIDGEWAY: And to the right Vertuous and Religious LADY his WIFE, all grace and happinesse in Earth, accompanyed with all glorie and renowne in Heauen.</title>
                 <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The practice of repentance. Or A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, the fifteenth of September last passed, by Radford Mavericke, preacher of Gods word in Devon</title>
                 <author>Mavericke, Radford</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 42 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>TO THE RIGHT Honorable</hi> THOMAS, <hi>Lord RIDGEWAY, Baron of GALTEN-RIDGEWAY: And to the right Vertuous and Religious LADY his WIFE, all grace and happinesse in Earth, accompanyed with all glorie and renowne in Heauen.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>HONORABLE PERSONAGES,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it please you to peruse these printed Papers, contayning the summe of a Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at the Crosse, not long sithence, the Printer perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it onward with this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, for that a Sermon touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Repentance, being preached at the same place now twentie yeeres gone, he thought it not meete that this present Sermon, perswading vnto the practice of Repentance, and being so neere of
<pb facs="3"/>
Kinne to the other, both in respect of the Author and Subiect, should sleepe in the graue of silence or obliuion, but rather taking her elder Sister by the hand, should seeke their fortunes in the wide Wildernesse of this World, where happily some godly disposed will either for pitty, or pieties sake, giue them intertaynement.</p>
   <p>And for mine owne part, this benefit I hope may redound by the printing of it, that as it may be with farre greater ease read and perused of them that heard it, then at that time it could well be attended vnto, by reason the winde was somwhat high and hard at the publishing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, so such as were not present may by this means be made partaker of the same both for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and comfort: the mayne point therein handled, being a doctrine so necessary and generall, that it concernes all persons and people whosoeuer, that either long for, or desire their eternall sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
   <p>And now (Honorables) I will not spend ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wordes to yeeld reasons or causes of this my Dedication to your honored selues; you are not ignorant that my ancient and long acquaintance, with you, (with reuerence I speake it) here in your owne Country, and the certayne knowledge
<pb facs="3"/>
I tooke of your zealous and pious courses you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer held in the right path of Religion, (which happily hath prepared you for these greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and Places) were motiues enough to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade me to suffer these lines (if they had beene written with gold) to passe vnder your godly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections, to speake nothing of the many fauours I haue receiued from you and your worthy Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, which as I may neuer forget, so I take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure with all thankefulnesse often to remember them. One thing more I must adde, and so I end; at my being in London when this Sermon was preached, some few dayes before I promised your brother and verily intended to shew my dutie vnto you at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> when my paynes had beene ended about the same; but I was hindred only by sicknesse and weakenesse, which made me to returne home speedily, where I thanke God, I haue now (after a long sicknesse) reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably well recouered my health and strength a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and am not altogether without hope, but that I may see you once more before I goe hence and be no more seene. Meane while and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, I will not cease to pray for your Honors prosperitie, both in your honored selues and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Progenie, that as God of his goodnesse hath
<pb facs="4"/>
aduanced you to these earthly Honors, which you know are but fading, so you may seeke by all meanes possible, to aduance Gods glorie in the Gospell of his Sonne, and the true Professors thereof, which shall be the Churches good, and your glorie for euer. AMEN.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>From my poore house at ILSINGTON in DEVON,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>the sixt of AVGVST. 1617.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Your Honors euer in the Lord to be commanded, RADFORD MAVERICKE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>