<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prologue.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105055_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09829</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20092</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105055</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prologue.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most noble and famous trauels of Marcus Paulus, one of the nobilitie of the state of Venice, into the east partes of the world, as Armenia, Persia, Arabia, Tartary, with many other kingdoms and prouinces. No lesse pleasant, than profitable, as appeareth by the table, or contents of this booke. Most necessary for all sortes of persons, and especially tor trauellers. Translated into English</title>
                 <author>Polo, Marco</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 167, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="11"/>
   <head>The Prologue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O all Princes, Lordes, Knightes, and all other persons that this my Booke shall sée, heare, or reade, health, prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and pleasure. In thys Booke I do mind to giue knowledge of strange and maruellous things of the world, and spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the partes of <hi>Armenia, Persia, India, Tartaria,</hi> and of many other prouinces and Countreys, whiche shall be declared in this worke, as they were séene by me <hi>Marcus Paulus,</hi> of the noble Citie of <hi>Venice:</hi> and that which I saw not, I declare by report of those that were wise, discrete, and of good credite, but that which I saw, I declare as I saw it, and that which I knew by others, I declare as I heard it. And for that this whole worke shall be faithfull and true, my intente is not to write any thing, but that which is very certaine. I do giue you all to vnderstande, that sithence the birth of our Sauioure and Lorde Iesus Christ, there hathe bin no man, Christian, nor Heathen, that hathe come to the knowledge and sight of so manye diuers, maruellous, and strange things, as I haue séene and hearde, whiche I will take in hande the laboure to write, as I did sée and heare it. For me thinke I shoulde do a great iniurie to the world, in not manifesting or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the truth. And for better information to them that shall reade or heare this worke, I do giue you to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that I trauelled in the foresayd Prouinces and Countreys, and did sée those things that I will declare, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> space of sixe and twentie yeares, &amp; caused thē to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to Mayster <hi>Vstacheo</hi> of <hi>Pisa,</hi> the yeare of our Lorde God <hi>.1298.</hi> He and I then being prisoners in <hi>Ianua,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>1298</hi>
      </note> raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in <hi>Constantinople</hi> the Emperoure <hi>Baldouino,</hi> and in his time in the yeare of oure Lord <hi>.1250.</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>1250</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Nicholas</hi> my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and <hi>Mapheo</hi> my vncle his brother, Citizens of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/>
went to <hi>Constantinople</hi> with their Merchandises. And béeyng there a certayne tyme, wyth councell of theyr friendes, passed wyth such wares and iewels as they had boughte in the Countrey of the Souldan, where they were a long time, determining to goe forwarde, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling a long iourney, came to a Citie of the Lorde of the <hi>Tartarians,</hi> which is called <hi>Barcacan,</hi> who was Lord of a greate parte of <hi>Tartaria, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>urgaria,</hi> and <hi>Asia.</hi> And this Lord <hi>Barcacan,</hi> tooke greate pleasure to sée my father <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> and my Vncle <hi>Mapheo,</hi> and shewed them greate friendship, and they presented to hym such iewels as they broughte with them from <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nstantinople,</hi> who receyued them thankefully, and gaue them giftes double the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew, whiche they sent into dyuers partes to sell, and they remayned in his Courte the space of one yeare, in which tyme warres beganne betwéene the sayde <hi>Barcacan</hi> and <hi>Alan,</hi> Lord of the <hi>Tartares</hi> of the East, and there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene them many great battayles, and muche shedding of bloud, but in the end, the victorie fell to <hi>Alan.</hi> And by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of these warres, my father and vncle coulde not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the way they went, but determined to go forwarde to the Eastward, and so to haue returned to <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and following their way, came to a Citie in the East partes, called <hi>Buccata,</hi> whiche is within the precinct of the East Kingdome. And departing from this Citie, pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the Riuer which is called <hi>Tygris,</hi> whiche is one of the foure that commeth out of Paradise terrenall, and goyng seauentéene dayes iourneys through a Deserte, not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Citie or Towne, yet méeting with manye companyes of <hi>Tartares,</hi> that went in the fields with their Cattel: béeing past thys Desert, they came to a great &amp; noble Citie called <hi>Bocora,</hi> and the same name hadde that Prouince, which the Kyng of that Countrey had, and the Citie was called <hi>Barache,</hi> and this is the greatest Citie in <hi>Persia.</hi> In thys Countrey, were these two bréethren
<pb facs="12"/>
thr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e yeares. And in this time came an Embassadoure from <hi>Hamil</hi> Lorde of the Easte, whiche wente to the greate <hi>Alan</hi> Lorde of the <hi>Tartares,</hi> that before was spoken of. This <hi>Alan</hi> is otherwise called the greate <hi>Cane.</hi> Thys Embassadoure maruelled muche to sée these two Brée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren béeyng Christians, and tooke greate pleasure at them, bycause they hadde neuer before that tyme séene any Christians, and sayde to them, Friends, if you wyll followe or take my councell, I will shewe you wayes or meanes whereby you shall gette greate riches and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowme. Oure Lorde the King of the <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>rtares,</hi> didde neuer sée anye Christians, and hathe great desire to sée of them, if you will goe with me, I will bring you to his presence, where you shall <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aue greate profite and friendshippe of hym.</p>
   <p>They hearing thys, determined to goe with hym, and trauelling the space of one yeare towardes the East Southeast, and after turning to the lefte hande towards the Northeast, and after towardes the North, in fine, they came to the Citie of the great <hi>Cane,</hi> in the whyche trauell they sawe manye straunge and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aruellous things, whyche shall be declared in thys B<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ke. And these two bréethren, béeyng presented to the great <hi>Cane,</hi> were receyued by him very fauourably, shewing to them greate friendshippe, demaundyng of them of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure of the Christians, of hys state, and howe hée ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and gouerned hys Countreys, and kepte them in peace and iustice. And when hée made anye warres, howe and after what manner hée brough<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e hys people into the fielde, andeh demaunded of them the state and order of other Kyngdomes and Dukedomes in Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome, or theyr conditions, and afterwarde wyth greate diligence, hée en<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uyred of them of the <hi>Pope</hi> and the Cardinalles, and of theyr fayth,
<pb facs="13"/>
and of the Catholike Church, and of all other conditions of the Christians, to the which demaundes the two brée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren aunswered in order very discretely and wisely, who hadde vnderstanding, and could speake the <hi>Tartarie</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. The great <hi>Cane</hi> vnderstandyng theyr answeres, had grat pleasure therein, and speaking to his Lords, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that hée woulde sende an Embassadour to the Pope, the head Bishop of the Christians, and requested the said two bréethren, that it woulde please them to be his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors to the Pope, with one of his Lordes: they aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, they were readie to doe all that he woulde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund them. Streight way the great <hi>Cane</hi> caused to bée written Letters of beliefe in the <hi>Tartarian</hi> tong to the Pope, and also commaunded by worde of mouth to hys sayd Embassadors, that they shoulde saye, and desire hys holynesse, that it would please him to send him a hundred men, discrete, wise, and learned Christians in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith, to instruct him and his Subiects, whereas then they did all worship Idols, and would gladly receyue the true faith. And also, the great <hi>Cane</hi> requested them to bring him some of the Oyle that did burne before the Sepulchre of Iesus Christe in <hi>Ierusalem.</hi> This done, the great <hi>Cane</hi> commaunded to be broughte to him a Table of gold, and wrote in it, commaunding expresly to all hys subiects that shoulde sée that his Table, that they shoulde receyue those Embassadors with all frendshippe, and to shew them honour and obedience, and to do al things that shoulde be necessarie, and to deliuer them money, and to prouide them what they woulde demaunde, as well for shipping, as also Horses, or any other thing, in as ample maner, as if it were for his owne person. When the sayd <hi>Nicholas</hi> and <hi>Mapheo,</hi> and <hi>Cocoball,</hi> Embassador to the great <hi>Cane,</hi> were at a poynt to depart, taking their leaue of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great <hi>Cane,</hi> they rode with their cōpany thirtie days iourney, and at the ende of them, the saide <hi>Cocoball</hi> fell
<pb facs="13"/>
sicke and dyed, and the two bréethren followed on theyr iourney, and in euery Towne where they came shewing the foresayd Table of gold, where very honourably recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and enterteyned, as the person of the King. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing their iourney, they came to a towne called <hi>Giaza,</hi> and from thence departed, and came to <hi>Acre</hi> in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of Aprill,<note place="margin">
         <hi>1272.</hi>
      </note> in the yeare of our Lord God <hi>.1272.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they vnderstoode that the Pope <hi>Clement</hi> was dead, and finding there a Legate of the Popes, which was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Miser Thebaldo,</hi> that was there for the defence of the holy Church, at the vttermost partes of the Seas, to him they did theyr Embassage of the greate <hi>Cane,</hi> and when <hi>Miser Thebaldo</hi> vnderstoode their Embassage, he prayed them to tarrie the creation of a newe Pope, and hearing this aunswere, the two bréethren departed incontinente, and went to <hi>Nigro Ponte,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Venice,</hi> to sée their houses, and founde the wife of <hi>Nicholas</hi> dead, and had left behinde hir a sonne, whose name was <hi>Marcus,</hi> of the age of fiftéene yeares, which neuer saw his father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for he left hir with child of him at his departing, and this is the same <hi>Marcus</hi> that made thys Booke, as héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after followeth. These two bréethren remayned in <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> the space of two yeares, tarying the creation of a newe Pope, and séeyng howe long they had taryed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>Venice</hi> to <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> for to gette some of the Oyle that burned in the Lampe before the holy Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hre of oure Lorde God, for to carrie with them to the greate <hi>Cane,</hi> according as he commaunded, and caryed with them <hi>Marcus,</hi> sonne to the saide <hi>Nicholas,</hi> and after they had taken of the sayd oyle, returned to <hi>Acre,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Popes Legate <hi>Theobaldo</hi> was, and taking leaue or licence of him to returne to the great <hi>Cane,</hi> for whome the sayde Legate gaue them Letters, séeing they woulde not tarrie to do their Embassage to the Pope, and sayde, as soone as there was a new Pope created, he would doe
<pb facs="14"/>
their Embassage to the Pope, and that he should prouide that which should be conuenient, and so departed the two bréethren, and <hi>Marcus,</hi> and trauelled till they came to a Towne called <hi>Giaza.</hi> And in this time the Legate recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Letters from <hi>Rome,</hi> that there was a new Pope crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, called <hi>Gregorie</hi> of <hi>Placentia.</hi> The sayd Legate incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent sent his messenger after these two bréethren, that they should returne to <hi>Acre,</hi> certifying thē, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> there was a new Pope created: and they vnderstanding this, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quested the King of <hi>Armenia</hi> to commaunde to arme forthe a Galley, wherein they sayled incontinente to the Pope, of whome they were well receyued, who hauyng hearde their Embassage, streighte way gaue them two Friers, of the order of <hi>Sainct Dominike,</hi> being greate Clearkes, to go with them to the greate <hi>Cane,</hi> the one of them was called Frier <hi>Nicholas</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> and the other Frier <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Tripolle,</hi> the whiche were well séene and exercised in disputations in the defense of the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith. And these two religious men with <hi>Nicholas</hi> and <hi>Mapheo,</hi> and <hi>Marcus,</hi> trauelled, till they came to a Towne called <hi>Giaza.</hi> And in this time the Souldan of <hi>Babylon</hi> came into <hi>Armenia,</hi> and did there greate hurte, and for that cause, fearing to passe anye further, the two Friers taryed there, and wrote to the greate <hi>Cane,</hi> that they were come thyther, and the cause wherefore, they wente not forwarde. The sayd <hi>Nicholas</hi> and <hi>Maph<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Marcus</hi> hys sonne wente on theyr iourney, and came to a Citie called <hi>Bemoniphe,</hi> where the great <hi>Cane</hi> was, but in the way they passed in greate daunger of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, and saw many things, as shall héereafter be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and taryed in going betwéene <hi>Giaza</hi> and <hi>Bomeniphe.</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> yeare and a halfe, by reason of great Riuers, rayne, and cold in those countryes: and when the greate <hi>Cane</hi> hadde knowledge that <hi>Nicholas</hi> and <hi>Mapheo</hi> were returned, he sent to receyue them, more than fortie dayes iourney, and
<pb facs="14"/>
at their comming receyued them with gret pleasure, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>they knéelyng down, making great reuerence, he commaūd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded them to arise vp, demaūding of them how they spedde in their voyage, and what they had done with the Pope, and after they had made their answeare to al things, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to him the Friers letters that remayned in <hi>Giaza,</hi> and the oyle they had taken out of the Lampe that burned before the holy Sepulchre of Iesus Christe, whiche he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued with great pleasure, and put it vp, and kept it in a secrete place, with also the letters, and demaunding of them, who <hi>Marcus</hi> was, they aunswered, he was <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> sonne, of the which the great <hi>Cane</hi> was glad, and toke him into his seruice, and gaue order to place him in his Court among his Lordes and Gentlemen.</p>
   <pb facs="15"/>
   <trailer>Here foloweth the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of many notable and strange things, that the noble and vvorthy <hi>Marcus Paulus</hi> of the Citie of <hi>Venice</hi> did see in the East partes of the world.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>