<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The preface vnto the deuout reders.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1541</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105112_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15118</idno>
           <idno type="STC">25420</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105112</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The preface vnto the deuout reders.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Here foloweth dyuers holy instrucyons and teachynges : very necessarye for the helth of mannes soule, newly made and set forth by a late brother of Syon Rychard whitforde</title>
                 <author>Whitford, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Middleton (Myddylton), William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1541</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 87, 89-90, 1 leave, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <head>¶ The preface vnto the deuout reders.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Byseche you all good deuout reders: take euer myne excuse (in setting forth of myne name) for a verye trothe, not otherwyse to be done: then that none other person shuld be supposed in bla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, for my defaultes: yf the worke went forth w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any named auctour I wrote th{is} worke: many peres ago (as I sayd of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worke of deth) &amp; by lyke occasion: haue nowe sende hyt forth in prynte I byseche our lorde: you may take profete, and edifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation therby (for that is my mynde and desyre) And troth hyt is: that in the redynge, and recount of any vertu, pfet may be takē. And (for a suerte) thys vertue of pacyence: is a noble vertu &amp; muche
<pb facs="3"/>necessarie for euery faythfull Christiane,<note place="margin">Cipria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus de Pacien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia.</note> as shall playnly appere vnto you, yf hyt maye please you, to rede hyt ouer, notwithstandyng hyt is better to haue hyt: then to rede hyt. Better to practise hyt: then to knowe hyt. Better to worke hyt, then to wyshe hyt. And yet by redyng: hyt may the better be knowne. And wel knowne: the vetter be put in vse, excercyse and practise. And well vsed, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cercysed: the more may hyt profet. Rede hyt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I praye you and take with charite, and good wyll: that therof is offred, and thus euer fare you wel in our lorde god and most swete sauiour Iesu Chryste, and of youre charite, praye for the olde wreche youre assured bedeman late of Syon Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde Whytforde.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>