<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READER, AND BVYER of this Booke.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105906_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17027</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3905</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105906</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRINTER TO THE READER, AND BVYER of this Booke.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The new invention, intituled, calligraphia: or, the arte of faire writing : vvherein is comprehended the whole necessarie rules thereof; by which anie who is capable and carefull to learne, may without the helpe of any other teacher, under God, both bee informed concernin the right writing of the most usuall characters in the world; and perfectly instructed how to write one of the most frequent in Europe, called the secretarie. ... By His Majesties scribe, Master David Browne</title>
                 <author>Browne, David</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Saint Andrews</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Burdon, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>54, 216 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="215" facs="141"/>
   <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READER, AND BVYER of this Booke.</head>
   <p>IT may bee <hi>(Gentle Reader)</hi> that you thinke the Price of this <hi>Booke</hi> too much for so little a Volume; yet if you will consider the Causes wherefore it must bee so, you will allow thereof the better, which bee foure: First, because hee who selleth it, intendeth, <hi>God</hi> willing, to bee r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>adie and present, or one in his name, whensoever it shall please you to inquire for the same: for it is better to sell in such sort, as hee who selleth may liue, and keepe the Town, nor at so low a rate, as he must leaue the same, and disappoint you, when you aske for such a one as is not to bee found. Secondlie, if you reade this <hi>Booke</hi> orderlie, and diligentlie, from the beginning, unto this place, I hope you will not finde it deare neyther, but within the value. Thirdlie, though it were otherwise, it may not bee solde anie cheaper at this first <hi>Impression:</hi> because there is but a few Printed, for an essay, upon an haste, and by guesse, as it were; partly since it is the Authors first Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, and partly in respect of the tedious writing of so manie Characters, and much Writ, upon each Booke, after the Imprinting of the matter thereof. And fourthlie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Author maintayneth two or three daylie to fill up, and write in, all the foresayd Exemplare Letters and
<pb n="216" facs="142"/> Words, in everie Extract, which it no small travell and charges, in comparison of tbose Bookes which haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in them, but such as is set downe, and printed all at ones, with one travell. But indeed within few yeares, <hi>God</hi> willing, when this Impression is solde, and newe Types bought, to supplie the travels nowe made with the Penne, and the Booke reformed, and Printed the second<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> time, then it may perhaps hee solde at a farre lower rate, though much better of it selfe: to the which time, I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate you to haue patience, and bee content with it as it is, and not only dispence with any apparent Dearth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of now, but also excuse any fault you finde eyther in the Author in downe-setting, and correcting; or in Mee, in the Imprinting: and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n I hope wee shall please you better both in Travels and Price. Thus in the meane time, and for ever, I wish you to fare-well.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>