<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Mirth and Musicke to the Cunning-catcher,
Derth and Physicke to the Cony-catcher.</title>
           <author>R., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105060_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10478</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20757</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105060</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Mirth and Musicke to the Cunning-catcher,
Derth and Physicke to the Cony-catcher.</title>
                 <author>R., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Deuteromelia: or the seconde part of Musicks melodie, or melodius musicke : Of pleasant roundelaies; K.H. mirth, or freemens songs. And such delightful catches</title>
                 <author>Ravenscroft, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Adams, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, music, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Music</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Mirth and Musicke to the Cunning-catcher,
Derth and Physicke to the Cony-catcher.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ecundae cogitationes</hi> are euer (they say) <hi>meliores;</hi>
and why may not then <hi>secundae Cantiones</hi> be as well
<hi>dulciores?</hi> I <hi>presume</hi> they are so, and that makes me
<hi>resume this vaine,</hi> with hope that I shall not <hi>consume
in vaine</hi> my labour herein.</p>
   <p>For first, the kinde <hi>acceptation</hi> of the former <hi>Impression</hi> is as a
new <hi>invitation</hi> to this latter <hi>Edition,</hi> though not of the same
things, yet of things of the same <hi>condition;</hi> full of the same <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectation,</hi>
made to <hi>please,</hi> as the other were; to <hi>please</hi> I say, and that
with as much <hi>ease,</hi> as the other; made truely Musicall with Art
by my <hi>correction,</hi> and yet plaine, and capable with ease, by my
<hi>direction.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Againe, <hi>Bonum quò communius eò melius,</hi> we know; and I know
no reason, why <hi>incundum, quò communius,</hi> should not be as well
<hi>iucundius:</hi> Now then the nature of these (call them as you will)
in regard of their <hi>facilitie</hi> and so their <hi>capabilitie</hi> is more <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable,</hi>
then any other kinde of Musicke, and in this respect more
<pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>commendable;</hi> and will be I am sure more acceptable, because the
things which many heretofore haue priuately <hi>ioyed in,</hi> may now
by this meanes, publikely be <hi>inioyed.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Neither, can he, that is the most <hi>able</hi> Musition say, but that of
these <hi>most</hi> men, <hi>almost</hi> all men are <hi>capable,</hi> that are not <hi>altogether</hi>
immusicall: Neither can He, that is most <hi>spitefull</hi> say, but they
are very <hi>delighfull,</hi> I, and some way <hi>gainfull</hi> too; (yet more <hi>paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
to me, I am sure, then <hi>gainefull.</hi>) But, though there bee but
little to bee <hi>gotten</hi> by them, yet pittie were it, such Mirth should
be <hi>forgotten</hi> of vs; And therefore to make an end, I say no more
but 1/M <hi>Siquid nouisti dulc̄ius istis.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <hi>Candidus imperti; si non, hijs vtere mecum,</hi> either <hi>commend</hi> me, or
<hi>come</hi> and <hi>mend</hi> me, and so I <hi>end</hi> me, as <hi>resolute</hi> as thou art <hi>dissolute.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine <hi>T. R.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>