<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The Preface.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1556</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105482_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A07941</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18310</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105482</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The Preface.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of the lawful and vnlawful vsurie amo [n] gest Christians, added by Wolfgang Muscul vnto the ende of his booke vppon the Psalmes</title>
                 <author>Musculus, Wolfgang</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Singleton (Syngleton), Hugh</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Germany--Wesel</pubPlace>
                    <date>1556</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Economics</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ The Preface.</head>
   <p>AMōgest other euils of this present tyme, also pestilente vsurie is soo farre growen and towardes the vengeance of God, that I maye thincke it altogether in vaine too speake any thinge agaynst it, yea, though it were spoken with much earnestnes, and singular endeuer.</p>
   <p>For we haue knowen by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that this euill did then spe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially encrease, whē as in our time it began to be openly blased &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by the preachinges &amp; wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges of godly learned men: that almoost euen as the disease of the Canker, after cuttinge groweth &amp; spredeth more hurtfulli thā afore so after iuste and deserued repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge <pb facs="3"/>is thys becomen vncurable and moost noisome.</p>
   <p>Wherefore I mighte well bee thought to loose my labor, and as it is sayde by a prouerbe, to wash tyle stones, if I were not bonden by promes, and forced by letters of my brethren.</p>
   <p>Therefore that I maye in anye wyse kepe promes, and please my brethren, I will soo farre speake of vsurie, as maye bee profitable vnto them that be godlye, and as yet not so much infected with this pestilente disease, as is paste all hope. I know at what tymes, and by what persons there hathe ben disputations concernynge vsurie, not onely in Germany, but also in the scholes of other contries: but I will not meddel with scholerly shredinges, that be as faste intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled one with an other, as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <pb facs="3"/>of vsurie it self is inwrapped together, but I will simply vtter those thinges, whiche are mete to be spoken, withoute anye cumbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous contention.</p>
   <p>Fyrste I wil tell what vsurie is. And then that it may be sene, if it can be lawful vntoo Christians, I will cōferre it with the doctrine of Chryste, and with the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fession of Christen religion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>