<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>OF
IEREMIES LIKENES
TO MOSES IN MANY
DEGREES.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105887_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A15997</idno>
           <idno type="STC">2780</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105887</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>OF
IEREMIES LIKENES
TO MOSES IN MANY
DEGREES.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Lamentationes of Ieremy, translated vvith great care of his Hebrevv elegancie, and oratorious speaches: vvherin his sixfold alphabet stirreth all to attention, of Gods ordered providence in kingdomes confusion. VVith explicationes from other scriptures, touching his story &amp; phrases. By Hugh Broughton</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Theunisz, Jan</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 5, 10-40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introduction">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>OF
IEREMIES LIKENES
TO MOSES IN MANY
DEGREES.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Eremy had great resemblances to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kē
him vnto Moses in many poincts,
pleasant to consider: &amp; much for his
auctority. As Moses vvas of Levj,
the godliest tribe, and the best fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie:
that vvhich by faith hid him three
moneths: So Ieremie vvas of Levj,
of the sacrificers of Anathoth: &amp; his father vvas Chelki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah
the high sacrificer: vvho found the Lavv, hid in the
temple: in Manasses dayes: vvhose repentance vvas but
a litle afore his death: that he could not think of the
Lavv. And Amon his sonne vvas vvicked. Of this Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite
came Ieremy: Sonne &amp; father honorers of Moses.
Moses vvas vnvvilling to go vpon his message: Ieremie
vvas vnvvilling to go vpon his message. Moses ovvne
tribe stood vp against him: Core &amp; his companie. Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie
his ovvne, the men of Anathoth stood vp against
him: Moses vvas cast into the river by his ovvn kindred:
Ieremye vvas cast into a dungeon by his ovvne kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.
Moses vvas taken out of the river by one
of Pharaohs maydens: Ieremie vvas taken out of the
dungeon by an Aethiopian, by Abdemelech. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses
reproved Israel: Ieremie reproved Israel: Moses
told Israel, of captiuitie: &amp; closly of seaventie yeres:
Levit. 26. and of a nevv remembrance of covenant▪
Ieremie told Israel of captivitie &amp; expressely to end at 70
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
yeres: and of the Nevv Testament Moses told that the
Kings should go to a strange Land: vpon desert, to
be rooted out: Ieremie telleth the Kings shall go to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel.
&amp; telleth expresly tvvise: Ier. 36. &amp; 22. that the
Kings stock shalbe rooted out. Moses desired of God to
shevv him his vvayes: seing the strange success of vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
here: Ieremie desired to knovv vvhy the vvicked pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spered.
Moses bade Israell they should no more returne
to Aegypt. Ieremie bade Israel they should no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne
to Aegypt. Moses spake frō his ovvn faith in God:
that the rebels against him should haue a strange death:
Ieremie from his fayth in God tolde the pseudoprophet
Ananias, S. of Azor, this yere thou shalt die. Moses
vvrote of sadnes to Rachel the mother, by her death at
Beth Lechem, Ieremy vvrot that Rachel shall vveep for
her childrens death at Beth Lechem. Moses prophecied,
a King, of Christ the King fortie yeares: Ieremie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied
vnto Kings, of Christ the true King forty yeres.
Moses vvrote most curious poetrie Ex. 15 &amp; Deut. 32.
Ieremies Lamētations bring more ioy for learned stile:
then sadnes by speach of the nations fall. Moses and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie
saued much of their company by their forty yeres:
for going into the Land: from the vvildernes: &amp; out of
the Land into the vvildernes of the heathen. The Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risees
despising Moses &amp; Ieremie, &amp; Apostles 40 yeres
bred Eternall Lamentations.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>THE COMMENDATION
OF IEREMIES LAMENTATIONS.</head>
      <p>THe holy spirit commendeth in Ier. 36. the booke of
Lamentations: that it abridgeth all Ieremies ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>
made from the thirtenth of Iosias vnto the fourth
of Ioakim, vvhich space Ieremy reckoneth to betvven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
three yeares. And as he abridgeth his ovvn sermons
made from the phrases of the Lavv, Iob, Psalmes, and
Salomons Books, &amp; from all the former prophets: So
his Lamentations in verie speach do call the reader to
former vvorks that the reading of them bringeth into
mind all the former holy vvriters. And the holy Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel
so delighted in him, that ch: 9. he abridgeth his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations
hovv vnder heaven it hath not bene done, as
it hath bene done to Ierusalem: vvhere everie curse spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
in the Lavv of Moses hath shevved full event. God
bade Ieremie vvrite the Booke: &amp; to read it in a great
fast. Baruc vvrot it &amp; read it to the nobles: they bring it
to Ioakim the King: &amp; read it: he being at a fier in his
vvinter chāber: in his fift yere: vvhen he had returned
from Babel, &amp; purposed rebellion in his hart. It vvas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
November: &amp; a burning fier vvas in his chamber:
&amp; as Iehudj read three or four Leaves, Ioakim vvith a
penknife cut them, &amp; cast them into the fier: till he cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed
all the Book. yet the nobles requested him not
to deale so. Also he commaunded to lay hold vpon Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy
&amp; Baruc. But God hid them: &amp; bade Ieremy vvrite
againe the book▪ vvith addition: the threefold Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet:
ch. 3. as vvell may be thought: &amp; to prophecy of
Ioakim, the rooting out of his succession and house: &amp;
that he shalbe buryed like an asse: cast out of Ierusalem.
Which fell out as he vvas caryed the second tyme for Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel.</p>
      <p>And thus in Ieremie GOD honoreth the Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationes
of Ieremie▪</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <pb n="6" facs="4"/>
      <head>HOVV DANIELS VISIONS HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVR
IEREMYES LAMENTATIONS.</head>
      <p>FIve yeres after Ieremies Lamētations vver first vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
Daniel vvriteth of the Ievves enemies: hovv
they make a great &amp; goodly image: &amp; figureth them not
by beastes, vvhile the Kings of Iudah be savage vvightes,
&amp; caused Ieremies Lamentations: But after threescore
yeres, vvhen the Kings race vvas gone, then Iudahs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies
vver likened vnto savage beastes: &amp; the Ievves
of Ieremies Lamentatiōs are the holy: vvhich shal pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess
a kingdome for Euer and Euer. Also Ieremie Lam.
4. closly telleth of Babels fall: that doth Daniel liuely
describe: chapt. 5. Ieremie Lam. 5 prayeth vnto God
to turne his People: because so onely they can be retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:
&amp; to renue his gratious face as of old. Daniel ch.
9. expresly nameth Ieremies 70 yeres for Gods anger:
&amp; prayeth for the renevving of Gods favour.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <head>THE STORY OF IVDAH, FOR THE
TIME OF IEREMIES LAMENTATIONS.</head>
      <p>Daniel onely recordeth, ch. 1. that in the third of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoiakim;
Nabuchadnezzar King of Babel came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
Ierusalem▪ But by Ieremy, ch. 25. vve gather that
part of Ioakim his fourth vvas also in Nabuchadnezar
his first. And then God gave the K. into his hands: &amp;
part of the vessels of the temple: &amp; God brought K. and
vessels vnto Babel: But the K. vvas suffred to returne:
for in his fift vere he vvas at Ierusalem: This captivity
vvas mentioned onely in Daniel: vvho vvas also caryed
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>
vvith three as godly, Ananias, Misael, &amp; Azarias: &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of the Kings race. Eight yeres after this vvould not
teach K. Ioakim that he vpon rebellion should be bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s
an Asse: For he had sinned against the holy Gh. in bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ing
Ieremies Lamentatiōs: &amp; could not be renued to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
         <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>nce:
but must haue open punishment here, as Eternal
<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> Gehenna. After five yeres Daniel &amp; Nab: both drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
of the great Image: that should rule not only Iudah
but all: a long time: Ioakim cared nothing for all this.
Nab. the K. presently maketh a Golden Image, to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
the visions memorie: &amp; his hope: as Diod: Sicul{us}
noteth: that he should be a Monarch: and vvould haue
it vvorshipped. Then Daniels godly cosyns quench the
fier. And the K. of Babel proclameth Gods glory: But
Ioakim contemneth God, to hasten iudgment! &amp; rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
against Nab: K. of Babell. The second &amp; third ch.
of Daniel must be here considered: hovv against them
the vvicked harden their hart. So God sent armies of
Chaldeans, Aram, Moab, &amp; Ammon against Iudah, &amp;
they took Ioakim and bound him in chaynes to haue
brought him to Babel: 2. ch. 36. But he died by the vvay,
&amp; he vvas buryed like an asse. Ier. 36. Iehoiachin reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
three moneths: like a Cruell Lion. Him Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezar
suffred not to sit any longer vpon Davids
throne: But caried him to Babel. And moo vessels of
the temple &amp; palace; &amp; all the nobles: &amp; Mardochaj thē
a suckling, one of Ieremies Lamented. Then also vvas
Ezekiel captiued. That he might freely in Babel tell the
rest of Iuda they should follovv. But they vvould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
beleue that Iudahs kingdome should erre to destruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
Many thousands also of the People, all saving
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>
the poore, he caried to Babel: &amp; kept Iechonias 37. yeres
in prison: that vvicked Thalmudists should not say: Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chonias
by repentance called back Gods oth: that said he
should dy childles. Repentance should haue holpen A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabs
broode; first out of prison. But no repentance, not
Moses repentance, can call back Gods oth: Besides the
oth passed as vvell for Ioakim that none of his seed sho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uld
sit vpon Davids throne. yet the infidels teach it to
be Atheisme to say that Salomons race is ended. But
the Gospell of S. Luke &amp; Ier. 36. &amp; 22. &amp; Aggej. 2. &amp;
Zach. 12. teach vs that it is infidelity
to deny it to be ended.
Let him that
readeth
vnderstand.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>