<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Forsyth, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105640_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01078</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11192</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105640</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Forsyth, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The great day of chancery : A sermon preached at White-Hall, the last day of October. 1619. By Iames Forsith, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinarie</title>
                 <author>Forsyth, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 47, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xpect not</hi> (cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle READER,) <hi>Critical conceits,</hi> nec ipsum Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceronem, <hi>not any Rhetoricall fine phrases, in this plaine Sermon: for we ought to come to the people, as Saint Paul speaketh;</hi> not with the wisedome of words,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.4.</note> but plaine euidence of the Spirit; <hi>to benefit and not to fit the humour, is my desire: not to please, but to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>please rather doe I seeke: that their</hi> sorrow might bee godly <hi>against sinne to cause repentance</hi> not to bee repented of. <hi>The dangerous secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and damnable Impietie of these last and perillous times, which euery</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>true iudicious eye discerneth, and euery good Christian lamenteth, did cause mee to choose this Text; that hereby I might rouze vp all <hi>carelesse sleepers</hi> and <hi>sluggish slumberers</hi> from their secured safety. for some there be <hi>(I pray God not too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny)</hi> that hardly entertaine at any time, so much as any shew of <hi>desire</hi> or <hi>care</hi> how they shall appeare <hi>in that day;</hi> as if they had made a <hi>coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with death and hell,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Esa. 28.15.</note> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>(I thinke)</hi> they beleeue that false Axiome of Atheisme, that there is neither <hi>heauen nor hell;</hi> nor yet such a day as is spoken of here: for their actions seeme such, as these in <hi>Iob</hi> bidding the Almightie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from them,
<note place="margin">Iob. 21.14.</note>
      <hi>for they desire not the knowledge of his waies,</hi> and stand scoffing like these Mockers in <hi>Peter,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Pet. 3.4.</note> that aske, Where is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of his comming? Such monsters there bee vnder the habite of men,
<pb facs="6"/>worse then the very deuils them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues:
<note place="margin">Ia. 2.19.</note> for the <hi>deuils beleeue this day, and tremble</hi> in remembrance of it: for whose prosperitie (I thinke charitably of all:
<note place="margin">Psal. 122.8.</note>
      <hi>de viuo speran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum)</hi> as <hi>for my brethren and companions sake,</hi> I am bound to pray, and he that is the searcher of the heart knoweth,
<note place="margin">Ro. 10.1.</note>
      <hi>that mine heart desireth their conuersion,</hi> that all men and women that haue heard of the trueth, may truly receiue this true doctrine concerning Christ, and his comming to Iudgement: that we all being in our liues reformed, in our consciences cleared, by true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of our sinnes, and that euery day wee may be readie,
<note place="margin">Luc. 1.17.</note>
      <hi>as a people prepared for the Lord;</hi> and my prayer dayly shall be vnto Almightie God, with the blessed Apostle <hi>for my selfe and all Christians,</hi> that he may grant vs, <hi>according to the riches of his glorie, that wee may
<pb facs="7"/>be strengthened in the Inner man, that Christ may dwell in our hearts by faith in this life.</hi> so that in that day wee may bee freed from Iudgement, and after that day conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually dwell with Christ in glory. <hi>Vnto that God, that brought Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ againe from the dead, and made him Iudge of quicke and dead:
<note place="margin">Eph. 3.20.</note> that is able to doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding abundantly aboue all that wee aske or thinke, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the power that worketh in vs, be praise in the Church by Christ Iesus throughout all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</hi> Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord IAMES FORSITH.</signed>
      <dateline>
         <hi>S. Michaels in the Quern, London,</hi>
         <date>20. Nouemb. <hi>1619.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>