<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GENTLEMEN Students of both Vniuersities health.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1591</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105962_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02099</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12241</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105962</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GENTLEMEN Students of both Vniuersities health.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Greenes farewell to folly : Sent to courtiers and schollers as a president to warne them from the vaine delights that drawes youth on to repentance. Robert Greene vtriusque Academiæ in Artibus magister</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1591</date>
                 <publisher>Aggas, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Scarlet, Thomas</publisher>
                            <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                            <distributor>Newman, Thomas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE GENTLEMEN <hi>Students of both Vniuersities health.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Gentlemen and Student<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>s (my olde fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ndes and companions) I presented you alate with my Mourning garment, howe you censure of the cloth or cut I knowe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ot, but the Printer hath past <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> all out of his shop, and the Pedler sounde them too dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e for his packe, that he was faine to ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>gain for the life of Tomliuolin to wrappe vp his sweete powders in those vnsauorie papers: If my garment did any Gentleman good I am glad, if it offended none I am proud, if good man find fault that hath his wit in his eyes, and can checke what he can not amend, mislike i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>, I am careles, for Diogenes hath taught me, that to kicke an asse when he strike<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>, were to smell of the asse for meddling with the asse. Hauing therefore Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen (in my opinion) mourned long enough for the misdeedes of my youth, least I shoulde seeme too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> in my fastes, or like our deare English breethren that measure their praiers by the houre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>lasse, fall a sleepe in preaching of repentance. I haue nowe left of the intent, and am come to the effect, and after my mourning present you with my Farewell to follies, an vltimum vale to al youthful vanities: wishing al Gentlem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>n as wel Courtiers as Schollers, to take view of those blemishes that dishonor youth with the quaint shew of pleasant delights. What a glorious shew would the Spring present if the beautie of hir floures were not nipt with the frostes? how would Autumne boast of hir fruites if she were not disguised with the fall of the leafe, and how would the vertues of youth shine (polished with the ripe conceit of wit) if they were not eclipsed with the cloudes of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Then sweete comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nions and louemates of learning, looke into my Farewel, and you shall find the poisons which infect young yeares, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning but the leafe reade the Anti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>otes to preuent the force of such deadly confections. Lay open my life in your thought and beware by my losse, scorne not in your age what you hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> learned in your Accidence, though stale yet as sure as check, <hi>Felix quem faciunt aliena pericula cantum.</hi> Such wags as haue bene wantons with me, and haue marched in the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers booke to please their Mistris eye with their brauerie, that as the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like phra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>eis haue made the tauerne to sweat with riotous expences, that haue spent their wits in courting of their sweetehearts, and emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ied their purses by being too prodigall, let them at last looke backe to the follies of
<pb facs="5"/>
their youth, and with me say farewell vnto all such vanities. But those young nouices that haue not yet lost the maidenhead of their innocency, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> haue not heard the melody of such alluring Syrens, let them read that they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, and that seeing into the depth of their follie, they may the more detest that whose poysoned sweetenesse they neuer tasted. Thus ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally I woulde wish all to beware by me to say with me farewell to follie. Then shoulde I glorie that my seede sowne with so much good will shoulde yeel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> a haruest of so great aduantage. But by your leaue Gentlemen, some ouer cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ous wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>l carpe and say that if I were not beyond, I would not be so b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ld to teach my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, their du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ie, and to shew them the Sunne that haue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ighter eyes than my selfe, well Diogenes tolde Alexander of his follie and yet he was not a King. Others will flout and ouer read euerie line with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>rumpe and say tis scuruie, when they them selues are such scabd Iades that they are like to dye of the fazion, but if they come to write or publish an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>e thing in print, it is either distild out of ballets or borrowed of Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall poets, which for their calling and grauitie, being loth to haue anie prophane phāphlets passe vnder their hand, get some other Batillus to set his name to their verses: Thus is the asse made proud by this vnder hande brokerie. And he that can not write true Englishe without the helpe of Clearkes of parish Churches, will needes make him selfe the father of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>. Otis a iollie matter when a man hath a familiar stile and can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite a whole yeare and neuer be beholding to art? but to bring Scripture to proue any thing he sayes, and kill it dead with the text in a trifling sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of loue, I tell you is no small peece of cunning. As for example two lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers on the stage arguing one an other of vnkindnesse, his Mistris runnes ouer him with this canonicall sentence, A mans conscience is a thousande witnesses, and hir knight againe excuseth him selfe with that sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ing of the Apostle, Loue couereth the multitude of sinnes, I thinke this was but simple abusing of the Scripture. In charitie be it spoken I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>d the sexten of Saint Giles without Creeple gate, would haue beene ashamed of such blasphemous Rhetoricke. But not to dwell in the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of those dunces, or trouble you with a long commentarie of such witl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>sse cockescombes, Gentlemen I humbly intreat pardon for my selfe, that you will fauour my farewell and take the presentation of my booke to your iudiciall insights in good part, which courtesie if I find at your hands as I little dout of it, I shall rest yours as euer I haue done.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Robert Greene.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>