<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>GRATAE POSTERITATI.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105879_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09169</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19480</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105879</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>GRATAE POSTERITATI.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The image of bothe churches : Hierusalem and Babel, vnitie and confusion. Obedienc [sic] and sedition. By, P. D. M</title>
                 <author>Pattenson, Matthew</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Quinque, Adrien</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Tournai</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 461, 3 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>GRATAE POSTERITATI.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTL reader, I present vnto the in lieu of a preface, a most ingenious inuention (borro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed from our English Lucan) full of iudgment and proper to my argument. The which (iudiciouslie conceaued will serue as a fit introduction, to illustrate this discourse: and as a fayre portall to let the in with more delight, into this great <hi>amphitheater,</hi> whear thou shalt see the tragedies and tumults of this latter age, (for the quarrel of religion) as trewlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented as they wear acted.</p>
   <p>The reason of the Poeme is this. The world haith bean ever (tho most of late) possessed with thre euel spirits, combined together to break the peace: curiositie, sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitie, and faction. The first is the moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of innouation, the root from whenc springs all <hi>fancies haereses opinionum commenta.</hi> The second nurces that issew, and as the harbinger of ambition, taketh vp such harts; as ar fittest to lodg presumption and Philautia. Euer in loue with it self onelie, and contempt of others: seducing men by new opinions of applause, as yf it onelie had bean created to guide the Carriot of
<pb facs="4"/>
the sonne. Faction, (wonn and corrupted by the other,) is the champion of them both, to defend the monsters they beget, masked vnder the formes of truthe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. Curiositie, bred in the brayne, by pestilent vapors rising from a prowd stomach) makes a <hi>quere,</hi> and <hi>quare,</hi> of all principles, and receaued Truthe.</p>
   <p>Singularitie, apprehending the theore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of curiositie, as a censor and Dictator will iudg and rule all, and labour to steale the harts of men, and perswade ther sowles, that <hi>eritis sicut d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>.</hi> Faction, as <hi>flagellum Dei</hi> armeth them both with powre to afflict all ther contradictors. None of them ar apt to obey, and singularitie will cōmand, making her own iudgmēt her idol: and yet it is cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie, like a tombe of glorie full of rotten bones, or like a fayr eye to show, and yet purblynd at hand. But faction ever preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth zeal of spirit, which yf it become con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror showes no mercie: yf subdewed, no patienc: how ever mutinous, and a boute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>few. These ar the thre furies, that torment the world at this instant: that <hi>Triceps <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berus</hi> that sett opē Helgates, to fill the world with impostors, seducers and calumniation. yf yow ask me <hi>quorsum haec?</hi> read this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, and therby yow shall learn how to applie them. <hi>Caue &amp; vale.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>