<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right worship∣full Maister Francis Rogers Esquire, one of the Gentlemen pen∣sioners vnto the Queenes Maiestie, Ni∣cholas Leigh wisheth long &amp; quiet lyfe, with much increase of vertue and worship.</title>
           <author>Leigh, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1568</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105534_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00382</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10499</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105534</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right worship∣full Maister Francis Rogers Esquire, one of the Gentlemen pen∣sioners vnto the Queenes Maiestie, Ni∣cholas Leigh wisheth long &amp; quiet lyfe, with much increase of vertue and worship.</title>
                 <author>Leigh, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A modest meane to mariage, pleasauntly set foorth by that famous clarke Erasmus Roterodamus, and translated into Englishe by N.L. Anno. 1568</title>
                 <author>Erasmus, Desiderius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Denham, Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1568</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>52 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Marriage, the debate on women</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶<hi>To the right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> Maister Francis Rogers <hi>Esquire, one of the Gentlemen</hi> pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners vnto the Queenes Maiestie, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Leigh wisheth long &amp; quiet lyfe, with much increase of vertue and worship.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I REMEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (gentle Maister Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers) the auncient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and the daylie and accustomed metings, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course and familiaritie that (amōg the rest) did happen and passe betwene vs in times past, in those our yong and tender yeares, and in those famous places of st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>die, vnto the which we were by oure friendes appointed and then sent for learning sake. And when moreouer, I doe remember, waye, and cōsider therin on the one side, that state and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, in the which I was then, with that, which for my part on the other side, I doe now find and haue long since felt and tasted of, I cannot but recken and thinke that time most happily passed
<pb facs="3"/> which I bestowed in the trauaile and study of good letters. For besides the inestimable fruit, &amp; the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable pleasure &amp; delectation, that the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses doe bring vnto the studious, beside the sweete rest of minde, voyde of all worldly cares and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, the faire &amp; pleasaunt walkes, which we there (with a number of vertuous, and well disposed, and a sort of learned, ciuill, friendly and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full compan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ons) enioyed, togither with the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some and cleane diet, not infected with outragious or any surfetings (a vice else where to much vsed) what honest and godly exercises had we then there to the furtherance and increase of vertue, &amp; to the abandoning of vice? insomuch that in a maner it hath fared with me euer since my departing thēce, as with one that being expelled and exuled from a second Paradise, replenished and adorned with all kinde of flagrant &amp; of most wholesome and sweete flowers and delights, is presently fallen as it were into a darke &amp; an yrkesome thicket of bushes and brambles of the cares and troubles of this worlde, daylie readie, not onely to molest and perturbe the quiet studious minde, but also so complete with an infinite number of displeasures, dammages, and daungers on euerye side that (verye much accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the auncient and wonted prouerbe) I may now iustly say <hi>vix fugiet Scyllam, qui vult
<pb facs="3"/> vitare Charybdim.</hi> Wherefore that mans saying seemed not altogither voyde of reason, that sayde, that if there were anye choyse to be had as touching the estate of man, the better parte and the first thereof was not to be borne at al, the next vnto that was to die verie shortly. And yet by the way neuerthelesse, as he that hath bene once in any suche kinde of Paradise or place of pleasure, as is aforesaide, hath alwayes nowe and then some motions and occasions, to cast his sorrowfull eye with a mournfull minde towardes the same: euen so I of late beholding and lamenting that chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged place and state of life, and in the meane sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son pervsing some pieces of mine olde exercises which I had then and did there (whereof I was alwayes bolde partly to make you priuie, as one among all others whose discreete iudgement and towardnesse in learning togither with the great curtesie and singuler humanitie and friendship, and the passing readie and great pleasantnesse of wit, ioyned therewith was then certes not a little had in admiration and embraced euery where) happily I founde certaine loose papers of two Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues of the famous and excellent Clarke <hi>Eras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> of <hi>Roterodame,</hi> by me translated into englishe (partly for the pleasantnesse of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as it seemed vnto me then, partly also for the
<pb facs="4"/> proofe and triall of my selfe what I coulde doe in translating, and lastly as the matter semed swete and pleasaunt, so not altogither voide of godlye and wholesome exhortations and lessons, for all sortes no lesse necessarie than profitable. Which when I had with earnest view pervsed, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in minde diuers times to gratifie your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse with some friendly token of remembraunce, forthwith I thought (renuing my wōted exercises) to dedicate these two Dialogues vnto you. Whose knowledge and learning I know, and gentlenesse therwithal to be such, that I am in an assured hope that (vntill I may giue better) ye will vouchsafe in the meane season thankefully to accept these my recreations, and these few lines at my handes as a pledge and a poore present of the continuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and the vnfeyned good will I beare towards you, &amp; your vertuous demerites. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in notwithstanding, albeit peraduenture the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of study and learning, and especially the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it selfe therein contained maye seeme to bee of very small importance or pleasure, &amp; rather other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise different or something disagreeable vnto your vocation on euerie side, and also vnto all such for the most part as in the roome and place of armes, are called towardes the seruice of the Princes Maiestie, and of their Countrie <hi>(Rara
<pb facs="4"/> enim inter Arma &amp; literas vel togas est amicitia vel societas)</hi> Yet I knowing the great reuerence and the singular regard and esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation that you do beare, and alwayes haue borne towardes the learned and towardes good letters, for the pleasant and fruitefull knowledge that you your selfe haue most happily and with great dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritie both reaped and tasted among them in times past, I doubt not but that (waying the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse of the Author of them, and accepting the faithfull indeuours of me the rude translator of them) you will be content to permit the same to passe vnder your wing, and so much (I know) the rather for that they both doe tende to vertues pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. The one of them being betweene a Woer and his Feere, wherein albeit the naturall ouerthwart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the womanishe minde, doth now and then burst out as out of the frayler and weaker vessell, yet is therein a godlye kinde of woeing without any scurilitie, very pleasantly, liuely, and plainly declared and set forth, to the good behauiour and honest inducement and furtherance of such as are yet to take that matter or enterprise in hand, farre from prouoking any vice, as the maner and guise of a number of lasciuious Louers and fayned woers nowe adayes is, whose craftie and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet dealings, fonde iestures and motions, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely
<pb facs="5"/> and vaine communications and ydle talks is better to be passed ouer with silence than paper to be stained therewith, or any time to bee spent therein. The other is betweene a yong man and a light Woman, who in times past had bene fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acquainted then honestie required, and hee hauing bene absent from hir for a certaine space, at last repaired to hir house, who after hir ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed maner and wont, beganne to entise and allure him to their former follies, who percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hir purpose therein, discreetly and properly perswaded hir by diuers and sundrie godly and vertuous reasons to leaue and forsake that kinde of life, as of all other most detestable, and in the ende making hir thereby to loath hir frayle and accustomed follies, bringeth hir vnto an honest and chaste conuersation. Thus the effect of the whole matter you haue in few words. Accept ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (I praye you) this my simple doing in good part, weying my good will in the friendly Ballance of your accustomed gentlenesse, which I trust shall somewhat counterpaise the vnworthinesse of this my so grosse and rude a transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of so worthy a writer. <hi>Vale.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours vnfeynedly Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Leigh.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>