<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO MY DREAD SO∣VERAIGNE IAMES, by the grace of God, of Britaine, Fraunce and Ireland, King.</title>
           <author>Craig, Alexander</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105268_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19527</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5958</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105268</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO MY DREAD SO∣VERAIGNE IAMES, by the grace of God, of Britaine, Fraunce and Ireland, King.</title>
                 <author>Craig, Alexander</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The poeticall essayes of Alexander Craige Scotobritane : Seene and allowed</title>
                 <author>Craig, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>White, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO MY DREAD SO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERAIGNE <hi>IAMES,</hi> by the grace of God, of <hi>Britaine, Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> King.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Atulus Lactatius</hi> hauing done the vtmost of his endeuours to stay his Souldiers that fled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their enemies, put him selfe among the Run-awayes, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled to be a Coward, to beare them companie; That so they might rather seeme to follow their Captaine, then runne away from the Enemie: This was a neglecting of his reputation, to conceale the shame and reproch of others. I haue (accomplished Archi-Monarch) with the rest of these <hi>Boreo-Britan</hi> Poets, been ingrately silent; and with the cold asshes of Feare, haue couered the coales of my Loue: Because (as <hi>Archileonida</hi> sayd to the <hi>Thratian</hi> Legates, There were many moe more valiant Cittizens in <hi>Sparta,</hi> then her Sonne <hi>Brasidas,)</hi> I found my selfe but a doltish <hi>Cheril,</hi> among so many delicate <hi>Homers:</hi> And thus, neither durst I prayse thy Fortunes, nor congratulate thy Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; But now am bold to present to your most sacred eyes these louely litures, both to encourage others, &amp; make sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
<pb facs="3"/> for my (seeming ingratitude) long silence. I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not with those <hi>Macedonian</hi> Parasites to call <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Iupiter:</hi> nor with <hi>Hermodorus</hi> to make <hi>Antigonus</hi> the sonne of <hi>Phoebus.</hi> I write not to enlarge thy fame, which is boundles; nor to begge reward, which I merit not; nor to purchase prayse, which I craue not; but in few lines to shew the infinitie of my Loue to your Grace. When <hi>Vitellius,</hi> at the Battell of <hi>Cremona</hi> was slaine, the <hi>Parthian</hi> King <hi>Vologesus</hi> sent Embassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours to <hi>Vespasian,</hi> offering him fourtie thousand <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian</hi> Horsemen to ayde him, (This was a glorious and ioyfull thing to be sought vnto with offers of so great as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistaunce, and yet not to need them): So thankes were giuen to <hi>Vologesus,</hi> and hee at perpetuall peace from thencefoorth with the <hi>Romans.</hi> I haue sent (dread Leige) those Papers Congratulatorie, and Paroenetic, to your Maiestie, not that your Highnes needes them, but with <hi>Vologesus,</hi> to shew my Loue to <hi>Vespasian,</hi> and purchase his thankes. If you like my labours, they come not too late: if you loath them, they come too soone to light. Thus, bold as a true and louing Subiect, fearefull as a blushing and onmanumitted Prentice in Poesie, I remaine your Maiestes,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Borne Subiect, and bound beadman, Alexander Craige.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>