<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ TO THE Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105601_Fr1_9</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00755</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10881</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105601</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ TO THE Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short discours of the excellent doctour and knight, maister Leonardo Phiorauanti Bolognese vppon chirurgerie : VVith a declaration of many thinges, necessarie to be knowne, neuer written before in this order: whervnto is added a number of notable secretes, found out by the saide author. Translated out of Italyan into English, by Iohn Hester, practicioner in the arte of distillation</title>
                 <author>Fioravanti, Leonardo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 64 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="2" facs="10"/>
   <head>❧ TO THE <hi>Reader.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing taken vpon me to write a briefe treatise of Chirurgerie, in the which I wil write the meere verity, &amp; that with as much breuitie as may be, bicause the troth occupieth but little roome, for the Philosopher writeth that the troth is such a light as all men doe hide, couering it with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse abuses, as the Poets many times doe: for when they write one of their tales they goe about to hide it, and thus to our purpose. Those that write greate vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes cannot choose many times but hide the troth, for in much matter there entreth both good and bad, &amp; therefore I will write no more then is necessary, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what Chirurgerie is, and in what order it should be vsed with all his accidents, shewing what woundes are, with Impostumes and vlcers, how they ingender, and when they are ingendred, howe to cure them and disolue them. A discourse which will please many bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is only troth, &amp; of great importance: Let euery one therfore know that science with experience do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be one thing, and at this present euery one is certeine thereof, that the experince of Phisicke as wel as of Chirurgerie, cannot be good without science, or Methode, as a man may terme it. But I say that expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience is better then Science, in these two arts, that is in Phisicke and Chirurgerie, for science onely sheweth the vertue the which may be done with practise that hath no theorike. Of which I haue written sufficiently in my Capricy medicinalle, Imprinted at Venice, and that this which I write is troth, I will proue it, for I say, that noe can helpe with the onely Methode, but alwayes it is necessary that there be some experience
<pb facs="11"/>
or practise therefore those that do delight to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stande, let them followe this my short treatise, in the which I will intreate of thinges most necessary to bee knowne, &amp; wil shew how easie it is to work in that art, declaring al the dificult matters, so that euery one may see and perceiue it plaine, and afterwards I will shewe howe to make many newe medicines, as well for wounds, as for the other sorts of sores, which haue not beene vsed neither of old Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, nor of new: the which remedies are of such vertue &amp; strength, that the world wil wounder at them for their notable quicke working, and hereafter I will write what Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is.</p>
   <p>
      <figure>
</figure>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>