<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Curteous Reader Health.</title>
           <author>G., R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105894_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02079</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12223</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105894</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Curteous Reader Health.</title>
                 <author>G., R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The blacke bookes messenger : Laying open the life and death of Ned Browne one of the most notable cutpurses, crosbiters, and conny-catchers, that euer liued in England. Heerein hee telleth verie pleasantly in his owne person such strange prancks and monstrous villanies b him and his consorte performed, as the like was yet neuer heard of in any of the former bookes of conny-catching. By R.G</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Danter, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Nelson, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>30 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Curteous Reader Health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, I knowe you haue long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the comming foorth of my <hi>Blacke Booke,</hi> which I long haue promised, and which I had many daies since finished, had not sickenes hindered my intent: Neuerthelesse, be assured it is the first thing I meane to publish after I am recouered. This Messenger to my <hi>Blacke Booke</hi> I commit to your curteous censures, being written before I fell sick, which I thoght good in the meane time to send you as a Fayring, discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing <hi>Ned Brownes</hi> villanies, which are too many to bee described in my <hi>Blacke Booke.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>I had thought to haue ioyned with this Treatise, a pithy discourse of the Repentance of a Conny-cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher lately executed out of Newgate, yet for asmuch as the Methode of the one is so far differing from the other, I altered my opinion, and the rather for that the one died resolute and desperate, the other penitent and passionate. For the Conny-catchers repentance
<pb facs="3"/>
which shall shortly be published, it containes a passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of great importance, First how he was giuen ouer from all grace and Godlines, and seemed to haue no sparke of the feare of God in him: yet neuerthelesse, through the woonderfull working of Gods spirite, euen in the dungeon at Newgate the night before he died, he so repented him from the bottome of his hart, that it may well beseeme Parents to haue it for their Children, Masters for their seruants, and to bee peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of euery honest person with great regard.</p>
   <p>And for Ned Browne of whome my Messenger makes report, hee was a man infamous for his bad course of life and well knowne about London: Hee was in outward shew a Gentlemanlike companion attyred very braue, and to shadowe his villany the more would nominate himselfe to be a Marshall man, who when he had nipt a Bung or cut a good purse, he would steale ouer into the Lowe Countries, there to tast three or foure Stoapes of Rhenish wine, and then come ouer forsooth a braue Souldier: But at last hee leapt at a daysie for his loose kind of life, and therefore imagine you now see him in his owne person, standing in a great bay windowe with a halter about his necke ready to be hanged, desperately pronounsing this his whole course of life and confesseth as followeth.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in all curtesie, <hi>R. G.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>