<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader, T. P. wisheth all furtherance in the way of righteousnesse.</title>
           <author>P., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105176_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09780</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20050</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105176</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader, T. P. wisheth all furtherance in the way of righteousnesse.</title>
                 <author>P., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The fauourite: or, A plaine demonstration from Holy Scripture of Gods especiall loue to the righteous, in a sermon preached at S. Andrewes in Norwich, the 18. of Nouemb. 1611. since enlarged and newly published for the comfort of Gods people. By Timo: Plummer preacher of Gods word</title>
                 <author>Plummer, Timothy</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Man, Samuel</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 45, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader, T. P. wisheth all furtherance in the way of righteousnesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, we finde in History both Sacred and prophane, and easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obserue in the practise of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that Kings and Princes haue alwaies had some or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be their speciall Fauourites, that is to say,</p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> Such as they haue priuiledged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue others to bee most neere in atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance about their Royall persons.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> Such as they haue graced and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
<pb facs="5"/>with excellent names, stiles and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of honour.</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> Such as they acquaint with the greatest and weightiest secrets of State, admitting them to bee of their Priuie Councell.</p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> Such as they readily heare and grant petitioning and soliciting for themselues and others.</p>
   <p>And nothing is more obutious in holy writ, then that God the King of Kings doth make the righteous man his onely Fauourite; The Lord sets apart him that is godly for himselfe.<note place="margin">Psal. 4.3.</note>
   </p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> He makes him attend vpon him in his speciall presence, in his House, in his Courts, in the best place he hath: <hi>A day in thy Courts is better then a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand:</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal.
84.10.</note> I had rather be a doore-keeper in the house of my God then to dwell in the tents of wickednesse.</p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> He giues him glorious names and titles, especially, calling him The Sonne of God: <hi>Behold,</hi> saith S. Iohn,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.1.</note>
      <hi>what manner of loue the Father hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed
<pb facs="6"/>vpon vs, that we should be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the sonnes of God.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> He reucales to him his secrets, <hi>The secret of the Lord is with the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Prou. 3.32. Psal. 25.14 Matth. 13.11.</note>
      <hi>To you it is giuen to know the misteries of the Kingdome of heauen.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> Hee willingly heares his requests, put vp in the behalfe of himselfe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>The feruent prayer of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous auayleth much.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Iam. 5.16. 1. Pet. 3.12. Ier. 14 11. Deut. 9.14.</note> It is strange to obserue how God seemeth to suffer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence by their prayer: he is enforced to crie out, Pray not for this people, let me alone.</p>
   <p>And will you see all these particulars exemplified in one of Gods fauourites, namely, in faithfull and righteous <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="1">
      <hi>1.</hi> God takes him from Vr of the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does from Idolatrie and superstition,<note place="margin">Gen. 11. &amp; 12. chap.</note> and entertaines him into his owne seruice; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenants to be his God, and commands him to walke before him and be vpright.<note place="margin">Gen.
17.1.</note>
   </p>
   <p n="2">
      <hi>2.</hi> His name is changed in token of further blessing, from <hi>Abram</hi> to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
      <pb facs="6"/>He must be a father of many nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the father of the faithfull,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.5. Rom. 4.13. Iam. 2.23.</note> the heire of the world, the friend of God, and what not?</p>
   <p n="3">
      <hi>3.</hi> God cannot finde in his heart to hide from
<hi>Abraham</hi> his secret purpose, shall I hide from <hi>Abraham</hi> the thing that I doe?<note place="margin">Gen. 18.19</note>
   </p>
   <p n="4">
      <hi>4.</hi> He is allowed to be a Master of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests both for himselfe and for others. As for <hi>Ishmael</hi> I haue heard thee;<note place="margin">Gen 17.20</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I haue blessed him &amp; will make him fruitfull, &amp;c. Againe, God saith to <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech,</hi> Restore the man his wife,<note place="margin">Gen. 20.7</note> is a Prophet, and hee shall pray for thee and thou shalt liue: But marke how in one prayer he preuailed with God in the case of Sodome; obserue, how soone hee brought God to an abatement;<note place="margin">Gen. 18.3</note> from fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to tenne: And I thinke if he had said, If there shall bee found one righteous in the Cittie, God would haue spared it for ones sake; This I am sure of, that God neuer ceased granting till <hi>Abraham</hi> cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed praying. But to what end tendeth this
<pb facs="7"/>discourse? to comfort and encourage thee Oh Christian in these last and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous times wherein wickednesse see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to get the vpper hand and true righteousnesse is outfaced.<note place="margin">Eccles. 3.16 Mal. 3.15.</note> Wee may see
<hi>the place of iudgement, that wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse is there; and the place of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse, that iniquitie is there.</hi> What though Antichrist for a time doe domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neere <hi>withall deceiueablenesse of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteousnesse in them that perish?</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>. Thess. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>10.</note> what though the number of them be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased that
<hi>beleeue not the truth but haue pleasure in vnrighteousnesse?</hi>
      <note place="margin">Verse 12.</note> Bee not thou disheartened, let them feare the Spirit of Gods mouth and the brightnes of his comming;<note place="margin">Verse 8.</note> but lift vp thy head; Be thou as bold as a Lyon,<note place="margin">Prou. 28.1</note> what though the wicked be rich and in amitie with the world?<note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>am. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>.4.</note> thou art more rich; thou hast the better part, that shall neuer be taken from thee.<note place="margin">Prou. 8.13</note>
      <hi>Durable riches and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse,</hi> thou art most happy in Gods sauour, if thou knewest thine owne hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse; and that thou mayest know
<pb facs="7"/>it in some degree, I haue for thy sake wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly published this little Treatise, It is my first borne, my might, and the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my strength; If thou reapest a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profite by it, it is the thing which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, onely praise God in my behalfe, for enabling me to performe any seruice for the good of his Saints, and afford me thy prayers vnto the same God, that I may grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord Iesus Christ.<note place="margin">2: Pet. 3.18</note>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thy brother in the same Lord. <hi>T. P.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>