<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE, Shewinge what vtility disputation may bringe, for discussion of matters in controuersie, &amp; how farre: togeather vvith the causes, vvhy the reuievv of these ten disputations is now pu∣blished.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1604</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105135_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09108</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19414</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105135</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE, Shewinge what vtility disputation may bringe, for discussion of matters in controuersie, &amp; how farre: togeather vvith the causes, vvhy the reuievv of these ten disputations is now pu∣blished.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A revievv of ten publike disputations : or conferences held vvithin the compasse of foure yeares, vnder K. Edward &amp; Qu. Mary, concerning some principall points in religion, especially of the sacrament &amp; sacrifice of the altar. VVherby, may appeare vpon how vveake groundes both catholike religion vvas changed in England; as also the fore-recounted Foxian Martyrs did build their new opinions, and offer themselues to the fire for the same, vvhich vvas chiefly vpon the creditt of the said disputations. By N.D</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bellet, Francois</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Saint-Omer</pubPlace>
                    <date>1604</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>370, 2 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE, <hi>Shewinge what vtility disputation may bringe, for discussion of matters in controuersie, &amp; how farre: togeather vvith the causes, vvhy the</hi> reuievv <hi>of these ten disputations is now pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT disputation is a good meanes and profitable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument, to examine and try out truth, euen in matters of faith, yf yt be rightly vsed, &amp; vvith due circumstances, no man can deny; for that experience in Gods Church doth teach yt, to vvitt, that great vtility hath often-tymes byn receaued by such disputations: and vve read amonge other examples, that in the tyme of <hi>Antoninus</hi> the Emperour sonne of <hi>Seuerus,</hi> that died in <hi>Yorke,</hi> a little more then a hundred yeares after Christ, the
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
      <hi>Montanists</hi> heresy, vvho vvere called also <hi>Cataphrigians,</hi> grovving strong, and dravvinge to it diuers pricipall men, and namely <hi>Tertullian,</hi> vvith the admiratiō of the vvhole vvorld; one <hi>Caius</hi> a Cath man most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently learned, and of rare and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous <note place="margin">
         <hi>Anno Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> 215.</note> life, tooke vpon him to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spute publikely in <hi>Rome</hi> in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of the vvhole Church, vvith licēce of <hi>Zepherinus</hi> the Pope, against a chiefe principall man of that sect called <hi>Proclus,</hi> and so confounded him therin, as frō that day forvvard the sect began greatly to decline; of vvhich disputatiō do make mentiō both <hi>Eusebius</hi> &amp; <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> &amp; yt did <note place="margin">
         <hi>Euseb. l.</hi> 6. <hi>hist. c.</hi> 14. <hi>Hier. de vir. Illust. in Caio.</hi>
      </note> much profitt that Catholike cause.</p>
   <p n="2">2. And about 2. hundred yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this againe, vve read of another profitable disputation held in our countrey, by <hi>S. Germanus</hi> &amp; his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovves, French Bishopps, vvith the
<pb n="5" facs="3"/>
Brittish <hi>Pelagians</hi> vpon the yeare of <note place="margin">
         <hi>Bed. l.</hi> 1. <hi>hist. c.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp; Const. presbyt. in vita S. Lupi episc.</hi>
      </note> Christ 429. vvherby they vvere so confuted, as also vvith the miracles vvrought by <hi>S. German,</hi> by certaine reliques brought from <hi>Rome,</hi> as their heresie neuer prospered there after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard, but vvas soone extinguished. VVe read in like manner of diuers publike cōflicts &amp; disputatiōs, held by <hi>S. Austen</hi> vvith diuers learned he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiks of sundry sects, as namely vvith <hi>Fortunatus</hi> a <hi>Manichean</hi> priest, in the citty of <hi>Hippo</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> vpon the yeare 392. al the clergy &amp; people being present, &amp; publike notaryes appointed to set dovvne both their argumēts: &amp; the issue of this dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiōs vvas, that vvhē the <hi>Manichean</hi> heretike could not ansvvere, he said (saith <hi>Possidonius) secum suis maioribus collaturum,</hi> that he vvould conferre those difficultyes vvith his betters, &amp; then if they could not satisfy him
<pb n="6" facs="4"/>
      <hi>se animae suae consulturum,</hi> that he <note place="margin">See the acts of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputatiō <hi>in Possid. l. de vita Aug. c.</hi> 3.</note> vvould haue care of his ovvne soule. But this care vvas (saith the same <hi>Possidonius)</hi> that he ranne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay from the citty, and neuer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared there againe. VVhich point <hi>S. Augustine</hi> himselfe obiecteth, in a certayne epistle, to another <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chee</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Aug. epist.</hi> 244.</note> Priest, that came to succeed in <hi>Fortunatus</hi> his place in that citty, prouokinge him also to like dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but the heretike refused the combatt.</p>
   <p n="3">3. And after this againe, the said Father being novv made Bishopp, vpon the yeare of Christ 405. he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputed publikely for tvvo dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, vvith another principall <hi>Manichean</hi> heretike named <hi>Foelix,</hi> in presence of the vvhole people, notaryes being appointed on both sides to take their arguments. In <note place="margin">
         <hi>S. Austens</hi> disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with <hi>Foelix Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichaeus</hi>
      </note> vvhich disputation, <hi>S. Austen</hi> did so
<pb n="7" facs="4"/>
euidently conuince his aduersarie, as he in the end yelded (a strange example in an heretike) and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced his heresie, and became a Catholike, vvhereby the <hi>Maui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chean</hi> heresie vvas so shaken and discredited throughout all <hi>Africa,</hi> as no man euer openly aftervvard durst defend the same in disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but it vanished avvay by little and little, as a smoke vvhen the fire is putt out. This vvhole disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to be seene at large in <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten,</hi> laid forth in tvvo books of his <hi>de actis cum Faelice Manichaeo.</hi> And this for the <hi>Manicheans.</hi>
   </p>
   <p n="4">4. But vvith the Donatists and Arrians, he had many other like conflicts: as for example, vpon the yeare of Christ 411. there vvas a sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne disputation held at <hi>Carthage</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>S. Ausren</hi> his dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists.</note> in <hi>Africa,</hi> for diuers daies togeather, betvvene the Catholike and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natist
<pb n="8" facs="5"/>
Bishopps, the Cath. Bishopps being in number 286. vvherof the principall disputer vvas <hi>S. Austen</hi>
      <note place="margin">Breuic. collat. primi diei.</note> himselfe; &amp; of the Donatist Bishops 279. vvhich shevveth the multitude of heretiks in those parts to haue byn great, notvvithstandinge they had bin much diminished by Cath. Bishops labours and vvrytings: for that 17. yeares before, there mett to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather against the Catholiks 400. Donatist Bishopps, exceptinge six: this disputation vvas before the <hi>Conte Marcellinus</hi> gouernour of that countrey, and publike notaryes vvere present to take the argumēts on both sides, and all being ended the Iudge pronounced this sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: <hi>Omnium documentorum mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festatione, à Catholicis Donatistas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futatos.</hi>
      <note place="margin">Aug. in Breuic.</note> That the Donatists vvere conuinced by the Catholiks, by the manifest truth of all kind of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb n="9" facs="5"/>
      <hi>S. Augustine</hi> himselfe setteth forth a breefe relation of all that meeting &amp; disputation, intituling yt <hi>Breuiculum.</hi> And in a certayne epistle of his testifieth moreouer of the euent, that albeit those mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <note place="margin">Epist. ad Gaudent.</note> Bishops vvere not conuerted therby, but rather made more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinate &amp; obdurate: yet that many of their people vvere, &amp; especially of the furious <hi>Circumcellians,</hi> that vvere ready to murder men vpon zeale of their heresie.</p>
   <p n="5">5. I lett passe another disputation vvhich the said Father had, some 10. or 11. yeares after that, by the order of <hi>Pope Zozimus</hi> of Rome, in the Citty of <hi>Caesarea</hi> in <hi>Mauritania,</hi> vvith one <hi>Emeritus</hi> a Donatist B. of that Citty; all the vvhole people of the Citty, togeather vvith diuers Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopps, being present; but little good could be done vvith him, his
<pb n="10" facs="6"/>
obstinacy vvas so great and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Acta apud Aug. ep.</hi> 157. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 2. <hi>Retract. c.</hi> 51. <hi>&amp; Possidon. in vita Aug. c.</hi> 14.</note> The acts of that disputation are extant in <hi>S. Austen,</hi> &amp; often men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therof is made by himselfe, &amp; by <hi>Possidonius</hi> in his life. And this for the Donatists.</p>
   <p n="6">6. But vvith the Arrians I find the same Father to haue had sundry di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputations also, as namely once vpon the yeare of Christ 422. the Gouernour <hi>Bonifacius,</hi> hauinge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">
         <hi>Possid. ib. cap.</hi> 17.</note> Gothes in his campe vvho vvere of the Arrian sect: they had also an Arrian Bishopp that gouerned them, named <hi>Maximinus,</hi> vvho in their opinion vvas very learned, and therfore they made instance, that he might dispute vvith <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi> vvhich the good Father ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, for he refused none, and so they had their meetinge and dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <note place="margin">
         <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputatiōs vvith the Atrians.</note> and the acts thereof are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in his vvorks, togeather vvith
<pb n="11" facs="6"/>
a certaine booke of his ovvne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thervnto, for explication of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers points, vvherof these heretiks vvere vvont to vaunt aftervvard, as though they had gott the victory; vvhich happened to the same Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in another combatt, held the very same yeare, vvith one <hi>Conte Pascentius</hi> of the same Arrian sect, vvho vvas cheefe fifchall or trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sourer of the Emperor, and most arrogantlie chalenged to dispute vvith <hi>S. Austen,</hi> but yet in priuate &amp; vvithout notaryes, in respect of the Emperiall lavves, that did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidd publike disputations in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of sects and heresies. VVhich disputation <hi>S. Augustine</hi> accepted; and the same vvas held priuatly, in the presence of many noble and learned men, but the heretikes <note place="margin">
         <hi>Aug. epist.</hi> 73. 74. 75. 76. 77.</note> vvould not yeld, but rather publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed soone after (as their fashion is)
<pb n="12" facs="7"/>
that they had the victory, vvhich <hi>S. Austen</hi> vvas forced to refute by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny seuerall epistles, and by settinge forth the disputation it selfe, as yt is to be seene in his vvorks.</p>
   <p n="7">7. And this may suffice for a tast of some disputations, held at diuers tymes and in diuers countreyes, vvith heretiks of sundry sects in the ancient Church: And I might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite <note place="margin">Photius in Bibliothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note> many more, as that of <hi>Maximus</hi> a learned Catholike monke in <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Anasta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius hoc anno.</note> vvho vpon the yeare of Christ 645. held a very famous disputation against one <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> a great pillar of those heretiks called <hi>Monothelits,</hi> that held one only vvill, and not tvvo to be in Christ our Sauiour, vvhich di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputation being made in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of many Bishopps, and of the gouernour of that <hi>Country,</hi> named <hi>Gregorius Patricius,</hi> the hereticall
<pb n="13" facs="7"/>
Archbishopp vvas so confounded, as he left his heresie, vvent to <hi>Rome,</hi> and gaue vp a booke of his pennance to <hi>Pope Theodorus,</hi> and vvas receaued by him into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike communion againe: and that vvas the euent of that dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
   <p n="8">8. And not full 20. yeares after this againe, to vvitt vpon the yeare 664. vvas that great disputation also in England, betvvene the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish and scottish Bishops, about the obseruation of <hi>Easter,</hi> in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of tvvo Kings <hi>Oswyn</hi> and <hi>Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frid</hi> his sonne, <hi>Kinges</hi> of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Beda l.</hi> 3. <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>st. cap.</hi> 25.</note> and of the <hi>Mercians:</hi> the cheefe disputers, on the Scottish Bishopps parte, vvere <hi>Colman</hi> and <hi>Cedda,</hi> and of the English, <hi>Agilber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> Bishopp of the <hi>VVestsaxons</hi> and <hi>VVilfrid:</hi> and the issue of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputation vvas, that Kings <hi>Osvvyn</hi>
      <pb n="14" facs="8"/>
vvas conuerted to the vnion of the Roman Church, and caused the vse thereof to be practized in his countrey.</p>
   <p n="9">9. And so vve see by these ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and many more that might be alleaged, that disputations in points of Religion are sometymes necessary, &amp; do much good, vvhen they are taken in hand vvith equall and due conditions, and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient lavves for indifferency in try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge out the truth, for that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvayes they may be pernicious, &amp; haue byn refused by anciēt Fathers, as vve read of one reiected by <hi>Saint Ambrose</hi> in <hi>Milayne,</hi> vpon the yeare <note place="margin">Publike disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by <hi>S. Ambros.</hi> vpon iust causes.</note> of Christ 286. vvhen <hi>Auxentius</hi> the Arrian-Bishopp, being puffed vp vvith pride &amp; arrogancy, by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the Empresse <hi>Iustina,</hi> infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vvith the same heresy, had not only prouoked <hi>S. Ambrose</hi> to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike
<pb n="15" facs="8"/>
disputation, but had further procured that <hi>Valentinian</hi> the yong Emperour, being yet a child, &amp; not baptized but only <hi>Cathecumenus,</hi> did make a publike edict, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the said disputations to be held vpō such a day, in his publike court or consistorie, before him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe &amp; the said Empresse, certaine learned Pagans and Ievves being appointed for iudges in that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But <hi>S. Ambrose,</hi> by the counsell of diuers Bishopps gathered togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vvith him, refused to come to those disputatiōs, vvryting a booke to the Emperour <hi>Valentinian</hi> for his <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ambros. epist.</hi> 31. vvhere is extant also the booke sent by <hi>Ambrose</hi> to <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinian.</hi>
      </note> excuse, shevvinge the iniustice and vnequality of the order, and of those tymes, and persuadinge him to recall the said lavv. And yf he vvould haue that controuersie in religion, betvveene them and the <hi>Arrians,</hi> treated againe, he should
<pb n="16" facs="9"/>
follovv therin the excellent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his predecessor <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the great, vvho suffered Priests and Bishopps only to handle that matter in the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> and so vvas this disputation broken of: &amp; presently there happened a thing of great admiratiō (saith <hi>Paulinus</hi> in the life of <hi>S. Ambrose)</hi> vvhich vvas, <note place="margin">Paul. in vita Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brosij.</note> that a certaine principall learned <hi>Arrian, acerrimus disputator; &amp; inconuertibilis ad fidem Catholicam,</hi> being a most eager disputer, and esteemed not possible to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to the Catholike faith; being deceaued, at it seemeth, of his hope and expectation to dispute in this conflict, vvent to the Church, to heare at least vvhat <hi>Ambrose</hi> could say out of the pulpit in his sermons: vvhere seing an Angell to speake as it vvere in his eare, he vvas by that miracle not only conuerted to be a
<pb n="17" facs="9"/>
Catholike, but became also a most vehement defendor of that faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the heretiks.</p>
   <p n="10">10. To returne then to our purpose of disputation, yt is of great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hovv, and in vvhat tyme and place, and vvith vvhat lavves and conditions they are made, vvherof yovv vvill see the proofe and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience also in these ten, that heere vve are to present; vvherof six being <note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison betwene Cath &amp; hereticall disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> held vnder the gouernemēt of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, and 4. vnder Catholike magistrates, yovv shall see com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints on both sides of inequality vsed: but he that shall read and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider them in differently, and vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out passion, euen as they are sett dovvne by Fox himselfe (for vve could gett no other records therof for the present) he shall easily see no small differences to appeare. For that the disputatiōs both at <hi>Oxford</hi>
      <pb n="18" facs="10"/>
and <hi>Cambridge</hi> in K. Henryes dayes, vvere only certaine ostentations of light skyrmishes a farre of, so vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fondly performed, as they haue no substance in them at all. And so he vvill see that shall read these examinations. The other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Queene Mary,</hi> though the first of them in the conuocation-house, vvherin Protestants only vvere op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents, vvas not much vnlike the former for substāce, or rather lacke of substance: yet the other three held in <hi>Oxford</hi> against <hi>Cranmer, Ridley</hi> and <hi>Latymer</hi> by Catholike disputers, are of a farre different kynd, as hauinge both iudges, nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, and arbitrators to the likinge of both parts appointed. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit in the manner of vrginge ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, there vvant not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the Protestant party, as after yovv shall heare: for that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb n="19" facs="10"/>
somtymes are said to haue spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken togeather, &amp; one man to haue putt himselfe into the prosecution of another mans argument, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvhat disorderly as to them yt see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: yet touchinge the thinges themselues, to vvitt the arguments &amp; proofes there laid forth &amp; prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, there vvere so many cleere, substantiall &amp; vveighty, as the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vvill cōfesse there vvas no tyme lost in those 3. dayes disputation of the Cath party. And so to the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination therof I remitt me.</p>
   <p n="11">11. One thing of no small impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance there is to be cōsidered in this preface about the nature of disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; to vvitt, that as it is a fit meanes <note place="margin">Disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō fitter in some to moue doubts &amp; examine the truth, then to resolue the same.</note> to styrre vp mans vnderstandinge to attēd the truth, by layinge forth the difficultyes on both sides; so is yt not alvvayes sufficient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solue his iudgement, for that yt
<pb n="20" facs="11"/>
moueth more doubts then he can aunsvvere or dissolue. And this happeneth not only in vnlearned people, vvhich by no meanes can descerne vvhich party hath the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vvhen both parts are learned &amp; alleage arguments for themselues, in matters aboue their capacity, but euen the most learned also, yf they haue no other meanes of resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then arguing to and fro by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputation, are brought many-times to be more doubtfull therby then before, &amp; this euen in matters both naturall and morall of this life. The reason vvherof is, that mans vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standinge being limited, and the light of knovvledge imparted vnto him from God, being but a little particle or sparkle of his infinite di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine knovvledge: yt cometh to passe, that the more this sparkle is exercised, &amp; inkendled in searching
<pb n="21" facs="11"/>
out Gods vvorks and secrets in this life, the more yt seeth her ovvne vveaknes, and beginneth to doubt more, &amp; to be more ambiguous in herselfe, vvhether that vvhich shee apprehendeth be truly apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or no, or vvhether by further search shee shall not find it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvise, and see herselfe deceaued in this apprehensiō, as she hath found in many other apprehensions that vvent before, vvhen she had lesse knovvledge.</p>
   <p n="12">12. And vpon this ground no doubt came those philosophers, called the <hi>Academicks,</hi> to found their sect &amp; profession, that they vvould belceue or affirme nothing, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spute of all things to and fro vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out assent. And heere hence came also the sayinge of that other philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher: <hi>Hoc Unum scio, me nihil scire.</hi> I knovv only this, that I knovv no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge.
<pb n="22" facs="12"/>
And <hi>S. Austen</hi> himselfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his conuersion, being yet a <hi>Manichee,</hi> &amp; vvearyed out vvith this search by vvay of arguments to and fro, vvhich should be the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giō (for this vvas one of their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall groūds, as himselfe testified, to beleeue nothinge, but that vvhich vvas euidēt by reason) fell at length to forsake the <hi>Manichees,</hi> &amp; to ioyne himselfe to the Academiks: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long search finding no certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty also therin, and hearing their sect <note place="margin">Aug. l. de moribus Ecclesiae contra Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheos.</note> euery day impugned by <hi>S. Ambrose</hi> Bishopp of <hi>Millayne</hi> (vvhere then <hi>Augustine</hi> remayned) he returned in the end by the motion of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, to consider vvhat more grounds the Catholike Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion had, to stay a mans iudgement <note place="margin">
         <hi>Aug. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 1. 2. 11.</note> or cōscience, then the vncertainty of disputations, and findinge the same, resolued himselfe to renoūce
<pb n="23" facs="12"/>
all sects and to be a Catholike, as in his ovvne confessions at large he declareth.</p>
   <p n="13">13. By this then vve do see, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit disputation rightly vsed, be a good meanes to discouer truth by mouinge doubts to and fro, yet is yt not alvvayes sufficient to resolue and quiett a mans iudgement, euen in naturall thinges: and yf not in these, hovv much lesse in superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and diuine, vvherin humaine disputation hath farre lesse force? For that humaine sciences, dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinge their disputation from prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples that are euidently knovvne vnto vs by light of nature, may farre better resolue a man by force of those disputations, and enforce <note place="margin">VVhat force di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputatiō hath in resoluing matters of faith.</note> him to yeld his assent, then in matters of diuinity, vvhere the first grounds and principles, are not knovvne to vs by light of nature,
<pb n="24" facs="13"/>
as in humaine sciences, but are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued only by light of faith, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyled from God: vvherfore these disputations may serue to examine and discusse matters, for stirring vp our vnderstanding, but the resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; determination, must come frō a more certaine meanes vvhich is infallible, and this vve see practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the very first cōtrouersy, that euer vvas handled in the priuitiue Church, as is recorded by <hi>S. Luke</hi> in the Acts of the Apostles, vvhere the question being, vvhether Christiās conuerted of gentills, should be bound to the obseruation of the mosayicall lavv or no? there vvas (saith the text) first <hi>magna conquisitio,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 15.</note> a great search or disputation about <note place="margin">The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Apostles.</note> the matter; and then secondly the Apostles declared their sentences in order; and finally the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vvas in all their names, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting
<pb n="25" facs="13"/>
the vvhole Church, <hi>visum est spiritui sancto &amp; nobis,</hi> yt seemed good to the holy-ghost and vs, and so vvas the matter determined, and the like forme hath byn obserued euer since that tyme in the Cath. Church, determining all cōtrouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies that haue fallen out, to vvit, that first there should be great search &amp; discussion of the matter, by lavvfull and free disputation, to vvhich end the most learned men of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are sent cōmonly to generall Councells, to performe this point. And secondly all argumēts on both sides being heard &amp; examined, the Bishops presēt do giue their voices, and accordinge to the greater part, vvith concourse &amp; generall appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the generall head, do they determine <hi>visum est spiritui sancto &amp; nobis.</hi> So as heere disputatiō serueth not to determine but to examine.</p>
   <p n="14">
      <pb n="26" facs="14"/>
14. And for that the sectaryes of our dayes haue not this sound meane to determyne matters, but do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend <note place="margin">The wāt which se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaryes haue to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne matters by <hi>Cicero in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox.</hi>
      </note> only vpon probability, and persuasibility of speach, or vvry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one against the other, <hi>by which</hi> (as <hi>Tully</hi> saith) <hi>nothinge is so incredible, that may not be made probable:</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are their questions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersies endlesse and indetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; and though they haue had aboue a hundred meetings, confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, disputations, Councells and synods from their first disputation held at <hi>Lypsia,</hi> vpon the yeare 1519. vnto their synodde in <hi>Vilna,</hi> vpon the yeare 1590. vvhereof yovv may see more largely in <hi>Stanislaus Rescius</hi> his obseruations: yet could they neuer agree, nor vvill hereafter, lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge the forsaid meanes of resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and determination vpon their disputations.</p>
   <p n="15">
      <pb n="27" facs="14"/>
15. And yf this do fall out euen in the learnedst of our sectaryes, that they cannot by disputations alone resolue soundly eyther themselues, or others in matters of cōtrouersy, for that still there remaine doubts and difficultyes, vvhether matters vvere vvell prosecuted or no; and nevv arguments do offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues dayly to and fro: vvhat shall vve thinke of the vnlearned and ignorant people, that cannot vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand that is argued, and much lesse iudge therof? and yet vpon the creditt of such disputations do aduenture their foules, as yovv haue seene by many lamentable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples before in both mē &amp; vveo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that vpon the fame &amp; creditt of these English disputations heere sett dovvne by Fox, partlie vnder <hi>K. Edward,</hi> &amp; partlie vnder <hi>Queene Mary,</hi> and vpon the probabilitie of
<pb n="28" facs="15"/>
some fond and broken arguments <note place="margin">The will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes of Foxtan vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes in disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> vsed therin for the Protestants side, as somevvhat apparant &amp; plausible to their senses &amp; capacity, haue not only stood therein most arrognatly against their Bishopps, and learned Pastors by open disputatiōs in their Courts and Consistoryes, but haue runne also to the fire for the same, vvherof <hi>Allerton, Tankerfield, Crash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, Fortune,</hi> and others <note n="*" place="margin">Mensi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>us Ian Mars. Sept &amp; Noucmb.</note> before mentioned being but <hi>Cooks, Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> and <hi>Coblars</hi> by occupation: yea vveomen also as <hi>Anne Alebright, Alice Potkins, Ioan Lashford, Alice Dryuer,</hi> and others may be ridiculous but lamentable examples.</p>
   <p n="16">16. Neither is this a nevv or strange thinge, that hereticall vveomen should grovv to such insolency, as to stand in disputation vvith the learnedst Bishops of the Catholike side, for that vve read it recorded in
<pb n="29" facs="15"/>
Ecclesiasticall historyes aboue 12. <note place="margin">The story of a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni hean</hi> woman that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputed with a Bishopp.</note> hundred yeares gone, to vvitt vpon the yeare of Christ 403. that a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne vvillfull vvoman of the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Antioch</hi> named <hi>Iulia,</hi> infected vvith the abhominable heresie of the <hi>Manichees</hi> and feruent therein, came vnto the citty of <hi>Gaza,</hi> vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>S. Porphyrius</hi> a holy learned man vvas Bishop, &amp; beginning there to peruert diuers Christians, &amp; being for the same reprehended by the Bishopp, she contemned him, yea chalenged him to open disputatiō, vvhich the good man admittinge, she behaued herselfe so insolently therein as vvas intolerable: So as vvhen he had suffered her a great vvhile to alleage her blasphemous arguments, &amp; could by no meanes reduce her or make her harken to the truth, he fell from disputation to vse another meane, turning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
<pb n="30" facs="16"/>
to God, sayinge: <hi>O Eternall</hi>
      <note place="margin">Mareus in vita <hi>S. Porphirij.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>God vvhich hast created all thinges, and art only eternall, hauinge no beginninge or endinge, vvho art glorified in the blessed Trinitie, strike this vvomans tongue, and stopp her mouth that she speake no more blasphemyes against thee.</hi>
      <q>VVhich vvords being vttered, <hi>Iulia</hi> began to stammer, and to change countenance, fallinge into an <hi>extasis,</hi> and so leesing her voyce, remained dumme vntill she died, vvhich vvas soone after, vvherat tvvo men and tvvo vveomen that came vvith her fell dovvne at the Bishopps feete as kinge pardon, and vvere conuerted, as vvere diuers gentills also by the same miracle.</q>
   </p>
   <p n="17">17. And this vvas the conclusion of that disputation; and though it pleased not almightie God to vse the like miracles externallie in <hi>Qu. Maryes</hi> dayes, for the repressinge of
<pb n="31" facs="16"/>
those insolēt vveomen that dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted so malepartlie, and vttered so manie blasphemous speaches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the soueraigne misterie of Christs reall presence in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yet can there be no great doubt, but that invvardlie he vsed the same, or no lesse iustice vnto them, especiallie seing he suffered them to go to the fire all vvithout repentance, and so to perish both bodilie and ghostlie, temporallie add eternallie. And for that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cytinge <note place="margin">The cause of the Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of these di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> their storyes before sett dovvne, intendinge all breuitie possible, I could not conuenientlie lay forth their seuerall arguments in disputation, as neyther of those that vvere their maisters and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers to this maddnes; I haue thought good heere to examine all togeather in this <hi>Re-vievv,</hi> vvhereby yovv shall see vvhat
<pb n="32" facs="17"/>
grounds they had of so great an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprise, and of so obstinate a prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution therof. And this shall suffice by vvay of <hi>Preface:</hi> Novv vvill vve passe to the recytall of the said di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputations.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>