<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE LEARNED AND IVDICIOVS READERS.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1628</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105608_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00972</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11078</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105608</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE LEARNED AND IVDICIOVS READERS.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of the perfect-cursed-blessed man : setting forth mans excellency by his generation, miserie [by his] degeneration, felicitie [by his] regeneration. By I.F. Master of Arts, preacher of Gods word, and rector of Wilbie in Suff</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, Joseph</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1628</date>
                 <publisher>Flesher (Fletcher), Miles.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Milbourne (Milburne, Mylbourne), Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 72, 4 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>TO THE LEARNED AND IVDICIOVS READERS.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot that I desire such Readers only, doe I prefix this Epistle; but only to desire, if any such shall vouchsafe to reade this poore Labor, that they would also vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to make a favourable construction of what they reade: and to take-notice that I doe not hold, that all the ther-in mentioned <hi>Decrees, Consultations, Iudgements,</hi> &amp;c. were just so <hi>in actu,</hi> as they are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in set-down; or as the tenour of the Story may seeme to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. For I have learned another lesson, which I desire those that have not, to learne, and beleeve with me.</p>
   <p>For mine owne part, I know and beleeve that all things whatsoever that either have bin, are, or shall be▪ so far as they have reference unto <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Primus Motor,</hi> ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall <hi>Author,</hi> and principall <hi>Actor</hi> of them; of whom, through whom, and for whom, they have and receive their being and motion: (all secondary causes being contained
<pb facs="8"/>
within the sphere of their first cause; I beleeve, I say) that being thus considered in <hi>God,</hi> they have neither <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ius</hi> nor <hi>posterius</hi>; first nor last: because God is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega,</hi> both first and last: the first of <hi>Causes,</hi> the last of <hi>Ends,</hi> that is, all in all: they being in Him <hi>semel &amp; si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul,</hi> as one individuall substance, or continued motion; He being in Him-selfe, <hi>Ens cujus centrum est ubi{que} &amp; cujus circumferentia nullibi:</hi> so that nothing can be besides Him, He being of Himselfe every way <hi>infinite.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Vpon this ground all Gods <hi>Purposes, Motions, Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> (whether in respect of the Creature, necessary or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent;) as also the subject wheron Hee workes, yea and likewise the instrumentall Causes whereby He workes, are all present unto Him: because He beholdeth all things, <hi>uno &amp; eodem intuitu,</hi> at one instant; there being no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Him at all betwixt things past, and present, and to come: these being meerly and onely the distinctions of time. But <hi>GOD</hi> who is <hi>Light,</hi> and dwelleth in light; <hi>which was, and which is, and which is to come; the same yesterday and to day,</hi> and the same for ever; needeth not the distinctions of Time for the resolution and execution of his <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Actions.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>All things then being in <hi>God, God</hi> in Himselfe is to be considered as a most rich, beautifull, and glorious <hi>Treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> of such transcendent, superexcellent, and incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible <hi>Nature, Majesty,</hi> &amp; <hi>Order,</hi> as that not any Creature
<pb facs="8"/>
in Heaven or Earth is able to conceive how any one thing in Him is either decreed, promoted, or acted, simply, truly, and as it is indeed: for <hi>Creatures</hi> are circumscribed in all their faculties and powers, and cannot goe beyond their extent.</p>
   <p>For us then positively to describe, define, or determine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of Gods <hi>Decrees, Consultations,</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> (I meane <hi>ad intus;</hi>) or of his order of doing them, as, that first He did that, afterwards this, and last of all thus, it is <hi>Satanicall</hi> pride, and arrogant presumption: so insearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able is his Wisedome, and his waies past finding out.</p>
   <p>Yet again the same insearchable things of God, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered <hi>quoad nos,</hi> and referred to their visible and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensible <hi>Causes, Ends, Objects,</hi> and <hi>Effects;</hi> so they admit of <hi>prius</hi> and <hi>posterius,</hi> and may be said to bee first or second according to the setled order of <hi>Nature, Time,</hi> or <hi>Being.</hi> And upon this ground we may look upon the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God, as issuing or proceeding from Him in a most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, comely, and beautifull <hi>order</hi> and <hi>succession,</hi> whereby Hee manifesteth his owne glory, and advanceth the good of his Creatures. And yet this acceptation, distinction, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Gods doings ariseth from our owne weak ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities and apprehensions, and not from the things of <hi>God</hi> them-selves: for as we conceive and understand them to be, or have beene done, so doe wee judge of them, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="9"/>Now, for that we are weake to conceive, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand aright the wonderfull things of <hi>God</hi> (as indeed the least worke of his is wonderfull in it selfe, and infinitely surpasseth our imagination,) <hi>God</hi> therefore in mercy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords us many helpes to further us therein; <hi>per corporalia spiritualia docens; &amp; per visibilia invisibilia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrans,</hi> and so speaketh to us of his owne immense and incomprehensible <hi>Resolutions</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> in phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and tearms sutable and agreeable to our owne weake capacities. Not for that we are to conceive it to be just so, and so with the Lord concerning that thing of which Hee speaketh, and no otherwise; but for that otherwise than so or so as He speaketh, wee cannot possibly conceive it to bee. He stoopeth to our infirmitie, and speaketh to us concerning <hi>Him-selfe</hi> in our own dialect, and giveth us leave to speak of Him and his Actions, as wee doe of our selves and our owne.</p>
   <p>And because we alwaies contrive and frame to our selves a methodicall order of what we doe before it bee done; and cannot attaine to the consummation of our ends, but by some orderly proceedings; as by <hi>intentions, meditations, consultations, endevours, executions,</hi> and the like: so likewise we (measuring the great works of <hi>God</hi> by the same compass we doe our owne) doe conceive them to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun and effected by such like passages and progressions as our own are; as by <hi>decrees, consultations, resolutions,</hi>
      <pb facs="9"/>
or some meanes or other to ripen and bring them to their productions.</p>
   <p>And thus it is that wee dare take-upon us to speake of Gods great workes of wonder: as (not to name any other) of these, of <hi>Mans Creation,</hi> and <hi>Redemption,</hi> both which we conceive to be on this manner:</p>
   <p>First touching <hi>Mans Creation;</hi> we conceive that <hi>God</hi> moved with zeale of propagating his own glory, did take in hand, even out of <hi>Nothing</hi> to frame and create <hi>Man,</hi> as a fit matter or subject, where-on to stamp and set the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of his owne <hi>Image,</hi> that so Hee might communicate his owne everlasting <hi>Goodness</hi> to a Creature so qualified and endowed. Which <hi>Creature</hi> notwithstanding so formed and enabled, is not, nor cannot be equall to his <hi>Creator</hi> in the excellencie of Goodness or power of Perseverance: though for qualitie He partake of his Creators Goodness, and for form He be made in his Creators Image.</p>
   <p>And for this we conceive a double reason; the one from <hi>God,</hi> the other from Man: from <hi>God,</hi> because He is (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding this his work of <hi>Creation,</hi> that is, of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another thing besides Himselfe into <hi>Esse,</hi> and so into open view, yet we say, He is) still infinite, and so no whit lessened, or any way impayred, either in quality of <hi>Essence,</hi> or in ability of <hi>perpetuity.</hi> For all excellency or goodness is fontally in Him; and what excellency or goodness soever is in any Creature, it is but <hi>guttula illius formositatis,
<pb facs="10"/>
bonitatis, suavitatis quae est in Creatore:</hi> which, being severed from God, doth ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>upon instantly perish, &amp; turne to nothing. And therfore Man no longer bears the perfect qualitie of his Creators <hi>Image,</hi> than that Hee continues in Him good, and constantly the same Hee was, according to that stamp and tincture which Hee received from God in his Creation. So that Mans perfection is not so excellent as his Makers, no nor any whit equivalent ther-unto; because perfection in Man is but as a beame of glorie issuing from <hi>God</hi> the fountain of glory: wheras in <hi>God</hi> it is originally essentiall, and everlastingly infinite.</p>
   <p>Again <hi>Man</hi> is not so excellent as his <hi>Maker;</hi> for wee must consider his originall matter, wher-on He was made; which was <hi>Nothing:</hi> now this <hi>Nothing,</hi> by the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Goodness of <hi>God,</hi> was made <hi>something,</hi> and this <hi>something</hi> was made <hi>Man</hi> bearing the stamp of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors goodness. Yet this goodnes in Man, though derived from the unchangeable goodness of God, was not otherwise than changeably good: because it was now seated or inherent in a dissoluble subject of a changeable disposition, able to stand in, or fall from its goodnes, as it selfe should resolve.</p>
   <p>Now, I say, the receptivitie of created matter affords no room for <hi>unchangeable goodnes.</hi> As it stood with Gods goodnes to make Man good, yea and very good: so it stood with the nature of Mans essence, being a made matter, not to be capable of unchangeable goodnes. For unchangeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb facs="10"/>
and immutability in goodness is proper onely to <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency,</hi> or the <hi>creating Power,</hi> because that onely hath subsistence in it selfe; which subsistence in it selfe is that onely which gives life and being to unchangeablness. Nor againe can the thing created comprehend the Creators good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, because that is finite, this infinite: and it is a certaine rule, <hi>Minus non habet in se majus,</hi> and therefore Man cannot comprehend his Makers goodness. Which if we should fondly imagine, that <hi>God,</hi> if Hee had pleased, might have made Man absolutely and constantly good like Him-selfe, no way liable to change or alteration: then we must also ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that <hi>Man</hi> should have bin more than made in the <hi>image</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or after his likeness; for then hee should have bin all one with his Creatour, both in <hi>Essence</hi> and <hi>qualitie:</hi> for there is less difference betwixt the Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of God, and unchangeable goodness, than betwixt <hi>fire,</hi> and the heat thereof; or the <hi>Sunne</hi> and the light thereof, though the one really and inseparably express the other. For set any subject in such an equall distance to the fire, as that it shall receive the heat thereof, and yet not be enflamed therewith: or conveigh the light of the Sunne by a reflecting object to enlighten a darke body; yet that heat, or this light thus divided from their proper seats and subjects, is neither the heat of the fire, nor yet the light of the Sun: their subjects being hot, or light, <hi>remissis gradibus,</hi> perhaps that but warme, it may be this
<pb facs="11"/>
but dim. Whereas the true heat of the fire in its proper na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and quality doth alwaies burne and consume; and the true light in the body of the Sun doth alwaies dazle and confound the sense of all humane sight to behold it. And yet it must be confessed that that heat, being but warm; and this light, being but dim, did both of them come originally the one from the very fire, the other from the very Sun.</p>
   <p>So likewise, touching the <hi>Goodness</hi> that is in <hi>Man,</hi> though it came originally from the <hi>unchangeable Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness that is in God,</hi> yet being now seated or inherent in a created substance (whose continent is infinitly less than the originall of the thing infused) it is no more of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable condition which is in <hi>God,</hi> than either the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <hi>heat</hi> or <hi>light</hi> can truly and properly be said to be either Sun or fire.</p>
   <p>But here I know some object the condition of the blessed <hi>Angels,</hi> saying, that sith they kept their first station and perfection, and never lost that <hi>goodness</hi> and <hi>holiness</hi> they were created in, therfore their goodness is <hi>unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able:</hi> to which I answer, it followes no more, that because they have not fallen from their goodness, that therefore their goodness is unchangeable; then because a cleare Cristall glass is not yet broken, or a faire timber-house is not yet burnt, that the one is not brickle, nor the other combustible. Though we grant that the blessed <hi>Angels</hi> neither ever did, nor ever shall fall from their goodness; yet we must know it
<pb facs="11"/>
was in their nature to have fallen as well as the Angels that did fall, (who as some are bold to affirm, were not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour, but more excellent in glory than the constant An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.) But these good Angels have resisted all <hi>inducements</hi> and <hi>allurements</hi> to procure their change: and happily by their resistance are now so confirmed in their goodness, (or else by some other than by an infused or created power, are now so upholden and enabled) that they shall never fall: the <hi>Providence</hi> of <hi>God</hi> over them enabling them to stand.</p>
   <p>But to returne to the goodness in Man: let us know it was changeable; that is, might continue, or vanish, even as him-selfe would: as that warm heat or dim light might last, or be extinct, as their subjects were kept to, or removed▪ frō their originall causes. So whiles <hi>Man</hi> kept that state &amp; disposition that God created him in, so long he continued cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant &amp; perfectly such as he was created: but going-about to alter or ad any thing to his state &amp; being; (which by Satans procurement he did) he ther-upon did alter his qualitie and condition: the image of God in him after which he was made, to wit, in his <hi>Naturall</hi> &amp; <hi>Personall Essence,</hi> remaining what it was, but the <hi>likenes</hi> or <hi>similitude</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in that <hi>image,</hi> being altogether depraved and spoiled in the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full form &amp; qualities ther-of: his <hi>Good,</hi> being turned into <hi>Ill;</hi> his <hi>Knowledge,</hi> into <hi>Ignorance;</hi> his <hi>Holines,</hi> into <hi>Pollution;</hi> his <hi>Domination,</hi> into <hi>Subjectiō;</hi> his <hi>Glory,</hi> into <hi>Shame;</hi> his <hi>Life,</hi> into <hi>Death</hi>; and all his <hi>Felicity</hi> into extreme <hi>Misery.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="12"/>Now this change was simply Mans owne act, and no way imputable to his <hi>Creatour:</hi> for <hi>God</hi> had made Him such, as (if Hee had would) Hee might as well have stood stedfast in his perfection and integritie, as thus to have fallen into this state of corruption and iniquitie. But He lost that heat of Life, which hee had received from the all-quickning fire of Gods breath: Hee put-out that light of Grace which reflected upon him, from the all-enlightning Sun-shine of Gods Love: and all because hee tooke-upon him-selfe (contrarie to Gods will) to alter his state and being from that, which God had set him in. This extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishment came from him-selfe, and not from the will of <hi>God. God</hi> had indeed given him freedome of <hi>Will,</hi> but hee used it <hi>in pejorem partem,</hi> to his owne destruction: not for that <hi>God</hi> had made him for that end to destroy him; but for that he used not his freedome to stand and continue in that state of holy Life, and light of Grace which Hee might have stood and continued in, if him-selfe had would.</p>
   <p>And thus He made, not <hi>Him-selfe</hi> onely, but all his <hi>Posteritie</hi> subject to Death and Damnation. For as by his Creation He had received Life and Grace from <hi>God,</hi> not for him-self only, but for all that should come of him: so like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise by his transgression he made all his whole Posterity li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Gods wrath, as well as himselfe: so that all were alike changed with him into the same state of <hi>corruption,</hi> and all were fallen alike with Him into the same pit of <hi>perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
      <pb facs="12"/>
There being no difference nor degrees at all, as if his Posteritie were some of them less, some more or deeper plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ther-in than other. For the same Death that by Sin en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred upon the first Offender, I say the same Death, both in measure and degree, went-over all Mankinde alike: because <hi>all</hi> had in <hi>Adam</hi> alike offended, <hi>all</hi> were alike deprived of the Glory of God. Thus all <hi>Mankinde</hi> was by Creation <hi>perfect,</hi> by Sinne <hi>corrupted,</hi> and by the guilt of Sinne <hi>accursed.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Now then for Mans <hi>Redemption,</hi> as God at first consulted with Him-selfe how and after what manner Hee might make Man, and at last resolved to make Him in his owne <hi>Image,</hi> after his <hi>likeness:</hi> so here againe finding Man to be thus fallen from that happy state into this wofull plight, surely much more did Hee now consult with Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, how, and by what meanes Hee might set Man on his feet againe, and so restore Him and his whole Race into their former state and happy being. This being a work (if we may compare Gods workes one with another) of greater glorie, difficultie, and labour <hi>(humano more loquor)</hi> than that of Creation.</p>
   <p>Which Consultation I mention not here, for that I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that <hi>God</hi> did not thinke nor provide for Mans <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> before He was fallen: for (I beleeve) as Gods all-seeing eye did fore-see the <hi>fall;</hi> so his insearchable <hi>Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> did provide for the same, even from all <hi>eternitie.</hi>
      <pb facs="13"/>
Yet seeing I have taken-in hand to speake of this <hi>Consul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> it falleth best into our order and method to speake of it here in this place.</p>
   <p>Here then to express and set-forth this wonderfull work of God for the Redemption of Mankinde, wee imagine him first to be moved ther-to by his <hi>Compassion</hi> or <hi>Pitie;</hi> his <hi>Pitie</hi> to stir up his <hi>Mercy</hi>; his <hi>Mercy</hi> for <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> sake to submit her selfe to his <hi>Wrath;</hi> his <hi>Wrath</hi> to be asswaged by his <hi>Peace:</hi> and so one Grace to advise &amp; deale with another, till at last they sweetly agree, and joyne all in one, how to perfect and effect a worke for the deliverance of all <hi>Man-kinde</hi> out of its <hi>misery.</hi> Which work was put upon <hi>Christ,</hi> the anointed <hi>Messias,</hi> who chearfully under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke it, and for his part effectually performed it.</p>
   <p>And as many of all Man kinde as (according to Gods purpose) doe receive this blessed and gratious <hi>Mediatour,</hi> apprehending Him by <hi>Faith,</hi> cleaving unto Him by <hi>Hope,</hi> &amp; giving obedience unto Him through <hi>Charity,</hi> so many are freed from their <hi>thraldome</hi> and <hi>miserie,</hi> &amp; are resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the inheritance and participation of <hi>life</hi> and <hi>felicity.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Those againe that either carelesly neglect, or wilfully reject this great love of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Christ,</hi> they not only still remaine over-whelmed in the same pit of perdition into which they were plunged by the sin of the first Father; but they also provoke <hi>God</hi> againe unto further wrath, for so lightly respecting his love, and casting his <hi>Mercy</hi> behinde
<pb facs="13"/>
them. For <hi>Grace</hi> not offered will it-selfe plead mercy for the <hi>offender;</hi> but offered &amp; contemned, justly cals for more wrath, and severity of punishment. But for those that thirst for deliverance, and embrace that meanes which is offered to them in <hi>Christ Iesus,</hi> they are <hi>borne-anew;</hi> they are <hi>inspired</hi> with good Graces; they are freely <hi>justified; san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified;</hi> and assured of Salvation: and shall at last attaine eternall Happiness.</p>
   <p>Now for the further divulging of this happy meanes to the encrease of Gods glorie; as also for the better winning and alluring of moe to embrace the same for the saving of their Soules, did I take-in hand to compose this Subject in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Historie, and to set it out in a familiar verse, that so the yonger (who are more ready to reade <hi>Poetry</hi> than <hi>Prose</hi>) may, (as in a Mappe, or Glass) behold one persona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them selves, and chalking out the way, or treading as it were those very steps whereby them-selves have depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from that <hi>Excellency</hi> and <hi>Perfection</hi> they were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in, and runne headlong into most cursed <hi>miserie,</hi> and <hi>thraldome:</hi> and yet againe how by new means offered, and by circumspect walking therein, they may come to the fruition of eternall <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>These together are the scope of my intendment; which, if in any measure I shall further and promote, I trust it shall repent neither mee to have spent some houres
<pb facs="14"/>
stollen from my ordinary studies for the worke of the <hi>Ministerie</hi> in my <hi>Pastorall</hi> charge, upon this kinde of writing; nor any other of their paines in reading; but shall occasion us all more seriously to praise the <hi>Lord:</hi> for whose sake I desire to become all unto all, to winne some.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>