<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Courtelike Dames and Ladie-like Gentlevvomen, the Authour sendeth greeting.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105776_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02027</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12174</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105776</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Courtelike Dames and Ladie-like Gentlevvomen, the Authour sendeth greeting.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The golden Aphroditis : a pleasant discourse, penned by Iohn Grange Gentleman, student in the common lavve of Englande. Wherevnto be annexed by the same authour asvvell certayne metres vpon sundry poyntes, as also diuers pamphlets in prose, which he entituleth his Garden: pleasant to the eare, and delightful to the reader, if he abuse not the scente of the floures</title>
                 <author>Grange, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>¶ To the Courtelike Dames and Ladie-like Gentlevvomen, the Authour sendeth greeting.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>I Greete (but whō?) the glittring stars &amp; troupes of <hi>Venus</hi> crewe,</l>
      <l>VVith painefull pen of ranging fiste, bedewde with <hi>Ganges</hi> dew,</l>
      <l>So <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ocundare</hi> leades my will, that wanton needlesse toyle</l>
      <l>Of Courtlike Dames, my pestred wittes <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>claro</hi> seekes to foyle.</l>
      <l>Draw neare therfore ye weried Nimphes, with such <hi>Mineruas</hi> toyles,</l>
      <l>And vewe this lading scope, which yeeldes for thē Veneriall foyles.</l>
      <l>As none so well as <hi>Caesars</hi> penne, could <hi>Caesars</hi> deedes indight,</l>
      <l>So none but of <hi>Morychus</hi> secte could dolor put to flight,</l>
      <l>Now I who wantes <hi>Apollos</hi> skill, and eke Dame <hi>Pallas</hi> witte,</l>
      <l>Herein to play <hi>Morychus</hi> parte, haue thought my selfe most fitte.</l>
      <l>Yet shall you finde an Ape, an Ape, in purple be she clothde,</l>
      <l>I come not from <hi>Trophonius</hi> care, for then I should be lothde:</l>
      <l>Nor from S. <hi>Patrickes</hi> purgatorie, but play <hi>Nepenth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s</hi> parte,</l>
      <l>The iuyce whereof perforce will keepe such sadnesse frō your harte.</l>
      <l>Thus labour I with tooth and nayle of <hi>Lethe</hi> force to be:</l>
      <l>Then with obliuion might I force your carping cares to flee.</l>
      <l>VVhiche once exilde, the better might the Muses then take place,</l>
      <l>And barefote might the tripping Nimphs the better shew their grace</l>
      <l>I ofte haue longde with penne to painte the trade of louers loue,</l>
      <l>Yet neare cold find what pen deserude, which was not known before.</l>
      <l>Thus dayly musing, where to finde whereon to wreake my spight,</l>
      <l>Me thought I harde <hi>Apollo</hi> sing full sweetely in the night,</l>
      <l>And play vpō his twinkling harp, whose warbling notes (me thought)</l>
      <l>Perforce cōstraynde my penne to write, what h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> in songs had tought.</l>
      <l>VVhich fed full wel my restles reume with Stories somwhat strāge:</l>
      <l>Marke now therfore, who liste to know whereon I list to range.</l>
      <l>It chaunste N. C. a valiant knight, possessed riches store,</l>
      <l>Yet wāted whom his goodes shold rule when <hi>Cloth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> yeldes no more.</l>
      <l>For chaste, and solemne vowe once made, <hi>Dianas</hi> Nymphe to be,</l>
      <l>Dame Nature helde hir as content to heare, and not to see.</l>
      <l>VVherefore as one deuoyde of ioy, and hauing issue n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ne,</l>
      <l>
         <pb facs="7"/>He oft reparde before the Goddes, with great complaynt, and mone,</l>
      <l>For that <hi>Cibile</hi> had transformde into a Lions shape</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Hypponunes</hi> his cosin deare: for taking yeelded rape,</l>
      <l>VVithout a reuerence of the place: when beautie prickte his harte,</l>
      <l>His lust to serue (al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s to soone) his hony waxed tarte.</l>
      <l>A Nymphe likewise of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
               <desc>•••</desc>
            </gap>os</hi> Ile, adornde with beautie rare,</l>
      <l>Before the Goddes with earnest sute, full oft she did repare:</l>
      <l>As for to haue <hi>Atlanta</hi> fayre to be restorde againe</l>
      <l>Vnto hir former shape, which once <hi>Cilele</hi> (to hir payne)</l>
      <l>Togither with <hi>Hyppomenes</hi> transformde to Lions route,</l>
      <l>And set them both at once to drawe hir chariot wheles aboute.</l>
      <l>Thus fortune frayle doth turne hir whele, to giue ech mā his chaūce:</l>
      <l>And fraught their laūcing ships with wiles, <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Cupids</hi> roūd to daūce</l>
      <l>For meeting both (as fortune would) before the Goddes with plaints,</l>
      <l>Loue gaue assault, the sparkes whereof, his tender harte attayntes.</l>
      <l>Such beautie (as <hi>Apollo</hi> sayde) consisted in hir face,</l>
      <l>That all the Heauens gan cleare to shine, not <hi>Phoebus</hi> yet in place,</l>
      <l>VVho, fearing lest the Gods thēselues with loue should be inflamde▪</l>
      <l>Sat all on thorne till she was gone, and was he to be blamde?</l>
      <l>No, no.</l>
      <l>Thus I at length, haue founde a texte to stubbe a ganders quill:</l>
      <l>VVhiche if it proue <hi>Ell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>borus,</hi> according to my will,</l>
      <l>A heauy harte needes must it purge, from care, and pensiue plight▪</l>
      <l>And like vnto <hi>Argivus</hi> harte inforce it to be light:</l>
      <l>To laugh indeede where cause is none, as this <hi>Argivus</hi> did,</l>
      <l>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>et <hi>Aiax</hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>ses to frequent, my story doth forbid.</l>
      <l>And I forbid a carping knight to catche where catche he can,</l>
      <l>For harde it is one dishe to please the mouth of euery man.</l>
      <l>VVho spies my fault (as easie) may by suyte I him forbid,</l>
      <l>To see and turne it to the worst, as <hi>Argus</hi> whilome did,</l>
      <l>That simple skill (whiche earst I had) I giue it you to vewe,</l>
      <l>Not doing as this <hi>Argus</hi> did, who kepte his vvife in mevv.</l>
      <l>For, <hi>quicquid in bucc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>m venit,</hi> the same with haste I pende,</l>
      <l>No maruell then (deare Dames) if ought herein ye may amende.</l>
      <l>Thus standing to your curtesie (madames) loade starres of light,</l>
      <l>The sequele shal my meaning shew here offred to your sight.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Tam Mineruae quàm Veneri.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>