<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE
CHARLES LORD
HOWARD, BARON OF EFFINGHAM,
Lord high Admirall of England, Knight of the most noble
order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most hono∣rable
priuie Counsell, E. Da. wisheth long life,
with increase of all honor and vertue.</title>
           <author>Daunce, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105195_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19863</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6290</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105195</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HO∣NORABLE
CHARLES LORD
HOWARD, BARON OF EFFINGHAM,
Lord high Admirall of England, Knight of the most noble
order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most hono∣rable
priuie Counsell, E. Da. wisheth long life,
with increase of all honor and vertue.</title>
                 <author>Daunce, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe discourse dialoguevvise : shevving how false &amp; dangerous their reports are, which affirme, the Spaniards intended inuasion to be, for the reestablishment of the Romish religion; for her Maiesties succors giuen to the Netherlanders, and for Sir Frances Drakes enterprise three yeares past into the VVest Indies</title>
                 <author>Daunce, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Field (del Campo), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>26 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE
CHARLES LORD
HOWARD, BARON OF EFFINGHAM,
Lord high Admirall of England, Knight of the most noble
order of the Garter, and one of her Maiesties most hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
priuie Counsell, E. Da. wisheth long life,
with increase of all honor and vertue.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HO so shall duely obserue Homer
describing contention (vvhom he
nameth the sister of Mars,<note place="margin">Lib. 4. Ilia.</note> being
at her birth litle, but after, though
keeping her feete on the earth, yet
increasing till she touch the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens
vvith her head: procuring
in this grouth, noises, debates, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scensions,
teares, sighes and late
repentance) vvil say, notvvithstanding that the Poet vvere
blind, that he savve as farre as our time in which this foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish
Goddesse shaketh like a fearefull earthquake the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
both of the Ecclesiasticall and ciuill state. In considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
vvhereof (right honorable Lord) and that many are
moued by some aspects of contention iniuriously to report her
Maiesties proceedings vvith the Spaniard (she hauing li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
in greater temperance then any Prince of her time) I
thought meete (those rumors extenuating his ambition and
auarice long preceding any act done by her Maiestie to him)
to prooue that his enterprises and desire of this kingdome
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>
vvere of longer life then her Maiesties attemptes: to the
end that our people (apprehending his iniustice for piety, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
against the dignitie of Kings, and equitie of nations)
may, knovving the counterfeit, abide in their place of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
and dutie. This labour, though neither for matter or
volume, vvorthy your honorable vievve, I notvvithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
(as bound heretofore for your L. fauors tovvards me to
yeeld some agreeable seruice) humbly dedicate to your good
L. vvhose noble bearing dravveth to it by a forcible povver
of vertue, the hartie and good affections of all men. Take
therefore my good Lord the same in good part of him, vvho
prayeth to your L. increase of long health, honor and all the
vertues of true Nobilitie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordships most
bounden in dutie
<hi>EDWARD DAVNCE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>