<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHORS PREFACE TO the READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1640</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105610_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09607</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19883.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105610</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHORS PREFACE TO the READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The academy of complements : VVherin ladyes gentlewomen, schollers, and strangers may accommodate their courtly practice with most curious ceremonies, complementall, amorous, high expressions, and formes of speaking, or writing. A worke perused and most exactly perfected by the author with additions of witty amorous poems. And a table expounding the hard English words</title>
                 <author>J. G. (John Gough)</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1640</date>
                 <publisher>Badger, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Moseley, Humphrey</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>18, 245, 1, 245-255, 13 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dialectics and rhetoric</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE AVTHORS <hi>PREFACE TO</hi> the READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no question but eloquence is a principall part in a well qualified man, for to see a subtle and a quicke wit foiled in this which is the onely quality that is eminent and adornes a man as usefull in all occasions, it were to be in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames,
<pb facs="6"/>
another <hi>Prometheus,</hi> who made a statue faire in appearance, but without motion; which could not be animated without Celestiall fire: it is eloquence which adornes our discourse, gives a grace and life to our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, opens us the gates and dores to the best company, and puts us in such esteeme as well borne spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ought to arrive to; without this we resemble walking rocks, all our actions being dull and heavie, our words without effect, our conceits without fruits, and our lives disgusted with those, with whom wee ordinarily asso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate our selves: to this purpose
<pb facs="6"/>
in this little volume feast thy fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie with variety of most eloquent expressions and formes of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy minde to all, from the King to persons of the most infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ranke or qualitie, for in this second edition, Let me tell thee that thou hast a Cabinet wherein the richest Iewels of our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage are lockt up, first thou hast choise and select complements set thee down in a forme which up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an occasion offered thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est imitate or with a little altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion make use of, thou hast in the next place variety of subjects with expressions to the height of eloquence penn'd to quicken thy
<pb facs="7"/>
mind upon the like objects pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to thy view or fancy, thou hast witty disputes, amorous dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, with an addition of most excellent Love Poems, comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall and most sweetly har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious fitted to the tastes of Cupids guests, Thou hast exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site Letters, such as containe the Quintessence of that sweetnesse our English tongue affords us at this day as it is now refined, then thou hast dedications, superscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fitted to thy owne desires for thy use upon any sudden oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, Lastly thou hast a table of the hard English words with their expositions, in summe both
<pb facs="7"/>
eloquence and love with their secrets and mysteries are made naked and manifestly revealed to the weakest Iudgement; all these benefits are heaped upon thee by one who is zealous for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Language, by one who bewailes those weake essayes that have beene made by others to this purpose, and with griefe viewed the former hasty and sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptitious edition of this booke, which now is purged and perfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the booke-sellers own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: read it therefore with dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and deliberative conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and endeavour to attaine to the quality of such worth that
<pb facs="8"/>
thou mayst learne from it to cure thy dumbenes, to discourse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently with thy friends, and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suredly to tender thy wit and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to those thou shalt have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to acknowledge, especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Court, where neatenesse and curiosities of all sorts, and principally of speech is to a silla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exactly studied: I will resolve thee good Reader but a doubt or two and detaine thee no longer from thy pleasure; first thou seest not the name of the Author, if thou knewest the gravity of his person thou mightst well have him excused, next for thy country objection that down-right deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="8"/>
is best, I answer thou mayest somtimes be too plain in the way of thy preferment; if thou namest the word dissimulation, thou er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, the whole heaven: this work relishes in respect of the subject more of curtesie, unlesse thou abuse it by craft: accept it then as every way beneficiall to thee, and take my wish with thee, that thou maist injoy as much pleasure in the perusing of it, as I had to pen it. <hi>Adieu.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>YOURS <hi>Philomusus.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>