<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PREFACE OF DE∣syderius Erasmus of Rotero∣dame unto a dukes soonne of his countree</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1542</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105498_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00316</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10443</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105498</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PREFACE OF DE∣syderius Erasmus of Rotero∣dame unto a dukes soonne of his countree</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Apophthegmes : that is to saie, prompte, quicke, wittie and sentencious saiynges, of certain emperours, kynges, capitaines, philosophiers and oratours, aswell Grekes, as Romaines, bothe veraye pleasaunt [et] profitable to reade, partely for all maner of persones, [et] especially gentlemen. First gathered and compiled in Latine by the ryght famous clerke Maister Erasmus of Roterodame. And now translated into Englyshe by Nicolas Vdall</title>
                 <author>Erasmus, Desiderius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1542</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 345, 15 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE PREFACE OF DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syderius Erasmus of Rotero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame unto a dukes soonne of his countree</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR asmucheas ye did so gentely afore receiue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other litle bookes whiche I had then sent as a poore earnest penie (suche as it was) of my good herte &amp; mynde towardes your grace right noble prince, &amp; not onely your self, but also bothe your moste noble parentes did so courteously ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte thesame: I haue thought good at this presēte to ioyne to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied bookes some other thyng bothe more meete for your noblenesse &amp; also (except I be muche deceiued) more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for your studies. I haue therfore out of euerie good autour for the moste parte, chosen and gathered, that the Grekes callen apophthegmata, that is in englyshe, nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good and brief saiynges: for that I sawe none other kynde of argumente or matier more fitte for a prince, especially beeyng a
<pb facs="5"/>
young manne not yet broken in the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the worlde. In deede ful conueniente and meete to bee knowen are those thynges whiche y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aunciente philosophiers haue lefte in wrytyng of honeste behaueour, of wel go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uernyng and ordreyng a cōmenweale, &amp; of kepyng warre. But what one manne emōg many thousādes (yea though he be nothyng cloggued nor letted w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> any publique office or ministerie) hath so muche vacaunte tyme, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he maye bee at leasure to turne ouer &amp; ouer in the bookes <note n="‡" place="margin">Plato wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth al his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes in dialo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues &amp; in the most parte of theim Socra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes is one of the disputers which Socra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes pretēdyng echewhere simplicitee &amp; ignoraūce did ofte tymes cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uince diuerse of theim that he reasoned w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all in their owne artes, vsyng to thē suche kynde of reasonyng as here in the texte is recited</note> of Plato the ragmannes rolles, and the taryers or toyes of the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile knackes, of the drye mockes, and of the lōg inducciōs by familiar exaumples, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Socrates dooeth there vse? And as for <note n="*" place="margin">Aristotle wrote tenne bookes enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleed Ethica, that is, of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neste behaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our &amp; vpright liuyng and dealyng.</note>Aristotle, in deede he wrote largely of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and behaueour, whiche werke he enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleeth in greke Ethica, but by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> entriked ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scuritee and derkenesse therof he appereth to haue wrytē thesame for philosophiers, that is to saie, for menne of high learnyng, and not for a prince. More clere and more plain to bee perceiued, been the werkes that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same Aristotle wrote of householdyng entitleed Oeconomica, and of ordreyng a citee or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menweale entitleed Politica, but this māne euerie where requireth a reader bothe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eraye attente, and earnestely myndyng
<pb facs="6"/>
that he readeth, &amp; also well at leasure. And besides this, forasmuche as he vseth no suche manier of rhetoricall style or writyng as maye moue the affectes &amp; passiōs, he dooeth not so greately hold or rauyshe a mannes mynde, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is wholy bent &amp; geuē to princely cures &amp; buisynesse. Sembleably in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bookes of morall philosophie, whiche Marc{us} Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li{us} wrote, many thynges there been of suche sorte, as it is not muche to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> purpose, nor anythyng at all necessarie, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> princes knowe theim: Of whiche kynde are those thynges y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he treacteth of the consummacion of good and ill (whiche wee christian menne would call of blisse and damnacion) with more subti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litee of reasonyng and argumentacion, thē fruite to edifie in vertuous liuyng. And suche manier thynges seruen well for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of theim, who all the dayes of their life dooe nothyng els but talke &amp; dispute of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e. But for a māne born to bee a prince and a gouernour, it is necessarie y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a readie &amp; shorte waye to learne vertue bee quickely dispeched, and not at leasure disputed &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned in woordes. Now resteth the histories whiche because thei dooe represēte to the yi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> (euē as in a peinted table to bee vewed) as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well the noble actes of prowesse, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, and that not without pleasure and
<pb facs="6"/>
delectacion: seme to bee more fitte for greate menne. But in this behalf though a prince might haue voide tymes enough to peruse y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> infinite multitude of bookes of histories, what manne wer hable to comprehend and kepe theim all freashe in his memorie? But like as those persones who been dooers in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> game or feacte of wrastleyng haue in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynesse at all tymes certain suer poinctes and wayes bothe to catche holde, and also to wend out of holde, when neede is, so thei y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> trauaill in the busie occupacions of peace and of warre must of congruence haue in a readynesse suer rewles, by whiche thei maye bee putte in remembreaunce what is in that presente case nedefull or expediente to bee dooen, and what not. And in this behalf, we see y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> diuerse highly well learned mēne haue assaied &amp; taken peine by their good diligence to ease the carefulnesse of princes and noble menne, emong whiche, some haue writen lessōs of vertue in brief sentēces, as <note n="*" place="margin">Theognis a Greke poete y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> wryteth in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeiacal vses suche morall preceptes of virtue as been in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> litle trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is reade vnder y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> of Cato.</note> The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ognis, and <note n="‡" place="margin">Isocrates a greke oratour wrytyng ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny litle trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tises in prose.</note>Isocrates: &amp; others haue wrytē the feactes of armes, or policies of warre, &amp; the goodly shorte saiynges of famous mēne as <note n="*" place="margin">Ualerius Max. a latine autoure that wrote a werk of .ix volumes whiche he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titleed, of the saiynges and actes of noble menne.</note> Ualerius Maximus, and Sextus Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius<note n="‡" place="margin">Sextus Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Frontin{us} wryteth also in latine .iiii. volumes, whiche he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titleeth strate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gematū, that is to saie of armes, or poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of warre.</note> Frontinus, whiche Frontinus decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> self fame thyng by diuerse other wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters before hym customeably to haue been
<pb facs="7"/>
dooen. It is a thyng of no small tyme of lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sure to serche out golde in the veines vnder the yearth, or to seeke precious stones in the sande or in the sea. Suche a feloe especially aboue others to a prince w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> high &amp; weightie matiers contynually embusied dooeth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable seruice and pleasure, whiche to the same exhibiteth &amp; presenteth golde alreadie fyned &amp; made in fagottes or plate, &amp; whiche bryngeth to his hande precious stones that are chosen pieces &amp; well poolyshed, alreadie sette in golde, or vpon cuppes of precious metalle. And this kynde of pleasure &amp; good turne, whereas it hath of many wryters been attempted, yet (after my mynde and sentēce) no māne hath with more dexterite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> or better effecte accomplyshed &amp; perfourmed then hath <note place="margin">Plutarchus was a Greke philosophier &amp; was schole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maister vnto the emperour Traianus in the citee of Roome wher he wrote in Greke many noble and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellente good werkes aswel of histories as also of morall philosophie &amp; of vertue.</note> Plutarchus, who after the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng foorth of an excellente good &amp; passyng fruitefull werke of the liues of noble mēne, (in whiche werke here &amp; there been myngled and recited aswell the factes as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saiynges of the same) he gathered in to one litle booke for the vse of Traianus Caesar y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> best com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended manne of all the Emperours that before his tyme had been, the notable sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges of soundrie renoumed persones, by whiche as in a veraye true &amp; perfecte glasse the herte and mynde of euerie of theim is to
<pb facs="7"/>
the yie of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> readers liuely and certainly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented. For in the actes &amp; deedes of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, a good porcion of the laude and praise the Counsaillour maye clayme and chalēge for geuyng his auise the Capitain for his chieualrie, &amp; the souldyours for their stoute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. And a veraye greate porcion of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same laude and thanke dooeth ladie fortune clayme to haue, by whose cōueighaunce ofte tymes wee see thynges not without high counsaill &amp; wysedome entreprised to haue a veraye vnluckie ende, and contrarie wyse y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> misaduised temeritee and vndescreetenesse of some persones to haue right prosperous chaunce, and in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ende to proue veraye wel. As it is reported that Siramnes the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sian, (a Capitain as I suppose) saied, when he was asked why his deedes wer not aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to his ioyly saiynges, for because (saieth he) what I wil speake, lyeth in myne owne power, but how suche thynges as I dooe, shall ende or bee taken, standeth in the pleasure of fortune and of the kyng. Albeeit honeste purposes &amp; deuises are not therefore vtterly defeacted of their due laude and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>digne praise. But the saied Plutarchus dooeth in this kynde ferre excede and passe all other wryters, not onely in choosyng y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> best, but also in expounyng and declaryng
<pb facs="8"/>
y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>same. For these saiynges (whiche, as afore is mencioned, the Grekes callē apophtheg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata) haue appropriated vnto theim a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain reason &amp; marke of their owne whereby to iudge, so that thei dooe plainly expresse &amp; sette out the veraye naturall inclinaciō and disposicion of eche speaker that thei procede frō, briefly, finely, quippyngly, and meryly within the boundes of good maner. And as euerie seuerall persone hath proprely belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng vnto hym a faciō of his owne wherby he is commended, and whereby his sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges &amp; dooynges haue a good grace orels other wyse: euen so like wyse hath euerie nacion, so that not one manier saiynges are conueniente for Alexander and for Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus or Antigonus. One sorte are meete for Alcibiades: Again one facion agreeable for a manne of Lacedaemon, and an other for a Scythian or a Thracian: and a diuerse from y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> again comely for a manne of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or for a Romain. Now, in expressyng &amp; vttreyng suche saiynges Xenophon seemeth to me somewhat weeryshe, Herodotus voide of quickenesse or life, Diodorus &amp; Quintus Curtius ouer full of woordes, and so foorth of the other wryters, whiche I surceasse by name to speake of. Plutarchus is a perfecte feloe in all poinctes, and therefore I haue
<pb facs="8"/>
thought best thesame Plutarchus to foloe principally aboue all others. Wherefore all y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euer is cōprised in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> werke of this autour whiche he entitleed de apophthegmatibus, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is, of feacte and brief saiynges, ye shall fynd here in this werke euerie whitte of it. Wee dooe all knowe that this werke of Plutar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus hath been twis translated out of greke into latine, first by Francisce Philelphus, and afterward again by Raphael Regius, with whom I was somewhat acquainted in the vniuersitee of Padwaye. Philelphus in diuerse places had missed y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> cushē, whiche places Raphael dooeth restore and correcte, and yet somewhere stumbleth hymself. The truth is, thei bothe wer menne, and might erre, mystakyng a thyng y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thei read. Albeit either of theim mynded to bee nothyng els but a plain trāslatour of the greke into la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, but I for many causes haue thought better the saied Plutarchus to foloe, thē to translate, to expoune at large, then woorde for woorde out of greke onely to enterprete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> first that the stile might bee the more clere &amp; plain as beeyng lesse bounden to the greke woordes: (For this presēt booke of myne is not wryttē vnto Traianus, a māne bothe in greke &amp; latine excellentely well seen, and also in lōge experiēce of all manier affaires
<pb facs="9"/>
gayly well brokē &amp; exercised, but to a prince beeyng yet but a young thyng, yea &amp; by you to all chyldrē and young strieplynges, that labour and sue to atteigne the knowelage of good learnyng and honeste studies: nor yet in that worlde when suche man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er saiynges and actes wer by the reporte and cōmuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people daily talked &amp; spokē of in baines or whotte houses, at dyners and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers &amp; abrode in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> streetes whensoeuer fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes bee assēbleed together: and secundaryly that I might h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue free libertee to declare &amp; expoune the fyne wittynesse of the saiyng, if any came to hand that was of sense obscure &amp; derke, as at this presente right many there been hard to bee vnderstanded not onely of suche as haue neuer gon to schoole, but also of suche as dooe ferre surmounte the cōmen sorte of clerkes. And certes for myne owne parte, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> geassyng and redyng what diuers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of these apophthegmes should meane or si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie, hath curstely troubleed &amp; vexed my braines, &amp; I cānot saie whether it hath some where beguyled me too. And in places not a fewe I haue had muche strougleyng &amp; wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stleyng with the faultes of enprientyng in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bookes, at whiche it could not bee avoided, but that the enterpreters and translatours maugre their heddes did stumble. For it is
<pb facs="9"/>
a thyng vneth beleueable how muche &amp; how boldely aswell the commen writers that frō tyme to tyme haue copied out the bookes of Plutarchus, as also certain y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> haue thought theim selfes hable to countrolle and emend all mēnes dooynges, haue taken vpō theim in this autour who ought with all reuerēce to haue been handleed of theim and with all feare to haue been preserued from altreyng deprauyng or corruptyng. For neuer hath there been emong y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> greke writers, (especialli as touchyng matiers of vertue and good be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>haueour,) any one more holy then Plutar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus, or better worthie of all menne to bee read. But the veraye same thyng hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked persones desirous of glorie &amp; of lucre, to depraue &amp; corrupte this autour, to putte in more then he wrote, and also to leaue out of that he wrote whiche ought moste of all to haue feared theim from soo dooyng. For euerie wryter y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> better accepted and sette by that he is, and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> greater name that he hath emong learned menne, so muche the rather shall he for lucre &amp; auauntage bee corrupted. That this autour hath been soo vsed, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raye diuersitee of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Greeke texte not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng one copie w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> an other dooeth right well argue and proue. For all others omitted, to speake onely of this presēt werke that nowe
<pb facs="10"/>
is in hand, the translacion of Philelphus hath certain thynges, whiche Raphael lefte vntouched, &amp; Raphael likewise some thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of whiche Philelphus maketh no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion at all. Besides this, where Plutarchus in the preface by expresse woordes dooeth plainly testifie that in the liues he had myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleed the saiynges and actes of noble mēne together thone with thother: &amp; in this werke for briefnesse to haue lynked together onely their apophthegmes or saiynges, yet dooe wee see right many thynges admixt &amp; putte in emōg y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> apophthegmes whiche in veraye dede are no saiynges at all, nor any other thyng but me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e pollices of warre which the Grekes callen Strategemata. Now in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> self same werke one and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>same thynges so often again and again repeated, dooen thei not openly crye this argumente and matier by some other feloe to haue been cōtamynated &amp; sloubreed? So y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> wee maye now pardone y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> in certain places an apophthegma is reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> name of the persone that it was spoken to, and not of hym by whom it was spokē, as of Lysymachus &amp; Philippus. For in this treactise of Plutarchus whiche is entitleed Collectanea, that is to saie a manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of soondrie and pretie histories and saiynges compiled together for all readers the aunswer
<pb facs="10"/>
that Philippus made vnto Lysimachus, is told and reported vnder the title or chapiter of Lysimachus. But yet it was an higher poincte of presumpcion y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> of one werke thei haue made it twoo. For because Plutar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus of the saiynges of Lacedaemonians, whiche been a veraye greate noumbre, had touched onely so many as for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperour beeyng with many matiers sore embus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed, semed like to suffice. He, whosoeuer it was, (at lest if it wer but one feloe &amp; no mo that sette handes therunto) hath assigned to the saiynges of Lacedaemonians one propre volume, and that accordyng to the ordre of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> greke letters as thei stand in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> alphabeete, whiche Raphael in his translacion hath turned into the ordre of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> letters of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> latine A,B.C. But this was of all the three euen the veraye wurst. For Ualerius and Frō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus folowen y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ordre of suche sentencies as thei shewe concernyng religion, concernyng affecciō &amp; loue to mēnes coūtrees, cōcernyng trueth in keepyng promisses made, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng mannefull hardynesse and cōcernyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ice, &amp; likewise of other matiers settyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>che of theim in his right ordre and place. Best stādyng with cunnyng and learnyng, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s thesame ordre that Plutarchus folowed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>bseruyng and kepyng the ordre of regions
<pb facs="11"/>
and kyngdomes as thei stand in rowe, &amp; in euerie of theim y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ordre of tymes, to euery of the kynges ioynyng his owne capitaines, &amp; to euerie of the capitaines their mates. Frō the Persians he cometh to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Egyptiās, frō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Egyptiās to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Thracians, frō the Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians to the Scythians, from the Scythiās to the Sicilians, from the Sicilians to the Macedonians, from thens to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Atheniense, from theim to the Lacedaemonians, folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng in euerie of these thordre of the tymes, and not of the letters in the alphabete. Frō the Lacedemonians he cometh to the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banes, frō the Thebanes to the Romaines, so that the reader by the saiynges of a fewe persones maye familiarly knowe the ordre of the whole historie, whiche ordre that feloe hath pieteously confounded &amp; trobleed and sette out of ordre, that soondreed and disse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the saiynges of the Lacedemonians frō the others, &amp; yet here and there repetyng the veraye same thynges that Plutarchus had gathered afore vnto Traianus, albeit in soondrie places one thyng repeated is muche more often deprehended and openly found in the other werke of apophthegmes, but in bothe werkes so oftē as thesame fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng in a slumbre and forgettyng hymself cannot lyghte on Plutarchus a writer of
<pb facs="11"/>
precise diligence. More ouer, this parte hath no preface at all, and the preface that goeth before the apophthegmes vnto Traianus will not s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rue to bothe werkes. Now, what thanke suche persones are worthie to haue whiche dooe in this wyse slabre and defyle y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bookes of famous autores, I will not at this tyme reason, but truely me thynketh it a veraye sacriliege. Yet of me (except a fewe saiynges of Lacedemonians, because the self same been repeated in the other table of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hersall euerie one of theim) is not so muche as one omitted af all that goeth abrode vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> name of Plutarchus partely to thēde that the reader beeyng rather a gredie glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, then a mynion deintie peece might not mysse any thyng that he would faine haue: and partely, for that I sawe nothyng there but woorthie to bee knowen, though some tyme rehersed &amp; tould out of his right place. Neuerthelesse, all the whole werke I haue in manier made my propre owne in y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I dooe more at large and more plainely expresse the thynges that bee tolde in greke, puttyng in sometymes suche thynges as I had well perceiued to bee added in other autours, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng also out of the other werkes of Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchus veraye many thynges whiche wer not in this presente treactise, &amp; eueriewhere
<pb facs="12"/>
as it wer with litle brief cōmentaries ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng &amp; shewyng aswell the sense of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> apoph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegme as also the vse wherfore, and how it maye serue, especially in those places whiche lacked some more light &amp; clerenesse, albeeit thesame haue I dooen briefly in fewe woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, lest I should haue clene turned awaye from the nature of apophthegmes, whiche ought not to cōtein many woordes. But as for the ordre is wurse broken &amp; confused euē of me, then I found it there, for that, where at the begynnyng I had purposed to make rehersal but of veraye fewe and onely of the principall best sorte, when I was ones en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treed in my warke, the veraye heate therof pricked &amp; sette me to chaūge my mynde &amp; to go on still a greate waye ferther, neither should I haue made any ende, had not this as ye would saie an hougemain sea of thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges stil freshe &amp; freshe comyng to mynde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced &amp; driuē me to blowe retreacte &amp; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule backe. For as Quintilian emōg y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues &amp; graces of a schoolemaister in gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer putteth this to bee one, that he bee in some thynges ignoraunte: so, in this kynde of argumēte it seemeth to bee some parte of diligence certain thynges to passe ouer and to leaue out. Therefore, I haue thought b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to make at this tyme a deintie feaste th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="12"/>
a coūbreous or troublesome, especially for y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> if any thyng be in this presente supper leafte out, it maye at some other supper bee sette before my geastes after y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all this shalbe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectely digested. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> incōmoditee of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre of thynges neglected &amp; not precisely kept I haue with a large reportorie or table re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubbed. For the title, it nothyng forceth to bee carefull or scrupleous, sens y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> emōg those saiynges whiche Plutarchus vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> title &amp; name of apophtegmes hath gathered &amp; cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled together, there bee many whiche an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther māne would rather cal, scornes, taūtes, checkes, iestes, or merie conceipted saiynges to laugh at. But forasmuche as Marcus Tullius in puttyng a seueral distinctiō be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene eche of these kindes, hath takē earnest labour &amp; peine, without any effecte, &amp; foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as Mars{us} a right wel learned māne hath in this behalf nothyng satisfied Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliā, no, nor yet Quintilian in knowlage &amp; litterature ferre passyng Marsus hath satis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied hymself: I haue not thought it a thyng woorthe y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> laboure in this behalf to bestowe muche buisie trauaill, cōtented &amp; thynkyng sufficiēte, here &amp; there by y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> waye as occasion serueth to haue opened &amp; shewed the kynde &amp; the nature of the saiyng or of the merie iest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Certes in those thynges that I haue of my
<pb facs="13"/>
self added besides Plutarchus dooynges, I haue diligentely foreseen and prouided in no wyse confusely to myngle policies of warre (hauyng no saiyng of this kynde an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed vnto theim) and apophthegmes bothe together, and also that I would in no wyse putte in here any thyng but taken out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> best allowed and thesame the moste auncy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente writers bothe in Greke &amp; Latine: not that I am ignoraunte the later wryters to haue recited many thynges sharpely &amp; also pleasauntly spokē: but suche thynges as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitee hath made precious iewels and as ye would saie reliques, been of more autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, and meete it was that this werke should haue an ende and not bee infinite. Nor this thyng neither ought to moue any manne that one and thesame saiyng is of one au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour ascribed vnto the persone of one māne and of an other autour is attributed to an other manne. For it forceth not so greately of what persone a thyng is spokē, as it doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, what is spokē: albeit in deede a famous speaker and one that hath the fauour and hertes of menne geueth to the saiynges muche weight and grace also. This thyng more often cometh in vre, then y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it needeth by exaumples to bee proued. But yet some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes it chaunceth by reason that mannes
<pb facs="13"/>
memorie failleth, albeeit there is no cause to the contrarie, but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> one and thesame sentēce maye procede frō soondrie speakers or wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whether imitacion be the cause therof orels chaunce, as for exaumple, this staffe of a metre in greke,
<q>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, that is</l>
         <l>Tyrannes by wisemennes conuersacion,</l>
         <l>Maye soone bee brought to goodnesse and wisedome,</l>
      </q>
This is well knowen to bee a verse of<note n="*" place="margin">Sophocles is a Greke poete of whose writyng we haue .vii. tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies.</note> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phocles, yet Plato citeth it out of <note n="‡" place="margin">Euripides also is a greke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>oete &amp; wrote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>x tragedies whiche we haue.</note>Euripi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Again this verse.
<q>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is,</l>
         <l>I beeyng aged, as I can,</l>
         <l>Will teache the beeyng also an old manne.</l>
      </q>
Wheras it is in the tragedie of Sophocles entitleed Philoctetes, yet is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same woorde for woorde found in Bacchis the tragedie of Euripides: like wise this verse.
<q>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap> y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is</l>
         <l>Whether thou talke, or hold thy pece,</l>
         <l>Thou must in due season, speake or ceasse.</l>
      </q>
Wheras it is in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tragedie of Aechylus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titleed Promotheus;<note place="margin">Aechyl{us} is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so a poete that wrote trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in greke.</note> it is foūd also in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripides onely twoo lettres chaunged <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, in steede of <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, Somewhyles autours agree not, neither on
<pb facs="14"/>
the mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>er not yet on the name. As he y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> cast in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> teethe of Marcus Fabius that he had by his meanes recouered again y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> towne of Tarente, in Tullie is named Liuius Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uator, in Titus Liuius is named Marcus Liuius, in Plutarche Marcus Lucius, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els as is in the greke exemplaries <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, Also Fabius Philostratus sheweth that one Leo a Sophiste brought all the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of Athenes in a laughter with his bodye beeyng notable grosse and fatte, and Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarche saieth lanke and litle. Ualerius Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus and Plinius, in the reportyng of a certain alteracion y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> was betwene Cn. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitius &amp; Lucius Crassus in Roome, how wyde been thei the one from the other, but without all life or solle been those thynges, that in some writers are feigned to haue beē the woordes of certain persones, in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of poetes mencioned, as in Philostra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus the Sophiste, when he forgeeth and sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth to Palamedes, to Ulysses, &amp; to other like persones, suche tales and speeches as lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted his owne phantasticall braine to deuise and imagyn, and thesame are made double dedde by euill handleyng, of whiche sorte of saiynges I dooe in this present werke medle with none at all. In the nexte degree to these been suche speeches as ar assigned to diuerse
<pb facs="14"/>
persones in dialogues, feigned &amp; endited, not for any truthe of the matier to bee beleued, but for disporte and passetyme onely. But in the speeches of the partes, in comedies (that is merie entreludes) and in tragedies (that is, sadde entreludes whiche wee call fraige plaies) there is some more life &amp; pith, and a greate grace thei haue beeyng sette in an apte and fitte place, albeeit the name of apophthegmes, no saiynges can haue except the speaker out of whose mouth thei dooen procede bee a persone of greate name and the woordes purposely applyed to some ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beeyng euen at that presente houre in cōmunicacion, yea and muche the better to bee liked, if thei bee a litle disframed to an other sense or a ferther meanyng then the veraye woordes dooe purporte. As when Aristotle vnto Callisthenes talkyng with kynge Alexander more homely and fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely then was expediente, gaue a bywar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng with this verse of the poete Homere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <q>
         <l>
            <gap reason="foreign">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>. That is.</l>
         <l>My soonne, if thou bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> thus large of tongue,</l>
         <l>Thou shalt surely leese thy life ere long.</l>
      </q>
      <pb facs="15"/>
Out of Herodotus I haue had no greate lust to gather any greate noumbre of sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges, because that most parte of theim ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere to haue been inuented of that wryters owne witte. Like trashe and bagguage been those saiynges that are incidente in oraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whiche the wryters of histories (eche as his witte serueth hym) are woonte to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to menne, albeit euen those dooe muche auaill aswell to the readers iudgemente as also to make a manne hable well to frame &amp; promptely to tell his tale. The principall best sorte of apophthegmes is y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> saiyng whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in fewe woordes dooeth rather by a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour signifie thē plainly expresse a sence not comen for euerie witte to picke out, &amp; suche a saiyng, as no manne could lightely feigne by studie, and whiche the longer ye dooe cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidre it in your mynde, the more and more it dooeth still delite you. And all these vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall sorte of wrytynges as doo comprehend prouerbes, sage sentencies, and notable sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges or actes, is moste fitte for Princes &amp; noble mēne, who for the vrgente causes and busie maters of the commenweale haue not leasure to spēd any greate parte of their life in studie or in readyng of bookes. And these wrytynges, as thei bee learned w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> pleasure &amp; delite, and dooe lightly synke and settle in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg>
      <pb facs="15"/>
mynde, so dooe thei contein more good knowelage and learnyng in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> deepe botome or secrete priuetee, then thei shewe at the first vieu. We reade that Augustus Caesar of a custome did cause as many as he could any where geat of suche good lessons to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplified, and the copies therof to send into diuers places. Also wee see the chief and principall studie of the ioyly aunciēte wyse mēne of old tyme to haue been, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thei might w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the lure of pleasaunt delectacion enplante in tendre young wittes thynges worthie &amp; expediente to bee knowen, to thende that the vnbroken youngth not yet full rype for the serious preceptes of philosophie, might euen with playe &amp; dalyyng learne suche thynges as might afterward dooe theim high ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice all daies of their life. For this entente &amp; purpose thei did as ye would saye spiece and powther Cosmographie, Astrologie, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sike &amp; philosophie aswel naturall as morall with fables and tales preatyly and wittyly feigned. But in this booke that I haue now made shall perauenture seeme to bee some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynges y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> maken nothyng to honeste beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueour, but dooe onely cause laughter. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dooe Iesteme it a thyng worthie blame euer now and thē with laughter to refreshe the mynde with cures and maters of charge
<pb facs="16"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n maner tiered, so that the matier to laugh at bee pure witte and hone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>te. For such<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> thynges gladdeth &amp; maketh lustie the wittes of young folkes, and dooeth passyng good helpe and fertheraunce aswell to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> familiar gentlenesse of condicions as also to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sauntnesse of counnyng. For what thyng better sweetteh y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> endityng of Marcus Tul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lius, then that he dooeth euer now and then sauce his stile with saiynges of this sorte? And I praye you, what been the moralles of Plutarchus, but aresse hangynges with suche like colours pictured? More ouer those saiynges that seme moste fond thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of all to laugh at, by well handleyng become maters of sadnesse. For what could bee a more fond thyng to laugh at thē Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes gooyng from place to place w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a cādle in his hande at high noonetid saiyng still y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he did seeke a manne? But in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meane tyme by laughyng, wee learne that he is not by &amp; by in all the haste a manne, that hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he figure and shape of a māne (whiche im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ges also of wood &amp; stone haue,) but to fynd out a māne, the botome of the herte and mynde must bee found out. If the herte and mynde bee guyded by reason and discrecion, rather then lead by wilful appetite: thē and els not hast thou found out a māne. Also what is
<pb facs="16"/>
so worthie to bee laughed at, as y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Phryne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> stroumpette in Athenes byndyng by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e and couenaunte that euerie one of the women that satte then in coumpaignie at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> table, should dooe thesame thyng that she would dooe first, diepped her hande twis in the water, and putte it to hir forehedde dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coueryng by this deuise the peintyng of all the other womennes faces, so that all the coūpaignie fel into a greate laughter: where as she by so dooyng appered a greate deale fairer &amp; better fauoured? But this laughter teacheth vs the self same thyng whiche So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates saied in good sadnesse, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> wee should applye ourselfes to bee in deede of suche sorte as wee would bee accoumpted and estemed lest that when the peintyng is pulled from our visages we haue in the ende shame and reproche in steede of glorie and renoume. It geueth vs also a lesson that wee putte not our wholle trust and staigh in thynges ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and transitorie, whiche by many dyuerse chaunces are w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a trice taken awaye from a manne, but wee should acquire and purchace y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> veraye true rychesse of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mynde and solle, on whiche fortune hath no power ne dominaciō, soo highe a poincte of serious philosophie dooeth that fond toye of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> saied peuyshe harlotte Phryne, teache vs. For
<pb facs="17"/>
this consideracion Lycurgus (although in other matiers he brought vp &amp; nurtured his countreemēne after a veraye streicte faciō:) yet honeste myrth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>estyng, he not onely permitted vnto theim, but also enioyned &amp; commaunded. For he ordeined a kynde of exercise, whiche he named in greke <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> as wee saie, gossopyng, to the whiche all the aunciente or aged menne that wer past bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng any publique funccions, and for the respecte of their ympotencie wer discharged of that burden, resorted and assēbleed plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sauntly passyng the tyme w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> feacte saiynges and honeste bourding, but alwayes of such<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> sorte, as might make either to the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion and praise of honestee &amp; vertue, orels to the rebukyng of vice. He sette vp also an image vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> god <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, that is, laughter for that he iudged it to bee a thyng of high vtilitee and profite with sobre myrth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freashe the lustynesse of the myndes, and to make thesame cherfull to honeste trauailles and labours, because that in this worlde as the poete Ouidius saieth.
<q>
         <l>
            <note place="margin">
               <hi>Quod caret alterna re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie durabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le non est.</hi>
            </note>What thyng resteth not, now &amp; thē emong.</l>
         <l>But still trauailleth, cannot endure long.</l>
      </q>
Cleomenes also of thesame Lacedemon bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng suche a sore and rigoro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s feloe that he would not licence neither rymers, nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="17"/>
that could syng or plaie on instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, nor any mynstrelles to bee in the commenweale, yet allowed that all the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same countree should striue their bealyes full one with an other in bourdyng or ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styng meete for honeste menne to vse, &amp; in poynaunte checkyng tauntes. For a finall conclusion, as often as vacaunte tyme is geuen, or the case requireth hilaritee and myrth, how muche more decente is it with suche maner saiynges as these been, to passe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tyme, then to take pleasure of fables voide of honestee, voide of learnyng, and full of rebaudrie. I am of this opinion, that young children might muche more to their profecte and benefite bee exercised in the grammer schooles with themes, or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes to wryte on, of this sorte, then with matiers to make vpon, suche as been commenly vsed, (whiche themes for the moste parte, as thei contein nothyng but litle trifleyng senses voide of all pith or fruite, so dooe thei nothyng open the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>teries of the Latine toung) so that the shoolemaister dooe open and declare the rewles &amp; wayes how that whiche is brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spoken maye bee dilated and sette out more at large, and how that that is so
<pb facs="18"/>
fondly spoken, that the hearers or readers cannot but laugh at it, maye bee turned or applyed to a serious vse and purpose. And this one thyng will I saie more. In sermones percase it is not conueniente to miengle iestyng saiynges of mortall menne with the holy scriptures of God, but yet might thesame muche more excusably bee vsed, to quicken suche as at sermones been euer noddyng, then olde wiues foolyshe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of Robyn Hoode &amp; suche others, whiche many preachers haue in tymes past cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomably vsed to bryng in, taken out euen of the veraye botome and grossest parte of the dreggues of the commen peoples foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyshe talkyng. Iulius Caesar Emperour of Roome susteinyng the burden of so many chargeable affaires of encoumbraunce and buisynesse, aswell at home in the citee when peace was, as also abrode in warrefare, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to drieue awaye y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> werynesse of takyng thought for suche thynges as he had in his hedde to carke &amp; care for, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> taūtyng woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of bourdyng and iestyng: with whiche he was so greately delited, that he did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and take in veraye good parte suche as wer spoken by others euen against his owne persone, so that thei wer propre
<pb facs="18"/>
feacte and well conueighed. Uneth any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all the aunciente Emperours of Roome was either more holy and better disposed, orels more encoumbreed with bui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>synesse of the worlde, then was Augustus Caesar: But again, what persone in this kynde more merie conceipted? Of Marcus Tullius, I will nothyng saie at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sente, who is of many menne thought in iestyng to haue remembred or considreed as he ought to haue dooen neither measure nor yet honestee and comelynesse. Xenocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> philosophier was of a more soure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a ioyly feloe in some other respectes: but Plato moe tymes thē one auised hym, with sacrifice to purchace the fauour of the Graces, that is, so to applye hymself, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his saiynges and dooynges might haue more grace and bee better accepted &amp; taken of the worlde. zeno beeyng outright alltogether a Stoique vsed to call Socrates the scoffer, or the Hicke scorner of the citee of Athenes: because of his merie conceiptes and taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, that he neuer ceassed to vse: but yet is there no manne, but he will saie that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates was a more godly feloe then either of those twoo whiche I named last afore. And to leaue vnspoken that no mennes
<pb facs="19"/>
saiynges are more taken vp and vsed, then those whiche bee sauced with a certain grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of pleasaunte myrth, vndoubtedly Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Diogenes, and Aristippus would serue better for teachyng and trainyng young children, then either Xenocrates orels zeno. That if the moste wyse aunciente fathers wer not deceiued in that thei thougt it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniente, with certain knackes of pleasaūte delectacion to lure y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> tendrenesse of youngth vnto the loue of sage ladie Sapiēce, muche more is thesame conueniente for one that is bothe tendre of age, and also born to bee a prince or gouernour: whom as it beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to bee vigilaunte, and to haue in all causes a diligente yie, so it behoueth not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue a soure couutenaunce hymself, orels to leat any persone with an heauie looke to departe from his presence. Now, the mynde brought vp in plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aunte and coumfortable studies of recreaciō, is made more lustie and courageous to sustein the burdē of all cures, &amp; also more pleasaūte for allmaner cōpaignie kepyng emong mēne. With these reasones I might sufficientely haue defēded myself though I had gathered together nothyng but merie iestes, wheras now suche saiynges of myrth are but here
<pb facs="19"/>
and there in fewe places entremedleed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong saiynges of grauitee and sadnesse, as sauces of the feaste. That if I shall perceiue your grace herewithall to bee well pleased: it shall neuer repente me of this my labour &amp; seruice dooyng, though (as some persones shall percase iudge) it bee ouer poore and base. Others dooē wryte bookes for theim that bee ferther entreed bothe in yeres and knowelage: I dooe (as ye would saie) feede the tendre age of a young babe of noble byrth. That if your grace hath alreadie outlearned this geare (as with all my herte I would wyshe that ye had) yet I knowe well it will stand with the good mynde and pleasure of thesame, that the commen studies of young scholares haue been fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threed, and haue fared thus muche the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for your sake. And I shall perhappes here after geue you thynges of more saige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and grauitee, when ye shall perfectely haue learned all this by herte. For these thynges must in any wyse bee cunned by herte, to thende that ye maye haue theim e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer readie at hande. Albeeit what nedeth you to haue any thynges of my makyng, ses ye haue at home in householde with you Conradus Heresbachius, a manne in all
<pb facs="20"/>
kyndes and sortes of learnyng absolute and perfecte, whom I see and perceiue to beare towardes your grace suche good herte and mynde, that (accordyng to the dutie and parte of an especiall good schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maister) he reioyceth at the comoditees and the honourable procedynges o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> you his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pille and scholare, muche more highly then at his owne. And this māne like as he hath alreadie trained &amp; instructed your childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood with learnyng, so shall he bee hable with prudente &amp; feithfull counsaill to dooe you greate helpe and fertheraunce when ye shalbee a manne. And to me also it shalbee a thyng to dooe no lesse ioye and coumforte, then high honestee and auauncemt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>te, in some behalf (bee it neuer so litle) to haue fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered your moste excellente towardnesse with my industrious labour. To conclude, I beseche almightie God, that he vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salue to conserue, to maintein, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creace his giftes of grace, whiche he hath moste aboundauntely bestowed on you, to the ende that ye maye aswell satisfie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires and wyshynges of your moste vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous parentes, and that ye maye proue euen like well in all worthynesse as thothers of your moste noble progenie hitherto haue
<pb facs="20"/>
dooen, as also that ye maye bee an hable manne to enioye the possessiō of that ioyly fruitefull Seigniourie to the whiche ye are born, and appoincted to bee heire. Thus will I make an ende, after one worde more. Whyle ye bestowe your self in this geare, thynk and remembre well, that ye dooe reade the saiynges, not of Christian menne, but of gentiles and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>screauntes, so that ye must reade theim with a iudgemente. Yeuen at Friburge the .xxvi. daye of Februarie in the yere of our Lorde. M.D.XXXI.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>