<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1623</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105046_Fr6_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09744</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20003</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105046</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vvhole sermons of that eloquent diuine, of famous memory; Thomas Playfere, Doctor in Diuinitie : Gathered into one vollume, the titles thereof are named in the next page</title>
                 <author>Playfere, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Law (Lawe), Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1623</date>
                 <publisher>Law (Lawe), Matthew.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Snodham, alias East, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 121, 7, 123-232, 6, 49, 5, 36, 6, 84, that is 72, 8, 261, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="216"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HAT a losse the Church of God had by the death of <hi>D. Playfere,</hi> I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the opinion of the world should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, then my slender pen attempt to expresse. If euer those combinations of Vertue and Learning, of Knowledge and Vtterance, of Wit and Memorie, of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and Vse, of Holesome and delightfull, of Schoole and Pulpit, of Olde and New, or in one word to say, of Nature and Industry, of humane felicitie and heauenly grace, concurred to make a Scribe perfect and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute to the kingdome of God, we may not be so much our owne back-friends (though wee detract not from the fortune of places
<pb facs="217"/>
further off) nay we may not so impeach the honour of the giuer, nor disparage the worth of our friend departed, as to doubt but this was principally manifested in <hi>M. Playfere.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>Who because he was but lent the world for a time, nay because he was redemanded soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then his time, (if it were lawfull to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll the heauenly wisedome with that word <hi>Sooner,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <hi>Phil. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>4.</hi>
      </note> but I mean in regard of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches vse, and that same <hi>propter vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>,</hi> which made the Apostle to demurre) I say since he was to be returned backe againe to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and ouer-ripe perfection not to conti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> ouerlong, it had bin to be wished, he had left behinde him some more monuments of his trauailes, as wel comfortable to the surui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, as honourable to himselfe. Which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he in his discretion, and because he had so resolued, was nice to doe, after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of them that would write nothing, though very able, or was then a doing most wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> God cal'd him, I cannot say. This which the good Reader will be loath perhaps to heare, I may not conceale, that these are the lost of all his labours which are like to be divulged. Into so small a compasse is that spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> ranged,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Cornel. apud Propet. l. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
            <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leg. 12.</hi>
      </note> as to be as she sayes,
<q>
         <l>En sum quod digit is quinque leuatur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap>,</l>
      </q>
      <pb facs="217"/>
or indeede not so much as a iust handfull, which lately was not confinable within bounds too great for me to speake of.</p>
   <p>But the summe is this: (For I lift not to defend his method of preaching against the Methods masters of our age, who me thinks should knowe either that of the Apostle, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitas donorum est, sed vnus spiritus:</hi> or that of the Prophet, <hi>Laudate eum in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, laudate in cithara;</hi> or if nothing will please them but what they do themselues, we must be faine to say as Crassus did to Scevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, <hi>Omnium igitur conciones tu confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies vnus, omnes ad te sub tempus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niemus, &amp;c.</hi>) I say the summe is this: that is the Sunne-light is pleasantest toward the set, and the skilfull eare finds most store of musicke in the close: so this Sun, this Swan, this sweet singer of Israel, (for what lesser tearmes can our loue affoard him? if any bring were we will not refuse them) his last monuments, and his last labours, that the world may euer hope for, shall finde we trust the dearer intertainement.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>