<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To my lou'd friend M. Iohn Fletcher, on his Pastorall</title>
           <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105619_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00962</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11068</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105619</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To my lou'd friend M. Iohn Fletcher, on his Pastorall</title>
                 <author>Rowlands, Samuel</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The faithfvll shepheardesse : By Iohn Fletcher</title>
                 <author>Fletcher, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 <distributor>Bonian (Bunnian), Richard</distributor>
                            <distributor>Walley, Henry</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>88 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomia">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <lg>
      <head>To my lou'd friend M. Iohn Fletcher, on his Pastorall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </head>
      <lg>
         <l>CAn my approouement (Sir) be worth your thankes?</l>
         <l>Whose vnknwne name and mnse (in swathing clowtes)</l>
         <l>Is not yet growne to strength, among these rankes</l>
         <l>To haue a roome and beare off the sharpe flowtes</l>
         <l>Of this our pregnant age, that does despise</l>
         <l>All innocent verse, that lets alone her vice.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>But I must iustifie what priuately,</l>
         <l>I censurd to you: my ambition is</l>
         <l>(Euen by my hopes and loue to Poesie)</l>
         <l>To liue to perfect such a worke, as this,</l>
         <l>Clad in such elegant proprietie</l>
         <l>Of words, including a mortallitie.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>So sweete and profitable, though each man that heares,</l>
         <l>(And learning has enough to clap and hisse)</l>
         <l>Ariues not too't, so misty it appeares;</l>
         <l>And to their filmed reasons, so amisse:</l>
         <l>But let Art looke in truth, she like a mirror,</l>
         <l>Reflects her comfort, ignorances terror</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Sits in her owne brow, being made afraid,</l>
         <l>Of her vnnatural complexion,</l>
         <l>As ougly women (when they are araid</l>
         <l>By glasses) loath their true reflection,</l>
         <l>Then how can such opinions iniure thee,</l>
         <l>That tremble, at their owne deformitie?</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>Opinion, that great foole, makes fooles of all,</l>
         <l>And (once) I feard her till I met a minde</l>
         <l>Whose graue instructions philosophicall,</l>
         <l>Toss'd it like dust vpon a march strong winde,</l>
         <l>He shall for euer my example be,</l>
         <l>And his embraced doctrine grow in me.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>His soule (&amp; such commend this) that commaund</l>
         <l>Such art, it should me better satisfie,</l>
         <l>Then if the monster clapt his thousand hands,</l>
         <l>And drownd the sceane with his confused cry;</l>
         <l>And if doubts rise, loe their owne names to cleare'em</l>
         <l>Whilst I am happy but to stand so neere'em.</l>
      </lg>
      <signed>N. F.</signed>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <head>To my friend Maister <hi>Iohn Fletceher,</hi> vpon his faithfull Shepheardesse.</head>
      <l>I Know too well that no more then the man</l>
      <l>That trauels through the burning desarts, can</l>
      <l>When he is beaten with the raging sunne,</l>
      <l>Halfe smotherd with the dust, haue power to runne</l>
      <l>From a coole riuer, which himselfe doth finde,</l>
      <l>Ere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e be slak'd: no more can he whose minde</l>
      <l>Ioies in the muses, hold from that delight,</l>
      <l>When nature, and his full thoughts b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>d him write,</l>
      <l>Yet wish I those whome I for friends haue knowne,</l>
      <l>To sing their thoughts to no eares but their owne:</l>
      <l>Why should the man, whose wit nere had a staine,</l>
      <l>Vpon the publike stage present his vaine,</l>
      <l>And make a thousand men in iudgement sit,</l>
      <l>To call in question his vndoubted wit,</l>
      <l>Scarce two o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> which can vnderstand the lawes</l>
      <l>Which they should iudge by, nor the parties cause,</l>
      <l>Among the rout there is not one that hath</l>
      <l>In his owne censure an explicite faith.</l>
      <l>One company kowing they iudgement lacke,</l>
      <l>Ground their beliefe on the next man in blacke:</l>
      <l>Others, on him that makes signes, and is mute,</l>
      <l>Some like as he does in the fairest sute,</l>
      <l>He as his mistres doth, and she boy chance,</l>
      <l>Nor wants there those, who as the body doth dance</l>
      <l>Betweene the actes, will censure the whole play:</l>
      <l>Some like if the wax lights be new that day:</l>
      <l>But multitudes there are whose iudgements goes</l>
      <l>Headlong according to the actors clothes.</l>
      <l>For this, these publicke things and I, agree</l>
      <l>So ill, that but to do aright to thee,</l>
      <l>I had not bene perswaded to haue hurld</l>
      <l>These few, ill spoken lines, into the world,</l>
      <l>Both to be read, and censurd of, by those,</l>
      <l>Whose very reading makes verse senceles prose,</l>
      <l>Such as must spend aboue an houre, to spell</l>
      <l>A challenge on a post, to know it well,</l>
      <l>But since it was thy happe to throw away,</l>
      <l>Much vvit, for which the people did not pay,</l>
      <l>Because they saw it not, I not dislike</l>
      <l>This second publication, which may strike</l>
      <l>Their consciences, to see the thing they scornd,</l>
      <l>To be with so much will and art adornd.</l>
      <l>Bisides one vantage more in this I see,</l>
      <l>Your censurers must haue the quallitie</l>
      <l>Of reading, which I am affraid is more</l>
      <l>Then halfe your shreudest iudges had before.</l>
      <signed>Fr. Beaumont.</signed>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>