<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE GENTLE∣men READERS, J wish no worse, then white Bootes, and wet WEATHER.</title>
           <author>D., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105207_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69184</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6386</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105207</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE GENTLE∣men READERS, J wish no worse, then white Bootes, and wet WEATHER.</title>
                 <author>D., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vox graculi, or Iacke Davves prognostication : No lesse wittily, then wondrously rectified, for the eleuation of all vanity, villany, sinne, and surquedrie sublimate, keeping quarter in the courts, cities, and countries, of all Christendome; for this yeere 1623. Published b authority</title>
                 <author>Daw, Jack</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Haviland, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 34, 4, 35-63, 66-72 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE GENTLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men READERS, J wish no worse, then white Bootes, and wet WEATHER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Allants, (and yet I hope no Gulls neither) As on a time I sate musing on the very verticke point of <hi>Hie-gate-hil,</hi> (with as little coyne in my Pocket, and as much cunning in my <hi>Craneon,</hi> as most of our Starre-gazers haue) To make experiment of my skill, if it could reach so high, as to take the iust <hi>Altitude</hi> of the <hi>Blindmans</hi> Bottle-ale at <hi>Holloway.</hi> I spied such a cluster of Knaues below in the valley, (like so many Danske Crowes summon'd on Douer sands against a storme) as that by my <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strolabe</hi> I began to collect; That this <note n="*" place="margin">Producing more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders then <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to's Mirabilis Annus.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Yeere</hi> would proue intemperate, by reason of an extreame heate in Summer; insomuch that the stones in <hi>Cheapside</hi> shall
<pb facs="3"/>
be so hot, that diuers Steeletto-bearded <hi>Scape-thrifts</hi> shall feare to goe from <hi>Paules</hi> to the <hi>Counter</hi> i'th Poultrie: Whereupon I betooke me to my <hi>Ephime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides,</hi> and erecting a figure, haue found such strange Accidents to fall out this yeere <hi>(Mercury</hi> being Lord and predominate in the house of <hi>Fortune)</hi> that many fooles shall haue full Bellies, and cramm'd Coffers; when wise men shall walke vp and downe with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry stomackes▪ and emptie pockets: and that many (who haue newly buried their Sires, and leap▪t into their Lands, before they be come to their wits) shall this yeere drowne many an Acre of their Ancestors, in the bottome of a wine-seller; and burie their <note n="*" place="margin">Quae malè parta, malè dilabuntur.</note>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mesnes in the Bellies of Brothell houses: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, if <hi>Iupiter</hi> were not ioyned with <hi>Mercurie</hi> in a more fauourable aspect, Butchers wines should haue little or nought to doe all <hi>Lent,</hi> but ride out of towne with their Iourneymen, and prouide Prickes against <hi>Easter:</hi> Seeing therfore the wonders that are like to ensue this succeeding yeere, I haue taken vpon me (for the beneficiall content of all my Countrymen) to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie this <hi>Prognostication,</hi> discoursing &amp; discouering briefly the disposition of the foure Quarters of the yeere <hi>1623.</hi> the <hi>Ecclipses</hi> both of <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moone,</hi> with their dangerous and subsequent effects: by which (if <hi>Pisces</hi> play not the Porter) many poore men, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting money, are like to fast on Sundayes for Lacke of food; and such as haue no Shooes, to goe bare-foot; if certaine deuout Coblers proue not the more propici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: Yet <hi>Astrologie</hi> is not so certaine, but that it may faile: and therefore diuers Ale-stufft-beleeuing
<pb facs="3"/>
Hostesses, may perhaps chalke vp more this yeere, then shall by their Customers be wiped out in two yeeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; But V. P. for that: <hi>Monedula capiet muscas,</hi> and digest them as easily, as some Church-men doe two liuings, and neuer surfet on them neither. Now as touching my Dedication; I was at first halfe way suggested to haue cull'd out some Church-warden or other for my <hi>Maecenas,</hi> who perhaps would haue bid me once a yeere to dinner, or haue fisted me with Forty-pence out of the poore-mans Boxe: But in the very rumination on this merry-thought, steps in a good Starre, and plainely told me, that <hi>Cum insipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entibus ludere, insipidum est.</hi> Therefore, with the rest of my weather-beaten brethen, I must needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that <hi>Sapiens dominabitur astris.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your vnparalleld Practitioner <hi>in Astrologie,</hi>
I. D.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>