<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Of Iob brought into dialogue: for our familiar speach.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105882_Fr2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16986</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3868</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105882</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Of Iob brought into dialogue: for our familiar speach.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iob : To the King. A Colon-Agrippina studie of one moneth, for the metricall translation: but of many yeres for Ebrew difficulties. By Hugh Broughton</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb n="103" facs="52"/>
   <head>Of Iob brought into dialogue: for our familiar speach.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He case of Iob, that he the godliest in the world should be most afflicted, would not be vnderstood of the children of this world: But that was to teach that the world of soules was the world of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: as Abrahā Isaac &amp; Iacob lived here in a peregrinatiō: looking for the heavēly citie, which God praepared for them in that part of Haides, <hi>Luc. 16.</hi> which was the kingdome of heaven, as Chrysostome speaketh vpon <hi>2 Cor. Hom. 6.</hi> Although the outward doctrine of the law had not perfection, God providing somewhat better for vs, that they should not have perfection in this world without vs: yet for perfect comprehending of Christ, by spirit of prophecy and plenty of grace, they far passed vs. In Iob God would revive Abrahams case: before the law was geven: which taught dull Israel, by outward blessings closly after spech of all such, how he would have his tabernacle amongst them, <hi>Levit. 26. 10.</hi> That when the earthly house of tabernacle should be dissolued, they should have a building from God, not made with hands, everlasting in the heavens. But worldlings, who all as the serpent go vpon the belly, would not vnderstand this. Therefore Iob is a rare exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: who in most high calamityes, wished to be with God. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane would scoph this pleading. Therefore God penned the book in such a style as Sadducees &amp; Epicures should not care to vnderstand it. And of my selfe I wil say, that the tongue, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie
<pb n="104" facs="53"/>
and trop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> and sequeles of arguments, hath ben hard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to me, then all the rest of the Bible. That he may be softer to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I have made a translation with great paynes and the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> circumspection that I could. Moreover I have brought the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puters spech, in termes hard and short, vnto a softer &amp; lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger veine: bringing the best examples at large to enlarge sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. As Targum Ierusalemy cited to generall sentences parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular exāples, &amp; sometime later then Iobs time, as a Paraphra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> might do: So when I make them Prophets, to speak of latt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> times then their owne: I speak it as my owne Paraphrase. The settling of arguments: to what verse of the formers speach, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyers do speake: that I studied to expresse clearly: and all har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Phrases. My desire was to have had the Ebrew text joyned to the English, with Rabbine commentary for their tongue: saving <hi>Iob. 10.</hi> where the incarnation and resurrection passeth Iew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> moderne faith: for the bare tongue, my desire was to force our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies the Thalmudiques to speak for vs: But I could fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> no cunning and ready hebrew printers vnlesse I had gone to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil. To print the whole Bible in the originall and my English, I would have done it: vpon allowance &amp; expected recompence. But I might not be at so great charges for one little book. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides this dialogue: I have before added sundry helpes: Short not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> in the Chapters, large Abridgementes and arguments of every chapter, &amp; here a description of the disputers story, how they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Abrahams kindred. To a plain book I would not have done so: But for this of vnspeakable difficulty it will not be tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: as the disputers themselves infinitely rowle one stone: The rest, all save Elihu: <hi>That Iob is wicked: yet by repentance may be sure of Gods grace:</hi> and, <hi>that still the wicked be punished: and the strangely punished, be so far in wiked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> Iob as often defendeth <hi>his integrity: and that he cannot</hi>
      <pb n="105" facs="53"/>
      <hi>be ever better then he was: and therefore would gladly know the reason of his afflictiō.</hi> As they often repeat their dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, so the cōmenter might. When this is abroad, if my readers think it not plain enough: questions vpon difficulties remayning shall come forth, if God will. So I have made two cōmentaries vpō <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>poc. one curt, that the hearer may soon see the tenour of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ork: the other larger, shewing by what mispolicy and mistudy, the City of Quirinus came to be so great. When those books be printed: I would bring in Dialogue some demaunding of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which breed hardnes. Dialogues haue brevity: and therefore Plato the learned contrived his mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into Dialogues. But now let the reader turne his mynd from me, vnto Iob.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>