<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1573</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105691_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01513</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11635</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105691</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Printer to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A hundreth sundrie flowres bounde vp in one small poesie : Gathered partely (by translation) in the fyne outlandish gardins of Euripides, Ouid, Petrarke, Ariosto, and others: and partly by inuention, out of our owne fruitefull orchardes in Englande: yelding sundrie svveet sauours of tragical, comical, and morall discourses</title>
                 <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Smith (Smyth), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1573</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Middleton, Henry</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 36, 45-164, 201-445, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath bin an old saying, that vvhiles tvvo
doggs do striue for a bone, the thirde may
come and carie it avvay. And this prouerbe
may (as I feare) be wel verefied in me which
take in hand the imprinting of this poeticall
Poesie. For the case seemeth doubtful, and I vvill disclose
my coniecture. Master. H. VV. in the beginning of this
worke, hath in his letter (vvritten to the Readers) cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly
discharged himselfe of any such misliking, as the
grauer sort of grey heared iudgers mighte (perhaps) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
in the publicatiō of these pleasant Pamphlets. And
nexte vnto that learned preamble, the letter of. G. T. (by
vvhome as seemeth, the first coppie hereof vvas vnto the
same. H. VV. deliuered, doth with no lesse clerkly cūning
seeke to persvvade the readers, that he (also) vvoulde by
no meanes haue it published. Novv I feare very muche
(all these vvords notvvithstāding) that these tvvo gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
vvere of one assent compact to haue it imprinted:
And yet, finding by experiēce that nothing is so vvel hād<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
novv adayes, but that some malicious minds may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
take occasion to mislike it themselues, or else finde
meanes to make it odious vnto others: They haue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
(each of them) politiquely preuented the daunger of
misreport, and suffered me the poore Printer to runne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay
vvith the palme of so perillous a victorie. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing,
hauing vvel perused the vvorke, I find nothing
therein amisse (to my iudgemente) vnlesse it be tvvo or
three vvanton places passed ouer in the discourse of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous
enterprise: The vvhich for as much as the vvords
<pb facs="3"/>
are cleanly (although the thing ment be somevvhat natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall)
I haue thought good also to let them passe as they
came to me, and the rather bicause (as master. H. VV.
hath vvell alleadged in his letter to the Reader) the well
minded mā may reape some commoditie out of the most
friuolous vvorks that are vvritten. And as the venemous
spider vvil sucke poison out of the most holesome herbe,
and the industrious Bee can gather hony out of the most
stinking vveede: Euen so the discrete reader may take a
happie exāple by the most lasciuious histories, although
the captious and harebraind heads can neither be encora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
by the good, nor forevvarned by the bad. And thus
muche I haue thought good to say in excuse of some sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours,
which may perchance smell vnpleasantly to some
noses, in some part of this poeticall poesie. Novv it hath
vvith this fault a greater commoditie than common poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies
haue ben accustomed to present, and that is this, you
shall not be constreined to smell of the floures therein cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined
all at once, neither yet to take them vp in such or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
as they are sorted: But you may take any one flowre
by it selfe, and if that smell not so pleasantly as you vvold
wish, I doubt not yet but you may find some other which
may supplie the defects thereof. As thus, he vvhich wold
haue good morall lessons clerkly handled, let him smell
to the Tragedie translated out of Euripides. He that wold
laugh at a prety conceit closely conueyed, let him peruse
the comedie translated out of Ariosto. He that vvould
take example by the vnlavvfull affections of a louer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stovved
vppon an vnconstant dame, let them reade the
report in verse, made by Dan Bartholmevv of Bathe, or
the discourse in prose of the aduentures passed by master
<pb facs="3"/>
F. I. vvhome the reader may name Freeman Iones, for
the better vnderstanding of the same: he that vvould see
any particuler pang of loue liuely displayed, may here ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue
euery Pamphlet by the title, and so remaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented.
As also diuers godly himnes and Psalmes may in
like manner be founde in this recorde. To conclude,
the worke is so vniuersall, as either in one place or
other, any mans mind may therevvith be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied.
The vvhich I aduenture (vnder
pretext of this promise) to present
vnto all indifferent eyes
as follovveth.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>