<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the worshipfull and his especiall good frend M. Latham of Sandowne in Essex.</title>
           <author>Vaux, R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105728_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01631</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11762</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105728</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the worshipfull and his especiall good frend M. Latham of Sandowne in Essex.</title>
                 <author>Vaux, R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two common places taken out of Andreas Hyperius, a learned diuine, whereof, in the one, he sheweth the force that the sonne, moone and starres haue ouer men, &amp;c. In the other, whether the deuils haue bene the shewers of magicall artes, &amp;c. Translated into English by R.V</title>
                 <author>Hyperius, Andreas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>79, 40-55, 78-110 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                    <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Witchcraft, demonology, occult writings</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>To the worshipfull and his especiall good frend M. Latham of Sandowne in Essex.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our very courteous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fabilitie, whereof I haue had so great experience, continuing without any shew of a mutable mind hath greatelye moued myne affection to make no small account of your worships frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship. And I would to God that it were in me by any meanes to make any small a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes vnto you for the same. Which to do is easier for me to wish than to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishe. Wherefore as there is no remedie but that I must remayne endebted: so on the contrary parte to shew no signes of a willing minde, were nothing els but a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest tokē of an ingrateful person. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon hauing perused certaine of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places contained in the Methode of <hi>Hyperius</hi> and lighting vpon these two here specified, and thinking them not vnmeete
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>to be reuealed for the instruction of the people: I purposed for declaration of my louing mind toward you to put them forth in print dedicated vnto your worship. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whome I know they shall be no lesse ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable then if they were thinges of very great account. Thus committing you and your affaires to the protection of the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghest; I bid you farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours to commaund R. Vaux.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>