<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>In Camera Stellata coram Con∣cilio ibidem, vndecimo die Iulij, Anno decimo tertio CAROLI Regis.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105578_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21452</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7757</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105578</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>In Camera Stellata coram Con∣cilio ibidem, vndecimo die Iulij, Anno decimo tertio CAROLI Regis.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A decree of Starre-Chamber, concerning printing : made the eleuenth day of Iuly last past. 1637</title>
                 <author>England and Wales, Court of Star Chamber</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Barker, Robert.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bill, John 1, Assignees of</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Ordinances, edicts, proclamations</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>In Camera Stellata coram Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio ibidem, vndecimo die <hi>Iulij, Anno decimo tertio</hi> CAROLI <hi>Regis.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His day Sir <hi>IOHN BANKES</hi> Knight, His Maiesties At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourney Generall, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in Court a Decree drawn and penned by the aduice of the Right Honourable the <hi>Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> of the great Seale of England, the most Reuerend Father in God
<pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
         <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="4"/>the Lord <hi>Arch-Bishop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury his Grace,</hi> the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and Right Reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God the Lord <hi>Bishop of London Lord high Treasurer of England,</hi> the <hi>Lord chiefe Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices,</hi> and the <hi>Lord chiefe Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> touching the regulating of Printers and Founders of letters, whereof the Court hauing conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the said Decree was dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and ordered to be here Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and to the end the same may be publique, and that euery one whom it may concerne may take notice thereof, The Court hath row also ordered, That the said Decree shall speedily be Printed, and that the
<pb facs="4"/>same be sent to His <hi>Maiesties</hi> Printer for that purpose. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the three and twentieth day of Iune in the eight and twentieth yere of the reigne of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and before, diuers De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and Ordinances haue beene made for the better gouernment and regulating of Printers and Printing, which Orders and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees haue beene found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be defectiue in some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars; And diuers abuses haue sithence arisen, and beene practised by the craft and malice of wicked and euill disposed persons, to the preiudice of the publike; And di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers libellous, seditious, and muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
<pb facs="5"/>bookes haue been vnduly prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and other bookes and papers without licence, to the disturbance of the peace of the Church and State: For preuention whereof in time to come, It is now Ordered and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, That the said former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and Ordinances shall stand in force with these Additions, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planations, and Alterations follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>