<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MOST MIGH∣TIE, AND RENOWNED MONARCH, JAMES, By the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the Fayth, Increase of prosperous Dayes here, &amp; perpetuitie of fe∣licitie hereafter.</title>
           <author>Brown, David</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105906_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17027</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3905</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105906</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MOST MIGH∣TIE, AND RENOWNED MONARCH, JAMES, By the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the Fayth, Increase of prosperous Dayes here, &amp; perpetuitie of fe∣licitie hereafter.</title>
                 <author>Brown, David</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The new invention, intituled, calligraphia: or, the arte of faire writing : vvherein is comprehended the whole necessarie rules thereof; by which anie who is capable and carefull to learne, may without the helpe of any other teacher, under God, both bee informed concernin the right writing of the most usuall characters in the world; and perfectly instructed how to write one of the most frequent in Europe, called the secretarie. ... By His Majesties scribe, Master David Browne</title>
                 <author>Browne, David</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Saint Andrews</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 <publisher>Burdon, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>54, 216 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MOST MIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIE, AND RENOWNED MONARCH, <hi>JAMES,</hi> By the grace of God, King of Great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the Fayth, <hi>Increase of prosperous Dayes here, &amp; perpetuitie of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie hereafter.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is sayde, (dread Soveraigne) by Salomon, that great King of Wisedome, Vertue, and Peace, that <hi>a Kinges favour, is like the dew upon the grasse:</hi> as if hee should say, that the commendation, or
<pb facs="3"/> loving countenance of a King to Vertuous Workes, both encourageth the Workers, and maketh the Works more and more to flowrish within his Kingdome, according to that other Proverbe, <hi>Virtus laudata crescit.</hi> The efficacie and validitie of eyther of these, I, (though a verie meane Instrument of a verie meane Worke, haue found to bee accomplished by your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, (whom <hi>GOD</hi> hath endued as another Salomon, with the like Princelie Prerogatiues, whose Name therefore bee praysed) and that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> diverse times, but chiefelie at your Majesties last beeing in your Highnesse Palace of <hi>HOLIE ROOD-HOVSE,</hi> after inspection of some of mine owne Exercises of <hi>FAIRE WRITING,</hi> with certaine rare practises of a nine-yeare-olde Disciple, which I then taught, &amp; at your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse superscribing of my former Priviledge. For the which Royall Testimonies, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie for the Priviledge, (which I esteeme the Seale thereof) I most humblie render all hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thanks unto <hi>GOD,</hi> and to your Majestie through <hi>HIM,</hi> in whome I hope to prooue your trustie Servant to the death.</p>
   <p>In memorie, consideration, and boldnesse whereof, I haue both with the better courage, and greater expedition, enterprized and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished this difficill Taske, in finding out a way how Writing may bee learned by Reading: and that for the regarde I owe to the glorie of <hi>GOD,</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/> who is the Author of all sortes of Vertue, of which the dexteritie of Writing is one, your Highnesse pleasure, who under <hi>HIM,</hi> is the maintainer of all Vertue, within your Royall Kingdomes, the Common-wealth of them all, which springeth from the Fountaine of all Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, &amp; to mine owne credite, which I owe both unto <hi>GOD,</hi> of whome I holde my meane Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, your Majesties selfe, Prince <hi>CHARLES,</hi> your deare and onelie Sonne, to all your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse Loyall Subjectes of this your Majesties famous Realme of <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie the Secret Counsell, Nobilitie, Colledge of Iustice, Vniversities, and chiefe Cities there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: (where I was borne, brought up, and doe spende my dayes:) which (albeit not verie woorthie of it selfe, yet because it justlie belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth unto your most Sacred Majestie, beeing both bred in your Highnesse owne Realme, and the first fruites of this kinde that ever did grow therein) I therefore, according as appertaineth, more for mine owne duety, than its valour, with heartie affection, moste humblie propine unto your Majesties most Royall Person, as Master of all the Ground, next unto <hi>IEHOVAH,</hi> (to remaine under the Saueguarde and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of your Highnesse, and your happie Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessoures favourable Patronage, and Imperiall authoritie, for a common use:) and I recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende
<pb facs="4"/> your Highnesse selfe, with all your most Princelie Progenie, to the blessed Tuition of the most mightie <hi>KING</hi> of Kinges, during your Reigne in the Earth; and to <hi>HIS</hi> joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Fruition, to reigne everlastingly with <hi>HIM</hi> in the Heavens: In whome I rest, while I breathe,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Maiesties Subiect, and humble Servant, <hi>DAVID BROWNE.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>