<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Postscript]</title>
           <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1593</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105222_Ba1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20028</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6467</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105222</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Postscript]</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The defence of contraries : Paradoxes against common opinion, debated in forme of declamations in place of publike censure: only to exercise yong wittes in difficult matters. Wherein is no offence to Gods honour, the estate of princes, or priuate mens honest actions: but pleasant recreation to beguile the iniquity of time. Translated out of French by A.M. one of the messengers of her Maiesties Chamber</title>
                 <author>Estienne, Charles</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1593</date>
                 <publisher>Waterson, Simon.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 99, 5 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Afterwords</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="postscript">
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, heere I thought good to breake off, and conclude this first Booke, both for your ease &amp; mine owne: least wearying you too much, you should fall in dislike of me and my labour, and so both of vs misse your gentle fauour, the only recompence I expect for my paines: and very vnkinde are ye, if ye cannot part with so small a reward. But not despairing thereof, let me intreat thus much at your hands, if ye finde any harsh English in my rude Translation, or faults vnwillingly escaped in the Printing: mend the one with Patience, and the other with your pennes, so both shall passe for currant, you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued, and I sufficiently contented.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours to his power,</hi> A. Mundy.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>