<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT vvorshipful sir Francis Castillion Knight, a Gentleman Pentioner vnto his Maiesty.</title>
           <author>Ellis, G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1605</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105479_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21255</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7606</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105479</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT vvorshipful sir Francis Castillion Knight, a Gentleman Pentioner vnto his Maiesty.</title>
                 <author>Ellis, G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The lamentation of the lost sheepe. By G.E</title>
                 <author>Ellis, G.</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jaggard, William</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1605</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>56 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT vvorshipful sir Francis <hi>Castillion Knight, a Gentleman</hi> Pentioner vnto his Maiesty.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE mightie Emperour <hi>Aurelius</hi> beeing demaunded what shoulde becom of a certaine stranger, that audatiouslie entred his <hi>Pauilion,</hi> he answered with words deseruing immortal memorie:</p>
   <p>
      <hi>If he come in loue let him liue, if otherwise, let him beare the price of his presumption.</hi> Wherefore though imboldned by a general report of your respectiue fauours to men any waies well quallited, I haue vnacquainted, boldly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed to present this little Booke vnto your worships good acceptance: yet my meaning pretending a loue and dutious well wishing, And the Subiect prefering
<pb facs="6"/>
no idle or vnprofitable substance, J hope, you will (with <hi>Aurelius</hi>) kindly regard the one, and fauorably censure of the other: for heerein J do but imytate the prescriptions of all former writers, who from time to time haue as well selected strangers, as those of their acquaintance to patronize their endeuors, beeing knowne to be louers of learning and vertue. I haue (in the like) heeretofore pleased many, and my trust is, J shall not now (in this) displease you, in which hope, J tender my labors to your good liking, And leaue your worship to the happy fruition of all your goldly, and hopefull expectations. Euer resting</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>At your commaundement in all humble duty. G. Ellis.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>