<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE TRVELIE RELIGIOƲS, AND Right Noble Ladie, LADIE ANNA KER, Ladie Balmerinoch, Grace, Mercie, and Peace, through IESVS CHRIST, our LORD, and onelie SAVIOVR.</title>
           <author>L., D.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1622</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105377_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05558</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15683.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105377</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE TRVELIE RELIGIOƲS, AND Right Noble Ladie, LADIE ANNA KER, Ladie Balmerinoch, Grace, Mercie, and Peace, through IESVS CHRIST, our LORD, and onelie SAVIOVR.</title>
                 <author>L., D.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>An heavenly chariot : layde open for transporting the new-borne babes of God, from time infected vvith sin, towards that æternitie in the which dwelleth righteousnesse. Made up of some rare pieces of that purest golde which is not to bee found but in that ritchest thesaurie of sacred scripture. By M. David Lindesey, minister of Christs Evangel at Leith</title>
                 <author>Lindsay, David</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Saint Andrews</pubPlace>
                    <date>1622</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE TRVELIE <hi>RELIGIOƲS, AND</hi> Right Noble Ladie, LADIE ANNA KER, <hi>Ladie Balmerinoch,</hi> Grace, Mercie, and Peace, through IESVS CHRIST, our LORD, and onelie SAVIOVR.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing in this last and most dead Age of the Worlde (Right Noble Ladie) there be not a few living (alace) not onelie under the blinding Darknesse, and corrupting Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition of abominable Poperie; but also un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that shining Lanterne of that saving Gospel, which leadeth men directlie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes that bright morning Starre CHRIST IESVS, blessed for evermore: who holding (ah mee!) this Earth for their Home, doe never dreame that they must bee remooved from it: and so who cannot bee mooved so much as to beginne to thinke upon another Habitation; let bee to fit themselues for it: not-with-standing that None-sparing Sworde of Death, slaying daylie, without respect of persons, men of all Rankes, in everie place, may sensiblie cleare unto them the trueth of that Golden Sentence, <hi>Heere wee haue no continuing Citie.</hi> I,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.14</note> the
<pb n="4" facs="3"/>basest in all respectes my LORD and MASTER hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about the building of His Tabernacle, longing now to bee dissolved, and to bee with Him whome my Soule lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth; haue out of that affection which I carrie to all such as call upon His Name, beene bolde (over-comming at length manie difficulties) to offer these few Lines unto the view of others; that if it were possible some one simple Soule or two, might bee mooved by them (GOD beeing happilie with them) to loose their affections from thinges heere beneath, and to set them upon those thinges which are aboue. I haue dedicated them unto your Honour, whome GOD hath so happily weaned from the deceitfull Milke of all things earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and so Graciouslie married unto His blessed Sonne: that nowe your Honour can wiselie account of nothing, but in so farre as it leadeth you unto Him who out of loue gaue Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe for you. Accept these Lines, Madame, as a Testimonie of that Loue and Reverence which I must carrie to that spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Grace of GOD bestowed happilie upon you: for the continuance and encrease whereof, I shall never cease to draw up my simple Prayers, unto that GOD who is readie to heare all such as call upon Him in trueth, &amp; is able to keepe your Honour unto His everlasting Kingdome.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Ladiships, in our Blessed Saviour, the</hi> LORD IESVS, <hi>D. L.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>