<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Myles .C. to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1542</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105580_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00673</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10808</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105580</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Myles .C. to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The supplicacion: that the nobles and comons of Osteryke made lately by their messaungers, vnto kyng Ferdinandus, in the cause of the Christen religion : Item. The kynges answere to the same. Vvherpon foloweth the wordes that the messaungers spake vnto the kyng agayne at their departing</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Crom, Matthias</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1542</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>Myles .C. to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His last moneth of mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che (most deare Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) was delyuered vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me in the hye Almay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes lāguaige a copie of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent supplicaciō in prynt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of trulye I was right glad: Not onely to heare of so many noble men &amp; so great a multitude of co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men people thus feruently hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring and thirsting after Gods holy worde, but also it dyd me good at my hert, to reade of the most humble &amp; gentle fashions, that they vse toward the same. For first they rūne not rashly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether on head, nether take they their clubbes in their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, to bring in Gods trueth by violence, but lowly &amp; with due subiectiō seke they such cōueniēt meanes, as are of Gods ordina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unce: knowinge, that the cōmen refourmacyon of euery realme
<pb facs="3"/>
coūtre, or citie, ought to be myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred by the office of the king, prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, or ruler of the same, and not by anye priuate personne. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, whā they haue their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, though they can not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne their iust sute, yet make they no murmuringe ner grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge, but committe their cause vnto God, and remayne in their supplicaciō. Thirdly, though the kinge be of another mynde, and willeth them to be as popysh in their beleue as their fathers we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re afore thē, yet in that behalfe they preferre the worde of God aboue all the preceptes of men, allbeyt they ceasse not from prayeng for their prynce, ner frō ioperding their bodies &amp; goodes with him and for him.</p>
   <p>Such holy &amp; vertues ensam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples (gentle reader) doth god set forth for our instruccion, &amp; all to
<pb facs="3"/>
gyde vs in his right waye, to mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue our hertes vnto ernest repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce, to make vs honger and thirst after righteousnesse, to plā<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te in vs all louyng obedience, &amp; peaceable behaueour towarde our heades and rulers, &amp; to sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me those wycked Babilonians &amp; sedicious Coraites, that disturbe all ordinaunces of God, euē tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se murmurers &amp; complayners, that had rather sitt in Egypte by the flesh pottes, &amp; to enioye the pleasures of synne for a sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, then to be refourmed &amp; fed of God in the wildernesse. O vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull and flowe bellyes. O where is now among vs such fer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uentnesse towarde Gods glorie, such ernest repentaunce &amp; amēd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of life, as the prophet Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas describeth in the Niniuites &amp; as this present supplcacion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth planely to be in this peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple?
<pb facs="4"/>
which though thy cā not be suffred to haue Gods trueth syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely preached among thē (exce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pte it be by stealth) yet are they feruent toward his glory, thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie after the water of life, wash their chekes with teares for lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke therof, vnfayned in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, true &amp; faithfull vnto God and their countre, &amp; euen ready with ten handes (as they saye) to receaue a right Christē refour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maciō, &amp; that in al vnite &amp; peacea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble behaueour. Lorde what shall worth of vs then, that hauyng such delite in oure old wicked cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaciō, shame not to refuse all honest amēdmēt of lyuinge? Full litle remebre we, that the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of God doth call us to repē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taūce. And what els do mē procu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp; heape vp vnto thē selues by such obstinate hertes, then the wrath of God agaynst the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te daye of his appearinge?</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Now (gētle reader) that thou mayest take some edifiēg by this present supplicaciō, cōsidre thou these poyntes therin: First, that for all the multytude of dogges which go againe to their vomite the lord ceasseth not yet frō ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing vp some to call vpō his holy name, as thou maiest se here in this people, whom the lord hath turned (as he daylye doth many other moo) vnto his trueth. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cōdly, lerne at their ensāple not onely to desyre &amp; wishe for amēd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt of all abuses, but also take so<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me paynes &amp; labour thy selfe in helping therto, and be content to bestowe thy body and goodes for the same. Thirdly, make thy first complaynte and sute to All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, and then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre, that in seking this precious perle and iewel of refourmacion at the office of the hyer powers,
<pb facs="5"/>
thou forget not the frutes of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manite &amp; loue. Fourthly though thou canst not haue thy laufull request, yet leaue not thy dewtie vndone, make no disturbaunce▪ be peaceable, cōmitte the cause to God, ād considre, that our syn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full lyues haue deserued no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; that it is euen the heuy in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dignacion of God, that so many Prynces and rulers had rather be disceaued with ypocrites (as Achab was with his foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth chaplēs) then to haue pitie on their owne soules, thē to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue cōpassion on their poore subie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctes, thē to haue Gods glorie ād his holy word to florish in their countrees, thē to be lerned be ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, and to embrace the deare sonne of God: whose wrath whā it is kyndled (as the .ij. Psalme sayeth) then blessed are all they, that put their trust in him. Amē</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>