<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Dedication]</title>
           <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105710_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01517</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11640</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105710</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Dedication]</title>
                 <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A delicate diet, for daintiemouthde droonkardes : Wherein the fowle abuse of common carowsing, and quassing [sic] with hartie draughtes, is honestlie admonished. By George Gascoyne Esquier</title>
                 <author>Gascoigne, George</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <opener>❧<hi>To the right Wor</hi>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <hi>shipfull his synguler good</hi> friend, <hi>Lewes Dyue</hi> of <hi>Broomeham,</hi> in the Countie of Bedforde, Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyer, <hi>George Gascoigne</hi> wysheth continuance of Gods fauour.</opener>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YR, you maye</hi> possibly condempne me of greate ingratitude, who (hauing combred the whole worlde with my thryft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse workes) haue yet neuer remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred to present you with any of them: And in deede your great friendshippe woulde rather challenge at my handes, the preheminence of suche pleasures, togeather with the redoubling of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter good wyll, as God shall please to enable mee.</p>
   <p>But Syr, when my wanton (and worse smelling) Poesies, presumed fyrst to
<pb facs="3"/>
peark abroade, they came forth sooner then I wyshed, and muche before they deserued to be lyked. So that (as you maye sithens perceyue) I was more combred with correction of them, then comforted in the constructions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto they were subiect. And too make amendes for the lost time which I mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bestowed in wryting so wantonlie: I haue of latter dayes vsed al my trauaile in matters both serious and Morall. I wrote first a tragicall commedie cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The Glasse of Gouernment:</hi> and nowe this last spring, I translated and collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a worthy peece of worke, called <hi>The Droomme of Doomes daie,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated the same to my Lord and Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster: And I inuented a <hi>Satyre,</hi> and an <hi>Ellegie,</hi> called <hi>The Steele glasse:</hi> and <hi>The complaint of Phylomene.</hi> Both which I dedicated to your good Lord and myne, <hi>the Lorde Greye of VVylton:</hi> These vvorks or Pamphlets, I esteeme both Morall and Godly: whereof al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I presented you no Coppies, yet am I not therein so blamefull as
<pb facs="3"/>
vnhappy. Surely I must needes alledge that I had verie fewe Coppies thereof my selfe: and yet of those fewe, I had one readie to haue sent you, the last time that my Brother <hi>Iohn Dy<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e</hi> was in the Cittye.</p>
   <p>But at the very instant of his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it was not redie: So that I fayled thereby of my determynation, and remayne at your curtesie for the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of this iust excuse, wherunto I hope the rather to persuade you, by presenting this small pamphlet called, <hi>A delycate Diet for Droonkards,</hi> vnto your name and patronage, the which I beseech you to accept as a pawne and token of my contynuing good wyll, I knowe you, and the world hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes esteemed you, for a paterne of Sobryetie', and one that doth zelously detest the beastlie vyce of droonken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: This small worke is therefore so much the meeter to bee dedicated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you: I present it, both for that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specte, and for mine owne discharge: and therewithall the Coppies of the
<pb facs="4"/>
workes before named: I dyd often reueale, but neuer preuayled, in the errande which my brother <hi>Iohn</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted to my sollycytyng when wee last were together. I praye you accept my good wyll in all things: and soone after Mgihelmas (by Gods leaue) I wyll see you. The God of our Forefathers continue his mercye and grace to vs all, now and euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From my lodging in London, <date>the. 10. of August. 1576.</date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>¶Your bounden and assured George Gascoigne.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>