<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull, Sir Charles Blount, Knight, indewed with perfections of learning, and titles of nobility: Robert Greene wisheth in∣crease of honour and vertue.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1617</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105886_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02073</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12216</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105886</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull, Sir Charles Blount, Knight, indewed with perfections of learning, and titles of nobility: Robert Greene wisheth in∣crease of honour and vertue.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Alcida : Greenes metamorphosis, vvherein is discouered, a pleasant transformation of bodies into sundrie shapes, shewing that as vertues beautifie the mind, so vanities giue greater staines, than the perfection of any quality can rase out: the discourse confirmed with diuers merry and delightfull histories; full of graue principles to content age, and sawsed with pleasant parlees, and witty answeres, to satisfie youth: profitable for both, and not offensiue to any. By R.G</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1617</date>
                 <publisher>Pindley, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Purslowe, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Wolfe (Woolfe), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>78 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull, Sir <hi>Charles Blount, Knight, indewed with perfections of learning, and</hi> titles of nobility: <hi>Robert Greene</hi> wisheth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <hi>crease of honour and vertue.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Chilles,</hi> the great Commander of the <hi>Mirmidones,</hi> had no sooner (Right Worshipfull) encountred the hardie <hi>Troian</hi> with his Courtelax, and regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred his valour on the helme of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, but returning to his tents, hee pourtraied with his pen the praise of <hi>Polixena,</hi> ioyning Amors with Armors, and the honor of his Learning with the resolution of his Launce. In the <hi>Olympiades</hi> the Laurell striued as well for the Pen, as the Speare: and <hi>Pallas</hi> had double Sacrifice, as well perfumes of torne papers, as Incense of broken truncheons. Entring (right worshipfull) with deep insight into these premis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, I found blazoning your resolute indeuors in deeds of Armes, and report figuring out your euer-intended fauours to good letters: presuming vpon the courteous disposition of your Worship, I aduentured to present you, as <hi>Lucius</hi> did <hi>Caesar,</hi> who offered him an Helmet topt with Plumes in warres, and a booke stuffed with precepts in peace, knowing that <hi>Caesar</hi> held it as hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to be counted an Orator in the Court, as a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier in the field. So (right worshipfull) after your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from the Low Countries, (passing ouer those praise-worthy resolutions executed vpon the enemie)
<pb facs="4"/>
seeing absence from armes had transformed <hi>Campus Martius</hi> to mount <hi>Helicon,</hi> I ouerboldned my selfe to trouble your Worship, with the sight of my Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phosis: A pamphlet too simple to patronage vnder so worthy a <hi>Maecenas,</hi> and vnworthy to be viewed of you, whose thoughts are intended to more serious studies. Yet <hi>Augustus</hi> would read Poems, and write Rounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>her to purge melancholly with toyes, then for any delight in such trifles. So I hope your Worship wil, after long perusing of great volumes, cast a glance at my poore pamphlet: wherein is discouered the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomy of womens affections: setting out as in a mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, how dangerous his hazard is, that sets his rest vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on loue: whose essence (if it haue any) is momentany, and effects variable. If either the method, or matter mislike, as wanting scholarisme in the one, or grauity in the other: yet if it shall serue your Worship as a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle to passe away the time, and so slip with patience, as a boord Iest, I shall be lesse grieued: if any way it please, as to procure you delight, I shall be glad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> satisfied, as hauing gained the end of my labours: but howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, hoping your Worship will pardon my presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in presenting; and weigh more of the well affected will, then of the bad labored worke, I wish your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship such fortunate fauours, as you can desire, or I i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships to command, Robert Greene.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>