<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶To the right worshipfull Mr. Edvvard Dyar Esquire, Iohn Frampton wisheth pro∣sperous health and felicitie.</title>
           <author>Frampton, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105055_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09829</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20092</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105055</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶To the right worshipfull Mr. Edvvard Dyar Esquire, Iohn Frampton wisheth pro∣sperous health and felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Frampton, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most noble and famous trauels of Marcus Paulus, one of the nobilitie of the state of Venice, into the east partes of the world, as Armenia, Persia, Arabia, Tartary, with many other kingdoms and prouinces. No lesse pleasant, than profitable, as appeareth by the table, or contents of this booke. Most necessary for all sortes of persons, and especially tor trauellers. Translated into English</title>
                 <author>Polo, Marco</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 167, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶To the right worshipfull M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. Edvvard Dyar Esquire, <hi>Iohn Frampton</hi> wisheth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperous health and felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING lying by mee in my chamber (righte Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipful) a translation of the great voiage &amp; lōg trauels of <hi>Paulus Venetus</hi> the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> manye Merchauntes, Pilots, and Marriners, and others of dyuers degrees, much bent to Discoueries, resorting to me vpon seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall occasions, toke so great delight with the reading of my Booke, finding in the same such strange things, &amp; such a world of varietie of matters, that I coulde neuer bee in quiet, for one or for an other, for the committing the same to printe in the Englishe tongue, perswading, that it mighte giue greate lighte to our Seamen, if euer this nation chaunced to find a passage out of the frozen Zone to the South Seas, and otherwise delight many home dwellers, furtherers of trauellers. But finding in my selfe small abilitie for the finishing of it, in suche perfection as the excellencie of the worke, and as this learned time did require, I stayed a long time, in hope some learned man woulde haue translat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d the worke, but finding none that would take it in hand, to satisfie so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny requests, nowe at last I determined to sette it forth, as I coulde, referring the learned in tongues, delighted in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, to the worke it selfe, written in Latine, Spanish, and Italian, and the reste that haue but the English tong,
<pb facs="3"/>
that seeke onelye for substaunce of matter to my playne translation, beseeching to take my trauell and good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the beste parte. And bethinking my selfe of some speciall Gentleman, a louer of knowledge, to whome I mighte dedicate the same, I founde no man, that I know in that respecte more worthy of the same, than your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe, nor yet any man, to whome so many Schollers, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> many trauellers, and so manye men of valor, suppressed or hindred with pouertie, or distressed by lacke of friends in Courte, are so muche bounde as to you, and therefore to you I dedicate the same, not bicause you your selfe wāt the knowledge of tongues, for I know you to haue the Latine, the Italian, the French, and the Spanishe: But by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of youre worthinesse, and for that I haue since my firste acquaintaunce founde my selfe without any greate deserte on my parte, more bound vnto you than to anye man in <hi>England,</hi> and therefore for your desert &amp; token of a thankefull minde, I dedicate the same to youre worship, moste humbly praying you to take it in good parte, and to bee patrone of the same: and so wishing you continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of vertue, with muche encrease of the same, I take my leaue, wishing you with many for the cōmon wealths sake, place with aucthoritie, where you maye haue daylye exercise of the giftes that the Lorde hathe endowed you withall in plentifull sorte. From my lodging this xxvj. daye of Ianuarie. 1579.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your vvorships to commaunde, IOHN FRAMPTON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>