<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶TO THE RIGHT HO∣norable Sir Fraunsis VValsingam Knight, principall Secretarie to her Highnesse and one of her Maiesties moste Honou∣rable priuie Counsaile: Barnabe Riche wi∣sheth increase of honor, continuance of healthe and happie estate.</title>
           <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105153_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A10724</idno>
           <idno type="STC">21004</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105153</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶TO THE RIGHT HO∣norable Sir Fraunsis VValsingam Knight, principall Secretarie to her Highnesse and one of her Maiesties moste Honou∣rable priuie Counsaile: Barnabe Riche wi∣sheth increase of honor, continuance of healthe and happie estate.</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true report of a late practise enterprised by a papist : with a yong maiden in Wales, accompted emongst our Catholiques in those partes for a greater prophetise, then euer was the holie maide of Kent, till now on Sundaie beyng the iiii. of Marche this present yere 1582. in the Cathedrall Churche at Chester, before the whole assemblie then at a sermon she confessed how she had been seduced by a ronegate priest, and how by his instructions she had feined to see certaine visions, whiche like wise followe in due forme. The pervsyng whereof, the reformed Protestaunte shall finde cause worhtie to laugh at: the wilfull papist matter is to bee ashamed at: and all sortes of people good example to be warned at: truly set doune without any maner of parciallitie, by Barnabe Riche gentleman. Pervsed and allowed accordyng to the order appointed</title>
                 <author>Rich, Barnabe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Kingston, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Walley (Waley), Robert</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>40 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶<hi>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Sir Fraunsis VValsingam Knight, principall Secretarie to her Highnesse</hi> and one of her Maiesties moste Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable priuie Counsaile: <hi>Barnabe Riche</hi> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth increase of honor, continuance of healthe and happie estate.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in all Actions and attemptes (Right Honorable) it is moste requisite to choose out suche as are moste politique and prudent performers, so in causes of prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction it is moste necessarie to account of suche as are greatest fauoures of the cause, whereuppon: knowyng your Honor to bee a Piller and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proppe of true Christianitie, a maintainer of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and a zealous professor of the Gospell, J thought it not amisse, to offer these trifles (in wisemens Judgementes, yet diuine miracles in the wilfull and Ignoraunt Papistes opinion) to your Honor, to be safcundited vnder your graue title, and the rather, for that my simplicitie shall finde sauegarde vnder so Honorable a name, and my good meanyng (whiche would stretche farre
<pb facs="3"/>
if abilitie were corespondent) might be manifest vnto you, who haue bounde me by seuerall good turnes, and in whom those in necessitie alwaies finde refuge.</p>
   <p>Maie it please you therefore to giue it the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerreading, and as it deserueth, the laughyng at, and as your Honor likes of the miracles, so imparte it for the straungenes to those shall best like you. And thus J moste humbly take my leaue.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors in all seruiceable dutie to commaunde. Barnabe Riche.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>