<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIP∣full Maister Edward Dyer Esquire, the Maecenas of worth, and mirror of all admi∣red perfections.</title>
           <author>Dickenson, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105351_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20406</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6817</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105351</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIP∣full Maister Edward Dyer Esquire, the Maecenas of worth, and mirror of all admi∣red perfections.</title>
                 <author>Dickenson, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Arisbas, Euphues amidst his slumbers: or Cupids iourney to hell : Decyphering a myrror of constancie, a touch-stone of tried affection, begun in chaste desires, ended in choise delights: and emblasoning beauties glorie, adorned by natures bountie. VVith the triumph of true loue, in the foyle of false fortune. By I.D</title>
                 <author>Dickenson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>68 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Maister Edward Dyer Esquire, the Maecenas of worth, and mirror of all admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red perfections.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ell might Telamonian Aiax (Right worshipfull) a Peere of the peerlesse Iliade, and owner of the seuen-fold target, stout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppose himselfe to inuading Hector, that vaunted his drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded prowesse, backed by succor of the gods, and strongly repulse the thick-darted Troian fires from their endaungered nauy, the sole staie of their then-doubted return, hauing for his vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous arme so massy a bulwarke, &amp; for his valiant heart so man-like a bodie. And (si magnis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere parua licebit) in like sort I, shrouded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the shadow of your worships winges, haue therfore the more boldly aduentured to thrust into the open light, this mine abortiue issue, the frute of some fewe idle houres, sith after many thoughts, I could not excogitate any more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
<pb facs="3"/>
recreatiō wheron I might bestow times of leasure, hoping that for the common good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king which all men conceiue of you, and for the generall good speeches which all men vse of you, they will the better censure of my dooing, when they see your worshippes name to whose worth this worthlesse Pamphlet is entitled, stā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the front as a strong fort of defence, to shield me from the descanting verdites of such vnfriendly readers, which conceiting the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors entent amisse, may wrest his meaning by wrōg cōiectures, &amp; frō the sowre cēsures of the ouer-curious Moralists of our age, which glory to be termed the new-vprearers of the lōg ago confuted Stoical Apathy, although these harsh ensuing lines merit no such high protectiō, sith they are not ouer-curiously labored: for I deem it mere folly to make a trifle a labor, or my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure my paine: and they may be tearmed the worke of a slumbring, rather then of a wakefull Muse: yet I haue obserued that Poetical method in my discourse, which the best &amp; most appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Authors of the ancientest and most famous languages haue alwaies vsed &amp; allowed, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in Medio, &amp; afterward at occasions, vnfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding former accidents. Howsoeuer, if these the
<pb facs="3"/>
saplesse frutes of greene youth, &amp; pithlesse blos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somes of a simple Authors vnripe wit, purchase such fauor &amp; acceptance as I desire, though they deserue not, I shall be emboldened to raise my Muses note that now yeelds harsh Musick, to an higher key, a fairer frute of my better ordred va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant houres, &amp; manifest my dutie to your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship in some matter of greater import, then a su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficiall toye: for I iudge it the extremitie of folly to trouble the worlde with heapes of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles. But fearing to grow offensiue through te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious interrupting of your worshippes serious affaires, and humbly crauing pardon of mine audacious enterprise, I ende, wishing to your worship manie daies of happinesse in this life, and heauen in the other life.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Worships most firmely deuoted in all dutie and seruice, Iohn Dickenson.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>