<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>AN ADMONITION TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105146_Bo1_20</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08200</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18537</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105146</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>AN ADMONITION TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A true report of the late apprehension and imprisonnement of Iohn Nichols minister at Roan : and his confession and ansvvers made in the time of his durance there. VVherevnto is added the satisfaction of certaine, that of feare or frailtie haue latly fallen in England</title>
                 <author>Allen, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Foigny, Jean de</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Reims</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 34, 2 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Literature</term>
                    <term>Jurisprudence</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="41"/>
   <head>AN ADMONITION TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are no more of regard, as farre as vve yet heare, that haue relented al this long &amp; perilous time of practize and persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, sauing <hi>M. Aufild,</hi> and <hi>M. Govwe,</hi> the former in <hi>England,</hi> through extreeme feare of torments yelding onely to goe to their church once, and that vvith many qualifications: the other in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> vpon other frailtie, specially for desire to retorne home and enioye the commodities temporal that God had giuen him in his countrey: vvho both streight vpon their fall (being in regard of humane frailtie not great) vvept bitterly, haue done penaunce accordingly, vvritten their letter to
<pb facs="42"/>our Presidet in <hi>Rhemes</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
         <desc>•••</desc>
      </gap> readines to doe any satisfaction for the scandal and offence committed, and so be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to Gods Church againe, and haue done since that, and doe, al they can possibly for th'aduauncement of the Catholike faith. Vvhose like pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike acknovvledge of their offence should here haue been set furth, but that the same could not be so speedely sent hither as the dispatch of these other vvas compted necessary.</p>
   <p>Onely in al this (gentil reader) I desire the to marke for thy cōsolatiō, the mercies of God: hovv in this lōg combat vvith so forcible and povvra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ennemies according to the flesh, vvho vvāt no meanes vvorldly, either to force by feare of death &amp; torments, or to tempt by pleasure proffit &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, or to entangle by art and pollicie, he hath giuen vs his poore
<pb facs="42"/>seruaunts and souldiars, not onely to fight, stand, hold out, &amp; haue assured hope of victory ouer the aduersaries, but to haue it vvith so small a losse, by the death of so fevv, vvith the fall or vvounding of so fevv, so easely reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered againe to farre more aduantage of the cause, as our Lord hath of his grace vsed the matter, then if they had neuer had experience of their ovvne infirmitie, and of the necessitie of his holy ayde, by vvhom onely vve are vpholden in this spiritual fight for our faith, and defence of his deare Spouse our Mother the Church, vvhich by no povver of man or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel can be ouerthrovvne.</p>
   <p>Fare vvel gentil reader, and make thy profit to saluation, of these ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of our frailtie, vvhereby thou seest Gods streinght to be perfited in our infirmitie, and our vveakenes to
<pb facs="43"/>be sustained by the force <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> his grace, to him be al honor and glorie. Amen▪ The first of Iune 1583.</p>
   <pb facs="43"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>