<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1609</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105249_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20057</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6499</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105249</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Foure birds of Noahs arke : viz. 1. The dove. 2. The eagle. 3. The pellican. 4. The phoenix</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Ballard, Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Butter, Nathaniel</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1609</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24, 65, 10, 58, 6, 71, 16, 29, 1, 14 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, I haue for thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort sent vnto thee 4. Birds of <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark, vpon foure seuerall messages: and haue changed the notes of those Birds voices into Prayers of different mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke, but all full of sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Vnder the wings of the Doue, haue I put
<pb facs="11"/>
Prayers, fitting the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Doue, that is to say, simple Prayers, or such as are fitting the mouthes of yong &amp; the meanest people: and for such blessings as they haue most need of. The Eagle soares more high, &amp; in his beake beareth vp to heauen supplications in behalfe of Kings and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. The Pellican carieth the figure of our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer on the crosse, who shed his blood to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish vs (hee being the right Pellican): with the drops of which blood, haue I writ Prayers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb facs="11"/>
all those deadly &amp; capitall sinnes, to wash out whose foulenes our Sauiour suffered that ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious death. And lastly, in the spiced nest of the Phoenix (in which Bird likewise is figured Christ risen againe) shalt thou find a book written ful of Thanks &amp; Wishes: of thankes, for those be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits which grow vnto vs by Christs death and resurrection: of Wishes, that hee would in diuers gifts bestow those bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings vpon vs. Nothing that is set downe is tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, because I had a care
<pb facs="12"/>
of thy memorie No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is done twice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause thou mayst take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in them. If thou art yong, here is pleasure for thee: if old, here is cōfort▪ if thou art poore, here is riches; if thou hast enough, here is more: vse this physicke wel, and liue well: runne this circle truely, and die wel: that is the goale: winne that, winne Heauen.</p>
   <trailer>Fare-well.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>