<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the right Honorable Sir Ed∣warde Osbourne Knight, hir Maiesties Leifte∣nante, Lorde Mayor of hir Highnes most ho∣norable Cittie London, the right Worshipfull Knight Syr Rowland Haiward, Alderman of London, the right worshipfull Mayster Iohn Spencer Alderman and Shriue of London, and the right worshipful of the fraternitie, and mis∣terye of Clothworkers. Iohn Phillip the sonne of Robart Phillip Clothworker disceased, wi∣sheth the feare of God, peace and prosperitie in our merciful Lord and Sauior Christ Iesus. &amp;c.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105036_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09595</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19875</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105036</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the right Honorable Sir Ed∣warde Osbourne Knight, hir Maiesties Leifte∣nante, Lorde Mayor of hir Highnes most ho∣norable Cittie London, the right Worshipfull Knight Syr Rowland Haiward, Alderman of London, the right worshipfull Mayster Iohn Spencer Alderman and Shriue of London, and the right worshipful of the fraternitie, and mis∣terye of Clothworkers. Iohn Phillip the sonne of Robart Phillip Clothworker disceased, wi∣sheth the feare of God, peace and prosperitie in our merciful Lord and Sauior Christ Iesus. &amp;c.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A sommon to repentance : Giuen vnto Christians for a loking glasse, wherin we may behold our owne deformities, and therein and thereby, we are not onely forewarned of our destructions, but we are learned to humble out selues in these dangerous dayes of wickednesse, before the throane of Gods mercy, that wee maye not be preserued from the lake of damnation, in the great and notable day of Christs comming to iudgemente. Published by J.P. student of Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Phillips, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jackson, Hugh</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>70 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ <hi>To the right Honorable Sir Ed</hi>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde Osbourne Knight, hir Maiesties Leifte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante, Lorde Mayor of hir Highnes most ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Cittie London, the right Worshipfull Knight Syr Rowland Haiward, Alderman of London, the right worshipfull Mayster Iohn Spencer Alderman and Shriue of London, and the right worshipful of the fraternitie, and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terye of Clothworkers. Iohn Phillip the sonne of Robart Phillip Clothworker disceased, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth the feare of God, peace and prosperitie in our merciful Lord and Sauior Christ Iesus. &amp;c.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F this small present right honorable and worshypful, rendered into your hands with all humility and reuerence, maye finde fauour in your sight, I shall not only accounte my selfe happye, but hereafter shew my selfe industerious to pleasure you wyth some other treatise, which with this shall redowne to the glory of god, your well liking, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of my natiue cuntrimen. In the meane sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, I most earnestly besech your good Lordship, and euery of you, to pardon my boldnes, and to satisfie your mindes with this poore mite of mine, which to the comforte of the godly, and the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the maleuolent is published, not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but as you are vertuous and godly affected, so
<pb facs="3"/>
your honor and euery one of you being patrons &amp; members of this common weale, in as much as in you shal consist, will doe your indeuors to beate down syn, whose branches are so monsterous, that they begin to ouer shade vertue, the which thing to cal vnto our memories, is a thing of al things to be lamented: who heareth not in the Gospel how diligently our wickednesses cōmitted against the maiestie of eternal God are reproued? but who or where are they that conuert and turne to the Lord in this our last time of our age and calling? no, we glory in our iniquityes and hate to be reformed, and generally to speake the truth, we I say for the most part and greatest number of vs that professe the name of Christ, are rockt and lulled in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt cradle of our owne securities, and therin we slepe so soundly, that neither can the remembrance of Gods graces, signes &amp; tokens, his greuous threat nings and terrible comminations serue, to rouse vs vp out of the dangerous and most perrilous slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our iniquyties, &amp; it cannot be chosen (right Honorable and Worshipful) but that the day of our visitation is at hand, and except we repent, we shal perishe in our wickednesses, for Gods heauie indig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>tion is readie to enter into the gates of our Cities, the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ols of his wrath are ready to be pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red forth vpon vs, &amp; our God is ready in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of his displeasure, to hew vs downe with the
<pb facs="3"/>
Axe of his vengeance for our ingratitude, to blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> our names out of the booke of lyfe, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his commandements, and to leaue vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> pray for our abhominable actions, to our aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent aduersarie sathan. I exhort your good Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship therefore, and euery one of you, to whome God hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> giuen authority, in the bowels of Iesus Christ, to perseuer and go forward from vertue to vertue, &amp; to the vttermost of your powers, to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishe from your Cities and Townes, al the may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of misrule, that both contemne God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spise good order. Thus shal you please God in discharging your dueties, and shewe your selues o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient subiects to hir excellent maiesty, that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth you in trust to bridle the outrage of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that range as gracelesse after their vncleanesse. Thus wishing you right honorable and euery one of you the feare of god, peace and prosperitye in Iesus Christ, I leaue you to his gracious &amp; heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preseruation, beseeching him of his infinite good nes, whilst his mercy holdeth his indignation at a bay, to giue vs the grace with humble and contrite hartes, to prostrate our selues before him, to craue pardon at his fatherly hands for our offences, to weepe bytterly for our sinnes, and to bring forth the fruites of repentance, thus shal we pacifie hys heauy displeasure, conuerte his fury to fauor, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> to loue, and his conceiued wrath to comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="4"/>
kindnes, the which we shal inioye in this life and after when the course of this our pilgrimage is fully finished, we shal stand before him in purity, be sanctified with his holynes, be crowned with honor and glory, and be made fellow heires with Christ Iesus of his celestial king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the which God for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> sonne Christ his sake graunt you and euery of you.</p>
   <p>Your humble and faythful wel willer in the Lord.</p>
   <p>Iohn Phillip.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>