<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A godly and Faithfull Re∣tractation made and publi∣shed at Paules crosse in London, In the yeare of oure Lorde God M. D. xlvij. the xv. daye of May, by M. Richarde Smyth Doctor of diuinity and reader of it in Oxforde.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1547</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105010_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12494</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22822</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105010</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A godly and Faithfull Re∣tractation made and publi∣shed at Paules crosse in London, In the yeare of oure Lorde God M. D. xlvij. the xv. daye of May, by M. Richarde Smyth Doctor of diuinity and reader of it in Oxforde.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A godly and faythfull retractation : made and published at Paules crosse in London, the yeare of oure lorde God 1547. the 15. daye of May, by mayster Richard Smyth Doctor of diuinitye, and reader of the Kynges maiestyes lecture in Oxford. Reuokyng therin certeyn errors and faultes by hym committyd in some of hys bookes</title>
                 <author>Smith, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wolfe, Reyner (Reginald)</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1547</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ A godly and Faithfull Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractation made and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed at Paules crosse in London, In the yeare of oure Lorde God M. D. xlvij. the xv. daye of May, by M. Richarde Smyth Doctor of diuinity and reader of it in Oxforde.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Prophet Dauid (good chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sten audiēce) saith right truly: <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis homo mendax.</hi> That is to wytt: Euery man is a Lyer of his owne corrupted nature: The which thing how trew it is, theldest &amp; best Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Christen Church, doo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently declare, because they all haue erred in their bookes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the great Clerke saynt Austen, in an Epipistle writen to Marcella writeth of himself; <hi>Vos qui me mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>diligitis, si talem me asseritis, vt nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in scriptis errasse me dicatis, frustra laboratis, nec bonam causam suscepistis: facile meipso iudice superamini, quoniā non placet mihi cum a charissimis meis ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lis existimor, qualis non sum.</hi> That is to say: Yee that loue me muche, if ye said that I am such that ye affirme that I neuer erred in my writyngs or Bokes, ye labor in vayne, ye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not taken in hand a good cause: ye are easely ouercome, I my selfe being Iudge: For it pleaseth not me whan I am estemed suche a man of my moast deare frendes as I am not. Here we se that this blessed father saynt Austen was not asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to confesse his error in writing: which thing he dyd not by woordes only, but also in a certayne Booke wherin he wrote very many things in which he confesseth that he was deceyued. This Booke is called in
<pb facs="3"/> Latyn, <hi>Liber Retractationum:</hi> And in Englysh, a Booke of Retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Reuocations, of such thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche he wrote amysse &amp; erred in. Shall I now be ashamed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knoledge my self to haue ben decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in my Booke of Traditions? Am I worthy to be resembled or compared to this noble aunciente Doctor of Christes church? Wyl ye not beleue S. Austen in other poyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of our Religiō because he erred, &amp; also confessed his error in dyuerse and sundry thynges of his bokes? To be short, who of all the Writers of bokes erred not? S, Ambros, S, Hierome, Chrisostome, Hilary, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, Origen, Tertulian, and all the other Doctors of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church were deceyued in some poyntes of their Bookes, as learned men do well know. Why therfore may nott I erre, or why shulde I be ashamed
<pb facs="4"/> too confesse myne Error and too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke it? Ought not euery good mā and woman too bee sory for my fall in this my Booke, and too reioyce with me acknowledging the trewth in this matier of mans Traditiōs, Preceptes, Ordinaunces, Rites, Ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remonies? Who sayth not that I haue a iust cause to excuse my weke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and fault, and aske of you mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy? which I trust I haue optayned of the Kynges gracious highnesse, and his moost honorable Counsell: by whose goodnesse and clemency I am here admytted and suffered too shew myne Errors and Faultes in my booke of Traditions, which I made of late entituled thus: A brief Treatise, setting furth diuerse tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, necessary both too be beleued of Christen people and kepte also, which ar not expressed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, but lefte to the Churche by the
<pb facs="4"/> Apostles Traditions, made and set furth by Richard Smyth, Doctor of Diuinite and Reder of it in Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde. Which Booke I do Reproue &amp; Reuoke in dyuers Faultes in it, of the which I wyll a non recite cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne perticulerly, and then I shall geue vnto you a trew and Generall Doctrine of all those thynges of which I doo entrete in that my Boke, that therby you may well perceyue &amp; see, after what sorte thei ought too be taken of Christen people that no man erre therin,</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>