<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the courteous and wel disposed Reader.</title>
           <author>Nicholls, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105660_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08197</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18535</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105660</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the courteous and wel disposed Reader.</title>
                 <author>Nicholls, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The oration and sermon made at Rome : by commaundement of the foure cardinalles, and the Dominican inquisitour, vpon paine of death. By Iohn Nichols, latelie the Popes scholler. Which sermon and oration was presented before the Pope and his cardinalles in his Consistorie, the xxvij. day of Maie. 1578. and remaineth there registred. Now by him brought into the English tongue, for the great comfort and commoditie of all faithfull Christians. Heerin also is aunswered an infamous libell, maliciouslie written and cast abroad, against the saide Iohn Nichols, with a sufficient discharge of himselfe from all the Papists lying reports, and his owne life both largelie and amplie discouered</title>
                 <author>Nicholls, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>238 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <head>To the courteous and wel disposed Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oure things (good Christian reader) haue caused me to be circumspect in vvritīg this Book, to vvit, Feare, Care, Necessitie, and Affection. Feare afflicted me: Care compelled me: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie bound me: and affection vvounded me. Feare afflicted me because the greef of cōming into infamie, reproch and troubles, caused a great circumspection in me, to mark diligently vvhat I vvrote, and to put the same dovvne in vvriting vvithout any spot of hipocrisie and double dealing. Care compelled me to be circumspect in my doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, lest that the Papists should finde a bone to gnavv there vpon. Necessitie vrged me bothe to ansvver to the infamous Libels vvritten against me, and to satisfie (if that I might) the honest request of certain zelous Christiās, in vvriting the Oratiō and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vvhich vvere doon at Roome. And as necessitie caused me to purge my self of
<pb facs="10"/>the false reports of lying Papists: so dooth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie prouoke me to be circumspect in all my sayings, affectiō stirreth me vp to vvrite those things, vvhich are no lesse true then profitable. But if my vvritings be neuer so true, yet notvvithstanding, some or other busie headed fellovv vvilspeak against thē: I haue not their tungs in keeping, let them speake vvhat they list, and I shall arme my self vvith pacience. And heerin vvil I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovve the steps of Zenocrates, vvho for his pacience vvas much commended: for though he vvere of his Maister Plato vniustly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of vngratefulnes, yet vvas he nothing mooued there vvith all, and being asked vvhy he did not ansvver Platoes defaming of hī, made this ansvver. That vvhich I do is good and profitable for me. So I say, that vvhich I haue vvritten in this Sermon made at Roome, novv I confesse to be true, and I hope this confession shalbe good and profitable for my soules helth. And as for the vvords of the Papists, as they are but vvīde: so let them passe as vvinde, as they proceed
<pb facs="10"/>from a malicious hart, so I conster them, and so I accept them, not vvith malice but vvith pacience. The pacience of Eusebius teacheth me so to doo, for vvhen a vvicked vvoman, infected vvith the heresies of Arrius, had vvilfully throvvne astone at him, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith all had vvounded him to death: hee vvas so far from taking reuenge, that he svvare his freends vpon his death bed, not to punish her therfore. O noble minde, O ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous act vvorthy of eternall memorie, he forgaue her that vvas his enemie and did him great iniurie. The like pacience GOD graunt vnto me, that vvhatsoeuer the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists say or doo against me: I be not angrye therfore, but take all things in good parte, and pray for them, that they may haue a peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent hart, to be sory for their dooings and say<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ings, against them vvhich vvish them no othervvise, then to them selues: one faith in Iesu Christe, &amp; brotherly looue one tovvard an other. God be mercifull vnto them and vnto vs all, and shevv vs the light of his Countenaunce. God increase the number of
<pb facs="11"/>his Elect▪ God conuert his enemies vnto the trueth of his sacred Gospell. God graunt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life vnto vs all, for surely as yet God is not serued aright, our vvoords and deeds doo greatly differ in effect, our vvoords are heauenly, our vvoorks are vvorldly, vvicked and deuilish. God graunt vs effectually grace, vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by vve may be saued, Graunt this O Lord for thy deere Sonnes sake. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine in the Lord, Iohn Nichols.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>