<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105107_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18995</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5412</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105107</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 <author>Breton, Nicholas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The flower of phisicke : VVherein is perfectlie comprehended a true introduction and method for mans assured health: with three bookes of philosophie for the due temperature of mans life. In which easily may be perceiued the high &amp; wonderfull workes of God in the gouernance of all thinges. Written by W.C. as a glasse of true knowledge for the better direction of al willing [et] vertuous practitioners</title>
                 <author>Clever, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Ward, Roger</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 122, that is 130 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or that in this our age, sundry strange alterations in the elements distraming the bodily health of man vppon earth with manie vnusuall corruptions: and also for that man hath a proper inclination to grosse libertie, contagiously nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing manie vncleane diseases in him selfe as a venemous serpent in his own bosome, for remedy whereof, as for the diligence and carefull furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of manie vnskilfull practicioners, with whome the world is ouercharged. I haue put forth this generall worke for the benefite of the common-wealth: and what profite may ensue heereof, time approueth the same: Remembring the olde prouerbe. <hi>Vino vendibili, non est opus sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensa hedera</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <salute>Fare you well.</salute>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>