<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christian Reader:</title>
           <author>H., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105087_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69149</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5854</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105087</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christian Reader:</title>
                 <author>H., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Gods promise to his plantation· : as it was delivered in a sermon, by Iohn Cotton, B.D. and preacher of Gods word in Boston</title>
                 <author>Cotton, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Jones, William 3</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bellamy, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 20 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Christian Reader:</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LTHOVGH no good Christian, or indeede inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous man, can doe any thing lesse, than approove of such endeavours, as aime at the glory of God, and a Common good, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they are mannaged by a cleare war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from Gods word. Yet for aymes and ends that men put to their actions being hidden in their hearts, there is no way to declare them, but by an honest profession of them, which is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent where wee are entertained but with that common charity one man is bound to yeeld ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; But for the grounds and rule an action is wrought by, and the praise of it in that respect, there is another iudgement than that of charity to guide us by, namely, by proving it by the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone of Gods word.</p>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <p>Now because many may either not know, or doe not consider upon how full a ground and warrant out of the word of God that underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king (which was the occasion of this Sermon) hath hitherto proceeded, J thought good (Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader) leave being with some diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie obtained of the Reverend Authour) to present unto thy view and consideration, that which may in part give thee satisfaction in this particular.</p>
   <p>Ere long (if God will) thou shalt see a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger declaration of the first rise and ends of this enterprise, and so cleare and full a iustification of this designe, both in respect of that warrant it hath from Gods word, and also in respect of any other ground and circumstance of weight, that is considerable in the warrant of such a worke, as (J hope) there will easily be removed any scruple of moment, which hitherto hath beene moved about it.</p>
   <p>If thou hast any doubts yet unresolved, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be intreated to understand from us, what may be the answer of them, than to discourage any man by them: so shalt thou be a helper and a friend, whereas otherwise (it may be against thy will) thou ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>st be an enemie to a worke
<pb facs="3"/>(for ought thou yet knowest) God is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of.</p>
   <p>Jt is hoped; there is none but will finde cause to approve of the worke, and of them that ingage themselves in it; But especially they who any way, at least by silence (a seeming applause) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved the Plantations of <hi>Virginia, St. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stophers, Bermudas,</hi> this having ends in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to none of them, and men (not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare but to give due honour to all employed in such noble enterprises) promising as much by their usefulnesse, industrie, love to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, piety, and other qualifications as those did.</p>
   <p>It is enough they adventure, that hazard their persons, families and estates, for that worke, which it may appeare to thee ere long thou art bound as well as they to further.</p>
   <p>Now it were iniurious, if not impious, not onely to denie the right and benefit of thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to such, but also to loade them with cause<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse aspersions (though but in thy thoughts) for that, for which thou hast great cause to praise God for thē, who hath stirred up their spirits to that which hath beene a maine meane of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling the world, and is likely to be of propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Gospell. For the furtherance of which
<pb facs="4"/>worke in the hands of those that sincerely intend it, let as fervent prayers passe from thee to the throne of grace for them, as J am confident, (thy occasions being made knowne unto them) would be put up from them in thy behalfe.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thine I. H.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>