<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVCTOR. TO THE LERNED TEACHERS of Salvation that know Great Britane speach.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105815_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17000</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3882</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105815</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVCTOR. TO THE LERNED TEACHERS of Salvation that know Great Britane speach.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A require of agreement to the groundes of divinitie studie : wherin great scholers falling, &amp; being caught of Iewes disgrace the Gospel: &amp; trap them to destruction. By H.B</title>
                 <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schilders (Grapheus, Painter), Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Middelburg</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 92, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_non-English-speaking_readers">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THE AVCTOR. TO THE LERNED TEACHERS of Salvation that know Great Britane speach.</head>
   <p>IEwes scattered over the world, having Satan breathing in them, the more they are provoked to beleve, the more they offre them selues to the Serpent to be deceaued &amp; to deceaue, from that plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that is in Christ. Since ambassedour Barton of Godly memorie moved a principal Rabbi at Stanpol, to write to Englād for Ebrew explication of our Gospel, the Iewes of Prage, Francfurt, Hanaw &amp; others bestir them selues to serch our crossing of the holy story. They plead that as ours teach, Messias Kindred is not in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel: how he cometh from Dauid. And infer, soundly vpon our treason, that so the Gospel should not be from God. So they say, that by ours, Mathew and Luke be vnreconcileeble: who bring sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathiel, as we say, the one from Iechonla of Salomon, as al of trueth must graunt, our blindes doth: the other of Neri of Nathan Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons brother. And they well think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> that men of grace should never be caught in such vmpossibilities. So they say, we as they, make the Romanes the fourth Kingdome in Daniel: which was to be destroyed before Christ should come in the flesh, and, that for ending, Moyses Law, by Daniels seauens: we haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> many mindes and heades: wheras so weighty a matter should haue consent of all Christendome. Also they obiect that our best spent 60. yeres to prove that we haue not the New Testament pure: which God had kept pure if he had geven it. And that we haue 20. Opiniones for our Principal article of Descent to Hell. To all these I answear: and pronounce all, a the an, which after warning will trap them to Eternal destruction. And to their modest I open our mysteries.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>