<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL MAISTER Doctour AIRAY Prouost of Queenes Colledge in Oxford, all felicitie both in this world and in the world to come.</title>
           <author>Gomersall, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1616</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105186_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13205</idno>
           <idno type="STC">23502</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105186</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT WOR∣SHIPFVLL MAISTER Doctour AIRAY Prouost of Queenes Colledge in Oxford, all felicitie both in this world and in the world to come.</title>
                 <author>Gomersall, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Englands first and second summons : Two sermons preached at Paules Crosse, the one the third of Ianuarie 1612; the other the fifth of Februarie, 1615. By Thomas Sutton Batchelour of Diuinitie, then fellow of Queenes Colledge in Oxford, and now preacher at Saint Mary Oueries in Southwarke</title>
                 <author>Sutton, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Okes, (Derwen, de Quercubus), Nicholas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Law (Lawe), Matthew</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1616</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>10, 249, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL MAISTER Doctour AIRAY Prouost of <hi>Queenes Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> all felicitie both in this world and in the world to come.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Jght Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, you may iustly maruell what importunity might bring my impolished
<pb facs="3"/>Meditations so quickly to the Presse, but (being much against my will enforced to let them try their fortune in the world) why I should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath them to your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection no man needs to wonder, considering the many encouragements, and continuall kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses which I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from you, vnto whose fauour, next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, I ascribe the
<pb facs="3"/>greatest part of my wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being, since first I came vnder your gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I know well you haue many learned Scribes in that <hi>Naioth,</hi> whereof God hath made you the chiefe <hi>Seer,</hi> more worthie to haue shewne their forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in this kinde then my selfe, who can leaue more learning for the gleaning, then my whole vintage. (For I am but
<pb facs="4"/>one of the least, and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est amongst all the sons of my mother) yet seeing you may iustly challenge the same interest in mee, which <hi>Paul</hi> did in <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemon, Thou owest vnto me thy owne selfe,</hi> I am willing to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge some part of my debt, if you shall allow of this coine and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression for currant: and yet euen in this, shall J runne farther vpon
<pb facs="4"/>the old score, as being rather in your debt for your kinde receiuing of it, then out of your debt by repaying so slender thankes. J know that the least Sabboth daies iourney of your owne, is more worth then any whole yeares paines of mine: Yet am I confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, you will both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider my yeares, which are but few, and the time J had, which
<pb facs="5"/>was but short, and my many other occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, wherewith in the meane time I was interrupted, and then accept of this for tryall, as if it were the extract of some purer and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wit. The Lord prosper your daies, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect your heart, and blesse all your labours, to the glorie of his Name, and the good of his Church: From
<pb facs="5"/>
      <hi>Queenes</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours in all duty and seruice,</hi> Thomas Sutton.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>