<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the ryght Noble Erle of Leycester, one of hir highnesse most Honora∣ble, wise, and graue Counselers.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1570</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105670_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01365</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11488</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105670</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the ryght Noble Erle of Leycester, one of hir highnesse most Honora∣ble, wise, and graue Counselers.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A very briefe and profitable treatise declaring hovve many counsells, and vvhat maner of counselers a prince that will gouerne well ought to haue : The book speaketh</title>
                 <author>Furio Ceriol, Fadrique</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1570</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>128 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>Courtesy, civil conversation, etiquette, sumptuary</term>
                    <term>Political tracts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the ryght Noble <hi>Erle of Leycester, one of</hi> hir highnesse most Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, wise, and graue Counselers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR LACK OF BET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter habilitie, I am bolde after my olde wonte, to presēt your Honor with Inke and Paper, more to doe my bounde dutie in shewing my selfe thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full towardes you, for your great benifites bestowed on mee: than for any profite or pleasure, that I know your Honor can reape any waye of my rude wryting. And yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst al the tryfles that euer I wrote, there was none in mine opinion that ought to please you better than this little Treatise, representing vnto you as it were in a glasse, manye of those good vertues and qualities that do raigne in you, &amp; ought to raigne in cuery other good counseler. Which Treatise was first written in the Spanishe tongue by a Spanyard called FEDERIGO FVRIO, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward trāslated into the Italian tongue by
<pb facs="3"/>
another Spanyard called ALFONSO D'VLLOA, but not with so good grace as I beleeue it had in the Spanishe, which in deede I neuer sawe, and therefore though my very friend May ster Iohn Baptist Castiglion one of the Gromes of hir Highnesse priuie chamber, vpō good zeale he had to profite many, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered me the saide booke at my last being at the Court, earnestly requesting me to put the same into our vulgar tong, yet I would not altogither trāslate it, but thought it best to make a briefe collection of the substance thereof, cutting of all superfluous talke, and yet leauing nothing out (I trust) that was necessary to be spoken. But how soeuer it be I most humbly beseech your Honor to take it well in worth, and in pervsing the same to conceyue of my labour bestowed therin, with that fauourable iudgement, which you haue alwayes vsed towardes mee, in all my other doings, and therwith to continue still my good Lord, euen as I think my selfe bounde to continue your faythfull seruant. Thus leauing to trouble your Honor any further: I pray God to graunt you helth &amp; long lyfe, with much prosperitie. From Newton Flotman the first of Aprill. 1570.</p>
   <p>Most bounde to your Honor</p>
   <p>Thomas Blundeuill.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>