<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honourable, the Lady Marie, Countesse of PEMBROOKE.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105172_Fr3_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19816</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6243.4</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105172</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honourable, the Lady Marie, Countesse of PEMBROOKE.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Delia and Rosamond augmented : Cleopatra by Samuel Daniel</title>
                 <author>Daniel, Samuel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Waterson, Simon</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>196 pages, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="55"/>
   <pb facs="55"/>
   <head>To the Right Honourable, the Lady <hi>Marie,</hi> Countesse of PEMBROOKE.</head>
   <lg>
      <l>LOE heere the worke the which she did impose,</l>
      <l>Who onely doth predominate my Muse:</l>
      <l>The starre of wonder, which my labours chose</l>
      <l>To guide their way in all the course I vse.</l>
      <l>Shee, whose cleere brightnes doth alone infuse</l>
      <l>Strength to my thoughts, and makes mee what I am,</l>
      <l>Call'd vp my spirits from out their low repose,</l>
      <l>To sing of state, and tragick notes to frame.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I, who (contented with an humble song.)</l>
      <l>Made musique to my selfe that pleas'd mee best,</l>
      <l>And onely told of DELIA, and her wrong,</l>
      <l>And prais'd her eyes, and plain'd mine owne vnrest:</l>
      <l>(A text from whence my Muse had not degrest.)</l>
      <l>Madam, had not thy well grac'd <hi>Anthony,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>(Who all alone hauing remained long,)</l>
      <l>Requir'd his <hi>Cleopatras</hi> company.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <pb facs="56"/>
Who if shee heere doe so appeare in act,</l>
      <l>That for his Queene &amp; Loue he scarce wil know her,</l>
      <l>Finding how much shee of her selfe hath lackt,</l>
      <l>And mist that glory wherein I should shew her,</l>
      <l>In maiestie debas'd, in courage lower;</l>
      <l>Yet lightning thou by thy sweet fauouring eyes,</l>
      <l>My darke defects which from her sp'rit detract,</l>
      <l>Hee yet may gesse it's shee; which will suffise.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>And I heereafter, in another kinde,</l>
      <l>More fitting to the nature of my vaine,</l>
      <l>May (peraduenture) better please thy minde,</l>
      <l>And higher notes in sweeter musique straine:</l>
      <l>Seeing that thou so graciously doost daine.</l>
      <l>To countenaunce my song and cherish mee.</l>
      <l>I must so worke posterity may finde</l>
      <l>How much I did contend to honour thee.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Now when so many pennes (like Speares) are charg'd,</l>
      <l>To chace away this tyrant of the North:</l>
      <l>
         <hi>Gross Barbarism,</hi> whose powre growne far inlarg'd,</l>
      <l>Was lately by thy valiant Brothers worth,</l>
      <l>First found, encountred, and prouoked forth:</l>
      <l>Whose onset made the rest audacious,</l>
      <l>Whereby they likewise haue so well discharg'd,</l>
      <l>Vpon that hidious Beast incroching thus.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <pb facs="56"/>
And now must I with that poore strength I haue,</l>
      <l>Resist so foule a foe in what I may:</l>
      <l>And arme against obliuion and the graue,</l>
      <l>That els in darknes carries all away,</l>
      <l>And makes of all our honors but a pray.</l>
      <l>So that if by my penne procure I shall</l>
      <l>But to defend mee, and my name to saue,</l>
      <l>Then though I die, I cannot yet die all;</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But still the better part of me will liue,</l>
      <l>Deckt and adorned with thy sacred name,</l>
      <l>Although thy selfe dost farre more glory giue</l>
      <l>Vnto thy selfe, then I can by the same.</l>
      <l>Who doost with thine owne hand a Bulwarke frame</l>
      <l>Against these Monsters, (enemies of honour,)</l>
      <l>VVhich euer-more shall so defend thy Fame,</l>
      <l>That Time nor they, shall neuer pray vpon her.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Those <hi>Hymnes</hi> that thou doost consecrate to heauen,</l>
      <l>Which <hi>Israels</hi> Singer to his God did frame:</l>
      <l>Vnto thy voyce eternitie hath giuen,</l>
      <l>And makes thee deere to him frō whence they came.</l>
      <l>In them must rest thy euer reuerent name,</l>
      <l>So long as <hi>Syons</hi> GOD remaineth honoured;</l>
      <l>And till confusion hath all zeale be-reauen,</l>
      <l>And murthered Fayth, and Temples ruined.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <pb facs="57"/>
By this, (Great Lady,) thou must then be knowne,</l>
      <l>VVhen <hi>Wilton</hi> lyes low loudl'd with the ground:</l>
      <l>And this is that which thou maist call thine owne,</l>
      <l>VVhich sacriligious time cannot confound;</l>
      <l>Heere thou suruiu'st thy selfe, heere thou are found</l>
      <l>Of late succeeding ages, fresh in fame:</l>
      <l>This Monument cannot be ouer-throwne,</l>
      <l>Where, in eternall Brasse remaines thy Name.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>O that the Ocean did not bound our stile</l>
      <l>VVithin these strict and narrow limmits so:</l>
      <l>But that the melody of our sweet Ile,</l>
      <l>Might now be heard to <hi>Tyber, Arne,</hi> and <hi>Po.</hi>
      </l>
      <l>That they might know how far <hi>Thames</hi> doth out-go</l>
      <l>The musique of Declyned Italie:</l>
      <l>And listning to our songs another while,</l>
      <l>Might learne of thee, their notes to purifie.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>O why may not some after-comming hand,</l>
      <l>Vnlock these limits, open our confines:</l>
      <l>And breake a sunder this imprisoning band,</l>
      <l>T'inlarge our spirits, and publish our dissignes;</l>
      <l>Planting our Roses on the <hi>Apenines?</hi>
      </l>
      <l>And teach to <hi>Rhene,</hi> to <hi>Loyre,</hi> and <hi>Rhodanus,</hi>
      </l>
      <l>Our accents, and the wonders of our Land,</l>
      <l>That they might all admire and honour vs.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>
         <pb facs="57"/>
Wherby great SYDNEY &amp; our SPENCER might,</l>
      <l>VVith those <hi>Po-singers</hi> beeing equalled,</l>
      <l>Enchaunt the world with such a sweet delight,</l>
      <l>That theyr eternall songs (for euer read,)</l>
      <l>May shew what great <hi>ELIZAS</hi> raigne hath bred.</l>
      <l>VVhat musique in the kingdome of her peace.</l>
      <l>Hath now beene made to her, and by her might,</l>
      <l>VVhereby her glorious fame shall neuer cease.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But if that Fortune doth deny vs this,</l>
      <l>Then <hi>Neptune,</hi> lock vp with thy Ocean key,</l>
      <l>This treasure to our selues, and let them misse</l>
      <l>Of so sweet ritches: as vnworthy they</l>
      <l>To taste the great delights that we inioy.</l>
      <l>And let our harmony so pleasing growne,</l>
      <l>Content our selues, whose errour euer is,</l>
      <l>Strange notes to like, and disesteeme our owne.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>But, whither doe my vowes transport me now,</l>
      <l>VVithout the compasse of my course inioynd?</l>
      <l>Alas, what honour can a voyce so low</l>
      <l>As this of mine, expect heereby to find?</l>
      <l>But, (Madam,) this doth animate my mind,</l>
      <l>That fauored by the Worthyes of our Land,</l>
      <l>My lynes are lik'd; the which may make me grow,</l>
      <l>In time to take a greater taske in hand.</l>
   </lg>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>