<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Churchyardes admonition to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105093_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18767</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5259</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105093</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Churchyardes admonition to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A warning for the wise, a feare to the fond, a bridle to the lewde, and a glasse to the good : Written of the late earthquake chanced in London and other places, the. 6. of April 1580. for the glorie of God, and benefite of men that warely can walke, and wisely can iudge. Set forth in verse and prose, by Thomas Churchyard Gentleman. Seen and allowed</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ Churchyardes admonition to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Trust (good Reader) that the fresh me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of this late woonder shall make thée to looke backe-warde vnto thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer faultes, and make thée a new man, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> cleannesse of life. For the straunger the things are that our eyes behold, the more the impression of the minde is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly occupied about the vnderstanding of a wonder. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> oftener we sée mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelles, the more is Gods might made manifest, &amp; we the more affrayed to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend. But perhaps, some fine headed fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes will wrest (by naturall argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes) Gods doing and works, to a world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or earthly operation▪ procéeding from a hidden cause in the body and bowels of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earth. As in déede of many other earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes before, hath bene written and throughly disputed: A reason that man
<pb facs="3"/>
maketh, and a matter to be spokē of, but not much to be cōmended. Let such fine wittes search out secretes, and sift what they can from the bottome of their sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. Yet those that feare God, (and féele in their consciences a diuine motion frō the consideration of worldly wonders) will take the Earthquake to be of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde of Nature: And beholding y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> myraculous manner of the same, with open armes, and humble heart, will em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Gods visitation, &amp; worthily wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the messanger he sendeth. Which assuredly cannot come, without his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, nor be séen without his heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will and pleasure. And this is much to be noted: If naturall causes onely compelled such Earthquaks (and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red such tremblings,) then aswell in the wilde fieldes, as in the ciuill Townes, these alterations were often to be foūd. In déede many graue Auctors write, how mightie mountaines haue bene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, &amp; whole Countreys haue bene drowned, by y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> occasion of Earthquaks. But in those kingdomes, the Lorde of al Kinges (for some hidden iudgement to
<pb facs="4"/>
himselfe) bore a greater sway in those causes and places, than any other natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral properties. And though that in many territories &amp; open fieldes (as good bookes make report) Earthquakes haue bene séene, and great hurt hath bene done: yet the harmes that come by Earthquakes in a ciuill towne (where God is honored and taketh care of his people) argues a maruellous mysterie, and perswades a further matter, than weake witted men may meddle withall. For sundry Cities haue soonk, &amp; millions of Houses, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Towres, and walles, haue bene by Earthquake vtterly ouerthrowen. But commonly such wonders are séen, where all the world may be a witnesse of Gods great glory: and mans vnsuretie of life may be thorowly vnderstoode. Now if for all things that sodenly happen, a reason may be made, and naturall argumentes leade mans beléefe from the hope, feare, &amp; confidence in God, then though thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sandes of wonders happened in a day, not one among ten thousād would thinke that God doth any thing at al, but as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural causes do fal out, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>h thing to haue
<pb facs="4"/>
both beginning and their end. God kéepe his chosen from such a conceit of chance, and beléefe of blindnesse. But now to be plaine, no threatning serueth a naughtie seruaunt, No whippe, nor rod, amendeth a loytering scholler, nor no example may reforme a filthie liuer. For whē y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> plague is past, the people fall to pleasure. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as a horse forgets the spurre, &amp; falles to a i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>nbeling pace, immediatly after his gentle remembrance: so man thinkes no longer on a wonder than a dreame, and makes no more accompt of a meruaile, than if a trifle had bene tolde him. Yet my hope is (good Reader) that the wise will be warned, and the well disposed person will be the better, while he liueth, as oft as this late Earthquake shal come to his minde and memorie. For it was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous in the sight of man, &amp; a great thing (no doubt) before the face of the Almightie: to whom be praise and glory for euer.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>