<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To maister Iohn Harlowe his approoued friende.</title>
           <author>Hake, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1574</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105953_Bo1_2_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02480</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12609</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105953</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To maister Iohn Harlowe his approoued friende.</title>
                 <author>Hake, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A touchestone for this time present : expresly declaring such ruines, enormities, and abuses as trouble the Churche of God and our Christian common wealth at this daye. VVherevnto is annexed a perfect rule to be obserued of all parents and scholemaisters, in the trayning vp of their schollers and children in learning. Newly set foorth by E.H</title>
                 <author>Hake, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Williamson, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1574</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>104 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Educational books</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <pb facs="32"/>
   <head>To maister Iohn Harlowe his approoued friende.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the right honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> the Lord chiefe Iustice of the common plees had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto me the othe of an Attourney, thereby admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me into the number of Attourneys in the common place, it vvas persvvaded vnto me by certain good friends of mine, for that the name of an Attourney in the common place is novv a dayes grovven into contempt, vvhether in respect of the multitude of thē, whiche is great besides an huge rable of Pettipractizers, or rather Petifoggers, dispersed into euerye corner of this Realme, or vvhether in respect of their loose and levvde dealinges, vvhich are manifolde, Or vvhether in both those respectes I knovve not: I say, it vvas for this cause per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svvaded vnto me, to dedicate a litle time wholy and altogether to my professed studies of the common Lavves, that I might therby the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enable my selfe to do good in that calling. VVherevpon, resoluing my selfe determinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to follovve that purpose, I thought it conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to seclude from me all those forreine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises
<pb facs="33"/>
vvhich might any vvayes seeme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne, or to be (as it were) <hi>a proposito aliena.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>But (as in those my studies prefixed) being tied vnto solytarinesse in the Countrey, vvhich for my lot, hath hapned vnto me by mariage, after a vvhile I perceiued that, vvanting (as I there did) the benefite of mine accustomed conference, it vvas impossible for me, vvithout some exercise of the minde, to cōtinue, or vvith profite to go forvvarde in the same. In vvhich respect, I contented my selfe (betvvixt vvhiles and for recreation sake) to resort vnto mine accustomed exercise, but so, as (if it might be) some profite might redound therof vnto others.</p>
   <p>And happening by good lucke vpon a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Latine booke intituled, <hi>De pueris sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim ac liberaliter instituendis,</hi> I gathered compendiously out of the same (as not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to allovve my selfe time enough from my said studies, to accomplish the part of a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slatour) such certaine summary documents as might seeme sufficient to frame an orderly and good forme of education: vvhich also I haue turned into English meter and that for these tvvo causes especially: First, for that prose re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth a more exact labour then meeter doth, and could not haue been enterprised vvithout
<pb facs="33"/>
going through the vvhole booke, vvhervnto my small allovvaunce of time (as is aforesayde) coulde not be aunsvverable. Secondly, because meeter vnto the vnlearned (vvhom I heartily vvish to be follovvers of this booke) doth seeme a great deale more pleasaunt then prose, and doth mitigate (as it vvere) the harshnes of the matter.</p>
   <p>VVhich litle booke I do offer vnto you (my approued friend) as a token of my good vvyll, in vvhom, as in my selfe, I do perceiue a special loue not onely vnto this, but also vnto euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good forme of education: as being trained vp (together vvith me your poore scholefellow) vvith the instructions of that learned and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite teacher, Maister <hi>Iohn Hopkins,</hi> that vvorthy Schoolemaister, nay rather, that most vvorthy parent vnto all children committed to his charge of education: Of vvhose memory if J should in such an oportunity as this is, be forgetful, J might iustly be accompted the most vnthankefull person in the vvorld, considering that I haue franckly tasted of his goodnes in this behalfe: that (if it be not vnseemely so to vvishe) vvould to God J had liued at his feete euen dayes and yeres longer then J did. But to returne, in respect onely of good vvyll and
<pb facs="34"/>
loue, I send vnto you these fevv quaiers, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to accept the same in equal part, resor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting indifferentlye vnto the consideration of those common affections of loue, vvhich are vvont rather patiently to beare reproche, that any vvayes to lye hyd and vnknovven vnto the party so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I rest.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>¶Your owne assuredlye</hi> Edvvarde Hake.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>