<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To his Neuew william Busher, Edmond Eluiden wisheth wealth, health, peace, and prosperitie.</title>
           <author>Eluiden, Edmund</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1569</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105487_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21270</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7622</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105487</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To his Neuew william Busher, Edmond Eluiden wisheth wealth, health, peace, and prosperitie.</title>
                 <author>Eluiden, Edmund</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The closet of counsells : conteining the aduice of diuers wyse philosophers, touchinge sundry morall matters, in poesies, preceptes, prouerbes, and parrables, translated, and collected out of diuers aucthors, into Englishe verse: by Edmond Eluiden Gent. Wherunto is anexed a pithy and pleasant discription of the abuses: and vanities of the vvorlde</title>
                 <author>Elviden, Edmund</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1569</date>
                 <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Colwell, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 99, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To his Neuew william Busher, Edmond Eluiden wisheth wealth, health, peace, and prosperitie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing diuersly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and motioned to further my dilygence and trauell as some acquittall for your cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesyes, and yet dispayring of my power (gentle Neuewe) I haue finyshed this indeuour, whych hath seemed to me a meete gift &amp; requisite rewarde, though not in sufficient ability: yet considering your disposition, able inough to satisfie your expectation. And for because I pon dered the obliuion of mortall memory and vngratefulnesse of nature in suche thinges as notwithstandinge be to hys proper commoditie, I haue renewed herein, and haue sette before your eyes such necessary precepts of liuing &amp; rules of wise experience as you haue read and perused before time: to the ende that by more perusing you may print the same in youre heart, that it also may beare
<pb facs="3"/>
fruits in your life, and waying wel you may perceaue that no knowledge is so requisite or needefull as morall philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, which not onely disseuereth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man from beastly brutish kynd, &amp; bewtifies &amp; adornes the sense and rate<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fies the life: but also teacheth &amp; instruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to auoyd inconuenience &amp; mischefe, &amp; leadeth the soule to the fauour of God. Wherfore finding this most meete for you and easyest for me to attayne, I haue ben bolde to offer you this same, as a token of my well wishing: Supposing me not needfull for to craue your pacience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I am assured of your gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlenes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your freend and kinsman
Edmond Eluiden.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>