<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable his very singular good Lord, the Lord Mount-eagle, all that can be wisht in his owne best wishes.</title>
           <author>M., G.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1607</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105308_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20372</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6785</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105308</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honorable his very singular good Lord, the Lord Mount-eagle, all that can be wisht in his owne best wishes.</title>
                 <author>M., G.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Rodomonths infernall, or The Diuell conquered : Ariastos conclusions. Of the marriage of Rogero with Bradamanth his loue, &amp; the fell fought battell betweene Rogero and Rodomonth the neuer-conquered pagan. Written in French by Phillip de Portes, and paraphrastically translated by G.M</title>
                 <author>Desportes, Philippe</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1607</date>
                 <publisher>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>60 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honorable his very singular good Lord, the Lord <hi>Mount-eagle,</hi> all that can be wisht in his owne best wishes.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing more vsually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in this last part of this worst age (most Honorable, and vertuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Honorable Lord) then the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Bookes, how-euer their genealogies spring euen from the lightest vanities: amongst whom, (to saue the World and Bitternesse a labour) I condemne my selfe, as an Author and Abettor of that customary error, onely with this halfe-part excuse, that albe in my writings I haue neither Feminine honie, nor Masculine gall, yet I either doe, or desire to retaine a tast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full rellish of a little saltnesse; which, may it ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie but the least imagined season in your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sence, I shall slieghtly respect the curiositie of any other, how-euer his stomacke be estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for best iudgement. The Noble French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Mounsieur Portes,</hi> who was the first Author of this worke, was a man of great wit, famous learning, and Noble place; each of which cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="3"/>
in them, defence sufficient to shield him from imputation: so that questionlesse, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the worke must needs be faire, and onely the deformitie in his English apparell: and no wonder, for I protest the Translation was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht, and forth of my hands aboue a dozen yeares agone, a time wherein bumbasted bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and straite whale-bon'd dublets had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vse nor estimation. How-euer, all mine es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capes, both boldnesse in daring to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, rudenesse in the worke, &amp; wants in mine Arts perfection, must flie vnder the couert of your Noble Patronage; a defence, that giuing my Muse an immortall life, shall binde my loue and seruice to you, and your Honorable house for euer.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honors humbly deuoted, <hi>G. M.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>