<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Francis de Sousa Tauares vnto the
high and mightie Prince Don
IOHN Duke of
Aueiro.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105675_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01426</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11543</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105675</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Francis de Sousa Tauares vnto the
high and mightie Prince Don
IOHN Duke of
Aueiro.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The discoueries of the world from their first originall vnto the yeere of our Lord 1555. Briefly written in the Portugall tongue by Antonie Galvano, gouernour of Ternate, the chiefe island of the Malucos: corrected, quoted, and now published in English by Richard Hakluyt, sometimes student of Christ church in Oxford</title>
                 <author>Galvão, António</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 <publisher>Bishop, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Eliot’s Court Press</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 97, 3 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="introductory_letter">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>Francis de Sousa Tauares vnto the
high and mightie Prince Don
IOHN Duke of
Aueiro.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ntonie Galuano</hi> vpon his death bed
left vnto me in his testament among
his papers this booke. And because
I am certaine he ordained it to bee
presented vnto your Grace, I haue
thought good herein to fulfill his wil
&amp; testament, though in other things
I haue done nothing, the fault remaining not in me. And
by all reason this treatie ought to be set foorth by a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall,
seeing it intreateth of the variable waies from
whence the pepper and spices came in times past into
our partes, and also of all the nauigations and discoueries
in the old time: In both of which things the Portugals
haue most trauailed. In this treatie and in nine or ten
bookes of things touching Maluco and India (which the
Cardinall willed me to giue to <hi>Damian de Goes,</hi> saying
that he should content me, for otherwise I could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer
them) this true Portugall occupied himselfe against
the vnfortunate and sorrow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ull times which he had been
in (which were all ended before all our daies and times:)<note place="margin">Antonie Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uano Captaine of Maluco.</note>
for when he receiued the captainship and fortresses of
Maluco, all the kings and gouernours of all the Ilands
about being agreed to make war against the Portugals,
vntill such time as they might driue them all out of the
countrey, he fought against them all▪ with onely 130. Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugals,
when they were all together, and strong in Tidore;
and he gaue them the ouerthrow and killed their king, and
one <hi>
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ernate,</hi> the principal author of that war, and he tooke
<pb facs="6"/>
from them their fortresse: so vpon this victorie they sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
themselues, and came vnder the obeisance and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice
of our king of Portugall. Herein two things happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
of great admiration▪ The first, that all the kings and
gouernours of Maluco agreed togither against vs, a thing
that neuer fell out, nor yet credible to be like to happen:
for they are euer at variance among themselues:<note place="margin">Variance vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally amon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> the kings of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luco.</note> The se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,
that the captaine of Maluco with onely his ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
soldiers should haue the victorie against so many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
all together. For sometimes it happeneth that some
of the captaines of Maluco with many extraordinarie
soldiers besides their ordinarie, yea and with the aide of
al the Kings and Lords of Maluco in their fauour and aide
went against one King onely of them, and came backe
againe with losse. So there may be reckoned three notable
things done in India, I say of qualitie: (but of more quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and importance there haue been others:) which were
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the taking of Muar by <hi>Emmanuel Falcon,</hi> and the winning
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of Bitam by <hi>Peter Mascarenas,</hi> and this, whereof we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently
treate. For all these three deedes seemed to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible
to be atchieued, considering the small quantitie
of soldiers which the captaines had in giuing the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise
against so many; with the order and maner by them
ordained how and which waies to obtaine their purpose
as well by their enimies as by themselues. And they could
not be atchieued otherwise but by vsing a meane and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
not thought of at the first by the Portugals, nor yet
euer suspected by their enimies. And, besides this, his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
and fower of his brethren were all slaine in the kings
seruice: And he now being the last of his linage, caried
with him into Maluco woorth ten thousand crusadoes,
which he spent not in idlenes, nor yet in play, but onely in
bringing of many kings and innumerable townes vnto
our holy faith, and in the preseruing of Maluco, employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
all his power and strength that all the cloues might
<pb facs="6"/>
come vnto the hands of the kings highnes: which with
Maluco yeelded vnto him euery yeere fiue hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand
crusadoes; being all to his great preiudice, let, and
hinderance. For if he had gathered cloues for himselfe,
as the captaines of Maluco haue done and doe, then he
had come home very rich. But when he came home into
Portugall in great hope (such is the simplicitie of the
best natures) to be rewarded for his good seruice,<note place="margin">Good seruice full ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded.</note> and to
be more fauoured and honored, then if he had brought
home with him an hundred thousand crusadoes, he was
greatly deceiued. For he found neither fauour, nor yet ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,
but onely among the poore and miserable, to wit, in
an hospitall: where he was kept seuenteene yeeres vntill
the hower of his death; and there he had allowed vnto
him his winding sheete to burie him in: and the brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
of the Couent prepared for his buriall as for a
poore courtier cast off by all men, leauing himselfe indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in two thousand crusadoes, whereof part came out of
India, and part thereof many of his friends had lent him
to maintaine him in the hospitall: for in all these seuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene
yeeres he had not of his highnes for to helpe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe
with so much as one riall of plate, nor yet I of the
bookes which I deliuered receiued any thing to discharge
his will with. Yet for all this, euen as vpon the prosperitie
of his victories he neuer made any boast, so likewise in his
aduersities his great stomacke did nothing abate his hart.
As there are good proofes that with so many and so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall
disgraces as he suffered, he neuer vnto the hower
of his death left off to raise and to augment the yeerely
rent vnto a Counto:<note place="margin">A Counto is 50000. cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadoes.</note> which some made strange and would
not giue eare vnto: So that euen as he was extreme pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
in the performance of his seruice, so he was the like
in the things sounding vnto the perfecting of the same,
which was the cause that he was brought vnto the state
that he died in. For he could not see the qualitie of the
<pb facs="7"/>
time, but onely those of his great seruice, by reason of the
great charges that it stood him in. And his saying was,
That he was borne, not for to say that his constellation
was in the wars victorious, but in the ouercomming of
kings by the arte of warfare, readines in resoluing, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
in conseruing, and great loialtie and patience with
many seruices vnto his king and master. In which of all
these he had most contentation it cannot easily be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.
Wherefore your noble Grace may see, that this
treatie and the others were made with sighes and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
which his inferiour will might haue raised vp in him
against his superiour reason. Neither was he willing to
take for his remedie that which that great Turke <hi>Zelim</hi>
sonne to the great <hi>Mahumet</hi> did, (for he tooke Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople
and died in Rome) who vsed to make himselfe
drunke, because he would not remember the great estate
which he lost: nor yet woulde he giue eare vnto those
things which many of his friends would tell him, wishing
he would settle his mind out of the kingdome: (for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
he should neuer be able to liue:) whereunto he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered,
that in this point he would rather be compared
vnto the great <hi>Timocles</hi> the Athenian,<note place="margin">Or rather The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mistocles.</note> then to be like the
excellent Romane <hi>Coriolanus.</hi> Which is a goodly exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of a true and faithfull Portugall. (Though it were not
so as I doe say, yet I doe heare, that the hospitals be full of
the most faithfull subiects to their prince and countrey.)
Wherefore by all reason this treatie ought to be of your
Grace fauoured, setting apart all ouersights, if there be
any, in this worke, of the author: I being not able to
attaine vnto the vnderstanding of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.
God prosper your Grace with
long life and increase of
honour.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>