<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the very Worthy Gentleman, Sir Iohn Hamden Knight.</title>
           <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1606</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105254_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20072</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6514</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105254</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the very Worthy Gentleman, Sir Iohn Hamden Knight.</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Nevves from hell : brought by the Diuells carrier. Tho: Dekker</title>
                 <author>Dekker, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Ferbrand (Firebrand, Forbrand), William</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1606</date>
                 <publisher>Blower (Blore), Ralph.</publisher>
                            <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Simmes (Sims, Symmes), Valentine.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stafford, Simon.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>62 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the very Worthy Gentleman, Sir Iohn Hamden Knight.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, the begetting of Bookes, is as common as the begetting of Children: onely heerein they differ, that Bookes speake so soone as they come into the world, and giue the best wordes they cā to al men, yet are they driuen to seek abroad for a father. That hard fortune followes al &amp; fals in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, vpō THIS of mine. It gladly coms to you vpō that errand, and if you vouchsafe to receiue it lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly, I shall account my selfe and It, very happie. Theise Paper-monsters are sure to beset vppon, by many terrible encounters; They had neede there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to get Armour of proofe that may not shrinke for a bullet; The strongest shieldes that I know for such fights, are good Patrons; from whom writers claime such antient priuiledges, that how-soeuer they finde entertainment, they make bold to take
<pb facs="3"/>
acquaintance of them (though neuer so meerely strangers) without blushing: wherein they are like to courtiers, that inuite thēselus, vnbidden) to other mens tables &amp; that's a most Gentleman-like, quality and yet holde it a disgrace, if they receiue not a complementall welcome. Custome making that shew handsomly, which (if the curious hande of Formality, should apparell) would appeare vile Fashion thereforeis the best Painter, for what pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures soeuer she draws, are workman-ly done: pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming vpon whose warrant, I send vnto you the discouery of a strange country, If it were of both Indyes, my loue could bestow it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you. Accept it therefore, and if here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after I may be a voyager to any happyer coast, the Fruits of (that as now of this) shallbe most affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately consecrated to you.</p>
   <p>From him that wishes he could be a deseruer of you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Tho. Dekker</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>