<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the vertuously No∣ble, and rightly honoured Lady, the Countesse of Sussex.</title>
           <author>K., T.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105698_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01500</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11622</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105698</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the vertuously No∣ble, and rightly honoured Lady, the Countesse of Sussex.</title>
                 <author>K., T.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Cornelia</title>
                 <author>Garnier, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Roberts (Robarts), James</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 <distributor>Busby, John 1</distributor>
                            <distributor>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</distributor>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>96 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Drama</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the vertuously No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and rightly honoured Lady, the <hi>Countesse of Sussex.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing no leysure (most noble Lady) but such as euermore is traueld with th'afflictions of the minde, then which the world affoords no greater misery, it may bee wondred at by some, how I durst vndertake a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this moment: which both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth cunning, rest and oportunity; but chiefely, that I would attempt the dedication of so rough vnpollished a worke, to the suruey of your so worthy selfe.</p>
   <p>But beeing well instructed in your noble and hercick dispositions, and perfectly assur'd of your honourable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours past, (though neyther making needles glozes of the one, nor spoyling paper with the others Pharisaical embro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derie,) I have persum'd vpon your true conceit and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement of these small endeuours, that thus I purposed to make known, my memory of you and them to be immortall.</p>
   <p>A fitter present for a Patronesse so well accomplished, I could not finde, then this faire president of honour, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie,
<pb facs="3"/>
and loue. VVherein, what grace that excellent <hi>GARNIER</hi> hath lost by my defaulte, I shall beseech your Honour to repaire, with the regarde of those so bitter times, and priuie broken passions that I endured in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it.</p>
   <p>And so vouchsafing but the passing of a VVinters weeke with desolate <hi>Cornelia,</hi> I will assure your Ladiship my next Sommers better trauell, with the Tragedy of <hi>Portia.</hi> And euer spend one howre of the day in some kind seruice to your Honour, and another of the night in wishing you all happines. Perpetually thus deuoting my poore selfe</p>
   <signed>Your Honors in all humblenes. <hi>T. K.</hi>
   </signed>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>