<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>❧ To the aduersaries of the grace of God in the Tower of
London or els where: I Iohn Keltridge wishe amendment of life, conuersion
to the moste aun∣cient and vndoubted faith, with true repentaunce and
contrition of hart, That they may become liuely and perfect members of Iesus
Christe.</title>
           <author>Keltridge, John</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105451_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A04790</idno>
           <idno type="STC">14921</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105451</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>❧ To the aduersaries of the grace of God in the Tower of
London or els where: I Iohn Keltridge wishe amendment of life, conuersion
to the moste aun∣cient and vndoubted faith, with true repentaunce and
contrition of hart, That they may become liuely and perfect members of Iesus
Christe.</title>
                 <author>Keltridge, John</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Two godlie and learned sermons : appointed, and preached, before the Jesuites, seminaries, and other aduersaries to the gospell of Christ in the Tower of London. In which, were confuted to their faces, the moste principall and cheefe poincts of their Romish and vvhoarish religion: and all such articles as they defend, contrarie to the woord of Cod [sic], vvere layed open and ripped vp vnto them. In Maye. 7 and 21. Anno. 1581. By Iohn Keltridge, preacher of the vvorde of God, in London</title>
                 <author>Keltridge, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>136 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>❧ To the aduersaries of the grace of God in the Tower of
London or els where: I Iohn Keltridge wishe amendment of life, conuersion
to the moste aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and vndoubted faith, with true repentaunce and
contrition of hart, That they may become liuely and perfect members of Iesus
Christe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit the rare &amp; strange com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of you into England, hath
kindled the harts of many men against you, &amp; so them see on fire: as
it is very apparāt, that the flāerher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is not like to be extinguished,
till either the godly people see your conuersion from your heresies: or
con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue some hope that you will return to God speedily. Yet we for our
partes, that haue endeuored by preaching to bring you to the Lord, may not,
&amp; cannot cease continually, either to pray with earnestnes, or desire
with stedfastnes, or begge with feruentnes, or intreat in all faithfulnes
at the handes of the Lord: that he would lighten you by his spirit, or
quicken you thorow his grace, or resolue you by the trueth, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme you
by the woord which you dayly heare: that the on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly true and perfect man Iesus
Christe maye be knowen unto you: which knowledge and perfect vnderstanding
you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ignorant of, if you shut not your eyes, or withdrawe your
harts from the hearing of the same. What you haue been hitherto we know, but
what heerafter you shal be, that the Lord our GOD knoweth, not we. We may
hope very hardly, for you refuse the trueth willingly, your conuersiō
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> we not looke for speedily, you perseuere in your errours so
stouely: So that for that matter we deforre and commit all to to the Lord.
Notwithstanding, for myne owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> some thing to say vnto you, &amp;
for your owne behalfe I haue much to charge you with: For my selfe, wheras I
haue bothe spoken heertofore, and doo now also write: I haue to lead me
therunto these causes. First, my office and calling draweth me, as beeing
a Dispensar of the woord of God: Secondly my dutie, which is to winne all,
but especially you which are so<pb facs="10"/>farre off: Thirdly, that
care which beyond measure I haue had, is a prick and a spurre within me,
since the firste time I was with you at the Tower: And which should
prouoke me, I haue a commaundement giuen me from the eternall God, to preach in
season and out of season, in time and out of time, whersoeuer I see
the Church to stand in need. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I beeing espetially mooued aboue
the rest: you haue no farther to enquire after me. As concerning the thinges
I am to charge you withall: they are many, great, importable, and such as you
can neuer answere: They concerne the Lord the high God, whose lawes you
contemne: They concerne the Church, from which you are fled: They concerne the
trueth, which you denye: They concerne Religion, which you ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre: They
concerne Christianitie, which you are farre from: They concerne true
Woorship, which you repose in your Image<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>: They concerne Faith, which you
lay in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>s: They concerne perfecte and Christian adoration, this you
claspe vp in the bosome of the Pope: They cōcerne pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, which in
steed of God you giue to men: They concerne Christe whose institutions
you chaunge: They concerne the perfect seruice of the Lord, which you infolde
in the Masse: They concerne our Meditation, which you make but a
sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: Propitiatorie, by the woork of a Preest: They concerne our
attonement and reconciler Christe, and him whome the heauens containeth, you
infolde in a Wafer cake: They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Gospell, which you refuse,
&amp; you stick to the cust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes of your fathers: And they concerne the
woord of the Lord, which you heare not, but compelled: which you slaun der
beeing hardened, which you contemne beeing blinded, and which you spurn &amp;
throwe away, euen before our faces to our great greef and your confusion if
you repent not. All these &amp; many things more I am to charge you with,
hauing this purpose in my selfe: That first you are to be loked vnto, and
if that you will not turne vnto the Lord our God, and serue him after the
manner that we his People <hi>Israell</hi> doo: either we must shut you
out of the Tents and dwelling pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the inheritaunce of our God: or we
must finde some way to pacifye the Lord withall.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>For I am certainly perswaded, that you haue been
kept ouer long, you and your fellowe <hi>Ammonites,</hi> yea these twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
yeares haue you been pricks and thornes in our sides, &amp; now you come out
of your holes wherin younestled, resist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing openly the hoste of the
Lord vnto their faces. But this may not be suffered: least your example of
gathering sud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> vpon the Sabaoth day, be an occasion also that others
shall violate and break the commaundements of God.</p>
   <p>I warne you therfore in time, and these Sermons of myne which I
made vnto you, haue I gathered together in a little volume, that you may read
them: They contayne in them, a breefe and short confutation of all such
Heresies as you doo holde. With this speech (if you be not contented) I wil
then call back and reclaime it when as I perceiue and see thorow ly, that you
are amended.</p>
   <p>More I cannot say, more I may not say, and more I dare not
say as yet to you: whom not I, but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Christian harts doo thinke to be
instruments of Satan, raysed vp for our sinnes, as two edged Swoordes to
rent and out in peeces, the poore Church of England. For mine owne parce, I wil
pray to the Lord our God for your amendement, and I will begge that
Discipline at his hands, which you if you come not to him, are woorthie to
haue: To whom I doo commit you, that hath both life and death, faluation and
condemnation in his handes.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in the Lord, if you come vnto the Lord.
<hi>Iohn Keltridge.</hi>
      </signed>
      <dateline>At London, 
<date>Iune. 10. 1581.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>