<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ Maister Rothorigo to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1579</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105055_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09829</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20092</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105055</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ Maister Rothorigo to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The most noble and famous trauels of Marcus Paulus, one of the nobilitie of the state of Venice, into the east partes of the world, as Armenia, Persia, Arabia, Tartary, with many other kingdoms and prouinces. No lesse pleasant, than profitable, as appeareth by the table, or contents of this booke. Most necessary for all sortes of persons, and especially tor trauellers. Translated into English</title>
                 <author>Polo, Marco</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery (Nuberie), Ralph</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1579</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>28, 167, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>¶ Maister Rothorigo to the Reader.</head>
   <head>¶ An Introduction into Cosmographie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Icause many be desirous of the knowledge of the partes of the worlde, what names they haue, and in what places they be, and that many and sundry times the holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth make mention, and also it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for suche as doe traffique and trade to haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I was moued to giue notice to all suche as are desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous or haue pleasure in reading.</p>
   <p>You shall vnderstande, that a man turning his face to the rising of the Sunne, that parte that is before hys eies where the Sunne doth rise, is called Orient or Easte, and his contrarie where the Sunne setteth, is Occident or Weast. The course or waye of the Sunne is called <hi>Media die,</hi> or South, whiche is on youre righte hande, his contrarie parte that is on the lefte hande is called <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentrion</hi> or North.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, you shall vnderstand, that if a manne stande in the Ilande of <hi>Cales,</hi> and looke towardes the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of the Sunne, he shall sée thrée principall parts of the worlde▪ diuided by the Sea called <hi>Mediterraneum,</hi> that cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth on<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e of the greate Occean and Weaste Sea, and runneth towardes the Easte, and by two very great and principall riuers, the one comming from the South, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Nilus,</hi> and the other from the North, called <hi>Taenais.</hi>
   </p>
   <div type="region">
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <head>Affrica</head>
      <p>YOu shall also vnderstande, that from the entring of the straite called <hi>Iuberaltare,</hi> vppon the right hande to the riuer <hi>Nilus</hi> bordering vppon <hi>Egipt,</hi> is called <hi>Affrica,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Sea that is towardes vs, is called <hi>Libya,</hi> that whiche is towardes the South, is called <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> whiche is the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, the Sea towardes the Weaste, is called <hi>Atlantica,</hi> and is also the greate Occean Sea. It hath these famous Cities and Prouinces. Ouer againste <hi>Iuberaltar,</hi> and the coaste of <hi>Mallaga</hi> is <hi>Mauritania,</hi> whiche we call <hi>Barbarie.</hi> It is named <hi>Barbaria,</hi> bycause the people be barbarous, not onely in language, but in manners and customes. Follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing towards the East is <hi>Numidia, Getulia, Tunes,</hi> a citie in <hi>Affrica,</hi> the name so giuen by <hi>Asu,</hi> to all <hi>Syria,</hi> and <hi>Aegipt.</hi> On the South parte be the <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> whiche hereafter shall be spoken of.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="region">
      <head>Europa</head>
      <p>
         <hi>EVropa</hi> is called al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> prouinces against <hi>Affrica</hi> towards the North from the greate Occean Sea, that entreth into the streits to the riuer <hi>Tanai,</hi> and the greate lake cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Meotis,</hi> where this riuer entreth into. In this there is comprehēded <hi>Portugale, Britania, Spaine, France, Almaine, Italie, Grecia, Polonia, Hungarie,</hi> or <hi>Panonia, Valachia, Asia</hi> the lesser, <hi>Phrygia, Turkia, Galatia, Lydia, Pamphilia, Lauria, Lycia, Cilicia, Scythia</hi> the lower, <hi>Dacia, Gocia</hi> and <hi>Thrasia.</hi>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="region">
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <head>Asia</head>
      <p>
         <hi>ASia</hi> the greater is tha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> that is beyond <hi>Europa</hi> and <hi>Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> that is to say, on the other side o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <hi>Nilus</hi> Southward, and the riuer <hi>Tanais</hi> Northward, following the way East<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and is as bigge as <hi>Europa</hi> and <hi>Affrica,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed with thrée Seas, Easterly or Orientall, <hi>Indico</hi> to the Southwarde, <hi>Scythia</hi> to the Northwarde, hauing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, <hi>Soria, Mesopotamia, Parthia, Sarmasia, Asiatica, Arabia, Persia, Armenia, Medea, Hircania, Carmania,</hi> the <hi>Indias</hi> on thys side and beyonde the riuer <hi>Ganges.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Also you shall vnderstande, that the greate Sea called the Occean, doth compasse aboute the foresaid thrée prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall partes of the worlde, and so doeth compasse all the whole worlde, althoughe there be diuers regions and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whereas they be, hauing diuers names.</p>
      <p>Moreouer, you shall vnderstande, that in whatsoeuer parts of the Sea that doe answere to any parts of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Countries, as there be many Ilands inhabited with diuers people, aswel as the East parts, whereas is <hi>Tapro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane</hi> and <hi>Thyle,</hi> and others infinite number on theyr sides, aswel as on the other parts before declared, and those that be betwéene them and al others, are to be vnderstanded to pertain to one of these thrée parts of the world beforesaid, to whiche it may be moste properly iudged to be, and lyeth nearest vnto.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="region">
      <head>Ethiopia</head>
      <p>MOreouer, you muste note, that <hi>Ethiopia</hi> is a common name to manye Prouinces and Countries, inhabited with blacke people called <hi>Negros.</hi> And to begin with the
<pb facs="5"/>
moste Weaste partes, the firste is <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap>, that is to saye, from <hi>Cab<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Verde</hi> or the gréene Cape, and following the co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st of the Sea, to the mouth or streite of the Redde Sea. Al those prouinces be called <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> and of these <hi>Ethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opians</hi> from <hi>Ginney</hi> vnto <hi>Cas<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap> Mansa,</hi> that is to saye, the Kings pallace, they be of the sect of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the most parte of them. And the chiefest and most prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall of these people be the <hi>Iolofos</hi> and <hi>Mandingos,</hi> and be moste parte vnder the gouernement of a King called <hi>Mandimansa,</hi> for <hi>Mansa</hi> is as muche to saye as Senior or Lord, and <hi>Mandy Mandinga,</hi> so by this his title he is Lord <hi>Mandinga.</hi> This King is blacke, and his abiding is in the prouince of <hi>Sertano</hi> four hundred leagues within the land, in a Citie compassed about with a wall called <hi>Iaga,</hi> which is riche of golde and siluer, and of all suche merchaundize as is occupied in <hi>Adem</hi> and in <hi>Meca:</hi> and from thence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the <hi>Ethiopians</hi> be Idolators to the cape called <hi>Buo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Esperanca,</hi> and there turneth againe to the sect of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi> Beyonde these prouinces following vp into the land of <hi>Sartan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>
         </hi> bée greate and highe mountaines or hilles, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led mountaines of the Moone, the toppes of them be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes couered with Snow, &amp; at the foote of thē springeth the riuer <hi>Nilus,</hi> and this Countrie is called <hi>Ethiopia</hi> beside <hi>Eg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>pt,</hi> and in <hi>Arabia</hi> it is called <hi>Abas,</hi> and the inhabitants <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>ssm<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>s,</hi> and be Christians, and doe vse to be marked with an yron in the face: they be not baptized with fire (as some doe saye) but as we are, but they be <hi>Heretikes, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobites.</hi> and <hi>Hebeyonites.</hi> They do holde on the olde lawe with the newe, and be circumcised, and doe kéepe the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth daye, and doe eate no Po<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ke, and some of them doe take manye wiues, and be also baptized, and doe saye, that their King came and descended of King <hi>Salomon,</hi> and of the Quéene <hi>Saba,</hi> and this King hathe continuall warres with the <hi>Moores.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>
         <pb facs="5"/>There is another <hi>Ethiopia</hi> called <hi>Asiatica interior,</hi> which the <hi>Arabians</hi> call <hi>Zenium,</hi> and these doe extende from the sayd hilles of the Moone,<note place="margin">
            <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lus.</hi>
         </note> and of <hi>Nilus,</hi> to the borders of <hi>Barbarie.</hi> And the saying is, that among all Riuers, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>Nilus</hi> entereth into two Seas, that is to saye, one braunche into the East Sea, and another braunche into the West Sea. All these <hi>Ethiopians</hi> bée <hi>Moores,</hi> and theyr laboure and occupation, is digging of golde out of the grounde, where they doe fynde great plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. There is also another <hi>Ethiopia</hi> called <hi>Tragodytica,</hi> and thys dothe reache or extende from the foresayde <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> to the streyte or mouth of the redde Sea,<note place="margin">The redde Sea.</note> and these bée somewhat whyter, and the King and people bée <hi>Moores,</hi> and came out of <hi>Arabia foelix,</hi> for the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians</hi> came ouer the streyte of the redde Sea, and gotte that Countrey of the <hi>Iacobites</hi> by force, and at this daye there is robbing and stealing among them secretely, for the King of the <hi>Iacobites</hi> is of so greate power, that the Souldan of <hi>Babilon</hi> doth giue him tribute.<note place="margin">Souldan.</note>
      </p>
   </div>
   <div type="region">
      <head>Arabia</head>
      <p>THat whiche wée doe call <hi>Arabia,</hi> the <hi>Arabians</hi> doe call <hi>Arab,</hi> and is called <hi>Gesyrdelaab.</hi> That whyche is betwéene the redde Sea, and <hi>Sinus Perficus,</hi> is called the Iland of <hi>Arabia,</hi> and thys is called <hi>Arabia Foelix,</hi> by reason of the Incense that groweth there.<note place="margin">Arabia Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix.</note>
      </p>
      <p>There bée other two <hi>Arabias</hi> besyde thys, the one of them extendyng from the Mount Sinay, to the dead Sea, where the Children of <hi>Israell</hi> wente fortye yeares, and thys is called <hi>Arabia petrea,</hi> takyng that name of a Citie that is there. The other dothe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende betwéene <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Euphrates</hi> towardes the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Lep<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>,</hi> and thys they doe call <hi>Arabia desan,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Alepo.</note>
         <pb facs="6"/>
which is as muche to say, as of <hi>Siria,</hi> and our Latines doe call it <hi>Arabia deserta.</hi> And wheras the vulgar people, and men for the most part, do thinke that <hi>Antilla,</hi> or those I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes lately found out by commaundemente of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike King <hi>Don Fernando,</hi> and Lady <hi>Isabell</hi> Quéene, be in the <hi>Indias,</hi> they be deceyued therein, to call it by the name of the <hi>Indias.</hi> And for bycause that in <hi>Spaniola,</hi> or newe <hi>Spayne,</hi> they do find gold, some doe not let to say it is <hi>Tharsis,</hi> and <hi>Ophin,</hi> and <hi>Sethin,</hi> from whence in the time of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
         <note place="margin">Erronious iudgements of the voya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi>
         </note> they brought gold to <hi>Hierusalem.</hi> And thus aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting erroures vpon erroures, let not to saye, that the Prophetes when they sayde that the name of oure Lorde God should be pronounced to people that haue not hearde of it, and in places and Countreys very farre off, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, which is sayd to be vnderstanded by those that be called <hi>Indians,</hi> and by these Ilandes, and furthermore doe not let to say to this day, that it is to be vnderstanded by the places mentioned in the holy Scripture, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike doctors, and that this secret God hath kept hidden all this time, and by finding out these Ilands did reueale it. I séeing how they are deceyued in their vayne inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and greate simplicitie, for zeale and good will of the truth, and to kill this canker, that it créepe no more nor ingender greater erroures, will giue light to this errour, answering to the said muttering talkers, according as to euery of them doth require.</p>
      <p>And first you shall vnderstande, that this name <hi>India,</hi> according to all Cosmographers, as well Christians as Infidels, of old time, and of later yeares, the name dothe come of a Riuer named <hi>Hynde,</hi> or <hi>Hyndo,</hi> that going to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the East, is the beginning of the <hi>Indias,</hi> whiche bée thrée in number,<note place="margin">Three In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias, the first is the lower India.</note> that is to say, the first is called the lower or nether <hi>India,</hi> the seconde is called the middle <hi>India,</hi> and the third is called the high or vpper <hi>India.</hi> The first or lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer <hi>India</hi> is renamed <hi>Caysar,</hi> and these do extend towards
<pb facs="6"/>
the East, from the Riuer <hi>India,</hi> vnto a Porte or Hauen on the Sea side, of great traffike and trade, called <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baya.</hi> And the King of this <hi>India,</hi> and also the most part of the people be <hi>Moores,</hi> and the rest Idolaters. The second or middle <hi>India</hi> is surnamed <hi>Mynbar,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <p>The second or middle India.</p>
            <p>Lading of Spices.</p>
         </note> and dothe reache to the borders of <hi>Colchico,</hi> and this hath very faire Hauens, and Portes of greate traffike, where they doe lade Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Ginger, and other Spices and Drugges. The Portes or Hauens be called <hi>Colocud, Coulen, Hely, Faten<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>r, Colnugur,</hi> and héere be many Christians Heretikes Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storians, and many <hi>Indians,</hi> although towards the North they be Idolaters. The thirde <hi>India,</hi> whiche is the hygh <hi>India,</hi> is surnamed <hi>Mahabar,</hi> and dothe extend vnto <hi>Cauch,</hi>
         <note place="margin">
            <p>The third India called the higher India.</p>
            <p>An Oxe worshipped.</p>
         </note> whiche is the Riuer <hi>Gange.</hi> Héere groweth plentye of Sinamon, and Pearle. The King and people of thys Countrey worship the Oxe. Besides these thrée <hi>Indias,</hi> whiche lye towardes the rising of the Sunne, there can not be found neyther Author nor Man that hathe trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the firme land, neyther the Seas adioyning there vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that can say, there is anye other Prouince or Ilande named <hi>India,</hi> sauing that if anye woulde giue to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that going towarde the West, he wente towardes the East, and that although he came vnto the terrenall Paradise, and that these Ilands shoulde lye in the greate Weast Occean Seas, it appeareth playnely, for that those that sayle thither, steame their Shippe towards the Occident, and his direct wind whiche he sayleth withall, is out of the Orient or the East. So it appeareth, that they sayle not vnto the <hi>India,</hi> but that they flye and depart from the <hi>India.</hi> And thus it appeareth that he would say, that the firste name that euer it hadde, or was sette, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it <hi>Antillya,</hi> seeming, that by the corruption of the vulgar, naming it <hi>Ante India,</hi> as to say against <hi>India,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as Antechrist is contrary or against Christ, or Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>north againste the North. And thus it appeareth, that it
<pb facs="7"/>
can not be named <hi>India,</hi> but to vnderstande it as an ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrase, cleane contrary, as a <hi>Negro,</hi> or a blacke <hi>Moore</hi> shoulde be named white <hi>Iohn,</hi> or a Negresse or blacke woman, to be named a Pearle, or a <hi>Margarita,</hi> that for finding gold in the Iland named <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>spaniola,</hi> it should haue the name set <hi>Tharsia,</hi> or <hi>Ophin,</hi> or <hi>Sethin,</hi> nor beléeue it standeth in <hi>Asia</hi> as some woulde saye, although the thyng is so cléere, that it séemeth a mockerie to proue it: but reason dothe leade, that wée shoulde gyue Mylke vnto Children and Infantes. <hi>Saincte Austine</hi> declareth, that the circumstance of the letter dothe il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate the sentence. And it appeareth in the thyrde Booke of Kings, in the tenth Chapter, and the second of Paralipomenon, in the ninth Chapter, do saye, that the Seruantes of <hi>Salomon,</hi> and of <hi>Diran,</hi> doe fynde they broughte from <hi>Ophin</hi> and <hi>Sethin,</hi> and <hi>Tharsis,</hi> not onely golde, but also Siluer and Timber, called <hi>Thina,</hi> and Elephantes téeth, and Peacocks, and Apes, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious stones, the whyche thyngs in infinite places of the very true <hi>Indians,</hi> as well in Countreys farre with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the lande, as also in Countreys vppon the Sea syde, and also in Ilandes wythout number, that bée in the Oriente or East Seas, shall be founde, as by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the Merchantes traffiking into the East, conforming to the holy Scripture, and to all those that doe write, as well Catholikes, as Prophanes, is many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest. And in the Ilande called <hi>Spaniola,</hi> there can bée found no suche Timber, nor all the other thyngs before named, sauyng Golde, the whiche as by this worke wyll appeare, is founde in a greate number of places of the Orientall partes. What is hée that in bringing gold from <hi>Antilla,</hi> will proue it is from <hi>Ophin,</hi> or <hi>Sethin,</hi> or <hi>Tharsis,</hi> from whence it was brought to <hi>Salomon.</hi> First hée must prooue that it was neuer founde but in one place, and that at thys daye it is not to bée had, but in
<pb facs="7"/>
the same place only, from whence it was broughte to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> the which is a manifest vntruth or false. And also they that vnderstande that the storie of the holy scripture, and the holy prophets, when they do now name countries from whence those things be brought, and farre Ilandes of Idolatours, wheeeas the name of God was not h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ard, did not speak but of <hi>Spaniola,</hi> and of the other West parts, he must proue there is no other Idolatours in the worlde but those whom he falsely calleth <hi>Indians,</hi> nor other Ilāds but the <hi>Spaniola,</hi> and the other West Ilandes, and thys is of a truth, all false, for <hi>Grecia</hi> is Ilandes, <hi>Scicilia,</hi> a noble I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and <hi>Malta,</hi> and <hi>Lipari, Yzcla, Serdenya, Corsica, Mallorca, Minorca, Ybisa, Canarias, England,</hi> and others infinite in the foure partes of the world, before now hath bin founde Of the whiche in the Orient or east, is <hi>Taprobano,</hi> which is the most noble Iland in the world, and the Ile which is sayde to be so happie and fortunate, that of neuer trée there fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a leafe of in the whole yeare, as also by thys Booke of <hi>Marcus Paulus</hi> is to be séene in the <hi>106.</hi> Chapter, of one Ilande that is in the Orientall seas <hi>.1500.</hi> myles, in the which there is found gold in so great abundaunce, that it is sayde the Kinges Pallace is couered or tyied wyth gold.</p>
      <p>And furthermore, it is sayd, that the fame is, that in those seas be seauen thousand four hundred fortie eight Ilandes, in the whiche there is not founde one trée, but that is swéete, pleasaunt, and fruiteful, and of great profit, wherby we may wel conclud, that in many other Ilands, there is gold to be found: therfore it is not necessarie, that the holye Scriptures shoulde be so vnderstanded by <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilla,</hi> when it is sayde, they went for gold to <hi>Tharsis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ophyn,</hi> and <hi>Sechyn,</hi> yea and although they wyll not beléeue the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
         <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther truthes, they can not denye the saying of the holye Scripture in the Seconde Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> where
<pb facs="8"/>
it is sayde that the first riuer that goeth out of Paradise is <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>hyson,</hi> which doth compasse the whole countrey of <hi>Eiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lath,</hi> where golde doth growe, and that the golde of that countrey is very good and pure, nor it was not néedefull to haue thrée yeres from Ierusalem to <hi>Antilla,</hi> as it is for the Ilands of the <hi>Indians,</hi> whiche is more further off, by a great deale, and with much more difficultnesse to prouyde the precious stones, and all other things they brought frō thence, and also the wayes be more difficulte and strange, by reason of contrarye windes, and manye other incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunces. And that this was not vnderstanded that the people a farre of are these Ilandes now founde, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by Saint Paule in the fiftéenth Chapter to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes, where is expounded the saying of Esay in the <hi>52.</hi> Chapter, wher it is sayde, That those to whom it was not pronounced vnto, shoulde sée, and those that did not heare of him, should vnderstande. And this, as a lyttle aboue is sayde, is vnderstanded, that from Ierusalem to the Iles of <hi>Grecia,</hi> to the sea <hi>Illyrico</hi> which is the end of <hi>Grecia,</hi> and the beginning of <hi>Italy,</hi> by <hi>Slauonia,</hi> or <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> and <hi>Venice,</hi> where before they had not hearde the name of Christ de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. And bycause the holye ghost hath interpreted thys sentence by Saint Paul, applying that prophecie with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like of his workes, there remayneth no licence for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to apply it to <hi>Antilla.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But now let vs come to the summe of this reckning, and say, that if for the golde that is founde in <hi>Antilla,</hi> wée should beléeue that it is <hi>Tharsis,</hi> and <hi>Ophyn,</hi> and <hi>Sethyn,</hi> by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other things that be founde in <hi>Ophyn,</hi> &amp;c, and not in <hi>Antil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> we must beléeue that it is not those, nor those it. And moreouer, it appeareth that <hi>Asia</hi> and <hi>Tharsis, Ophyn,</hi> and <hi>Sethyn,</hi> be in the East, and <hi>Antilla</hi> the <hi>Spanyola</hi> in the west, in place and condition much different.</p>
      <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>