<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE READER.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1563</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105952_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A17059</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3933</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105952</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE READER.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The historie of Leonard Aretine : concerning the warres betwene the Imperialles and the Gothes for the possession of Italy, a worke very pleasant and profitable. Translated out of Latin into Englishe by Arthur Goldyng</title>
                 <author>Bruni, Leonardo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1563</date>
                 <publisher>Buck, George.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hall, Rowland</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 180 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>TO THE READER.</head>
   <p>FOrasmuche as thys worke of Leonard Aretine entreateth of the repulsyng of the Gothes out of Italy by the Captaines of thempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure of Constantinople, touchynge lightly by the way the cause of their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuall in the same countrye. It semeth expedient to make further rehearsall of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> cause of their first enterance with in the boundes of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Romaine Empire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of their successe in the same through which they grewe so strong in processe of tyme, that they not only beareft it o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> dyuerse prouinces &amp; members pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereto, but also gatte into their handes Italy it self with y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Ilands ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oyning, making thēfelues Lordes and Maisters of Rome somtime soueraine lady &amp; Empresse of the world, In decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration wherof y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> matter it self wil som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what minister occasion to speake of the Erules and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> out of whose handes the Gothes wrested y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> dominiō
<pb facs="5"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nd possession of Italy: and fynally of the two politique martiall and fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Captaynes Belisarius and Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>oe after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> yeares war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, recouered the same agayne to the Empyre. The whyche thynges I wyll ouer conne as bryefely as the matter wyll permytte, The Gothes therefore by the assertion and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ente of allowable Authors, enhabyted som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme beyonde the ryuer Istre or Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now in the Countrye called in olde tyme Dacia nowe named Ualachia. So that the Ostrogoth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s or Easterne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gothes borderyng vppon the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>aste of <note n="*" place="margin">Now called <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
               <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
            </gap> maiore</hi>
      </note> Pontus Eurinus, (of whom thys presente hystorye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>.) are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted for the Gettes and Triballes: and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> enhabytyng more into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and mayne lande towarde the head of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now and Ger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>anie, are accompted for the Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es or Daues. Nowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> of our Lorde God. 373.
<pb facs="5"/>
In the tyme of Ualens Emperour of the Easte, a certayne people of <note n="*" place="margin">Now called Tartarie.</note> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia named Hunnes assembling them selues in greate number, vnder the conducte of their Captayne Cadaris inuaded the Easterngothes &amp; brought them in subiection. The western<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gothes strycken wyth feare at the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne misfortune of their neyghbours, abandonyng theyr natyue Countrye sent Ambassadours to the Emperour Ualens▪ proferyng to receaue the Christen fayth, and to set themselues as a wall &amp; bulwarke to the Romayne Empyre agaynst the assaultes of the cruell Hunnes and other Barbarous nations, so that he woulde suffer them to passe the ryuer Danow and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ue them Mysia to enhabyte. Uppon thys condition their requeste was graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and they receaued both Christen Religion and also gouernours of the Emperour.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="6"/>Through the misgoueruement and ex torcion of whō they were so vered, that they made insurrection agaynst y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Em pyre, subdued Mysia &amp; Thrace ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came themperour in battel &amp; burnt him in a cotage where he had hiddē himself, and finally besteged Constantinople. Neuerthelesse afterwarde as well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peased and pacified by the vertuous &amp; vpright gouernement, as vanquished &amp; subdued by the force &amp; puissance of The odesius (who succeded Ualens) they submitted themselues agayne to y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Empyre, &amp; serued in the warres at cōmaundement by the space of. xxxv. yeares, vntill suche tyme as Stillico (trayterously practisyng the confusion of Honorius fonne of the sayd Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dosius, to the entent to haue made hys own fonne Eucherius Emperour) by puttyng them out of wages, &amp; defran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them of their pensions, compelled them to rebell agayne. Wherupon ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng weapon in hande, they inuaded Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nonie, &amp; there makyng one Alari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cicus
<pb facs="6"/>
a noble and valiante gentleman King, wasted all Pannonic, Thrace, &amp; Sclauonie, with all the countryes bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deryng vppon Italye, and fynally after great slaughter both geuen and recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, spoyled al Italy with fyre &amp; sword, sacked Rome, and conquered Spayne, where they also settled themselues, and within fewe yeares afrer grew to such wealth authoritye &amp; puissance, that the yonger Ualcntinian Emperoure of Rome (of whom mention shalbe made in the begynnyng of thys worke) ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng in leage with their King Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doriche, vsed hys ayde agaynst Attila Kyng of the Hunnes. For the Hunnes lyke good bloudhoundes followyng freshly the pursute of their foresaid vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye agaynst the Easterngothes part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moued of enuye towarde the state of the Romayne Empyre, and partly sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited thereto by the traytour Ruffin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> whom T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eodosius had left as gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and protector of hys other sonne Arcadius Emperoure of the Easte,)
<pb facs="7"/>
associatyng vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> them the sayed Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ngothes, the Gepides, the Erules, and other Barbarous people to the number of fyue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>thousande men, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conducte of Attila (worthely surnamed the scourge of God) afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the dominions and prouinces of the Romayne Empyre, and in especially wasted and spoyled Italye, razyng her Cytyes to the grounde, and bearyng downe all thynges before them lyke a moste vyolente and horrible tempeste. After whose returne into Pannon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, the seate of their kyngdome, Attila immediatly dyed. Whereuppon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued dyscord betwene the Hunnes and the Easterngothes, in whiche the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes: drawing to their parte: the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pides, preuayled, and draue the Hunnes oute of Pannonie backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne into Tartarie from whence they fyrst came. Howbeit they left theyr name styll behynde them to the Countrye, the whiche after them is
<pb facs="7"/>
called Hungarye vnto thys daye.</p>
   <p>Aboute the same tyme that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes had dryuen the Hunnes oute of Hungarie, it fortuned that one Aspar a noble man of greate power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tye proclaymed hys sonne Arda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buris Ceaser agaynst Leo then Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroure of Constantinople. In so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche that Leo was fayne to assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a power and encounter wyth hym wyth in the Cytye. In the whyche conflicte Aspar and Ardaburis beyng ouercome were yelded to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure and put both to death. The Gothos takyng occasion of aduantage vppon thys ciuyll warre, wasted all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> and neuer rested vntyll such tyme as Leo had graunted them Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garye (from whence they had vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye expulsed the sonnes of Attila) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Misia to haue and holde freely withoute tribute or subiection to the Empyre. Uppon whyche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition truce was taken, and for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obseruyng thereof.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>Theodenur Kyng of the Gothes gaue hys sonne Theodorich in Hostage vnto Leo. It was not long after but that there fel grudge &amp; consequently warre betwene Theodenur and hys brother Ualanur wherin Ualanur was slaine. By meanes whereof it came to passe, that Theodenur enioyed quietly the whole and entier possessiō of all Dacia, Masia, and both the Pannonies. Leo therfore fearyng the power &amp; puissance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Theodenur, deliuered him hys sōne Theoderich. Theodenur in recōpence of that good turne, tourned the truce y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> was taken betwene them into conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual peace, and so the Gothes ceased to molest the Empyre. In the meane sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son after muche alteration &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>surpyng by Tirantes, Angustu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>us a very childe the sonne of Orestes a sage and wyse Senatour of Rome, beyng by fauoure of the Citizens of Rauenna proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med emperour of the Weste, to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to refreshe and ease the Empyre of the long contynued trouble that it had
<pb facs="8"/>
suffered many yeares before, (by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>unsell of hys father Orestes) tooke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e with the Uandales in Affricke, who had alwayes synce their first com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, bene euill neyghbours to the Empyre. But whyles all was caulme and quiet on the south, beholde an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous and horrible tempeste riseth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> agaynst hym out of the North. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rules and Turinges the miserable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of the armye of Attila, (who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the sayd Attila was dead &amp; hys sonnes dryuen away, being vanquished by y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Easterngothes &amp; compelled backe againe toward Tartarie w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Hunnes, had a whyle helde themselues in quiet about y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> mouth of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>yuer Danow) allured with the former spoyle of Italy (to whose vtter vndoing wel nye al the warres that were made in those dayes dyd tend,) came backe agayne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queryng it, slewe Orestes and deposed Augustulus, in whom the honorable and renouned name of Augustus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied the. 517. yeare after that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>
      <pb facs="9"/>
Ceser fyrst had that name and title of honour geuen vnto hym of the Senate and people of Rome. By meanes wherof it came to passe, that Italy and Rome became afterward the common pray of Barbarous kinges, so y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> he that coulde make hymself strongest enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the possission therof. For Odoacer &amp; his Erules had scarcely yet fully set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled thēselues, when y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Easterngothes (who after the decease of Theodenur were now vnder y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> gouernement of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ne Theoderich) enuying y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> prosperity of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Erules, &amp; therwith callyng to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e how their own country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mē the westerngothes had already cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Spayne, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Uandales Affricke, the Frenchmē, &amp; Burgonions Gallia, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Saxons Britaine, &amp; other nations o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleasant &amp; fertile coūtries, earnest ly besought and required their king, to leade them into Italye to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>utent as well to aduaunce the fame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noune of their Cheualrie, as also to place thēselues in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ntrye which as
<pb facs="9"/>
it was the head and soueraine of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, so had it also the report to be the most pleasant, welthie, and fertile of al the Regions of Europe. Theoderich albeit he were in manner constrained by his subjectes to doe the thinge that they requested, yet as one myndfull of the great benefites that his ancestours had receiued of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Emperours of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople, and of the honorable enter tainem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>nt that he himselfe had had at suche tyme as he laye in hostage in the Emperours Court, he aduertised the Emperour Zeno therof, protesting y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> he would doe nothing without his con sent. Zeno who at that tyme stood in feare of Theoderich and the Gothes, (as one that for doubte least he should grow to strong for him in that parte of Europe, was fully determined before, to haue profered that vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>age vnto him though no such question had bene mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) gladly condescended to his pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ō &amp; for the more honour created him Cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Herevppon Theoderich and hys
<pb facs="10"/>
countrimen with their wiues and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren remoued into Italye. Of whose good successe and of the good successe of his posteritie in that countrie, togither with their expulsing or rather subdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Imperialls, for as much as this Historie of Leonard Aretine doth at large entreate I will not be tedious in repeating the same. Howbeit it is to be vnderstanded that after the battell of Nuceria where Teias last kinge of the Gothes was slayne, althoughe some departed awaye wyth such thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as they had according to couenant yet the greater part of them taryed stil: y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which degenerating into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> name of Italians, lost both their empyre &amp; own name for euer the lxxi. yere after their first cōming into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> coūtry vnder Theo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derich, being y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yere of grace CCCCC L. IIII. Nowe as concernynge the two noble and valiant captaines Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisarius and Narses the Conquerours and subduers of them, it is to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted whether the miserable misfortune
<pb facs="10"/>
of the one be more to be lamented, or the vnaduisednesse and follye of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (if I maye terme the thyng accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to desert) be to be blamed. For Belisarius after that he had recouered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> from the Uandales, vanquis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed the Persians, fought prosperously agaynste the Medes, abated the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and pulled downe the hygh cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages of the Gothes openinge a waye of conquest to hys successour, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheued so many hault enterprises and Marciall exploytes that the gloryous fame of hys doynges did sprede hys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne ouer all the worlde and made hys name immortall, in so muche that he was accompted as a perfecte and incomparable Mirrour for all Captaynes to beholde, and a verrye mayster of Cheualrye, whome neyther ambytion the common cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupter of noble hartes, nor the licentyous lybertye of the Campe, nor the instigatyons of myghtye
<pb facs="11"/>
Princes could withdrawe from hys al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeans and promise made to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Iustinian. Was in the ende in hys olde dayes vppon lyghte suspicion wythoute proofe, by the same Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour for whom he had so often put hys lyfe in perill: to whom he had acquired so muche honour, whose fauour he had estemed more then to raygne himselfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> an Emperour, depriued of both his eyes, and constrayned to begge hys bread miserably from doore to doore, an vnworthye rewarde for so manye good dedes and so muche good seruice done to the Empyre. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>arses the subduer of the Gothes and reducer of Italy to the Empyre when he had go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned it quietlye manye yeres togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bys greate honour and admy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, at the laste (lyke a shrewd cow whyche when she hath geuen a good quantitie of mylke ouerthroweth the payle wyth her heele and spyllethe the same) prouoked onely by the presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous wordes of a vayne and enuious
<pb facs="11"/>
woman, weued suche a web (according to his owne wordes) as neyther she nor the Emperour were able to weare oute, no nor he hymselfe to vnweaue agayne after he had ones putte it into the loome, thoughe he dyd the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sts he could to haue stayed it, so hard and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult a matter is it to stoppe a mischief of the course, when it ones hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the reynes in the necke, and hathe set foote forward to runne the race. For the Lombardes beynge by hym in the extasie of his fumyshe rage called oute of Pannonie (which by that tyme was become the common receptacle of the enemyes of the Empyre) not onelye wythin shorte tyme after hys decease broughte Italye in subiection to them, but also syns that daye hytherto (why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thyng neyther the Gothes, Hūnes Uandales, Erules, nor anye other of the barbarous nations with their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfolde and terrible assaultes were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to compasse and brynge to effecte) haue helde a porcion thereof as a
<pb facs="12"/>
perpetuall possession and inheritan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to themselues, whych retaineth their name vnto this daye. But forasmuch as these thinges were done somewhat after the subduing of the Gothes, and doe lytle or nothinge pertaine to the presente purpose of thys Historie I will not stand any lenger vppon them, but remit the to the readynge of myne Author.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>