<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen-Readers.</title>
           <author>D., I.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1594</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105351_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20406</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6817</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105351</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen-Readers.</title>
                 <author>D., I.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Arisbas, Euphues amidst his slumbers: or Cupids iourney to hell : Decyphering a myrror of constancie, a touch-stone of tried affection, begun in chaste desires, ended in choise delights: and emblasoning beauties glorie, adorned by natures bountie. VVith the triumph of true loue, in the foyle of false fortune. By I.D</title>
                 <author>Dickenson, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1594</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>68 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen-Readers.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Earned and curteous Gentlemen, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the whitest Swanne &amp; sweetest of Apolloes musicall birdes, hath put an endlesse periode to his euer-liuing lines, being preuented by vntimely death the Herauld of ouer-hastie destiny, though he the honour of Art &amp; hope of Armes, Mineruaes nourse-childe, and beloued Secretary to the sacred Muses, was in the spring-time of his glorie, raised from below to reigne aboue: yet as his heroique spirit disrobed of the perishing habit of mortalitie, swiftly passing through the inferior orbes, hath ascended to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre heauen, participating eternall ioyes in the habitation of the blessed, and doth with happier eyes view the glorious light of the Deitie, and resting in that blisfull seate of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, wōders at heauens huge frame, wherto his high thoghts did alwaies honourably aspire: So his Fame winged with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert, suted in robes of immortalitie, vanquishing death, try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing ouer time, and nothing staied by triuiall stoppes, towres to the cloudes, and not comprehended in smal limits, fils the eares of all men with oft-rebounded ecchoes of his praise, &amp; ouerspreading Europe, nay the worldes wide conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, as did the flourishing vine which seemed to dismaid A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>styages in his ill-presaging dreame, to couer Asia with a spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious shade.</p>
   <p>If you demaund whom I meane, euen he it is to whom I wil ascribe no other titles, thē the world hath allotted, though I cannot duly affoord them as he deserues them, yet take thē as I haue placed them in this English distich, a testimonie of
<pb facs="4"/>
the reuerent affection which I beare to the memorie of such a famous Worthie.</p>
   <q>
      <l>Sweet Astrophil the solace of my pen,</l>
      <l>Wonder of worth, and Peere of peerlesse men.</l>
   </q>
   <p>But who can adde to that which is infinite? or what pen can sufficiently expresse his praise which exceeds the praises of al pens, especially of mine, whose slender wit treating such an ample subiect, feeles want in plentie, raunging in a large field of copious matter, and being engulfed in an Ocean of conceit, lies there ouerwhelmed? But some may demaund wherto this tendes, to whom I answere thus briefly, framing mine owne Apologie▪ I hope that it shall not minister iust occasion of offence to any, that my blushing Muse reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the steps wherein he traced, and houering aloofe with awe-full dread, doth yet at last warily approach, and carefully obserue the directiōs of so worthie a guide, &amp; in part, glance at the vnmatchable height of his heroique humor.</p>
   <p>Did not Statius charge his Thebaide to attend with like reuerence, on the loftie foote-steps of the royall Aeneide? But to conclude, I shall be full heire of mine hope, and shall esteeme it no small good hap, if you grace mine endeuours with fauourable doome, and accept my good-will in lieu of currant performance. Thus Gentlemen, committing my Pamphlet to your friendly view, and submitting my selfe to your curteous censures, I end, wishing to you al, seueral good fortunes, and concluding my resolution in this harsh Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gramme, hatched in codde humour:
<q>
         <l>Quaeris delicias, faeetiasque,</l>
         <l>Festiuosque iocos? habes quod optas,</l>
         <l>Faecunda Astrophili petens fluenta,</l>
         <l>Late mellifluis referta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>iuis.</l>
         <l>Quaeris dulce melos, sales; &amp; omnes</l>
         <l>Verborum veneres? habes quod optas,</l>
         <l>
            <pb facs="5"/>Foecunda Astrophili petens fluenta,</l>
         <l>Passim nectareis adaucta lymphis.</l>
         <l>Quaeris suauiculi nouos lepores,</l>
         <l>Gazas ingeni▪ tenes quod optas</l>
         <l>Faecunda Astrophili petens fluenta,</l>
         <l>Lauro &amp; littorea superba myrto.</l>
         <l>Illi Pierides fuere curae:</l>
         <l>Illum Pieridesque Gratiaeque</l>
         <l>Curant. Quin petis illius fluenta,</l>
         <l>Queis tot lacteoli canunt olores?</l>
         <l>At me saeuior, insidere terrae</l>
         <l>Cogit Calliope, negatque vela:</l>
         <l>Exemit tamen infimo illa vulgo,</l>
         <l>Et sperare dedit placere posse.</l>
      </q>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>I. D.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>