<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>W. S. in commendation of the Aucthor.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1577</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105776_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02027</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12174</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105776</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>W. S. in commendation of the Aucthor.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The golden Aphroditis : a pleasant discourse, penned by Iohn Grange Gentleman, student in the common lavve of Englande. Wherevnto be annexed by the same authour asvvell certayne metres vpon sundry poyntes, as also diuers pamphlets in prose, which he entituleth his Garden: pleasant to the eare, and delightful to the reader, if he abuse not the scente of the floures</title>
                 <author>Grange, John</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1577</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>W. S. in commendation of the Aucthor.</head>
   <l>OF siluer pure thy penne is made, dipte in the Muses well,</l>
   <l>Thy Eloquence and loftie style all other doth excell:</l>
   <l>Thy wisedome great and secrete sense diffusedly disguysde,</l>
   <l>Doth shew how <hi>Pallas</hi> rules thy minde, and <hi>Phoebu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </hi> hath deuisde</l>
   <l>Those Golden lines, which polisht are with <hi>Tagus</hi> glittring sandes.</l>
   <l>A pallace playne of pleasures great vnto the vewers handes.</l>
   <l>Thy learning doth bewray it selfe and worthie prayse dothe craue,</l>
   <l>VVho so thee knew, did little thinke suche learning thee to haue.</l>
   <l>Here <hi>Vertue</hi> seemes to checke at <hi>Vice,</hi> and wisedome folly tauntes:</l>
   <l>Here <hi>Venus</hi> she is set at naught, and Dame <hi>Diane</hi> she vauntes:</l>
   <l>Here <hi>Pallas Cupid</hi> doth detest, and all his carpet knightes:</l>
   <l>Here doth she shew, that youthfull impes in folly most delightes.</l>
   <l>And how when age comes creeping on, with shewe of hoary heares,</l>
   <l>Then they the losse of time repent, with sobbes and brynish teares.</l>
   <l>Thou <hi>Ambodexter</hi> playste herein, to take the first rebounde,</l>
   <l>And for to shew thy minde at large, in earth doth the same cōpound:</l>
   <l>So that <hi>Apollo</hi> claddes his corps all with <hi>Mory<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
            <desc>••</desc>
         </gap>us</hi> clothes,</l>
   <l>And shewes himself still friendliest there, where most of al he lothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.</l>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>