<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen Readers, Health.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105824_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02121</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12261</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105824</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen Readers, Health.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Greenes vision : vvritten at the instant of his death. Conteyning a penitent passion for the folly of his pen</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Allde, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newman, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>64 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Gentlemen Readers, Health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, in a vision before my death, I foresee that I am like to sustaine the shame of many follies of my youth, when I am shrowded in my winding sheete. O let not iniurious tongues tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ouer a dead carcase. Now I am sick, and sorrow hath wholy sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>d on me: vaine I haue beene, let not other men shewe themselues vaine in reproching my vanitie. I craue pardon of you all, if I haue offended any of you with laciuious Pamphle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ing. Many things I haue wrote to get money, which I could otherwise wish to be supprest: Pouertie is the father of innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable infirmities: in seeking to salue priuate wantes, I haue made my selfe a publique laughing stock. Hee that commeth in Print, setteth himselfe vp as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon marke for euery one to shoote at: I haue shotte at many abuses, ouer s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e my selfe in describing of some: where truth failed, my inuention hath stood my friend. God forgiue me all my misdeameanours: now in the best lust of my yeares, death I feare will depriue me of any further proceeding in securitie. This booke hath many things, which I would not haue written
<pb facs="4"/>
on my Tombe: I write this last, let it be my last will and testament. Farewell, if I liue you shall heare of me in deuinitie, in the meane time, accept the will for the deede, and speake well of me when I am dead.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Yours dying.</hi> Robert Greene.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>