<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>NICOLAS VDALL VNTO the gentle and honeste herted readers well to fare.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1542</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105498_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00316</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10443</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105498</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>NICOLAS VDALL VNTO the gentle and honeste herted readers well to fare.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Apophthegmes : that is to saie, prompte, quicke, wittie and sentencious saiynges, of certain emperours, kynges, capitaines, philosophiers and oratours, aswell Grekes, as Romaines, bothe veraye pleasaunt [et] profitable to reade, partely for all maner of persones, [et] especially gentlemen. First gathered and compiled in Latine by the ryght famous clerke Maister Erasmus of Roterodame. And now translated into Englyshe by Nicolas Vdall</title>
                 <author>Erasmus, Desiderius</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Grafton, Richard</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1542</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 345, 15 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>NICOLAS VDALL VNTO the gentle and honeste herted readers well to fare.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmucheas the autour self in his preface here ensuyng doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at large declare the nature, the purpose, and the vse of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pophthegmes, to make of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same matier double inculcacion should bee (as me semeth) bothe on my parte and behalf a thing superfluous, and also a tedious dullyng to the reader. It shall therefore at this presēte tyme be sufficiēte to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyshe you gentle readers, that of the whole werke of Apophthegmes by the right excellente clerke Erasmus: for the moste plesaunte and the same moste honeste, profitable, &amp; holsome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dnyg of allmaner persones, &amp; in especiall of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble menne collected and digested into eight vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes, I haue thought better with twoo of the eight to ministre vnto you a taste of this bothe delectable and fruiteful recreacion, then by sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressyng it vntil y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> whole werke might bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectely absolued and finysshed, to defraude you of so many goodly histories, so many high poin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctes of counsaill, so many notable preceptes of wysedome, so greate a noumbre of philosophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call lessōs, suche vnestymable treasure of morall doctrine, as may of this litle porcion in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meane tyme with small labour &amp; incomparable delite, coūforte and solace of mynd, bee perceiued, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and acquired. And although vpon consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracions, (at a more propice tyme herafter by goddes grace to bee declared) I haue beē so bolde with myne autour, as to make the firste booke &amp;
<pb facs="3"/>
secounde, whiche he maketh thirde and fourth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> Yet in these twoo presente volumes whiche ye see here sette foorth, I haue labou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the duetie of a translatour, that is, ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng and folowyng the sense of my booke, to interprete and turne the Latine into Englyshe with as muche grace of our vulgare toung, as in my slendre power and knowelage hath lyen: not omittyng ne leattyng passe, either any one of all the Apophthegmes as thei stand in ordre (except twoo or three at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> moste beeyng of suche sorte as honestee perswaded me, to bee better passed ouer, then rehersed or spoken of,) orel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> any Greke or Latine verse or woorde, wherof y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pith and grace of the saiyng dependeth. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I desire the vnlearned readers not to bee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended for that I haue in many places entremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed Greke and Latine with the Englyshe. For in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>l thynges that I haue alreadie heretofore or herafter shall sette foorth, I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e an especiall regarde vnto young scholares and studentes, vnto whom it is not possible to bee expressed, what great vtilitee, benefite &amp; knowelage doeth redound of conferryng one straunge language with an other. Neither is it to bee doubted, but that suche as are towardes the disciplines of good litterature in diuerse tounges, maye of suche dooynges as this, pieke out a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> muche v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitee and furtheraunce of their studies, as the vnlearned shall take pleasure, and fruite of the Englyshe for their vse. Whoso careth not for the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ine maye passe it ouer and satisfie hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with the Englyshe. Who passeth not on the Greke, maie sembleably passe it ouer, and make as though he see none suche. Ther is in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half no mannes labour lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t but myne, and ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> not that all lost neither, if my good zele &amp; honest
<pb facs="3"/>
entente to dooe good to all sortes, bee in good parte interpreted and accepted. Leat the vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned readers somewhat beare with young stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, as the learned must and will dooe with theim. For as y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> one parte maie thynke it muche superfluous to fynd Latine and Greke in an Englyshe booke, so the learned haue no nede of certain annotacions (whiche I haue in places not a fewe entremyngleed, partely to supplye &amp; redubbe that wanteth of the whole werke, and partely to geue necessarie light to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Greke and Romaine histories) of whiche annotacions euē he peraduēture shall fynd ease, whiche wil fynd faulte with the admixtion of Greke and Latine &amp; will auouche thesame confused medleyng of soundrie tounges rather to contein some spiece of ostentacion &amp; braggue of the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>incted sheath, then any argumente or prouf of erudicion. To all whom would Christe I could perswade (as trueth it is) that I seke nothyng lesse then suche shadoe of vnstable glorie, &amp; that my onely wille and desire is to further honeste knowelage, and to call (awaye the studious youth in especiall) from hauyng delite in readyng phantasticall trifles, (whiche contein in manier nothyng but the seninarie of pernicious sectes and sedicious doctrine, vnto a more fruitefull sorte of spēdyng good houres, &amp; by inuityng thesame youth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the imitacion of honeste exercises, to dooe good if I maye. But to procede in that I was now about to saie, truly for the Englysheman to bee offended with the admixtion of Latine, or the Latine manne to myslyke the pouthreyng of Greke, appereth vnto me a muche like thyng, as if at a feaste with varietee of good meates &amp; drynkes furnyshed, one that loueth to feede of a Capon, should take displeasure that an other
<pb facs="4"/>
manne hath appetite to a Coney, or one y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his stomake with a Pertrige, should bee angrye with an other that hath a mynde to a Quaylle, or one y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> drynketh single beere should bee greued with his nexte feloe for drynkyng ale or wyne. Now for the better vnderstandyng of the cōceipte, trade and conueighaunce of this booke, I haue thought requisite to admonyshe you, that in eche mānes Apophthegmes the sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng self is sette out in a greate texte lettre: after whiche ymmediately foloweth in a middle let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre (with this marke) the moralizacion of Erasmus, wheresoeuer to thesame it semed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediente any suche morall sense to gather of the Apophthegme for edifiyng of the reader in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or ciuile honestee. That if any matier depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of some Greke or Romaine chronicle hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> semed needefull to bee expouned, if any poeticall fable hathe come in place, if to any obscure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe or straunge historie hath been made some preatie allusiō nedefull to bee declared, all suche thynges together with the names of persones here mencioned, ye shall fynd sette foorth, and added of myne owne notyng, ouer and besides the woordes and matier of the Latine werke in a small lettre, with some directorie marke. Yea and sometymes in the middes of the texte with this marke of myne if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>he place semed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire some more light. Sembleably to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> morall interpretacion of Erasmus (where occasiō was minis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>red) yea and to some Apophthegmes (where Erasmus saied nothyng,) in case my so dooyng myght any thyng helpe the weake and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>endre capte of the vnlearned reader, I haue putte addicions of thesame lettre and marke, to the ende that in case it bee not all of the fynest, the blame therof maye not light on the autour,
<pb facs="4"/>
but redound vnto my self accordyngly. And to the entente that nothyng should lacke whiche to the ease and commoditee of the vnlearned rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der might seme necessarie, there is added also a large &amp; plain table in ordre of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> A.B.C. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to the name of any persone, or to any good matier in the booke conteined, readie waye and recourse maye with a weat fynger easily bee foūd out. That if in any of the premisses either the interpretour or els the prienter shalbe found to haue failled, I for my parte shall not onely thynk my laboure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> bounteou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ly rewarded, but also knowelage myself highly bounden to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre moste hertie thākes, if the gentle reader shall of his humanitee &amp; honeste herte vouche salue to sette his penne and helpyng hande to emende whatsoeuer errour it shall happē hym to espye: and in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> residue so to accepte both our laboures as we maye thereby bee encouraged gladly to sustein ferther trauaill in wrytyng and settyng foorth suche autours, as maye to the reader bee bothe pleasaunte and profitable.</p>
   <p>¶Wryten in the yeare of our Lorde God. M.CCCCC.xlii.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>