<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable Robert Lee, Lord Maior of the honorable Citie of London: And to the Right worshipfull the Aldermen his brethren.</title>
           <author>Crosse, Henry</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1603</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105137_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19641</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6070.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105137</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT Honourable Robert Lee, Lord Maior of the honorable Citie of London: And to the Right worshipfull the Aldermen his brethren.</title>
                 <author>Crosse, Henry</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Vertues common-vvealth: or The high-way to honour : Wherin is discouered, that although by the disguised craft of this age, vice and hypocrisie may be concealed: yet by tyme (the triall of truth) it is most plainly reuealed. ... By Henry Crosse</title>
                 <author>Crosse, Henry</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Creede, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Newbery, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1603</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>160 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable <hi>Robert Lee,</hi> Lord Maior of the honorable Citie of <hi>London:</hi> And to <hi>the Right worshipfull the Aldermen his brethren.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant (Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and right worshipfull Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators) of the custome of this age, which is, that such as write bookes do vse to dedicate thē to some worthy persō or other, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whose protection they might passe with more safetie from the byting of the enuious: so that many times a light discourse is grac't with a iudiciall censor: I was therefore imboldned to obserue the same Method, and that chiefly because I know true <hi>Vertue</hi> loueth whatsoeuer is like it selfe be it neuer so little, and accepteth what is zealously offered, though not alwayes deseruingly excellent, whē base deiected minds want wisedome &amp; experience to direct the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb facs="3"/>
of iudgement. And although I haue scatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red here and there some iarring notes and harsh consonants, vntunable to a modest eare: yet the vglines of vice made me striue to paint out her <hi>lanus</hi>-face to the eye of the world. <hi>Alexander</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused not a cup of colde water at the hands of a silly begger, the poore widows myte was more accepted then the abundance of the Scribes and Pharises, for she offered all that she had, they of their superfluitie: so a noble mind doth alwaies patronize a poore gift as willingly, as it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly dedicated. If in like sort your bounties wil deign to giue free admittance to this home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worke, I shall be prouoked not to end with this my rude beginning, but striue to shewe some greater monument of my loue heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And thus leauing to trouble your wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms with tedious circumstance, I rather abre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiate of that I would say, then by speaking too much to breed suspitiō of my simple well mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And so I humbly commit your affaires to the good guidance of the Almightie, and my selfe to your fauourable censures.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honors and worships most dutifull to commaund.</hi> Henry Crosse.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>