<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT REVE∣RENDE FATHER IN GOD AND his especiall good Lorde, Rycharde by the grace of God byshop of VVorcetter, his humble oratour and dayely bedeman, Leonarde Pollarde vvyssheth perpetual health both of soule and body.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1556</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105125_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09827</idno>
           <idno type="STC">20091</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105125</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT REVE∣RENDE FATHER IN GOD AND his especiall good Lorde, Rycharde by the grace of God byshop of VVorcetter, his humble oratour and dayely bedeman, Leonarde Pollarde vvyssheth perpetual health both of soule and body.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Fyve homiles of late, made by a ryght good and vertuous clerke, called master Leonarde Pollarde, prebendary of the Cathedrall Churche of Woster, directed and dedicated to the ryght reuerende Father in God Rychard by the permissyon of God bysshoppe of Woster his specyall good Lorde. Vewed, examined, and alowed by the right reuerende Father in God Edmonde byshop of London, within whose diocese they are imprinted. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum</title>
                 <author>Pollard, Leonard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1556</date>
                 <publisher>Griffith (Gryffyth), William.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Powell, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>94 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ TO THE RIGHT REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RENDE FATHER IN GOD AND his especiall good Lorde, Rycharde by the grace of God byshop of VVorcetter, his humble oratour and dayely bedeman, Leonarde Pollarde vvyssheth perpetual health both of soule and body.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsyderynge with my selfe (most reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rende father) the bountifull goodnes of Almyghtly God, who dyd so thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receaue the myte offered by the poore wyddowe, as he did the precious giftes offered to him by the ryche and welthy persons, I haue byn there by encoraged to offer towardes the buylding ageyne of his blessed Temple (the Church I meane) de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faced and almost destroyde by heretickes, these simple and rude sermons, not bicause that I thynke them to be of suche force or learnynge that they can helpe muche thereunto, or that the greate and precious treasures of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fryd by other myght not suffyce, but rather (as I sayd) to declare the promptnes and redynesse of my mynde, which ought to be in me and all men to do seruyce vnto his maiestie accordynge to our habilitie. It is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to your Lordeshyp the number of bookes and sermons that were made to deface the churche, and the number and the diligentnes of them that wold haue de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stroyed the churche, the which diligence of them or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther continuall ragynge yf it shulde not be matched or with like diligence of our parte ouercome and outmat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,
<pb facs="3"/>it shulde be much to the reproche of vs all. For yf we se (as we can not but se) them to haue taken suche peynes to suppresse and ouerthrowe the truth (yf it lay in them so to do) howe iustely shall our conscience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs beinge negligent or retchlesse by Gods helpe to defende the same. Let vs not thynke but God (who hath alredy plaged the churche of this realme for the rechlessenes of our fathers wyl) much more greuously punyshe vs beinge nothinge amended but rather worse after this his chastisement and correction. For this is the tyme to take hede and to be diligent and as it were the tyme to haruest and of labour and not of reapynge and rest. If we repe before our tyme our corne wyll be greene. If we rest eare our busynes be done, we shalbe cōpelled to worke when we shulde rest, &amp; yet it shal not auayle vs. We must therfore (as the prouerbe is) take the tyme whyle tyme is, for tyme wyl away. Thus my most reuerend Father &amp; honorable Lord I being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued partly as I haue sayde with the bountifull magny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycence of Almyghty God, who dyd so louingly accept the offryng of the poore wyddowe, and partly with the consideration of my duety after this miserable tyme of sisme and heresy, haue wrytten certeyne sermons or Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miles the whiche I thought to offer to your reuerende Fatherhod and honorable Lordeshyp, as the gyftes of a chylde to his father bothe for the fatherly loue that I do knowe you to beare towardes vs your diocessans and chyldren, and for your great affection and feruent zeale in the defence and meintenaunce of Gods Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke fayth and true religion, the which your father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="3"/>loue and byshoplyke zeale beinge well knowen to all men, shall cause these my sermons to be I truste the better accepted, both with God and man. Wherefore I shall moste hartely desyre your honour to accepte this my small oblation or offerynge, and with your wysedome and discretion to vse the same accordyngely, as thereby the Catholyke fayth may be mein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned, and almyghty god best honored.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>who haue your good Lordeshyp in his blessed kepynge nowe and euer Amen.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>