<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT Honorable, Robert Deuorax, Earle of Essex, and Ewe: Viscount of Hereford and Bourchier: Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Bourchier and Louayne: Maister of the Queenes Maiesties Horsse: A. M. wisheth increase of all happinesse.</title>
           <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1588</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105031_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19128</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5541</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105031</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ TO THE RIGHT Honorable, Robert Deuorax, Earle of Essex, and Ewe: Viscount of Hereford and Bourchier: Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Bourchier and Louayne: Maister of the Queenes Maiesties Horsse: A. M. wisheth increase of all happinesse.</title>
                 <author>Munday, Anthony</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The famous, pleasant, and variable historie, of Palladine of England : Discoursing of honorable aduentures, of knightly deedes of armes and chiualrie: enterlaced likewise with the loue of sundrie noble personages, as time and affection limited their desires. ... Translate out of French by A.M. one of the messengers of her Maiesties Chamber</title>
                 <author>Colet, Claude</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1588</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, Edward.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Perrin (Perin), John</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>3, 92 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ TO THE RIGHT Honorable, <hi>Robert Deuorax,</hi> Earle of Essex, and Ewe: Viscount of Hereford and Bourchier: <hi>Lord Ferrers of</hi> Chartley, Bourchier and <hi>Louayne:</hi> Maister of the <hi>Queenes</hi> Maiesties <hi>Horsse:</hi> A. M. wisheth increase of all happinesse.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong those (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) that offered incense in the Temple of Iupiter, in plates of Golde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the custome, a simple Heards<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man religiously affected, brought his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering on a broken potsheard: for which he being reprooued by Iupiters Priest, boldly returned this answere. The Gods that dispose all, knowe all, rich men are discerned by their great gifts, and poore men by their simple, yet happily their zeale is not alike: for rather had I be thought vnmannerly by this homely present, then vndutifull by want of better abilitie.</p>
   <p>In like manner, right noble Lord, among those ripe and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious wittes, that offer to your learned view matter of valew, squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and leueld by deepe knowledge and experience: a simple zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous man, more deuoted in affection to your honors welfare, then able to expresse the same as other can, presents this rude and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pullished peece of worke, not handled with arte, because I want it, nor glozed with borrowed phrases, because I am loth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come indebted: but equall with the poore Heardsmans potsheard, and with him chusing rather to be thought homely, then vnduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="3"/>
knowing that the Eagles eyes of Iupiter, can search into the substance of the one and other.</p>
   <p>This woorke of Palladine, with all his imperfections, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie commit to your honorable protection: knowing, that in respect of your owne loue to Chiualrie, you will thinke well of him, and because he is an English man, in the better sort fauour him. For my selfe, as I neuer knew honor partiall in opinion, but with vpright iudgement to ballance each mans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing: so in this assurance, with reuerence, I end, as forward as any in affection to your Honor.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>A. Monday.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>