<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶The maydens dreme Compyled and made by Chrystofer Goodwyn, In the yere of our Lorde. M.CCCCC.xlij.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1542</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105755_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01908</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12047</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105755</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶The maydens dreme Compyled and made by Chrystofer Goodwyn, In the yere of our Lorde. M.CCCCC.xlij.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The maydens dreme compyled and made by Chrystofer Goodwyn, in the yere of our Lorde. M.CCCCC.xlij</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Wyer (Wyre), Robert</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bankes, Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1542</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16 pages, illustrations, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>¶The maydens dreme Compyled and made by Chrystofer Goodwyn, In the yere of our Lorde. M.CCCCC.xlij.</head>
   <p>
      <figure>
</figure>
   </p>
   <div type="prologue">
      <head>¶The Prohemye of the Authour.</head>
      <lg>
         <l>BEholde you yonge Ladyes, of hyghe parentage</l>
         <l>And you yonge virgyns, of eche degre</l>
         <l>Here is a pamphlet, euen mete for your age</l>
         <l>Where as in a myrrour, you maye lerne and se,</l>
         <l>Howe vycyous loue, you shulde eschewe and fle</l>
         <l>Hauynge alway shamfastnes, ī your maydenly face</l>
         <l>Then can you neuer mysse, of vertue and grace.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <pb facs="2"/>
         <l>¶To loue I counceyll you, neuer enclyne</l>
         <l>Excepe onely, it be for maryage</l>
         <l>To the entent, to haue therby lyne</l>
         <l>yet in that case, take hede you not rage</l>
         <l>For hasty loue cōmonly, ryght soone wyll aswage</l>
         <l>And beware that you loue not, before you be wyse</l>
         <l>Lest you repent you, more ofter than twyse.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>¶Yet dyuers in loue, hath had happy chaunce</l>
         <l>I speke by my selfe, and many one mo</l>
         <l>That of perfyte chaste loue, haue ben in the daunce</l>
         <l>And sped to our myndes, yet for to do so</l>
         <l>Thousandes haue myssed, and fynysshed in wo</l>
         <l>Therfore I rede you, take good aduysement</l>
         <l>Of good abydynge, none can repent.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>¶Called is the name, of this lytell boke</l>
         <l>The (Maydens dreme) whiche I hope shalbe</l>
         <l>For your erudycions, yf you therin loke</l>
         <l>Many a good instruccyon, here shall you se</l>
         <l>Howe vertue to ensue, and vyce for to fle</l>
         <l>For herein is contayned, both golde and glasse</l>
         <l>They that worke well, shall well brynge to passe.</l>
      </lg>
      <lg>
         <l>¶Thus to god, I do you cōmyt</l>
         <l>Prayenge you to accept, this my lytell warke</l>
         <l>For that it is so rudely done, is but for lacke of wyt</l>
         <l>Howe be it euery man, can not be a clarke</l>
         <l>Nor euery byrde flye, so hyghe as the larke</l>
         <l>Ye wot what I meane, thus fare you well</l>
         <l>Happy be they, that folowe good councell.</l>
      </lg>
   </div>
   <trailer>¶Thus endeth the Prologue.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>