<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE MIGHTY Prince, IAMES, King of Albion France and Ierne, defendour of the faith in power &amp; learning: Supreme governour vnder God, in his Lands.</title>
           <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1610</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105882_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A16986</idno>
           <idno type="STC">3868</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105882</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE MIGHTY Prince, IAMES, King of Albion France and Ierne, defendour of the faith in power &amp; learning: Supreme governour vnder God, in his Lands.</title>
                 <author>Broughton, Hugh</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Iob : To the King. A Colon-Agrippina studie of one moneth, for the metricall translation: but of many yeres for Ebrew difficulties. By Hugh Broughton</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Thorp, Giles</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Netherlands--Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1610</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>144 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb n="3" facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE MIGHTY Prince, IAMES, King of Albion France and Ierne, defendour of the faith in power &amp; learning: Supreme governour vnder God, in his Lands.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Eternal testified of <hi>Abraham,</hi> how he would teach his house to keep holy wayes. That hath story in Iobs book: where most learned Princes, five of his howse, shew Gods wayes for Christ: in such eloquence, that may argue applying of all knowledge and their dayes that way. The stile is in his language for verse, shortnes, and strange words, as Pindarus in Greek: and fuller of difficultie, then all the other books of Adams tongue: And hath cost me time and paines accordingly: more then my translation of the Prophets volume into Greek: which work I think your Maiestie hath: &amp; more then my shewing of Scripture concent: and defending of it, against D. Reinolds and Mr Livelie, having 2000 yeres Libraries on their side: and more then my clearing of Daniel, and Apocalyps, to admiration of thowsands. God would have this book as a Iewel hid in the ground, not seen playn without paines. What I have done for your nations use, the King should judge &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your M. m. h. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
H. Br.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>