<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOV∣RABLE, WYSE, AND VER∣tuouslie disposed Gentleman, WILLIAM FORBES of TOLQVHON.</title>
           <author>Skene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1631</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105267_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A69157</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5957</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105267</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOV∣RABLE, WYSE, AND VER∣tuouslie disposed Gentleman, WILLIAM FORBES of TOLQVHON.</title>
                 <author>Skene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pilgrime and heremite : in forme of a dialogue, by Master Alexander Craig</title>
                 <author>Craig, Alexander</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Raban, Edward</publisher>
                    <distributor>Melvill, David</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--Scotland--Aberdeen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1631</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, WYSE, AND VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouslie disposed Gentleman, <hi>WILLIAM FORBES</hi> of <hi>TOLQVHON.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving collected the dispersed, and long neglected <hi>Papers,</hi> of this subsequent <hi>Poësie,</hi> the <hi>Posthumes</hi> of a worthie <hi>Penne,</hi> for preserving them from pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing, for the Perfections of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted,</hi> maker of immortall memorie; who was one of the Faythfull, affectionate, (and re-affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) Favourers of the honourable <hi>House of BAMFE,</hi> wherevnto Your selfe, and Yours, by a faythfull Affection, and affectionate Affinitie, are vnseparably tied. And also, Sir, for the singular and ever bound duetie, wherevnto by many Obliedgements; and vnspeakable Respects, I ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my selfe to be vnterminably tied, to loue, serue, and honour, You and Yours, and to doe all that my possibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie can performe, to the eternitie of Your <hi>Name, House,</hi> and <hi>Honour.</hi> Herefore, Sir, I haue taken the boldnes, after the <hi>Author's</hi> expiring, to publish, and present, his <hi>Papers</hi> to Your Honours Hands, to passe vnder the Patrocinie and Protection of Your honourable Name. Receiue, therefore, Sir, this fatherles <hi>Orphane,</hi> vnder the Shield and Shadow of Your powerfull protection, &amp; courteous acceptation: and
<pb facs="3"/>
as hee presenteth to Your view a wandring <hi>Pilgrime,</hi> and a retired <hi>Heremite,</hi> both Despisers of the fleeting <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures,</hi> and flitting <hi>Ritches</hi> of this wretched World, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon most wretchedly so many doe doate: So, Sir, let the same call vs to mynd, what we are here, and what we should ayme to bee heereafter; that as wee are <hi>Pilgrimes</hi> on earth, wee may bee <hi>Citizens</hi> in Heaven; this being our way, but Aboue, our natiue Countrey; here our travell, there our rest; heere our race, there our prize; heere our fight, there our triumph; here our seed-time, there our harvest; and as wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Pilgrimis here our Innes only, from whence we must remoue, but there our home, and mansion place, wherein we must remayne. In this estate then, Sir, let worldly things be but our <hi>Viaticum,</hi> which we should vse, as if we vsed them not: and let vs neyther be cloyed with their loue, nor clog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with their cares; but seeke those things that are aboue, &amp; to temper the edge of our eager distractions, about many thinges with <hi>Martha,</hi> let vs with <hi>Marie</hi> consider that one thing which is necessarie; and requite, in some measure, that loue which CHRIST IESVS hath carried and kythed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs; not as this poore <hi>Heremite</hi> was with disdayne of her whom hee affected, but with mutuall tender affection, and a Christian care to keepe His Commandements; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we shall gayne to our selues, more than the greatest Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours, or busiest Worldlings, could ever acquire; even a glorious Kingdome, and a Crowne incorruptible. To the advancement whereof, Sir, both of you and yours, after manie and happie dayes heere, as my earnest Petition to GOD shall bee; so in all other thinges I haue vowed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours, in all serviceable and obsequious duetie, ROBERT SKENE.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>