<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The preface to the chri¦sten reader, with an exhortation, to moue al men to leaue disputinge, and reasonynge vpon the highe and vnsearcheable mysterie of te sacra∣mēt of the aulter, geuynge euer fyr∣me credence vnto christes catholi¦ke church therin, which neuer er∣rethe yn our fayth whollie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1550</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105000_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A12490</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22819</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105000</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The preface to the chri¦sten reader, with an exhortation, to moue al men to leaue disputinge, and reasonynge vpon the highe and vnsearcheable mysterie of te sacra∣mēt of the aulter, geuynge euer fyr∣me credence vnto christes catholi¦ke church therin, which neuer er∣rethe yn our fayth whollie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A confutation of a [́sic] certen booke : called á [sic] defence of the true, and Catholike doctrine of the sacrame [n] t, &amp;c. sette fourth of late in the name of Thomas Archebysshoppe of Canterburye. By Rycharde Smyth, Docter of diuinite, and some tyme reader of the same i Oxforde</title>
                 <author>Smith, Richard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Chaudiere, Regnault</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Paris</pubPlace>
                    <date>1550</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>166, that is 168, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>The preface to the chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sten reader, with an exhortation, to moue al men to leaue disputinge, and reasonynge vpon the highe and vnsearcheable mysterie of te sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēt of the aulter, geuynge euer fyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me credence vnto christes catholi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke church therin, which neuer er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethe yn our fayth whollie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He first consel, good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, holden at Ephesus, aboue M. C. yeres passed, yn which S. Cyril was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident, wrote thus in an epistle vnto one Nestorius an heretike, which the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryn was condemned for his heresie.</p>
   <p>We do offre an vnbloudie wourshi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge of à sacrifice, and so we do also come vnto the holie sacrament, and are made holie, beinge partakers of the holie bodie, and precious bloud of Christ, which was made the redeamer
<pb facs="3"/> of vs al, not receauinge it as common flesh, (god forbid that), nor as the fleash of à mā made holie, and ioyned vnto the sonne of god, by an vnite of worthynes, or els as beinge à mansion of god, but as that, which verilie ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth lyfe (to mans soul), &amp; was made propre vnto goddes owne sonne hym selfe. Hytherto this aunciēt and great councel, yn which were assembled. cc. bysshoppes, and which is one of the foure general concels, that S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie sayed that he esteamed no lesse then the foure gospelles. Wherfore <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. 24.</note> seinge that this coūcel hath so playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sette fourth botb the holy sacrifice of the masse, and also declared by the īspiratiō of the holy goost, the au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> and gouernour, of such leful, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conseylles, that we do receaue yn the sacrament that flesh, which is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to goddes owone sonne, and wbich geueth lyfe to them, that do worthilie receaue it, what wisdome
<pb n="5" facs="3"/> were it to beleue the bisshoppe of Canterburies doctrine, which denyeth both of these twoo? Is it not muche meter to beleue al those fathers, ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther then this bisshoppes teachynge the contrarie? Promysed not Christ, that he wold be in the middes of. ij. or. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.</note> iij. assembled in his name? Hou then was he not with these. cc. learned men, that they erred not yn their iudgemē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes? Wherfore lette vs beleue steadfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stly, (as this councel teacheth vs plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eie) that christes owne very natural bodie is in this sacrament, althoughe this bysshoppe, and such other carnal preachers, and writers, do barke neuer so muche against that our belefe, and do make neuer so manye argumētes, and natural reasons to subuert it, for as stronge and much stronger reasons may and heretofore hath bene made of heretikes, against al the articles of our faith, as it appreareth in dyuers old, and late writers bookes. Lette vs <note place="margin">Ceasse thy reasonynge vpon the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly sacramēt</note>
      <pb facs="4"/> not dispute, and reason vpō this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which can not be compased, nor perceaued by any natural reason, or witte of man, but by faith only, as S. Damascene, and many other holy <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note> doctours do testifie, but lette vs stead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastly beleue christes wordes, which sayeth, this is my bodie, that shal be geuen to death for you, which wordes no mà can truelie vnderstand of bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.</note> because that it was not crucyfied for vs, as that bodie which he gaue his apostles to eate, was. To these wordes <note place="margin">
         <hi>Hom.</hi> 93 <hi>in Matthaeum</hi>
      </note> (sayeth holy chrysostom.) lette vs ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue fyrme credence, yea thoughe our sēses, natural wytte, vnderstandynge, and reason be clerely al against yt, for christes wordes can not be false, nor disceaue vs, but oure senses are ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sye to be disceaued. The carnal iewes <note place="margin">
         <hi>Note reader Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>in</hi> 10.</note> (as wytnesseth S. Cyril) lackynge fayth, (as this bysshoppe, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> hoper, Ridley, ponete▪ and such o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>her do), and leanyng only to natural argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
<pb n="7" facs="4"/> and reasons, asked hou christ could geue them his fleash to eate.</p>
   <p>They remēbred not (sayeth he) that <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lucae.</hi> 1.</note> nothynge is impossible to god, and therfore they iudged that this myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie was but mere follye, and that it was but manifest madnes to beleue, that Christ would, or could geue them his oune flesh to eate bodily with their mouthes, as my lord of Canterburye, hoper, ponete, Ridley, coxe, and many such other, do now thinke, and also te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach, to their owne damnation, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny others besides, our lord amēde thē yn tyme, for his blessed names sake.</p>
   <p>These men do now euen as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythful iewes did yn christes tyme, when he intreated of this matter. For they measured it by natural reasō, &amp; witte, &amp; wold not beleue t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>at christes very bodie was in this sacramēt real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, &amp; bodilie, because they could not perceaue hou it so myght be by any natural reasō, &amp; because the senses of
<pb facs="5"/> man do iudge the contrarie. They do forgaette, that the prophete Esaie <note place="margin">
         <hi>Isaiae.</hi> 7.</note> sayeth, Excepte ye beleue, ye shal not vnderstand. They sette the carte (as they saye) before the horses, when they, putte reasō afore, &amp; fayth after. For is not fayth the fundation of our <note place="margin">1. <hi>cor.</hi> 3.</note> religion? Why do they not remembre that reasoninge, and fayth agree not <note place="margin">Cicero</note> wel together? Cotta sayed to Lucilius, why doest thou requyre à reason, yf thou doest beleue? for yf thou doest be leue, thou doest aske no reason, which may cause, that thou shouldest not beleue. Saith not also S. Paule, that <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lactantius Heb.</hi> 11.</note> faith is the fundatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>, and thinge that holdeth vp the thinge that appeareth not, and is the profe of thinges not seane? What follie is it then to laboure and stud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> for to trie out by reason the trueth yn this contro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ersye of this holy sacrament, which is vnsear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheable, and appertayneth onlie to our faith, excedinge al mans witte,
<pb n="9" facs="5"/> and reason? Are there not à thousand thinges and moo, which god hath <note place="margin">
         <hi>Damasce.</hi> 4. <hi>lib. ca.</hi> 14</note> done, that no reason of man can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue by what meanes they were done but onlye by fayth? Also cannest thou, I praye the, tel me hou god ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de <note place="margin">
         <hi>Gene.</hi> 1.</note> by his word al thinges of nothing? Did not the natural reasoners, and stu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dentes, denie this point of our fayth, because they sawe that yt was directe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie contrarie vnto al mans witte, and reason? Canst thou by reason tel me hou Adam was made of the earthe, &amp; Eue of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ybbe? Hou the busse of thornes, which flamed wyth fire, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">
         <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.</note> not? Hou the rod was made à ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent? Hou the ryuers of Egypte were <note place="margin">
         <hi>Exod.</hi> 4. 7.</note> turned yn to bloud? Hou Moyses ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. xl. daies and xl. nightes without meate, and drinke? Hou the children <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 77.</note> of Israel were fed with Manna? Hou their clot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>es were not worē away the space of xl. yeres? hou the iewes passed <note place="margin">
         <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.</note> thorou the red sea saflye? Hou water
<pb facs="6"/> tes beynge yet closed? Are not these <note place="margin">Note this.</note> thinges, as impossible to mans reason, and witte, as that the same his bodie to be at one tyme, both yn heauen, and earth, and yn euery place, where the sacrament is? Why then doest not thou beleue this, as wel as the other two? Doth not goddes word teach it the as plainlie, as the other? Also, did <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 20. <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 10.</note> not Christ eate, and drinke with his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, after his resurrection, and yet no part of that meate, and drinke was turned in to his bodilie nouryshemēt, for then he neaded no nouryshemēt? Was not this as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>trange à matter, and as farre abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ans reason, as christ to be bodilie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n dyuers places at one ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me? Wherfore then doest thou not ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asse disputinge vpon this deape, and vnsearchable mysterie, and geue fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me credence vnto it, althoughe thy reason can not perceaue it? Why doest thou not remembre also, that christ promysed his disciples to geue them
<pb n="13" facs="6"/> suche bread, as shoulde be his oune ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry natural fleash, which he wold geue <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 6.</note> to death for the lyfe of the woorld?</p>
   <p>Can this his promes be veryfied of cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bread? Was that geuen vpon the crosse for the life of the woorld? Hath not Christ, which is the trouth it selfe, and can not lye, perfourmed yet this his promes? And when gaue he that <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioan.</hi> 14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.</note> bread, which was his very fleash, that he gaue for vs to death, yf he did it not at his last soupper, when he sayed. Take, and eate, this ys my bodie, that <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> shal be geuen for you? Hou manifest are these wordes of oure dear s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uiour Christ? did he euer speake more play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne wordes vpon any article of oure fayth, then these are? Were it not thē mere madnes, and à strange folyshe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to beleue the bisshoppe of canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, coxe, hoper, Ridley, ponete, and suche other, that do teache contrarie to this? S. Paul affirmeth, that he, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</note> which receaueth this holy sacrament
<pb facs="7"/> vnworthily, is gyltie of christes bodie <note place="margin">Marke.</note> and bloud? Hou cā this be true, yf the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re be nothinge els yn the sacrament, but bread, and wyne? Is à man gyltie of christes bodie and bloud, which ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and drinketh nothinge els but bare bread, and wyne? Who, that wise is, wil saye, that I am gyltie yn eatin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to muche moutton, and yn drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of wyne, when I eate nothinge but milk, and drinke only water?</p>
   <p>Agayne, sayeth not S. Paule, that he, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> which receaueth this holy sacrament vnworthilie, eateh, and drinketh it to his oune dānation, because he discer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not our lordes bodie, that is to say, he doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> beleue that that thin ge is his bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>e, or els he doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> greater deuotion, and pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>renes of conscience, than other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mō meates? Hou should this be true, yf we did eate, and drinke but onlye bread made of corne, and mere wyne of the grape, yn the receauinge of the
<pb n="15" facs="7"/> blessed sacrament? Byddeth not us S. Paule to examyne, and proue oure cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sciences, <note place="margin">Marke.</note> before we receaue this sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? And what neade we to do this, when we shal eate but common bread and drinke wyne of the grape? Doth he synne deadly, that receaue the those thinges yn synne? Doth not then this place of paule proue sufficiently, that oure sauiour Christes bodie, and bloud are present reallie in this sacrament? This haue al doctours of Christe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> church expounded the scriptures, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernīge this matter, as it shal appeare, by goddes gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>e, hereafter, thoughe the bisshoppe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>, that they be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap>. Therfore bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue mā this doctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>, without al doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng therof. Lette no mās persuasiō, nor reasonynge turne thy mynde frō this belefe. Beware that thou trust not thy senses iudgement yn this matter. Remembre that Isaac was disceaued, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.</note> because he trusted more to his feelīge
<pb facs="8"/> of his sonne Iacobs handes, than he did his uoice? Shalt not thou be after lyke sort disceaued in this matter, yf thou do folou the iudgement of thy senses, and not only the hearinge, or readinge of these christes wordes, This is my bodie? It is sufficient for the to beleue that christes bodie is both at ones yn the holie sacrament, and also in heauen, because the scripture tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth both indifferently, and teacheth not hou these two may stande toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but only by goddes almyghtie pouer, to whom nothyng his impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as scripture witnesseth plainly. <note place="margin">
         <hi>Marci.</hi> 10. <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford his first doctrine of the sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and so did also the bysshop pe of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turberie.</hi>
      </note>
   </p>
   <p>This taught peter Martyr, at his first commyng to oxford, when he was but á lutheran in this matter, whose wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des I, and may other mo wrate in the diuynite schole, when he redde lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re there, but when he came ones to the court, and sawe that that doctri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne myslyked them, that myght do hym hurt yn his lyuīge, he anon after
<pb n="9" facs="8"/> turned his tipped, and sange an other songe. The bysshop also of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in his catechysme did ones sette furth the real presence of christes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die <note place="margin">Note.</note> in the sacrament, but he chaunged that doctrine, when he saw, that the world serued for hym. O lord, what man is so madde to beleue suche mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table teachers which chaunge their do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctrine at mēs pleasir, as they see àvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and profite? They turne, and wil turne, as the winde turneth, but to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tourne to my matter. Tel me, why may not christes bodie (as I sayed afo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re) be as wel yn the sacrament, and yn heauen both at ones, as that his bodie was with the bodie of the stone, that lay stil vpō his graue, when he rosevp agayne from death to lyf, yn one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre place, and as his bodie was in one propre place at ones, with the bodie of <note place="margin">
         <hi>Hierony. in Epitaphio Paulae. Ioan.</hi> 20. <hi>Ampros. in lu.</hi> 24. <hi>Aug.</hi>
      </note> the dore, or gate, when he entred yn to the house to his apostles, when the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes were yet shitte, and closed? Christ
<pb facs="9"/> went vp out of this world yn to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and sitteth there at the right han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of his father, &amp; yet paule saw hym bodily vpon earth after his ascension (as he testifieth), and by that sight he <note place="margin">1. <hi>cor.</hi> 9. 15.</note> proued that he was risen againe bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from death to lyf, which he could not haue done, yf that seinge of hym, <note place="margin">Lib. de pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sione petri apostoli.</note> had bene but à spiritual visiō. S. Linus which was in the apostles tyme, and wrote saynt peters, and paules passion, wytnesseth euidently, that saynt peter saw christ, and talked wyth hym when he was goyng out of Rome for fear of persecution, and that peter sayed to hym, lord, whyther goest thou? To whom christ anusweared, I go to Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to be Crucyfied agayne. Then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non after christ departed away from peter, and peter vnderstandyng that Christment, he wold be crucyfied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, not in his oune bodie, but in hym, retourned to Rome, and there was crucified, for christes sake. Of this <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cōmē</hi>
      </note>
      <pb n="10" facs="9"/> storie wrote Egesippus, which was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>epist.</hi>
      </note> nighe to the apostles tyme, and also S. Ambrose. This storie declareth, that <note place="margin">Christ ascen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded in to heauen, and yet he is al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>so ī the bles<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the aulter bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilie.</note> althoughe christ departed hence at the tyme of his ascension yn to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and sitte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> at the right hand of god his father, yet he may be also here yn the blessed sacrament of the aulter This is the very catholike fayth which christes church, that cā not whollie er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re yn the fayth, hath euer taught, doth and shal euer vntil the worldes ende. Wherfore leaue reasonīg, reader, vpō this matter, and geue credence to this oure mother the churche, and than thou shalt neuer be disceaued yn any point of thy fayth, because she neuer <note place="margin">
         <hi>The catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke church erreth not yn the faith Matth.</hi> 16.</note> erreth whollie theryn For promysed not christ, that hel gates, which are syn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, and heresies, by which men do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre yn to hel, should not preuaile agaīst <note place="margin">Matth. vlt.</note> her? Sayed he not also, that he wold be with the churche vntil the worldes ende? Hou then could she erre so sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefullie
<pb facs="10"/> these. M. ccccc. yeres, and mo, as to beleue that christ was bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in the sacrament, and to honoure hym therin, and yet he was not there, but bare bread, &amp; wyne? What cal, ye <note place="margin">Note.</note> my lord, this, yf it be not hel gates to preuaile against christes church?</p>
   <p>Hou could she be discea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ed so many yeres in this weightie matter of our fayth, with whom christ, the trueth it selfe, euer was, as he promysed to be? Did not christ saye, that he wold be in the middes of twoo or three assēbled in his name? Was he not thē emonge <note place="margin">In concilio lateranensi.</note> the M. ccc. xv. fathers, which were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together out of al costes of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stendome, and determyned that the <note place="margin">Matth. vlt.</note> bread and wyne were yn their natures and substances vtterly turned yn to christes very natural bodye, &amp; bloud, and that there remayned only their qualites, and properties? The apostles <note place="margin">
         <hi>Act.</hi> 15.</note> with the elders were assembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at hierusalem yn à councel for
<pb n="11" facs="10"/> the decysion of à question, touchynge the chargynge of the Gentyles with the keping of Moses law, and whē they had done, &amp; finyshed that their coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sail, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Actorum.</hi> 15</note> S. Iames ponounced their senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and sayed, that it pleased the holy goost, and them, that the gentyles should not be burdened with that ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial law, by which it appeareth playnly that the holy goost ruleth and directeth the councels lefullye assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, that they erre not yn the fayth why then doth he not euen so nou to <note place="margin">Marke rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der.</note> the councels, and hath euer done?</p>
   <p>Hath nowe christ forsaken his deare <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ioā.</hi> 14 16.</note> spouse the church? Dyd he not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myse to send his holy spirite to the churche, whiche should teach her al trueth, and abyde stil with her for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer? Hath he not then yet performed this his promyse, which he made to his apostles, and yn them to the whole churche, at al tymes being? Of did he not fulfil it vntil Berengarius came, <note place="margin">Berēgariu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <pb facs="11"/> which about M. yeares, after that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes <note place="margin">Was the first autour of this here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sie, which he did pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytently ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iure, and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cante.</note> was made, first of al men taught and maynteyned this heresie, which sayeth that christes very natural bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye is not reallye in the blessed sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the aulter? Was this promes made onlie to hym, and his scholers? Was it made to a feu carnal, vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men yn any one countrey, &amp; not rather to al the whole catholike chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and to al christen nations? Was berengarius, which was an hereretike in many other pointes, (as stories do wytnesse of hym), and also à man of à very il lyfe, a meter man, and more worthye to receaue the performance of that highe pròmes, than any of the apostles were, or than any other parsō, which then lyued, or els sense, yea thā al the churche of christ? But lette vs graunt, that this promes was not fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd nor the trueth in this matter decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vntil Berēgarius came, &amp; that the <note place="margin">Marke wel reader this.</note> holy ghoost, the spirite of the trueth,
<pb n="12" facs="11"/> was geuen vnto hym, and first did set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te furth by hym this verite. Tel me then, hou it chaunced, that the holy goost forsoke hym, suffered hym to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cante, to abiure, &amp; forswaere for euer that opinion, departinge out of this world with great repentance for that his heresie? Did not Christ saye, that the holy goost should euer abyde with them, to whō he was promysed? Did not Berengarius, which first wrote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this our fayth of the sacrament, <note place="margin">Li. de gestis regum f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ā corum in vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta Henrici Regis Fran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciae.</note> recāte his heresie wyllyngly (as Gagwi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus testifieth) and dyed wyth great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce for yt? For this was his last recantation. I Berengarius do beleue <note place="margin">Berēgarius later recan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation.</note> wyih my hert, and confesse wyth my mouth, that the bread, &amp; wyne, which are set vpon the aulter, are throughe prayer, and the wordes of christ in sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stance turned in to our sauiours body and bloud, which he toke of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, offered vpon the crosse, and that nowe doth sit in heauen at the fathers
<pb facs="12"/> ryght hand, and that this is not done only by á signe, and the vertu of the sacrament, but in the propriete of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the veryte of substance. This was his confession, and beliefe euen vntil his death. Our lord gyue al thē, that haue foloued his errour in this matter, grace to forsake it, by his exā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to dye in the true fayth of christ, as he did. After this mans death by the space of c yeres, and more, no man wrote against the very real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of Christes natural body in the sacrament. Then at the length came <note place="margin">Almericus heresie.</note> one Almericus, à wycked man, which sayed, that christes body was as wel in al manier of bread, and in euery other thing els, as in the blessed sacrament of the aulter. After hym noman spake (as much as we can fynde yn wryting) against the catholike faith of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the space of more then á hundred yeres. Then rose vp one Ihon wyclefe our countrey man, which of mere ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lice,
<pb n="13" facs="12"/> that he could not obteyne the bys<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shoprych of worcetur, and because he <note place="margin">Wyclefes heresie.</note> was excommunycated and banyshed out of oxford, sowed many heresies in England, emong which this, that my lord defendeth in his booke, was one, but he was condemned yn à councel kept at Constantia about. c. xxxiiij. yeares sence, and his heresie was then abhorred of al chrystendome. After hym came Carolostadius, Aecolāpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, <note place="margin">Aecolampa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dius. Swinglius.</note> and Swynglius, which when they had of lōg tyme set furth (as their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster luther had taught them) that chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes very natural body was really yn the sacrament, and not only à sygne of them, at the length (as heresie creapeth <note place="margin">2. <hi>timot.</hi> 2.</note> lyke vnto à canker (paul beyng wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse they forsoke that opinion, and denyed vtterly (as my lord doth) the bodilie presence of christ in this holie <note place="margin">My lordes opinion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan of late.</note> sacrament. May we then not now see good christian reader, that this doctry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne can not be true, which began first of
<pb facs="13"/> al wythyn the space of fyue hundred yeres passed, and hath bene euer conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from tyme to tyme, not rysing agayne the space of c. yeres, where the true fayth of christ hath euer cōtinued and was neuer wholy suppressed from the first begynnynge of it, nor neuer shal be vntil the worldes ende? For the church can not wholly erre (as it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared afore) and as saynt Paul affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth callyng her the pyller of the trueth. For hou can the pyller of the <note place="margin">1. <hi>tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>t.</hi> 3.</note> trueth susteyne, and support heresie, &amp; idolatrye? S. Austen sayed, that christes <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ianuario. Bpist.</hi> 119.</note> church approueth nothing, nor doth any thing either against the fayth, or els against good meaners. Doth not my lord then erre abomynablye, whē he sayth that the church hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted blasphemy, heresie, and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, at the least foure hundred yeres? Is this the church not to do any thing against the fayth, and good lyfe? Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore let vs beleue the catholike chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="14" facs="13"/> doctryne, no lesse then the holy scripture, which the church teacheth vs to beleue, or els we wold not beleue it. For sayed not Austen, that he wold <note place="margin">
         <hi>Contra epi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stol funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti. ca.</hi> 5.</note> not beleue the gospel except the autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite of the church had moued hym? Sayth not also Tertulian, against Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, that we do knowe, receaue, and beleue al the gospels of christ by the <note place="margin">Aduersus vigilantiū.</note> church, and not other wyse? Sayth not hierom lyke wyse, I reproue al opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions against the church, and openlie condemne them? Moreouer the anciēt docter Vincentius lyrinensis, aboue <note place="margin">Aduersus prophatto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp;c.</note> M c. yeres sence, described à uery true christien man, saynge, he is á good ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike man, that loueth gods tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eth, and the church, preferryng nothyng vtterly before the catholike fayth, no mans authorite, no mans loue, no mās reason, no mans wyt, no mans eloquē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, nor nothynge els, but abydyng su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly in the fayth, he determyneth to beleue, &amp; keepe steadfastly euery such
<pb facs="14"/> thyng, that the catholike church hath of old tyme vnyuersally beleued, and holden, and what so euer shold be set furth against that doctrine, he iudgeth yt not to pertayne any thinge vnto christes religiō, but to tentation. And yf it do chaūce any thing to be taught, &amp; defended contrary to that doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp; the scriptures to be alleged ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, then he must (sayth he) nead<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s folou those doctours expositiō, which agree together theryn in one sense, &amp; <note place="margin">Note this.</note> set nothynge by al other mens iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, be they neuer so wel learned, and godly. And yf any man shal aske (sayth he) of me, what neade is it to fo lou the authorite of christes church &amp; her vnderstandinge of the scriptures, seyng the scripture is perfect of it sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, and sufficient? I answere to hym, that we must neade so do, because al men do not expound the scripture yn one sense, but euery mā after his oune wit, and fantasie, and so there shold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryse
<pb n="15" facs="14"/> much dissension, debate, confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and many heresies spring vp, and <note place="margin">Marke rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der.</note> be defended in christes church, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept her exposition shold be admitted At the length he gyueth vnto vs à godly lesson, which yf men wold folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we they shold not so much erre, as they nowe do. In ipsa catholica eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia <note place="margin">A godly les<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son, to auo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yd heresies.</note> magnopere curandum est, vt id te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neamus, quod vbique, quod semper, quod ab omnibus creditum est. Sequē da est nobis antiquitas, vniuersitas, &amp; consensus. We must (sayth he) take great hede, that in that same catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke church, we do hold that thīg, which hath bene beleued in al places, euer, &amp; of al mē. We must folou the ancyēte, the generalite, and the cōsent. By the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se three notes, or els by one of them at the lest we may sone knowe heresie, &amp; al false doctrine frō the true and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doctryne. For either it is newely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, and not old (as my lords do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is, which began first by Berenga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rius
<pb facs="15"/> about, ccccc. yeres passed) or els it is but particularly receaued of one countrey, and of a fewe of them (as is also my lords opinion) or finallie, the authours of it do not agree emong thē selfes in the teaching, &amp; setting furth of it, as in dede they do not, that write and teach, as my lord doth in this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, and therfore it appeareth plainlie, that his doctryne is not catholike, nor godly. For as touchinge the consent, and agreynge of thē, that hath taught it, who knoweth not, that Aecolam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padius, Swinglius, Carolastadius, my lord, peter Martyr, and their scholers dissent cleane in yt from their father, and master, Marten luther? For luther confessed and defended the real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of christes body in the holy sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, euen vntil his death, which those other his disciples denye vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, althoughe they did of long tyme teach no other wise, but they recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as they sawe occasion, and auaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="16" facs="15"/> serue. Were it not then à great madnes to forsake the old catholike faith, which hath bene euer beleued of al nations, and in the teaching therof the fathers neuer dissented, and to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe my lords doctrine? Moreouer, what arrogāt blyndnes, and blynd ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancye is it, to say, that al christien nations haue erred yn the beliefe of this matiere, so many hundred yeres, as they saye, that they haue done, and that à very smal nombre of men, but sclenderly learned, should only kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we the trueth therof? What is this, good reader, yf it be not à merueilous blyndnes, and these men to leane, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Salomons counsail, vnto theyr oune wysdom? Are they not à frayed <note place="margin">
         <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 3. <hi>Esaiae.</hi> 5.</note> of this gods curse? Woo to yowe, that seame vnto your selfes wyse? Who may much merueile, yf such men be shamefullie disceaued in their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, that so proudly procede? For sayeth not christ, that his father hath
<pb facs="16"/> hiddē the knowlage of his word from proud men, and opened it vnto hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.</note> persons? Wytnesseth not also Saīt <note place="margin">
         <hi>Iacobi.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>petri.</hi> 5.</note> Iames, that god doth gyue grace vnto the humble, and resisteth the proud? Is it thē lyke, that he gyueth so great gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to them, to see only the trueth, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferynge the humble, that mystrust their oune wittes, iudgement, and lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng, &amp; do folowe meakely the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches decrees, and ordonnaunces, her vnderstandyng of the scriptures, the general conciles, and the docteurs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions of gods word, to be so much blynded, and so long à tyme? But pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de wyl haue à fal, as it hath euer had heretofore, &amp; espacially in thē, that ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue matched them selfes in matieres of religion against his dear espouse the church, agaynst whom hel gates, that is to say, synne, &amp; heresie, neuer could nor neuer shal preuaile. For did not <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.</note> christ, which euer was hard in his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers (as he sayth hym self), praye for
<pb n="17" facs="16"/> Peter, that his fayth, that is to say, the fayth of the catholike church, which <note place="margin">
         <hi>Lucae.</hi> 20. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.</note> he had receaued, and confessed, should not decaye? Agayne, doth not paul af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.</note> that christ loued his spouse the church so dearly that he gaue hymself for her to death, for to cleanse her frō al fylthynes of synne, that she should not haue one spotte therof? Houe can these sainges of christ, and paul stand wyth their opinion, that say (as my lord doth) that the church hath erred yn the fayth, and hath committed ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latry so many hundred yeares, euen sēce the begynnyng of it? Is this christ dearly to loue her? Is this the office of <note place="margin">
         <hi>Ro</hi> 12. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 12 <hi>Coloss.</hi> 1.</note> à good husband towardes his wyfe? Is this to purge her from euery spot of synne? Wold christ, which is head of the church, and the church his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, suffre that his oune hody runne in to heresie, superstition, blasphemye, &amp; <note place="margin">
         <hi>Marke.</hi> 1. <hi>paril.</hi> 9. <hi>Psal.</hi> 136</note> such other abymynable crimes, and to abide so long yn them? He suffered
<pb facs="17"/> the Synagoge of the ieues to fal yn to bodilie captyuite, and to lye afflicted theryn, but. lxx. yeres, and then he ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de her francke and free agayne, and wold he then suffre christes church, which he loued much more, then he did the Synagoge, to runne in to such abomynations, and to continue stil in them, at the least (as my lord sayeth in his booke) foure, or fyue hundreth yeares? Went not (as christ sayth in <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.</note> the parable) god furth in the morning early to cal men to wourke yn his vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyard? Howe is it then true, that he called not men vnto the ryght fayth of this sacramēt the space of M. yeres after this sacrament was instituted, vntil berengarius came, and then cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led but à very fewe in nombre? Called not christ his church the kyndome <note place="margin">
         <hi>Matthaei.</hi> 13 <hi>Note.</hi>
      </note> of heauen? Why then do these men make her the kyndom of hel, by ascri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>binge vnto her heresie, blasphemye, &amp; idolatrie? What blynd arrogancye,
<pb n="18" facs="17"/> and arrogant blyndnes is this? Who can abide it? What hart is so hard and stony, that it can forbeare weapyng, lamenting, and mournyng for them, that are this blynded, &amp; do dailie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke many other mē so blynd, that they do fal vnwares headlong in to the den of heresie, and damnation for euer? Cal, and crye, good reader, contynual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 67.</note> nyght, &amp; daye, vnto god, and saye. Aryse, ó lord, aryse, that thy enny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies may be dispersed, and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Say deuoutly wyth tongue and <note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal.</hi> 43.</note> mynde, Aryse vp, o lord, why doest thou sleap? Aryse vp, expel vs not from the for euer. Why turnest thow thy face from vs? Doest thou forget our pouerte, and trouble? Arise vp, ó lord, helpe vs, ó lord, and delyuer vs for thy names sake. Pray, I say, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian reader, and ceasse not, that thou be not led yn to tentation, and fal frō the ryght belief of the holy church, but that thou maest stand theryn mā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="18"/> and confesse it vntil thy death, and therby obteyne that infinite and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ioyes, which god hath promysed vnto al that contynue in his loue, and the kepyng of his commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vntil their lyfes endes. The whych our lord Iesus Christ for his deare, and bytter passions sake, graunt vnto vs, to whom wyth the father, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie goost, be honour, and prayse for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>