<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE FRANCIS Lord VERVLAM, Lord high Chancellor of England, and one of his MAIESTIES most Honou∣rable priuie Counsell: Grace and peace from God the Father, in the mediation of his Sonne Iesu Christ, and by the operation of the blessed Spirit for euer. Amen.</title>
           <author>Forsyth, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105640_Fr1_1</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01078</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11192</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105640</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE FRANCIS Lord VERVLAM, Lord high Chancellor of England, and one of his MAIESTIES most Honou∣rable priuie Counsell: Grace and peace from God the Father, in the mediation of his Sonne Iesu Christ, and by the operation of the blessed Spirit for euer. Amen.</title>
                 <author>Forsyth, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The great day of chancery : A sermon preached at White-Hall, the last day of October. 1619. By Iames Forsith, one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinarie</title>
                 <author>Forsyth, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bill, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14, 47, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <pb facs="1"/>
   <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE FRANCIS Lord VERVLAM, Lord high Chancellor of England, and one of his MAIESTIES most Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>priuie Counsell: Grace and peace from God the Father, in the mediation of his Sonne Iesu Christ, and by the operation of the blessed Spirit for euer. Amen.</hi>
   </head>
   <opener>
      <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> did preach the word of God at <hi>Antioch,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Act. 13.14</note> the people seemed to giue such attendance vnto their words of exhortation, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/> that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired to heare the same the
<pb facs="2"/>next <hi>Sabboath day.</hi> When I preached this Sermon at Court, the auditors did seeme to giue such attention vnto what was spoken, (although vnworthy of their meanest attention) that they did ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly desire to see in writing what that day they had heard by preaching, <hi>Visus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim est perfectior sensus:</hi> so that my weake labours, <hi>through Gods blessing,</hi> passed along the Court, like <hi>plaine honestie,</hi> with euery mans good leaue and liking: and if this place had beene the furthest period, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> had beene eased of some fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture paines. But then it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="2"/>some, <hi>Honorable and worthy friends,</hi> to impose vpon mee this second view: and surely <hi>pruritus scribendi,</hi> the disease of our age, had almost hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered me; for I know <hi>litera scripta manet,</hi> and is more sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to censure, then <hi>quod au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus auditur:</hi> for which cause I did not at the first yeelde. Yet at last, vpon more seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deliberation, (least I should haue encurred the breach of loue of some <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and much respected friends:</hi> as also the censorious conceit of some <hi>supercilious Stoickes:</hi>) I resolued <hi>prodere in vulgus,</hi> to lye <hi>Noah-like,</hi> in the Tent
<pb facs="3"/>doore, that euery scoffing <hi>Cham</hi> may smile at my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse: And because that a seruant of meane birth and qualitie is many times pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred aboue his worth, for <hi>his Lord and Masters sake;</hi> I haue therefore made choise of your <hi>Honorable Patronage,</hi> being at that time when it was deliuered, one of my most Noble Auditors. <hi>Vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam esset possibile me vnum esse ex principibus offerre geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas ad ornamentum Pontificis; sed quia haec supra me sunt, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te vel pilos caprarum habere merear in Tabernaculo Dei,</hi> as <hi>Origen</hi> elegantly; I wish that
<pb facs="3"/>I could speak any thing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of this Text, or your <hi>Honours Dedication.</hi> A <hi>day</hi> it is, and that a great one, when not onely all criminall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses will be heard, as in the Court of the Kings Bench; as also euery mans case shall be adiudged, as at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-pleas barre: but when, and where the iust Iudge of all the world, will accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the euidence of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans conscience, distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute righteous Iudgement; and therefore more properly I call it <hi>The great day of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery:</hi> plaine it is, that the <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest</hi> and most <hi>Ignorant,</hi> may
<pb facs="4"/>vnderstand it: yet (as I thinke) profitable, that the most <hi>wise</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> may reape some instruction by it: the best Remembrancer that Iudges can haue about them, is to remember the <hi>day of Iudgement; Summus enim iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex iudicata reiudicabit:</hi> and vnto whom much is giuen, of him much shall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in that day: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beseech the Lord of heauen and earth, to assist your <hi>Honour</hi> with his grace and holy Spirit, that you may Honourably long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, as hitherto a good Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticiar, in that place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
<pb facs="4"/>you are worthily called, to his glory, and your eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall comfort, that you may stand boldly before the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall in that day. Amen.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours in all seruice, in the Lord, <hi>IAMES FORSITH.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>