<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Gentlemen Readers Health.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105814_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02136</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12276</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105814</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Gentlemen Readers Health.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Morando the tritameron of loue : wherein certaine pleasaunt conceites, vttered by diuers woorthy personages, are perfectly dyscoursed, and three doubtfull questyons of loue, most pithely and pleasauntly discussed: shewing to the wyse howe to vse loue, and to the fonde, howe to eschew lust: and yeelding to all both pleasure and profitt. By Robert Greene, Maister of Artes in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the Gentlemen Readers</hi> Health.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Emosthenes Gentle</hi>
      <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) alwaies sought to win the goodwill of the Senate, by vnfolding the equitie of the caze, and I seeke to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine your fauour by appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to your courtesie, hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to finde you as readie to graunt me the one, as the Senate to graunt him the other. <hi>Protagenes</hi> founde the more fauour in setting foorth his simple Pictures, in that he did what hee coulde, and I hope to finde the more freendshipp at your handes for this imperfect worke, in that I doo what I can. Yet I knowe I shall be compared of some to <hi>Damides</hi> Parrat, which prated nothing but that she hearde her maister speake. Well though some bee Sauage, all are not Satyres, though diuers be sturdie, all are not Stoickes. Let flearing <hi>Sycophants</hi> carpe at my want, yet I doubt not but courteous Gentlemen will account of will, and as it is follie to reiect the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure of the one, so it is fondnes to respecte the freendshippe of the other. But to them that shall pardon my offence, and spare to spite at my fault. I wish them such prosperous happe, as they can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, or I imagine: to the rest, I will to them as they wish to me, and yet I bidd them both farewell.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Robert Greene.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>