<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The same letters patents in english.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1582</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105954_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02494</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12624</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105954</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The same letters patents in english.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Diuers voyages touching the discouerie of America, and the ilands adiacent vnto the same : made first of all by our Englishmen, and afterward by the Frenchmen and Britons: and certaine notes of aduertisements for obseruations, necessarie for such as shall heereafter make th like attempt, with two mappes annexed heereunto for the plainer vnderstanding of the whole matter</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Woodcock, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1582</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>124 pages 2 folded woodcut maps, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>The same letters patents in english.</head>
   <opener>
      <signed>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Enrie by the grace of GOD king of England, and France, and Lorde of Irelande,</signed>
      <salute>to all, to whom these presentes shall come, greeting.</salute>
   </opener>
   <p>Be it knowen that wee haue giuen and gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by these presentes doe giue and grant for vs and our heyres, to our well beloued Iohn Gabote citizen of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, to Lewes, Sebastian, and Santius, sonnes of the saide Iohn, and to the heires of them and euery of them, and their deputies, full and free authoritie, leaue, and power to sayle to all partes, countreys and seas of the East, of the West,<note place="margin">Licence grā<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
            <desc>•••</desc>
         </gap> to Iohn Gabot, his sonnes and heires, to disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnknowen lands vnder the kings banner.</note> and of the North vnder our banners and ensignes, with fiue ships, of what burden or quantitie soeuer they be: and as many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners or men as they will haue with them in the saide ships, vpon their owne proper costes and charges to seeke out, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer and finde whatsoeuer iles, countreyes, regions, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, of the heathen and infidelles whatsoeuer they bee, and in what part of the worlde soeuer they be, whiche before this time haue been vnknowen to all Christians. We haue gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them also and to euery of them, the heires of them, and euery of them and their deputies, &amp; haue giuen them li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to set vp our banners and ensignes in euery village, towne, castel, yle, or maine lande of them newely founde. And that the foresaid Iohn and his sonnes or their heires and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes may subdue, occupie, and possesse all such townes, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, castles and yles of them founde, which they can subdue,<note place="margin">To subdue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
            <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
         </gap> possesse those landes as the kings vassalles.</note> occupie, and possesse, as our vassailes and lieutenantes, get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto vs the rule, title, and iurisdiction of the same villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, townes, castles, and firme lande so founde.</p>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <p>Yet so that the foresaide Iohn and his sonnes and heires, and their Deputies bee holden and bounden, of all the fruites, profites, gaines &amp; commodities growing of such nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for euery their voyage as often as they shall arriue at our port of Bristoll, (at the which port they shall be bounde and holden only to arriue) all manner of necessarie costes and charges by them made being deducted, to pay vnto vs in wares or money the fifth part of the Capitall gaine so gotten.<note place="margin">The fift of all goods to be paid to the king.</note> Wee giuing and graunting vnto them and to their heires and Deputies, that they shall bee free from all paying of customes of all and singuler such merchandize,<note place="margin">Freedome from all customes.</note> as they shall bring with them from those places so newely founde.</p>
   <p>And moreouer wee haue giuen and graunted to them, their heires and Deputies, that all the firme landes, Iles, Villages, Townes, Castles and places whatsoeuer they be,<note place="margin">None but they &amp; their assignes may trauaile thither.</note> that they shall chaunce to finde, may not of any other of our subiectes bee frequented or visited without the licence of the foresayd Iohn, his sonnes and their deputies vnder paine of forfayture as well of their shippes, as of all and singuler goods of all them that shall presume to sayle to those places so founde. Willing and most straightly commaunding all and singuler our subiectes as well on lande as on sea ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed officers, to giue good assistāce to the aforesaid Iohn and his sonnes and deputies, and that as well in arming and furnishing their ships or vessels, as in prouision of quietnesse, and in buying of victualles for their money and all other thinges by them to be prouided necessarie for the saide naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, they doe giue them all their helpe and fauour. In witnesse whereof wee haue caused to bee made these our let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patentes.<note place="margin">The 5. of march 1594.</note> Witnesse our selfe at Westminster the fifte day of March in the xi. yeere of our reigne.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>