<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           <author>Davison, Fra.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1611</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105119_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19945</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6375</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105119</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 <author>Davison, Fra.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A poetical rapsodie : containing: diuerse sonnets, odes, elegies, madrigals, epigrams, pastorals, eglogues, with other poems, both in rime and measured verse. For varietie and pleasure, the like neuer yet published</title>
                 <author>Davison, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jackson, Roger</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1611</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 71, 74-167, 178-211, 1 page, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EING induced by some priuate reasons, and by the instant entreaty of speciall friends, to suffer some of my worthlesse poems to be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, I desired to make some writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by my deere friends <hi>Anonymoi,</hi> and my deerer <hi>Brother,</hi> to beare them company: Both without their consent, the latter being in the low-Country warres, and the rest vtterly ignorant thereof. My friends names I concealed; mine owne and my brothers, I willed the Printer to suppresse, as well as I had concealed the other, which he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing put in without my priuity, we must now vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go a sharper censure perhaps then our namelesse workes should haue done, and I especially. For if their Poems be liked, the praise is due to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention: if disliked, the blame both by them, and all men, will be deriued vpon mee, for publishing that which they meant to suppresse.</p>
   <p>If thou thinke we affect fame by these kinds of writings, though I thinke them no disparagement euen to the best iudgements, yet I answere in all our behalfes, with the princely shepheard <hi>Dorus▪</hi>
   </p>
   <q>Our hearts do seeke another estimation.</q>
   <p>If thou condemne Poetry in generall, and affirme that it doth intoxicate the braine, and make men vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vnfit, eyther for more serious studies, or for any actiue course of life, I onely say, <hi>Iubeo te stultum esse libenter.</hi> Since experience proues by examples of many, both dead and liuing, that diuers delighted,
<pb facs="4"/>
and excelling herein, being Princes or States-men, haue gouerned and counselled as wisely, being soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, haue commanded armies as fortunately, being Lawyers, haue pleaded as iudicially and eloquently, being Diuines, haue written &amp; taught as profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and being of any other profession, haue dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gèd it as sufficiently as any other men whatsoeuer: If liking other kinds, thou mislike the Lyricall, because the chiefest subiect thereof is Loue; I reply, that louc being vertuously intended, and worthily placed, is the whetstone of wit, and spurre to all generous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and many excellent spirits with great fame of wit, and no staine of iudgement, haue written ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently in this kind, and specially the euer-praise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthly <hi>Sidney:</hi> So as if thou will needs make a fault, for mine owne part,</p>
   <q>Hand timeo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>i iam neque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> defendere crimen Cum tanto commune viro.</q>
   <p>If any except against the mixing (both at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning &amp; end of this booke) of diuerse things writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by great &amp; learned personages, with our meane and worthlesse scriblings, I vtterly disclaime it, as being done by the Printer, eyther to grace the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front with Sir <hi>Philip Sidneys,</hi> and others names, or to make the booke grow to a competent volume.</p>
   <p>For these Poems in particular, I could alledge these excuses, that those vnder the name of <hi>Anonymos</hi> were written (as appeareth by diuers things to Sir <hi>Philip Sidney</hi> liuing, and of him dead) almost twenty yeares since, when Poetry was farre from that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, to which it hath now attained; that my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is by profession a Souldier, and was not 18 years old when he writ these toyes: that mine owne were made most of them sixe or seuen yeares since, at idle
<pb facs="4"/>
times as I iourneyed vp and downe during my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uails. But to leaue their works to iustifie themselues, or the Authors to iustifie their works, and to speake of mine owne; thy mislikes I contemne, thy praises (which I neither deserue, nor expect) I esteeme not, as hoping (God vvilling) ere long, to regaine thy good opinion, if lost; or more deseruedly to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue it, if alreadie obtained, by some grauer worke. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>FRA. DAVISON.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>