<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Honourable and hys singuler good Lord, George Clifford, Earle of Cumberland: Thomas Greepe wysheth long life, encrease of honor, with happy and eternall felicitie.</title>
           <author>Moffett, Peter</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1587</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105774_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02201</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12343</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105774</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Honourable and hys singuler good Lord, George Clifford, Earle of Cumberland: Thomas Greepe wysheth long life, encrease of honor, with happy and eternall felicitie.</title>
                 <author>Moffett, Peter</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The true and perfecte newes of the woorthy and valiaunt exploytes, performed and doone by that valiant knight Syr Frauncis Drake : not onely at Sancto Domingo, and Carthagena, but also nowe at Cales, and vppon the coast of Spayne. 1587</title>
                 <author>Greepe, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Hacket, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1587</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>24 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Travel, topography, maps and navigational manuals</term>
                    <term>Funeral orations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Honourable and hys singuler good Lord, George Clifford, Earle of Cumberland: Thomas Greepe wysheth long life, encrease of honor, with happy and eternall felicitie.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, reuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> regarding your most worthie &amp; condign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> fame, together with your most rare vertues, and find<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing such correspondence in both, as seemeth inseperable, I coulde not chuse but in all humilitie to offer to the handes of so noble a personne, (beeing a louer of all vertuous attempts) this rude vnpublished worke, more true in effect then fine in forme, and better for example (though rudelie written) then to be obscured, if penned by the best. The worke is a true breefe discourse of the most rare and worthy exploytes, performed by the right worshipfull Sir <hi>Frauncis Drake</hi> Knight, and his consortes in the fortunate Isles, which although the trueth thereof be not vnknowne to your Honor, yet the vulgar sorte of people in the Realme hauing hearde, and yet wanting the veritie of the fame, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ay by the pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet be the better aduertised. The which by howe much the playner it is written by mee, the better it is to be vnderstoode
<pb facs="3"/>
of the simplest, who in this case I seeke most to pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>se, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> my selfe a rude Countriman, brought vppe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>nie yeeres in Husbandrie, and more knowledge in Culturing of lande, then in descriptions of conquestes of Countries: Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, weighing your honourable Lordships affabilitie &amp; cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tesie in nature, to take well in worth the meanest thinges (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to the encouragement of vertue &amp; valor, vvhereof you are patron) I presume the more to presse your Honour, to vouchsafe the acceptation and patronising of this small work of so great worth, in respect of the honourable action of so vvorthie men. Who neither number could daunt, nor force of vvall and shot keepe out, whereby it may be seene vnto the vvorlde, that God vvhich hath alvvayes defended his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts in former ages▪ hath not let to shevv a miracle by these in our latter dayes. And so humbly crauing pardon of your honor for this presumption ministred, I rest a continuall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seecher of the almightie for your Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>hips most happy health vvith increase of honor in this life, and in the other euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting felicitie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
   </p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Honors for euer</hi> at commaundement in <hi>the Lorde, Thomas Greepe.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>