<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>[Poem]</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1595</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105039_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18748</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5245</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105039</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>[Poem]</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A musicall consort of heauenly harmonie (compounded out of manie parts of musicke) called Churchyards charitie</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hatfield, Arnold</publisher>
                    <distributor>Holme (Holmes, Hulme), William 3</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1595</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 43, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="poem">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <lg>
      <l>WHat song should please, a sacred princes eares</l>
      <l>Which likes no tunes, but musick sweet &amp; sound</l>
      <l>Weake were my muse, to offer sighes and teares</l>
      <l>Where ioyfull mirth, and gladnes doth abound</l>
      <l>But troubled mind, that rowles on restles ground</l>
      <l>In sorrow sings, the secrets of the hart</l>
      <l>Because sad man, can sing no sweeter part.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Of charitie, that makes a solemne noies</l>
      <l>A strange consort, I hope well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>unde I bring</l>
      <l>Of heauenlie loue, that passeth earthlie Ioies</l>
      <l>In formall wise, a true set song I sing</l>
      <l>Would God the sound, through al the world might ring</l>
      <l>That charitie, which ech one ought to keepe</l>
      <l>Might waken now, that long hath laine a sleepe.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Shee hath bin brought, in slumber sundrie waies</l>
      <l>With lullabie, as nurse doth rocke hir childe</l>
      <l>The cradle gaie, of pleasant nights and daies</l>
      <l>With too much ease, hath charitie beguilde</l>
      <l>And now God wot, the world is waxt so wilde</l>
      <l>That charitie, must needs make ech thing tame</l>
      <l>That wilde discord, hath brought cleane out of frame.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Pity and ruth, are fled or banisht quite</l>
      <l>And in their place, comes rigor rudelie cled</l>
      <l>Godlie remorse, is drownd in worlds delite</l>
      <l>Good cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ence feares, that charitie is dead</l>
      <l>Loue looketh downe, and hate holds vp the head</l>
      <l>Troth barelie liues, and tretchrie thriues apace</l>
      <l>Deserts doth starue, and meanewell hides his face.</l>
      <l>O charitie help<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>
      </l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <l>Franknes is blinde, affection dims his sight</l>
      <l>Larges is lost, hardnes supplies his place</l>
      <l>Wrong runs so swift, it ouer-gallops right</l>
      <l>Goodnes limps downe, and halts in many a case</l>
      <l>Do well doth droupe, or walks with mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>fled face</l>
      <l>Vertue and vice, now wrastles for a fall</l>
      <l>And so the strong, will thrust the weake to wall.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Stoutnes with strength, strikes flat the feeble force</l>
      <l>Downe is kept downe, and neuer like to rise</l>
      <l>Malice and might, rides both vpon one horse</l>
      <l>(Sir Packolets nagge, that gallops through the skies)</l>
      <l>Iudgement growes grosse, ore weening wanteth eies</l>
      <l>Will is a wagge, waste hath the wager woon</l>
      <l>For all the date, of our redresse is done.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Loyaltie weeps, and flattrie laughes and smiles</l>
      <l>Goodwill is scornd, and puts vp many a taunt</l>
      <l>Pouertie is plagude, or ouermatcht with wiles</l>
      <l>Plainnes complaines, but pride bids him auaunt</l>
      <l>Crueltie the curre, with crie of hounds will chaunt</l>
      <l>But bandog bites, full sore before he barke</l>
      <l>And craft the carle, still iuggles in the darke.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Friendship lookes pale, it hath an ague fit</l>
      <l>Fauour is faint, and lame it cannot go</l>
      <l>Finenes is false, and full of subtill wit</l>
      <l>Faith giues faire words, and breaketh promis so</l>
      <l>Constancie reeles, and staggers to and fro</l>
      <l>Charitie must needs, reforme these follies strange</l>
      <l>That by abuse, doth noble nature change.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <l>Dutie doth die, to driue on diuelish drifts</l>
      <l>Stubbornes striues, to wrangle for a strawe</l>
      <l>Cunning long liues, by cusnage and by shifts</l>
      <l>Disorder thriues, with neither rule nor laue</l>
      <l>People growes proud, without true feare or awe</l>
      <l>If suffrance see, these prancks and hold his peace</l>
      <l>Goodnes decaies, and badnes shall encrease.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If charitie be, the foode or fruite of faith</l>
      <l>Where bloomes that tree, where doth those branches bud</l>
      <l>True charitie sure, as wisest people saith</l>
      <l>Is working still, and euer dooing good</l>
      <l>Loue helpes our health, as life maintaines the blood</l>
      <l>But where no helpe, nor succour we may finde</l>
      <l>There charitie, is almost out of minde.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If through my faith, great mountaines I may moue</l>
      <l>And can raise vp, to life the dead from graue</l>
      <l>That withred faith, brings foorth no fruite of loue</l>
      <l>It gaines no grace, what euer hope I haue</l>
      <l>If charitie be, the thing which good men craue</l>
      <l>God graunt that I, and all that heares the same</l>
      <l>May sing that song, like Sidrack in the flame.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>My humble hart, hopes now but for dispatch</l>
      <l>Of life that wastes, away like candle blase</l>
      <l>The clocke will stricke, in haste I heare the watch</l>
      <l>That sounds the bell, whereon the people gase</l>
      <l>My forces faile, my wits are in a mase</l>
      <l>My corps consumes, my skin and bones doth shew</l>
      <l>The soule is glad, the bodie hence shall go.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="7"/>
      <l>Truth waited long, on your sweete sacred raigne</l>
      <l>To catch some crums, that from your table fals</l>
      <l>I sowe in teares, and reaps but bitter paine</l>
      <l>That makes sicke soule, lie groning by the wals</l>
      <l>Where hands a crosse, for helpe to heauen cals</l>
      <l>So sucks vp sighes, and sorrow of the minde</l>
      <l>As boyling brest, blowes fast for aire and winde.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>My muse doth muse, how labour lost his time</l>
      <l>And seruice great, doth get so small regarde</l>
      <l>I neuer thriude, by prose nor pleasant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ime</l>
      <l>Nor could in world, be any way prefard</l>
      <l>An open signe, my thankles hap is hard</l>
      <l>Yet numbers of, my verie name and race</l>
      <l>By prince in court, were cald to woorthie place.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>I am the Drone, that bees beats from the hiue</l>
      <l>The vglie Oule, that kites and crowes do hate</l>
      <l>The drawing oxe, that clounes do daily driue</l>
      <l>The haples hinde, that hath the hatefull fate</l>
      <l>(That weares a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>l sutes, and seasons out of date)</l>
      <l>If destny so, alots men such hard chance</l>
      <l>They passe the pikes, that fortune will aduance.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>My passage is, like one that rides in post</l>
      <l>Through water, fire, and all the hazards heere</l>
      <l>And so draws home, a weary grisly ghost</l>
      <l>Whose losse of youth, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>es loathsome age too deere</l>
      <l>Now coms acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>nt, of daies, of houres and yeere</l>
      <l>My debts are stald, as oft bare bankrouts be</l>
      <l>The graue paies all, and sets my bondage free.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <l>The wo of wars, and pride and pompe of peace</l>
      <l>The toile of world, and troubles here and there</l>
      <l>And churlish checks, of fortune I release</l>
      <l>Their heauie crosse, I can no longer beare</l>
      <l>In peeces small, my scribbled scrowles I teare</l>
      <l>So flinging verse, and bookes before your feet</l>
      <l>I craue some crownes, to bie my shrouding sheet.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>All hope is gone, of any earthly hap</l>
      <l>The axe is come, to giue the falling blow</l>
      <l>Downe flies the bowes, the tree hath lost his sap</l>
      <l>Vp to the clouds, like smoke the breath shall go</l>
      <l>A sillie puffe, of winde ends all this wo</l>
      <l>O grashous Queene, then some compassion take</l>
      <l>Before my soule, this combrous caue forsake.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>If nothing come, of seruice, sute and troth</l>
      <l>True man must trudge, and leaue his natiue soile</l>
      <l>Abroad the world, to see how fortune goth</l>
      <l>In any place, where faith is free from foyle</l>
      <l>Heere with vaine hope, my selfe and life I spoile</l>
      <l>First lost my youth, so time and all is gone</l>
      <l>Age sindes no friends, nor helpe of any one.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe.</l>
   </lg>
   <lg>
      <l>Of charitie, a great discourse is made</l>
      <l>Vnto an Earle, I honor in this land</l>
      <l>It is not hid, nor sits in silent shade</l>
      <l>Would God it were, in your faire blessed hand</l>
      <l>There lies the notes, as thicke as is the sand</l>
      <l>And there I sing, three parts in one at lest</l>
      <l>And in sweete sound, true musicke is exprest.</l>
      <l>O charitie helpe, or else adue the pen</l>
      <l>For I must march, againe with marshall men.</l>
   </lg>
   <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>