<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Preface to
the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105340_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20438</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6842</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105340</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Preface to
the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Euerard Digbie his dissuasiue : From taking away the lyuings and goods of the Church. Wherein all men may plainely behold the great blessings which the Lord hath powred on all those who liberally haue bestowed on his holy temple: and the strange punishments that haue befallen them vvhich haue done the contrarie. Hereunto is annexed Celsus of Verona, his dissuasiue translated into English</title>
                 <author>Digby, Everard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 <publisher>Gilbert, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Newman, Thomas.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Robinson, Robert</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 80, 87-242 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
   <head>The Preface to
the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F my pen (Gentle Reader) had erst bin dipped in the
siluer streames flowing from Parnassus hill, or that
<hi>Apollo</hi> with his sweet sounding harp would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe
to direct the passage thereof vnto the top of that
high <hi>Olympus:</hi> after so general a view of great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie
f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>r and neere, I might bouldly begin with that most excellent
Poet <hi>Cicelides Muse paulo maiora canamus.</hi> But sith I finde it
true in this my simple state of life, now wel nere spent, which the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
said vnto his sonne, affecting his goulden tressed chariot drawē
with breathing horses through the christall skies: <hi>Magna petis
Phaeton &amp; quae non viribus istis, munera conueniunt:</hi> I feare
to flie so high a pitch, &amp; leaue the loftie discourse of higher argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to those, which with the Eagles eies of perfect wit are able to
behould the bright radiant Sunne of true inuention. And sithens
sometimes in giuing attentiue eare to the sweetstrains of melodious
musicke, I have most affected the pleasant mean: sith in the life of
man the goulden mean is that sure rule, by which the wise do passe
they sie seas of worldly calamities. In a mean stile I mind to record
to you a true Christian argument, which though in these daies
it be but meanly regarded of the most: yet it is and alwaies hath bin
had in great honor with the highest, the greatest &amp; mightiest Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
in the world. And what is that meane that soundeth so high?
If you wil listen, the note is sweete, and the dittie resoundeth the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
Church of Iesu Christ. Though my musike bee verie simple, and
I not practised in the art, though the song bee plaine truth, and the
Echoe thereof most vsually <hi>odium parit:</hi> yet sith naked truth by
her owne meere strength preuaileth against all the armies, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
men of the world, sith her simplicitie is not able to bee refuted
by the finest wittes and most eloquent tongues, I am bould to sound
my slender oten pipe amongest <hi>Mineruaes</hi> muses, and therewith to
gratifie you with <hi>Celsus of Verona</hi> his dissuasiue, plainly transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
into our English tongue. The truth whereof incited me in simple
stile, no lesse effectuallie to record the good blessings of the Lord pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
on those which loue his church, than <hi>Celsus</hi> hath done to the
contrarie.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="7"/>Considering that these be those euil daies foreshewed by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle,
of which it was said, charitie, shall wax cold, and that the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
flow of iniquitie ouer the face of the whole earth doth argue
vnto vs the dauning of the latter daie: For our soules health I
thought it expedient to shew vnto those which shall read this rudely
written treatise, how daungerous a thing it is in the sight of God, &amp;
how loath some in the eies of all true christians to detract any thing
from the true worship of God, his holy temple, and the reuerend fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
the true disposers of the sacred mysteries in the same. In which
discourse though in the eares of some, I may seeme to sing the tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
rather than the meane, to nisse the moode, and to mistake the
figure, and therewith to sound some sharps insteed of flattes: yet in
that my purpose is to profit the good, and so little as I may to offend
the euill, I hope (God willing) to shewe the truth so plainely, so briefly,
and so truely, as that the well disposed may vouchsafe to read, and
the euill may desire to learne. To the end that this little fountaine
might flow more abundantlie, and therewith deriue it selfe into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
passages: I ment before this to haue published the same, indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentlie
to all. But afterwards considering the simple plainnes of the
same scarce worthie the reading of the learned: (on good cause ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
halfe vowed neuer to publish any thing hereafter) I thought
it good rather to present my friend with it, as a priuate token of my
goodwill, then by publishing it, to make my selfe a marke for such
boults, as in this case vsually flie abroad. Hauing sometimes wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
this waye heeretofore, I finde that Poeticall prouerbe most true,
pronounced by that anncient <hi>Alceus:</hi>
      <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: vnder
euery stone there lieth a Serpent. If the enuious toong were but as
the winde which changeth often, or as the sting of the little Bee
whose greatest swellings are easily asswaged with the annointing of
sweet honey. Then might I aduenture my little boate into the wide
Ocean seas: and crie alowd with old <hi>Anchises: Vela date ventis.</hi>
But sith the venimous tong more mortal then the Cockatrice, empoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soneth
farther then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>the eye can see, infesting the absent with deadly
disgrace: heereafter, <hi>Spes &amp; fortuna valete,</hi> shall be my song, and
<gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap> my full conclusion.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>