<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all my good frends
health.</title>
           <author>Cony-Catcher, Cuthbert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1592</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105058_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19241</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5656</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105058</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all my good frends
health.</title>
                 <author>Cony-Catcher, Cuthbert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The defence of conny catching. Or A confutation of those two iniurious pamphlets published by R.G. against the practitioners of many nimble-witted and mysticall sciences. By Cuthbert Cunny-catcher, licentiate in Whittington Colledge</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Gubbin (Gubbins), Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1592</date>
                 <publisher>Busby, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jeffes, Abel</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>36 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To all my good frends
health.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Plato</hi> (my good friendes)
trauelled from Athens to
Aegypt, and from thence
through sundry clymes to
increase his knowledge: so
I as desirous as hee to search
the deapth of those liberall
Artes wherein I was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessour,
lefte my studie in
<hi>Whittington Colledge,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Newgate builded by one Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington</note> &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
the country to grow famous in my facultie, so that
I was so expert in the <hi>Art of Cony-catching</hi> by my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall
practise, that that learned Philosopher <hi>Iacke
Cuttes,</hi> whose deepe insight into this science had drawn
him thrise through euery gaole in England, meeting of
mee at <hi>Maidstone,</hi> gaue mee the bucklers, as the subtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest
that euer he sawe in that quaint and mysticall forme
of Foolosophie: for if euer I brought my Conny but
to crush a potte of ale with mee, I was as sure of all the
crownes in his purse, as if hee had conueyed them into
my proper possession by a deede of gifte with his owne
hande.</p>
   <p>At <hi>Dequor,</hi>
      <note place="margin">
         <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 span">
            <desc>〈…〉</desc>
         </gap>
      </note>
      <hi>Mumchaunce, Catch-dolt, Oure le bourse,
Non est possible, Dutch Noddie,</hi> or <hi>Irish one and thirtie,</hi>
none durst euer make compare with me for excellence:
but as so many heades so many wits, so some that would
<pb facs="3"/>
not stoope a farthing at cardes,<note place="margin">Al the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in their purse.</note> would venter all the
<hi>byte in their boung</hi> at dice. Therefore had I cheates for
the very sise, of the squariers, langrets, gourds, stoppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,
high-men, low-men, and dice barde for all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntages:
that if I fetcht in anie nouyce eyther at ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
or anie other game of hazard, I would bee sure
to strippe him of all that his purse had in Esse, or his
credyt in Posse, ere the simple Connie and I parted.</p>
   <p>When neyther of these would serue, I had consorts
that could verse, nippe, and foyst, so that I had a super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall
sight into euery profitable facultie. Insomuch
that my principles grew authenticall, and I so famous,
that had I not beene crost by those two pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uish Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets,
I might at the nexte Midsommer haue worne
Doctor <hi>Stories</hi> cappe for a fauor. For I trauelled almost
throughout all England, admired for my ingenious ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie:
till comming about Exceter, I began to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise
my art, and drawing in a Tanner for a tame Conie,
assoone as he had lost two shillings he made this replie.
Sirha,<note place="margin">So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>e Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatchers dare weare noblemens liueryes, as W. Bicker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> although you haue a liuery on your backe, and a
cognisance to countenance you withall, and beare the
port of a Gentleman, yet I see you are a false knaue and
a Conny-catcher, and this your companion your setter,
and that before you and I part Ile proue.</p>
   <p>At these wordes Conny-catcher and Setter, I was
driuen into as great a maze, as if one had dropt out of
the clowds, to heare a pesant cant the wordes of art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lōging
to our trade: yet I set a good face on the matter
and asked him what he ment by Cony-catching. Marry
(q. he) althogh it is your practise, yet I haue for 3. pence
bought a litle Pamphlet, that hath taught me to smoke
such a couple of knaues as you be. When I heard him
talke of smoaking, my heart waxed cold, and I began to
gather into him gently. No no sir (q. he) you cānot verse
vpon me, this booke hath taught me to beware of cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting:
<pb facs="3"/>
And so to be breefe he vsed me curteously, and
that night causd the Constable to lodge mee in prison,
&amp; the nexte morning I was carried before the Iustice,
where likewise he had this cursed book of Cony catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
so that hee could tel the secretes of mine art better
then my selfe: whereupon after strict examination I was
sent to the gaole, &amp; at the Sessions by good hap &amp; some
friend that my money procured mee, I was deliuered.
Assoone as I was at liberty, I got one of these bookes,
&amp; began to tosse it ouer very deuoutly, wherin I found
one art so perfectly anotomized, as if he had bene prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner
in our facultie forty winters before: then with
a deepe sigh I began to curse this <hi>R. G.</hi> that had made a
publike spoyle of so noble a science, and to exclaime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
that palpable asse whosoeuer, that would make
any pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>-man priuy to our secret sciences. But see the
sequel, I smoothered my sorrowe in silence, and away I
trudged out of Deuonshire, &amp; went towards Cornwal,
&amp; comming to a simple Ale-house to lodge, I found at
a square table hard by the fire halfe a doozen countrie
Farmars at cardes. The sight of these penny-fathers at
play, draue me straight into a pleasant p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ssion, to blesse
fortune that had offred such sweet opportunity to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise
my wits, &amp; fil my purse with crowns: for I coūted
all the mony they had, mine by proper interest. As thus
I stood looking on them playing at cros-ruffe, one was
taken reuoking, whereat the other said; what neighbour
wil you play the cony-catcher with vs? no no, wee haue
read the booke as wel as you. Neuer went a cup of small
beare so sorowfully down an Ale-knights belly in a fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty
morning, as that word stroke to my hart, so that for
feare of trouble I was fain to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ry my good hap a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> square
play, at which fortune fauoring mee▪ I wan twenty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap>,
and yet doe as simply as I could, I was not onelie
suspected, but called Conny-catcher and crosse-biter.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>
But away I went with the money, and came pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently
to London, where I no sooner arriued amongst
the crue, but I heard of a second parte worse then the
first, which draue mee into such a great choller, that I
began to enquire what this <hi>R. G.</hi> should bee. At last I
learned that hee was a scholler, and a Maister of Artes,
and a Conny-catcher in his kinde, though not at cards,
and one that fauoured good fellowes, so they were not
palpable offendors in such desperate lawes: wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
reading his bookes, and surueying euery line with
deepe iudgement, I began to note folly in the man, that
would straine a Gnat, and lette passe an Elephant: that
would touch small scapes, and lette grosse faultes passe
without any reprehension. Insomuch that I resolued
to make an Apologie, and to aunswere his libellous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiues,
and to proue that we Conny-catchers are like
little flies in the grasse, which liue: or little leaues and
doe no more harme: whereas there bee in Englande
other professions that bee great Conny-catchers and
caterpillers, that make barraine the field wherein they
baite.</p>
   <p>Therfore all my good friends vouch of my paines,
and pray for my proceedings, for I meane to haue about
with this <hi>R. G.</hi> and to giue him such a veny, that he shalbe
afrayd heereafter to disparage that mysticall science of
Conny-catching: if not, and that I proue too weake for
him in sophistrie, I meane to borrowe <hi>Wili Bickertons</hi>
blade, of as good a temper as <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>glay</hi> King <hi>Arthures</hi>
sword was, and so ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#tech" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>llenge him to the single combat:
But desirous to ende the quarrell with the penne if it
be possible, heare what I haue learned in <hi>Whittington</hi>
Colledge,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Yours in cardes and dice
<hi>Cuthbert cony-catcher.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>