<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ The principal Authors of these Libels.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1601</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105130_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B15184</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19391.5</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105130</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ The principal Authors of these Libels.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A briefe apologie, or defence of the Catholike ecclesiastical hierarchie, &amp; subordination in England : erected these later yeares by our holy father Pope Clement the eyght; and impugned by certayne libels printed &amp; published of late both in Latyn &amp; English; by some vnquie persons vnder the name of priests of the seminaries. VVritten and set forth for the true information and stay of all good Catholikes, by priests vnited in due subordination to the Right Reuerend Archpriest, and other their superiors</title>
                 <author>Parsons, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Conincx, Arnout</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Belgium--Antwerp</pubPlace>
                    <date>1601</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>20, 232, that is 222 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="authors_note">
   <head>¶ The principal Authors of these Libels.</head>
   <p>THe chiefe doers in making and spreading these infamous libels are held to be these fiue or six following aboue the rest, to wit, M. Christo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Bagshaw, Iohn Colington, Rob. Charnoke, Iohn Mush, VVilliam Bishop, Anthony Champney: wherof the three last haue put their names in print to diuers partes of these Libels, the other three haue not, though the first be esteemed to be the penner of the latyn booke, and chiefe broacher of most of these calumniations with counsel and consent of the rest.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>