<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the reuerende father in god &amp; his singuler good lorde / the lorde Hugh Faryngton Abbot of Redynge / his pore client and perpetuall seruaunt Leonarde Cockes desyreth longe &amp; prosperouse lyfe with encreace of honour.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1532</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105098_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19517</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5947</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105098</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the reuerende father in god &amp; his singuler good lorde / the lorde Hugh Faryngton Abbot of Redynge / his pore client and perpetuall seruaunt Leonarde Cockes desyreth longe &amp; prosperouse lyfe with encreace of honour.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The art or crafte of rhetoryke</title>
                 <author>Cox, Leonard</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Redman, Robert</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1532</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>94 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Dialectics and rhetoric</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ To the reuerende father in god &amp; his singuler good lorde / the lorde Hugh Faryngton Abbot of Redynge / his pore client and perpetuall seruaunt Leonarde Cockes desyreth longe &amp; prosperouse lyfe with encreace of honour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsyderynge my spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall good lorde how great ly and how many ways I am bounden to your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp / and among all other that in so great a nombre of connynge men whiche are now within this region it hath pleased your goodnes to accepte me as worthy for to haue the charge of the instruction &amp; bryngynge vp of suche youth as resorteth to your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer schole / foūded by your antecessours in this your towne of Redynge / I studied a longe space what thyng I myght do next the busy &amp; diligent occupienge of my selfe in your sayd seruyce / to the whiche bothe conscience and your stipende doth straytly bynde me / that myght be a significacion of my faithfull and seruysable hart which I owe to your lordeshyp / &amp; agayne a long memory bothe of your singuler and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall
<pb facs="3"/>
fauour towarde me: and of myn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry and diligence employed in your ser uyce to some profite: or at the leest way to some delectacion of the inhabitauntes of this noble realme now slouryshynge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the most excellent &amp; victorious prynce our souerain Lorde kyng Henry the. viii.</p>
   <p>¶ And whan I had thus long prepensed in my mynde what thynge I myght best those out: non offred it selfe more conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyent to the profyte of yonge studentes (which your good lordshyp hath alwayes tenderly fauoured) and also meter to my {pro}fession: than to make som proper werke of the right pleasaunt and persuadible art of Rhetorique / whiche as it is very neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to all suche as wyll either be Aduoca tes and Proctours in the law: or els apte to be sent in theyr Prynces Ambassades / or to be techers of goddes worde in suche maner as may be moost sensible &amp; accepte to theyr audience / and finally to all them hauynge any thyng to purpose or to speke afore any companye (what someuer they be) So contraryly I se no science that is lesse taught &amp; declared to Scolers / which ought chiefly after the knowledge of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ones had to be instructe in this facul tie / without the whiche oftentymes the
<pb facs="3"/>
rude vtteraunce of the Aduocate greatly hindereth and apeyreth his cliētes cause. Likewise the vnapt disposicion of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher (in orderyng his mater) confoundeth the memory of his herers / and briefly in declarynge of maters: for lacke of inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and order with due elocucion: great tediousnes is engendred to the multitude beyng present / by occasion wherof the spe ker is many tymes ere he haue ended his tale: either left almost aloon to his no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle confusiō: or els (which is a lyke rebuke to hym) the audience falleth for werynes of his ineloquent language fast on slepe.</p>
   <p>¶ wyllynge therfore for my parte to help suche as are destrouse of this Arte (as all surely ought to be which entende to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded in any comynaltie) I haue parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly translated out a werke of Rhetorique wryten in the Latin tongue: and partely compyled of myn owne: and so made a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle treatyse in maner of an Introductyon into this aforesayd Science: and that in our Englysshe tongue. Remembrynge that euery good thyng (after the sayeng{is} of the Philosopher) the more comon it is: the more better it is. And furthermore tru stynge therby to do som pleasure and case to suche as haue by negligence or els fals
<pb facs="4"/>
persuacions be put to the lernyng of other sciences or euer they haue attayned any meane knowlege of the Latin tongue.</p>
   <p>¶ whiche my sayd labour I humbly offre to your good Lordeshyp / as to the chyefe maintener &amp; nouryssher of my study / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sechynge you / thoughe it be ferre within your merites done to me / to accepte it as the fyrst assay of my pore and simple wyt / which yf it may fyrst please your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp / and nexte the reders / I trust by the ayde of almyghty god to endyte other werkes bothe in this facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and other to the laude of the hygh godhed / of whome all goodnes doth procede / and to your Lordshyps plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure / and to profyte and delectacion of the Reder. ❧</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>