<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Anthony Scoloker vnto the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1548</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105735_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A08443</idno>
           <idno type="STC">18765</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105735</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Anthony Scoloker vnto the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Sermons of the ryght famous a [n] d excellent clerke Master Bernardine Ochine, borne within the famous vniversyte of Siena in Italy, nowe also an exyle in this life, for the faythfull testimony of Jesus Christ</title>
                 <author>Ochino, Bernardino</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Scoloker, Anthony</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Ipswich</pubPlace>
                    <date>1548</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>62 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="7"/>
   <head>Anthony Scoloker vnto the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the multytude of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyous vnder heaven / ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to gether at Kieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem / after that the holy-goost was geven vnto the Apostles / were stonied / ād mardayled moche / that they hearde them / speaking every man wyth hys owne ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue / declaring the wonderous doyngs of God / howe moche more then ought we to wonder in these our latter dayes / that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve the same myracle wrought dayly amō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest vs also?
<note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> For not only the fathers that were labouring (not many yeres synnes) ande travaylinge in thys oure pilgrimage with vs / and now are gone vnto the lyuīg God / do both lyvely and moost godly even styll at this daye preache vnto vs / but also the very Prophetes ād Patriarkes ād al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the whole company that have been evē frō the beginning of the worlde / are nowe familiar vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> / ād are become Inglish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Yea / god hi selfe of his great infinite
<pb facs="7"/>mercie in our owne tongue speaketh vnto vs / oute of his moost sacred worde / to our great ioye and spirituall comforte. And Paul being ā hebrue borne / hath chaūged his tonge / ād is become oures / as though he had been bredde and brought vp all the dayes of his lyfe amongest vs. Wherfore albeit that the Gospell beyng nowe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmed / it maye appeare / that myracles at these dayes are nothynge so necessarye as they were in the prymatyue Churche / when by the vertue of the holighoost and by myracles / that newe doctryne was to be confirmed / yet the verité it self sheweth the same power styll even nowe vnto vs / that said My father worketh evē vntil th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is time / ād I also do worke.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> Howe great a wondre therfore is it that almost no mā doth marvail at / to see that by the meanes of thigs cōmitted to writtig two / though one be never so farre distaūt frō the other / may cōmunicate their secrets tegether? ād yet passig this / by the helpe of the same / we receave the v{er}tuous coūsels / the moost ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly instrueriōs the godly prechigs of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers (as they called the prophetes: because ī the maiesté of the aet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rnall god they did see
<note place="margin">1. Reg. 2.</note>
      <pb facs="8"/>as it had been in a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ece microur / the secret misteryes of thinges both past and for to com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>) and yet we mardall nothing at all. But God (not leauyng vs thus / where as by the very true monuments of the godly that are passed from vs / theyr mindes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>eft with vs still / we are urle or nothig amended) doth sende vnto vs hys Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes oute of straūge countreis / that the congregation therby maye be edifyed / and moost bounde to render thankes vnto hī for his infinite mercy.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> Amongest the wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich Bernardinus Ochinus and Petrus Martyr men of great learninge / whiche are nowe come vnto vs. And for as moch as the sayd Bernard preachech in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talyan tongue which all men vnderstand not / I have seth forth syx of his Sermōs oute of this tongue into Inglysh. Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to set forth the rest very shortlye (yf these shalbe thankefully receaued) to the intent that his nature tongue therby may be made oures / and that the glory of God maye the better be set forth. Vnto whom all honour is due / world wythourende.</p>
   <p>So be it.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>