<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ To the Right worship∣full, M. Gryffyn Ham∣den, of Hamden Essquyer: one of the Queenes Maiesties Iustices, of the Countie of Buckingham. VV. C. wysheth health, and happines, in Christ Iesus. (∴)</title>
           <author>Cleaver, William</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1576</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105734_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01786</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11920</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105734</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ To the Right worship∣full, M. Gryffyn Ham∣den, of Hamden Essquyer: one of the Queenes Maiesties Iustices, of the Countie of Buckingham. VV. C. wysheth health, and happines, in Christ Iesus. (∴)</title>
                 <author>Cleaver, William</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A knowledge for kings, and a warning for subiects : conteyning the moste excellent and worthy history of the Raellyans peruerted state, and gouernment of their common wealth: no lesse rare, then strange ... First written in Latine, by Iames Glaucus a Germaine: and now translated into enlgish by VVilliam Cleuer scholemaster. By speciall recorde, this monument was two thousande yeares of antiquity: and so dusked and forworne with age, that being in a plaine writte [n] letter, could scarce be read ... I with my painefull indeuour haue now renewed it into fresh memorye</title>
                 <author>Glaucus, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Charlewood, John</publisher>
                    <distributor>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1576</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 60 leaves, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ <hi>To the Right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, M. Gryffyn Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> of Hamden Essquyer: one <hi>of the Queenes Maiesties Iustices, of the</hi> Countie of Buckingham. <hi>VV. C.</hi> wysheth health, and happines, in Christ Iesus. (∴)</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T maye seeme straunge vnto you, right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, that you in respect of diuers, are chosen to bee the patron and defender of this worke: It is not for that I woulde fyll your eares with new and straunge delites: It is not in that I would flatteringlye aduaunce you, neither yet to draw you to anye purpose pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate vnto my selfe: but for that you al waies haue shone in the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ddest of renowned ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: your actions testyfying the constant sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastnes of your hart, your fruitefull fame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge witnessed by Christians, and the deare children of God: that such is the synceritye of
<pb facs="3"/>
noble vertue, dwellinge within your minde, alwaies gnerdoning your affections stedfastly, do prefix your eyes vppon the eternall cown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Gods mercy: am moued the rather to tell you of the commen wealth of the Rael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyans, an vnrulye idolatrous people, drowned in ignoraunce, stumblinge on the myschife of many syns: had many warnings: many signes, wonders and tokens were reuealed vnto them: and all which beinge the gentell offeringes of God, to call them out of the stincking dunghil in which they sleapt: yet in the hardnes of their own hartes no wayes could there appeare any repentance or amendement of life, vntill the full purpose of synne had worne them to the stumpes, by distruction. Idolatry which is the great grandmother of all syufulnes did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue diuers desperate children: which being muffled vnder the paynted v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>sarde of their own conceates, or that the prvuidence of Gods eye sight, lookinge into their vilitye, or that a desperate beginning coulde not prosper: but that God ouer reachinge the wicked with iustice, doth pursue thē to a desperate ending, continuing their impenitencie. I am sory-right worshipfull, that as I purposed to shewe my
<pb facs="3"/>
inward louing minde towards you, so to haue dealt in such a matter as had belonged to the zelous grauity of your study: Notwithstanding, right worshipfull, accept my inwarde minde, for I do not write vnto you as I woulde, but as I maye. For when <hi>Alexander</hi> the great had thorow many tormentes, punished <hi>Calis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenes,</hi> being subdued (without remorce or pity) to many cruelties, when as other waies hee could not vtter his vsuall accustomed speaches in the noble documēts of vertue, would speake the priuy intention of his hart by diuers secret shewes. Once againe, I hartely beseech you to accept rather the inward desier of my mind towards you, then the excelentnesse of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: yet the matter is such that for the feeding delites of the worlde, is more delectable, then laudable: yet not being altogether disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge from the lawes of vertue, the matter is both ciuil and necessarye in the politycall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of mans life: Thus trustinge vpon your vsuall gentlenes, in receauing a small talent from a poore frinde: impute the wante hereof, not in the geauer, but in the quantitie of the gift. And herein to yeelde such accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as my inwarde affection desireth, and
<pb facs="4"/>
not as the worke deserueth. God our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie father preserue you and yours in that course and race of true godlynes which you haue begon to fulfill, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish the samein the bright Sunne beames of his mercy, vnto the end, (∴)</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>From Colshill, in the Parishe of Amersom, <date>the .iij. day of Nouember:</date>
      </dateline> By your worships to commaund <signed>VVilliam Cleauer</signed> Scolemaster.</closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>