<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1637</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105181_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A11920</idno>
           <idno type="STC">22232</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105181</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The vveapon-salves maladie: or, A declaration of its insufficiencie to performe what is attributed to it : Wherein also is described, 1. The severall wayes of making the weapon-salve. 2. The manner of vsing it. 3. Reasons of confirmation to justifie it. 4. Arguments of confutation to overthrow it. By the learned and judicious physitian Daniell Sennertus, Doctor and publique professor at Wittenberg. Translated out of his 5th. booke, part. 4. chap. 10. Practicæ medicinæ</title>
                 <author>Sennerts, Daniel</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Clarke, John 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1637</date>
                 <publisher>Alsop, Bernard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fawcet (Forcet), Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>6, 29, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN READER,</hi> This Argument of the <hi>Weapon-Salve,</hi> is a thing often talked of in private Meetings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Friends, and not seldome disputed of by Learned men in their publike Writings. Nor can any man with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son blame them for sifting out the Truth; especially, in a point that involveth a case of <hi>Conscience</hi> in it, the mistaking whereof, might breed an offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst GOD and his Sacred truth. But yet they are blame worthy, who in searching for the Truth doe fly upon their Adversarie with uncivill lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. In which kinde, I must needes confesse Mr. <hi>FOSTER</hi> hath exceeded the bounds of Christian cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Hee hath in mine opinion the Truth on his side, and hath cleared it well: but yet hee should have remembred the Apostles rule, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>, Ephes. <hi>4.15. That wee speake the truth,</hi> or (as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers translate it) <hi>follow the truth in love;</hi> Not forgetting, that even the Heathen could say,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Tuscul. Q. lib. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>176.</hi> Aldin, edit.</note>
      <hi>Et
<pb facs="3"/> refellere sine pertinaria, &amp; refelli sine iracundia parati sumus.</hi> And againe,<note n="(b)" place="margin">De finib. lib. <hi>2</hi> fol. <hi>81.</hi> pag <hi>2.</hi>
      </note>
      <hi>Sit ista in Graeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum levitate perversitas, qui malidictis insectan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eos, à quibus de veritate dissentiunt:</hi> That is, <hi>Let the light-brain'd Grecians pursue them with reproaches, who dissent from them in opinion: wee are ready both to refute without pertinacie, and to bee refuted without anger.</hi> These rules I wish had beene observed in that Disputation; especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally considering that the Adversary whom hee oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, is a learned Doctor, well esteemed at home for his practicall skill in Physick, and much<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ʋ. Iacob. Boissard. Bibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth. clarorū vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum, part. <hi>2.</hi> effigie <hi>60.</hi> pag. <hi>198.</hi>
      </note> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured abroad for his learned Bookes in Print.</p>
   <p>Now this little Treatise, sent abroad in our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> tongue, is the worke of a man not onely famous for his Learning, but one that had no interest in these personall quarrels. And therefore, I hope the learned Doctor will with his good leave permit vs to publish this small Treatise in our Mother tongue, for the direction of such, as seeke satisfaction in this questionable Point. And that is all, that eyther the Translator or Publisher doe seeke after in this Worke. GOD grant vs peace and truth in <hi>CHRIST</hi> our Lord, Amen.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>