<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶ A Preface to al that loue the earnest promotinge of Gods glo∣rye, in his Churche by true religion.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1562</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105053_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A09658</idno>
           <idno type="STC">19927</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105053</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶ A Preface to al that loue the earnest promotinge of Gods glo∣rye, in his Churche by true religion.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Aggeus and Abdias prophetes : the one corrected, the other newly added, and both at large declared</title>
                 <author>Pilkington, James</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Seres, William 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1562</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>486 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶ A Preface to al that loue the earnest promotinge of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, in his Churche by true religion.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthoughe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vsage of dedicating bookes, is to require the defense of some woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye personage of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge or authoritye for the thing that it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: yet the maiestie of the matter in thys boke, is such, that it rather defendes than sekes defence, and thexample of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, whych wrytes it not to one, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, suffers me not to sende it, to any one sorte of menne particularly, but general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to all that should vnfeinedly promote the encrease of Gods glory, bicause all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of men do owe a dutye to the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, of this gods house. And if anye of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence be taken (as God knowes, none is purposelye giuen) the defence of manye is greater than of a fewe, and that authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye or credite, which one manne alone can not bring to passe, al iointly together shal more easely obtaine. The Prophet is sent from God to the Prince, the highe Priest


<pb facs="3"/>
and the people: so I speake to the rulers, the ministers and comminalty. The cheef intent of his Prophecie, is to stirre all to the spedye buildinge of Gods house, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they had so long neglected: my labour is to bring some of euery sort (for al is not possible) to an earnest fortheringe of gods true religion, of late most mercifullye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored vnto vs, which not long agoe, most cruellye was persecuted, of manye yet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and of euery man almost now to cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye folowed and practised. But if this Prophecy were read and depelye conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, with such a hungry desire of gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, as the Prophete spake and wrote it, and I for my parte and pore abilitie, haue declared it: I doute not, but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> good should be stirred by gods spirit, more earnestly to seke gods glory, &amp; the froward shuld be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed of gods plague, &amp; ashamed stubber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely to striue against y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> trueth cōtinually.</p>
   <p>The state of religion in these our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable dayes, is much like to the trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>som time that this Prophet liued in: God graunt that after many greuous stormes it may take like roote in vs, as it did than in them. After the long captiuity of gods people in Babilon, god gaue them gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous king Cyrus, which set them at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">
         <hi>Esdra. i.</hi>
      </note>and sent them home to builde Goddes


<pb facs="3"/>
house: So after our longe Romish slaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, God raysed vs vp good kynges which restored vs gods booke that long had bin buried, and loused vs from the bondage of straunge gods, forreyn powers, cruell hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, and wicked Idols. And as after that short fredome vnder good Cirus, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued the crueltye of Hamman, for negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently handling gods buildinge: And not long after milde Ester,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Ester. iii.</hi>
      </note> came blouddy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus for their falling from god: So for our talking gospel, and not worthely wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king nor folowing it, vnder our gracyous late Iosias,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Macha. i.</hi>
      </note> crept out a swarm of Romish waspes, stinging to death all that would not worship their Gods, nor beleue their doctrine.</p>
   <p>God for his mercies sake, graūt that now for our vnthankful coldnes in gods cause vnder our myld Ester, burst not out again bloudy Antiochus with his whelpes, iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to auenge our cold slacknes in gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and insensible dulnes.<note place="margin">
         <hi>ii. cor. ii.</hi>
      </note> Gods word is neuer offered and geuen in vaine, or to vse at our pleasure: but it workes eyther saluacion in them that here beleue and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe it, or els condemnacion in them that proudely despise it, sturdely rebell, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfully do heare, and vnthankfullye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue his mercies. Therefore as after a


<pb facs="4"/>
storme folowes a calme, and after winter comes sommer: so nowe where God hath geuen a breathing time, (lest our weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes had not bene able to haue borne hys heauy displeasure anye longer) let vs ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestlye applye our worke, whan we haue time, for the nyghte wyll come whan no man shall be able to worke.</p>
   <p>If this be true (as it is most true in deede) that euerye dede of our sauiour Christ, is our instruction: &amp; also that what thynges soeuer are wrytten, they be writtē for our learning (as S. Paul teacheth) let vs cal to remēbraunce,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Rom. xv.</hi>
      </note> what zele &amp; earnest loue our sauiour Christ, especially shewed in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his fathers house, and restoringe the true vnderstanding of the scriptures, frō the supersticious gloses of the Scribes &amp; Pharises, and also what a feruent desire of promoting gods glory our fathers haue shewed afore vs, that we may be good sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of our schoolemaister Christe Iesus, and obedient childrē, walking in the step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of our fathers.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Iohn. ii. Luke. xix.</hi>
      </note> Oure Lorde and sauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our christ, comming into the temple, and finding it full of biers, sellers and chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, was greeued to see Gods house so misused, gate a whippe and droue them al out, saiyng: My house is a house of praier: but ye haue made it a denne of theues, so


<pb facs="4"/>
surely al Christians, whiche vnfeynedly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> beare the name of christ, and zelously loue the building of his house, woulde gladlye see sinne punyshed, and lamente that the whip of Gods disciplyne is not shaken in gods house, to the driuing out and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of all gredy theues, which if they can not get in at the dore, by lawfull meanes, wil climbe in at the wyndowe, and for a litle money wil sel the bodyes and soules of Christes sheepe, and make gods house the Popes market place. But as she that had so much worke to doe, that she could<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> not tell where to begin, sate her downe &amp; left al vndone: so I say, worldly wise men see so many thinges out of order in Gods house, and so little hope of redresse, that they can not tell which to correct or amēd first, and therefore let the whippe lye stil, and euery man to do what him lust, &amp; sin to be vnpunished.</p>
   <p>And not onely this euil reignes, but the worlde is come to such a dissolute liberty, and negligēt forgetting of god, that men sleping in sinne, nede not so much a whip to driue anye out of the Churche, so fewe come there, but they nede a great sorte of whips, to driue some fewe thitherwarde. For come into a Church on the Sabboth day, and ye shall see but few though there


<pb facs="5"/>
be a sermon: but the alehouse is euer full. Wel worth the Papistes therfore in their kind, for they be earnest, zelous and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in their doinges, they will build their kingdom more in one yeare with fire and fagot,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Zele in correcting sinne is godly.</hi>
      </note> than the colde gospellers will do in seuen. A popishe summoner, spy, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter, will driue mo to the church with a worde, to heare a latin masse, than seuen Preachers will brynge in a wekes prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, to heare a godly Sermon. If this be not true, remember the late dayes of popery, and see who durst offend him that weere a shauen crowne. Who loked so high than, but he woulde geue place to a priestes cappe: and now who regardes the best preacher ye haue? O what a condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion shall this be to al such, as haue the whip of gods correctiō in their hande, to se the wicked so diligēt, and earnest in their doinges, to set vp Antichrist: and Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an rulers and officers of al sortes, hauing the whip of correction in their hande, both by gods lawe, and the Princes, so colde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behaue them selues, in settinge vp the kingdom of Christ, that neither they giue good example theym selues in diligente prayinge, and resorting to the church, nor by the whippe of dyscipline driue others thitherward. Where apperes in any chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,


<pb facs="5"/>
in these our dayes this earnest zele of Christ, to promote gods glory by suche correction, that we maye say we be his fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers. I feare rather that Christ, of whō we more talke, than diligently folowe, or earnestly loue, for this cold slacknes that he sees in vs, will say vnto vs.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Reuel. iii</hi>
      </note> Bicause ye be neither hote nor colde, I will spue you out of my mouthe. Wo be to that Realm where god is compelled to take the whip in hand to punish sinne bicause the rulers will not: great shalbe the plage thereof. Phinees turned awaye gods anger from his people,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Num. xxv</hi>
      </note> bicause so zelously he auenged gods quarell and punished that wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, which other wincked at. Dauid se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gods glory defaced, and his enemies so contemptuouslye to forget the lawe of the lorde, was so greued that he said.<note place="margin">
         <hi>Psal. c.xix</hi>
      </note> The earnest loue that hee bare towarde God, made him to pine awaye, bicause his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies had forgotten the worde of God. Elias fleing from cruell Iesabell, thret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge to kill him, bicause he had destroied Baals priestes, liued in wyldernesse, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired he might die,<note place="margin">
         <hi>iii. king. xix.</hi>
      </note> for he was wery of his life to see how manye were fallen to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye, &amp; how few (or none as he thought) worshipped truly the liuing god. Though Iehu was a euil man otherwaies, yet god


<pb facs="6"/>
gaue him a worldly blessing, and commē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him for his earnest zele in rooting out the posterity of Achab,<note place="margin">
         <hi>
            <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
               <desc>••</desc>
            </gap>ii. kin. x</hi>
      </note> pulling down Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and his sacrificinge priestes, makinge a common Iakes of the house, where they worshipped him. S. Paule seing the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, rather reioysinge then lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge or punishinge that filthinesse com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted amonge them: that one of theym had defiled his stepmother,<note place="margin">
         <hi>i. corin. v.</hi>
      </note> wrytes vnto them, rebukes al thē sharply, bicause they did not correct him, and willes them al to assemble them selues in the name of god, to excomminicate and geue him to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than that had done this wickednes, not to eat and drinke with him, that he might be ashamed, repent, and amend. So whereas this great zele and loue towarde god and his house buildinge, standes either in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting euill and lamenting the defacing of gods glorye, or els in wisshinge and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good therto, and fortheringe it to our powers: for the first part to be earnestlye folowed, these fewe examples shall serue: for the other, there be so manye that it is harder to tell where to ende, then where to beginne.</p>
   <p>Moyses in the wildernesse, wyllinge to make a Tabernacle and place where the people should resort to worship their god,


<pb facs="6"/>
had the Princes and people so liberall to offer and bringe to the makinge thereof,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Zele to promote gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses him. Exo. xxxv</hi>
      </note> golde, siluer, precious stones, silke, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, heare, iron, brasse and timber, of all sortes such plentye, that they would haue geuen more then neded. Dauid earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly desiringe to builde a house for the Lord (if god would haue suffered him) lefte his son Salomon so great plenty of al things necessary to that buildinge in a readines,<note place="margin">
         <hi>i. Chro. xxix.</hi>
      </note> that he finished that costly building in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeares. Good king Cirus restored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to Gods people al that couetous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bucho had robbed from them: Cirus, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Artaxerxes, and hys Princes gaue out of their treasures to the buildinge of the temple, and maintenaunce of their sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices according to the lawe of Moyses,<note place="margin">
         <hi>Esdr.</hi> 6.7.</note> sufficientlye that they myght pray for the king, his children, &amp; the common wealth. Constantinus the firste, worthelye called magnus, a Chrystyan Emperour gaue great liberty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> the Bishoppes, and other ministers. Iustinianus, Theodosius, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolus magnus, Ludouicus Pius. &amp;c. aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and encreased the same with lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and lawes. This zeale and earnest loue to build gods house,<note place="margin">
         <hi>We are vnlike our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
      </note> and punishe sin was in our fathers: this liberality was in Princes and rulers that vnderstoode not


<pb facs="7"/>
gods benefites and mercies so plentifully as we do. They pacified gods wrath, in correcting sinne, &amp; we prouoke his plages with heapinge vp of sinne: They were greued and wery of their liues when they see Gods enemies despise his worde, we winke and cloke it, we laugh and smile at it, and thinke it not to be a fault. They were offended if wickednesse were vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, and the partye not ashamed that sinned, and we be offended if any man go about to see it punished, or the offendour ashamed. They were liberall in geuinge, relieuinge &amp; maintaining the ministery, we are greedy in snatching and plucking away from them: They were ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende with priuileges the ministers, that they shoulde not be withdrawen from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their dutie, and we bind them to such clogges, that they can not do their dutye: They restored all that was taken from them, and we study daily how to get more from them. When I compare these doin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges together, and see howe good successe the one had, and gods Church was glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouslye builded that waye bothe vnder the law &amp; the gospell, it makes me to quake when I loke what shall fall vpon vs, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so farre cleane contraryway. Surelye both they and we go not in the right way.


<pb facs="7"/>
The lord for his crucified Christes sake, which came downe from the bosom of his father, to teache vs to builde him a house here, that afterward we might raigne in glory with him there: graunt vs all, in all degrees from the higheste to the lowest, suche an earneste simple loue to the true buildinge of hys house, as the Prophete here teaches vs, that vprightly we might walke the right way that he hath gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs.</p>
   <p>If the Prince and nobylitye will main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that honorable estate that god hath called them to, and auoyde the bondage of forreine powers: If the Bishoppes and clergie will feede Gods people with the liuely foode of oure soules, gods doctrine and discipline, and not with mannes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions: If the people will trulye serue God and obey their prince, flee from Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye, &amp; escape gods plagues: let vs ioint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together earnestly abhorre poperie, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect sinne, turne vnto the Lord, delight in his worde, reuerence his ministers, be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in prayer, that we maye be liuelye stones, mete for his building, and become the temples of the holy ghoste, where he with the father and the sonne .iii. persons and one god, may dwell and be praysed.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>
      <hi>I. P. L. C. D.</hi>
   </p>
   <p>My earnest loue to God hath pined me away, because my enemies haue forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thy wordes. Psalm. 119.</p>
   <p>I haue bene earnestlye zelous for the Lord god of hostes: because they haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken thy couenaunt .3. king. 19.</p>
   <pb facs="8"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>