<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Printer.</title>
           <author>Harris, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105942_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02722</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12854</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105942</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Printer.</title>
                 <author>Harris, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Tvvo sermons : vvherein vve are tavght, 1. Hovv to get, 2. How to keepe, 3. How to vse a good conscience. Preached in Alldermanbury Church, London. Not heretofore published. By Robert Harris</title>
                 <author>Harris, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Brudenell, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Bartlet, John</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 43, 1 page, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>X to the Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_printer">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Printer.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas you request mee to enlarge my selfe in some passages of my former Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons touching Conscience, against this new Impressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I haue resolued rather to adde two new Sermons of the same subiect, than to alter any thing in the old, and this I haue beene led vnto vpon these reasons. First, because I would haue you deale firmely with all men in the venting of Copies. Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that labour would haue beene as tedious to me as this. Thirdly, because I haue now ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded something touching the vse of Conscience, which my former text would not so fitly beare; My request vnto you is double; first, that you would be carefull in obseruing stops, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogations
<pb facs="3"/>and distinctions, which neglected, the sence becomes sometimes darke, sometimes imperfect and none vt all, as is tobee seene in some passages of the Sermons on <hi>Prouerbs</hi> and <hi>Samuel.</hi> Secondly, that you will seuer these so from the former, as that who so pleases may haue them alone. Thus resting in your care for the due publishing of all, I commend you and the worke to the Lords blessing.</p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>
         <hi>Hanwell,</hi>
         <date>
            <hi>Oct. 8.</hi>
         </date>
      </dateline>
      <signed>Yours, ROBERT HARRIS,</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>