<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To all them that haue vnfai∣nedly embraced true Religion.</title>
           <author>Topsell, Edward</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105980_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A13823</idno>
           <idno type="STC">24127</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105980</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To all them that haue vnfai∣nedly embraced true Religion.</title>
                 <author>Topsell, Edward</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The revvard of religion : Deliuered in sundrie lectures vpon the booke of Ruth, wherein the godly may see their daily and outwarde tryals, with the presence of God to assist them, and his mercies to recompence them: verie profitable for this present time of dearth, wherei manye are most pittifully tormented with want; and also worthie to bee considered in this golden age of the preaching of the word, when some vomit vp the loathsomnes therof, and others fall away to damnable securitie</title>
                 <author>Topsell, Edward</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Windet, John</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>48, 311, 1 page, 1 leaf of plates, table, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Bibles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="15"/>
   <head>To all them that haue vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly embraced true Religion.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Earely beloued in Christe, when I consider that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Oracle of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, when he saith that god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse hath the promises of this life and of the life to come; it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into my mind, that religion is none of the meanest professions, that is labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for in the worlde: for the greatest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes are promised to the chiefest ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploytes; and the worthiest enterprises are Crowned with glorious benefits. <hi>Ioseph</hi> for his wisedome was made the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Egypt. <hi>Othniel</hi> for his seruice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued <hi>Aisah</hi> the daughter of <hi>Caleb</hi> for his wife. <hi>Iiphtah</hi> for his victorie was made iudge of Israel, and <hi>Dauid</hi> for his Musicke was made one of the Courtiers of <hi>Saul.</hi>
      <pb facs="16"/>
In so much as it seemeth an ordinarie practise that euerie knowledge is rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with some curtesie: whereby wee are certified, that it is no maruaile to heare &amp; hope for so excellent blessings as are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to the Religious. For they are the house of the Lorde, and as hee dwelleth with all maiestie in heauen, so he raigneth with all Authoritie in the righteous; they are a chosen generation borne of God, a Royall and holy priesthood, a holy nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a peculiar people, the free men of Christ, the inheritours of the earth, the iudges of the worlde, the coheires of Christes kingdome, and the Cittizens of heauen. If wee looke for their Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, they are the Sonnes of God; if for their instruction, they are taught of God; if for their tuition, the heauenly Angels are their seruants; if for their degrees they are kings and priestes for the eternal God, if for their calling they are Saintes; if for their life it is heauenly; if for their wealth it is the whole worlde; and finally their death is the birth day of all felicitie. For this cause <hi>Dauid</hi> desired rather to bee a doore-keeper in the house of God, then a dweller in the stately tents of the wicked;
<pb facs="16"/>
as if the meanest condition among the professors of Religion, were more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then the chiefest estates among the worldlings, their Crosses excell the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Crownes, their barrenesse the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fruitfulnesse, their humilitie the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers honour, their ignorance the others knowledge, their simplicitie the others wisedome, their weakenesse the others strength, and a little thing that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hath, is better then the great possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the vngodly. When there is famine they are satisfied, when ther is warre they are deliuered, when there is plague they are without daunger, if fire fall from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it shall not burne them, if the waters arise aboue the mountaines, they are not drowned, if the earth quake and rend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunder, yet they are not swallowed vp, if the wilde beastes fall vpon them they are not deuoured, and if the Deuill himselfe would oppresse them, yet he shall not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome them. Then how glorious is our calling? That liue vnder the wings of God, that feede with the flocke of Christ, to whome are reuealed the secrete Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels of the Lord, speaking vnto vs by his Ministers, giuing vs the euidence of our
<pb facs="17"/>
saluation by his testament, regenerating vs by the immortall seede of his holye word, sealing vs with the spirit of promise, lifting vs vp from the dust of worldly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie, to the thrones of heauenly Maiestie. <hi>Salomons</hi> seruants were happie that stood in his presence and heard his wisedome. <hi>Daniel</hi> was happy when the Lyons could not destroie him, his fellowes were hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie when the fire coulde not consume them, the Israelites were happie when the Egyptians were drowned, <hi>Iob</hi> was happy when his wealth was restored, and the Disciples were blessed when they hearde Christ preach. How many blessings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the religious? Sathan that roaring Lyon cannot ouercome them, the fire shall haue no power on them, their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies shall neuer hurt them, the riches of the grace of God shall be powred vppon them, and the word of life is dayly prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto them. Consider therefore my beloued, what is the hope of our profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion whereunto we are called, the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our condition wherein wee stande, and the reward of our Religion prepared for our soules. Call to mind the examples of the Fathers, the promises of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
<pb facs="17"/>
the oath of the Lorde himselfe, the price of our redemption, and the place of our saluation: you shall finde nothing wanting in Religion, that might encrease your blessednes. Therefore how happie are the eares that heare the things which wee heare, the eyes that see the thinges which wee see, the hands that handle the thinges which wee touch, nay; the soules that are assured of the fauour of God. If all the worlde woulde goe about to set downe the felicitie of the godly and the dignitie of the chosen, they could neuer atchieue it: no, not that which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy in this life, for their thoughts are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, their hearts the throne of the holy Ghost, their hands feele the Lord of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, their tongues talke of his praise, their feete stand in his Temple, their words are acceptable before him, their Prayers like sweete sauours of incense, their worship like Euening sacrifices, their eyes behold his glorie, their eares heare his wisedome, and their names are written in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. Would not any man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come religious, that he might bee rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with this excellent honour? To eate his meate with the Kinge of heauen, to
<pb facs="18"/>
weare the Crowne that neuer shall haue ende, to haue the Angels his attenders, the Saintes his fellowes, the heauens his dwelling place, the starres vnder his feete, the euerlasting light to walke in, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of God to delight? him, &amp; the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of Paradise for the recompence of his Religion. For this cause I haue giuen this title vnto these my slender labours vpon this booke of Ruth, wherein (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in Christ) you shall find the matter to agree with the title, and the hope of all the faithfull concerning the end of their profession, so profitably deciphered, as hath comforted manye troubled soules, confirmed many wauering mindes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded many obstinate Atheists, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged many godly persons; and therefore I hope wil offer the same fauour vnto you in reading, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>as it hath vnto many other in preaching. Herein the holye Ghost (I meane in the booke of Ruth) hath laide open whatsoeuer can bee expected of them that feare the Lord, here are afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to humble vs, death to preuent vs, &amp; examples to admonish vs; here is the zeale of the godly, the vertue of an effectuall calling, the vizard of hypocrisie declared
<pb facs="18"/>
vnto vs; heere is the loue of the faithfull, the obedience to parents, and the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence of godly persons commended vnto vs; here is the care of our parents, the gifts of the spirite, and the holines of the religious committed to the Church; here is the office of Magistrates, the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers of our brethren, and the calling of the Gentiles expressed, in the marriage of <hi>Ruth</hi> with <hi>Boaz,</hi> who was made a mother of many Kings, but especially of the king of glorie, the Sonne of God, the Sauiour of the world, &amp; the gatherer together of the heires of grace. My desire therefore is this, that you trye it by perusing and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this treatise, for it is but superfluous labour for me, any farder to trouble you with the Argument heereof, seeing the whole matter lyeth before your consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. I wil pray for your successe, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the ende of my trauailes, (which is the comfort and instruction of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Christ, to the fountaine of mercy, by whome the heauens water the earth, and the earth multiplieth with encrease, and the encrease thereof preserueth the world, that by the same power, your souls may be edified, your faith may be strēgth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb facs="19"/>
my labours may bee blessed, that his name may be glorified, his worde may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore be taught among vs, that many generations may embrace his Gospel, and the course thereof finished, our Religion by the mercie of the Father, in the Sonne with the holy Ghost may bee rewarded with eternall saluation, to whome let vs euermore giue thankes because hee hath vouchsafed vs the dignitie thereof, and walke worthie of our calling, least our se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure liues, our Idle faith, our vaine hope, our colde profession, and our common conuersation with the vngodly, bring vpon vs euerlasting damnation.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Your Louing brother who desireth your Prayers.</hi> Edward Topsell.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>