<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right ho∣norable, the Lorde ROBERT DVD∣DELEY Maister of the Queenes horse, and Knight of the noble order of the Sarter, Iames Rowbothum wis∣sheth long lyfe with encrease of godly honour.</title>
           <author>Rowbothum, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1562</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105152_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19788</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6214</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105152</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right ho∣norable, the Lorde ROBERT DVD∣DELEY Maister of the Queenes horse, and Knight of the noble order of the Sarter, Iames Rowbothum wis∣sheth long lyfe with encrease of godly honour.</title>
                 <author>Rowbothum, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The pleasaunt and vvittie playe of the cheasts renewed : with instructions both to learne it easely, and to play it well. Lately translated out of Italian into French: and now set furth in Englishe by Iames Rowbothum</title>
                 <author>Damiano, da Odemira</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Hall, Rowland</publisher>
                    <distributor>Rowbotham (Robothum), James</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1562</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>112 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Games and recreations</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>
      <hi>To the right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, the Lorde ROBERT DVD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DELEY</hi> Maister of the Queenes horse, and Knight of the noble order of the Sarter, Iames Rowbothum wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth long lyfe with encrease of godly honour.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S THE graue and waightye affaires of Princes (moste hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) require men of profoūde knowledge and experience, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che must dayly consider and easte in their myndes some good, holesome and profitable counsell for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of the common wealth by good lawes: so also muste they for recreation sake, surcease some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time from those extreme trauailes of the mynde, and refreshe theyr memorie and carefull heades with some recreatiue exercise meete for their estate. And as there bee for noble men noble pastimes (and
<pb facs="3"/>
inuented first onelye for the nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) as feates of armes, turneys, fighting at the barriers, runninge at the tilt, cleane ryding of horses, with other like, whereby the nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of realmes was first increased and great renowne gotten, &amp; were done altogether with the strength of the arme and corage of the hart: so is there also for the lyke, certain other wittie inuentions of playes or games to recreate the mynde withall, and are learned and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised not with the outward stregth of the bodye, but with the inwarde force of witte and intelligence, to the great sharpening of the enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue partes of mannes vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the which I will not trouble your Lordship with in numbringe them: but amonge so many as are vsed and exercised in courtes of Princes, in Lordes, Knightes, and Gentelmens houses, none (in my iudgement) is more meete for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, then the noble playe or game of the Cheastes inuented first
<pb facs="3"/>
by a noble Philosopher, or as some thinke by the noble King Xerxes. Wherein if I shoulde declare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerly the witte, the inuention, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> warlyke order, the polityke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyaunce, that great pleasure is ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken in it, of them that haue practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the knowledge of it, I shoulde seeme to tedious vnto your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippe: but yet left I should preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the commendation of suche a kingly game, I thought it my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to present your Lordship with this lytle booke, teaching an order how to playe perfitly and to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage, with the names that both the French men, Spaniardes and Italians call the Cheastmen by, &amp; also the fashion and ordering of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chrast bourd, which was neuer before this tyme in our tonge as farre as I can learne with so good and compendious a waye to learne the same. And althoughe I knowe that bothe your Lordship, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> noble men &amp; gentle mē of this realme cā play excellent
<pb facs="4"/>
ly at this game of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Cheast, &amp; haue as deepe knowledge therein as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther French men, Italians or Spa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niardes haue: yet because none e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer attempted to put in writynge the feate, witte, and pollicie that is in it, and that they vnderstande. I was so bolde (hauing found it tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated out of French into Englishe after the forme and maner in all poyntes as it is here printed) to choose your honoure to whome I mighte offer this simple present, trustinge that as your Lordshippe doth alwais gratefully accept more the giuers good will, than the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the gift, the same will recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue this booke into the number of those which other haue geuen vnto your honour, although of greater importaunce, yet not of greater good will. Which I doubt not but in many thinges you wil delyte to reade, and to consider when so euer occasion shalbe offred to your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship to playe at the same game, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a pastime w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out all tediousnes,
<pb facs="4"/>
malice, melancoly, anger, gyle, or deceit, and hath in it self a certaine maiestie bothe in the setting of the men and also in naming them. Besides that it hath <hi>formam instructae acici</hi> and of a raunged battaile the Kinge placed in the middle as is seene by the settinge of the men. The cause why, of whom, and whē it was made, your Lordship shall read in the beginning of the booke which is a thing worthy to be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, for that it is now so common lye vsed in this realme, as well of noble men as of others of lower e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state and degree, to the great quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening of their wit and memorie. Whiche game as it is kinglye and honest, and meete for diuers sortes of men, so is it (in manye mennes iudgements) not altogether vnpro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable for Captains, Conductours of armies, and commō Soldiours. For out of those wodden men may some knowledge bee had howe to marche and sette furth Soldiours in the fielde, how to garde a King,
<pb facs="5"/>
and what forces ought to be in the sides of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> battaile, as in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> discourse of playing it, men maye easely see.</p>
   <p>Thus leauynge to holde your Lordshippe with any longer Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, from the reading of the booke, I wishe the same longe lyfe in healthe, with muche en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of vertus and honor. (‡)</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Lordshippes to commaunde
Iames Rowbothum.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>