<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE ARGVMENTE OF THE Chapters.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1583</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105168_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A68438</idno>
           <idno type="STC">17263</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105168</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE ARGVMENTE OF THE Chapters.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A manual of prayers nevvly gathered out of many and diuers famous authours : aswell auncient as of the tyme present. Reduced into. 13. chap. very commodious and profitable for a deuout christian</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Fr. Parsons’ Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>France--Rouen</pubPlace>
                    <date>1583</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>7, 151, 10+ leaves, 16°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="instructions_for_reading">
   <div type="argument">
      <pb facs="4"/>
      <head>THE ARGVMENTE OF THE Chapters.</head>
      <p>
         <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auinge expressed the causes that moued me to the collection and translation of this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall, I am now to lay downe a direction whereby thou mayest with more facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye finde out such particular prayers as semeth beste to thy discrete deuotion: that seeing the particular praiers of this booke deuided into certayne chapters, thou mayest as tyme, place and necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye requireth, vse these kynde of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, whiche shall bee moste to Gods glory, thy owne soules health, and the profit of thy euen-christian.</p>
      <p>The firste and second chapters are such, as whereby the Christian Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke may learne and knowe howe to craue the ayde and succour of God in all his endeuours, enterpryses and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which that daye he purposeth and meaneth to take in hand: and before he goe to bed, to thanke God for his beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites receyued that day: and to knowe
<pb facs="5"/>how to examine his conscience, calling to minde his sinnes committed the day past: but specially in the seconde chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the catholicke man may learne howe to behaue him selfe at the tyme of the dreadful misteries, which christian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple commonly call the Masse. Further he may there learne what to craue of God, and what kinde of meditations to vse in the Church, and withall howe to moue him selfe to spirituall deuotion.</p>
      <p>The rest which are ten chapters, are put in a seuerall Index, whereby the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke shall easely finde what prayers are thought moste conuenient for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye day in the weeke: that so he may as leasure and deuotion serueth him, reade either the whole, or parte, as they are set downe in this Index folowing.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="index">
      <pb facs="5"/>
      <list>
         <label>Read vpon. Soundaye these chap.</label>
         <item>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Prayers to the holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Of thankesgyuing to God for his benefites.</item>
            </list>
         </item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <label>Vpon. Moundaye these chap.</label>
         <item>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> To the B. Virgin Marie and to the holy Saintes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> For obteyning remission of sinnes.</item>
            </list>
         </item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <label>Vpon. Tewesdaye these chap.</label>
         <item>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> For ayde and comfort in tribulations and afflictions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> For obteyning of God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaries for body and soule.</item>
            </list>
         </item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <label>Vpon. VVednesday these chap.</label>
         <item>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> For the Churche, our friendes, and others.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> For the departed soules.</item>
            </list>
         </item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <label>Vpon. Thursdaye these chap.</label>
         <item>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> For obteyninge of God, necessaries for body &amp; soule.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Of thankes-gyuinge to God for his benefites.</item>
            </list>
         </item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <label>Vpon. Fydaye these chap.</label>
         <item>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> For obteyninge remission of synnes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Prayers of the lyfe and Passion of our Sauiour Iesus Christ.</item>
            </list>
         </item>
      </list>
      <list>
         <label>Vpon. Saturdaye these chap.</label>
         <item>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> For the departed soules.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> To the B. Virgin and to the holy Saintes.</item>
            </list>
         </item>
      </list>
   </div>
   <div type="part">
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <p>THe firste weeke shall be read the chapters which are put in the firste rankes for euery daye: and the nexte weeke after, the chapters put in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ranckes: So shalt thou reade ouer all the within named ten chapters in the Index twyse euery moneth, and some of the sayed chapters foure tymes: As for the other three chapters they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient at certayne times, and for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne persones, for which cause they are not meete to be put in order with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as aboue named.</p>
      <p>But those that haue neither time nor leasure to read euery day a whole chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, may yet reade of the same chapter some of the sayde prayers, and suche as they thincke conueniente for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of God his glory, their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and for the profit of others: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stāding, in no wise may they omit their dayly prayers, or those prayers which they ought to say in Masse time.</p>
      <p>Also when any holy day falleth, that you haue no saynte by name in your chapter of Saintes, then must you take one of the prayers which be common to any Apostle, Martyr, Confessor or Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</p>
      <pb facs="6"/>
      <p>Further it is necessary for all deuoute Catholickes to knowe, that the accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med prayers vsed in the Church accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the auncient and laudable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our forefathers, and obserued by continuall practise of both the learned and vnlearned, (to the greate glorye of God, and increase of deuotion, religion and pietie of lyfe) are not to be omitted for the desire that any may haue to any speciall prayers either in this or anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pamphlet, translated or collected by any priuate persons, which is done to moue men to deuotion, but not to withdrawe men from obedience or any receyued Catholicke custome or tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
      <p>And therefore I counsayle the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Reader that of deuotion hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed him selfe to these prayers fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, not to omit thē in any case (for they are not deuised by the wit and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate deuotiō of mā, but by the holy spirit of God, the Author and delyuerer of all trueth) which are the seuen canonicall houres in the Breuiarye or in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, commonly called our Ladyes mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins: the seuen penitentiall psalmes, with
<pb facs="7"/>the lytanies: the dyrige for the soules departed: the houres of the holy Ghost: the houres of the Crosse: prayers of the passion: the fiftiene graduall psalmes: the beades which consisteth in a certayne number of pater nosters, angelicall sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutations, with the Creede of the Apos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles: commonly is called the Rosarye of our Lady.</p>
      <p>Thus hauinge gyuen thee an order (gentle Reader) to vnderstand this litle Manuall of prayers, with my opinion touching the vse of the same: I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with earnest request and humble supplication vnto thee, desiring thee to remēber me in thy vndistracted deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, saynge this prayer folowinge for me and others, whose helpes I vsed in collecting this sayed worke out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny authors, and translating many pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers out of latin and french into this our vulgar tonge.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="prayer_for_the_translator">
      <p>O Omnipotent almightie and euerli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge God, haue mercye vpon thy seruaunt N. for the loue of thy sweete sonne our sauiour Iesu Christ, the true lighte and lyfe of all that shall be saued:
<pb facs="7"/>O Iesu the seconde person in Trinitie, equall God with the Father and the holy Ghoste, conserue and keepe him in thy grace, fauour and loue, and suffer him not to be drawen from thee through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny suttle perswasions of the enemy: O holy Ghost proceedinge from the father and the sonne, the comforter of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: the inspirer of all good giftes: the onely schole-maister and teacher of all truth: graunte that through thy giftes he maye euermore dwell in thy trueth: replenishe his harte with all charitable desires and heauenlye inspirations ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarye to his saluation: graunt this O holye Trinitie for the bitter passion of our Sauiour: by the merites and intercession of the gloriouse Virgin Marye and all Angels and saintes. Amen.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>