<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>¶TO MY DEARE FRIENDE AND CHRI∣stian Brother, Richard Atlee, Inhabitant of the desolat Towne of Eastdearham, and to his vertuous wife, Alice Atlee: ARTHVR GVRNEY wissheth prosperitie, and all good thinges, in CHRIST IESV.</title>
           <author>Gurney, A. R.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1581</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105908_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02401</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12531.3</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105908</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>¶TO MY DEARE FRIENDE AND CHRI∣stian Brother, Richard Atlee, Inhabitant of the desolat Towne of Eastdearham, and to his vertuous wife, Alice Atlee: ARTHVR GVRNEY wissheth prosperitie, and all good thinges, in CHRIST IESV.</title>
                 <author>Gurney, A. R.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A doleful discourse and ruthfull reporte of the greate spoyle and lamentable losse, by fire, in the towne of East Dearham, in the countie of Norfolke : vpon Tuesday the. 18. of Iulie, this present yere .1581</title>
                 <author>Gurney, Arthur</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1581</date>
                 <publisher>Bradock, Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Hollins (Hollens), Richard.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16+ pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Letters</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="letter">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>¶TO MY DEARE FRIENDE AND CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian <hi>Brother,</hi> Richard Atlee, <hi>Inhabitant of the desolat Towne</hi> of Eastdearham, <hi>and to his vertuous wife,</hi> Alice Atlee: ARTHVR GVRNEY wissheth prosperitie, and all good thinges, in CHRIST IESV.</head>
   <p>
      <hi>
         <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Boute a fortnight since, it was my hap to vnderstande</hi> of a Ballet (as I take it) then newly come from the Presse, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a brief and doleful Discourse of the late burning of East DER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAM. And (as for mine owne part) I both was and am a witnes of the wonderful euents therof: and therwithall (what for my conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall trauell of body and mind, the ruines of my friendes &amp; allies and mine owne smal losses) a fellow feeler of the heauy burthen imposed vpon the townes estate: euen so, with so much the more good will I entertey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the newes, expecting some better sequell, and rested not, til mine eyes were testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the trueth. But when I perused the same, and approued the penning as suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in that or such like cases, I was (neuerthelesse) well aduised of sundrie vntruethes, whiche the Author (no doubt) not so much vppon pretenced deprauation, as for want of necessarie instruction had inserted. And allbeit, no important thing hath therin escaped, which (for mine owne part) I would not tollerate, of verie good wil in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect: yet sithe her Maiestie, her honorable counsaile, many noble, worshipful, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon personages, bee otherwise infourmed of the matter: as also, the duetie of a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, requiring by all meanes to intercept the course of an vntrueth: and last of all, in diuersities of wandring reportes to establish some certaintie, I haue vndertaken in the discourse of the matter, to set downe such an assurance of his particuler errours, and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stead therof, interposed such trueth, as the diligent obseruation of mine owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and the triall of many sound iudgements can confirme and testifie.</p>
   <p>¶One poinct (therfore) wherin he failed, is touching the nomber of Tenementes, Messuages, or mansion houses subuerted and spoyled.</p>
   <p>The .2. cōcerning the dissolution of our houses necessarie for diuers domestical vses.</p>
   <p>¶The .3. his insinuation of a totall losse and detriment susteined.</p>
   <p>In these three (speciallie) hath he left the matter destitute of true report: for, as I haue expressed in the sequell of my treatise: the nomber of tenementes is. LII. whiche he calleth. LX. The houses of office, 350. or there aboutes: which hee reducethe into the nomber of .80. The value of all together .8000. li. or very litle lesse, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth to be .14000. The two first (without al controuersie) are mistaken, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisshed falselie: But as for the last, I must confesse, that (at a blush) it seemeth to carrie great appearance of truth: and I my selfe was therin greatly ouerseene &amp; deceiued, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till with certaine other (of good experience) I had made an estimate of euerye parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer losse, and brought them to a generall and grosse summe.</p>
   <p>Neuerthelesse, if we may recken the charge, which the towne (if euer she be repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) wil exact, to make returne of her former estate, I meane in nomber and quantitie of houses, and (therwith) not pretermit her manifold losses, namely, of coyne, corne, implements of Houshold stuffe, victuales, wood, Timber, chattell, fruict, wels, pumps, hay, straw, time and trades, wherby euer since they haue declined and gone backward, which with the rest are and ought to be brought into the rekning: It is certaine true, that of, 14000 .li. a small remnant wyll remaine, if any deale be left at all.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="3"/>But this is an other case: for an accompt is rather to be raised accordinge to the rate of so much money as euery mans house and stuffe would yeald in sale, if now it weare in STATV QVO PRIVS. For albeit the buildinges were such as might haue ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued many yeares and ages, if it had pleased the Lorde to permitte them to posteryties: yet of a newe house, in quantitie of proportionable resemblance with an old, and of an old, is not one and the selfe same reason: because by how mvch it excedeth in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, by so much ought it to be preferred in price and estimation.</p>
   <p>So then the whole losse which towne hath susteyned is 8000 .li. or there abouts, &amp; the reedifiyng or restauratiō of the same in necessary maner with such other reconings adhearent as I haue allready cast ouer, will amount to litle lesse then 14000. and so it seemeth not vainely saide.</p>
   <q>
      <l>He that buyeth a house ready wrought,</l>
      <l>Getteth many a nayle fot nought.</l>
   </q>
   <p>Thus much Sir, touching the cause that moued me to intermedle &amp; busie my selfe about the affayres of this processe.</p>
   <p>Now whereas the Lord of his owne especiall grace from amongest the rest of that part of the towne destroyed, hath gleaned out your house, as one eare out of a shocke of corne, and preserued it alone amids the multitude of so monsterous flames, though I am in no case to exhort you whome I prefer before my selfe, or at the least do make no inferiour, eyther in the due acceptation of suche a benefit at his Highnes hande, or in recounting the causes why he hath ben more mercyfull to you then the rest of all that towne, and what purposes he seemeth to haue pointed and aymed at therein: yet sith I dayely heare men more reddye to attribute occasion vnto the meanes whiche the Lord vsed in that action of mercy, and to detract from him that honour and priuiledge that in all good thinges is due to him onely: then to waye and consyder what it is to neglect the meryte of his grace herein: I am to craue your pardon if this my Epistle shall seeme any thing tedious and not facioned with that DECORVM that best might become so short a discourse as is the treatis it selfe.</p>
   <p>You knowe I am sure that albeit the case of the towne in that dismall daye wherein it was afflicted, was no lesse myraculous in the eyes of good men, then feareful to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ad whose tonges at the same instant could implore the ayde of God and attende vpon his ordinance, yet hath it pleased some since that time to make so diuers constructions thereof as dothe agree and ioyne with all vntrueth: and to take so slender tast of true knowledge as if their sences had eyther of late forsaken them, or as if they were newe drunke and lulled a sleepe in their obliuion, as in truthe they seeme in all goodnesse.</p>
   <p>These be the mē that turn al things be they neuer so graue &amp; waightie vnto wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes, that are alwaies musling with beasts in the myre of worldly matters, &amp; neuer vouchsafe to lend so muche as half an eye to looke vpō the sunshine of Saluation, ne will be procured to put forth one poore nuger to take acquaintance of the power and prouidence of God: but readily proffer their hand &amp; the seruice of al the instrumē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tal parts of their bodye to welcome &amp; enterteine Māmon that monster their Maister.</p>
   <p>But it is no matter, thei shew euē the same modestie towards God whē he sheweth himself vnto thē, that in the cōmō course of their life thei haue don towards those that are presēt with thē, namely the professers of the Gospel, &amp; in the ende, shal find their fault I doubt not, &amp; throughly vnderstād it either vnto perpetual pain, or repētance: In the meane seasō, sith in their darkenes we perceiue faire daylight &amp; the glory of God
<pb facs="3"/>
in their iust cōdēnation, if that be the reward of their ingratitude let thē accumelate their sinnes, seing they wil needes be filthy, till they haue ascend, the throne of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and we shal see and they feele the greatnes of their owne greeuous fall.</p>
   <p>Let vs I say, be sure, that God reuealeth himself to no infidel, preordeined to perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiō, &amp; therefore cōfirme our selues so much the more in our hope, by how much the lesse they make reconing of the trueth &amp; their own headines &amp; wretched cōditiō. For in truth, nothing can cōmend the good estate of a Christiā to his own soule &amp; cōsci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with more vndoubted argumēts, thē whē he seeth himself cōtinēt in the wicked actions &amp; demeanour of worldlings, &amp; hath fayth in all the changes &amp; chaūces of this vnconstant lyfe to pul true obedience vppon him for his protectiō: The rest rowle euery waye &amp; tumble vp &amp; downe like restlesse waues of water, allwayes relatinge the mercies and myracles of the Lord as accidents to prophane beginninges.</p>
   <p>And as they are seldome possessed with the spirit of humilitie, euen so they tosle and turmoyle them selues in affliction til they are windlesse, and then breathe and to it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, with infinit curssinges and quarreles till tract of time hath worne awaye the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe of their case, or made them feele the pricke that posteth their danger, of sicknesse death, or desperation.</p>
   <p>These poore soules neuer learned of Dauid, Iob and the rest, howe to behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues vnder the Crosse and hand of God, they accompt him a God no longer then he pynneth prosperitie vppon their sleeues, or wayghteth vpon them with aboundance of wealth and pleasures if they accompt him a God at all.</p>
   <p>But if their eyes were not seeled that they might flye right vpp till they are wearie &amp; then fal straight downe &amp; breake their neckes, they might gather a heape of myracles together passed in the ruines of this our towne, and by the same learne to knowe the prouidence of God.</p>
   <p>As the wall couered with drye &amp; parched strawe, which although it be platted where the fire had free accesse and stood like a stake in the midest of ouerwhelming floudes, yet doth it stand whole and sound, yea &amp;, which is more, with one of the corner postes burnt a good depth iust in the midst of the top, with strawes stroughtinge ouer it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perished. What? hath fortune care of strawes? or could these (little wretches) laye hold on her heary side, &amp; a whole streat of houses so many furlongs long not misse the bald. Oh fine strawes, if your dexteritie haue saued you, thanke your selues. If Fortune, fie on her harlot, that would be so freendly vnto you, who neuer did her good, and so fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the rest, that neuer wisht her harme.</p>
   <p>Lykewise the winde which allwayes changed in defence of those houses that nowe stand, and then were in danger, may shew how farr the Lord did purpose to reache his rod, It cannot be denied with anye colloure of trueth, that when the fire had gotten the market stead, the wind from the sowthwest chaunced full west, whereby that side was preserued, and when it had gotte, by your house and beyond it, so that had the fire taken the next rowe, the remnant, except God being able to do what he wil, had shewed a wonderful myracle: must of necessitie haue gon with the fore end of the pece, then I say he brought the winde from the west to the northwest, which kept off both the blaze &amp; sparcks &amp; turned them almost backe again, or at the least, that way wherin lay no dāger. If any deny this, not only my self who duly obserued these alterations as I labored, but other credible witnesses also can testifie with me, &amp; in the end when the fire was suppressed &amp; beaten downe, then lo, it returned into the same stead wherein it stode at the first.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="4"/>Moreouer, why cannot our fortune men gather nothing out of the preseruation of your house, knowing that another was burnt to the earth whichin the on end, namli on the stree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> syde was ioyned to it and came somwhat within it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> on the backe syde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the foūdations of the crosse buildings was at the most but foure foot distance, so that by al likelihod of imagination the eues of ech other must concur within lesse then thre quarters of a yard? if thei say your mansion hous (wherof the question is) is a tiled house &amp; that you had the assistance of the pit &amp; great help of mans hand, I graunt. But I pray you who put that boldnes and courage in one only man, whom we neuer before knew desperat in rash attempts whē your hous was al redy fired, for want of ladders to break out betwen two spars, there to indure that great peril &amp; danger that not only his parents &amp; frends cried out on, but al the standers by also for dread of his presēt death? who I say in this notable distres made him the instrumēt of your good &amp; an incorage mēt to the rest? was it God or fortune? now, al this say our Epicures was fortune forsoth: it was but good &amp; euil luck, it was but habardepas, it was but this or that, &amp; which for a penny. Alas if I should go about to persuade thē that before the pit was made, or er the hous was raised, or er you were born, God held the purpose of your defence, I think thei would iudge me mad, and yet is it greater madnes by oddes to denye it.</p>
   <p>Finallie in a world of such witnesses &amp; argumēts of the prouidēce of god to make short with thē &amp; cōclude in a word: so sone as the fire was ceased, who sēt that notable shoure of rain? was it fortune to show her self in her pōtificalibus, or the lord to declare to vs &amp; proue what he cold haue don in time for our safty, if it pleased him? they which ascribe these things to fortune, let them set her on the top of the pinacle, rest in her cōtempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; seruice &amp; seek non other gods, for she is euen good ynough to show them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of eternall shame.</p>
   <p>It repented godly Augustine that euer he dishonored the name of God by talking of fortune with his tong, but these men are not afraid to rob God of his glory, &amp; honour her with their harts▪ But if thei happen to be hunted (like hogs that are led by the eares) from this fortres of theirs, so as they must eyther confes God or els be pointed out for blaspheming Atheysts, then straight way theie say that indeed he suffered it, but neither willed it, nor did it: wherin also thei shape them out a God according to their own sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, who by this resō must suffer that which he wold not or be a carelesse &amp; idle ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seer of worldlie maters. wel I leaue thē to their grosnes til the lord shal please to vouch safe their better knowledge or bring vpon them the iust effects of wilfull ignorance.</p>
   <p>Now for asmuch as amidds so great desolatiō he hath left you this notable trial of his loue, &amp; tumbled the rest together before the owners faces as thogh he wold haue you to know &amp; cōfesse, &amp; the rest to beare witnes of his fauour towards you: For the loue of god (for your parts) āswere him again with your due obedience in that caling wherin he hath placed you, euen of a redy &amp; willing mind to bring glory to his name, profit to his church &amp; cōfort to your own consciences. And as you haue hitherto ben counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naūcers of the poore professors of Iesus christ in this your town, &amp; louing frends to al other: so herafter, be not wāting (as I trust you wil not) in reforming &amp; bridling those, whose religion &amp; maners, you daily see too too far out of square &amp; order, haling the iugdemēts of god vpō them &amp; others, who but for them wold be more teachable, &amp; in short space better taught. And the Lord (who in althings can see the secrets of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents) shal blesse your labours &amp; reward you with the open liberalitie of his glorious kingdome: which I beseeche him graunt vnto you both. Amen,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>¶Yours, in the Lord, A R. GVRNEY.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>