<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THOMAS ELYOT KNYGHT TO HIS VVOR∣shypfull frende, syr Edwarde North knight chancellour of the court of the augmentacions of the reuenues of the kinges croune, desireth well to doo.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1545</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105472_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A21327</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7674</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105472</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THOMAS ELYOT KNYGHT TO HIS VVOR∣shypfull frende, syr Edwarde North knight chancellour of the court of the augmentacions of the reuenues of the kinges croune, desireth well to doo.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A preseruatiue agaynste deth</title>
                 <author>Elyot, Thomas, Sir</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Berthelet (Barthelet), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1545</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>72 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>THOMAS ELYOT KNYGHT TO HIS VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shypfull frende, syr Edwarde North knight chancellour of the court of the augmentacions of the reuenues of the kinges croune, desireth well to doo.</head>
   <p>THe lyttell boke whyche I sent to you at the begynnynge of lent last passed, a smal requitall of your gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll benefites, I haue caused nowe to be printed: as well for a testimonie of the herty loue, whiche I doo beare toward you, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge printed it maie the lengar endure with you and others, as also that my priuate gyft maie be beneficiall to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men, whiche without disdaine or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy will oftentymes reade it. I knowe well, some men will thinke, and saie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so perchaunce, that I spende my witte vainely. for it is the office of priestes for to preache, and that it dothe not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine to a knyght, muche lesse to a she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe, to write, specially of suche holy
<pb facs="3"/>
mattiers. Also that in writyng to you, whiche are continually occupied about the kynges maiesties busynesse, I lose all my labour: considering that beside the tymes of meale and of slepe (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che also be littell and scarse, as I well haue perceyued) there remaineth with you none oportunitie to reade any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of englyshe or latin. Truely I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, that priestes ought to preache, and that it is their propre office. And yet no christen man is excluded to gyue good counsaile in that whiche pertayneth to the lawes and commandementes of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty god. And he that can do it, and will not (though he be no priest) I dout not but he shall make a straite reknyng for hydynge his talent. A knyght hath receiued that honour not onely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende with the swerde Christis faithe and his propre countrey, agaynst them, whiche impugneth the one or inuadeth the other: but also, and that most chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the meane of his dignitie (if that be imploied where it shuld be, and este<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as it ought to be) he shuld more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually with his learnyng and witte assayle vice and errour, moste pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ennemies to christen men, hauinge
<pb facs="3"/>
thervnto for his sworde and speare his tunge and his penne. And where for the more reuerēce due to the order of priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode, it is most congruent and sittyng, that preaching in commune assembles, be reserued onely to that ministracion, yet where a knyght or other man, not being of a lite estimacion, hath lernyng ioyned with moderate discrecion, yf he being zelouse of vertue, and meued on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by charitie, wolde fayne haue other men to remembre their state and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, and according to their dueties, to loue god, and to feare his terrible sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, what lawe or raison should lette hym, with an humble spirite and vncor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupted intent, to set furth in writing or print, that whiche shalbe commodious to many men? And if he be a knight, or in other authoritie (for the rarenesse of learnynge founden in suche men) the warke shal be muche the better imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and of the moo men desyred. Also for asmuche as I am a sheriffe, I think my selfe the more bounden to bee thus occupied. For sens it pertaineth to myn office, and also the lawes of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme doo compell me to punishe trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressours: Howe muche more is it my
<pb facs="4"/>
duetie, to doo the best that I can, by all studye and meanes to withdrawe men from transgressing the lawes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes of god, whiche beinge diligently and truely obserued, the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions of transgressyng of temporall lawes should be clerely excluded? Moreouer as often as I doo consyder the temporall punyshementes, and doo abhorre the sharpenesse of theim, I do reuolue in my mynde, what horrible peynes are prepared for theim, whome the sonne of god shall condemne at his generall iugement, to the whiche, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall tormentes being compared, doo seme but a shadow: here begynne I to feare, not for my selfe onely, but alsoo for other, which either in transgressing goddis lawes, or neglectynge our due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties do prouoke his wrath daily by dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plesyng hym. Wherfore aswel for myn owne erudicion, as for the remembrāce of other men, I haue gathered togither out of holy scripture this litle treatise: whiche often tymes radde and kept in remembraunce, shall be a preseruatiue against death euerlasting. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching your oportunitie in the receiuyng it, althoughe your ministraciou be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary,
<pb facs="4"/>
yet remembre the wordes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che our sauiour Christ spake vnto Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tha. What I meane therby, by redyng and digestyng that place, whiche is in the tenthe chapitre of Luke, ye shal ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily perceiue, without an expositour. At the least waie either by day or by night Martha shall finde oportunitie to sitte downe by her sister, if not, she shall find but litle thanke for all her good house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyfery. If Martha ministrynge vnto Christ temporally, had no more thanke for hir labor, what thanke shal we loke fore, whiche alwaie bee occupied about thynges that be worldly? thereby see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng onely our temporall commoditie. But yet in our dayly exercise we maie oftentymes ioyne the two systers togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as well by secrete thankes gyuen to god for his sundry benefittes, as by frequent meditacion of our laste daie. Whervnto we shall fynde occasion, as often as we do here the bell ryng at the death or terrement of any man, or here reported of pestilence or warre, thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng theim than to be the trumpettes of death, whiche do call vs to reknyng. And as touchynge the readyng of this litle woorke, if ye do rede it in the masse
<pb facs="5"/>
while, for lacke of tyme more conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, I dare vndertake, god will bee therwith nothyng offended: but ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therwith stered the more deuoutly to serue hym, he shall receyue it of you as a good praier, sens that meditacion and praier be but one thing in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And yet meditacion is the more constant. For in praier the mynde is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes wandring, and thinketh least on that, whiche by the tunge is expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. In this wise dooinge, ye shall not lacke oportunitie to reade ouer this boke, whiche shall not seme longe vnto suche as I thinke that ye be, that is to saie, in whome witte ouerfloweth not grace, but gyueth place to her. Finally by readyng therof I trust vnto god we bothe shall receyue eche comforte of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as well in this present worlde, as in the worlde to come: whiche is the perfection of amitie, whiche many mo men haue writen of, than haue truely vsed as they should doo. Thus I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte you to god, whom I moste herti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly praie, to keepe you alwaie in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour long to continue.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>