<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honourable Sir Iohn Hart, Knight, Lorde Mayor of the Cittie of London: and to the right worshipfull Ma. Richard Gurney, and Ma. Stephen Soame, Sheriffes of the same Cittie. Robert Greene wysheth increase of ho∣nour and worshippe.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1590</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105811_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02167</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12307</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105811</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honourable Sir Iohn Hart, Knight, Lorde Mayor of the Cittie of London: and to the right worshipfull Ma. Richard Gurney, and Ma. Stephen Soame, Sheriffes of the same Cittie. Robert Greene wysheth increase of ho∣nour and worshippe.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The Royal Exchange : Contayning sundry aphorismes of phylosophie, and golden principles of morrall and naturall quadruplicities. Vnder pleasant and effectuall sentences, dyscouering such strange definitions, deuisions, and distinctions of vertue and vice, as may please th grauest cittizens, or youngest courtiers. Fyrst written in Italian, and dedicated to the Signorie of Venice, nowe translated into English, and offered to the cittie of London. Rob. Greene, in Artibus Magister</title>
                 <author>Rinaldi, Oraziofin id s105920/upd</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <distributor>Wright, William 1</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1590</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Nelson, Thomas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>80 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the right honourable Sir Iohn Hart, Knight, Lorde Mayor of the Cittie of London: and to the right worshipfull Ma. Richard Gurney, and Ma. Stephen Soame, Sheriffes of the same Cittie. Robert Greene wysheth increase of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and worshippe.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the golden Tripos, (right Honourable, and no lesse Worshipfull) whereon was written <hi>Detur sapients,</hi> was found in the Promontories of Grecia, they presented it to <hi>Socrates:</hi> and such Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaries as could from the Gymnosophists, draw any speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all principle of gouernment, brought all their opinions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Librarie of <hi>Themistocles.</hi> The Graecians dooing the one because <hi>Socrates</hi> was a wise man, the Antiquaries the other, for that <hi>Themistocles</hi> was a great polytitian. Apollo is worthy of his Laurell, Mercurie of his Caduceus, Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Scepter: Caesar must haue his due, Kinges theyr fealtie, and Magistrates their honours, euen with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. Hauing (right Honorable and Worshipful) read ouer an Italian Pamphlet, dedicated to the Signorie of Venice, called <hi>La Burza Reale,</hi> full of many strange &amp; ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall Aphorismes, ending in short contriued Quadru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicities, translating it in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>o our vulgare English tongue, &amp; keeping the tytle, which signifieth the <hi>Royall Exchange,</hi> I presumed, as the Italian made offer of his worke to the Venetian state, so to present the imitation of his labours to
<pb facs="3"/>
the pyllers of thys honourable Cittie of London, which to counteruaile theyr <hi>Burza Reale,</hi> haue a <hi>Royall Exchange:</hi> flourishing with as honorable Merchaunts, as theirs with <hi>valorosissim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap> Mercadori.</hi> But to leaue off comparisons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause such insertions are odious, yet this boldly wee may boast out of the Antiquaries, that our Cittie of London, that famous Troyno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ant, plotted and erected by <hi>Brute</hi>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> and after famozed by king <hi>Lud,</hi> and his successors, is more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient farre then their Cittie of Venice. For theyr Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, although theyr cheefe Gouernour be a Duke, yet his estimation is so circumscript within the counterchecks of the <hi>Consiliaedori,</hi> that his Dukedome is a bondage, his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie small, and his commaund little, and <hi>Ex Cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>mper manca <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>st iustitia,</hi> in so much that the verie poore C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ttizens will in derision, call him <hi>Aurco s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ruidore:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Lord Mayor of London, entituled with honour and knight-hoode, purchased by his Predicessours valour, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom the Sheriffes are next in authoritie, hath by a speciall Charter and priuiledge, graunted him from the Crowne, the Lie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tenantshyp, and absolute gouernaunce and reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ment of the Cittie, in such ample manner, as hys commaund stretcheth to the setting vp and aduauncing of ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>tue, and to the suppressing and abolishing of vice and vanities. Prouided that the honourable C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ttizens alwaies carefull for the Common-wealth, elect such a graue, an auncient Magistrate, as for his vertue, religion, wealth &amp; worthinesse, may rightly be called <hi>Pater Patria.</hi> For our Merchaunts and other Cittizens, though they generalli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> attaine not to that excesse of riches that the Venetians do, yet for the enlargement of the liberties of their Citie, they stand so much vppon their credits, as they grudge not to disburse any sum, eyther necessarie to their priuate <hi>Polu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>ia,</hi> or helpfull to the common profit of theyr Countrey. For religion they haue the Gospel, for iustice a seuere law executed with clemencie, beeing Merchaunts wyth theyr
<pb facs="3"/>
freendes and traffique fellowes, otherwise martiall minded souldiours, to resist the violence eyther of any priuate mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinie, or any common enemie, as valiant to attempt in wars as to counsaile in peace. And although Venice be a Cittie seated in the Ocean, and enuironed round about with the Sea, standing much vpon their Armado and Nauall fight, yet our Cittizens of London, (her Maiesties royall fleete excepted) haue so many shyppes harboured within the Thames, as wyll not onelie match with all the Argoses, Galleyes, Galeons, and Pataches in Venice, but to encoū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by sea with the strongest Cittie in the whole worlde: Considering therefore, (right honourable and worshipful) the excellencie of thys Cittie, the honour of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, the worshyp of the Merchaunts, and the generall worthines of all in one simpathie. I thought good, as the Italian presented his <hi>Bursa Reale</hi> to the Venetians, so to presume the patronage of this <hi>Royall Exchange</hi> vnto your Honour, being worthily aduaunced to the regiment of the Cittie, and to the right worshipfull Sheriffes, for their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues called to their speciall offices: hoping your Lordship and theyr worships, will vouchsafe to patronise the labours of so meane a Scholler, if not for the worthines of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet for the name and tytle of the Pamphlet: frō which <hi>Royall Exchange,</hi> if any Cittizen or other gather any prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of worth, or haue in-sight for the following of vertue or auoyding of vice, their profits shall be noted to proceed from your honourable and worshipfull dispositions, vnder whose patronage this booke is shrowded. And thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting vpon your gracious and fauourable acceptaunce, I commit your Lordship and theyr worships to the tuition of the Almightie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Bounden to the honorable and worshipful of the Cittie,
<hi>Rob. Greene.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>