<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the louing Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105092_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18764</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5255</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105092</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the louing Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A scourge for rebels : wherin are many notable seruices truly set out, and thorowly discoursed of, with euerie particular point touching the troubles of Ireland, as farre as the painfull and dutiful seruice of the Earle of Ormound in sundrie sortes is manifestfestly [sic] knowen. Written by Thomas Churchyard Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cadman, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the louing Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y waking goodwil to the world, first for the
pleasuring of friends, generally to please
the multitude, keepes my <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> alwaies occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied
in suche matter as the time bringeth
forth, whiche time is mother &amp; nurse aswel
to bad causes, as to good actiōs. And it is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable
to a true Writer, to treate of both the
<gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>des, as the maner and nature in thinges discoursed of, giueth
light vnto. So finding plentie &amp; store of matter, both to study on,
&amp; trauaile with, I cannot but (for easing my burden) impart a
peece of my study with thee (of vertunous disposition) good friendly
Reader, not that my wordes haue such effect to worke a common
commodity, &amp; leade thee to like my doinges, (voyde of cunning,
style, &amp; eloquence) but to winne thy fauour, creeping as I may,
vnder thy sounde consideration, I laye my selfe playne &amp; open to
the iudgement and hastie opinions of many, which sodainely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
&amp; slowly allow the labour of willing writers. The grounde
whereof proceedes not of enuie, but of further cause then I name,
(Ignoraunce peraduenture a let for the true vnderstanding of
matter well meant) yet my hope is, thy grauitie and goodnesse,
(that beares with my ouerbolde presumption) will accept my
good meaning, &amp; passe ouer the faults of my booke &amp; fantasies I
had, when I took in hand to write this Discourse. The truth is in
sleeping softly on the cushion or carpet of peace (where age is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente
to take a nappe) the sounde of Drumme and Trumpet
awakened my muse. For a loude blast and brute of Irishe warres
bade me looke about me, and here what might be saide by good
seruices for the scourging of Rebelles. Then hearinge the
<pb facs="4"/>
fall or tragedie of Desmond, the faithful seruices and noblenesse
of Ormound: with many more thinges then nowe I expresse: I
tooke pen and registred in memorie, what was moste meete, and
fitte for thee to knowe in causes not yet published by anie true
report or Writer, doubting not, though the matter be but little,
the trueth thereof shal greatly delight thee. So commending all
that followes to thy vpright iudgement, I craue and earnestly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire
thee wishingly to reade this small discourse, called <hi>The
Scourge for Rebels.</hi> Promising out of hande to print another
woorke, called <hi>A rebuke to rebellion, and a triumph
to true Subiectes. So fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>