<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Argument to the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1596</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105074_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">B12205</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5737</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105074</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Argument to the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A fig for fortune. A.C</title>
                 <author>Copley, Anthony</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1596</date>
                 <publisher>A.,C.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Copley, Anthony.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Danter, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Jones (Jhones, Johnes), Richard</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 74, that is 84, 4 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Poetry</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>The Argument to the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N <hi>Elizian</hi> out-cast of Fortune, ranging on his Iade <hi>Melancholie</hi> through the Desert of his affliction, in hope to find out some where either ease or end of the same, hapneth first vpon <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toes</hi> ghost a spirit of Dispair &amp; self-misdoom which perswades him to kill himselfe: But, for she ended her Oratory with a Sulphur vanish frō out his sight, he misdoubted both her and her tale. Then posting onward through the residue of the night; he next chanceth on the spirit of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge:</hi> She perswades him blood and treacherie against all his enemies, as th'onlie means to remount to pristin blesse in despight of Fortune: But she likewise manifesting in the end the treason of her tale by a sudden whip-away from his eye at the sight of break of day in the East, left him also conceipted of her daunger. Thirdly, rapt from off his <hi>Melancholie</hi> (which now began to faint vnder him at the light of a new day of Grace) he was sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denlie mounted vpon the Steed of <hi>Good Desire,</hi> and by him brought to Mount-<hi>Sion</hi> the Temple of Peace; where by <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chtysius</hi> an Hermit (who greatlie woondred to see a distressed <hi>Elizian</hi> in those partes vnder so happie daies of <hi>Eliza</hi>) he was by him in the house of <hi>Deuotion</hi> catechized, and there also cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stially arm'd by an Angell, and within a while after in-denized by the high Sacrificator a Champion of that Temple against the insults of Fortune; whom I haue titled by the name of <hi>Doblessa</hi>
      <pb facs="5"/>in respect of the double danger both of her luring and lowring inconstancie: She, whiles the Sionttes were all in peacefull adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Almightie God in the Temple, came with her Babello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian-rout to assault the place, but was eftsoons by the valure of those Templers shamefullie repulsed: Feast and thankes was made to God therfore throughout all the Region; in which solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie the Grace of God houering ouer the multitude in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession time like a virgin attended vpon with all the Court of heauen, showr'd downe Roses amongst them, leauing them there a scambling for the same. The <hi>Elizian</hi> was one that scambled his lap-full among the rest: and for he thought it was his soueraigne Ladie <hi>Eliza,</hi> and those Roses hers, he was suddenly in ioy therof rapt home againe to <hi>Elizium.</hi>
   </p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>