<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>HOW THAT OVR PHISICKE AND Chyrurgerie is better, then that, the which the Auncients haue commonly vsed.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105601_Fr1_7</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A00755</idno>
           <idno type="STC">10881</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105601</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>HOW THAT OVR PHISICKE AND Chyrurgerie is better, then that, the which the Auncients haue commonly vsed.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A short discours of the excellent doctour and knight, maister Leonardo Phiorauanti Bolognese vppon chirurgerie : VVith a declaration of many thinges, necessarie to be knowne, neuer written before in this order: whervnto is added a number of notable secretes, found out by the saide author. Translated out of Italyan into English, by Iohn Hester, practicioner in the arte of distillation</title>
                 <author>Fioravanti, Leonardo</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>East (Est, Este), Thomas</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>8, 64 leaves, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Other</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Medical texts</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="medical_miscellany">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>HOW THAT OVR PHISICKE AND Chyrurgerie is better, then that, the which the Auncients haue commonly vsed.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no doubt, but that our newe Phisicke and Chyrurgerie, is better then that, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which the Auncients haue vsed: bicause it helpeth the sick with more ease and spéede, and much more safer, and to shew the troth, the Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciēts had neuer knowledge of our <hi>Dia Aromatico,</hi> nor of <hi>Electuario Angellica,</hi> nor of our <hi>Pillole Aquilone,</hi> nor did not make our <hi>siropo solutiuo,</hi> nor yet our <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no licore,</hi> with a number of other medicines found out by me, the which are written in the ende of this booke, with the which I haue done wonderful cures, as thou maist read in my <hi>Thesoro de la vita humana,</hi> and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly most necessary for all professours of this Arte, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause therein thou shalt finde so manye goodly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and it would cause the world to wonder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at. But to tourne to our purpose, I say that the Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients the which had not knowledge of our remedies, they wanted also knowledge of the true Phisicke, and Chyrurgerie, as by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> experience thou mayst sée, I say not this to speak euil of those wise auncient Doctors, that were inuentours there-off, but I say it to say the troth, and many shall be my testimony of this troth. Bicause in many countrys, wher our worke that are Imprinted are come, they begin to practise after our order. And this order of curinge: I repute it not to my science, but a worke that God would reueale vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worlde, thorow my meanes, and to shewe the troth, there hath bene none, that hath found the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines for woundes with so much ease and breuitie as I haue done.</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="8"/>Who hath euer founde the true Remedie for the Goute, for the Ouartain, for Fluxes, and all sorts of Feuers, as I haue done? or what is he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> euer brought the whole Art of Phisicke and Chyrurgerie into .viij. small volumes, as I haue done? What is he that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer writ of the Pestilence, and of his qualytie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies and orders to be vsed in the same, as I haue done. And if there be any that doth not credite me, let them make experience of all that I haue sayde, and I promise you and sweare as I am a true Knight, they shall finde more truth then I will write at this time, being as I haue said, a worke giuen of God, for a vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersal benefit of all the world, and forasmuch I exhort euery one of the professors of Physick &amp; Chirurgery, to follow this our truthe, bicause they are of so great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it séemeth miraculous vnto man, as I haue séene many yeares agoe, to my great honour, and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the people of the world, &amp; thus doing &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, thou shalt come to know y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> our Physick &amp; Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie is more better &amp; wholesome, then y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which hath bene vsed of the Auncients vntill this present time.</p>
   <div type="part">
      <head>Certeine remedies, for al Capitaines and souldiers that trauell eitherby water or lande.</head>
      <p>THere are <hi>.3.</hi> infirmities, that offend the souldiours in the campe aboue al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rest, the which are these, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, Woundes, &amp; Fluxes of the body, the which thou maist help in this order following, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> these medicines, that is our <hi>Quintaessence</hi> of wine, our <hi>Balsamo, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no licore, Quintaessencia solutiua,</hi> &amp; <hi>Specie Imperiale,</hi> &amp; the order to vse thē is thus. When any hath a feuer or a flux, then presently when y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> disease beginneth, let him bloud in one of the <hi>.2.</hi> vaines vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tongue, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it ouerthwart, &amp; this thou shalt do in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> euening, thē y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> next morning, take a dose of our imperial powder
<pb facs="9"/>
mixt with wine, and this ye may do with-out any dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et or strayght order, that being done, giue him <hi>.3.</hi> mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings together, halfe an ounce of our <hi>Quintaessence</hi> solutiue with broth. But if it be a flux, and that the Patient is not cured, let him stand in a colde bath of salt water of the Sea <hi>.3.</hi> or <hi>.4.</hi> houres or more, and hée shall bée perfectly holpe.</p>
      <p>Then as concerning wounds, as wel cuts as thrusts, and as wel gallings with arrows, as hargabush shot, and other sortes, thou shalt cure them thus. The first thing that ye shall doe to them, is to wash them very cleane with vrine, and then drye them well, then put there-in our <hi>Quintaessence</hi> of wine, &amp; presently ioyne the parts together, &amp; sow or stitch them close, then put there-vpon <hi>5.</hi> or <hi>.6.</hi> droppes of our <hi>Balsamo,</hi> and vppon the wound lay a cloth wet in our <hi>Magno licore,</hi> as hot as he may suffer it, and this ye shall do the first day: Than the next day follow this order: First put ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Quintaessence,</hi> and a lyttle of our <hi>Balsamo,</hi> &amp; then our <hi>Magno licore</hi> very hot, &amp; neuer change that medicine, and thus doing the wounde shall heale with great spéed, and in a quarter of the time, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chyrurgians is able to doe it, by the grace of God.</p>
   </div>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>