<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right honourable my verie
good Lord, the Lord Haward of Effingam, Lorde Cham∣berlaine
of the Queenes Maiesties houshold, one of her
Highnesse priuie Councell, and Knight of the most
noble order of the Garter, Thomas Church∣yard
wisheth increase of honour, and
many happie newe yeeres.</title>
           <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105092_Fr1_3</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18764</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5255</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105092</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right honourable my verie
good Lord, the Lord Haward of Effingam, Lorde Cham∣berlaine
of the Queenes Maiesties houshold, one of her
Highnesse priuie Councell, and Knight of the most
noble order of the Garter, Thomas Church∣yard
wisheth increase of honour, and
many happie newe yeeres.</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A scourge for rebels : wherin are many notable seruices truly set out, and thorowly discoursed of, with euerie particular point touching the troubles of Ireland, as farre as the painfull and dutiful seruice of the Earle of Ormound in sundrie sortes is manifestfestly [sic] knowen. Written by Thomas Churchyard Gentleman</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Dawson, Thomas</publisher>
                    <distributor>Cadman, Thomas</distributor>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>22 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right honourable my verie
good Lord, the Lord Haward of Effingam, Lorde Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine
of the Queenes Maiesties houshold, one of her
Highnesse priuie Councell, and Knight of the most
noble order of the Garter, Thomas Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard
wisheth increase of honour, and
many happie newe yeeres.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S all worldly giftes, good tournes, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
friendship and true affection springs
of good wil, so my good Lord, a certaine
kind of seruiceable liking towards your
Honour, thrusteth me forwarde to this
boldnesse, in presenting your L. a little
bare worke of mine, being stirred ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.
First, for the general fauour that the world beares
you (a loue not wonne without desert) and next, for the
fauour your noble Parents shewed me, I am encouraged
not onely to proceede to present some matter meete for
you to reade, but likewise to shew my selfe thankefull for
fauour receiued. So in waying those causes (as becomes
me) and knowing the good consideration your Lordship
carries (in sounde iudgement) of friendes that time did
plant, trueth makes growe, and triall doeth gather, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought
me of the Earle of Ormounde, who honoured
your Parentes, and loueth your selfe, in whiche conceite
of mine, I found that you hearing well of that woorthie
friend by my meanes, woulde beleeue I were zealous of
your Honour, and a fauourer of noble actions.</p>
   <p>Wherefore, and in respect a writer ought to be plaine,
I treate plainly in my booke of the Earle of Ormoundes
<pb facs="3"/>
seruices (knowne to many, and hid to a few) naming him
the scourge of Rebels as truely I proue.</p>
   <p>Which presumption of mine, in that regard and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
of his in gayning good report, I trust your Lordeship
will peyze in ballaunce of equall weight, iudging me to
boldnes as I merite, and his deseruings, as they shal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
by proofe to credite. So wishing great grace &amp; good
happe to your L. I present this my first new yeeres gift in
the latter time of mine age to your Honour, and the
worldes iudgement.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your L. humblie at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
Thomas Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>