<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right Hono∣rable, Phillip Earle of Arundell, Robert Greene wisheth increase of honour, with the full fruition of perfect felicity.</title>
           <author>Greene, Robert</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1584</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105814_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02136</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12276</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105814</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right Hono∣rable, Phillip Earle of Arundell, Robert Greene wisheth increase of honour, with the full fruition of perfect felicity.</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Morando the tritameron of loue : wherein certaine pleasaunt conceites, vttered by diuers woorthy personages, are perfectly dyscoursed, and three doubtfull questyons of loue, most pithely and pleasauntly discussed: shewing to the wyse howe to vse loue, and to the fonde, howe to eschew lust: and yeelding to all both pleasure and profitt. By Robert Greene, Maister of Artes in Cambridge</title>
                 <author>Greene, Robert</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1584</date>
                 <publisher>Charlewood, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Kingston, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>White, Edward 1</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>48 pages, 4°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Literature</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, <hi>Phillip</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundell, Robert Greene</hi> wisheth increase of honour, with the full fruition of perfect felicity.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Emperour <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitian</hi> (Right Honourable) made him nets to catch flies, least happily he might be found idle. <hi>Caligula</hi> beeing wearied with weighty affayres, woulde (to passe away the time) gather Cockles. The <hi>Persian</hi> Kinges semetimes shaued stickes. <hi>Virgill</hi> chose rather to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>ade rude <hi>Ennius,</hi> then to be founde without a booke in hys hande. Time wisheth rather to be spent in vaine toyes, then in idle thoughts, the one driueth away fantasies, the other breedeth Melancholie. <hi>Mercurie</hi> vouchsafed once to drinke of <hi>Philemons</hi> Earthen potte. <hi>Apollo</hi> gaue Oracles at <hi>Delphos,</hi> as well to the poore man for his mite, as to the rich man for his treasure. <hi>Phillip</hi> thought well of the water which a poore shepheard offred to him, in a greasie Bottle: duety bindes the Subiecte to present, and courtesie the Prince to accept, in the one, will is an excuse, in the other, courtesie a bountifull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde. <hi>Apelles</hi> (right Honourable) presented <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> with the counterfaite of <hi>Campaspe,</hi> the face not fully finished, because he liked the picture: and I offer this pamphlet vnto your Lordship, not well furnished because
<pb facs="3"/>
you are a louer of learning.</p>
   <p>
      <hi>Zewxes</hi> paynting <hi>Triton,</hi> drewe onely his face, the rest he hidde with the tumbling waues of the Sea. And I setting foorth <hi>Morandos</hi> discourse, shew onely his bare talke, the rest I rudely shaddowe with an imperfect tale. The <hi>Persians</hi> caused their Apes alwayes to maske in cloth of Golde, to couer theyr deformetie. <hi>Timocles</hi> caused his Popingay to perke vnder a Dragon of Brasse, that the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trature might defende her from the <hi>Vultures</hi> tyranny: and I seeke to shrowde my simple worke, vnder your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours winges, thinking one dramme of your Lordships fauoure, sufficient to fence me from the venemous teeth of those byting Vypers, who seeke to discredite all, hauing themselues no credite at all. <hi>Achilles</hi> made it not strange to take a viewe of <hi>Phidias</hi> clownish woorke, because it was the image of <hi>Mars:</hi> and I hope your Honour wyll vouchsafe to cast a glaunce on this silie Booke, for that it represents the discourse of diuers woorthy personages, although of it selfe, it is like <hi>Zewxes</hi> counterfaits, which seemed at a blush to be Grapes, but being throughly view<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, were bare shaddowed coloures. The Phisitions prescribe in theyr dyet, that sometimes bitter Pills, doo asmuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>acks, as sweete Potions. <hi>Augustus</hi> sometimes would solace himselfe, as well with <hi>Ennius</hi> drosse, as with <hi>Maros</hi> Golde: and it may bee your Honour passing ouer many learned workes, will at the last stumble at this fonde toye, and laugh as <hi>Sigismonde</hi> did at the Pomegranat, not that he smiled at the fruite, but at the simple mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the man which presented him with so small a gift<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap> Resting vpon this point, I commit your Lordship to the Almightie.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your Honours humbly to commaund
Robert Greene.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>