<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Of the zealous Author, his much respected Vnkle, and his comfortable Description.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1629</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105012_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19123</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5533</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105012</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>Of the zealous Author, his much respected Vnkle, and his comfortable Description.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Of death a true description : and against it a good preparation: together with a sweet consolation, for the suruiung mourners. By Iames Cole merchant</title>
                 <author>Cole, James, merchant</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Mathewes (Mathusius), Augustine</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1629</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 207, 1 page, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Poems</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                    <term>Poetry</term>
                    <term>Philosophy and morality</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="encomium">
   <pb facs="8"/>
   <head>Of the zealous Author, his much respected Vnkle, and his comfortable Description.</head>
   <l>SHall I reioyce because his Penne doth teach</l>
   <l>Ʋs how die, and heauenly blisse to reach?</l>
   <l>Or shall I mourne, because to be our guide,</l>
   <l>His worthy selfe he hath to vs den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>d</l>
   <l>Longer on earth? His words perswade beliefe,</l>
   <l>Farther confirmance but augments our griefe.</l>
   <l>His Booke suffu'd, that pointing Mercurie,</l>
   <l>He needed not to guid vs, and to die.</l>
   <l>His life wee wanted more, that could vs tell</l>
   <l>That hee that liued godly should die well.</l>
   <l>Yet what it was I dare not well set downe,</l>
   <l>For feare his ashes modesty sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>uld frowne.</l>
   <l>But let them speake that comment on his name,</l>
   <l>A man of pious, learned, vpright fame:</l>
   <l>Whose words and deedes did so concurre in one</l>
   <l>That what he said, t'was true, t'was sure, twas done;</l>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <l>Whose vertuous presence was so pretious deere,</l>
   <l>That most did wish he still might haue beene heere.</l>
   <l>But loe his liberall charity: If thus</l>
   <l>His company was gratefull vnto vs,</l>
   <l>He shewes vs how we may enioy it still,</l>
   <l>And striues our wishes happier to fulfill</l>
   <l>Then we conceiue: He cann't descend againe:</l>
   <l>We must ascend, and there by him remaine.</l>
   <l>Thus while we enter his societie,</l>
   <l>Ours will be Saints and Angels companie.</l>
   <l>But lest wee should vnskilfull Pilgrims stray,</l>
   <l>Not knowing how to goe, which is the way;</l>
   <l>Lest that our eyes waxe dim'd by sinfull slime,</l>
   <l>That we perceiu'd not which way he did clime,</l>
   <l>Behold in this good legacie of his</l>
   <l>He shewes vs the true way, through death, to blisse.</l>
   <l>Lest we should feare th'aff ighting face of death,</l>
   <l>And quake to heare the fare-well of our breath;</l>
   <l>To his olde Mate, he doth vnmaske the fiend,</l>
   <l>Shewes her sting forcelesse, prooues our foe our friend.</l>
   <l>So that we bold m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y gaze her in the face,</l>
   <l>And that we fear'd so much with ioy embrace.</l>
   <l>She is no euill thing, but naturall,</l>
   <l>According to Gods will common to all.</l>
   <l>
      <hi>The bodie's but a sleepe, it feeles no paine,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>The soule dies not, but mounts vnto the traine</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Of heauenly Saints. Why should earths vanities</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Detaine vs from these happy glorious skies?</hi>
   </l>
   <pb facs="9"/>
   <l>
      <hi>Or feare of iudgement? by it we receiue</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>A ioy which mortall minde cannot conceiue.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Therefore when sicknesse pale doth enter in</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>By Gods command, vsherd by in-bred sinne,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>That messenger of death; thy house befit,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Thy body, soule, and all to welcome it.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Thy selfe striue well to arme, death to vnarme,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>By shunning sinne with faith, and feare no harme.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Repent and pray, and to thy heauenly peace,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>And certaine comfort will thy faith encrease.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>So that death shall thy soule not terrifie,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>But be to thee a wished victorie,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Which brings thee to a ioyfull Paradise,</hi>
   </l>
   <l>
      <hi>Before the Lambe, aboue the starrie skies.</hi>
   </l>
   <l>There is our Author now; and there doth shine</l>
   <l>Like a cleare starre, our once Marchant-diuine.</l>
   <l>There he's in his reward. If we desire</l>
   <l>To beare a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>rt in that celestiall quire,</l>
   <l>Let vs these his directions embrace,</l>
   <l>And follow thus through death his fore-runne trace.</l>
   <l>Then shall our end be happy, for they will</l>
   <l>Direct vs through this dale to <hi>Sions</hi> bill.</l>
   <q>
      <l>Vt terror Mortis tibi sit victoria, larvam</l>
      <l>Aspicias intus; Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>s fera vita placens.</l>
   </q>
   <bibl>Abr. Bush. <hi>Art. Mag.</hi>
   </bibl>
   <pb facs="10"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>