<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Right worshipfull his verie good friend, M. Alex∣an Nowel, Deane of Paules.</title>
           <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1580</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105093_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A18767</idno>
           <idno type="STC">5259</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105093</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Right worshipfull his verie good friend, M. Alex∣an Nowel, Deane of Paules.</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A warning for the wise, a feare to the fond, a bridle to the lewde, and a glasse to the good : Written of the late earthquake chanced in London and other places, the. 6. of April 1580. for the glorie of God, and benefite of men that warely can walke, and wisely can iudge. Set forth in verse and prose, by Thomas Churchyard Gentleman. Seen and allowed</title>
                 <author>Churchyard, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1580</date>
                 <publisher>Allde, John.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Ling (Lyng), Nicholas</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>32 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                    <term>News books</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>To the Right worshipfull his verie good friend, M. Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
         <desc>•…</desc>
      </gap>
      <hi>Nowel,</hi> Deane of Paules.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fatherlye and faithfull maner of your diuine Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (M. Deane,) with the blotlesse life you lead (soū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the vniuersal report of good people) made mee often desirous to dedicate some labour of mine, to the protectiō of your sound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And now pricked forward by Gods mightie motion (and maruellous workes of late) to bestowe a fewe verses to a vertuous personage, in a vitious world &amp; dangerous season, I haue chosen you among a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to sounde out the trumpet of Gods glorie, and to giue passage to the playnesse of my pen, and willing paines I haue taken: Not as though my wordes or inuention (voide of depe profundity) might aduance any waye the high maiestie of God, or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the good Fame you haue gotten. But being in humility of minde, loking to the basenesse of this world, and meannes of my
<pb facs="2"/>
calling, (vnfurnished both of heauenly gifts &amp; worldly good fortunes) I presumed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row my pen and studie, to purchase you a friend, and reclaime the enimies of God to come home to their consciences, and looke on the wonders of the Lorde, that dayly is working amōg his louing people. So ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaning to flatter (where tender eares can abyde no doublenesse) nor stretche out a bare Epistle, with a long discourse of bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed wordes, I betake you to the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, committing that followes (this simple short Scedule) to the great and good consideration of your Wisdome. From my lodging this eight of April. Your wel willer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes at commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Thomas Churchyard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1+ letters">
            <desc>•…</desc>
         </gap>.</signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>