<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the right honourable, Lord Robert Dudley, Earle of Ley∣cester, Baron of Denbigh, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter.</title>
           <author>Sanford, James</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1573</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S105885_Fr1_4</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A02336</idno>
           <idno type="STC">12464</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S105885</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the right honourable, Lord Robert Dudley, Earle of Ley∣cester, Baron of Denbigh, Knight of the most noble order of the Garter.</title>
                 <author>Sanford, James</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The garden of pleasure : contayninge most pleasante tales, worthy deeds and witty sayings of noble princes [et] learned philosophers, moralized. No lesse delectable, than profitable. Done out of Italian into English, by Iames Sanforde, Gent. Wherein are also set forth diuers verses and sentences in Italian, with the Englishe to the same, for the benefit of students in both tongs</title>
                 <author>Guicciardini, Lodovico</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Bynneman (Benneyman, Binneman), Henry</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1573</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>4, 111, 1 leave, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Adages, aphorisms, emblem books, jests, proverbs</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="3"/>
   <head>To the right honourable, Lord Robert Dudley, Earle of Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester, Baron of Denbigh, Knight <hi>of the most noble order</hi> of the Garter.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is lefte in writing that vvhē the <hi>Teians</hi> could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the spitfulnes of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians,</hi> forsakyng their Citie, they remoued to <hi>Abdera,</hi> a Citie of <hi>Thrace,</hi> &amp; that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of grew this Prouerbe, <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>: whereby is signified, that in great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie vve shuld not despaire, but haue some hope: and that there is some place for vs to flee vnto for succour, if any (beyond all mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure) continueth to molest vs. This I vvrite to this ende, that beyng (I knovv not by vvhat destiny) greuously troubled fevv yeares past, &amp; finding true that of the vnfortunate there is no fortunate friend, I had recourse altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to my former studies, vvhich for a time I had left off, and eftsoones toke bookes in hand, vvhich are the faithfullest counsellers, in aduersitie the best comforters, and vvhose fruits in both fortunes are the richest posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions: for learning by no meanes can be taken
<pb facs="3"/> avvay: all other things as fickle being placed in fortunes hand, ebbing &amp; flovving like the sea, vvaxing and vvaning like the Moone, are full of change and mutabilitie, so that a lyfe voide of afliction hath hapned to none: and true it is as <hi>Hesiodus</hi> saith, time is othervvhile a mother, othervvhile a stepdame: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Plinie</hi> sayeth, that he is in doubte, vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature bee oftner a stepdame, or a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as she vvhich bringeth foorth so manye poysons, and so manye remedies. There is none almost but hath susteined some greuous misfortune in the course of his life, and he that hath passed the most part of his age vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trouble, is many times assailed vvith som sharp storme of fatall aduersitie in the end, as <hi>Policrates</hi> the tyrant of <hi>Samia</hi> vvas, vvho be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proude of his long prosperitie, and desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to proue the malice of Fortune, caste a ring of great value into the sea, vvhich being svvallovved by a fish, and the same takē came again to his hands, so fortune hitherto ceased not to flatter him, but at last shee gaue him a most cruel fall for being taken of his enemy, he ended his life miserably vpon the gallovvs together vvith his false felicitie, vvhiche she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveth that continuall prosperitie is not good and turneth lastly into aduersitie remedilesse,
<pb facs="4"/> that none should flatter himselfe in vvelfare, &amp; that it is better othervvhyle to endure some storms of trouble in youth, than most misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aduersitie in elder age. VVhō fortune che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risheth in the beginning in the ende many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes she bringeth to destruction, &amp; vvhen she most fauoureth, she is chiefly to be feared. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Frances Pescione</hi> a learned Italian said, that aduersitie is better than prosperity, for the one maketh a man to knovv himself, and to remē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his mortal state, the other engēdreth pride and forgetfulnesse of our humaine condition. Fortune beareth rule ouer the body, but not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the mind, she vvorketh hir tyrānie on out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvarde things, and not on invvarde: and if the mind be vvith holsom doctrin diligently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, the crueltie of fortune may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter endured, nay rather nothing at all estemed, if vvith the diuine <hi>Plato,</hi> &amp; after him vvith the <hi>Stoike Epistetus</hi> vve hold, that the minde alone is man, and that the bodye is nothing else but the prison or sepulchre of the soule, vvhose e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils as they are greater and more greuous than them of the body, so is the minde by no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes more to be comforted &amp; kept in constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, than by good doctrin and reading of vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie authors, to vvhom I haue fled for cōfort and counsaile, as the <hi>Teians</hi> for succour vvent
<pb facs="4"/> to <hi>Abdera,</hi> and out of vvhome I haue gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red such things as haue priuately recreated &amp; comforted me, translating them, as also (as I truste) shall delighte all suche as do reade the same. I haue long time thought vvith my selfe vvhome specially I shoulde make patrone of this booke, and among many noble persona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, your honoure came to my remembrance, vvho is able to purchase him credite and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie vvith those mē vnto vvhom your god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse, goodnesse and constancie (vvhiche you haue hitherto alvvays shevved, &amp; do yet shevv in maintayning true religiō) is thorovvly kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vven. VVherfore I besech you most ernestly to accept this token of my good vvil, &amp; at leasure to read it, for I hope it vvil not seme vnplesant to youre lordship and others, in the reading, asvvell for the pleasaunt verses of sundrie Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Poets therein recited, as also for the graue and plesaunt sayings &amp; deedes of diuers prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Philosophers, sentences, &amp; prouerbes, in it contayned. The Almightie, vvho hathe blessed you vvith his heauenly giftes, vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to preserue you in healthe, and encrease &amp; multiply youre honoure and his good giftes in you.</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>Your honours moste humbly to cōmaund. <hi>IAMES SANFORD.</hi>
      </signed>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>