<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>The Prolog</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1485</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106502_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A23591</idno>
           <idno type="STC">9995</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106502</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>The Prolog</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Here begynnys a schort [and] breue tabull on thes cronicles</title>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Schoolmaster—Printer</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--Saint Albans</pubPlace>
                    <date>1485</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>580 pages, illustrations, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="prologue">
   <pb facs="10"/>
   <head>The Prolog</head>
   <p>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>N so myche that it is necessari to all creaturis of cris<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten religyon. or of fals religyon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>s gētyles and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>
      <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>homytes to knaw theer prince or prynces that regne a pon them. and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m to obey. So it is commodyus to knaw theer n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ill actis or d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ys. and the circumstās of theer lyu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>. Ther fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> ī the yeer of our lorde .M.iiij<seg rend="sup">C</seg>.lxxxiij. And in the xxiij. yeer of the regne of Kyng Edward the fourth at Saynt Albons so that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>en may knaw the actys naemly of our no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bull kyngys of Englond is cōpylit to gether thys book. &amp;̄ moor ouer is translayt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 span">
         <desc>〈…〉</desc>
      </gap> latin ī to englich froom the beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>ng of the world the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ynage of crist: from Adā till it be cōm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> to Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid. &amp;̄ from Dauid the kyngys of israel &amp;̄ of Iuys: the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>gh byschoppys in theer days wyth the Iuges and {pro}phettis. The iiij pryncipall Reames of the worlde. that is to say of Babulon: of Perces. of Grekys. and of Romans. &amp;̄ all the Em{per}oures of Rome or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 word">
         <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
      </gap> by o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>dyr and theer namys. and mony a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabull fadyr: wyth cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> of ther actys breuyatly as moor plan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly is dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>t in the chapytur n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap>t aftyr. And heer be rehersit the namys of the autors of whom thees Cronyclys ben translatte moost naamly. Galfridus Munmoth monke in hys boke of Brute. Saynt Beed ī the actys of Englond I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>m̄ Beed in hys boke of tymys. Gyldas in the actys of Bretan Wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Malmisbery monke in the actis of kyngys of Englond &amp;̄ bisshoppys. Cassiderus of the actys of Em{per}ours and bisshop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pys. Saynt Austyn de Ciuitate dei Tytus Lyuyus de ges<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis Romanorum Martyn Penytēcia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>y to the pope in his Cro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyclys of Em{per}ours &amp;̄ bysshoppys. And namly Theobaldus Cartusiencis contenyng in hys boke the progresse off all nota<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bull fadyres from the begynyng off the worlde vn to oure tyme wyth the notabull actys of the saem. ¶In thys neew transla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion ar contened many notabull and meruelles thyngys▪ &amp;̄ the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap> been legged by auctoryte of mony famous clerkys</p>
   <p>
      <pb facs="11"/>And that eu{er}y man may knaw how thes croniclis be ordyrt ye shall vndyr <abbr>stond</abbr> that this boke is deuidit ī to vij partys. Off the wych the fyrst {per}te cōtenys from Adam till Brute cam in to bretan ¶The secūd parte contenes from brute cam fyrst in to Englond vn to the cyte of Rome was byld be romol{us}. ¶The therd part cōtenes sethyn rome wos byld vn to Crist wos born of our lady mari ¶The fourth from thens vn to the cōyng of the saxons ī to englond ¶The fyft part from thēs vn to the cōmīg of the danys ¶The sext part from thens vn to the cōmyng off the normās ¶The seuīt part from the Normās vn to owr tym the wich is vndir the regne of kyng Edward the fourth xxiij yer whos nobull croniclis be custū may not be seen ¶And so in e{er}<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy part of thes .vij. partes is shewed the most and necessary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys of all the kyngis of Englond &amp;̄ ther namys wrettyn abooe in the margent that euery man may fynd them soon. And afor the kyng{is} of englōd actis be writī. ther is writī y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> linage of crist from Adā till that crist was borne of our lady with the egh bys<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shopp &amp;̄ the iuge that war ī that tyme. &amp;̄ certan of ther actis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessari. till it be cūmyn to crist wos borne. And aftir that cryst wos borne &amp;̄ peter wos pope of rome is shewed be ord{er} the namys of all the popys and Emprours of rome afoor and aftir wyth cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tan off ther actis breuyatly. And mony other dyu{er}es thyngis &amp;̄ in̄uellus ī thes mens days fallyng. And it is shewid eueri thīg in his place how mony yere it fell aftyr the begynyng of the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lde and how long afoor that Crist was borne. And when that I cum to crist wos borne then it is wrettyn how long any thyng fell aftyr the Natiuite of crist. And this is the ordyr off thys boke and the thyngis that be spokyn of.</p>
   <p>And to men desyryng to haue aueray knawlech of thes Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyclis or of any other hit is necessary to knaw sex thīg{is}
<pb facs="11"/>
¶The first is the statye of thīg{is}. &amp;̄ thos ben ij. con is fro the begynnyng of the world vn to cryst: the wych is <abbr>cald</abbr> the state of demacion. The secund is from cryst to the end of the world the wych is cald the state of reconsiliacion ¶The secund thyng is the diuision of tymys. &amp;̄ thoo be iij. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>n is a foor the law of Moi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ses. anodir is vndyr the law of moyses. anodir is vndyr the law of grace aftyr cryst <abbr>dyed</abbr> ¶The iij. is the gou{er}nyng of kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>domes &amp;̄ as for that ye most knaw that all thogh thar war iii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>. principall kyngdōys that is to say of Babulon of Perses of G<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>recis &amp; Romans neu{er} the lees os to the course of the world &amp;̄ the ordyr of holy scriptur the fyrst gouernyng wos vndirfadyrs from Adam vn to Moyses. The secund vndir Iuges fro moises vn to saul The thyrd vndyr kyng{is} fro Saul vn to Zorobobel. The forthe vnd{er} Bisshoppis fro zorobobel vn to crist ¶The iiij. is the diu{er}site of lawis and thos war .v. The fyrst wos the law of Natur &amp;̄ that wos cōmyn to all men. The <abbr>secūd</abbr> is the law or the custum of Gētils when that vndir kyng Nyno be gan the pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pull to worshype fals goddys. The thyrd vndir the law writtyn roos the law of Iues when circūcision diuidyt the iues from odir pepull. The iiij. vndir Crist roos thhe law of cristyn men wheen fayth and grace of the sacramentis informyd y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lyffe of mē. The v. vndir Machomyte roos the law of Sarysons &amp;̄ torkys. The sext is the nobulnes or vnnobulnes in dedys. and as to thes it is to knaw that vij. {per}sons be red of whom the dedys mony tymes har had in mynd in hystoryes. That is to wete of a Prince ī his reame. of a Knyght in batell. of a Iuge in his place. of a Bys<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shope in the clergy▪ of a Polityke man in the pepull. of an Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band man in an howse. and of an Abbot ī his chyrche. And of thes ar wretyn mony tymes the laudes of good men. and the pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nychmentis of the curssit men. The sext is the trew cowntyng of the yeris. and as to that it is to be knaw that ther war viij. ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of nombring or cōtyng of the yeris iii. aftyr the hebreus ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>.
<pb facs="12"/>
aftyr thee Greky. con. aftyr the Romans. and. con. now aftyr the Cristyn men. The hebreus iij. maner of wyse begynyth thar yere. aftyr the Hebre{us} ther is the yere vsuall begynyng at Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuary the wych they vse in connandys and bargans makyng. And the yere lefull begynnyng at Marche the wych they vse in ther <abbr>ceimonyes</abbr>. And the yere emergens from May begynyng when they went from Egypte. the vse in ther Cronyclys &amp;̄ Cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culacionis ¶The Grekys nomburth ther yeres iij. maner of wyse. fyrst to the glory and ioy of ther victory. Contyth thar ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res from the destruccion of Troy the fyrst the secund the therd the fourth <abbr>etc</abbr> ¶Then aftyr the cheualry be gon at the hyll of O<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lympus the notefied ther yeres aftyr the same Olimpiadū &amp;̄ wat Olimpiodes is ye shall knaw after in tha boke. The iij. when they be gan to haue lordshyp of all the world they notefyed theer yeres thes māer of wyse. In the yere of the regne of grekys the iiii. the x. the xv. <abbr>etc.</abbr> as is it opyn in the boke of machabeorum ¶Then after the Romans gou{er}nyng the world. cōtyt or nō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buryt ther yeres Ab vrbe cōdita ¶The last of all cristyn mē<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cowntitt ther yeres from the Incarnacion of Crist. and be cause we be criseyn men. we vse most to nomb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#pdcc" extent="2 letters">
         <desc>••</desc>
      </gap> fro the begynyng off the world vn to crist wos borne. And fro crist wos borne. vn to our tyme. and this ordyr is kepyt in all the boke of euery thyng in his place as it is sayd a foor.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>