<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>To the Christiā reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1551</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106489_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A05392</idno>
           <idno type="STC">15544</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106489</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>To the Christiā reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>A meditacion vpon the Lordes prayer, made by Thomas Leuer, at Sayncte Mary Wol Churche in London. Anno. M.D.LI</title>
                 <author>Lever, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <publisher>Day, John 1</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1551</date>
                 </imprint>
                 <extent>14 pages, 8°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <pb facs="2"/>
   
   <head>To the Christiā reader.</head>
   <p>
      <q xml:lang="lat">
         <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ropter, laborem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opū, et gemitum pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perum, nunc exurgā dicit dominus.</q>
      <note place="margin">Psal. xii.</note> Sure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye euen nowe in great scarsitie lack and dearth of meate, dryncke, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and all other necessaries, the sorowful sighes of the poore and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, muste either sinke into the riche mennes hartes, and from theim pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure relyue, and comforte, vnto the nedye members of Christes bodye: or els directlye ascende vnto the throne of Goddes Iustice, and from thence bryng downe indignacyon and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce, to destroye wycked worlde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, which being thē selfs in welth and aboundaunce, fele no gryete of their brothers distresse and misery.</p>
   <p>¶But if any man, euery weke wil be content, to spare one meale of him self, &amp; bestowe the price of that meale in Charitable Almose to relyue the pore, and the time of the same in god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly meditacion and Praier, to dispose his owne mynde deuoutly: then shal
<pb facs="3"/>
      
al suche feele and taste, both of poore mennes honger, and of Godly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in abstinēce and praier, yea, and many poore be much relyued, and no rich man any thynge charged, and so thereby Goddes vengaunce auoided and Gods grace procured, when as fastyng and praier doeth plucke out of mennes hartes coueteousnes which is the roote of all euil and the cause of all calamities that nowe dooe trouble, greue, and daunger al men: This meditacion therfore of the Lordes praier, shall be good comfortable spirituall fode, in that tyme of bodi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly abstinence.</p>
   <figure>
      <figDesc>typographic decoration</figDesc>
   </figure>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>