<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE PRAEFACE OF THE Author, setting out the dignitie, and Am∣ple vse of Cosmographie.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1559</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106671_Fr1_6</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A19700</idno>
           <idno type="STC">6119</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106671</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE PRAEFACE OF THE Author, setting out the dignitie, and Am∣ple vse of Cosmographie.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The cosmographical glasse : conteinyng the pleasant principles of cosmographie, geographie, hydrographie, or nauigation. Compiled by VVilliam Cuningham Doctor in Physicke</title>
                 <author>Cuningham, William</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1559</date>
                 <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Day, John 1.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stationers’ Company, London</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>12, 202, 10 pages, 2 folded leaves of plates, illustrations, portraits, maps, table, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Prefaces &amp; Introductions</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Astrology and cosmography</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="preface">
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <head>THE PRAEFACE OF THE Author, setting out the dignitie, and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vse of Cosmographie.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F EVER THERE wer Art for all mēs vse inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Science set forth wherein consisteth Sapience, or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure worthy to be had in esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: no doughte (louynge Reader) either Cosmographie is the same, or els it is not to be founde vppon th'Earth. For if we do well consider with oure selues what her office is, there is no man I suppose, so meane witted, but will confesse her ample vse, nor yet so simply learned but must acknowledge her manifold benefites. And if I shall begin with the defence of our Coūtry, which ought to be more praecious, thē Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes wife Children or Consanguinitie, Cosmographie herein do so much profite, that without it both valeaunt Corage, Policy and Pui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunce oftentimes can take no place. For by her we are taught whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che way to conduct most safely our ooste, where to pitch oure tentes, where to winter: yea, and where most aptlye to encounter with them in the fielde. VVhich thing Alexander the mighty Conqueroure vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, accustomed to haue the Mappe and Carte of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, by his Cosmographers set out, with which he would warre. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding it also to be hanged in open markets for all men to behold, wherby the Capitaines did for see, and seke out where was the easiest places to arriue, and the Souldiors allured with the commodities of the Countries, were made the willinger to the thinge. This was it which got him so many victories, and made him so great à Cōqueror. This was it which obteined the Romanes their fame, more then ther force and strength. This hathe bene to all men profitable, and iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to no man. On the contrarye parte, what domage, yea vtter sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertion hathe folowed to moste noble Princes, and valeaunte Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines throughe Ignorance of this Art, histories full well can testify.
<pb facs="5"/>
And that amonge manye, I maye resight one Example, was not the mightye pertian King Cyrus (who had brought Babilon, and all the East partes in subiection) vanquished withall his armye of Tomyris the Scythiā Quene, at the Riuer Oaxis, as he shuld haue passed ouer? what shall I speake of Agamemnons armye in the Troian warres: of the Persians, against the Leonidians: or of Crassus, against the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theans: whiche ware them selues destroyed, or made captiue, theyr wiues children and family spoyled, and theyr country most ruinously subuerted, for want of Cosmographie. Also, as touching the study of diuinitie, it is so requisite, and neadfull, that you shall not vnderstād any boke, ether of th' old law or Prophets (yea I had almost said, any part of à booke, or Chapter of the same) being in this Art ignoraunt. For what numbre of places, Ilands, Regions, Cities, Townes, Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Seas, Riuers, and such like, is ther to be found in euery Booke? How often doth father Moses in his. v. bookes, make mention of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, Sinehar, Armenia (in whose hilles, Noë his Arke stayed after the vniuersal deludge) Assur, Charan, Caphdorim or Caldaea, Aegipt called of the Hebrues Mizraim, Syria (deuided into thre parts, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopotamia, Arabia, and Aethiopia,) with infinite like places, whiche without Cosmographie can nether be rightly vnderstand, or yet tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye expounded? VVhat contention, and strife, haue ther spronge in all ages amonge th' Interpreters of the scriptures, touching the situatiō of Paradice: their owne workes moste euidentlye beare witnesse. All they agree in this poynt, that it is à place of ioy, reast, and abounding in all kinde of pleasures, but yet as touchinge the situation, some vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand it spiritually: some imagin it ether in heauen or in the harts of the quiet and faithfull: other affirme it à place in th'Earth at this praesent yet remaining, but is so kepte with Angels that no man maye come to it: some say it is in th' East part of the worlde, aboue the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle reagion of th' Aëre, and so is free from the violence of all windes. Other suppose it to be in the burning Zone, vnder th' Equinoctiall: So that not two in this poynt do accord. But yet of all the rest, ther o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions semeth most fond, whiche place it in the middle region of the Aëre, and also those, that vnderstand it spiritually, for that the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture affirmeth it to be in th' Earth, and the. iiij famous floudes (Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates, Hidekel nowe called Tigris, Gihon, which many interprete Nilus, and Phison at this daye named Ganges (to come from thence.
<pb facs="5"/>
These thinges I bring in only as example, to proue the necessarye vse of it in deuinitie, and not to dispute ether of Paradise or his situatiō, seing it belongeth not to my profession, and office. Moreouer mannes helth (withoute whiche Honour, Fame, Richesse, Frendes, and Life it selfe, semeth bothe troublous, and noysome) can not be conserued in perfite estate, or once lost be recouered and restored without Cosmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie. For howe greatlye herein it profiteth, to consider the tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature of Regions, Cities, and Townes, in what Zone, &amp; vnder what Clymate and Parallele they are situated: Hippocrates dothe plainlye set out. Yea it might seme superfluous, to show how bothe he &amp; Gale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, commaunded ther pacients to remoue from one place, to an other (especiallye in longe sickenesse) because of th' alteration of th' Aëre. VVhat it auaileth also, to know the natures of waters, the quality &amp; pertition of windes, the maners &amp; complexions of th' inhabitantes all Physicions right well do vnderstand. And to cōclude, in th' election of simples, as stones, treis, rotes, herbes, gummes, earthes, metals, beasts, foules, &amp; fishes, what lighte springeth by consideringe the countrye from whence they are brought: I suppose no man of that profession, is ignorant. In the making, &amp; ordaining lawes, for brideling mans fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appetide, Cosmographie is not vnfrutfull. For she setteth out the natures of all people, the lawes and statutes by which they are gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; the sequele of euery decre established. Grammarians also, can not fullye vnderstande the pleasaunt inuention &amp; perfite sence of the witty Poëtes, but by Cosmographies aide, because of the names of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, Cities, Townes, waters, fluddes, mountaines, ceremonies, people and monsters, which euery Poet do commenlye introduce, in all theyr writinges. I omit for breuitie, th' incredible benefits, whiche springe by reading of Histories: the beautye, &amp; ornature of which, consisteth in the description of countreis, names of people, &amp; nature of th' inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants: whiche remaine as vnknowne of th' inexperte of Cosmogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghie. Moreouer, the famous marchaunts, haue by it not onlye inriched them selues, but also their country: fineding out suche commodities, as without it shuld remaine, as not knowne. Yea &amp; that is daily more &amp; more perceiued, for what countrie, or Iland, is not in oure age sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out? what shall I herein speake of Vesputius Americus, who (by his knowledge in Cosmographie) found out America, the .iiij. parte of the world, (vnknowne in all ages before our time) to the great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites
<pb facs="6"/>
of all Europe. I may seme to vtter that all men know, in making rehersall of th' Indians, Calicute, Ginea, the. v. Ilandes Moluccae, also Porne, Sololi, &amp; infinite other, which are the frutes of Cosmographie in this our age. Mariners &amp; trauailers on the seas (without which no realme can long stand, or mans life be sustaind) are bound to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Cosmographies benefites. For it setteth forthe there portes, it sheweth ther course, it declareth th' ordre of windes, it warneth them of rockes, shaloues, sandes, &amp; infinite like dangers. In trauailing by land, her tables poynteth which way to folow, that thy iornay may be spedier, safe, short, &amp; plesant, wher you shall ascend vp to hilles, wher to passe ouer waters, where to walke through woodes, and wher most aptly to remaine at night. If al these were not (as it serueth to infinite vses more then time will permit to repete,) yet this one were sufficiēt to kepe it in honor, that by it, in so small à lumpe, or piece of clay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding such strange formes of men, beastes, foules, and fishes: such di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie of times, such burning hilles, such merueilous stones, metalles &amp; plants, we are inforced to confesse th' omnipotency, and wonderous worke of God. This is it, that prouoked Dioscorides to leaue cities, &amp; townes, &amp; trauail into deserts, &amp; wods, to serch the nature of herbes This caused Atlas, Ptolomaeus, &amp; Alfonce, to be so diligēt in setting out the heauens course, &amp; forme of this earthly mansion. The vtilitye of this, alured Orpheus, Solon, Democritus, Pythagoras, Eudoxus, Plato, Hipparchus, Polybius, Strabo, &amp; an hundreth more of the auncient Philosophers, to leaue their country, frends &amp; acquaintāce, not doubting perel of the seas, dāgers of enemies, losse of substāce, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines of body: or anguish of mind. Yea the sweatnes therof was so great that Strabo after his trauails said, that if any arte were requisite for à Philosopher: it was Cosmographie. And Homer called Vlisses the wi sest among the Graecians, because he knew the natures of people, and the diuersitie of nations: Adding, that his eloquence, prudence, forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, constancye, &amp; other like vertues (mete for à man) insued of hys perigrinations, &amp; trauails, which remaining at home, he shuld neuer haue learned by any preceptes, discipline, or teacher. But seing diuers in oure age are desirous of knowledge no lesse then the Philosophers were, &amp; yet can not trauaile for the discorde of nations, the sondrye sectes of people, and diuers other impedimentes, our refuge is, to saye with Propertius.</p>
   <q>
      <pb facs="6"/>Cogor et è Tabula, pictos ediscere Mundos.</q>
   <q>
      <lg>
         <l>In Tables set out, Countries to decerne</l>
         <l>Constrained am I, and eke for to learne.</l>
      </lg>
   </q>
   <p>In which, I had almoste (through making ouer much hast) forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to resight the benefits we receiue of Cosmographie: in that she de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth vs from greate and continuall trauailes. For in à pleasaunte house, or warme study, she sheweth vs the hole face of all th' Earthe, withal the corners of the same. And from this perigrination, thy wife with sheadinge salte teares, thy children with lamentations, nor thy frendes with wordes shal dehort &amp; perswade the. In trauailing, thou shalt not be molested with the inclemencye of th' Aere, boysterous windes, stormy shoures, haile, Ise, &amp; snow. Comming to thy lodginge, thou shalt not haue à churlish &amp; vnknowne hoste, which shall myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster meate twise sodden, stinking fish, or watered wine. Going to rest, thou shalt not feare lowsy beddes, or filthy sheates. In Somer, the sōne with his fierye beames, shall not vexe thee: nor yet in winter, stormye Saturnus shal make thy beard frosen. In sayling, thou shalt not dread Pirates, feare Peries and greate windes, or haue à sicke stomacke through vnholsome smelles. Therfore these things considered, who is not incoraged to acheue suche an interprice, as shall redounde to his countries fame, &amp; his perpetuall memorye? what wise man dothe not delite to reade such thinges, as Emperoures, Kinges &amp; Princes haue painfully trauailed in, esteming ther labours plentuouslye rewarded, with the frute of this Art? But least these my wordes, should stirre vp the greadye appetides of diuers to this knowledge, &amp; then to wante herein that mighte satisfie the same, beholde I haue compiled this my Cosmographical glasse. By which, such as are delighted in trauailing as well by land, as water, shal receiue no small comfort (If I be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued) &amp; th' other sort, by it may also protract, &amp; set out perticuler cardes for anye countrye, Region, or prouince: or els th' vniuersall face of th' earth in à generall Mappe. Firste if they describe Parallele cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles in the Mappe, answeringe to the like circles in the heauens: &amp; by the right or croked Horizont, th' equinoctiall, polary circles, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the pole, to limite out the Zones, Climates, &amp; Paralleles of Longitude, and Latitude: which being once praepared, you shall place there in the countries, hilles, fluddes, seas, fortresses, Ilandes, cities, desertes, &amp; such like (according to the praecepts of th' art) as are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on the platte forme of th' earthe. And that the praeceptes myghte
<pb facs="7"/>
seme the more facile &amp; plaine, I haue reduced it into the forme of à Dialoge: the names of the personages in dede fained, but yet most apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly seruing our institutiō. In which Spoudaeus (repraesenting the Scho ler) maketh doubtes, asketh Questions, obiecteth: yea, &amp; some tyme, digresseth not from the fonde imaginations of the grosse witted. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which, Philonicus (supplying th'office of à teacher) answereth to to all th'obiections, &amp; giueth praeceptes. VVhat diligēce I haue giuen in time of the Printing, to the correction herof, and also in diuisinge sundry newe Tables, Pictures, demonstrations, &amp; praeceptes: that you may easely iudge by readyng the same worke. Also what charges the Printer hath susteined, that his good will might not be wanting, that shalbe euident conferryng his beautiful Pictures &amp; letters, with suche workes, as herto hath bene published. And thus I leaue the with my Cosmographicall Glasse, requiryng that these my trauayles &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, be not rewarded with ingratitude, or ill reporte. And if for the difficultie of the worke, any errour escape: remember I am the firste that euer in oure tongue haue written of this argument, &amp; therfore am constrained, to finde out the pathe. whiche if it be not at this time made plaine, smothe &amp; pleasaunt: if God graūt life, &amp; leisure, I trust so to treade it againe, that both night and day (walking in the same) thou shalt not misse of the desired Port. Againe fare well, &amp; fauoure me, as I wishe thy furderaunce in knowledge. </p>
   <closer>
      <dateline>At Norwich, <date>the xviij. of Iuly. 1559.</date>
      </dateline>
   </closer>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>