<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>TO THE KINGS MOST ECCEL∣LENT MAIESTIE: The Author wisheth all Content and Happines.</title>
           <author>Stock, Si.</author>
        </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1619</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106011_Fr1_2</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A20673</idno>
           <idno type="STC">7072.6</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106011</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>TO THE KINGS MOST ECCEL∣LENT MAIESTIE: The Author wisheth all Content and Happines.</title>
                 <author>Stock, Si.</author>
              </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>The practise how to finde ease, rest, repose, content, and happines. Written by a religious man of the congregation of St. Elias the prophet, and of the order of our Blessed Lady of mount Carmell, restored by the Blessed mother Teresa. The second part. Containing directions how to end all controuersies, and take away all discontentments, and euils, and attaine vnto true ioy of minde, and content of heart, and all good</title>
                 <author>Doughty, Thomas</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England</pubPlace>
                    <date>1619</date>
                 <publisher>—Recusant.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Fouet, Jacques, pseud</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>36, 478, 2 pages, 12°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>Dedications</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>N</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>Religious</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="dedication">
   <pb facs="2"/>
   <head>TO THE KINGS MOST ECCEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENT MAIESTIE: The Author wisheth all <hi>Content</hi> and <hi>Happines.</hi>
   </head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst all our Labours in this life (most dread SOVERAIGNE) there are none better imployed then those, which are spent in seeking after, and in establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our selues, and others, true <hi>Content,</hi> and <hi>Happines:</hi>
      <pb facs="3"/>
      <hi>For what doth it profit a man, if</hi>
      <note place="margin">Math. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
            <desc>•</desc>
         </gap>6.</note>
      <hi>hee gaine the whole world, and sustaine the damage of his soule? or what permutation shall a man giue for his soule?</hi> and deliuer it to be afflicted in this life with temporall discontent, and in the other with eternall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Will hee take to be an <hi>Emperor,</hi> or <hi>King</hi> of the whole Globe of the earth; to raigne with discontent, for seauen yeares, ouer all the people in the world? It is so hard an exchange, that none indued with reason would accept of such conditions: for what is an <hi>Emperor,</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> or any man, but his <hi>Content,</hi> and <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines?</hi> To be, and not to be happy, is but to be by a priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of well being, wretched, and miserable. Neither is it sufficient to Happines, that a
<pb facs="3"/> man thinke himselfe happy, and be not, for this is but an increase of misery; not to seeme to be, that which hee is, vntill it bee too late, to obtaine that which he would; true <hi>Content:</hi> whereby wee see, that true <hi>Happines</hi> is more woorth then King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; and true <hi>Content</hi> is more to bee esteemed, then all the treasures of the East, and West <hi>Indyes,</hi> since it indueth <hi>Emperors</hi> and <hi>Kinges</hi> with whatsoeuer true goods they haue, and filleth Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects with what they can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, if they will not desire that which is hurtfull to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues: Insomuch, as let but a <hi>Prince</hi> establish in himselfe, his Court and Subiects, the practise of true <hi>Happines,</hi> they rest and remaine, each
<pb facs="4"/> one reioicing at others good, and all well content, with that which euery one hath of his owne: and let him but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, false, and deceitfull <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines,</hi> to bee practised in himselfe, and Subiectes; and doe what he can, hee and they will become wretched, and miserable, in all thinges else, sauing in imaginations: which considerations haue moued mee to seeke out the pathes of <hi>Content,</hi> and set downe at large the way to true <hi>Happines,</hi> and <hi>Rest,</hi> that I might thereby asmuch as in mee lyeth, call all my Countrey men from the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustes, and dissentions of this age (which the iniquitie of heresie hath brought forth) to a rich <hi>Repose,</hi> and <hi>Ioy</hi> in our Lord.</p>
   <pb facs="4"/>
   <p> And hauing Dedicated our First part, vnto the most wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Prince</hi> CHARLES your Sonne (whome <hi>God</hi> Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty long preserue.) I could not set out these our Second labours, vnder the protection of any other, but your <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie:</hi> For seeing I am to speake of <hi>Content,</hi> and <hi>Happines,</hi> to whome may I more fitly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate our labours, then to my <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> vnto whome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all men liuing I hartily wish them. Accept therefore most dread <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> the protection of this our worke against all calumniators; and bee well pleased, that true <hi>Content,</hi> and <hi>Happines,</hi> which your <hi>Maiestie</hi> cannot but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to your selfe, may with your Gracious fauour, and vnder your protection, bee
<pb facs="5"/> communicated to all your Subiects: that all dissentions and discontentments taken out of your Highnes King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: it may bee verified of your Monarchy; which was spoken of <hi>Sion</hi> the Temple of God: <hi>The habitaiton in thee, is as it were of all Reioycing,</hi>
      <note place="margin">Psal. 86.</note> which is that I desire, and hartily pray for, and so humbly submit my selfe, and rest,</p>
   <closer>
      <signed>
         <hi>Of your Maiesties Subiects, the meanest:</hi> SI: STOCK.</signed>
   </closer>
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <pb facs="6"/>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>