<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        
        <titleStmt>
           <title>THE AVTHOVRS PREFACE TO the Reader.</title>
           </titleStmt>
        
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>
              <date>1630</date>
           </edition>
        </editionStmt>
        
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>To the Reader: The English Preface in Print, c. 1475-1640 / Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership</publisher>
           <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
           <date when="2021">2021</date>
           
           <idno type="TTR">S106901_Fr1_5</idno>
           <idno type="DLPS">A01811</idno>
           <idno type="STC">11947</idno>
           <idno type="ESTC">S106901</idno>

           
        </publicationStmt>
        
        <sourceDesc>
           <biblStruct>
              <analytic>
                 <title>THE AVTHOVRS PREFACE TO the Reader.</title>
                 </analytic>
              
              <monogr>
                 <title>Annales of England : Containing the reignes of Henry the Eighth. Edward the Sixt. Queene Mary. Written in Latin by the Right Honorable and Right Reverend Father in God, Francis Lord Bishop of Hereford. Thus Englished, corrected and inlarged with the author's consent, by Morgan Godwyn</title>
                 <author>Godwin, Francis</author>
                 <imprint>
                    <pubPlace>Great Britain--England--London</pubPlace>
                    <date>1630</date>
                 <publisher>Islip, Adam.</publisher>
                            <publisher>Stansby, William</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                 <extent>16, 394, that is 294, 293-342, 2 pages, engraved portraits, 2°</extent>
                 
              </monogr>
           </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
        
     </fileDesc>
     
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="TTR Div type Categories">
              <term>To the reader</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="TTR">
              <term>Y</term>
           </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="USTC Subject Classification">
           <term>History and chronicles</term>
                </keywords>
           
           <keywords scheme="Farmer and Lesser Genres">
              <term/>
              <term/>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
        
     </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
  <text>
     <body>
     <div type="author_to_the_reader">
   <pb facs="5"/>
   <head>THE AVTHOVRS PREFACE TO the Reader.</head>
   <p>
      <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the many who have in <hi>Latin</hi> compiled the History of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Polydore Virgill</hi> in the opinion of most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth: not that hee hath written either more truly or copiously, then many others; but more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litely, andlatest of any that have taken paines in this kinde. For indeed it could not be, that a Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainer, an <hi>Italian,</hi> well gone in yeares even at his first arrivall in <hi>England,)</hi> where being made Archdeacon of <hi>VVells,</hi> he long survived not) should not often erre in the delivery of our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and in reguard of his meere ignorance in the <hi>English</hi> tongue, in silence bury many worthy passages recorded by our <hi>English</hi> Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="6"/>
only. Jt being therefore to be wished, and is much desired, that some one versed in our Antiqnities would (as learned Master <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> hath alreadie done for the description of the Island) consecrate part of his learned la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to the Eternitie of <hi>Britaine,</hi> not in refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that obsolete <hi>Virgilian</hi> History, but in composing a new one; our Antiquaries may iust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be taxed of Slouth (I had almost said slouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnesse) who had rather suffer the famous Acts of their Ancestors to die eternally in silence, and so (as much as in them lieth) defraud their Couutrey of its true and deserved Glory, then bestow any the least paines in commenting; that so the examples of most eminent Ʋertues (whereof the harvest here hath ever beene most plentifull) might not want the Record of their due Monuments. This J hope some or other will in good time performe. In the meane time, others drawing backe, although I was never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with such eloquence, as that I should dare adventure the writing of an History (but now especially
<q>
         <l>—vires vltra sortem{que} senectae,</l>
      </q>
when having passed the age of fifty, long desue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude may have dulled my faculty of penning) yet have I thought it might prove paines-worthy, to vndertake briefly in three small Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb facs="6"/>
to set forth the deeds of three Princes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Successors to <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, so far forth as I have had notice of them. And that, partly that by tovching at the fountaine (as they say) J might stir vp the wits of others; partly that the desires of Forainers might in some sort be satisfied, who not without cause complaine, that these times, then which for a thousand yeares wee have had none more memorable in reguard of their divers and remarkable chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, are not described by any, otherwise then slightly, and as if they they had not intended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such thing. As for <hi>Polydore Virgill,</hi> he hath written either nothing or very little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them; and that little so false and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beseeming the ingenuitie of an Historian, that he seemeth to have aimed at no other end, then by bitter invectives against <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth and Cardinall <hi>Wolsey</hi> to demerit the favour of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> already more then befitted incensed against both for the Divorce of her Mother. J have therefore written (friendly Reader) and so written, that although many things (I will not deny) conducing to an Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian may be wanting in me; yet am I confident, that this my endeuour will finde acceptance with many. Other Writers may here have as it were a store-house, from whence they may if I be not
<pb facs="7"/>
deceived) furnish themselves with some mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which may helpe to raise an everlasting mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument. Forainers also ignorant of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> tongue may have a taste of these times, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vntill some one arise, who can and will compile a History of our Nation worthy the maiestie of the <hi>British</hi> name. J have in this worke beene so observant of Jmpartiality, Simplicity, and Truth, that I feare nothing so much as a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestique anger for not being pious enough, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I would not be over-pious. Many contend, that a good Prince should be <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>. This (I thinke) no man will affirme of an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storian, though some seeme to opine it; So that he shall come short of his duty either to God or his Countrey, who in the delivery of an History will not be at the least <gap reason="foreign">
         <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
      </gap>; and who by affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming incertainties▪ and knowne truthes, shall not yeild much to his affections, so they be ioined with the love of Religion and Countrey. But how much do they inure Truth, who from lies and falshood beg helpes to vnderprop her? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. We have no need of them, And had we, yet would it not much profit vs to rely on such weake advantages, one <hi>pious lye</hi> detected pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more hurtfull, then a thousand others, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though so artificially contrived that they avoid discovery, can prove profitable. For example
<pb facs="7"/>
whereof seeke no farther then the <hi>Papists,</hi> whose fained miracles, impostures, and Legends pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vp of lyes have brought to passe, that even in those things which are true, they scarce gaine beliefe. Wherfore, I am well content that Truth, which maugre her enemies will at length be every where victorious, shall prevaile with me. J have done to my power. Politely, eloquently, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiquely, I could not write: Truly, and <hi>fide Atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>câ</hi> as they say, I could. If I have done amisse in ought, it is not out of <hi>malice,</hi> but <hi>errour,</hi> which the gentle Reader will (I hope) pardon. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#apex" extent="1 letter">
         <desc>•</desc>
      </gap>ernestly intreate, withall beseeching the All-good and All-mighty God, that this my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour directed to no other end, then to his glory and the good of his Church, may attaine its due, and by me desired suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse. Farewell.</p>
</div>
        </body>
  </text>
</TEI>